<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th</link>
    <description>hep-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 05:00:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Gauge-Invariant Entire-Function Regulators and UV Finiteness in NonLocal Quantum Field Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11756v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We clarify the status of gauge-invariant entire-function regulators in NonLocal Quantum Field Theory. The regulator is implemented as an entire function of the covariant Laplace--Beltrami operator. Working in the background-field formalism and expanding around flat, trivial backgrounds, we show that plane waves diagonalize the d'Alembertian, so that the entire function reduces to a multiplicative form factor in Minkowski momentum space. After Wick rotation, to the Euclidean axis, producing exponential ultraviolet damping in loop integrals without introducing additional poles or branch cuts. Our analysis provides a concise, gauge-covariant justification for the use of entire-function regulators in nonlocal quantum field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11756v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. W. Moffat, E. J. Thompson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analyticity of the Black Hole S-Matrix</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11794</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11794v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish the analytic structure of the S-matrix in the complex-frequency plane for classical wave scattering on a Schwarzschild background in four space-time dimensions. Our argument relies on the analytic continuation of the gravitational potential, with the singularity behind the horizon playing a crucial role. We find that in the lower half-plane the partial-wave amplitudes are analytic except for the quasinormal-mode poles and the branch cut associated with late-time tails. As a direct consequence of causality, the retarded Green's function and absorption amplitude are analytic in the upper-half plane. We show, however, that Stokes phenomena can obstruct this analyticity domain from carrying over to the elastic amplitude, which instead develops a branch-cut in the upper-half plane. We also determine the effect of infrared (IR) regulators on the analytic structure, showing that polynomial boundedness requires a sharp lower bound on the IR cutoff in terms of the Schwarzschild radius.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11794v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Correia, Tushar Gopalka, Giulia Isabella, Anna M. Wolz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>E-Strings and Four-Manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11807v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the physics of the E-string theory and its compactifications as well as their applications to four-dimensional topology. In particular, we compute the partition function of the topologically twisted theory on $M_4\times T^2$, where $M_4$ is a four-manifold. In a range of examples, we verify that this partition function, as a $q$-series, 1) has integral coefficients, 2) is modular, and 3) can be lifted to a topological modular form. Remarkably, the E-string theory "knows" about various subtle aspects of the world of smooth 4-manifolds, as the (topological) modularity of the partition function is contingent on a collection of properties of 4-manifolds and their Seiberg-Witten invariants, including, notably, the simple-type conjecture. Furthermore, both theoretical and empirical evidences indicate that this partition function defines a genuine smooth invariant, even when $b_2^+\le 1$. Therefore, the E-string theory may offer powerful new tools for exploring regions in the geography of 4-manifolds that have been inaccessible to existing invariants obtained from gauge theory and quantum field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11807v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Du Pei, David H. Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The fate of Schwarzschild--de Sitter black holes: nonequilibrium evaporation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11873v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a fully analytic treatment of Schwarzschild--de Sitter (SdS) black-hole evaporation in two-dimensional dilaton gravity with anomaly-induced backreaction. Starting from the spherical reduction of four-dimensional Einstein gravity with a cosmological constant, we construct an exactly solvable 2D model that captures the full causal and thermodynamic structure of the SdS static patch, including both black-hole and cosmological horizons. Incorporating the trace anomaly of $N$ conformal matter fields via the Polyakov action, we determine the evolution of the black-hole mass and geometry in the Unruh--de Sitter state, track the steady nonequilibrium Hawking flux, and compute local thermodynamic observables for static observers. The conserved Killing energy flux drives an irreversible heat current from the black hole to the cosmological horizon whenever their surface gravities differ, ensuring monotonic entropy growth and satisfaction of the generalized second law. We prove that $\kappa_b &gt; \kappa_c$ throughout the physical static patch, so the only zero-flux configuration is the Nariai limit where the horizons coincide. Extending the framework to the quantum-information regime, we construct a thermally controlled estimate of the Page curve and show how quantum extremal surfaces and entanglement islands emerge naturally within the anomaly-induced steady state. These results constitute a fully analytic, backreacted solution for SdS evaporation that unifies semiclassical thermodynamics and information flow in a cosmological setting, thereby elucidating the ultimate fate of evaporating black holes in de Sitter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11873v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Damien A. Easson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large N limit of spectral duality between the classical XXX spin chain and the rational reduced Gaudin model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11911v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the large $N$ limit of the spectral duality between the classical $\mathfrak{gl}_M$ XXX spin chain and the $\mathfrak{gl}_N$ trigonometric Gaudin model in its rational reduced form. The infinite-dimensional limit of the Gaudin model is constructed within the framework of the noncommutative torus algebra, following the approach of Hoppe, Olshanetsky and Theisen. In this formulation, the matrix dynamical variables are promoted to fields on the torus, and the corresponding Lax equations acquire the Moyal star-product structure. The dual model is obtained as the large $N$ limit of the $\mathfrak{gl}_M$ classical XXX spin chain with $N$ sites, represented by Laurent series satisfying a quadratic $r$-matrix relation associated with the rational solution of the classical Yang--Baxter equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11911v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Potapov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IR/UV mixing from higher-order interactions in a Scalar Field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12622v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is well known that the calculated cosmological constant, when regularized with a cutoff, differs hugely from the measured value. These calculations are made on the basis of a wave-vector cut-off that is usually set at the Planck scale. Further, Weinberg's no-go theorem indicates that in the presence of translational invariance, local quantum field theories cannot produce a zero cosmological constant without fine-tuning. Various non-local theories have been constructed, starting from modifications to Einstein's equations, in order to `cancel' away the cosmological constant term. There is also a well-known theory, due to Coleman, that assumes one can compute a probability distribution function for baby universes connected by wormholes that has the most probable value of the constant to be zero under some assumptions. The current paper starts from a QFT in 4-dimensions, breaks translational invariance by confining the fields to a box and adds a marginal (in power-counting terms) non-linear, momentum-dependent term that dominates the dynamics produced by the quadratic terms in the high-energy limit. It immediately produces an equation for the wave-vector cutoff applicable to the theory - the equation is reminiscent of that from UV/IR mixing and it effectively lowers the cutoff massively for a box the size of the Universe. However, as will be shown, the wave-vector cutoff for a box relevant for regular particle physics experiments is much larger, in fact, the Planck scale, so there is no conflict with current experiments, including the Casimir effect. We consider several possibilities for these additional terms and conclude that only one is relevant to a low cut-off. We also make a connection to the recent DESI results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12622v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Satish Ramakrishna</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orientations of Orbi-K-Theory measuring Topological Phases and Brane Charges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12720v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Topological Chern phases of quantum materials, as well as brane charges on M-theory orbifolds, have famously been argued to be classified by (orbi) topological K-theory, or possibly by other stable and, notably, complex-oriented cohomology theories, such as elliptic cohomology or Morava K-theory.
  However, closer inspection reveals that the most fine-grained "fragile" microscopic classification in both cases is in (orbi) Cohomotopy, which is the primordial "unstable" or nonabelian generalized cohomology. Coarsening takes the latter (fragile) to the former (stable) cohomology along an nonabelian cohomology operations. But what then is the role of complex orientation on the stable side?
  We observe here (i) that over gapped nodal lines in the 2D Brillouin torus and on probe M5-branes in 11D spacetime, the cohomotopical phases/charges lift through the complex/quaternionic Hopf fibration, and (ii) that measuring this fragile situation in stable cohomology means equivalently to ask for universal complex/quaternionic orientation on stable cohomology in four/ten dimensions!
  Then we give an explicit realization of such unstable four/ten-dimensional complex/quaternionic orientation in U(2)/Sp(2)-equivariant K-theory, using real division-algebraic tools within a new model of twisted orbifold K-theory in cohesive homotopy theory; and we explain this as an extraordinary character map from orbi Cohomotopy-twisted Cohomotopy to relative orbi K-theory.
  Finally, we discuss an application to the classification of 2-band crystalline topological insulator phases sensitive to the topology in the gapping process of their nodal line semimetal parent phase, and to the measurement of M-string charges inside M5-brane probes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12720v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hisham Sati, Urs Schreiber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Quantum Effective Actions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12864v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We first note that, at least in perturbation theory, there is a well-defined (subject to regularization) Lorentzian definition of the quantum effective action in both flat and curved space including (perturbative) gravity. The advantage of the latter is that we do not need to deal with the conformal factor problems of Euclidean quantum gravity. We then make some remarks on the Euclidean version (in flat space) and convexity and resolve a puzzle that highlights the importance of keeping the initial and final states in the functional integral. Next we discuss the gauge invariant effective action of Vilkovisky and DeWitt and show its gauge fixing independence. We conclude with the expression for the Wilsonian effective action in this framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12864v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. P. de Alwis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Application of Solving Inverse Scattering Problem in Holographic Bulk Reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12886v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the problem of bulk metric reconstruction in holography by leveraging the inverse scattering framework applied to boundary two-point correlation functions. We generalize our previous work of scalar field and show that reconstruction can be achieved using a single operator rather than a pair. We also apply this method into reconstruction of static homogeneous anisotropic black holes and the reconstruction using correlation function of gauge field. In addition, we analyze the method's robustness under measurement noise and propose filtering strategies to improve reconstruction accuracy. This work advances data-driven bulk reconstruction by providing a concrete, experimentally viable pathway to recover spacetime geometry from field-theoretic observables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12886v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bo-Wen Fan, Run-Qiu Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precision tests of bulk entanglement: AdS3 vectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13549v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider single particle excitations of the massive Chern-Simons field of mass M in AdS3 and evaluate their contribution at the first sub-leading order in GN to the entanglement entropy across the Ryu-Takayanagi surface. Quantizing the Chern- Simons field in AdS3, we evaluate the corrections to the holographic entanglement entropy using the Faulkner-Lewkowycz-Maldacena formula. The massive Chern-Simons field also obeys the equations of motion of a massive vector in AdS3. The lowest energy single particle excitation of this field is dual to the primary operator of conformal dimensions M + 1 with spin one in the dual CFT, all other single particle excitations are dual to its global descendants. We compare the result for the entanglement entropy from the Faulkner-Lewkowycz-Maldacena formula to the single interval entanglement entropy in large charge holographic CFT obtained using the replica trick for the primary and its tower of holomorphic descendants. The two results agree precisely in the leading and sub-leading terms of the short interval expansion. On taking the massless limit the result coincides with the contribution of a U(1) current to the single interval entanglement entropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13549v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rayirth Bhat, Justin R. David, Semanti Dutta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global quenches and correlator dynamics in de Sitter space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13563</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13563v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study non-equilibrium initial states of quantum fields in curved space-time and develop a framework for describing global quenches as unitary perturbations of the initial density matrix. Using the Keldysh-Schwinger functional integral, we derive expressions for post-quench correlators in arbitrary geometries and apply the method to both Minkowski and de Sitter backgrounds. In flat space, the approach reproduces the known relaxation behaviour for massive fields and reveals qualitatively distinct dynamics in the massless case. In de Sitter space, we find that the late-time decay of quench-induced corrections depends sensitively on the mass and may influence the behaviour of cosmological observables such as the power spectrum. The framework also extends straightforwardly to non-Gaussian initial states, providing a basis for future studies of loop effects and primordial non-Gaussianities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13563v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ivan A. Belkovich, Damir Sadekov, Gleb S. Zverev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$T\bar{T}$ Deformations and Form Factor Program</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13597v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this proceeding contribution, we review a recently proposed method to compute the minimal form factors (MFFs) of diagonal integrable field theories perturbed by irrelevant fields of the $T\bar{T}$ family. Our construction generalizes standard form factor techniques to deal with the deformed two-body scattering amplitudes, which are typical in this setting. The results are minimal form factors which are the product of the undeformed solution and a new function. This function can be fixed by requiring constant asymptotics for large rapidities, smoothness in the limit when the perturbation parameters go to zero, and agreement with standard MFF formulae for particular choices of the perturbation couplings. We observe that, for a certain range of parameters, the new MFF develops a pole at $\theta=0$. By considering several UV-complete theories, we argue that such poles can emerge naturally from the MFF integral representation and suggest how they may be eliminated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13597v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olalla A. Castro-Alvaredo, Stefano Negro, Fabio Sailis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surface Observables, $2$-Knot Invariants, and Nonabelian Electric Fluxes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13623</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13623v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work introduces a surface observable for nonabelian four-dimensional $BF$ theory with a cosmological term. The surface observable yields new $2$-knot invariants that may extend beyond known examples such as the Alexander invariant. By BV pushforward, the surface observable induces an electric observable in nonabelian Yang-Mills theory, offering a concrete realization of 't~Hooft operators. An application to self-dual Yang-Mills theory is also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13623v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto S. Cattaneo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact holomorphic solution of the Hodge-dual minimal surface: a confining quantum QCD string</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13688</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13688v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an exact analytic solution for the quaternionic Hodge-dual minimal surface in four dimensions, which provides a geometric fixed point of the Yang-Mills Wilson loop equation. The area of this surface is expressed through the eigenvalues of the Douglas-Gram matrix of the boundary loop, and is identical for the self-dual and anti-self-dual chiralities related by parity. We prove the Confinement Theorem by showing that the effective string tension sigma_eff[C] (ratio of our Hodge dual area to a Euclidean one bounded by the same loop) is bounded as sigma_eff[C]&gt;= sqrt(2) , remaining finite and positive for all regular loops. Consequently, the Wilson loop decays exponentially with the Euclidean area, providing a purely geometric proof of confinement. Quantization of the quadratic holomorphic action yields a quantum string, with a universal constant correction for each of the two chiral strings. The worldsheet theory is one-loop exact. This construction defines a solvable quantum Hodge-dual string theory reproducing the QCD area law with explicit tension dependence on the loop shape.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13688v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Migdal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Global Symmetries of $T[M]$ Theories: Part II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13696v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We continue the investigation of symmetries and anomalies of $T[M]$ theories obtained by compactifying 6d SCFTs on an internal manifold $M$. We extend the notion of "polarizations on a manifold $M$" to cases where $M$ may have boundaries or defects. Through examples with $M$ of dimension two, three, and four, we illustrate recurring themes in compactifications -- for instance, the important roles played by Kaluza-Klein modes, and how the generalized symmetries (including higher-group and non-invertible ones) of $T[M]$, together with their anomalies, arise from non-trivial combinations of the parent 6d symmetries and the geometric structures of the internal manifold. For each dimension, we also focus on several topics that are especially interesting in that setting. These include: for 2-manifolds, the geometry of the "full moduli space" of $T[M_2]$ and its interaction with polarizations and symmetries; for 3-manifolds, the effect of torsion in homology on the spectrum of line operators in $T[M_3]$, together with applications to the study of quantum invariants such as $\hat Z_a(M_3, q)$; and for 4-manifolds, predictions for VOA$[M_4]$ following from symmetries of $T[M_4]$, as well as the construction of a new invariant of 4-manifolds that depends on two "$q$-parameters." Along the way, we discuss a range of topics that are of independent interest, such as how non-invertible symmetries in higher dimensions can become invertible under compactification, how to classify defects in quantum field theory via their response to a change of framing, and the interplay between $\hat Z_a$ and volume conjectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13696v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergei Gukov, Po-Shen Hsin, Du Pei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bosonisation Cohomology: Spin Structure Summation in Every Dimension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13718</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13718v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Gauging fermion parity and summing over spin structures are subtly distinct operations. We introduce 'bosonisation cohomology' groups $H_B^{d+2}(X)$ to capture this difference, for theories in spacetime dimension $d$ equipped with maps to some $X$. Non-trivial classes in $H_B^{d+2}(X)$ contain theories for which $(-1)^F$ is anomaly-free, but spin structure summation is anomalous. We formulate a sequence of cobordism groups whose failure to be exact is measured by $H_B^{d+2}(X)$, and from here we compute it for $X=\text{pt}$. The result is non-trivial only in dimensions $d\in 4\mathbb{Z}+2$, being due to the presence of gravitational anomalies. The first few are $H_B^4=\mathbb{Z}_2$, probed by a theory of 8 Majorana-Weyl fermions in $d=2$, then $H_B^8=\mathbb{Z}_8$, $H_B^{12}=\mathbb{Z}_{16}\times \mathbb{Z}_2$. We rigorously derive a general formula extending this to every spacetime dimension. Along the way, we compile many general facts about (fermionic and bosonic) anomaly polynomials, and about spin and pin$^-$ (co)bordism generators, that we hope might serve as a useful reference for physicists working with these objects. We briefly discuss some physics applications, including how the $H_B^{12}$ class is trivialised in supergravity. Despite the name, and notation, we make no claim that $H_B^\bullet(X)$ actually defines a cohomology theory (in the Eilenberg-Steenrod sense).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13718v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philip Boyle Smith, Joe Davighi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combinatorial twists in gl_n Yangians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21690v5 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the special set-theoretic Yang-Baxter algebra and show that it is a Hopf algebra subject to certain conditions. The associated universal R-matrix is also obtained via an admissible Drinfel'd twist. The structure of braces emerges naturally in this context by requiring the special set-theoretic Yang-Baxter algebra to be a Hopf algebra and a quasi-triangular bialgebra after twisting. The fundamental representation of the universal R-matrix yields the familiar set-theoretic (combinatorial) solutions of the Yang-Baxter equation. We then apply the same Drinfel'd twist to the gl_n Yangian after introducing the augmented Yangian. We show that the augmented Yangian is also a Hopf algebra and we also obtain its twisted version.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21690v5</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.46298/cm.15770</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Communications in Mathematics, Volume 33 (2025), Issue 3 (Special issue: European Non-Associative Algebra Seminar) (September 26, 2025) cm:15770</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Anastasia Doikou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-order coupling as a driver for Mott insulating behavior in Holography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11645</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11645v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct a simple holographic model incorporating higher-order coupling terms for electron self-interactions. It can exhibit typical behavior of a Mott insulator, including a metal-insulator transition and a decrease in DC conductivity with the increase of charge density. In the analysis of AC conductivity, a soft gap is generally observed. Notably, when the DC conductivity approaches zero, the AC conductivity reveals a multi-peak structure, which can be attributed to the Mott and charge-transfer gaps observed experimentally in transition metals. With the increase of DC conductivity, the multi-peak structure gradually reverts to soft-gap behavior or even metallic conductivity. The numerical reliability is confirmed by the agreement between zero-frequency AC and DC conductivities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11645v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lin-Yue Bai, Ren\'e Meyer, Zhen-Hua Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Complexified Spacetime Manifold Mapping of AdS to dS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11658</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11658v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In a complex manifold, one can bridge anti-de Sitter and de Sitter spacetimes via analytic continuation, preserving geometric invariants and regularity, avoiding singularities during the AdS-dS transition. It unifies gravitational and gauge interactions under a complexified symmetry group, maintaining bulk unitarity for both AdS and dS. Boundary unitarity is upheld in AdS but not in dS due to the spacelike conformal boundary. The theory uses holographic principles like the MacDowell-Mansouri and Quantum Extremal Surface prescriptions to align entanglement and black hole entropy with AdS/CFT and general relativity. HUFT provides insights into AdS and dS holography, the cosmological constant, and quantum gravity unitarity and entanglement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11658v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. W. Moffat, E. J. Thompson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal properties of Klein-Gordon Oscillator in the Context of Amelino-Camelia and Magueijo-Smolin Doubly Special Relativity (DSR) frameworks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11709v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We examine the thermal and statistical properties of the one dimensional Klein-Gordon oscillator within two prominent Doubly Special Relativity (DSR) frameworks: Amelino-Camelia and Magueijo-Smolin. Using the modified dispersion relations specific to each formulation, we derive the positive energy spectra, construct the partition function via the Euler-Maclaurin method, and compute key thermodynamic quantities, including the specific heat $C_v$, as functions of temperature and the deformation scale. Planck-scale corrections produce distinct, theoretically resolvable shifts in both the position and magnitude of the $C_v$ peak in the two models. An accompanying entropy analysis reveals that these peaks correspond to smooth Schottky-type anomalies: the specific heat curves remain analytic and positive across the explored temperature range, and thus do not indicate latent or continuous thermodynamic phase transitions. These comparative results provide a robust diagnostic framework for differentiating DSR prescriptions in relativistic quantum systems and reinforce the transition-free character of their thermal response.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11709v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-025-14892-6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur.Phys.J.C 85 (2025) 10, 1147</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Abdelmalek Boumali, Nosratollah Jafari, Bekdaulet Shukirgaliyev, Fadila Serdouk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universality of Quasinormal-Mode Shifts from Small Nonlocal Effective Couplings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11726v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate perturbative quasinormal-mode (QNM) shifts of black holes arising from fractional, nonlocal modifications to the wave operator. Starting from a scalar master equation corrected by a small fractional Laplacian term $(-\Delta)^{s}$ with $0&lt;s&lt;1$, we derive an analytic expression for the complex frequency shift at first order in the nonlocal coupling $\varepsilon$. Evaluation of the fractional operator in both coordinate and momentum representations reveals a universal scaling law $\delta\omega/\omega \propto \varepsilon/M^{2s}$, largely independent of the field spin, with an additional $\ell^{2s}$ enhancement in the eikonal regime $\ell \gg 1$. Applying the formalism to Schwarzschild, slowly rotating Kerr, Hayward regular, and LQG-corrected black holes, we demonstrate that the leading-order fractional QNM shift is universal, with geometric details entering only through overlap integrals of the mode functions. This universality provides a model-independent signature of nonlocality in strong-gravity ringdown spectra and offers a potential observational window into quantum-gravity-inspired modifications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11726v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anisur Rahaman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A few comments on (hyper)k\"ahler geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11786v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this note, we make two methodical observations.
  $\bullet$ We prove in a simple explicit way that a necessary and sufficient condition for a K\"ahler manifold to be hyperk\"ahler is $h_{i\bar k} h_{j\bar l } \Omega^{\bar k \bar l} \ =\ C \Omega_{ij}$, where $h_{i\bar k}$ is a complex metric, $\Omega$ is a symplectic matrix and $C$ is a positive constant.
  $\bullet$ The procedure of K\"ahler reduction includes two stages. On the first stage, a K\"ahler manifold of dimension $2n$ is reduced to a $(2n-1)$ - dimensional manifold, while on the second stage, one arrives at a K\"ahler manifold of dimension $2(n-1)$. We note that this second stage has the meaning of Hamiltonian reduction. We illustrate the procedure by discussing a simple toy model when $\mathbb{R}^3 \times S^1$ is reduced down to $S^2$. We elucidate also hyperk\"ahler reduction of $\mathbb{R}^7 \times S^1$ down to the Taub-NUT metric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11786v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. V. Smilga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kerr-Bertotti-Robinson Black Holes Surrounded by a Cloud of Strings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11792v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In a recent study [1], authors introduced a new class of exact space-times in Einstein's gravity, which are Kerr black holes immersed in an external uniform magnetic field that is oriented along the rotational axis. Motivated by this work, we investigate a Kerr-like black hole solution with a cloud of strings surrounded by a uniform magnetic field. For the zero rotation case, the space-time reduces to the Schwarzschild-Bertotti-Robinson black hole with a cloud of strings. Moreover, for zero magnetic field, the metrics simplify to a Kerr-like black hole surrounded by a cloud of strings, and its static counterpart reduces to the Schwarzschild black hole with a cloud of strings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11792v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Faizuddin Ahmed, \.Izzet Sakall{\i}, Ahmad Al-Badawi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Divergences in the hadronic light-by-light amplitude of the holographic soft-wall model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11797</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11797v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We use the WKB approximation to uncover divergences and instances of non-commuting limits in a large class of holographic soft-wall models. We show that the infinite sum over single resonance contributions for a variety of observables involving the Chern-Simons term, such as the VVA correlator or the hadronic light-by-light tensor, does not converge. These divergences can in some cases (such as the VVA correlator) be traced back to non-commuting limits and avoided by working directly in the 5-dimensional setup with bulk-to-boundary propagators. However, the hadronic light-by-light scattering tensor also diverges in the 5-dimensional formulation with corresponding Green functions, preventing a correct implementation of the Melnikov-Vainshtein short-distance constraint and even leading to an infinite contribution to the muon $g-2$. We also discuss modifications of the standard soft-wall model that are able to resolve this issue.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11797v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Josef Leutgeb, Jonas Mager, Anton Rebhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inflation without an Inflaton II: observational predictions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11808v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a complete computation of the scalar power spectrum in the \emph{inflation without inflaton} (IWI) framework, where the inflationary expansion is driven solely by a de~Sitter (dS) background and scalar fluctuations arise as second-order effects sourced by tensor perturbations. By explicitly deriving and numerically integrating the full second-order kernel of the Einstein equations, we obtain a scale-invariant scalar spectrum without invoking a fundamental scalar field. In this framework, the amplitude of the scalar fluctuations is directly linked to the scale of inflation. More precisely, we show that matching the observed level of scalar fluctuations, $\Delta_{\phi}^2(k_\ast)\approx 10^{-9}$ at Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) scales, fixes the inflationary energy scale $H_{\rm inf}$ as a function of the number of observed e-folds $N_{\rm obs}$. For $N_{\rm obs}\simeq 30 - 60$, we find $H_{\rm inf} \simeq 5\times 10^{13}\,\mathrm{GeV} - 2\times 10^{10}\,\mathrm{GeV}$, corresponding to a tensor-to-scalar ratio $r \simeq 0.01 - 5\times 10^{-9}$. In particular, requiring consistency with instantaneous reheating, we predict a number of e-folds of order~$\mathcal{O}(50)$ and an inflationary scale $H_{\rm inf} \simeq 10^{11}\,\mathrm{GeV}$. We also incorporate in our framework the quantum break-time of the dS state and show that it imposes an upper bound on the number of particle species. Specifically, using laboratory constraints on the number of species limits the duration of inflation to $N_{\rm obs}\lesssim 126$ e-folds. These results establish the IWI scenario as a predictive and falsifiable alternative to standard inflaton-driven models, linking the observed amplitude of primordial fluctuations directly to the quantum nature and finite lifetime of dS space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11808v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marisol Traforetti, Mariam Abdelaziz, Daniele Bertacca, Raul Jimenez, Sabino Matarrese, Angelo Ricciardone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coexisting phases in the chiral transition within the Linear sigma model with quarks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11822</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11822v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It is believed at present that the chiral transition changes from a smooth crossover to a first-order transition at low temperatures and high densities. Such regime is commonly analyzed using effective models since first principle calculations, as in lattice arrangements, are not feasible. This transition is assumed to be discontinuous, with unstable or metastable intermediate states. However, if multiple charges are simultaneously conserved the system could undergo a continuous change through a coexistence of equilibrium states. This type of transition has multiple manifestations, as in the nuclear liquid-gas transition causing the spinodal fragmentation. The coexistence of phases in the chiral transition is studied here for quark matter assuming the conservation of the isospin composition. Using the Linear sigma model with quarks several remarkable effects are found and discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11822v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. M. Aguirre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing general relativity with amplitudes of subdominant gravitational-wave modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11886v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present an improved subdominant-mode amplitude (SMA) test of general relativity (GR), which probes amplitude-level deviations in the higher-order modes of gravitational-wave (GW) signals from binary black hole mergers while keeping the dominant quadrupole mode fixed. Using a comprehensive parameter-estimation campaign, we benchmark the test against Gaussian noise fluctuations, waveform modeling systematics, and physical effects such as spin precession and orbital eccentricity. When applied to numerical-relativity simulations, the SMA test performs reliably for aligned-spin and mildly precessing systems but exhibits measurable biases for strongly precessing or eccentric binaries. Although designed to detect amplitude deviations, the test also responds coherently to phase perturbations, yielding apparent GR violations when applied to phase-modified waveforms. Applied to recent GW detections, we report the strongest constraint on the hexadecapolar (4,4) mode amplitude deviation, $\delta A_{44} = -0.30^{+1.16}_{-3.45}$, consistent with GR. With these results, this work establishes the SMA test as a robust and broadly sensitive framework for probing strong-field gravity and demonstrates a systematic approach for assessing the robustness of GW tests of GR.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11886v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ish Gupta, Purnima Narayan, Lionel London, Shubhanshu Tiwari, Bangalore Sathyaprakash</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetric Bimetric Cosmology: A Minimal Extension of {\Lambda}CDM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11929v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct and analyze a symmetric bimetric cosmological model connecting Anti-de Sitter (AdS) and de Sitter (dS) regimes through a coupled scalar field. Starting from a Lagrangian with Einstein-Hilbert terms for two FLRW metrics and an inter-metric potential, we derive modified Friedmann and Klein-Gordon equations governing their evolution. In the symmetric effective-fluid limit, the model reproduces the main phenomenology of the $\Lambda$CDM cosmology with a small dynamical correction proportional to $(1+z)^{-3}$, and naturally satisfies local-gravity constraints through Vainshtein screening. This article outlines the theoretical structure and calibration of the model within a dual-geometry cosmological setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11929v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ghani Imadouchene</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Upper Bound on the Cosmic Baryon Chemical Potential from Lepton-Flavor Asymmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11995</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11995v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the early Universe trajectory around the QCD transition in lepton-flavor-asymmetric cases with small total lepton asymmetry ($|\ell|\lesssim 10^{-2}$), while allowing large individual lepton asymmetries. For each temperature, we find an upper bound on the baryon chemical potential $\mu_{\mathrm B}(T)$: $\tau$--$\mu$ asymmetric cases exhibit a local maximum, whereas $\mu$--$e$ cases approach a limiting curve. Thus, even extreme lepton-flavor asymmetry alone cannot reach a first-order region, unless the critical point is moved to a substantially lower $\mu_\mathrm{B}/T$ because of the nonzero $\mu_\mathrm{Q}$. Therefore, we constrain the QCD-era relic to the standard scenario of a chiral crossover transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11995v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Di Clemente, Alessandro Drago, Lorenzo Formaggio, Claudia Ratti, Volodymyr Vovchenko, Geetika Yadav</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hofstadter-Herman Visualization as a Diagnostic Tool for Systematic Effects in Electromagnetic Form Factor Extractions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12007</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12007v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The internal charge and magnetization distributions of the proton are characterized by electromagnetic form factors GE and GM. They are experimentally extracted via Rosenbluth separation, which measures the elastic scattering of electrons and protons at multiple beam energies and angles at fixed momentum transfer Q2. Conventionally, form factor values are obtained by plotting reduced cross sections against the virtual photon polarization parameter epsilon and then extracting the slope and intercept of the best fit lines. An alternative visualization method, proposed by Hofstadter and Herman in 1960, plots GM2 vs. GE2 curves instead. The best fit values of GE2 and GM2 are immediately visible from the intersection region of the curves and their uncertainty bands. In this work, we apply both conventional and Hofstadter-Herman visualizations to classic 1994 SLAC elastic scattering data. We demonstrate that the Hofstadter-Herman method reveals previously obscured regions of form factor parameter space and highlights subtle experimental discrepancies among data sets. Our results motivate adopting this visualization method as a routine diagnostic cross-check at the Electron-Ion Collider and elsewhere to flag normalization shifts and related adjustments before they enter global fits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12007v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tyler Williams (Contact person), Jennifer Rittenhouse West (Contact person), Douglas W. Higinbotham (Contact person), Fatiha Benmokhtar (Contact person)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational wave standard sirens from GWTC-3 combined with DESI DR2 and DESY5: A late-universe probe of the Hubble constant and dark energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12017</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12017v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently, the combination of the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) Data Release 2 (DR2) baryon acoustic oscillation (BAO) data and the Planck cosmic microwave background (CMB) measurements has shown a $\sim$3$\sigma$ preference for a dynamical dark energy model with a phantom-crossing behavior. However, such a phantom-crossing dark energy evolution further exacerbates the already severe Hubble tension in the $\Lambda$CDM model. Moreover, there exists a $\sim2\sigma$ tension between the DESI DR2 BAO and CMB datasets. Therefore, it is essential to measure the Hubble constant and dark-energy equation-of-state (EoS) parameters using only late-universe observations. In this work, we investigate a novel late-universe data combination: gravitational-wave (GW) standard sirens, BAO, and Type Ia supernovae (SNe Ia). This combination provides a fully distance-ladder- and CMB-independent determination of the Hubble constant and the dark-energy EoS. Using 47 GW standard sirens from the third Gravitational-Wave Transient Catalog, the DESI DR2 BAO data, and DESY5 SNe Ia data, in the $w_0w_a$CDM model, we obtain $H_0=74.8^{+6.3}_{-8.9}$ km s$^{-1}$ Mpc$^{-1}$, $\Omega_{\rm m}=0.320^{+0.015}_{-0.012}$, $w_0=-0.775^{+0.072}_{-0.074}$, and $w_a=-0.80\pm0.47$, indicating a mild phantom-crossing behavior within the $1\sigma$ credible interval with an $H_0$ value consistent with the distance ladder measurements. Our analysis demonstrates the power of GW standard sirens in breaking parameter degeneracies, and this novel data combination provides joint constraints on the Hubble constant and the dark-energy EoS parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12017v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ji-Yu Song, Guo-Hong Du, Tian-Nuo Li, Ling-Feng Wang, Jing-Zhao Qi, Jing-Fei Zhang, Xin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement degradation of static black holes in effective quantum gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12245</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12245v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum information science has been broadly explored in Einstein gravity and in various modified gravity theories; however, its extension to quantum gravity settings remains largely unexplored. Motivated by this gap, in this paper we investigate the degradation of quantum entanglement of scalar and Dirac fields in the third-type black hole geometry arising from effective quantum gravity, which incorporates generic quantum gravitational corrections beyond classical general relativity. This quantum corrected spacetime is free of a Cauchy horizon and can be cast into a Rindler form in the near-horizon regime, allowing a direct identification of vacuum modes and a clear correspondence with the framework developed for uniformly accelerated observers. Within this framework, we compute the quantum entanglement and mutual information of uniformly entangled detector pairs in terms of the quantum parameter $\tilde{\zeta}$, the mode frequency $\tilde{\omega}$, and Bob's radial position $R_0$. The quantum parameter $\tilde{\zeta}$ consistently weakens the horizon-induced loss of correlations. For scalar fields this effect is pronounced, producing clear departures from the classical behavior, whereas for Dirac fields the familiar correlation pattern remains intact but its degradation is noticeably reduced. Overall, $\tilde{\zeta}$ acts as a universal protective factor against gravitational suppression of quantum correlations. The third-type effective quantum black hole therefore provides a controlled and physically transparent arena for probing how quantum-gravity corrections influence relativistic quantum information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12245v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaobao Liu, Wentao Liu, Shu-Min Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The conditional probabilities and the empirical laws in a free scalar QFT in curved spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12311v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Unlike QFT in Minkowski spacetime (QFTM), QFT in curved spacetime (QFTCS) suffers from a conceptual obscurity on the empirical (experimentally verifiable/falsifiable) laws. We propose to employ the notion of prior conditional probabilities to describe a part of the empirical laws of QFTCS. This is interpreted as a quantum conditional probability without no information on the initial state. Hence this notion is expected to be free from the inevitable vagueness of the empirical meaning of quantum states in QFTCS. More generally in quantum physics, this notion seems free from the conceptual problems on state reductions. We confine ourselves to the probabilistic laws of the free scalar fields (Klein-Gordon fields) in curved spacetime, which require some reconsideration on the empirical meaning of the canonical commutation relation (CCR). We give some examples of empirical laws in terms of prior conditional probabilities, concerning the CCR and the free scalar QFTCS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12311v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hideyasu Yamashita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Formal geometry and Tamarkin--Tsygan calculi of dg manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12399v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The main goal of this paper is to study the formal geometry of dg manifolds \`a la Fedosov. For any dg manifold $(\mathcal{M}, Q)$, we construct a Fedosov dg foliation (or dg Lie algebroid) $\mathcal{F}_Q \to \mathcal{N}_Q$. We establish homotopy contractions between their respective spaces of polyvector fields, differential forms, polydifferential operators, and polyjets. As a consequence, we prove that their respective Cartan calculi and noncommutative calculi, in the sense of Tamarkin--Tsygan, are isomorphic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12399v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hsuan-Yi Liao, Mathieu Sti\'enon, Ping Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Tidal Response of Non-rotating Black Holes: Connecting the MST Formalism and Worldline EFT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12580v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The response of a black hole (BH) to tidal forces encodes key information about the underlying gravitational theory and affects the waveform of gravitational waves emitted during binary inspiral processes. In this paper, we analyze the dynamical tidal response of static and spherically symmetric BHs in a low-frequency regime within general relativity (GR), based on a matching between the Mano-Suzuki-Takasugi (MST) methods for an analytical approach to BH perturbations and the worldline effective field theory (EFT) for an efficient and unified computation of the binary dynamics within the post-Newtonian regime. We show that the renormalized tidal response function is subject to inevitable ambiguities associated with the choice of renormalization scheme and with the initial condition of the renormalization flow equation. Once these ambiguities are fixed, we obtain scheme-dependent dynamical tidal Love numbers. We also discuss possible extensions of our formalism, including generic non-rotating compact objects (e.g., neutron stars) in GR and BHs in theories beyond GR.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12580v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hajime Kobayashi, Shinji Mukohyama, Naritaka Oshita, Kazufumi Takahashi, Vicharit Yingcharoenrat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digit anomalies in the hadronic mass spectrum, Shannon information entropy, and the dynamical QCD scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12789</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12789v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum Chromodynamics (QCD) has an emergent dynamical energy scale $\Lambda_{\rm QCD}$ which sets the threshold between perturbative and nonperturbative regimes. This characteristic scale causes hadronic masses to cluster within certain mass ranges, instead of following a uniform distribution. Analyzing the Shannon information entropy underlying the hadronic mass spectrum provides novel insight into this phenomenon, revealing a pronounced deviation from the law of anomalous numbers.
  This deviation quantifies the emergence of the dynamical scale in strongly interacting systems, also encoding the information-entropy cost associated with the breaking of scale invariance in QCD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12789v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. da Rocha, R. D. Vilela</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational aspects of a new bumblebee black hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12839v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we examine the physical consequences of a recently introduced black hole solution in bumblebee gravity [1]. The geometry is first presented and then reformulated through suitable coordinate adjustments, which make its global conical character evident. We then study the propagation of particles by solving the geodesic equations for null and timelike trajectories. The associated critical orbits (or photon spheres) are obtained, and shadow radius are computed and compared with other Lorentz-violating configurations in bumblebee and Kalb-Ramond models, including their charged and cosmological extensions. Massive particle motion is analyzed separately, followed by the construction of the effective potentials for scalar, vector, tensor, and spinor perturbations. These potentials allow the calculations of quasinormal frequencies and the corresponding time-domain evolution. Gravitational lensing phenomena are investigated in the weak and strong deflection regimes, and the light-travel time delay is also evaluated. The study concludes with bounds on the Lorentz-violating parameter based on classical Solar System experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12839v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. A. Ara\'ujo Filho, N. Heidari, Iarley P. Lobo, V. B. Bezerra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantization and Algebraic Index</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12875v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This article reviews the program on connecting Batalin-Vilkovisky (BV) quantization with index theories of algebraic type. We explain how the classical algebraic index theorem can be proved in terms of BV quantization of topological quantum mechanics. This is generalized to 2d chiral CFT in which we present an elliptic chiral analog of the algebraic index theory. As an application, we show how the generating function of all genus Gromov-Witten invariants on elliptic curves is mirror equivalent to an elliptic chiral index in the mirror BCOV theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12875v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Si Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Redshifting the Cosmological Constant in Unimodular Gravity via Nonlinear Quantum Mechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12897</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12897v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The cosmological constant problem represents a profound conflict between quantum field theory and general relativity. Unimodular gravity offers a compelling starting point by de-gravitating the vacuum energy of the Standard Model, but this framework traditionally trades the problem of vacuum energy for a fine-tuning of initial conditions, which manifest as a ``shadow" cosmological constant. In this paper, we resolve this initial conditions problem by proposing a novel modification to gravity based on nonlinear quantum mechanics. We introduce specific state-dependent terms to the Hamiltonian, constructed from expectation values of the metric such as the average Ricci scalar. These terms alter the dynamical equations of gravity such that the shadow energy density associated with unconstrained initial conditions redshifts away with cosmic expansion, rendering it negligible at late times. The resulting cosmology is naturally dominated by matter and radiation without fine-tuning. We demonstrate that this significant infrared modification of gravity is consistent with local and cosmological tests of gravity. We comment on the possibility of testing this solution in cosmological measurements of Newton's constant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12897v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David E. Kaplan, Surjeet Rajendran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modified Gravity and Regular Black Hole Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12902v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The prediction of spacetime singularities, regions of infinite curvature where classical physics breaks down, is one of the most profound challenges in General Relativity (GR). In particular, black hole solutions such as the Schwarzschild and Kerr metrics feature central singularities that signal the incompleteness of the theory in high curvature regimes. This thesis is devoted to the study of modified theories of gravity that aim to resolve these singularities and construct physically viable models of regular black holes: black holes that retain an event horizon but exhibit no curvature divergence anywhere in the spacetime ... Throughout the thesis, particular care is taken to ensure that the proposed models are physically sensible: they reduce to GR in the appropriate limits and lead to well behaved curvature scalars. Collectively, these results highlight the viability of regular black hole models in modified gravity theories, providing a promising path toward a consistent semiclassical description of black holes that avoids the need for quantum gravitational resolution of singularities. (Full abstract can be found in document).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12902v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose Pinedo Soto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radiative Decays of Vector Mesons with Light-Cone Sum Rules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12996v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hadronic electromagnetic form factors and radiative decay properties offer a crucial window into the nonperturbative dynamics of Quantum chromodynamics (QCD). In this work, we employ the light-cone sum rules (LCSR) method to systematically investigate the M1 radiative decay of vector mesons. Our study covers processes including $K^{*-}\rightarrow K^-\gamma$, $D^*\rightarrow D\gamma$, $B^*\rightarrow B\gamma$, $D^{*+}_s\rightarrow D^+_s\gamma$, and $B_s^*\rightarrow B_s\gamma$, and further extends to the excited charmonium state $\psi(2S)$. Our calculations yield decay widths for $K^*$ and $\psi(2S)$ that are in excellent agreement with experimental data. For the charm and bottom meson decays, where precise measurements are lacking, we provide theoretical predictions and compare them with other theoretical approaches. Most notably, our analysis reveals a universal linear dependence of the decay width on a function A(x) in the logarithmic coordinate system, which originates from the two-body decay dynamics and the ratio of the initial and final state decay constants. This relationship holds for the ground state $V \rightarrow P \gamma $ processes here and suggests a broader applicability to radiative decays of ground-state vector mesons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12996v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhi Jun Wang, Di Gao, Kai Kai Zhang, Yuan Yuan Ma, Yan Jun Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unbounded Radius of Innermost Stable Circular Orbit in Higher-Dimensional Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13086v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The innermost stable circular orbit (ISCO) offers a fundamental test of spacetime structure. However, its behavior in higher-dimensional black holes influenced by anisotropic energy-momentum tensors remains insufficiently explored. In this work, we investigate the upper bound of the ISCO in higher-dimensional, static, spherically symmetric, and asymptotically flat black hole spacetimes in the presence of an anisotropic energy-momentum tensor. The energy-momentum tensor is assumed to satisfy the weak energy condition, possess a non-positive trace, and obey constraints on radial and tangential pressures, collectively equivalent to the dominant energy condition with additional constraints. By analyzing the effective potential for timelike geodesics and imposing ISCO conditions, we demonstrate the general absence of an upper bound on the ISCO radius in higher-dimensional spacetimes. For dimensions greater than or equal to eight, an ISCO may not exist, depending on the radial and tangential components of the energy-momentum tensor. If an ISCO exists, its radius remains unbounded. These findings advance our understanding of orbital stability in higher-dimensional gravitational systems and highlight fundamental differences from four-dimensional black hole dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13086v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hocheol Lee, Bogeun Gwak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent spectral geometry in the Coherence--Curvature Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13423</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13423v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the Coherence--Curvature Model (CCM), a dynamical ensemble of connected graphs governed by a Hamiltonian that couples algebraic connectivity, Ollivier-Ricci curvature, and an edge-density penalty. Using connected simulated annealing we generate low-energy graph configurations and characterize their emergent geometry through the spectral dimension (ds), the Hausdorff dimension (dh), and the average distance. Finite-size scaling shows a clear growth of ds with system size, while dh increases more mildly. At the largest volumes explored the data are compatible with ds ~ 4 and dh ~ 3, implying ds &gt; dh and a nontrivial hierarchy between spectral and volumetric notions of dimension. We also map the dependence on the curvature coupling gamma and the locality coupling beta, and we find a slow power-law growth of typical distances with a small exponent eta. The CCM therefore provides a controlled numerical laboratory in which the interplay of coherence, curvature, and locality yields finite-dimensional, fractal-like geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13423v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jorge Lamas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Birth of Gravitational Particle Creation: the Enduring Legacy of Leonard Parker's 1966 Thesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13518</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13518v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper offers a historical overview of the origins and enduring significance of gravitational particle creation, a groundbreaking discovery first formulated in Leonard Parker's 1966 doctoral thesis at Harvard University. By tracing the context in which Parker developed this idea and examining its subsequent influence, the paper highlights how the concept of gravitational particle creation advanced the study of quantum field theory in curved spacetime and profoundly shaped modern cosmology, as well as the quantum theory of black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13518v1</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Ferreiro, Jose Navarro-Salas, Silvia Pla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SO(3) real algebra method for finite baryon-number density QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13551v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For lattice QCD calculations at finite baryon-number densities, we propose the ``SO(3) real algebra method'', in which the SU(3) gauge variable is divided into the SO(3) and SU(3)/SO(3) parts. In this method, we introduce the ``maximal SO(3) gauge'' by minimizing the SU(3)/SO(3) part of the SU(3) gauge variable. In the Monte Carlo calculation, the SO(3) real algebra method employs the SO(3) fermionic determinant, i.e., the fermionic determinant of the SO(3) part of the SU(3) gauge variable, in the maximal SO(3) gauge, as well as the positive SU(3) gauge action factor $e^{-S_G}$. Here, the SO(3) fermionic determinant is real, and it is non-negative for the even-number flavor case ($N_f=2n$) of the same quark mass, e.g., $m_u=m_d$. The SO(3) real algebra method alternates between the maximal SO(3) gauge fixing and Monte Carlo updates on the SO(3) determinant and $e^{-S_G}$. After the most importance sampling, the ratio of the SU(3) and SO(3) fermionic determinants is treated as a weight factor. If the phase factor of the ratio does not fluctuate significantly in the sampled gauge configurations, then lattice QCD calculations at finite densities would be feasible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13551v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hideo Suganuma (Kyoto U.), Kei Tohme (Kyoto U.)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bimodular Gravity: Unimodularising Bimetric Scalar-Tensor Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13562v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It is the object of the present paper to unimodularise a disformal bimetric scalar-tensor theory, thereby defining what we call bimodular gravity. We impose one unimodular constraint per metric via multipliers $\lambda_{1,2}$ and show that two natural implementations-a dual fixed-determinant (BUG) and a dual diffeomorphism-invariant (BHT/BDUG) formulation-are classically inequivalent. In BUG the relative volume element $\nu=\sqrt{1-2BX}$ is fixed, enforcing a kinematic constraint on the biscalar and we derive the "bimodular cosmological constant" $\Lambda=\lambda_1+\nu\lambda_2$. In BHT/BDUG, $\lambda_{1,2}$ are individually constant but $\nu$ (hence $BX$) remains dynamical. Recasting the theory in an Einstein-frame form, we derive the biscalar sound speed and identify a subluminal domain $1+B(V+\lambda_2)&gt;0$. At the background level, BUG admits constant-roll solutions governed by first-order flow, whereas BHT supports solutions with time-dependent roll. These structural differences yield distinct, in-principle testable predictions for the expansion history, the dark-energy equation of state, and the propagation of biscalar perturbations. Finally, we present a diffeomorphism-invariant completion that correlates the two HT volume forms, reproducing the $\Lambda$ of BUG on shell whilst maintaining full covariance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13562v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Hallam, Jo\~ao Magueijo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graviton propagator in de Sitter space in a simple one-parameter gauge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13660v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct the graviton propagator in de Sitter space in a one-parameter family of noncovariant gauges. This family generalizes the simple gauge in which most graviton loop computations in de Sitter space have been performed. The resulting propagator has a relatively simple form and will facilitate checks of the gauge dependence of one-loop computations and proposed observables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13660v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dra\v{z}en Glavan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Einstein-Maxwell fields as solutions of Einstein gravity coupled to conformally invariant non-linear electrodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13665v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study Einstein-Maxwell (non-null) sourcefree configurations that can be extended to any conformally invariant non-linear electrodynamics (CINLE) by a constant rescaling of the electromagnetic field. We first obtain a criterion which characterizes such extendable solutions in terms either of the electromagnetic invariants, or (equivalently) of the canonical Newman-Penrose form of the self-dual Maxwell field. This is then used to argue that all static configurations are extendable (more generally, all configurations admitting a non-null twistfree Killing vector field). One can thus draw from the extensive literature to straightforwardly extend to CINLE various known exact solutions, whereby the duality invariance of the Einstein-Maxwell theory allows for dyonic solutions even in more general theories. This is illustrated by a few explicit examples, including the homogeneous $\Lambda&lt;0$ universe of Ozsv\'ath, a black hole in the universe of Levi-Civita, Bertotti and Robinson, a generalization of the charged $C$-metric, and non-expanding gravitational waves in the Bonnor-Melvin background.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13665v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcello Ortaggio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A model-independent assessment of the late-time dark energy density evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13666v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Combined measurements of Baryon Acoustic Oscillations (BAO) from the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Survey (DESI), the Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) and Type Ia Supernovae (SN Ia), have recently challenged the $\Lambda$-Cold Dark Matter ($\Lambda$CDM) paradigm, indicating potential evidence for a dynamical dark energy component. These results are usually obtained in the context of the dark energy equation-of-state (EoS) parameterizations, generally implying in phantom-crossing at intermediate redshifts. However, a general mapping between these parameterizations that yields approximately the same background observables clouds the inference of the true nature of dark energy in the context of these parametric methods. In this work, we propose a model-independent reconstruction of the dark energy density, which is more directly constrained than its EoS, based on the Gaussian Process (GP) regression method with the use of DESI DR2 BAO data and the Pantheon+, Union3 and DESY5 SN Ia samples. In addition, we perform a statistical comparison between the energy densities of $\Lambda$, a non-phantom thawing quintessence-type dark energy, and the Chevallier-Polarski-Linder parameterization with the reconstructed function. We find that all models agree with the GP reconstruction at 95\% C.L., with the largest discrepancy coming from $\Lambda$CDM with DESY5 at low redshifts. Even in this case, our findings suggest that it may be premature to claim statistically significant evidence for evolving or phantom dark energy with current DESI and SN Ia measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13666v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rayff de Souza, Agripino Sousa-Neto, Javier E. Gonz\'alez, Jailson Alcaniz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Error Correction Codes for Truncated SU(2) Lattice Gauge Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13721</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13721v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct two quantum error correction codes for pure SU(2) lattice gauge theory in the electric basis truncated at the electric flux $j_{\rm max}=1/2$, which are applicable on quasi-1D plaquette chains, 2D honeycomb and 3D triamond and hyperhoneycomb lattices. The first code converts Gauss's law at each vertex into a stabilizer while the second only uses half vertices and is locally the carbon code. Both codes are able to correct single-qubit errors. The electric and magnetic terms in the SU(2) Hamiltonian are expressed in terms of logical gates in both codes. The logical-gate Hamiltonian in the first code exactly matches the spin Hamiltonian for gauge singlet states found in previous work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13721v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaojun Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetric Ghost Lagrange Densities for the Coupling of Gravity to Gauge Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.07593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.07593v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We derive and present symmetric ghost Lagrange densities for the coupling of General Relativity to Yang--Mills theories. The graviton-ghost is constructed with respect to the linearized de Donder gauge fixing condition and the gauge ghost with respect to the covariant Lorenz gauge fixing condition. Both ghost Lagrange densities together with their accompanying gauge fixing Lagrange densities are obtained from the action of the diffeomorphism and gauge super-BRST differential -- which we define as the composition of the BRST differential with its anti-BRST differential -- on suitable gauge fixing bosons. In addition, we introduce a total gauge fixing boson and show that the complete symmetric ghost and gauge fixing Lagrange density can be generated thereof using the total super-BRST differential. In particular, we generalize two earlier approaches for flat-spacetime Yang--Mills theories to General Relativity and covariant Yang--Mills theories: The original approach by Curci and Ferrari (1976), using the Faddeev--Popov method on non-linear gauge fixings, and the modern approach by Baulieu and Thierry-Mieg (1982), using BRST and anti-BRST symmetries with gauge fixing bosons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.07593v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Prinz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beauty And The Beast Part 2: Apprehending The Missing Supercurrent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.02382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.02382v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Moonshine module is a $c=24$ conformal field theory (CFT) whose automorphism group is the Monster group. It was argued by Dixon, Ginsparg, and Harvey in \cite{Dixon:1988qd} that there exists a spin lift of the Moonshine CFT with superconformal symmetry. Reference \cite{Dixon:1988qd} did not provide an explicit construction of a superconformal current. The present paper fills that gap. In fact, we will construct several superconformal currents in a spin lift of the Moonshine CFT using techniques developed in \cite{Harvey:2020jvu}. In particular, our construction relies on error correcting codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.02382v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00220-025-05471-7</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Gregory W. Moore, Ranveer Kumar Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher-Derivate Corrections via the Double Copy Procedure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05628v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent advances in the off-shell formulation of the Double Copy (DC) procedure have revealed a profound connection between gauge theories and T-duality invariant frameworks. The main example is Double Field Theory (DFT), emerging as the the off-shell DC of Yang-Mills theory up to cubic order in perturbations. Extending this procedure to a higher-derivative gauge theory gives rise to a Higher-Derivative Double Theory (HDDT), which incorporates Weyl gravity along with $b$-field and dilaton contributions, all in a T-duality invariant manner. In this work, we show that the quadratic contributions of HDDT are directly related (up to field redefinitions) to DFT+, a T-duality invariant model associated with the bosonic string that incorporates first-order $\alpha'$ corrections upon parameterization. Our results expand the potential applications of the off-shell DC program towards constructing perturbative $\alpha'$-corrected Lagrangians, while also opening up possibilities for reversing the map by considering the single and zeroth copies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05628v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Lescano, Jes\'us A. Rodr\'iguez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum aspects of heterotic $G_2$ systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14715v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Compactifications of the heterotic string, to first order in the $\alpha'$ expansion, on manifolds with integrable $G_2$ structure give rise to three-dimensional ${\cal N} = 1$ supergravity theories that admit Minkowski and AdS ground states. As shown in arXiv:1904.01027, such vacua correspond to critical loci of a real superpotential $W$. We perform a perturbative study around a supersymmetric vacuum of the theory, which confirms that the first order variation of the superpotential, $\delta W$, reproduces the BPS conditions for the system, and furthermore shows that $\delta^2 W=0$ gives the equations for infinitesimal moduli. This allows us to identify a nilpotent differential, and a symplectic pairing, which we use to construct a bicomplex, or a double complex, for the heterotic $G_2$ system. Using this complex, we determine infinitesimal moduli and their obstructions in terms of related cohomology groups. Finally, by interpreting $\delta^2 W$ as an action, we compute the one-loop partition function of the heterotic $G_2$ system and show it can be decomposed into a product of one-loop partition functions of Abelian and non-Abelian instanton gauge theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14715v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xenia de la Ossa, Magdalena Larfors, Matthew Magill, Eirik E. Svanes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reassessing aspects of the photon's LQG-modified dispersion relations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09370v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Our present contribution sets out to investigate a scenario based on the effects of the Loop Quantum Gravity (LQG) on the electromagnetic sector of the Standard Model of Fundamental Interactions and Particle Physics (SM). Starting then from a post-Maxwellian version of Electromagnetism that includes LQG effects, we work out and discuss the influence of LQG parameters on classical quantities, such as the components of the stress-tensor. Furthermore, we inspect the propagation of electromagnetic waves and study optical properties of the QED vacuum in this scenario. Among these, we contemplate the combined effect between the LQG parameters and a homogeneous background magnetic field on the propagation of electromagnetic waves, considering in detail issues like group velocities and refractive indices of the QED vacuum. Finally, with the help of the LQG-extended photonic dispersion relations previously analyzed, we re-discuss the kinematics of the Compton effect and conclude that there emerges an interesting nonlinear profile in the wavelengths of both the incoming and the deflected photons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09370v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. A. L. Mour\~ao, G. L. L. W. Levy, J. A. Helay\"el-Neto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum complexity in gravity, quantum field theory, and quantum information science</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10753v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum complexity quantifies the difficulty of preparing a state or implementing a unitary transformation with limited resources. Applications range from quantum computation to condensed matter physics and quantum gravity. We seek to bridge the approaches of these fields, which define and study complexity using different frameworks and tools. We describe several definitions of complexity, along with their key properties. In quantum information theory, we focus on complexity growth in random quantum circuits. In quantum many-body systems and quantum field theory (QFT), we discuss a geometric definition of complexity in terms of geodesics on the unitary group. In dynamical systems, we explore a definition of complexity in terms of state or operator spreading, as well as concepts from tensor-networks. We also outline applications to simple quantum systems, quantum many-body models, and QFTs including conformal field theories (CFTs). Finally, we explain the proposed relationship between complexity and gravitational observables within the holographic anti-de Sitter (AdS)/CFT correspondence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10753v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physrep.2025.11.001</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rept. 1159 (2026) 1-77</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Baiguera, Vijay Balasubramanian, Pawel Caputa, Shira Chapman, Jonas Haferkamp, Michal P. Heller, Nicole Yunger Halpern</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-perturbative renormalization group for pseudo-hermitian scalar fields in 4D</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09327v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We define a model of 2 coupled SU(2) doublets of scalar fields in $4$ spacetime dimensions which have a rich structure of renormalization group (RG) flows to 1-loop when the SU(2) is broken to U(1). The model is pseudo-hermitian, $H^\dagger = {\cal K} H {\cal K}^\dagger$ with ${\cal K}^\dagger {\cal K} = {\cal K}^2 =1$, which makes it non-unitary, however in a very specific manner with some desirable properties. In this article we mainly leave the non-unitarity issue aside and focus on the RG flows to higher orders in perturbation theory, which is sufficient for applications of non-unitary quantum field theory to statistical mechanics. We compute the beta functions to 3 loops from the operator product expansion and show that the 1-loop structure of flows persists to higher orders. For SU(2) broken to U(1), we conjecture a beta function to all orders. The flows can be extended to large coupling using a strong-weak coupling duality $g \to 1/g$ One finds a line of fixed points which are non-unitary conformal field theories in 4 spacetime dimensions that were previously unknown. We also find massless flows between 2 non-trivial fixed points, and a regime with a cyclic RG flow, which is allowed since the model is non-unitary. For the flows between fixed points on the critical line, we compute the anomalous dimensions of the perturbations in the UV and IR, and identify some special points where anomalous dimensions are rational numbers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09327v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'e LeClair</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On canonical differential equations for Calabi-Yau multi-scale Feynman integrals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17757v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We generalise a method recently introduced in the literature, that derives canonical differential equations, to multi-scale Feynman integrals with an underlying Calabi-Yau geometry. We start by recomputing a canonical form for the sunrise integral with all unequal masses. Additionally, we compute for the first time a canonical form for the three-loop banana integral with two unequal masses and for a four-loop banana integral with two unequal masses. For the integrals we compute, we find an $\epsilon$-form whose connection has at most simple poles. We motivate our construction by studying the Picard-Fuchs operators acting on the integrals considered. In the appendices, we give a constructive explanation for why our generalisation works.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17757v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP10(2025)202</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 10 (2025) 202</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sara Maggio, Yoann Sohnle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can metric-affine gravity be saved?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.23894v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Like general relativity, metric-affine gravity should be a viable effective quantum theory, otherwise it is a mathematical curiosity without physical application. Assuming a perturbative quantum field theory, the universal, flat limit of metric-affine gravity offers a good foundation for model-building only when symmetry constraints are themselves sufficient to get rid of ghosts and tachyons in the spectrum of propagating particle states, without requiring any further tuning of the couplings. Using this symmetry-first criterion, we find that for parity-preserving models with a totally symmetric distortion, only massless spin-one and spin-three modes are possible besides the graviton. Moreover, no viable models result from gauge symmetries generated by a scalar field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.23894v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Will Barker, Carlo Marzo, Alessandro Santoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective action of bosonic string theory at order $\alpha'^3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19471v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we derive the classical effective action of bosonic string theory at order $\alpha'^{3}$ for the metric, Kalb-Ramond field, and dilaton by imposing a higher-derivative extension of the Buscher rules on the circular reduction of the minimal basis at this order, in the schemes where their corresponding actions at order $\alpha'$ are the Meissner and the Metsaev-Tseytlin schemes. We find that T-duality fixes all coupling constants in terms of the known overall factor at order $\alpha'$ and a single remaining parameter. This final parameter is determined by matching the single-trace term $\Tr(\epsilon \epsilon \epsilon \epsilon)$ in the four-graviton S-matrix element which lacks a massless pole, with the corresponding string theory amplitude. Our results for the Riemann quartic terms are in full agreement with those obtained from the nonlinear sigma-model approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19471v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mehdi Ameri, Alireza Pahlavan, Mohammad R. Garousi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complete Minimal Form Factors for Irrelevant Deformations of Integrable Quantum Field Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20517v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a method to compute the minimal form factors (MFFs) of diagonal integrable field theories perturbed by generalized $T\bar{T}$ perturbations. Building on existing results by the same authors, these MFFs are constructed in such a way as not to allow for any free parameters, an issue that plagued previous solutions. The MFFs are derived from a generalization of the standard integral representation which has been used for UV-complete theories since the birth of the form factor bootstrap program. By UV-complete we mean theories whose short-distance/high-energy limit is a local conformal field theory. Their asymptotics is characterized by exponential decay at large rapidities. By computing higher particle form factors, we find that any natural higher-particle solutions involve the cancellation of parts of the newly found MFF. We conclude that the assumption that the form factor equations, particularly the kinematic residue equation, remain unchanged in the presence of $T\bar{T}$ perturbations, is too strong. There is a trade-off between having MFFs satisfying desirable analyticity and asymptotic properties and finding analytic solutions to the form factor equations, which is likely solved by nontrivial changes to the form factor equations, especially those where locality or semilocality of fields are essential assumptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20517v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2025.117131</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nuclear Physics B1019 (2025) 117131</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fabio Sailis, Olalla A. Castro-Alvaredo, Stefano Negro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear Resistivity from Spatially Random Interactions and the Uniqueness of Yukawa Coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09442v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent studies have shown that a spatially random Yukawa-type interaction between a Fermi surface and critical bosons can produce linear-in-temperature resistivity, the defining signature of strange metals. In this article, we systematically classify all scalar couplings of the form $(\psi^{\dagger}\psi)^n\phi^m$ in arbitrary dimensions to identify possible candidates for strange-metal behaviour within this disordered framework. We find that only spatially random Yukawa-type interaction in $(2+1)$ dimensions can yield linear resistivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09442v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sang-Jin Sin, Yi-Li Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resurgent structure of 2d Yang-Mills theory on a torus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19943v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the resurgent structure of the topological string dual to 2d $U(N)$ Yang-Mills on torus. We find closed form formulas for instanton amplitudes up to arbitrarily high instanton orders, based on which we propose the non-perturbative partition function including contributions from all the real instantons, which is real for positive modulus and string coupling. We also explore complex instantons and find two infinite towers of them. We expect them to correspond to BPS states in type II string.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19943v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiashen Chen, Jie Gu, Xin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $L_\infty$ structure of Free Differential Algebras and $d=11$ Supergravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.20344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.20344v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We discuss free differential algebras (FDA's), a generalization of the Cartan-Maurer equations for the group manifold vielbein, appropriate for theories containing $p$-forms ($p &gt;1$). Their dual formulation is an extension of Lie algebras, called $L_\infty$ algebras, and we illustrate this duality in a simple example. Finally we review the FDA structure and the dual $L_\infty$ structure of $d=11$ supergravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.20344v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Castellani, R. D'Auria</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Euclidean Wormholes and Gravitational States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14165</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14165v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Euclidean wormholes are known to encode important non-perturbative effects in the physics of quantum black holes. In this paper, we discuss the slicing of Euclidean wormholes along a time-reflection symmetric slice which treats half of the Euclidean geometry as a gravitational machinery to produce a semi-classical state. This type of state preparation is different from Hartle-Hawking states prepared with the CFT path integral, such as the thermofield-double state. Nevertheless, the two different types of states have order one overlaps provided the gravitational data agrees on the initial data slice. This raises an interesting puzzle: one can easily construct an infinite family of semi-classical states that have order one overlap with the thermofield double state, while having a very different Euclidean preparation. We provide a microscopic description of wormhole states in the dual CFT and reformulate the factorization puzzle in the language of entanglement and the Hilbert space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14165v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Belin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spontaneous collapse effects on relativistic fermionic matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04585</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04585v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study expands the spontaneous collapse assumptions into the relativistic quantum field theory framework for Dirac fields. By solving Lindblad's master equation using the Keldysh formalism, the effective action is derived, which captures the dynamics of fermions with spontaneous collapse represented as an imaginary self-interaction term. Utilizing the corresponding Dyson-Schwinger equations at 1-loop approximation, the effective mass induced by the nonlinearity is computed. The findings indicate the presence of a new mechanism that introduces a qualitative change in the mass spectrum, where the particle's mass becomes complex. This mechanism, which generates a Lorentz invariance violation in the infrared regime, recovers the Lorentz invariance in the ultraviolet regime. The corresponding hydrodynamics of the system is analyzed through the Keldysh component of the propagator, and a conserved charge is found. In contrast, the energy-momentum tensor is shown to be non-conserving. This phenomenon represents a new contribution to the understanding of the spontaneous collapse and the transition from quantum to the classical realm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04585v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-025-15062-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Y. M. P. Gomes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical mass generation and critical behavior in pseudo-Proca quantum electrodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19134v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate dynamical mass generation in pseudo-Proca quantum electrodynamics (PPQED) using Schwinger--Dyson equations in rainbow-quenched and unquenched approximations. The (3+1)D gauge-field mass $m$, fine-structure constant $\alpha$, flavor number $N$, and ultraviolet cutoff $\Lambda$ determine the critical thresholds for chiral symmetry breaking in the reduced (2+1)D theory. We derive $\alpha_c(m,\Lambda)$ (quenched) and $N_c(m,\Lambda,g)$ (unquenched), with the gauge-field mass suppressing dynamical mass generation via Yukawa screening. For anisotropic fermions with Fermi velocity $v_F \neq c$, the critical coupling scales as $\alpha^*_c \propto (1 + v_F^2/c^2)^{-1}$. These results clarify the non-perturbative dynamics of massive gauge fields in dimensionally reduced QED and connect to effective photon propagation in Proca metamaterials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19134v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Helio G. Barroso, Van S\'ergio Alves, Leandro O. Nascimento</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Newtonian Gravity Produce Quantum Entanglement?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23584v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this note, we consider specific scenarios of matter-gravity interaction based on the source theory to clarify the issue regarding the Gravitationally Induced Entanglement (GIE) protocol, which posits that the detection of quantum entanglement induced by a pure gravitational effect serves as a probe of quantum gravity. Thus, the GIE protocol implies that classical gravity cannot produce or mediate quantum entanglement, to which a recent paper \cite{Aziz:2025ypo} shows the opposite. In all three scenarios of matter-gravity interactions, including mini-superspace, semiclassical gravity, and stochastic gravity approaches, our results agree with the GIE protocol and its implications. More precisely, we show that the mesoscopic quantum bodies with their parities of mass quadrupoles interacting via Newtonian gravity can get entangled only if the parity of the gravitational tidal field sourced by the quantum body is also quantized. We also point out a possible loophole that could seemingly violate the GIE protocol due to the truncation of higher-order terms in the perturbative expansion by orders of the Newton constant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23584v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Feng-Li Lin, Sayid Mondal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maxwell Chern-Simons gravity in 3D: Thermodynamics of cosmological solutions and black holes with torsion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25559v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct generalized sets of asymptotic conditions for both three-dimensional Maxwell Chern-Simons gravity and a novel extension that incorporates torsion through a deformation of the Maxwell algebra. These boundary conditions include the most general temporal components of the gauge fields that consistently preserve the corresponding asymptotic Maxwell algebras with identical classical central charges, while allowing for the inclusion of chemical potentials conjugate to the conserved charges. We show that both sets of asymptotic configurations admit nontrivial solutions carrying not only mass and angular momentum but also an additional global spin-2 charge. In the torsionless case, the theory admits locally flat cosmological spacetimes, whereas in the presence of torsion, it generalizes to BTZ-like black hole geometries. For each case, the thermodynamic properties are consistently derived in terms of the gauge fields and the topology of the Euclidean manifold, shown to correspond to a solid torus. Furthermore, we obtain a general expression for the entropy, depending on both the horizon area and its spin-2 analogues, which can be written as a reparametrization-invariant integral of the induced spin-2 fields on the spacelike section of the horizon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25559v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luis Avil\'es, Patrick Concha, Javier Matulich, Evelyn Rodr\'iguez, David Tempo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Complexity of Nonlocal Field Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00649</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00649v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Entanglement entropy for nonlocal field theories displays a universal ``volume law" scaling \cite{Barbon:2008ut, Karczmarek:2013xxa, Shiba:2013jja, Pang:2014tpa} as opposed to the ``area law" scaling for local field theories. The aim of this work is to determine whether complexity displays any such an universal scaling laws. The field theories considered here are obtained by deforming $\mathcal{N}=4$ SYM theory by higher dimension operators introducing nonlocality, namely a dipole deformation and noncommutativity (NCSYM) by turning on world volume Kalb-Ramond $B$ field. The dual gravity backgrounds have a running dilaton, in addition to the $B$-field background, which alter AdS asymptotics. Our results capture nonlocality in the hyperscaling behavior for complexity. We also compute the subregion complexity which display phase transitions in the nonlocal field theories with the transition point being the same as that for the phase transition of entanglement entropy \cite{Karczmarek:2013xxa}. These new results dovetail nicely with our findings from our previous works \cite{Chakraborty:2020fpt, Katoch:2022hdf, Bhattacharyya:2022ren} on other lower dimensional nonlocal field theories such as little string theories (LSTs) and warped conformal field theories (WCFTs).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00649v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohan sai Balusu, Gaurav Katoch, Sanhita Parihar, Shubho R. Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monodromy-Matrix Description of Doubly Rotating Black Rings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05353v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Extending the single-angular-momentum case analyzed in our previous work, we investigate the solution-generating technique based on the Breitenlohner-Maison (BM) linear system for asymptotically flat, stationary, bi-axisymmetric black hole solutions with two angular momenta in five-dimensional vacuum Einstein theory. In particular, we construct the monodromy matrix associated with the BM linear system for the doubly rotating Myers-Perry black holes and the Pomeransky-Sen'kov black rings. Conversely, by solving the corresponding Riemann-Hilbert problem using the procedure developed by Katsimpouri et al., we demonstrate that the factorization of the monodromy matrix precisely reproduces these vacuum solutions, thereby reconstructing both geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05353v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun-ichi Sakamoto, Shinya Tomizawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Derivation of Classical Gravitational Second Law of Thermodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07510v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is established that black holes have entropy and behave as thermodynamical systems. Associating entropy to gravitational fields has not remained limited to black holes, necessitating the notion of the second law of thermodynamics in gravitating systems. There have been many ideas and attempts to prove the second law in gravitational systems starting from first principles. Within the covariant phase space formalism, we define gravitational entropy as the charge associated with the local boosts, detaching the gravitational entropy from horizons or trapped surfaces. Our definition encompasses and generalizes the existing notions of entropy. Using this definition for the Einstein gravity case, we compute variations of the entropy along the path of any causal observer and establish that the entropy variations are always non-negative if the matter content satisfies the strong energy condition integrated along any segment of the causal path.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07510v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. R. Shajiee, M. M. Sheikh-Jabbari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Macdonald Index From Refined Kontsevich-Soibelman Operator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07521v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a refinement of the Kontsevich-Soibelman operator for a class of ``special'' 4d $\mathcal{N}=2$ superconformal field theories characterized by the following conditions: (1) their Coulomb branch admits a source/sink chamber, i.e., a chamber in which the BPS quiver consists of only source and sink nodes, (2) The nodes with valency greater than 2 of the BPS quiver in a source/sink chamber are either all sources or all sinks. We present strong evidence that the trace of this refined operator is related to the Macdonald index of the theory. In particular, we conjecture closed form expressions for the Macdonald indices of the $(A_1,\mathfrak{g})$ Argyres-Douglas theories for any simply-laced Lie algebra $\mathfrak{g}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07521v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George Andrews, Anindya Banerjee, Ranveer Kumar Singh, Runkai Tao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Symmetry and Geometry in Double-Scaled SYK</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08743v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The emergence of the quantum $R$-matrix in the double-scaled SYK model points to an underlying quantum group structure. In this work, we identify the quantum group $\mathcal{U}_q(\mathfrak{su}(1,1))$ as a subalgebra of the chord algebra. Specifically, we construct the generators of $\mathcal{U}_q(\mathfrak{s} \mathfrak{u}(1,1))$ from combinations of operators within the chord algebra and show that the one-particle chord Hilbert space decomposes into the positive discrete series representations of $\mathcal{U}_q(\mathfrak{s} \mathfrak{u}(1,1))$. Using the coproduct structure of the quantum group, we build the multi-particle Hilbert space and establish its equivalence with previous results defined by the chord rules. In particular, we show that the quantum $R$-matrix acts as a swapping operator that reverses the ordering of open chords in each fusion channel while incorporating the corresponding $q$-weighted penalty factors. This action enables an explicit derivation of the chord Yang-Baxter relation. We further explore a realization of the quantum group generators on the quantum disk, and present a novel factorization formula for the bulk gravitational wavefunction in the presence of matter. We further discuss the relation between the $\mathcal{U}_q(\mathfrak{s} \mathfrak{u}(1,1))$ structure uncovered here and the $\mathcal{U}_q(\mathfrak{s} \mathfrak{l}(2, \mathbb{R}))$ algebra previously studied from the boundary perspective. Finally, we study the gravitational wavefunction with matter in the Schwarzian regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08743v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeremy van der Heijden, Erik Verlinde, Jiuci Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tests of General Relativity with GWTC-3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.06861</link>
      <description>arXiv:2112.06861v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The ever-increasing number of detections of gravitational waves (GWs) from compact binaries by the Advanced LIGO and Advanced Virgo detectors allows us to perform ever-more sensitive tests of general relativity (GR) in the dynamical and strong-field regime of gravity. We perform a suite of tests of GR using the compact binary signals observed during the second half of the third observing run of those detectors. We restrict our analysis to the 15 confident signals that have false alarm rates $\leq 10^{-3}\, {\rm yr}^{-1}$. In addition to signals consistent with binary black hole (BH) mergers, the new events include GW200115_042309, a signal consistent with a neutron star--BH merger. We find the residual power, after subtracting the best fit waveform from the data for each event, to be consistent with the detector noise. Additionally, we find all the post-Newtonian deformation coefficients to be consistent with the predictions from GR, with an improvement by a factor of ~2 in the -1PN parameter. We also find that the spin-induced quadrupole moments of the binary BH constituents are consistent with those of Kerr BHs in GR. We find no evidence for dispersion of GWs, non-GR modes of polarization, or post-merger echoes in the events that were analyzed. We update the bound on the mass of the graviton, at 90% credibility, to $m_g \leq 2.42 \times 10^{-23} \mathrm{eV}/c^2$. The final mass and final spin as inferred from the pre-merger and post-merger parts of the waveform are consistent with each other. The studies of the properties of the remnant BHs, including deviations of the quasi-normal mode frequencies and damping times, show consistency with the predictions of GR. In addition to considering signals individually, we also combine results from the catalog of GW signals to calculate more precise population constraints. We find no evidence in support of physics beyond GR.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2112.06861v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.112.084080</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 112, 084080 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> The LIGO Scientific Collaboration,  the Virgo Collaboration,  the KAGRA Collaboration, R. Abbott, H. Abe, F. Acernese, K. Ackley, N. Adhikari, R. X. Adhikari, V. K. Adkins, V. B. Adya, C. Affeldt, D. Agarwal, M. Agathos, K. Agatsuma, N. Aggarwal, O. D. Aguiar, L. Aiello, A. Ain, P. Ajith, T. Akutsu, P. F. de Alarc\'on, S. Albanesi, R. A. Alfaidi, A. Allocca, P. A. Altin, A. Amato, C. Anand, S. Anand, A. Ananyeva, S. B. Anderson, W. G. Anderson, M. Ando, T. Andrade, N. Andres, M. Andr\'es-Carcasona, T. Andri\'c, S. V. Angelova, S. Ansoldi, J. M. Antelis, S. Antier, T. Apostolatos, E. Z. Appavuravther, S. Appert, S. K. Apple, K. Arai, A. Araya, M. C. Araya, J. S. Areeda, M. Ar\`ene, N. Aritomi, N. Arnaud, M. Arogeti, S. M. Aronson, K. G. Arun, H. Asada, Y. Asali, G. Ashton, Y. Aso, M. Assiduo, S. Assis de Souza Melo, S. M. Aston, P. Astone, F. Aubin, K. AultONeal, C. Austin, S. Babak, F. Badaracco, M. K. M. Bader, C. Badger, S. Bae, Y. Bae, A. M. Baer, S. Bagnasco, Y. Bai, J. Baird, R. Bajpai, T. Baka, M. Ball, G. Ballardin, S. W. Ballmer, A. Balsamo, G. Baltus, S. Banagiri, B. Banerjee, D. Bankar, J. C. Barayoga, C. Barbieri, B. C. Barish, D. Barker, P. Barneo, F. Barone, B. Barr, L. Barsotti, M. Barsuglia, D. Barta, J. Bartlett, M. A. Barton, I. Bartos, S. Basak, R. Bassiri, A. Basti, M. Bawaj, J. C. Bayley, M. Bazzan, B. R. Becher, B. B\'ecsy, V. M. Bedakihale, F. Beirnaert, M. Bejger, I. Belahcene, V. Benedetto, D. Beniwal, M. G. Benjamin, T. F. Bennett, J. D. Bentley, M. BenYaala, S. Bera, M. Berbel, F. Bergamin, B. K. Berger, S. Bernuzzi, C. P. L. Berry, D. Bersanetti, A. Bertolini, J. Betzwieser, D. Beveridge, R. Bhandare, A. V. Bhandari, U. Bhardwaj, R. Bhatt, D. Bhattacharjee, S. Bhaumik, A. Bianchi, I. A. Bilenko, G. Billingsley, S. Bini, R. Birney, O. Birnholtz, S. Biscans, M. Bischi, S. Biscoveanu, A. Bisht, B. Biswas, M. Bitossi, M. -A. Bizouard, J. K. Blackburn, C. D. Blair, D. G. Blair, R. M. Blair, F. Bobba, N. Bode, M. Bo\"er, G. Bogaert, M. Boldrini, G. N. Bolingbroke, L. D. Bonavena, F. Bondu, E. Bonilla, R. Bonnand, P. Booker, B. A. Boom, R. Bork, V. Boschi, N. Bose, S. Bose, V. Bossilkov, V. Boudart, Y. Bouffanais, A. Bozzi, C. Bradaschia, P. R. Brady, A. Bramley, A. Branch, M. Branchesi, J. E. Brau, M. Breschi, T. Briant, J. H. Briggs, A. Brillet, M. Brinkmann, P. Brockill, A. F. Brooks, J. Brooks, D. D. Brown, S. Brunett, G. Bruno, R. Bruntz, J. Bryant, F. Bucci, T. Bulik, H. J. Bulten, A. Buonanno, K. Burtnyk, R. Buscicchio, D. Buskulic, C. Buy, R. L. Byer, G. S. Cabourn Davies, G. Cabras, R. Cabrita, L. Cadonati, M. Caesar, G. Cagnoli, C. Cahillane, J. Calder\'on Bustillo, J. D. Callaghan, T. A. Callister, E. Calloni, J. Cameron, J. B. Camp, M. Canepa, S. Canevarolo, M. Cannavacciuolo, K. C. Cannon, H. Cao, Z. Cao, E. Capocasa, E. Capote, G. Carapella, F. Carbognani, M. Carlassara, J. B. Carlin, M. F. Carney, M. Carpinelli, G. Carrillo, G. Carullo, T. L. Carver, J. Casanueva Diaz, C. Casentini, G. Castaldi, S. Caudill, M. Cavagli\`a, F. Cavalier, R. Cavalieri, G. Cella, P. Cerd\'a-Dur\'an, E. Cesarini, W. Chaibi, S. Chalathadka Subrahmanya, E. Champion, C. -H. Chan, C. Chan, C. L. Chan, K. Chan, M. Chan, K. Chandra, I. P. Chang, P. Chanial, S. Chao, C. Chapman-Bird, P. Charlton, E. A. Chase, E. Chassande-Mottin, C. Chatterjee, Debarati Chatterjee, Deep Chatterjee, M. Chaturvedi, S. Chaty, K. Chatziioannou, C. Chen, D. Chen, H. Y. Chen, J. Chen, K. Chen, X. Chen, Y. -B. Chen, Y. -R. Chen, Z. Chen, H. Cheng, C. K. Cheong, H. Y. Cheung, H. Y. Chia, F. Chiadini, C-Y. Chiang, G. Chiarini, R. Chierici, A. Chincarini, M. L. Chiofalo, A. Chiummo, R. K. Choudhary, S. Choudhary, N. Christensen, Q. Chu, Y-K. Chu, S. S. Y. Chua, K. W. Chung, G. Ciani, P. Ciecielag, M. Cie\'slar, M. Cifaldi, A. A. Ciobanu, R. Ciolfi, F. Cipriano, F. Clara, J. A. Clark, P. Clearwater, S. Clesse, F. Cleva, E. Coccia, E. Codazzo, P. -F. Cohadon, D. E. Cohen, M. Colleoni, C. G. Collette, A. Colombo, M. Colpi, C. M. Compton, M. Constancio Jr., L. Conti, S. J. Cooper, P. Corban, T. R. Corbitt, I. Cordero-Carri\'on, S. Corezzi, K. R. Corley, N. J. Cornish, D. Corre, A. Corsi, S. Cortese, C. A. Costa, R. Cotesta, R. Cottingham, M. W. Coughlin, J. -P. Coulon, S. T. Countryman, B. Cousins, P. Couvares, D. M. Coward, M. J. Cowart, D. C. Coyne, R. Coyne, J. D. E. Creighton, T. D. Creighton, A. W. Criswell, M. Croquette, S. G. Crowder, J. R. Cudell, T. J. Cullen, A. Cumming, R. Cummings, L. Cunningham, E. Cuoco, M. Cury{\l}o, P. Dabadie, T. Dal Canton, S. Dall'Osso, G. D\'alya, A. Dana, B. D'Angelo, S. Danilishin, S. D'Antonio, K. Danzmann, C. Darsow-Fromm, A. Dasgupta, L. E. H. Datrier, Sayak Datta, Sayantani Datta, V. Dattilo, I. Dave, M. Davier, D. Davis, M. C. Davis, E. J. Daw, R. Dean, D. DeBra, M. Deenadayalan, J. Degallaix, M. De Laurentis, S. Del\'eglise, V. Del Favero, F. De Lillo, N. De Lillo, D. Dell'Aquila, W. Del Pozzo, L. M. DeMarchi, F. De Matteis, V. D'Emilio, N. Demos, T. Dent, A. Depasse, R. De Pietri, R. De Rosa, C. De Rossi, R. DeSalvo, R. De Simone, S. Dhurandhar, M. C. D\'iaz, N. A. Didio, T. Dietrich, L. Di Fiore, C. Di Fronzo, C. Di Giorgio, F. Di Giovanni, M. Di Giovanni, T. Di Girolamo, A. Di Lieto, A. Di Michele, B. Ding, S. Di Pace, I. Di Palma, F. Di Renzo, A. K. Divakarla,  Divyajyoti, A. Dmitriev, Z. Doctor, L. Donahue, L. D'Onofrio, F. Donovan, K. L. Dooley, S. Doravari, M. Drago, J. C. Driggers, Y. Drori, J. -G. Ducoin, P. Dupej, U. Dupletsa, O. Durante, D. D'Urso, P. -A. Duverne, S. E. Dwyer, C. Eassa, P. J. Easter, M. Ebersold, T. Eckhardt, G. Eddolls, B. Edelman, T. B. Edo, O. Edy, A. Effler, S. Eguchi, J. Eichholz, S. S. Eikenberry, M. Eisenmann, R. A. Eisenstein, A. Ejlli, E. Engelby, Y. Enomoto, L. Errico, R. C. Essick, H. Estell\'es, D. Estevez, Z. Etienne, T. Etzel, M. Evans, T. M. Evans, T. Evstafyeva, B. E. Ewing, F. Fabrizi, F. Faedi, V. Fafone, H. Fair, S. Fairhurst, P. C. Fan, A. M. Farah, S. Farinon, B. Farr, W. M. Farr, E. J. Fauchon-Jones, G. Favaro, M. Favata, M. Fays, M. Fazio, J. Feicht, M. M. Fejer, E. Fenyvesi, D. L. Ferguson, A. Fernandez-Galiana, I. Ferrante, T. A. Ferreira, F. Fidecaro, P. Figura, A. Fiori, I. Fiori, M. Fishbach, R. P. Fisher, R. Fittipaldi, V. Fiumara, R. Flaminio, E. Floden, H. K. Fong, J. A. Font, B. Fornal, P. W. F. Forsyth, A. Franke, S. Frasca, F. Frasconi, J. P. Freed, Z. Frei, A. Freise, O. Freitas, R. Frey, P. Fritschel, V. V. Frolov, G. G. Fronz\'e, Y. Fujii, Y. Fujikawa, Y. Fujimoto, P. Fulda, M. Fyffe, H. A. Gabbard, W. E. Gabella, B. U. Gadre, J. R. Gair, J. Gais, S. Galaudage, R. Gamba, D. Ganapathy, A. Ganguly, D. Gao, S. G. Gaonkar, B. Garaventa, C. Garc\'ia N\'u\~nez, C. Garc\'ia-Quir\'os, F. Garufi, B. Gateley, V. Gayathri, G. -G. Ge, G. Gemme, A. Gennai, V. Gennari, J. George, O. Gerberding, L. Gergely, P. Gewecke, S. Ghonge, Abhirup Ghosh, Archisman Ghosh, Shaon Ghosh, Shrobana Ghosh, Tathagata Ghosh, B. Giacomazzo, L. Giacoppo, J. A. Giaime, K. D. Giardina, D. R. Gibson, C. Gier, M. Giesler, P. Giri, F. Gissi, S. Gkaitatzis, J. Glanzer, A. E. Gleckl, P. Godwin, E. Goetz, R. Goetz, N. Gohlke, J. Golomb, B. Goncharov, G. Gonz\'alez, M. Gosselin, R. Gouaty, D. W. Gould, S. Goyal, B. Grace, A. Grado, V. Graham, M. Granata, V. Granata, A. Grant, S. Gras, P. Grassia, C. Gray, R. Gray, G. Greco, A. C. Green, R. Green, A. M. Gretarsson, E. M. Gretarsson, D. Griffith, W. L. Griffiths, H. L. Griggs, G. Grignani, A. Grimaldi, E. Grimes, S. J. Grimm, H. Grote, S. Grunewald, P. Gruning, A. S. Gruson, D. Guerra, G. M. Guidi, A. R. Guimaraes, G. Guix\'e, H. K. Gulati, A. M. Gunny, H. -K. Guo, Y. Guo, Anchal Gupta, Anuradha Gupta, I. M. Gupta, P. Gupta, S. K. Gupta, R. Gustafson, F. Guzman, S. Ha, I. P. W. Hadiputrawan, L. Haegel, S. Haino, O. Halim, E. D. Hall, E. Z. Hamilton, G. Hammond, W. -B. Han, M. Haney, J. Hanks, C. Hanna, M. D. Hannam, O. Hannuksela, H. Hansen, T. J. Hansen, J. Hanson, T. Harder, K. Haris, J. Harms, G. M. Harry, I. W. Harry, D. Hartwig, K. Hasegawa, B. Haskell, C. -J. Haster, J. S. Hathaway, K. Hattori, K. Haughian, H. Hayakawa, K. Hayama, F. J. Hayes, J. Healy, A. Heidmann, A. Heidt, M. C. Heintze, J. Heinze, J. Heinzel, H. Heitmann, F. Hellman, P. Hello, A. F. Helmling-Cornell, G. Hemming, M. Hendry, I. S. Heng, E. Hennes, J. Hennig, M. H. Hennig, C. Henshaw, A. G. Hernandez, F. Hernandez Vivanco, M. Heurs, A. L. Hewitt, S. Higginbotham, S. Hild, P. Hill, Y. Himemoto, A. S. Hines, N. Hirata, C. Hirose, T-C. Ho, S. Hochheim, D. Hofman, J. N. Hohmann, D. G. Holcomb, N. A. Holland, I. J. Hollows, Z. J. Holmes, K. Holt, D. E. Holz, Q. Hong, J. Hough, S. Hourihane, E. J. Howell, C. G. Hoy, D. Hoyland, A. Hreibi, B-H. Hsieh, H-F. Hsieh, C. Hsiung, Y. Hsu, H-Y. Huang, P. Huang, Y-C. Huang, Y. -J. Huang, Yiting Huang, Yiwen Huang, M. T. H\"ubner, A. D. Huddart, B. Hughey, D. C. Y. Hui, V. Hui, S. Husa, S. H. Huttner, R. Huxford, T. Huynh-Dinh, S. Ide, B. Idzkowski, A. Iess, K. Inayoshi, Y. Inoue, P. Iosif, M. Isi, K. Isleif, K. Ito, Y. Itoh, B. R. Iyer, V. JaberianHamedan, T. Jacqmin, P. -E. Jacquet, S. J. Jadhav, S. P. Jadhav, T. Jain, A. L. James, A. Z. Jan, K. Jani, J. Janquart, K. Janssens, N. N. Janthalur, P. Jaranowski, D. Jariwala, R. Jaume, A. C. Jenkins, K. Jenner, C. Jeon, W. Jia, J. Jiang, H. -B. Jin, G. R. Johns, N. K. Johnson-McDaniel, R. Johnston, A. W. Jones, D. I. Jones, P. Jones, R. Jones, P. Joshi, L. Ju, A. Jue, P. Jung, K. Jung, J. Junker, V. Juste, K. Kaihotsu, T. Kajita, M. Kakizaki, C. V. Kalaghatgi, V. Kalogera, B. Kamai, M. Kamiizumi, N. Kanda, S. Kandhasamy, G. Kang, J. B. Kanner, Y. Kao, S. J. Kapadia, D. P. Kapasi, C. Karathanasis, S. Karki, R. Kashyap, M. Kasprzack, W. Kastaun, T. Kato, S. Katsanevas, E. Katsavounidis, W. Katzman, T. Kaur, K. Kawabe, K. Kawaguchi, F. K\'ef\'elian, D. Keitel, J. S. Key, S. Khadka, F. Y. Khalili, S. Khan, T. Khanam, E. A. Khazanov, N. Khetan, M. Khursheed, N. Kijbunchoo, A. Kim, C. Kim, J. C. Kim, J. Kim, K. Kim, W. S. Kim, Y. -M. Kim, C. Kimball, N. Kimura, M. Kinley-Hanlon, R. Kirchhoff, J. S. Kissel, S. Klimenko, T. Klinger, A. M. Knee, T. D. Knowles, N. Knust, E. Knyazev, Y. Kobayashi, P. Koch, G. Koekoek, K. Kohri, K. Kokeyama, S. Koley, P. Kolitsidou, M. Kolstein, K. Komori, V. Kondrashov, A. K. H. Kong, A. Kontos, N. Koper, M. Korobko, M. Kovalam, N. Koyama, D. B. Kozak, C. Kozakai, V. Kringel, N. V. Krishnendu, A. Kr\'olak, G. Kuehn, F. Kuei, P. Kuijer, S. Kulkarni, A. Kumar, Prayush Kumar, Rahul Kumar, Rakesh Kumar, J. Kume, K. Kuns, Y. Kuromiya, S. Kuroyanagi, K. Kwak, G. Lacaille, P. Lagabbe, D. Laghi, E. Lalande, M. Lalleman, T. L. Lam, A. Lamberts, M. Landry, B. B. Lane, R. N. Lang, J. Lange, B. Lantz, I. La Rosa, A. Lartaux-Vollard, P. D. Lasky, M. Laxen, A. Lazzarini, C. Lazzaro, P. Leaci, S. Leavey, S. LeBohec, Y. K. Lecoeuche, E. Lee, H. M. Lee, H. W. Lee, K. Lee, R. Lee, I. N. Legred, J. Lehmann, A. Lema\^itre, M. Lenti, M. Leonardi, E. Leonova, N. Leroy, N. Letendre, C. Levesque, Y. Levin, J. N. Leviton, K. Leyde, A. K. Y. Li, B. Li, J. Li, K. L. Li, P. Li, T. G. F. Li, X. Li, C-Y. Lin, E. T. Lin, F-K. Lin, F-L. Lin, H. L. Lin, L. C. -C. Lin, F. Linde, S. D. Linker, J. N. Linley, T. B. Littenberg, G. C. Liu, J. Liu, K. Liu, X. Liu, F. Llamas, R. K. L. Lo, T. Lo, L. T. London, A. Longo, D. Lopez, M. Lopez Portilla, M. Lorenzini, V. Loriette, M. Lormand, G. Losurdo, T. P. Lott, J. D. Lough, C. O. Lousto, G. Lovelace, J. F. Lucaccioni, H. L\"uck, D. Lumaca, A. P. Lundgren, L. -W. Luo, J. E. Lynam, M. Ma'arif, R. Macas, J. B. Machtinger, M. MacInnis, D. M. Macleod, I. A. O. MacMillan, A. Macquet, I. Maga\~na Hernandez, C. Magazz\`u, R. M. Magee, E. Maggio, R. Maggiore, M. Magnozzi, S. Mahesh, E. Majorana, I. Maksimovic, S. Maliakal, A. Malik, N. Man, V. Mandic, V. Mangano, G. L. Mansell, M. Manske, M. Mantovani, M. Mapelli, F. Marchesoni, D. Mar\'in Pina, F. Marion, Z. Mark, S. M\'arka, Z. M\'arka, C. Markakis, A. S. Markosyan, A. Markowitz, E. Maros, A. Marquina, S. Marsat, F. Martelli, I. W. Martin, R. M. Martin, M. Martinez, V. A. Martinez, V. Martinez, K. Martinovic, D. V. Martynov, E. J. Marx, H. Masalehdan, K. Mason, E. Massera, A. Masserot, M. Masso-Reid, S. Mastrogiovanni, A. Matas, M. Mateu-Lucena, F. Matichard, M. Matiushechkina, N. Mavalvala, J. J. McCann, R. McCarthy, D. E. McClelland, P. K. McClincy, S. McCormick, L. McCuller, G. I. McGhee, S. C. McGuire, C. McIsaac, J. McIver, T. McRae, S. T. McWilliams, D. Meacher, M. Mehmet, A. K. Mehta, Q. Meijer, A. Melatos, D. A. Melchor, G. Mendell, A. Menendez-Vazquez, C. S. Menoni, R. A. Mercer, L. Mereni, K. Merfeld, E. L. Merilh, J. D. Merritt, M. Merzougui, S. Meshkov, C. Messenger, C. Messick, P. M. Meyers, F. Meylahn, A. Mhaske, A. Miani, H. Miao, I. Michaloliakos, C. Michel, Y. Michimura, H. Middleton, D. P. Mihaylov, L. Milano, A. L. Miller, A. Miller, B. Miller, M. Millhouse, J. C. Mills, E. Milotti, Y. Minenkov, N. Mio, Ll. M. Mir, M. Miravet-Ten\'es, A. Mishkin, C. Mishra, T. Mishra, T. Mistry, S. Mitra, V. P. Mitrofanov, G. Mitselmakher, R. Mittleman, O. Miyakawa, K. Miyo, S. Miyoki, Geoffrey Mo, L. M. Modafferi, E. Moguel, K. Mogushi, S. R. P. Mohapatra, S. R. Mohite, I. Molina, M. Molina-Ruiz, M. Mondin, M. Montani, C. J. Moore, J. Moragues, D. Moraru, F. Morawski, A. More, C. Moreno, G. Moreno, Y. Mori, S. Morisaki, N. Morisue, Y. Moriwaki, B. Mours, C. M. Mow-Lowry, S. Mozzon, F. Muciaccia, Arunava Mukherjee, D. Mukherjee, Soma Mukherjee, Subroto Mukherjee, Suvodip Mukherjee, N. Mukund, A. Mullavey, J. Munch, E. A. Mu\~niz, P. G. Murray, R. Musenich, S. Muusse, S. L. Nadji, K. Nagano, A. Nagar, K. Nakamura, H. Nakano, M. Nakano, Y. Nakayama, V. Napolano, I. Nardecchia, T. Narikawa, H. Narola, L. Naticchioni, B. Nayak, R. K. Nayak, B. F. Neil, J. Neilson, A. Nelson, T. J. N. Nelson, M. Nery, P. Neubauer, A. Neunzert, K. Y. Ng, S. W. S. Ng, C. Nguyen, P. Nguyen, T. Nguyen, L. Nguyen Quynh, J. Ni, W. -T. Ni, S. A. Nichols, T. Nishimoto, A. Nishizawa, S. Nissanke, E. Nitoglia, F. Nocera, M. Norman, C. North, S. Nozaki, G. Nurbek, L. K. Nuttall, Y. Obayashi, J. Oberling, B. D. O'Brien, J. O'Dell, E. Oelker, W. Ogaki, G. Oganesyan, J. J. Oh, K. Oh, S. H. Oh, M. Ohashi, T. Ohashi, M. Ohkawa, F. Ohme, H. Ohta, M. A. Okada, Y. Okutani, C. Olivetto, K. Oohara, R. Oram, B. O'Reilly, R. G. Ormiston, N. D. Ormsby, R. O'Shaughnessy, E. O'Shea, S. Oshino, S. Ossokine, C. Osthelder, S. Otabe, D. J. Ottaway, H. Overmier, A. E. Pace, G. Pagano, R. Pagano, M. A. Page, G. Pagliaroli, A. Pai, S. A. Pai, S. Pal, J. R. Palamos, O. Palashov, C. Palomba, H. Pan, K. -C. Pan, P. K. Panda, P. T. H. Pang, C. Pankow, F. Pannarale, B. C. Pant, F. H. Panther, F. Paoletti, A. Paoli, A. Paolone, G. Pappas, A. Parisi, H. Park, J. Park, W. Parker, D. Pascucci, A. Pasqualetti, R. Passaquieti, D. Passuello, M. Patel, M. Pathak, B. Patricelli, A. S. Patron, S. Paul, E. Payne, M. Pedraza, R. Pedurand, M. Pegoraro, A. Pele, F. E. Pe\~na Arellano, S. Penano, S. Penn, A. Perego, A. Pereira, T. Pereira, C. J. Perez, C. P\'erigois, C. C. Perkins, A. Perreca, S. Perri\`es, D. Pesios, J. Petermann, D. Petterson, H. P. Pfeiffer, H. Pham, K. A. Pham, K. S. Phukon, H. Phurailatpam, O. J. Piccinni, M. Pichot, M. Piendibene, F. Piergiovanni, L. Pierini, V. Pierro, G. Pillant, M. Pillas, F. Pilo, L. Pinard, C. Pineda-Bosque, I. M. Pinto, M. Pinto, B. J. Piotrzkowski, K. Piotrzkowski, M. Pirello, M. D. Pitkin, A. Placidi, E. Placidi, M. L. Planas, W. Plastino, C. Pluchar, R. Poggiani, E. Polini, L. Pompili, D. Y. T. Pong, S. Ponrathnam, E. K. Porter, R. Poulton, A. Poverman, J. Powell, M. Pracchia, T. Pradier, A. K. Prajapati, K. Prasai, R. Prasanna, G. Pratten, M. Principe, G. A. Prodi, L. Prokhorov, P. Prosposito, L. Prudenzi, A. Puecher, M. Punturo, F. Puosi, P. Puppo, M. P\"urrer, H. Qi, N. Quartey, V. Quetschke, P. J. Quinonez, R. Quitzow-James, N. Qutob, F. J. Raab, G. Raaijmakers, H. Radkins, N. Radulesco, P. Raffai, S. X. Rail, S. Raja, C. Rajan, K. E. Ramirez, T. D. Ramirez, A. Ramos-Buades, J. Rana, P. Rapagnani, A. Ray, V. Raymond, N. Raza, M. Razzano, J. Read, L. A. Rees, T. Regimbau, L. Rei, S. Reid, S. W. Reid, D. H. Reitze, P. Relton, A. Renzini, P. Rettegno, B. Revenu, A. Reza, M. Rezac, F. Ricci, D. Richards, J. W. Richardson, L. Richardson, G. Riemenschneider, K. Riles, S. Rinaldi, K. Rink, N. A. Robertson, R. Robie, F. Robinet, A. Rocchi, S. Rodriguez, L. Rolland, J. G. Rollins, M. Romanelli, R. Romano, C. L. Romel, A. Romero, I. M. Romero-Shaw, J. H. Romie, S. Ronchini, L. Rosa, C. A. Rose, D. Rosi\'nska, M. P. Ross, S. Rowan, S. J. Rowlinson, S. Roy, Santosh Roy, Soumen Roy, D. Rozza, P. Ruggi, K. Ruiz-Rocha, K. Ryan, S. Sachdev, T. Sadecki, J. Sadiq, S. Saha, Y. Saito, K. Sakai, M. Sakellariadou, S. Sakon, O. S. Salafia, F. Salces-Carcoba, L. Salconi, M. Saleem, F. Salemi, A. Samajdar, E. J. Sanchez, J. H. Sanchez, L. E. Sanchez, N. Sanchis-Gual, J. R. Sanders, A. Sanuy, T. R. Saravanan, N. Sarin, B. Sassolas, H. Satari, B. S. Sathyaprakash, O. Sauter, R. L. Savage, V. Savant, T. Sawada, H. L. Sawant, S. Sayah, D. Schaetzl, M. Scheel, J. Scheuer, M. G. Schiworski, P. Schmidt, S. Schmidt, R. Schnabel, M. Schneewind, R. M. S. Schofield, A. Sch\"onbeck, B. W. Schulte, B. F. Schutz, E. Schwartz, J. Scott, S. M. Scott, M. Seglar-Arroyo, Y. Sekiguchi, D. Sellers, A. S. Sengupta, D. Sentenac, E. G. Seo, V. Sequino, A. Sergeev, Y. Setyawati, T. Shaffer, M. S. Shahriar, M. A. Shaikh, B. Shams, L. Shao, A. Sharma, P. Sharma, P. Shawhan, N. S. Shcheblanov, A. Sheela, Y. Shikano, M. Shikauchi, H. Shimizu, K. Shimode, H. Shinkai, T. Shishido, A. Shoda, D. H. Shoemaker, D. M. Shoemaker, S. ShyamSundar, M. Sieniawska, D. Sigg, L. Silenzi, L. P. Singer, D. Singh, M. K. Singh, N. Singh, A. Singha, A. M. Sintes, V. Sipala, V. Skliris, B. J. J. Slagmolen, T. J. Slaven-Blair, J. Smetana, J. R. Smith, L. Smith, R. J. E. Smith, J. Soldateschi, S. N. Somala, K. Somiya, I. Song, K. Soni, S. Soni, V. Sordini, F. Sorrentino, N. Sorrentino, R. Soulard, T. Souradeep, E. Sowell, V. Spagnuolo, A. P. Spencer, M. Spera, P. Spinicelli, A. K. Srivastava, V. Srivastava, K. Staats, C. Stachie, F. Stachurski, D. A. Steer, J. Steinhoff, J. Steinlechner, S. Steinlechner, N. Stergioulas, D. J. Stops, M. Stover, K. A. Strain, L. C. Strang, G. Stratta, M. D. Strong, A. Strunk, R. Sturani, A. L. Stuver, M. Suchenek, S. Sudhagar, V. Sudhir, R. Sugimoto, H. G. Suh, A. G. Sullivan, J. M. Sullivan, T. Z. Summerscales, L. Sun, S. Sunil, A. Sur, J. Suresh, P. J. Sutton, Takamasa Suzuki, Takanori Suzuki, Toshikazu Suzuki, B. L. Swinkels, M. J. Szczepa\'nczyk, P. Szewczyk, M. Tacca, H. Tagoshi, S. C. Tait, H. Takahashi, R. Takahashi, S. Takano, H. Takeda, M. Takeda, C. J. Talbot, C. Talbot, K. Tanaka, Taiki Tanaka, Takahiro Tanaka, A. J. Tanasijczuk, S. Tanioka, D. B. Tanner, D. Tao, L. Tao, R. D. Tapia, E. N. Tapia San Mart\'in, C. Taranto, A. Taruya, J. D. Tasson, R. Tenorio, J. E. S. Terhune, L. Terkowski, M. P. Thirugnanasambandam, M. Thomas, P. Thomas, E. E. Thompson, J. E. Thompson, S. R. Thondapu, K. A. Thorne, E. Thrane, Shubhanshu Tiwari, Srishti Tiwari, V. Tiwari, A. M. Toivonen, A. E. Tolley, T. Tomaru, T. Tomura, M. Tonelli, Z. Tornasi, A. Torres-Forn\'e, C. I. Torrie, I. Tosta e Melo, D. T\"oyr\"a, A. Trapananti, F. Travasso, G. Traylor, M. Trevor, M. C. Tringali, A. Tripathee, L. Troiano, A. Trovato, L. Trozzo, R. J. Trudeau, D. Tsai, K. W. Tsang, T. Tsang, J-S. Tsao, M. Tse, R. Tso, S. Tsuchida, L. Tsukada, D. Tsuna, T. Tsutsui, K. Turbang, M. Turconi, D. Tuyenbayev, A. S. Ubhi, N. Uchikata, T. Uchiyama, R. P. Udall, A. Ueda, T. Uehara, K. Ueno, G. Ueshima, C. S. Unnikrishnan, A. L. Urban, T. Ushiba, A. Utina, G. Vajente, A. Vajpeyi, G. Valdes, M. Valentini, V. Valsan, N. van Bakel, M. van Beuzekom, M. van Dael, J. F. J. van den Brand, C. Van Den Broeck, D. C. Vander-Hyde, H. van Haevermaet, J. V. van Heijningen, M. H. P. M. van Putten, N. van Remortel, M. Vardaro, A. F. Vargas, V. Varma, M. Vas\'uth, A. Vecchio, G. Vedovato, J. Veitch, P. J. Veitch, J. Venneberg, G. Venugopalan, D. Verkindt, P. Verma, Y. Verma, S. M. Vermeulen, D. Veske, F. Vetrano, A. Vicer\'e, S. Vidyant, A. D. Viets, A. Vijaykumar, V. Villa-Ortega, J. -Y. Vinet, A. Virtuoso, S. Vitale, H. Vocca, E. R. G. von Reis, J. S. A. von Wrangel, C. Vorvick, S. P. Vyatchanin, L. E. Wade, M. Wade, K. J. Wagner, R. Wald, R. C. Walet, M. Walker, G. S. Wallace, L. Wallace, J. Wang, J. Z. Wang, W. H. Wang, R. L. Ward, J. Warner, M. Was, T. Washimi, N. Y. Washington, J. Watchi, B. Weaver, C. R. Weaving, S. A. Webster, M. Weinert, A. J. Weinstein, R. Weiss, C. M. Weller, R. A. Weller, F. Wellmann, L. Wen, P. We{\ss}els, K. Wette, J. T. Whelan, D. D. White, B. F. Whiting, C. Whittle, D. Wilken, D. Williams, M. J. Williams, A. R. Williamson, J. L. Willis, B. Willke, D. J. Wilson, C. C. Wipf, T. Wlodarczyk, G. Woan, J. Woehler, J. K. Wofford, D. Wong, I. C. F. Wong, M. Wright, C. Wu, D. S. Wu, H. Wu, D. M. Wysocki, L. Xiao, T. Yamada, H. Yamamoto, K. Yamamoto, T. Yamamoto, K. Yamashita, R. Yamazaki, F. W. Yang, K. Z. Yang, L. Yang, Y. -C. Yang, Y. Yang, Yang Yang, M. J. Yap, D. W. Yeeles, S. -W. Yeh, A. B. Yelikar, M. Ying, J. Yokoyama, T. Yokozawa, J. Yoo, T. Yoshioka, Hang Yu, Haocun Yu, H. Yuzurihara, A. Zadro\.zny, M. Zanolin, S. Zeidler, T. Zelenova, J. -P. Zendri, M. Zevin, M. Zhan, H. Zhang, J. Zhang, L. Zhang, R. Zhang, T. Zhang, Y. Zhang, C. Zhao, G. Zhao, Y. Zhao, Yue Zhao, R. Zhou, Z. Zhou, X. J. Zhu, Z. -H. Zhu, A. B. Zimmerman, M. E. Zucker, J. Zweizig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Search for Classical Subsystems in Quantum Worlds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10895v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Decoherence and einselection have been effective in explaining several features of an emergent classical world from an underlying quantum theory. However, the theory assumes a particular factorization of the global Hilbert space into constituent system and environment subsystems, as well as specially constructed Hamiltonians. In this work, we take a systematic approach to discover, given a fixed Hamiltonian, (potentially) several factorizations (or tensor product structures) of a global Hilbert space that admit a quasi-classical description of subsystems in the sense that certain states (the "pointer states") are robust to entanglement. We show that every Hamiltonian admits a pointer basis in the factorization where the energy eigenvectors are separable. Furthermore, we implement an algorithm that allows us to discover a multitude of factorizations that admit pointer states and use it to explore these quasi-classical "realms" for both random and structured Hamiltonians. We also derive several analytical forms that the Hamiltonian may take in such factorizations, each with its unique set of features. Our approach has several implications: it enables us to derive the division into quasi-classical subsystems, demonstrates that decohering subsystems do not necessarily align with our classical notion of locality, and challenges ideas expressed by some authors that the propensity of a system to exhibit classical dynamics relies on minimizing the interaction between subsystems. From a quantum foundations perspective, these results lead to interesting ramifications for relative-state interpretations. From a quantum engineering perspective, these results may be useful in characterizing decoherence free subspaces and other passive error avoidance protocols.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10895v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arsalan Adil, Manuel S. Rudolph, Andrew Arrasmith, Zo\"e Holmes, Andreas Albrecht, Andrew Sornborger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A universal framework for the quantum simulation of Yang-Mills theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13161</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13161v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We provide a universal framework for the quantum simulation of SU(N) Yang--Mills theories on fault-tolerant digital quantum computers adopting the orbifold lattice formulation. As warm-up examples, we also consider simple models, including scalar field theory and the Yang--Mills matrix model, to illustrate the universality of our formulation, which shows up in the fact that the truncated Hamiltonian can be expressed in the same simple form for any N, any dimension, and any lattice size, in stark contrast to the popular approach based on the Kogut--Susskind formulation. In all these cases, the truncated Hamiltonian can be programmed on a quantum computer using only standard tools well-established in the field of quantum computation. As a concrete application of this universal framework, we consider Hamiltonian time evolution by Suzuki--Trotter decomposition. This turns out to be a straightforward task due to the simplicity of the truncated Hamiltonian. We also provide a simple circuit structure that contains only CNOT and one-qubit gates, independent of the details of the theory investigated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13161v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jad C. Halimeh, Masanori Hanada, Shunji Matsuura, Franco Nori, Enrico Rinaldi, Andreas Sch\"afer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complementarity between Cosmic String Gravitational Waves and long-lived particle searches in a laboratory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03326v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Cosmic strings are powerful witnesses to cosmic events including any period of early matter domination. If such a period of matter domination was catalysed by metastable, long-lived particles, then there will be complementary signals to ascertain the nature of dark sector in experiments detecting primordial features in the gravitational wave (GW) power spectrum and laboratory searches for long-lived particles. We give explicit examples of global and local U(1) gauge extended dark sectors to demonstrate such a complementarity as the union of the two experiments reveals more information about the dark sector than either experiment. Demanding that Higgs-portal long-lived scalar be looked for, in various experiments such as DUNE, FASER, FASER-II, MATHUSLA, SHiP, we identify the parameter space which leads to complementary observables for GW detectors such as LISA and ET.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03326v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/fcg5-bkbn</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Satyabrata Datta, Ambar Ghosal, Anish Ghoshal, Graham White</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complementary signatures of $\alpha-$attractor inflation in CMB and cosmic string Gravitational Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03557</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.03557v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: When cosmic strings are formed during inflation, they regrow to reach a scaling regime, leaving distinct imprints on the stochastic gravitational wave background (SGWB). Such signatures, associated with specific primordial features, can be detected by upcoming gravitational wave observatories, such as the LISA and Einstein Telescope (ET). Our analysis explores scenarios in which cosmic strings form either before or during inflation. We examine how the number of e-folds experienced by cosmic strings during inflation correlates with the predictions of inflationary models observable in cosmic microwave background (CMB) measurements. This correlation provides a testable link between inflationary physics and the associated gravitational wave signals in a complementary manner. Focusing on $\alpha$-attractor models of inflation, with the Polynomial $\alpha$-attractor serving as an illustrative example, we find constraints, for instance, on the spectral index $n_s$ to $0.962 \lesssim n_s \lesssim 0.972$ for polynomial exponent $n=1$, $0.956 \lesssim n_s \lesssim 0.968$ for $n=2$, $0.954 \lesssim n_s \lesssim 0.965$ for $n=3$, and $0.963 \lesssim n_s \lesssim 0.964$ for $n=4$, which along with the GW signals from LISA, are capable of detecting local cosmic strings that have experienced $\sim 34 - 47$ e-folds of inflation consistent with current Planck data and are also testable in upcoming CMB experiments such as LiteBIRD and CMB-S4.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.03557v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/81v4-pp8q</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Mainak Baidya, Anish Ghoshal, David F. Mota</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-interacting holographic dark energy with Torsion via Hubble Radius</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19880</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19880v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We reconstruct a holographic dark energy model within a Friedmann cosmology incorporating torsion scalar, assuming no interaction between dark energy and dark matter. Setting the Hubble radius as an infrared (IR) cut-off, we focus on a system dominated by contribution of a time-dependent torsion scalar induced by the spin of matter. In this regime, our results show that even very weak torsion causes cosmic acceleration. Specifically, we find that minima of the current equation of state for holographic dark energy, $(\omega_X^{0})_{min}$, lies in the range $-1 &lt; (\omega_X^{0})_{min} &lt; -0.778$ as a free parameter $d$ varies from $1$ to $0.654$. Focusing on the free parameter $d \approx 1$, we find that $(\omega_X^{0})_{min}$ exhibits slightly different behavior from the cosmological constant. Introducing torsion allows the Hubble radius to serve as a viable IR cut-off even without assuming the interaction between them. Moreover, this approach provides a non-interacting limit not found in earlier interacting models that use the Hubble radius as the IR cut-off.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19880v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongjun Yun, Jungjai Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact Chiral Symmetries of 3+1D Hamiltonian Lattice Fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07708v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct Hamiltonian models on a 3+1d cubic lattice for a single Weyl fermion and for a single Weyl doublet protected by exact (as opposed to emergent) chiral symmetries. In the former, we find a not-on-site, non-compact chiral symmetry which can be viewed as a Hamiltonian analog of the Ginsparg-Wilson symmetry in Euclidean lattice models of Weyl fermions. In the latter, we combine an on-site $U(1)$ symmetry with a not-on-site $U(1)$ symmetry, which together generate the $SU(2)$ flavor symmetry of the doublet at low energies, while in the UV they generate an algebra known in integrability as the Onsager algebra. This latter model is in fact the celebrated magnetic Weyl semimetal which is known to have a chiral anomaly from the action of $U(1)$ and crystalline translation, that gives rise to an anomalous Hall response - however reinterpreted in our language, it has two exact $U(1)$ symmetries that gives rise to the global $SU(2)$ anomaly which protects the gaplessness even when crystalline translations are broken. We also construct an exact symmetry-protected single Dirac cone in 2+1d with the $U(1) \rtimes T$ parity anomaly. Our constructions evade both old and recently-proven no-go theorems by using not-on-siteness in a crucial way, showing our results are sharp.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07708v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Gioia, Ryan Thorngren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Korteweg-de Vries Integrals for Modified Black Hole Potentials: Instabilities and other Questions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09918</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.09918v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quasi-normal modes (QNMs) and greybody factors are some of the most characteristic features of the dynamics of black holes (BHs) and represent the basis for a number of fundamental physics tests with gravitational wave observations. It is therefore important to understand the properties of these quantities, naturally introduced within BH perturbation theory, in particular the stability properties under modifications of the BH potential. Instabilities in the QNMs have been recently shown to appear in the BH pseudospectrum under certain circumstances. In this work, we give a novel point of view based on the existence of some recently discovered hidden symmetries in BH dynamics and the associated infinite series of conserved quantities, the Korteweg-de Vries (KdV) integrals. We provide different motivations to use the KdV integrals as indicators of some crucial BH spectral properties. In particular, by studying them in different scenarios described by modified BH barriers, we find strong evidence that the KdV conserved quantities represent a useful tool to look for instabilities in the BH spectrum of QNMs and in their greybody factors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.09918v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/09/021</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 09 (2025) 021</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Michele Lenzi (ICE-CSIC, IEEC), Arnau Montava Agudo (ICE-CSIC, UIB), Carlos F. Sopuerta (ICE-CSIC, IEEC)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insights on the Cosmic Origin of Matter from Proton Stability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18259</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.18259v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the phenomenology of a model in which the proton is rendered absolutely stable by an IR mechanism that remains robust against unknown quantum gravity effects. A linear combination of baryon number and lepton flavors is gauged and spontaneously broken to a residual $\mathbb{Z}_9$ discrete gauge symmetry enforcing a strict selection rule: $\Delta B = 0\,(\mathrm{mod}\,3)$. Despite its minimal field content, the model successfully accounts for established empirical evidence of physics beyond the SM. High-scale symmetry breaking simultaneously provides a seesaw mechanism explaining the smallness of neutrino masses, minimal thermal leptogenesis, and a viable phenomenology of the majoron as dark matter. Any cosmic string-wall network remaining after inflation is unstable for numerous charge assignments. Lepton flavor non-universality, central to the construction, leads to predictive neutrino textures testable via oscillation experiments, neutrinoless double beta decay, and cosmology. The model motivates searches in $X$- and $\gamma$-ray lines, neutrino telescopes, and predicts CMB imprints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.18259v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/11/043</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP11(2025)043</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Admir Greljo, Xavier Ponce D\'iaz, Anders Eller Thomsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational wave cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19747v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Gravitational waves (GWs) originating from cosmological sources offer direct insights into the physics of the primordial Universe, the fundamental nature of gravity, and the cosmic expansion of the Universe. In this review paper, we present a comprehensive overview of our recent advances in GW cosmology, supported by the national key research and development program of China, focusing on cosmological GW sources and their implications for fundamental physics and cosmology. We first discuss the generation mechanisms and characteristics of stochastic gravitational wave backgrounds generated by physical processes occurred in the early Universe, including those from inflation, phase transitions, and topological defects, and summarize current and possible future constraints from pulsar timing array and space-based detectors. Next, we explore the formation and observational prospects of primordial black holes as GW sources and their potential connection to dark matter. We then analyze how GWs are affected by large-scale structure, cosmological perturbations, and possible modifications of gravity on GW propagation, and how these effects can be used to test fundamental symmetry of gravity. Finally, we discuss the application of GW standard sirens in measuring the Hubble constant, the expansion history, and dark energy parameters, including their combination with electromagnetic observations. These topics together show how GW observations, especially with upcoming space-based detectors, such as LISA, Taiji, and Tianqin, can provide new information about the physics of the early Universe, cosmological evolution, and the nature of gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19747v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11433-025-2740-8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Sci. China Phys. Mech. Astron. 69, 210401 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ligong Bian, Rong-Gen Cai, Yu-Qi Dong, Qing Gao, Yungui Gong, Zong-Kuan Guo, Qing-Guo Huang, Zhaofeng Kang, Li Li, Jing Liu, Lang Liu, Yu-Xiao Liu, Xuchen Lu, Zhi-Zhang Peng, Jin Qiao, Puxun Wu, Yue-Liang Wu, Jiang-Hao Yu, Chen Yuan, Chao Zhang, Tao Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Axion-mediated photon-to-photon transitions in high finesse dielectric resonators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04666v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Axions are hypothetical particles that could address both the strong charge-parity problem in quantum chromodynamics and the enigmatic nature of dark matter. However, if axions exist, their mass remains unknown, and they are expected to interact very weakly with the electromagnetic field, which explains why they have not been detected yet. This study proposes a way to substantially augment the axion-photon interaction by confining the photons within high-quality-factor dielectric resonators, increasing their intensity and lifetime, and thus the possibility of interacting with axions in the background. In view of this, we study resonant axion-mediated photonic transitions in millimeter-sized spherical dielectric resonators, based on fully analytical calculations to the first order in perturbation theory. Such resonators exhibit high lifetime Mie resonances in the microwave part of the spectrum, with a separation that can be tailored with the radius of the sphere to match the expected axion frequency, allowing axion-mediated photonic transitions when particular selection rules are fulfilled. We predict experimentally accessible axion mass regimes where such triply resonant transitions can be realized with standard dielectric resonators. We propose an experiment for probing such interactions named DARK-ROSE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04666v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evangelos Almpanis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MatBYIB: A Matlab-based code for Bayesian inference of extreme mass-ratio inspiral binary with arbitrary eccentricity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05954v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Accurate parameter estimation(PE) of gravitational waves(GW) is essential for GW data analysis. In extreme mass-ratio inspiral binary(EMRI) systems, orbital eccentricity is a critical parameter for PE. However, current software for for PE of GW often neglects the direct estimation of orbital eccentricity. To fill this gap, we have developed the MatBYIB, a MATLAB-based software package for PE of GW with arbitrary eccentricity. The MatBYIB employs the Analytical Kludge (AK) waveform as a computationally efficient signal generator and computes parameter uncertainties via the Fisher Information Matrix (FIM) and the Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC). For Bayesian inference, we implement the Metropolis-Hastings (M-H) algorithm to derive posterior distributions. To guarantee convergence, the Gelman-Rubin convergence criterion (the Potential Scale Reduction Factor R) is used to determine sampling adequacy, with MatBYIB dynamically increasing the sample size until R &lt; 1.05 for all parameters. Our results demonstrate strong agreement between FIM- based predictions and full MCMC sampling. This program is user-friendly and allows for estimation of gravitational wave parameters with arbitrary eccentricity on standard personal computers. Code availability:The implementation is open-source at https://github.com/GenliangLi/MatBYIB.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05954v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/universe11080259</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Universe 2025, 11(8), 259</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gen-Liang Li, Shu-Jie Zhao, Huai-Ke Guo, Jing-Yu Su, Zhen-Heng Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tri-hypercharge versus tri-darkcharge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12873v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a minimal, ultraviolet-complete, and renormalizable extension of the Standard Model, in which the three generations of ordinary fermions are distinguished by family-dependent hypercharges, while three right-handed neutrinos are separated by a dark gauge symmetry that is trivial for all Standard Model fields. This setup yields a fully flipped inert doublet model. The model naturally realizes a hybrid scotoseesaw mechanism that accounts for the smallness of neutrino masses and the largeness of lepton mixing. Simultaneously, it explains the stability and relic abundance of dark matter through a residual dark parity and addresses the hierarchies of charged fermion masses and the suppression of quark mixing via higher-dimensional operators involving high-scale scalar singlets and vector-like fermions. We explore the phenomenological implications of the model and derive constraints from electroweak precision tests, collider searches, flavor-changing processes, and observations of dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12873v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-025-14855-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur.Phys.J.C 85 (2025) 10, 1160</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Duong Van Loi, A. E. C\'arcamo Hern\'andez, Van Que Tran, N. T. Duy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interaction-enhanced quantum to classical transport crossover temperature in a Luttinger liquid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05356</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05356v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Strange metals are highly entangled gapless states of matter that exhibit anomalous transport, such as linear in temperature resistivity, over more than a decade of temperature. Why a single power law should be so robust is an open question. We propose a scenario in which interactions enhance the domain of certain scattering regimes, effectively suppressing other ``would-be regimes." We test this proposal in a one-dimensional Luttinger liquid coupled to a one-dimensional acoustic phonon. We use the memory matrix formalism to calculate the dc electrical and thermal conductivities at low and high temperatures, relative to the Debye cutoff on phonon frequencies, in both the ``clean" (umklapp scattering) and ``dirty" (disorder scattering) limits. We find the crossover temperature separating the low and high temperature regimes to be interaction-dependent, with repulsive interactions substantially increasing it, generally by more than an order of magnitude. This provides a concrete illustration for how interactions can extend a single transport regime over a wider temperature range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05356v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yen-Wen Lu, Michael Mulligan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interior Dynamics of Regular Schwarzschild Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00816v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present an exact, purely geometric account of the interior dynamics of Schwarzschild black holes, formulated without invoking any specific gravitational theory and free of additional charges beyond the total mass ${\cal M}$. We show that dynamical evolution generically produces new singularities, absent in the static case, whose resolution imposes highly restrictive conditions on gravitational collapse.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00816v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Ovalle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modified Black Hole Potentials and Their Korteweg-de Vries Integrals: Instabilities and Beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01500v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Black Hole (BH) Quasi-Normal Modes (QNMs) and Greybody Factors (GBFs) are key signatures of BH dynamics that are crucial for testing fundamental physics via gravitational waves. Recent studies of the BH pseudospectrum have revealed instabilities in QNMs. Here, we introduce a new perspective using hidden symmetries in the BH dynamics, specifically the Korteweg-de Vries (KdV) integrals - an infinite series of conserved quantities. By analyzing modified BH potentials, we find strong evidence that KdV integrals are valuable indicators for detecting instabilities in QNMs and GBFs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01500v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michele Lenzi (ICE-CSIC, IEEC), Arnau Montava Agudo (ICE-CSIC, UIB), Carlos F. Sopuerta (ICE-CSIC, IEEC)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is the $\Lambda$CDM Model in Crisis?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17124</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.17124v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present strong evidence for dynamical dark energy that challenges the standard $\Lambda$CDM model. Several dark energy scenarios are explored, including $\omega_0\omega_a$CDM, logarithmic, exponential, JBP, and BA parameterizations, along with non-flat cosmologies allowing for spatial curvature ($\Omega_k \neq 0$). Our analysis supports a flat Universe with $\Omega_k \approx 0$. Using MCMC techniques, we constrain these models with observational data from DESI~DR2 baryon acoustic oscillations, Type~Ia supernovae, and compressed CMB likelihoods. The results provide strong statistical evidence that $\omega \neq -1$, favoring dynamical dark-energy behavior consistent with a Quintom-B scenario ($\omega_0 &gt; -1$, $\omega_a &lt; 0$, and $\omega_0 + \omega_a &lt; -1$). We also derive upper bounds on the total neutrino mass, $\sum m_\nu$, using CMB + DESI~DR2 data: $\sum m_\nu &lt; 0.066~\mathrm{eV}$ for $\Lambda$CDM and $\sum m_\nu &lt; 0.075~\mathrm{eV}$ for $\omega$CDM. In the non-flat extensions, o$\Lambda$CDM and o$\omega$CDM, the limits relax to $\sum m_\nu &lt; 0.263~\mathrm{eV}$ and $\sum m_\nu &lt; 0.520~\mathrm{eV}$, respectively. For the other models $\omega_0\omega_a$CDM, logarithmic, exponential, JBP, BA, and GEDE the constraints range between $&lt;0.043$ and $&lt;0.127~\mathrm{eV}$. The effective number of relativistic species remains consistent with the standard value, $N_{\mathrm{eff}} = 3.044$, across all models. Bayesian evidence further shows that combining DES-SN5Y or Union3 supernova samples with CMB + DESI~DR2 produces measurable deviations from $\Lambda$CDM. Although no model reaches the $5\sigma$ significance threshold, several exhibit tensions exceeding $3\sigma$, suggesting emerging cracks in the cosmological constant paradigm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.17124v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jheap.2025.100507</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEAp 50, 100507 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Himanshu Chaudhary, Salvatore Capozziello, Subhrat Praharaj, Shibesh Kumar Jas Pacif, G. Mustafa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Importance of being nonminimally coupled: Scalar Hawking radiation from regular black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12257v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In curved space-time, a scalar field $\phi$ is generically expected to couple to curvature, via a coupling of the form $\xi\phi^2R$. Yet in the study of Hawking emission from regular black holes (RBHs), where scalar fields are often introduced as simple probes of the geometry, and the Ricci scalar is generically non-zero, this non-minimal coupling is almost always ignored. We revisit this assumption by studying scalar Hawking emission from four representative RBHs (the Bardeen, Hayward, Simpson-Visser, and D'Ambrosio-Rovelli space-times), within two benchmark cases: the conformal case $\xi=1/6$, and a large negative value $\xi=-10^4$ motivated by Higgs inflation. We compute the graybody factors and emission spectra, showing that the latter can be either enhanced or suppressed, even by several orders of magnitude. A crucial role is played by the sign of the term $\xi fR$, with $f(r)=-g_{tt}$ in Schwarzschild-like coordinates, as it determines whether the non-minimal coupling suppresses or enhances the geometric potential barrier. For the D'Ambrosio-Rovelli case with large negative $\xi$, the low-energy emission spectrum is enhanced by up to five orders of magnitude, since $\xi fR&lt;0$ throughout the space-time, leading to a deep potential well which broadens the transmissive window. The deviations we find can be particularly relevant in the case where primordial RBHs are dark matter candidates, given the impact of the non-minimal coupling on their evaporation history.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12257v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/s4cf-bclq</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Marco Calz\`a, Massimiliano Rinaldi, Sunny Vagnozzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black Holes in Asymptotic Safety: A Review of Solutions and Phenomenology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14552</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14552v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Asymptotic Safety offers a conservative and predictive framework for quantum gravity, based on the existence of a renormalization group fixed point that ensures ultraviolet completeness without introducing new degrees of freedom. Black holes provide a natural arena in which to explore the implications of this scenario, as they probe the strongest gravitational fields and highlight the shortcomings of classical general relativity. In recent years, a variety of quantum-corrected black-hole solutions have been constructed within the Asymptotic Safety approach, either by renormalization-group improvement of classical metrics or through effective actions inspired by the flow of couplings. This review summarizes the current status of these developments. We discuss the structure and properties of the proposed solutions, their thermodynamics and evaporation, and their dynamical aspects such as quasinormal modes and shadows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14552v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.53941/ijgtp.2025.100008</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Journal of Gravitation and Theoretical Physics 2025, 1(1), 8</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Spina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Resummation of Soft Gluon Radiation in Heavy Meson Pair Photoproduction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18949</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18949v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop a unified resummation framework for heavy-meson pair photoproduction that treats soft-gluon radiation in a massive scheme for $|\boldsymbol q| \lesssim m_Q$ and is consistent with the massless limit $m_Q \ll |\boldsymbol q|$, where $\boldsymbol q$ denotes the transverse momentum of the pair and $m_Q$ the quark mass. This framework describes the full correlation regime $|\boldsymbol q| \ll |\boldsymbol P|$, with $\boldsymbol P$ the pair's relative transverse momentum. Next, within the Color Glass Condensate framework, we quantify the impact of soft gluon radiation on two important phenomenological observables, namely, the azimuthal $\Delta\phi$ correlation and the harmonic asymmetries $\langle \cos(2n\phi_{qP})\rangle$. Our results show that the resummation provides an excellent description of the H1 $\Delta\phi$ data. We then find that the angular-asymmetry harmonics are sizable and their ratios in $\gamma A$ to $\gamma p$ collisions are highly sensitive to gluon saturation. We further find a clear mass hierarchy in both observables, indicating that heavy-quark masses suppress soft radiation and thereby enhance genuine small-$x$ saturation signals. Our work demonstrates that heavy-quark pair photoproduction provides a quantitative probe of gluon saturation, directly measurable in forthcoming EIC and UPC measurements. Finally, the unified resummation is readily extendable to other processes involving massive particles and jets in both $eA$ and $pA$ collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18949v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cyrille Marquet, Yu Shi, Bo-Wen Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new regularization scheme for the wave function of the Universe in the Lorentzian path integral</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09621v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Lorentzian path integral for the wave function of the Universe is only conditionally convergent and thus requires a well-defined prescription. The Picard-Lefschetz approach ensures convergence through contour deformation, but it has been argued that this leads to unsuppressed perturbations due to relevant saddle points residing in the region ${\rm Im}N&gt;0$. As an alternative, we propose a simple regulator for the lapse integral in minisuperspace. Specifically, we impose the vanishing initial size of the Universe via a delta function, represented as a narrow Gaussian of width $\sigma$, and take the limit $\sigma \to 0$ only after performing the functional integrations. This regulator has a clear physical interpretation: it corresponds to a vanishingly small quantum uncertainty in the initial size of the Universe. For any fixed $\sigma &gt; 0$, the lapse integral is absolutely convergent along (or slightly below) the real axis, and no excursion into the region ${\rm Im}N&gt;0$ is required. We further argue that the initial wave function for scalar and tensor perturbations should be incorporated in the Lorentzian path integral formalism, and we show that these perturbations are then appropriately suppressed. A purely Lorentzian path integral thus yields the tunneling wave function with suppressed perturbations. We also demonstrate that the Hartle-Hawking wave function can be reproduced by choosing a contour for the lapse integral extending from $-\infty$ to $+\infty$ that passes below the singularity near the origin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09621v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masaki Yamada</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
