<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th</link>
    <description>hep-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 03:10:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Position dependence of the holographic entanglement entropy for an accelerating quark-antiquark pair</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08007</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08007v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Through the holographic correspondence, we compute the entanglement entropy of the gluonic field sourced by a quark-antiquark pair undergoing uniform back-to-back acceleration. Previous calculations had obtained this only for the case where the entanglement surface is located midway between the quark and antiquark. Here, we consider the more general case with a relative lateral displacement, and determine the entanglement entropy as a function of the distance between the quark and the entanglement surface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08007v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'es Argando\~na, Alberto G\"uijosa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Celestial Symmetries of Black Hole Horizons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08027v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish a correspondence between the gravitational phase space at null infinity and the subleading phase space near a finite-distance null hypersurface, such as a black hole horizon. Within this framework, we identify the celestial $Lw_{1+\infty}$ symmetries in the subleading phase space at the horizon by constructing their canonical generators and imposing self-duality conditions. This leads to an infinite tower of conserved charges in the absence of radiation, revealing new gravitational observables relevant to black hole physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08027v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Romain Ruzziconi, C\'eline Zwikel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Consequences of Symmetry Fractionalization without 1-Form Global Symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08036v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the fractionalization of 0-form global symmetries on line operators in theories without 1-form global symmetries. The projective transformation properties of line operators are renormalization group invariant, and we derive constraints which are similar to the consequences of exact 1-form symmetries. For instance, symmetry fractionalization can lead to exact selection rules for line operators in twisted sectors, and in theories with 't Hooft anomalies involving the fractionalization class, these selection rules can further imply that certain twisted sectors have exact finite-volume vacuum degeneracies. Along the way, we define topological operators on open codimension-1 manifolds, which we call `disk operators', that provide a convenient way of encoding the projective action of 0-form symmetries on lines. In addition, we discuss the possible ways symmetry fractionalization can be matched along renormalization group flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08036v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Daniel Brennan, Theodore Jacobson, Konstantinos Roumpedakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The canonical ensemble of a self-gravitating matter thin shell in AdS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08059v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We build the canonical ensemble of a hot self-gravitating matter thin shell in anti-de Sitter (AdS) space by finding its partition function through the Euclidean path integral approach with fixed temperature at the conformal boundary. We obtain the reduced action of the system by restricting the path integral to spherically symmetric metrics with given boundary conditions and with the Hamiltonian constraint satisfied. The stationary conditions, i.e., the mechanical equilibrium and the thermodynamic equilibrium, are obtained from minimizing the reduced action. Evaluating the perturbed reduced action at the stationary points yields the mechanical stability condition and the thermodynamic stability condition. The reduced action calculated at the stationary points gives the partition function in the zero-loop approximation and from it the thermodynamic properties of the system are acquired. Within thermodynamics alone, the only stability condition that one can establish is thermodynamic stability, which follows from the computation of the heat capacity. For given specific pressure and temperature equations of state for the shell, we obtain the solutions of the ensemble. There are four different thin shell solutions, one of them is fully stable, i.e., is stable mechanically and thermodynamically. For the equations of state given, we find a first order phase transition from the matter thermodynamic phase to the Hawking-Page black hole phase. Moreover, there is a maximum temperature above which the shell ceases to exist, presumably at these high temperatures the shell inevitably collapses to a black hole.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08059v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tiago V. Fernandes, Francisco J. Gandum, Jos\'e P. S. Lemos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Replica manifolds, pole skipping, and the butterfly effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08139</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08139v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The black hole butterfly effect is a signal of quantum chaos in holographic theories that can be probed in different ways, including out-of-time-order correlators (OTOCs), pole skipping (PS), and entanglement wedge (EW) reconstruction. Each of these three phenomena can be used to define a butterfly velocity that measures the speed at which chaos spreads. In a general quantum system the three velocities $v_B^{\text{OTOC}}$, $v_B^{\text{PS}}$, and $v_B^{\text{EW}}$ can be different, but it is known from explicit calculations that they are all equal in certain holographic theories dual to Einstein gravity plus higher-curvature corrections. A conceptual explanation for this apparent coincidence is lacking. We show that it follows from a deeper relationship: The pole-skipping mode, added to the black hole background, can be reinterpreted as the gravitational replica manifold for the late-time entanglement wedge, and its imaginary part is the shockwave that computes the OTOC. Thus pole skipping is directly related to entanglement dynamics in holographic theories, and the origin of the pole-skipping mode is an extremal surface on the horizon. This explains the coincidence $v_B^{\text{OTOC}} = v_B^{\text{PS}} = v_B^{\text{EW}}$ in known cases, and extends it to general theories of gravity with a pole-skipping mode having the usual behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08139v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wan Zhen Chua, Thomas Hartman, Wayne W. Weng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundary Scattering and Non-invertible Symmetries in 1+1 Dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08375</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08375v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent studies by Copetti, C\'ordova and Komatsu have revealed that when non-invertible symmetries are spontaneously broken, the conventional crossing relation of the S-matrix is modified by the effects of the corresponding topological quantum field theory (TQFT). In this paper, we extend these considerations to $(1+1)$-dimensional quantum field theories (QFTs) with boundaries. In the presence of a boundary, one can define not only the bulk S-matrix but also the boundary S-matrix, which is subject to a consistency condition known as the boundary crossing relation. We show that when the boundary is weakly-symmetric under the non-invertible symmetry, the conventional boundary crossing relation also receives a modification due to the TQFT effects. As a concrete example of the boundary scattering, we analyze kink scattering in the gapped theory obtained from the $\Phi_{(1,3)}$-deformation of a minimal model. We explicitly construct the boundary S-matrix that satisfies the Ward-Takahashi identities associated with non-invertible symmetries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08375v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soichiro Shimamori, Satoshi Yamaguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbative Distinguishability of Black Hole Microstates from AdS/CFT Correspondence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08402v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish direct evidence for the perturbative distinguishability between black hole microstates and thermal states using the AdS/CFT correspondence. In two-dimensional holographic conformal field theories, we obtain the short interval expansion of subsystem fidelity and quantum Jensen-Shannon divergence, both of which provide rigorous lower and upper bounds for trace distance. This result demonstrates that quantum gravity corrections break semiclassical indistinguishability, thereby supporting the recovery of information even from a small amount of the Hawking radiation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08402v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaju Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Delta functions on twistor space and their sign factors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08523v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When performing the Fourier transform of the scattering amplitudes in Yang-Mills theory from momentum space to real twistor space, we encounter sign factors that break global conformal invariance. Previous studies conjectured that the sign factors are intrinsic in the real twistor space corresponding to the split signature space-time; hence, they will not appear in the complex twistor space corresponding to the Lorentzian signature space-time. In this study, we present a new geometrical interpretation of the sign factors by investigating the domain of the delta functions on the real twistor space. In addition, we propose a new definition of delta functions on the complex twistor space in terms of the Cech cohomology group without any sign factors and show that these delta functions have conformal invariance. Moreover, we show that the inverse Fourier transforms of these delta functions are the scattering amplitudes in Yang-Mills theory. Thus, the sign factors do not appear in the complex twistor space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08523v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun-ichi Note</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Screened volume law of Holographic Entanglement Entropy in Holographic Spontaneous Vectorization model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08549v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a holographic study of spontaneous vectorization in the background of an isotropic asymptotically AdS black brane. By extending spontaneous scalarization to vector fields, we demonstrate how the effective mass of the vector field drives tachyonic instability, leading to a transition from the AdS-RN phase to a vectorized phase. Thermodynamic analysis reveals the critical temperature $ T_c $ and coupling $ \alpha_c $ for this transition, with the vectorized phase exhibiting lower free energy. A central discovery is the emergence of a ``screened volume law'' in the holographic entanglement entropy (HEE), a novel phenomenon where the entanglement entropy scales with the subregion size via a screened entropy density distinct from thermal entropy. This arises from a geometric constraint tied to the vanishing of the Christoffel symbol $ \Gamma^z{}_{xx} $, which defines an effective boundary outside the horizons. Unlike conventional ``entanglement shadows'' in black hole systems, this surface acts as a boundary for minimal surfaces in a translationally invariant geometry. This screening effect suggests the inability of entanglement measure to fully probe the Hilbert space of this thermal system. Additionally, the HEE in the vectorized phase displays non-monotonic temperature dependence. These results establish spontaneous vectorization as a mechanism for generating novel entanglement structures in holographic systems, with implications for quantum information and critical phenomena in strongly coupled systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08549v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chong-Ye Chen, Guang-Zai Ye, Peng Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bootstrapping Shape Invariance: Numerical Bootstrap as a Detector of Solvable Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08586v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Determining the solvability of a given quantum mechanical system is generally challenging. We discuss that the numerical bootstrap method can help us to solve this question in one-dimensional quantum mechanics. We analytically show that the bootstrap method can derive exact energy eigenvalues in systems with shape invariance, which is a sufficient condition for solvability and which many solvable systems satisfy. The information of the annihilation operators is also obtained naturally, and thus the bootstrap method tells us why the system is solvable. We numerically demonstrate this explicitly for shape invariant potentials: harmonic oscillators, Morse potentials, Rosen-Morse potentials and hyperbolic Scarf potentials. Therefore, the numerical bootstrap method can determine the solvability of a given unknown system if it satisfies shape invariance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08586v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Aikawa, Takeshi Morita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalar subleading soft theorems from an infinite tower of charges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08612v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the emergence of infinite-dimensional symmetries in the absence of gauge invariance by analyzing massless scalar theories. We construct an infinite tower of charges that arise from the subleading equations of motion at null infinity and are built from specific combinations of asymptotic field coefficients. Interestingly, these expressions are finite from the outset, requiring no holographic renormalization. By carefully analyzing the dynamics at spatial infinity, we show that this tower of surface integrals commutes with the S-matrix of the interacting model. As an application, we demonstrate that these symmetries lead to an infinite set of subleading soft relations, valid at leading order in a cubic interaction with massive scalar fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08612v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mat\'ias Brice\~no, Hern\'an A. Gonz\'alez, Alfredo P\'erez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scale separation, rolling solutions and entropy bounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08634v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revisit scale separation for compactifications of ten- and eleven-dimensional supergravity. For cosmological solutions rolling down flux-generated potentials, we observe that scale separation is achieved as time flows, and is fairly generic. This is realized without the need of orientifolds nor corrections to the classical supergravity approximation. We then confront scale separation with the Covariant Entropy Bound (CEB) and the CKN bound. We show that a naive application of these bounds to vacua hints at the existence of at least two extra dimensions. For rolling solutions, we observe that the CEB is not always respected, but since these examples lack a cosmic horizon, the application of entropy bounds remains delicate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08634v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Andriot, Niccol\`o Cribiori, Thomas Van Riet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The LSZ reduction formula from homotopy algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08653</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08653v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When we describe string field theory or quantum field theory in terms of homotopy algebras, on-shell scattering amplitudes at the tree level are obtained by the formula based on the minimal model. While this formula can be extended to loop amplitudes and it generates the correct set of Feynman diagrams, the evaluation of each Feynman diagram may fail to be well defined because of mass renormalization. Furthermore, this formula does not explain why we use Feynman propagators in loops. In this paper we first present the LSZ reduction formula in terms of quantum $A_\infty$ algebras, which provides a well-defined prescription for loop amplitudes. We then present a formula for connected correlation functions based on quantum $A_\infty$ algebras, and we use it to discuss the relation between the LSZ reduction formula and the extension of the minimal model to loop amplitudes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08653v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keisuke Konosu, Yuji Okawa, Shono Shibuya, Jojiro Totsuka-Yoshinaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry Resolved Entanglement with $U(1)$ Symmetry: Some Closed Formulae for Excited States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08668v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we revisit a problem we addressed in previous publications with various collaborators, that is, the computation of the symmetry resolved entanglement entropies of zero-density excited states in infinite volume. The universal nature of the charged moments of these states has already been noted previously. Here, we investigate this problem further, by writing general formulae for the entropies of excited states consisting of an arbitrary number of subsets of identical excitations. When the initial state is written in terms of qubits with appropriate probabilistic coefficients, we find the final formulae to be of a combinatorial nature too. We analyse some of their features numerically and analytically and find that for qubit states consisting of particles of the same charge, the symmetry resolved entropies are independent of region size relative to system size, even if the number and configuration entropies are not.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08668v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olalla A. Castro-Alvaredo, Luc\'ia Santamar\'ia-Sanz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic duality from Howe duality: Chern-Simons gravity as an ensemble of code CFTs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08724</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08724v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss the holographic correspondence between 3d "Chern-Simons gravity" and an ensemble of 2d Narain code CFTs. Starting from 3d abelian Chern-Simons theory, we construct an ensemble of boundary CFTs defined by gauging all possible maximal subgroups of the bulk one-form symmetry. Each maximal non-anomalous subgroup is isomorphic to a classical even self-dual error-correcting code over $\mathbb Z_p\times \mathbb Z_p$, providing a way to define a boundary "code CFT." The average over the ensemble of such theories is holographically dual to Chern-Simons gravity, a bulk theory summed over 3d topologies sharing the same boundary. In the case of prime $p$, the sum reduces to that over handlebodies, i.e. becomes the Poincar\'e series akin to that in semiclassical gravity. As the main result of the paper, we show that the mathematical identity underlying this holographic duality can be understood and rigorously proven using the framework of Howe duality over finite fields. This framework is concerned with the representation theory of two commuting groups forming a dual pair: the symplectic group of modular transformations of the boundary, and an orthogonal group mapping codes to each other. Finally, we reformulate the holographic duality as an identity between different averages over quantum stabilizer states, providing an interpretation in terms of quantum information theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08724v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anatoly Dymarsky, Johan Henriksson, Brian McPeak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-equilibrium dynamics of long-range field configurations in the Proca theory and the counterexample to the law of periodic charge oscillations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07846</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.07846v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Long-range field configurations exist in the Proca theory and their non-equilibrium evolution is of interest in this work. General arguments suggest that a charge can be assigned to them and that its evolution is governed by the law of periodic charge oscillations. We discuss an elegant analytically-solvable example of a field configuration in the Proca theory respecting such a law. We also identify a weak point in the aforementioned general arguments, construct the counterexample to the law of periodic charge oscillations in the Proca theory, and comprehensively discuss it. The Gibbs-Wilbraham phenomenon is discussed in the course of these studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.07846v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bogdan Damski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From kinetic gasses to an exponentially expanding universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08062v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the gravitational field of a kinetic gas beyond its usual derivation from the second moment of the one-particle distribution function (1PDF), that serves as energy-momentum tensor in the Einstein equations. This standard procedure raises the question why the other moments of the 1PDF (which are needed to fully characterize the kinematical properties of the gas) do not contribute to the gravitational field and what could be their relevance in addressing the dark energy problem? Using the canonical coupling of the entire 1PDF to Finsler spacetime geometry via the Finsler gravity equation, we show that these higher moments contribute non-trivially. A Finslerian geometric description of our universe allows us to determine not only the scale factor but also of the causal structure dynamically. We find that already a Finslerian vacuum solution naturally permits an exponential expanding universe, without the need for a cosmological constant or any additional quantities. This solution possesses a causal structure which is a mild deformation of the causal structure of Friedmann-Lema\^itre-Robertson-Walker (FLRW) geometry; close to the rest frame defined by cosmological time (i.e., for slowly moving objects), the causal structures of the two geometries are nearly indistinguishable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08062v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Pfeifer, Nicoleta Voicu, Annamaria Friedl-Sz\'asz, Elena Popovici-Popescu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sheaf Topos Theory: A powerful setting for Lagrangian Field Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08095</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08095v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We provide an introductory exposition to the sheaf topos theoretic description of classical field theory motivated by the rigorous description of both $\bf{(i)}$ the variational calculus of (infinite dimensional) field-theoretic spaces, and $\bf(ii)$ the non-triviality of classical fermionic field spaces. These considerations naturally lead to the definition of the sheaf topos of super smooth sets. We close by indicating natural generalizations necessary to include to the description of infinitesimal structure of field spaces and further the non-perturbative description of (higher) gauge fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08095v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grigorios Giotopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rational Extension of Quantum Anisotropic Oscillator Potentials with Linear and/or Quadratic Perturbations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08236</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08236v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive study of the rational extension of the quantum anisotropic harmonic oscillator (QAHO) potentials with linear and/or quadratic perturbations. For the one-dimensional harmonic oscillator plus imaginary linear perturbation ($i\lambda x$), we show that the rational extension is possible not only for the even but also for the odd co-dimensions $m$. In two-dimensional case, we construct the rational extensions for QAHO potentials with quadratic ($\lambda \, xy$) perturbation both when $\lambda$ is real or imaginary and obtain their solutions. Finally, we extend the discussion to the three-dimensional QAHO with linear and quadratic perturbations and obtain the corresponding rationally extended potentials. For all these cases, we obtain the conditions under which the spectrum remains real and also when there is degeneracy in the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08236v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rajesh Kumar Yadav, Rajesh Kumar, Avinash Khare</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Einstein ring of dust shells with quantum hair</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08343</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08343v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The information about the internal structure of a compact object is classically inaccessible to external observers. In this paper, we investigate how quantum corrections to gravitational fields can reveal the internal structure of compact objects composed of dust shells. Using an effective field theory approach to incorporate quantum corrections up to second order in curvature, we derive a quantum-corrected metric for $N$ uniformly spaced shells with equal surface mass density and then examine how these corrections manifest in the deflection angle for gravitational lensing. In particular, we mainly investigate quantum-corrected astrophysical observables such as the Einstein ring and image magnification. Compared to the classical scenario, the deflection angle and the corresponding Einstein angle differ by a term that depends explicitly on the number of dust shells, which play the role of quantum hair. Specifically, the quantum correction to them diminishes as $N$ increases, yet a finite deviation from the classical result remains even in the continuum limit $N\to\infty$. Consequently, our results show that the internal structures of compact objects with identical mass and radius can be distinguished by quantum hair through their lensing observables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08343v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sojeong Cheong, Wontae Kim, Mungon Nam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Acoustic black holes in BECs with an extended sonic region</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08564v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the context of Hawking-like radiation in sonic black holes formed by BECs we investigate the modifications of the emission spectrum caused by a finite width of the sonic transition region connecting the subsonic to supersonic flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08564v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Pe\~nalver, Marco De Vito, Roberto Balbinot, Alessandro Fabbri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regular BTZ black holes from an infinite tower of corrections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08565v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explore $2+1$-dimensional scalar-tensor theories derived from well-defined dimensional regularizations of the Lovelock invariants. In the limit where an infinite series of corrections is included, we obtain theories that admit fully regular black hole solutions. We analyze the properties of these regular black holes, investigate geodesics in these spacetimes, and examine the tidal forces, finding they remain finite everywhere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08565v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro G. S. Fernandes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deformations of Clarke-Oliveira's Instantons on Bryant-Salamon $Spin(7)$-Manifold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08723</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08723v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we compute the deformations of Clarke-Oliveira's instantons on the Bryant-Salamon $Spin(7)$-Manifold. The Bryant-Salamon $Spin(7)$-Manifold -- the negative spinor bundle of $S^4$ -- is an asymptotically conical manifold where the link is the squashed $7$-sphere. We use the deformation theory developed by the author in a previous paper to calculate the deformations of Clarke-Oliveira's instantons and calculate the virtual dimensions of the moduli spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08723v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tathagata Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Actions for Self-dual Higher Spin Gravities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2105.12782</link>
      <description>arXiv:2105.12782v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Higher Spin Gravities are scarce, but covariant actions for them are even scarcer. We construct covariant actions for contractions of Chiral Higher Spin Gravity that represent higher spin extensions of self-dual Yang-Mills and self-dual Gravity theories. The actions give examples of complete higher spin theories both in flat and (anti)-de Sitter spaces that feature gauge and gravitational interactions. The actions are based on a new description of higher spin fields, whose origin can be traced to early works on twistor theory. The new description simplifies the structure of interactions. In particular, we find a covariant form of the minimal gravitational interaction for higher spin fields both in flat and anti-de Sitter space, which resolves some of the puzzles in the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2105.12782v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP08(2021)076</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Kirill Krasnov, Evgeny Skvortsov, Tung Tran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal Bootstrap Equations from the Embedding Space Operator Product Expansion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.06816v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We describe how to implement the conformal bootstrap program in the context of the embedding space OPE formalism introduced in previous work. To take maximal advantage of the known properties of the scalar conformal blocks for symmetric-traceless exchange, we construct tensorial generalizations of the three-point and four-point scalar conformal blocks that have many nice properties. Further, we present a special basis of tensor structures for three-point correlation functions endowed with the remarkable simplifying property that it does not mix under permutations of the external quasi-primary operators. We find that in this approach, we can write the $M$-point conformal bootstrap equations explicitly in terms of the standard position space cross-ratios without the need to project back to position space, thus effectively deriving all conformal bootstrap equations directly from the embedding space. Finally, we lay out an algorithm for generating the conformal bootstrap equations in this formalism. Collectively, the tensorial generalizations, the new basis of tensor structures, as well as the procedure for deriving the conformal bootstrap equations lead to four-point bootstrap equations for quasi-primary operators in arbitrary Lorentz representations expressed as linear combinations of the standard scalar conformal blocks for spin-$\ell$ exchange, with finite $\ell$-independent terms. Moreover, the OPE coefficients in these equations conveniently feature trivial symmetry properties. The only inputs necessary are the relevant projection operators and tensor structures, which are all fixed by group theory. To illustrate the procedure, we present one nontrivial example involving scalars $S$ and vectors $V$, namely $\left\langle SSSV\right\rangle$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.06816v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Fran\c{c}ois Fortin, Wen-Jie Ma, Valentina Prilepina, Witold Skiba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlation functions in expanding universes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15168v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: By using the braneworld model, we investigate the time evolution of microscopic and macroscopic correlations in expanding universes. To describe the FLRW cosmologies in the holographic setup, we take into account a braneworld moving in the $p$-brane gas geometry, where the radial motion of the braneworld determines the cosmology in the braneworld. We show that the braneworld model reproduces the standard cosmology exactly. In this braneworld model, we investigate the time-dependent mutual information between two disjoint macroscopic subregions and the time-dependent two-point functions in the expanding universes. We find that the mutual information becomes zero when the distance between two subregions is slightly larger than the subsystem size. We also find that it decreases as time and the density of matter increase. On the other hand, the microscopic two-point function in the short-distance limit decreases by a power law, while it is exponentially suppressed in the long-distance limit due to the screening effect. In addition, we find that the two-point function is also suppressed by a power law with time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15168v5</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chanyong Park, Hanse Kim, Kyungchan Cho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher spin swampland conjecture for massive AdS$_{3}$ gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09151v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we show that a possible version of the swampland weak gravity conjecture for higher spin (HS) massive topological AdS$_{3}$ gravity can be expressed in terms of mass $M_{hs}$, charge $Q_{hs}$ and coupling constant $g_{hs}$ of 3D gravity coupled to higher spin fields as $M_{hs} \leq \sqrt{2}$ $Q_{hs}$ $g_{hs}$ $M_{Pl}$. The higher spin charge is given by the $SO(1,2)$ quadratic Casimir $Q_{hs}^{2}=s\left (s-1\right) $ and the HS coupling constant by ${\large g}_{hs} ^{2}=2/\left (M_{Pl}^{2} l_{AdS_{3}}^{2}\right )$ while the mass expressed like $\left( l_{AdS_{3}} \text{M}_{hs}\right) ^{2}$ is defined as $ \left (1+\mu l_{AdS_{3}} \right ) ^{2} s \left ( s-1 \right ) +[1- \left ( \mu l_{AdS_{3}} \right ) ^{2} \left ( s-1 \right ) ]$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09151v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Sammani, E. H Saidi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Casimirs of the Virasoro Algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18172v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explicitly solve a recurrence relation due to Feigin and Fuchs to obtain the Casimirs of the Virasoro algebra in terms of the inverse of the Shapovalov form. Combined with our recent result for the inverse Shapovalov form, this allows us to write the Casimir operators as linear combinations of products of singular vectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18172v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Fran\c{c}ois Fortin, Lorenzo Quintavalle, Witold Skiba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unitarity through PT symmetry in Quantum Quadratic Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08278</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08278v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Theories described by non-Hermitian Hamiltonians are known to possess strictly positive energy eigenvalues and exhibit unitary time evolution if the Hamiltonian is symmetric under discrete parity and time (PT) transformation. In this work, we demonstrate how quantum quadratic gravity, a theory that generally violates unitarity when viewed as a Hermitian quantum field theory, can be complex-deformed into such a PT-symmetric theory with an action that consists of a ghost-less Hermitian free part and non-Hermitian interactions. Paying special attention to the gauge symmetry present in the theory, we quantize in the covariant operator formalism after suggesting how the framework might be extended to the pseudo-Hermitian picture. We find compelling evidence that the resulting quantum theory possesses a unitary inner product and a sensible interpretation of quantum probability, thus avoiding the ghost problem present in the Hermitian formulation of quadratic gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08278v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeffrey Kuntz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher form symmetries, membranes and flux quantization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14051</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14051v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Higher Forms Symmetries (HFS) of a closed bosonic M2-brane theory formulated on a compactified target space $\mathcal{M}_9 \times T^2$ are obtained. We show that the cancellation of the 't Hooft anomaly present in the theory is related to a 3-form flux with $\mathcal{G}_1^{\nabla}$-gerbe structure associated to the world-volume flux quantization condition. A Wilson surface is naturally introduced on the topological operator that characterize the holonomy of the M2-brane. The projection of the flux quantization condition inherited from the gerbe structure onto the spatial part of the worldvolume, leads to a flux quantization on the M2-brane. The topological operators realise discrete symmetries associated with the winding and the flux/monopole condition. The algebra of operators is well defined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14051v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Caro-Perez, M. P. Garcia del Moral, A. Restuccia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is the Geometry of Effective Field Theories?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21378v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We elaborate on a recently proposed geometric framework for scalar effective field theories. Starting from the action, a metric can be identified that enables the construction of geometric quantities on the associated functional manifold. These objects transform covariantly under general field redefinitions that relate different operator bases, including those involving derivatives. We present a novel geometric formula for the amplitudes of the theory, where the vertices in Feynman diagrams are replaced by their geometrized counterparts. This makes the on-shell covariance of amplitudes manifest, providing the link between functional geometry and effective field theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21378v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timothy Cohen, Xiaochuan Lu, Zhengkang Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature-Resistant Order in 2+1 Dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09459v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High temperatures are typically thought to increase disorder. Here we examine this idea in Quantum Field Theory in 2+1 dimensions. For this sake we explore a novel class of tractable models, consisting of nearly-mean-field scalars interacting with critical scalars. We identify UV-complete, local, unitary models in this class and show that symmetry breaking $\mathbb{Z}_2 \to \emptyset$ occurs at any temperature in some regions of the phase diagram. This phenomenon, previously observed in models with fractional dimensions, or in the strict planar limits, or with non-local interactions, is now exhibited in a local, unitary 2+1 dimensional model with a finite number of fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09459v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zohar Komargodski, Fedor K. Popov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>${\mathcal N}=3$ nonlinear multiplet and supergravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11339v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose an ${\mathcal N}=3$ nonlinear multiplet coupled to conformal supergravity and use it to formulate the equations of motion for ${\mathcal N} = 3$ Poincar\'e supergravity. These equations, which are naturally described in a new curved supergeometry with structure group $\mathsf{SL}(2,\mathbb{C})$, imply that the ${\mathcal N} = 3$ super-Bach tensor vanishes, and thus every solution of Poincar\'e supergravity is a solution of conformal supergravity. The aforementioned superspace formulation, which we refer to as $\mathcal N=3$ Einstein superspace, is described in terms of two dimension-$1/2$ superfields: (i) the super-Weyl spinor $W_\alpha$; and (ii) a spinor isospinor $\chi_\alpha^i$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11339v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergei M. Kuzenko, Emmanouil S. N. Raptakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Applying Constraints from Outside the System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06338v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the role of external constraints in quantum field theory using the path integral formalism. We begin by reviewing the quantization of constrained systems and extend the analysis to cases where constraints are added to the action via auxiliary fields. These constraints involve both the degrees of freedom and their time derivatives. Using the resulting framework, we derive the generating functional for matter vector fields constrained to the spin-one state. However, for systems with singular actions, preserving the classical form of constraints at the quantum level requires conditions, and we provide examples of sufficient conditions. We also present an example where the classical form of constraints is not preserved, involving a singular action with an antisymmetric tensor field leading to a strength-field interpretation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06338v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amin Akhavan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large $N$ Wess-Zumino model at finite temperature and large chemical potential in $3d$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17999</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17999v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the supersymmetric Wess-Zumino model at large $N$ in $(2+1)$ dimension. We introduce a chemical potential($\mu$) at finite temperature($T$). The non-trivial fixed point of this model is described by a pair of coupled gap equations. This fixed point behaves as a thermal CFT for all values of the coupling. We find that at large chemical potential these coupled equations simplify and solutions become analytically tractable. We solve them analytically for all values of the coupling at this limit. The solutions admit a systematic series expansion in $\frac{T}{\mu}$. Thus, using the solutions of the gap equation at large chemical potential we can evaluate the analytic form of the partition function, stress tensor and spin-1 current as a perturbative expansion in orders of $\frac{T}{\mu}$. Applying the OPE inversion formula on the scalar and fermion two point functions of the theory, we compute higher spin currents at large $\mu$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17999v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Srijan Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlation functions for non-conformal D$p$-brane holography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18770</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18770v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We use holography to study correlation functions of local operators in maximally supersymmetric Yang-Mills theories arising on the world-volume of D$p$-branes in the large-$N$ and strong-coupling limit. The relevant supergravity backgrounds obtained from the near-horizon limit of the D$p$-branes enjoy a scaling similarity, which leads to an auxiliary AdS space of fractional dimension. This suggests that holographic correlation functions in this setup can be computed by integrating standard CFT correlators over the auxiliary extra dimensions. We apply this prescription to analytically compute two- and three-point correlators of scalar operators. The resulting two-point functions take a familiar CFT form but with shifted conformal dimensions, while the three-point correlators have a much more involved position dependence which we calculate explicitly in terms of a sum of Appell functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18770v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikolay Bobev, Guillermo Mera \'Alvarez, Hynek Paul</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum complexity phase transitions in monitored random circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.15475</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.15475v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recently, the dynamics of quantum systems that involve both unitary evolution and quantum measurements have attracted attention due to the exotic phenomenon of measurement-induced phase transitions. The latter refers to a sudden change in a property of a state of $n$ qubits, such as its entanglement entropy, depending on the rate at which individual qubits are measured. At the same time, quantum complexity emerged as a key quantity for the identification of complex behaviour in quantum many-body dynamics. In this work, we investigate the dynamics of the quantum state complexity in monitored random circuits, where $n$ qubits evolve according to a random unitary circuit and are individually measured with a fixed probability at each time step. We find that the evolution of the exact quantum state complexity undergoes a phase transition when changing the measurement rate. Below a critical measurement rate, the complexity grows at least linearly in time until saturating to a value $e^{\Omega(n)}$. Above, the complexity does not exceed $\operatorname{poly}(n)$. In our proof, we make use of percolation theory to find paths along which an exponentially long quantum computation can be run below the critical rate, and to identify events where the state complexity is reset to zero above the critical rate. We lower bound the exact state complexity in the former regime using recently developed techniques from algebraic geometry. Our results combine quantum complexity growth, phase transitions, and computation with measurements to help understand the behavior of monitored random circuits and to make progress towards determining the computational power of measurements in many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.15475v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.22331/q-2025-02-10-1627</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Quantum 9, 1627 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ryotaro Suzuki, Jonas Haferkamp, Jens Eisert, Philippe Faist</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direction-dependent conductivity in planar Hall set-ups with tilted Weyl/multi-Weyl semimetals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.10203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.10203v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We compute the magnetoelectric conductivity tensors in planar Hall set-ups, which are built with tilted Weyl semimetals (WSMs) and multi-Weyl semimetals (mWSMs), considering all possible relative orientations of the electromagnetic fields ($\mathbf E $ and $\mathbf B $) and the direction of the tilt. The non-Drude part of the response arises from a nonzero Berry curvature in the vicinity of the WSM/mWSM node under consideration. Only in the presence of a nonzero tilt do we find linear-in-$ | \mathbf B| $ terms in set-ups where the tilt-axis is not perpendicular to the plane spanned by $\mathbf E $ and $ \mathbf B $. The advantage of the emergence of the linear-in-$ | \mathbf B| $ terms is that, unlike the various $| \mathbf B|^2 $-dependent terms that can contribute to experimental observations, they have purely a topological origin, and they dominate the overall response-characteristics in the realistic parameter regimes. The important signatures of these terms are that they (1) change the periodicity of the response from $\pi $ to $2\pi$, when we consider their dependence on the angle $\theta $ between $\mathbf E $ and $\mathbf B $; and (2) lead to an overall change in sign of the conductivity depending on $\theta$, when measured with respect to the $\mathbf B =0$ case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.10203v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-648X/ad38fa</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 36, 275501 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Rahul Ghosh, Ipsita Mandal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on Bulk Fields: No-Go Conjectures for Braneworld Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04567v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This work establishes a series of no-go conjectures that impose rigorous constraints on the localization of bulk fields in braneworld scenarios, specifically affecting gauge and spinor fields within five-dimensional spacetimes. Our approach differs from traditional methods as it does not rely on specific equations of motion, making our results broadly applicable across various braneworld models. These no-go conditions reveal fundamental limitations in field localization, challenging the feasibility of embedding fields on the brane. For instance, our analysis demonstrates that existing models fail to achieve consistent localization for gauge and spinor fields. Additionally, one of our conditions indicates that the effective Lagrangian on the brane cannot exhibit conformal invariance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04567v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Alencar, M. Gogberashvili, R. N. Costa Filho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capped Vertex Functions for $\text{Hilb}^n (\mathbb{C}^2)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00498v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We obtain explicit formulas for capped descendent vertex functions of $\text{Hilb}^n(\mathbb{C}^2)$ for descendents given by the exterior algebra of the tautological bundle. This formula provides a one-parametric deformation of the generating function for normalized Macdonald polynomials. In particular, we show that the capped vertex functions are rational functions of the quantum parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00498v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeffrey Ayers, Andrey Smirnov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semi-automatic Calculations of Multi-loop Feynman Amplitudes with AmpRed</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.06426v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a Mathematica package AmpRed for the semi-automatic calculations of multi-loop Feynman amplitudes with high efficiency and precision. AmpRed implements the methods of integration by parts and differential equations in the Feynman-parameter representation. It allows for the calculations of general parametric integrals (which may not have momentum-space correspondences). Various user-friendly tools for multi-loop calculations, such as those to construct and solve differential equations for Feynman integrals, are provided. It can also deal with tensor algebras in non-relativistic field theories. Interfaces to some packages, like QGRAF and FORM, are also provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.06426v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Comput.Phys.Commun. 312 (2025) 109607</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wen Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetically charged black-bounce solution via nonlinear electrodynamics in a k-essence theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09182</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09182v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the present work, we obtain and analyze a new class of analytical solutions of magnetically charged black bounces in k-essence theory, spherically symmetric in (3+1)-dimensions, coupled to nonlinear electrodynamics (NED). We consider two metric models, Simpson-Visser and Bardeen, for the k-essence configurations n = 1/3 and n = 1/5. We obtain in an analytical way which scalar field, field potential, and Lagrangian NED are necessary to support the metrics. We analyze the behavior of these quantities and the energy conditions due to the scalar field and the NED.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09182v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.084025</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 111, 084025 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Carlos F. S. Pereira, Denis C. Rodrigues, Marcos V. de S. Silva, J\'ulio C. Fabris, Manuel E. Rodrigues, H. Belich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The unification in an $\widehat {\mathfrak{s}\mathfrak{u}}(8)_{ k_U = 1}$ affine Lie algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12979v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A flavor-unified theory based on the simple Lie algebra of ${\mathfrak{s}\mathfrak{u}}(8)$ was previously proposed to generate the observed Standard Model quark/lepton mass hierarchies and the Cabibbo-Kobayashi-Maskawa mixing pattern due to their non-universal symmetry properties. A level-$1$ affine Lie algebra of $\widehat{ \mathfrak{s}\mathfrak{u} }(8)_{ k_U =1}$ with the ${\cal N}=1$ supersymmetric extension is found to unify three gauge couplings through the maximally symmetry breaking pattern.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12979v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP04(2025)048</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ning Chen, Zhanpeng Hou, Zhaolong Teng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extra-dimensional axion patterns</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.00179</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.00179v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the $\textit{complete}$ parameter space of a bulk axion in flat and warped extra spacetime dimensions. We characterize in detail the regimes where no single KK mode is produced along the canonical QCD axion line, and instead, it is maximally deviated along with several other axions that constitute a multiple solution to the strong CP problem. In both flat and Randall-Sundrum scenarios, and assuming that all Peccei-Quinn breaking comes from QCD, we find that these solutions are however subject to tight phenomenological constraints. In light of these results, we expect that only KK canonical patterns (with the zero-mode close to the standard QCD line) can emerge from a bulk axion in one or more extra spacetime dimensions. As a byproduct, we generalize the axions eigenvalue and eigenvector equations for an arbitrary number of spacetime dimensions and compactifications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.00179v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.075006</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Arturo de Giorgi, Maria Ramos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermion liquids as quantum Hall liquids in phase space: A unified approach for anomalies and responses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08379v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The discovery of many strongly correlated metallic phases has inspired different routes to generalize or go beyond the celebrated Landau Fermi liquid theory. To this end, from universal consideration of symmetries and anomalies, Else, Thorngren and Senthil (ETS) have introduced a class of theories called ersatz Fermi liquids which possess a Fermi surface and satisfy a generalized Luttinger's theorem. In this work, we view all such fermion liquids obeying the Luttinger theorem as incompressible quantum Hall liquids in higher-dimensional phase space and use it as the starting point to derive their effective low-energy field theory. The noncommutativity of phase space motivates us to use the Seiberg-Witten map to derive the field theory in an ordinary (commutative) space and naturally leads to terms that correspond to the correct topological Chern-Simons action postulated by ETS in one, two, and three dimensions. Additionally, our approach also reproduces all the non-topological terms that characterize important contributions to the response, including the semiclassical equations of motion. Finally, our derivations of Chern-Simons terms from the Seiberg-Witten map also verify a longstanding conjecture in noncommutative field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08379v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.125138</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 125138 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jaychandran Padayasi, Ken K. W. Ma, Kun Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robustness of dark energy phenomenology across different parameterizations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04929v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The recent evidence for dynamical dark energy from DESI, in combination with other cosmological data, has generated significant interest in understanding the nature of dark energy and its underlying microphysics. However, interpreting these results critically depends on how dark energy is parameterized. This paper examines the robustness of conclusions about the viability of particular kinds of dynamical dark energy models to the choice of parameterization, focusing on four popular two-parameter models: the Chevallier-Polarski-Linder (CPL), Jassal-Bagla-Padmanabhan (JBP), Barboza-Alcaniz (BA), and exponential (EXP) parameterizations. We find that conclusions regarding the viability of minimally and non-minimally coupled quintessence models are independent of the parameterization adopted. We demonstrate this both by mapping these dark energy models into the $(w_0, w_a)$ parameter space defined by these various parameterizations and by showing that all of these parameterizations can equivalently account for the phenomenology predicted by these dark energy models to a high degree of accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04929v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William J. Wolf, Carlos Garc\'ia-Garc\'ia, Pedro G. Ferreira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical Unstable Qubits: an Application to $B^0\bar{B}^0$-Meson System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15625v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We extend our previous work on a novel class of unstable qubits which we have identified recently and called them Critical Unstable Qubits (CUQs). The characteristic property of CUQs is that the energy-level and decay-width vectors, ${\bf E}$ and ${\bf \Gamma}$, are orthogonal to one another, and the key parameter $r = |{\bf \Gamma}|/|2{\bf E}|$ is less than 1. Most remarkably, CUQs exhibit two atypical behaviours: (i) they display coherence-decoherence oscillations in a co-decaying frame of the system described by a unit Bloch vector ${\bf b}$, and (ii) the unit Bloch vector ${\bf b}$ describing a pure CUQ sweeps out unequal areas during equal intervals of time, while rotating about the vector ${\bf E}$. The latter anharmonic phenomenon emerges beyond the usual oscillatory pattern due to the energy-level difference of the two-level quantum system, which governs an ordinary qubit. By making use of a Fourier series decomposition, we define anharmonicity observables that quantify the degree of non-sinusoidal oscillation of a CUQ. We apply the results of our formalism to the $B^0\bar{B}^0$-meson system and derive, for the first time, generic upper limits on these new observables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15625v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dimitrios Karamitros, Thomas McKelvey, Apostolos Pilaftsis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometrical Proof of Generalized Mirror Transformation for Multi-Point Virtual Strucutre Constants of Projective Hypersurfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21280v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a geometric proof of the generalized mirror transformation for multi-point virtual structure constants of degree k hypersurfaces in CP^{N-1}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21280v5</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masao Jinzenji (Okayama University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thin-shell gravastar model in a BTZ geometry with minimum length</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03824v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we construct two spherically symmetric thin-shell gravastar models within a BTZ geometry with minimum length. Therefore, in the inner region of the gravastar, we consider an anti- de Sitter metric with minimum length. Thus, for the first model, we introduce the minimum length effect using the probability density of the ground state of the hydrogen atom in two dimensions. For the second gravastar model, we adopt a Lorentzian-type distribution. Also in the outer region, we consider the BTZ black hole metric. So, by examining the inner spacetime, the thin shell, and the outer spacetime, we find that there are different physical characteristics regarding their energy densities and pressures that make the gravastar stable. This effect persists even when the cosmological constant is zero. In addition, we determined the entropy of the gravastar thin shell. Besides, we explore the thermodynamic properties of the BTZ black hole with minimum length in Schwarzschild-type form and also check its stability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03824v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. A. Anacleto, A. T. N. Silva, L. Casarini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Has DESI detected exponential quintessence?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.04226v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The new Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) DR2 results have strengthened the possibility that dark energy is dynamical, i.e., it has evolved over the history of the Universe. One simple, but theoretically well motivated and widely studied, physical model of dynamical dark energy is minimally coupled, single-field quintessence $\phi$ with an exponential potential $V(\phi)=V_0\,e^{-\lambda\phi}$. We perform a full Bayesian statistical analysis of the model using the DESI DR2 data, in combination with other cosmological observations, to constrain the model's parameters and to compare its goodness of fit to that of the standard $\Lambda$CDM model. We find that the quintessence model provides a significantly better fit to the data, both when the spatial curvature of the Universe is fixed to zero and when it is allowed to vary. The significance of the preference varies between $\sim3.3\sigma$ and $\sim3.8\sigma$, depending on whether the curvature density parameter $\Omega_K$ is fixed or varied. We obtain the values $0.698^{+0.173}_{-0.202}$ and $0.722^{+0.182}_{-0.208}$ at the $68.3\%$ (i.e., $1\sigma$) confidence level for the parameter $\lambda$ in the absence and presence of $\Omega_K$, respectively, which imply $\sim3.5\sigma$ preference for a nonzero $\lambda$. We also obtain $\Omega_K=0.003\pm 0.001$, which implies $\sim3\sigma$ preference for a positive $\Omega_K$, i.e., a negative curvature. Finally, we discuss the differences between quintessence and phenomenological parametrizations of the dark energy equation-of-state parameter, in particular the Chevallier-Polarski-Linder (CPL) parametrization, as well as a few caveats to our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.04226v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yashar Akrami, George Alestas, Savvas Nesseris</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
