<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th</link>
    <description>hep-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 09:34:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Irrational CFTs from coupled anyon chains with non-invertible symmetries?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14280v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Irrational CFTs in 1+1d with a discrete spectrum and no conserved currents other than the stress-tensor are expected to be generic, unsolvable by standard methods, and hard to construct explicitly. We introduce a lattice model that realizes a candidate for such a CFT as a conformal phase of matter without fine-tuning. The model is constructed by coupling $N\geq2$ golden anyon chains together, preserving $N$ copies of the Fibonacci non-invertible symmetry. We use the MPS/DMRG approach to study this model numerically, which allows us to calculate the corresponding conformal data, obtaining hints of its irrationality. As a byproduct of our analysis, we provide an extensive list of rational CFTs with $1&lt;c&lt;2.1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14280v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ant\'onio Antunes, Junchen Rong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic Safety and Canonical Quantum Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14296v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the context of gravity the Lagrangian and Hamiltonian formalisms have been developed largely independently, emphasizing renormalization and quantization, respectively. The formalisms use a different methodology to distinguish between gauge and physical degrees of freedom. In this review we analyze the connection between the Asymptotically Safe and Canonical Quantum Gravity approaches. Based on the Hamiltonian formulation, the Canonical Quantum Gravity approach inherently provides a natural framework for defining observables. This serves as the foundation for constructing the generating functional of the $n$-point correlation functions of physical degrees of freedom. By means of background-independent, non-perturbative renormalization methods well-established in the Lagrangian framework and typically employed in Asymptotic Safety, the resulting generating functional can be handled. In particular, we employ the Functional Renormalization Group to regularize the path integral and to compute the flow connecting the bare theory in the ultraviolet with the effective infrared theory. An important advantage of this approach is that it establishes an explicit, systematic relation between the quantization procedure and the systematics of quantum field theory-based renormalization group methods. More importantly, this synthesis not only bridges canonical and covariant approaches but also paves the way for a consistent and predictive quantum theory of gravity grounded in physically meaningful, gauge-invariant observables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14296v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renata Ferrero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Notes on flat-space limit of holographic defect correlators in position space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14421v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the large AdS radius limit of correlation functions in holographic defect CFTs. For two-point functions of operators inserted away from the defect, we derive a position space formula relating a certain scaling limit of the correlators to the flat-space scattering form factors. We show that our position space prescription is equivalent to the flat-space limit formula recently conjectured in Mellin space and also test our result in a few nontrivial theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14421v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qi Chen, Yi-Xiao Tao, Xinan Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BCFW like recursion for Deformed Associahedron</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14583v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we explore the applicability of the BCFW-like recursion relations \cite{He:2018svj,Yang:2019esm} to a wider class of positive geometries. Previously it was found in \cite{Jagadale:2022rbl}, the tree level scattering amplitude of a theory with more than one type of scalar particles interacting via cubic couplings of different strength can be captured by a deformed realization of the ABHY-associahedorn in the kinematic space. In the literature, we explore the adaptation of the recursion relations for the case of deformed associahedron. The formalism is further generalized to the deformed realization of the D-type cluster polytopes which captures the one-loop amplitudes in this class of cubic theories. These recursion terms correspond to projective triangulation of the associahedron (or D-type cluster polytopes). Towards the end, we briefly mention the idea of recovering EFT amplitudes from the cubic theory in terms of recursion relations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14583v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sujoy Mahato, Sourav Roychowdhury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confinement, Nonlocality and Haag Duality Violation in the Algebraic Structure of 1+1D QED</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14699</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14699v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article, we present a novel formulation of the massless Schwinger model-quantum electrodynamics in $1+1$ dimensions-within the framework of Algebraic Quantum Field Theory (AQFT), emphasizing features that transcend the traditional bosonized treatments. Instead of mapping the model to a free massive scalar field, we construct a net of local observable algebras directly from the gauge-theoretic content, subject to the local ${U(1)}$ gauge symmetry and Gauss's law constraint. We show that local algebras can be consistently defined in terms of gauge-invariant composite operators, while charged fields necessarily fail to be localizable in bounded regions, manifesting confinement as the absence of DHR superselection sectors. Furthermore, we rigorously characterize nonlocal observables such as Wilson line operators within an extended net, and demonstrate the violation of Haag duality as a signature of the nontrivial topological and gauge structure of the theory. We additionally propose a conjecture linking the violation of Haag duality in confining gauge theories to a breakdown in entanglement wedge reconstruction, suggesting that confinement obstructs the local recovery of quantum information. Our approach provides a complete AQFT-based treatment of confinement, Gauss law, and nonlocal gauge-invariant operators in a solvable gauge theory, laying the groundwork for future extensions to non-Abelian models like QCD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14699v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fidele J. Twagirayezu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact Green's function for fermions in an external Yang-Mills gauge field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14911v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We obtain the Green's function for fermions in an external non-Abelian gauge field with an $SU(N)$ symmetry group. As an external field, we examine the solution to the Yang-Mills equation presented as a plane wave on the light cone.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14911v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. V. Parazian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electromagnetic helicity flux density for radiative systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14966</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14966v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The electromagnetic (EM) helicity flux density and the magnetic helicity are related by topological Chern-Simons terms. We show that the helicity flux density is distinguished from magnetic helicity by analysing Hopf solitons. We find the helicity flux density for a point charge moving with an acceleration, extending the Li\'enard-Wiechert angular distribution of radiant power. We also derive the multipole expansion of the helicity flux density, generalizing the Larmor's formula for the radiant power. These formulae have been applied to discuss the helicity flux density in several toy models such as circular and helical motion as well as soft bremsstrahlung. We also comment on the potential applications of the EM helicity flux density to pulsar systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14966v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhen-Yu Heng, Jiang Long, Run-Ze Yu, Xin-Hao Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective Action in M-Theory: $(DF)^4$ Superinvariants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14984v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct superinvariants in M-theory via local supersymmetry, which include $(DF)^4$ terms and fermionic bilinear terms with mass dimension eight. The bases of the $(DF)^4$ and the fermionic bilinear terms are classified and the variations under the local supersymmetry are evaluated by using the Mathematica codes. By imposing the local supersymmetry, we find that 24 independent terms of $(DF)^4$ are governed by 10 parameters. The result is consistent with the effective action obtained by analyzing scattering amplitudes of superparticles or supermembranes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14984v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoshifumi Hyakutake</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperbolic monopole data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14990v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is known that hyperbolic monopoles, with a particular value of the curvature, can be obtained from ADHM instanton data that satisfies additional constraints. Here this data is reformulated in terms of a triplet of real matrices that satisfy a set of quartic equations, with solutions associated with representations of su(2). Many of the known examples of hyperbolic monopoles can easily be recovered in this formulation by evaluating Nahm data for Euclidean monopoles at the centre of its domain. Toda reductions of Nahm's equation correspond to cyclic Euclidean monopoles, and this is adapted to the hyperbolic setting to obtain solutions, even when the corresponding Nahm data is not tractable. A new family of charge 4 hyperbolic monopoles with square symmetry is presented as an example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14990v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Sutcliffe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticality in 1-dimensional field theories with mesoscopic, infinite range interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15095</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15095v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The study of critical phenomena in one-dimensional field theories with long-range interactions has garnered significant attention following the implications of the Hohenberg-Mermin-Wagner theorem, which precludes phase transitions in most low-dimensional theories with local interactions. This research investigates a novel class of one-dimensional theories characterised by a distinctly defined infinite interaction range. We propose that such theories emerge naturally through a mesoscopic feedback mechanism. In this proof-of-concept study, we examine Ising-type models and demonstrate that the natural emergence of phase transitions, criticality, and previously unidentified universality classes is evident.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15095v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kurt Langfeld, Amanda Turner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective dynamics of open 2D CFTs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15165</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15165v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We analyze the momentum-space representations of the Lorentzian correlators of scalar primary operators in an arbitrary 2D CFT. These correlators characterize the effective dynamics of open quantum systems. We derive the results from the Euclidean correlators through a systematic continuation to Lorentzian signature. Abstractly, it is known that the convergence of the OPE guarantees that the analytic continuation can be carried out also in the case of the four-point function. Here we explicitly perform such analytic continuation, showing that the general structure of the four-point correlator is preserved in Lorentzian signature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15165v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Toni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-perturbative aspects of entanglement structures in $T\bar{T}$-deformed CFTs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15220</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15220v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Turning on the $T\bar{T}$-deformation in a two-dimensional CFT provides a unique window to study explicitly how non-local features arise in the UV as a result of the deformation. A sharp signature is the dynamical emergence of an effective length-scale $\propto \sqrt{\mu}$ that separates the local and non-local regimes of the deformed theory, effectively serving as a UV cut-off for computing observables in the local regime. In this paper, we study this phenomenon through the entanglement structures of the deformed theory. We focus on computing the Renyi entropies of single-interval sub-regions in the deformed vacuum states. We pay particular attention to the interplay between the bare entanglement cut-off inherited from the CFT computation and the effects from the $T\bar{T}$ deformations. Applying the general replica trick to the string theory formulation of $T\bar{T}$-deformed CFTs, we derive an explicit representation of the deformed replica partition function as a weighted integral of the CFT results evaluated at a dynamical cut-off, which is integrated over. We computed in detail the kernel functions of the integral representation, and performed the saddle-point analysis in the semi-classical limit of small $\mu$. We found that in addition to the perturbative saddle-point which identifies the dynamical cut-off with the bare entanglement cut-off, there exists another non-perturbative saddle-point that identifies the dynamical cut-off with the $T\bar{T}$ length-scale $\propto \sqrt{\mu}$, but whose contribution is exponentially small. We discuss how these non-perturbative effects can shed lights on the mechanism through which the $T\bar{T}$ length-scale may eventually replace the bare counter-part and become the effective entanglement cut-off.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15220v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Xin Lai, Huajia Wang, Yongjiang Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fluid Boundary Conditions from AdS/BCFT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15250</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15250v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we initiate our program to classify conformal fluid boundary conditions, by utilizing the fluid/gravity correspondence in the AdS/BCFT correspondence. The AdS/BCFT correspondence is a conjectured duality between a quantum gravity in asymptotically AdS spacetime with an end-of-the world brane and a boundary conformal field theory (BCFT). We show that a choice of boundary condition for the metric on the end-of-the world brane naturally leads to specific boundary conditions for velocity field and temperature field of BCFT in the hydrodynamic limit. We analyze the Neumann, Dirichlet and Conformal boundary conditions for the metric on the end-of-the world brane, and discuss their implications for conformal fluid boundary conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15250v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomohito Shiga, Kenta Suzuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multipartite Markov Gaps and Entanglement Wedge Multiway Cuts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15262v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Markov gap, defined as the difference between reflected entropy and mutual information, serves as a diagnostic for quantum recoverability and multipartite entanglement. In holographic settings, it admits a geometric interpretation as the deviation between entanglement wedge cross-sections and RT surfaces. Motivated by this holographic perspective, we propose a generalization of the Markov gap to multipartite systems by using a reflected multi-entropy. The resulting Multipartite Markov gap can capture geometric obstructions to bulk reconstruction. We investigate the properties of this quantity from both information-theoretic and holographic viewpoints, and examine its potential operational significance through candidate recovery maps. We further introduce the genuine reflected multi-entropy, which is designed to vanish for states containing only lower-partite entanglement. Together, these quantities offer complementary probes of recoverability and multipartite structure in holographic quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15262v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Norihiro Iizuka, Akihiro Miyata, Mitsuhiro Nishida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$Q$-operators, $q$-opers, and R-matrices in 5d $\mathcal{N}=1$ gauge theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15450</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15450v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the quantization of the moduli space of multiplicative Higgs bundles through the lens of five-dimensional $\mathcal{N}=1$ supersymmetric gauge theories in $\Omega$-background. We extend the 4d $\mathcal{N}=2$ gauge theoretical construction of key geometric and representation-theoretic structures, established in earlier works, to the five-dimensional uplift. We construct and analyze the $Q$-operators and $q$-opers associated with the canonical codimension-two defect: the $Q$-operators are defined via the insertion of the defect, while the $q$-opers arise as the $q$-difference chiral ring equations in its presence. The $q$-oper difference equations are further identified with the Baxter TQ equations for XXZ spin chains constructed from tensor products of bi-infinite evaluation modules over quantum affine algebras of type ${\mathfrak{gl}}(n)$. We define a $q$-difference module structure on the space of monodromy codimension-two defect partition functions and show that the eigenstates of the $Q$-operators, constructed from monodromy defects, simultaneously diagonalize the quantum Hamiltonians of the XXZ spin chain. A Fourier transformation exchanges the $Q$-operators associated with two XXZ spin chains bispectral dual to each other. Finally, we relate these constructions to the quantum cluster algebra arising from the BPS quiver of the 5d theory, and re-express the R-matrices in terms of the cluster variables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15450v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saebyeok Jeong, Norton Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One-point functions in AdS/dCFT: MPS and twisted Yangian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15462v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: I focus on the scalar one-point functions in SO(6) sector of D5-D3 probe-brane set-up. Start with a general introduction of integrability, I explore both coordinate Bethe ansatz and algebraic Bethe ansatz, with possible generalization. I then shortly review how to use the Bethe ansatz in $N = 4$ super Yang-Mills theory, and then apply such procedure to the D5-D3 system. The dual field theory of such system corresponds to a defected version of $N = 4$ super Yang-Mills theory, where the one-point functions of certain scalars are non-zero. The calculation of one-point functions is mapped to the overlap between matrix product states and Bethe states. The matrix product states are found to be solutions of the twisted Boundary Yang-Baxter equation, and equivalently the representations of extended twisted Yangian. By dressing procedure or coproduct property, we can connect the scalar matrix product state and higher dimension matrix product states. We have used the branching rules to find the connection with some detailed parameters needed to be fixed. Such method can not only be used for calculations of one-point functions in probe-branes system, but also shed some light on non-equilibrium system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15462v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Qian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>'t Hooft Anomalies and Defect Conformal Manifolds: Topological Signatures from Modulated Effective Actions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15466v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Symmetry breaking of continuous symmetries by extended dynamical defects entails the existence of continuous families of defects, which form conformal manifolds in a critical setup. In the presence of bulk 't Hooft anomalies, defects are in fact required to break the symmetry: defect conformal manifolds are anomaly-enforced. We show that, by coupling the system to a modulated deformation parameter, the geometric structure of the conformal manifold is sensible to the 't Hooft anomaly. This leads to measurable effects in the presence of a boundary/defect: in (1+1)d the anomaly predicts a quantized boundary charge pumping, while in higher dimensions it gives rise to non-dissipative boundary Hall currents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15466v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Copetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The role of scalar current coupling along surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15625v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we propose a coupling between the complex scalar field and an external Dirac delta-like planar potential. The coupling is achieved through the Klein-Gordon current normal to the plane where the potential is concentrated. The results are obtained exactly and exhibit many peculiarities. We show that a complex scalar charge does not interact with the potential, but the potential modifies the interaction between two scalar charges if they are placed on opposite sides of the planar potential. When the coupling constant between the potential and the field goes to infinity, the classical field solutions satisfy a kind of MIT boundary conditions along the plane where the potential is concentrated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15625v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-024-12671-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. C 84, 322 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>F. A. Barone, L. H. C. Borges, G. Flores-Hidalgo, H. L. Oliveira, W. Y. A. da Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meson mass spectrum in Ising Field Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15766</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15766v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the two-particle approximation of the Ising Field Theory (IFT), formulated in terms of the Bethe-Salpeter (BS) equation. Derived by Fonseca and Zamolodchikov as a systematic realization of the McCoy-Wu approach, this equation captures confinement by modeling ``mesons'' as bound states of two Majorana fermions (``quarks''), in a way analogous to the integral equation in the 't Hooft model. Despite its approximate nature, the BS equation provides remarkably accurate predictions for the mass spectrum of stable mesons across a wide range of parameters. Motivated by the striking structural similarity between the BS equation in IFT and the 't Hooft equation in two-dimensional QCD, we develop a new non-perturbative analytical framework inspired by the method of Fateev, Lukyanov, and Zamolodchikov (FLZ). Within this approach, we compute spectral sums and systematically derive the large-$n$ WKB expansion for the Bethe-Salpeter equation, which governs the spectrum of an infinite tower of mesons. We further examine how our analytical results capture the known behavior of the spectrum in well-studied asymptotic regimes, such as the $E_8$ limit and the free-fermion point, where exact solutions are available for comparison. Finally, we discuss how the obtained spectral data admit a natural analytic continuation to complex values of the parameters -- an extension that was one of the primary motivations for this work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15766v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey Litvinov, Pavel Meshcheriakov, Egor Shestopalov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gauge dependence of momentum running in higher-derivative gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15835</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15835v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent works have argued that improved one-loop beta-functions capturing the physical momentum dependence of one-loop corrected higher-derivative gravity theories are the most suitable to describe their high-energy behaviour. This work critically tests the validity of this claim. We compute the explicit gauge dependence of the one-loop momentum running of curvature-squared operators in quadratic gravity and conformal gravity using the background field method. We find them to be gauge dependent, and we discuss the implications of this result for the theory and its physical predictivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15835v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diego Buccio, Gustavo P. De Brito, Luca Parente</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causal Fermion Systems: An Introduction to Fundamental Structures, Methods and Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06450</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06450v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This textbook introduces the basic concepts of the theory of causal fermion systems, a recent approach to the description of fundamental physics. The theory yields quantum mechanics, general relativity and quantum field theory as limiting cases and is therefore a candidate for a unified physical theory. From the mathematical perspective, causal fermion systems provide a general framework for describing and analyzing non-smooth geometries and "quantum geometries." The dynamics is described by a novel variational principle, the causal action principle.
  The book includes a detailed summary of the mathematical and physical preliminaries. It explains the physical concepts behind the causal fermion system approach from the basics. Moreover, all the mathematical objects and structures are introduced step by step. The mathematical methods used for the analysis of causal fermion systems and the causal action principle are introduced in depth. Many examples and applications are worked out.
  The textbook is addressed to master and graduate students in mathematics or physics. Furthermore, it serves as a reference work for researchers working in the field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06450v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Cambridge Monographs on Mathematical Physics, Cambridge University Press (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Felix Finster, Sebastian Kindermann, Jan-Hendrik Treude</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the relation between perspective-neutral, algebraic, and effective quantum reference frames</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14131v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The framework of internal quantum reference frames (QRFs) constitutes a universal toolset for dealing with symmetries in quantum theory and has led to new revelations in quantum gravity, gauge theories and foundational physics. Multiple approaches have emerged, sometimes differing in scope and the way symmetries are implemented, raising the question as to their relation. Here, we investigate the relation between three approaches to QRFs for gauge symmetries, namely the effective semiclassical, algebraic, and perspective-neutral (PN) approaches. Rather than constructing Hilbert spaces, as the PN approach, the effective approach is based on a quantum phase space parametrized by expectation values and fluctuations, while the emphasis of the algebraic approach is on the state space of complex linear functionals on a kinematical algebra. Nevertheless, external frame information is treated as gauge in all three formalisms, manifested in constraints on states and algebra. We show that these three approaches are, in fact, equivalent for ideal QRFs, distinguished by sharp orientations, which is the previous setting of the first two approaches. Our demonstration pertains to single constraints, including relativistic ones, and encompasses QRF changes. In particular, the QRF transformations of the PN framework agree semiclassically with those of the older effective approach, by which it was inspired. As a physical application, we explore the QRF covariance of uncertainties and fluctuations, which turn out to be frame-dependent. This is particularly well-suited for the effective and algebraic approaches, for which these quantities form a natural basis. Finally, we pave the way towards extending these two approaches to non-ideal QRFs by studying the projection and gauge-fixing operations of the Page-Wootters formalism, built into the PN framework, on algebraic states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14131v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julian De Vuyst, Philipp A. Hoehn, Artur Tsobanjan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The BRS Cohomology of the Wess Zumino Chiral Scalar supersymmetric model with exotic pairs and exotic triplets (E2)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14174v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Using the spectral sequence method, this paper advances some of the construction of the BRS cohomology of the Wess Zumino supersymmetric action. An important missing part was the inclusion of the sources for the variations of the fields. In this paper, these sources are called pseudofields. Since the most interesting part of the result contains unsaturated spinor indices, we include a constant spinor to saturate those indices. At dimension zero, this gives rise to a new set of invariants and a closely related new set of possible supersymmetry anomalies in the theory, and we call this an `exotic pair'. At dimension one, this becomes more complicated, and the theory adds a new ghost charge - 1 term, which we call a change, and we call this an `exotic triplet'. For higher dimension and higher spin, it appears that more complications are likely to occur.
  These exotic pairs and triplets are constrained by some simple equations which arise from the spectral sequence. The invariants of the exotic pairs are all dependent on the pseudofields, which means that the field parts of these invariants are not supersymmetric, though the invariants are in the cohomology space of supersymmetry. In this paper we examine the BRS cohomology for low spins and low dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14174v1</guid>
      <category>physics.gen-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John A. Dixon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite Nonlocal Holomorphic Unified Quantum Field Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14203v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper the non-local finite quantum-gravity framework is incorporated into the Complex non-Riemannian Holomorphic Unified Field Theory formulated on a complexified four-dimensional manifold. By introducing entire-function regulators $F(\Box) = \exp\!\bigl(\Box / M_*^2\bigr)$ into the holomorphic Einstein-Hilbert action, we achieve perturbative UV finiteness at all loop orders, while preserving BRST invariance and holomorphic gauge symmetry. We derive the modified gauge-gravity coupling sector, perform a one-loop effective-action computation in a contour-regularized metric background, and demonstrate the absence of new counterterms and problematic complex-pole structures. Extending the construction to nontrivial curved backgrounds, we verify infrared recovery of General Relativity and full holomorphic gauge invariance. Finally, we explore phenomenological consequences, including corrected graviton and gauge-boson scattering amplitudes in self-dual backgrounds, finite Hawking spectra for regularized Schwarzschild and Kerr geometries, and proposed tests of the equivalence principle. This work lays the foundation for a self-consistent, unitary four-dimensional quantum-gravity and Holomorphic Unified Field Theory framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14203v1</guid>
      <category>physics.gen-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. W. Moffat, E. J. Thompson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new parametric observational study of $f(Q,B)$ gravity with modified chaplygin gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14251v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we explore the cosmological dynamics of a modified gravity framework based on the function $f(Q,B)=\delta Q^{2}+\beta B$, where $Q$ denotes the nonmetricity scalar and $B$ is the boundary term that relates $Q$ to the Ricci scalar. The matter sector is modeled using the Modified Chaplygin Gas (MCG) with the equation of state $p=A\rho-\frac{B}{\rho^{\alpha}}$, allowing the model to interpolate between early-time matter behavior and late-time cosmic acceleration. By deriving an analytical expression for the Hubble parameter $H(z)$, we perform a parameter estimation using Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) techniques in conjunction with the latest cosmological observations: $46$ Hubble parameter measurements, $15$ BAO data points, DESI DR2 BAO data and the Pantheon+ Type Ia supernovae compilation. The best-fit values are obtained as $H_0 = 72.22^{+3.64}_{-4.46}$, $A_s = 0.696^{+0.082}_{-0.129}$, $\alpha = 0.0029^{+0.022}_{-0.021}$, and $A = 0.0038^{+0.071}_{-0.047}$. The deceleration parameter transitions at redshift $z_{tr} \approx 0.946$, while the present-day value is $q_0 = -0.789$. The model yields an age of the Universe $t_0 \approx 13.53$ Gyr and a present EoS parameter $\omega_0 \approx -0.691$, which reflects the late-time acceleration consistent with observational bounds. These results demonstrate that the MCG scenario within $f(Q,B)$ gravity provides a viable and observationally consistent framework for explaining the late-time accelerated expansion of the Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14251v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amit Samaddar, S. Surendra Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A quantum algorithm for the n-gluon MHV scattering amplitude</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14252v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a quantum algorithm for computing the n-gluon maximally helicity violating (MHV) tree-level scattering amplitude. We revisit a newly proposed method for unitarisation of non-unitary operations and present how this implementation can be used to create quantum gates responsible for the color and kinematic factors of the gluon scattering amplitude. As a proof-of-concept, we detail the full conceptual algorithm that yields the squared amplitude and implement the corresponding building blocks on simulated noiseless quantum circuits for n = 4 to analyze its performance. The algorithm is found to perform well with parameter optimizations, suggesting it to be a good candidate for implementing on quantum computers also for higher multiplicities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14252v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erik Bashore, Stefano Moretti, Timea Vitos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Sound of an Orbit: A Quantum Spectrum at the ISCO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14254v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the quantum signature of the innermost stable circular orbit (ISCO), a region of profound importance in black hole astrophysics. By modeling an atom as an Unruh-DeWitt detector coupled to a massless scalar field in the Boulware vacuum, we calculate the excitation rate for a detector following a circular geodesic at the ISCO of a Schwarzschild black hole. In stark contrast to the continuous thermal spectra associated with static or infalling observers, our analysis reveals a unique, non-thermal excitation spectrum characterized by a discrete "frequency comb" of sharp, resonant peaks. We show that the locations of these peaks are determined by the orbital frequency at the ISCO, while their intensity increases dramatically as the orbit approaches this final stability boundary. This distinct spectral signature offers a novel theoretical probe of the quantum vacuum in a strong-field gravitational regime and provides a clear distinction between the quantum phenomena experienced by observers on different trajectories. Our findings have potential implications for interpreting the emission spectra from accretion disks and open new avenues for exploring the connection between quantum mechanics and gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14254v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reggie C. Pantig, Ali \"Ovg\"un</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deciphering the dynamics of nuclear collisions with elongated structure of $^{20}$Ne</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14262v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the results obtained from the study of $^{20}$Ne$-$$^{20}$Ne collisions at $\sqrt{s_{NN}}$= 6.8 TeV using the Monte Carlo Pythia8/Angantyr model. Angantyr models heavy-ion collisions as a superposition of independent nucleon-nucleon (NN) collisions, without incorporating collective effects. We construct a bi-pyramidal structure of $^{20}$Ne nucleus composed of five $\alpha$-clusters and compare its collision dynamics against those generated using Woods-Saxon nuclear density distribution. The results are further compared for different orientations of the $^{20}$Ne nuclei, including tip-tip, body-body, body-tip, and random orientations of the bi-pyramidal structure. The results show that the geometric arrangement of $\alpha$-clusters in the $^{20}$Ne nucleus significantly influences the particle production patterns in final state multiplicity, mean transverse momentum ($\langle p_T \rangle$), and elliptic flow coefficient ($v_2$). These results highlight the sensitivity of final state observables to the nuclear structure and orientation of colliding nuclei, providing insights into the dynamics of small collision systems, even in non-hydrodynamic framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14262v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Deependra Sharma, Arpit Singh, Md. Samsul Islam, Sadhana Dash</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Speed of sound peak in isospin QCD: a natural prediction of the Medium Separation Scheme</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14343</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14343v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present predictions for the zero-temperature equation of state at finite isospin density using the Nambu--Jona-Lasinio (NJL) model within the Medium Separation Scheme (MSS) -- a scheme that explicitly disentangles medium effects from the ultraviolet divergent vacuum terms. Recent lattice QCD results reveal a nonmonotonic speed of sound ($c_s^2$) as a function of isospin chemical potential ($\mu_I$), exhibiting explicit violation of the conformal bound $c_s^2 = 1/3$. These findings have attracted significant theoretical interest, as established models -- including the NJL model -- failed to anticipate this behavior prior to lattice simulations. Conventional NJL implementations yield unphysical artifacts, often attributed to regularization scale sensitivity stemming from nonrenormalizability. However, in this work, we demonstrate that the standard NJL framework combined with MSS quantitatively reproduces state-of-the-art lattice data for isospin QCD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14343v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruno S. Lopes, Dyana C. Duarte, Ricardo L. S. Farias, Rudnei O. Ramos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Goldstone bosons across thermal phase transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14348v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Temperature has a significant effect on the properties of quantum field theories (QFTs) with a spontaneously broken symmetry, in particular on the massless Goldstone bosons that exist in the vacuum state. It has recently been shown using lattice calculations for a $\mathrm{U}(1)$ complex scalar field theory that the Goldstone mode persists even when the symmetry is restored above the critical temperature $T_{c}$, and has the properties of a screened massless excitation, a so-called thermoparticle. In this work, we continue the investigation of this theory by determining explicitly how the Goldstone mode evolves as the temperature is increased both below and above $T_{c}$. We find that the two phases of the theory are entirely characterised by the thermal dissipative effects experienced by the Goldstone mode, with the broken and symmetry-restored phases associated with weak and strong damping, respectively. These findings are consistent with the non-perturbative constraints imposed by spontaneous symmetry breaking, and provide a new way in which to characterise thermal phase transitions in QFTs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14348v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Lowdon, Owe Philipsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Susceptibilities and Taylor coefficients of magnetic QCD from perturbation theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14360v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We compute the coefficients $c_2(T,B)$ and $c_4(T,B)$ of the Taylor expansion for the pressure in powers of $\mu_B/T$ in the presence of a large magnetic field within perturbative QCD at finite temperature and baryon density up to two-loops for $N_f=3$ flavors with physical quark masses. We also present results for the excess of pressure, baryon density and baryon number susceptibility as functions of $\mu_B$, as well as susceptibilities as functions of the temperature in the $\{ \mu_B,\mu_Q,\mu_S \}$ basis. Our results can be directly compared to recent lattice QCD data. Even though current lattice results do not overlap with its region of validity, perturbative results seem to be compatible with those obtained on the lattice for large temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14360v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eduardo S. Fraga, Let\'icia F. Palhares, Tulio E. Restrepo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seven Sphere Quantization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14363v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Co-oriented contact manifolds quite generally describe classical dynamical systems. Quantization is achieved by suitably associating a Schr\"odinger equation to every path in the contact manifold. We quantize the standard contact seven sphere by treating it as a homogeneous space of the quaternionic unitary group in order to construct a contact analog of Fedosov's formal connection on symplectic spinor bundles. We show that requiring convergence of the formal connection naturally filters the symplectic spinor bundle and yields an exact flat connection on each corresponding subbundle. A key ingredient is a generalization of the Holstein--Primakoff mechanism to the quaternionic unitary group. The passage from formal to bona fide quantization determines unitary irreducible representations of the quaternionic unitary group, whose dimensions tend to infinity as the formal deformation parameter approaches its classical limit. This appearance of finite-dimensional representations is not surprising since the contact seven sphere is closed and physically describes generalized positions, momenta and time variables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14363v1</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhobrata Chatterjee, Can G\"ormez, Andrew Waldron</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Supersymmetric Standard Model, combined with a special Exotic Invariant, yields a new kind of SUSY mass splitting (E6)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14381</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14381v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Exotic Invariants, with Lorentz invariance, have been found in the BRS cohomology of SUSY in 3+1 dimensions. Until recently, it was generally accepted that no such objects could exist. It is shown here that the Supersymmetric Standard Model (``the SSM'') can be coupled to a special Exotic Invariant to form a new model, which we call the Exotic Model (``the XM'') . This Exotic Model continues to generate the usual Vacuum Expectation Value (``VEV'') that breaks gauge symmetry from SU(3) X SU(2) X U(1) to SU(3) X U(1) But now, from the same VEV, the Exotic Model also generates SUSY violating mass splitting of the neutral ``ZX'' sector at tree level. This is possible because the Exotic Model changes the algebra of SUSY. This ``ZX'' sector is flavour neutral, which might explain the suppression of flavour changing neutral currents observed in experiments. The Exotic Model is governed by a very restrictive Master Equation, so there should be a very small number of parameters in it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14381v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John A. Dixon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multipartite entanglement from ditstrings for 1+1D systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14422v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that multipartite entanglement can be used as an efficient way of identifying the critical points of 1+1D systems. We demonstrate this with the quantum Ising model, lattice $\lambda \phi^4$ approximated with qutrits, and arrays of Rydberg atoms. To do so we make use of multipartite compositions of entanglement quantities for different parts combined to form the strong subadditivity, weak monotonicity, and a convex combination of these with conformal properties. These quantities display some remarkable properties. We will demonstrate how the entanglement of individual parts together displays behavior at phase boundaries, but the combination of these in the aforementioned quantities sharpens and localizes this behavior to the boundaries even better. We will show that we can extend a scheme for approximating the entanglement with the mutual information, and that this acts as a lower bound which will also follow the changes in the entanglement for the above quantities, despite the additional contributions of different signs. This mutual information approximation to the identifying quantities can have its lower probabilities removed in a process we call filtering, and despite the combination of terms will respond well to the filtering and offer improvements to the lower bound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14422v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zane Ozzello, Yannick Meurice</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comments on Exploring Quantum Statistics for Dirac and Majorana Neutrinos using Spinor-Helicity technique (arXiv:2507.07180 [hep-ph])</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14463v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We give our comments on Ref. [1](arXiv:2507.07180) which critiques our idea of exploring quantum statistics to distinguish between Dirac and Majorana neutrinos proposed in some of our earlier works. We show that the ad-hoc symmetrization of the Dirac case amplitude square advocated in Eqs. (16) and (35) of [1], have no physical basis and it leads to violation of lepton number in the the standard model. Therefore, we consider this symmetrization by hand as incorrect and misleading. Moreover, we show that it is even unnecessary for the proof of pDMCT in context of final states containing a neutrino and antineutrino pair.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14463v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. S. Kim, M. V. N. Murthy, Dibyakrupa Sahoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal Cauchy Slice Holography: An Alternative Phase Space For Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14517v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The phase space of gravitational theories in asymptotically Anti-de Sitter (AAdS) spacetimes consists of geometries, matter configurations, and their conjugate momenta on a Cauchy surface, subject to the Hamiltonian, momentum, and matter-gauge constraints. When a unique maximal volume slice exists in all classical solutions of the bulk equations of motion, and the matter fields satisfy certain conditions, we show that this phase space is physically equivalent to an alternative phase space in which the Hamiltonian constraint is replaced by the real Weyl-anomaly constraint, while the momentum and matter-gauge constraints remain unchanged. A necessary requirement for a functional of the metric and matter configurations to qualify as a valid quantum gravity state is that it satisfies the operator gauge constraints. Partition functions of certain conformal field theories with imaginary central charge, defined on bulk Cauchy slices, satisfy these operator gauge constraints and therefore provide candidate quantum gravity states in the alternative phase space formulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14517v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rifath Khan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Properties of compact objects in quadratic non-metricity gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14591v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Astrophysical compact objects are studied in the context of quadratic non-metricity gravity. The solutions to the gravitational field equations, which include fluid components, are analyzed to investigate the density and pressure properties of radio pulsars. It is explicitly demonstrated that the theoretically stable models are consistent with astronomical data, due to the geometric features of the quadratic component. Furthermore, it is shown that, in contrast to the compactness limits of black holes in general relativity, the core density can significantly exceed the density at which nuclear saturation occurs, and the surface density can also surpass the value of nuclear saturation. Additionally, it is found that the radial sound speed remains below the conformal upper bound for sound velocity established by perturbative quantum chromodynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14591v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.aop.2025.170139</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Annals of Physics, 170139 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>G. G. L. Nashed, Kazuharu Bamba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Lattice Physics Approach to Spin-Networks in Loop Quantum Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14630v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this study, we model a spin-network in loop quantum gravity as a regular tetrahedral lattice, applying lattice physics techniques to study its structure and vertex dynamics. Using the area eigenvalue, $A\propto 8\pi l_P^2$, we derive a lattice constant $a = 2.707\,l_P$ and construct a vertex Hamiltonian incorporating a Lennard-Jones potential, zero-point energy, and simple harmonic oscillations. A foliation approach enforces the Wheeler-DeWitt constraint via locally non-zero Hamiltonians that globally cancel. Graviton-like perturbations (treated here as spin-0 bosons) modify the vertex energy spectrum, with variational analysis suggesting twelve coherent excitations per vertex. This model frames flat spacetime as a graviton-rich lattice while enforcing a Brownian-like stochastic picture for the gravitons, and offers a basis for extension into curved quantum geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14630v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noah M. MacKay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universality of gravitational radiation from magnetar magnetospheres</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14634v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The intense magnetic fields inferred from magnetars suggest they may be strong gravitational-wave emitters. Although emissions due to hydromagnetic deformations are more promising from a detection standpoint, exterior fields also contribute a strain. However, numerical evidence suggests that the free energy of stable magnetospheric solutions cannot exceed a few tens of percent relative to the potential state, implying that the gravitational-wave luminosity cannot differ significantly between models. This prompts `universality', in the sense that the strain provides a direct probe of the near-surface field without being muddied by magnetospheric currents. Using a suite of three-dimensional, force-free, general-relativistic solutions for dipole and dipole-plus-quadrupole fields, we find that space-based interferometers may enable marginal detections out to $\lesssim$ kpc distances for slowly-rotating magnetars with fields of $\gtrsim 10^{15}$ G.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14634v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arthur G. Suvorov, Petros Stefanou, Jos\'e A. Pons</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconciling Translational Invariance and Hierarchy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14656v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Tensor networks are not only numerical tools for describing ground states of quantum many-body systems, but also conceptual aids for understanding their entanglement structures. The proper way to understand tensor networks themselves is through explicit examples of solvable ground states that they describe exactly. In fact, this has historically been how tensor networks for gapped ground states, such as the matrix product state (MPS) and the projected entangled paired state, emerged as an elegant analytical framework from numerical techniques like the density matrix renormalization group. However, for gapless ground states, generically described by the multiscale entanglement renormalization ansatz (MERA), a corresponding exactly solvable model has so far been missing. This is because the hierarchical structure of MERA intrinsically breaks the translational invariance. We identify a condition for MERA to be compatible with translational invariance by examining equivalent networks of rank-3 tensors. The condition is satisfied by the previously constructed hierarchical tensor network for the Motzkin and Fredkin chains, which can be considered a non-unitary generalization to the MERA. The hierarchical TN description is complemented by a translationally invariant MPS alternative, which is used to derive the power-law decay of the correlation function and critical exponents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14656v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olai B. Mykland, Zhao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on entropy of matter in presence of gravity: status of extensivity of entropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14817</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14817v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Entropy of matter in a very strong gravity depends on cross-sectional area of the container of the system -- is being further bolstered by calculating entropy of a monoatomic gas kept under uniform strong gravity at Newtonian scale. This bypasses the earlier analysis where existence of horizon is crucial. Also the extensivity of this entropy has been discussed in the light of the same of a two-space dimensional ultra-relativistic non-interacting gas without gravity. The whole analysis, as far as entropy is concerned, indicates that under strong gravity the microscopic degrees of freedom of the system are effectively contributed by the cross-sectional area of the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14817v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saurav Samanta, Bibhas Ranjan Majhi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optics in spiral dislocation spacetime: Torsion as a geometric waveguide and frequency-filtering mechanism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14865v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present an exact analytical investigation of null trajectories and scalar wave propagation in a $(2+1)$-dimensional spacetime containing a spiral dislocation-a topological defect characterized by torsion in the absence of curvature. For null rays, the torsion parameter $\beta$ modifies the affine structure, enforcing a finite turning radius $r_{\min} = \sqrt{b^2 - \beta^2}$ and inducing a torsion-mediated angular deflection that decreases monotonically with increasing $\beta$. The photon trajectory deviates from the curvature-induced lensing paradigm, exhibiting a purely topological exclusion zone around the defect core. In the wave regime, we recast the Helmholtz equation into a Schr\"odinger-like form and extract a spatially and spectrally dependent refractive index $n^2(r,k)$. This index asymptotically approaches unity at large distances, but diverges strongly and negatively near the dislocation core due to torsion-induced geometric terms. The resulting refractive index profile governs the transition from propagating to evanescent wave behavior, with low-frequency modes experiencing pronounced localization and suppression. Our findings reveal that torsion alone, absent any curvature, can act as a geometric regulator of both classical and quantum propagation, inducing effective anisotropy, frequency filtering, and confinement. This framework provides a rare exact realization of light-matter interaction in a torsion-dominated background, with potential applications in analog gravity systems and photonic metamaterials engineered to replicate non-Riemannian geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14865v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Semra Gurtas Dogan, Omar Mustafa, Abdullah Guvendi, Hassan Hassanabadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lifshitz Quantum Mechanics and Anisotropic Josephson Junction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14996v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider quantum mechanics in spacetime with time anisotropy. Such Lifshitz quantum mechanics is characterized by a kinetic term with fractional derivatives. We show that, contrary to popular belief, local conservation of probability is respected when the probability current is properly identified. As an application we consider a Josephson Junction with an anisotropic insulating layer. We show that anisotropy affects the tunneling rate and can greatly enhance the working of Josephson Junction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14996v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chong-Sun Chu, Alfian Gunawan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transversal non-Clifford gates on qLDPC codes breaking the $\sqrt{N}$ distance barrier and quantum-inspired geometry with $\mathbb{Z}_2$ systolic freedom</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15056</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15056v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Historically, a $\sqrt{N}log^{1/2}(N)$ distance barrier for quantum low-density parity-check (LDPC) codes with $N$ qubits persisted for nearly two decades, until the recent discovery of the fibre-bundle code. An open question is whether such a distance barrier can be broken while preserving the ability to perform transversal non-Clifford gates. In this direction, another long-standing distance barrier of $N^{1/3}$ for LDPC stabilizer codes -- present since the discovery of the 3D color code -- was only recently overcome by a construction achieving an $\Omega(\sqrt{N})$ distance (arXiv:2501.19375). The present work further breaks the $\sqrt{N}$ distance barrier by taking a homological product of three good qLDPC codes, combined with the Freedman-Hastings code-to-manifold mapping and the triple cup product to implement transversal CCZ gates. The resulting code achieves an $\Omega(N^{2/3})$ distance (a linear $X$-distance of $\Theta(N)$) and a dimension of $\Theta(N^{2/3})$, which enables fault-tolerant preparation of $\Theta(N^{1/3})$ independent logical CCZ magic states in a single shot, without distillation (`magic state fountain'). This new quantum code also inspires the discovery of a family of exotic $3q$-dimensional manifolds $\mathcal{M}$, which exhibit both a power-law $\mathbb{Z}_2$-($q$, $2q$)-systolic freedom and $\Theta(vol(\mathcal{M}))$ triple intersection points of $2q$-dimensional submanifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15056v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guanyu Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smooth binary evolution from wide resonances in boson clouds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15110v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ultralight scalars can form superradiant clouds around rotating black holes. These may alter the dynamics of compact binaries and the ensuing waveform through orbital resonances and cloud ionization. We re-examine resonances involving states with nonzero decay width, deriving an effective treatment for resonances that are wider than the binary's frequency chirp. We demonstrate the utility of this approach by calculating an upper bound for the cloud's mass surviving up to the latest stages of the inspiral. Next, we study the accumulation of resonances with high-energy bound states. When these infinitely many, increasingly weak resonances are properly taken into account, they smooth out the "sharp features" in the binary's evolution that had been attributed to the ionization of the cloud. We compare our Newtonian results with recent relativistic calculations, highlighting common features as well as discrepancies. Our conclusions emphasize the need to carefully incorporate resonances in boson cloud waveform modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15110v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Maria Tomaselli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is the shear induced spin polarization non-dissipative?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15238</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15238v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The shear-induced polarization plays a crucial role in understanding the local polarization of $\Lambda$ and $\overline{\Lambda}$ hyperons. A key puzzle is whether the shear-induced polarization is non-dissipative or not. In this work, we analyzed the shear-induced polarization and the anomalous Hall effects using the entropy flow and H-theorem introduced from quantum (chiral) kinetic theory. While the shear-induced polarization and the anomalous Hall effect do not directly contribute to the entropy production rate, the perturbations associated with the shear tensor lead to an increase in entropy, similar to the role of the shear tensor in classical kinetic theory. We also examined these effects within the framework of linear response theory using Zubarev's approach. The analysis of time-reversal transformation on the spin current in coordinate space suggests that shear-induced polarization violates time-reversal symmetry and, therefore, should vanish. However, a similar analysis of the Wigner function in phase space does not impose any additional constraints on shear-induced polarization, allowing it to persist in phase space as expected. This discussion indicates that time-reversal analysis in coordinate space alone may not be sufficient to determine whether an effect is dissipative. Furthermore, our analysis based on Zubarev's approach suggests that these effects may indeed possess a dissipative nature. These findings highlight the limitations of the current theoretical framework in fully characterizing the dissipative properties of these phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15238v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Rong Wang, Shuo Fang, Di-Lun Yang, Shi Pu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark energy era with a resolution of Hubble tension in generalized entropic cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15273v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a new dark energy (DE) model from four parameter generalized entropy function of apparent horizon in a spatially flat universe. Such kind of generalized entropy is able to generalize all the known entropies proposed so far, for suitable representations of the entropic parameters. It turns out that the scenario can describe the correct thermal history of the universe, with the sequence of matter and dark energy epochs. Comparing with the $\Lambda$CDM model, the proposed generalized entropic DE model provides a higher value of present Hubble parameter for certain range of entropic parameter(s) leading to a possible resolution of Hubble tension issue. We confront the scenario with CC, PantheonPlus+SH0ES, DESI DR1 and compressed Planck likelihood datasets, which clearly depicts the phenomenological viability of the present model for some best fitted values of entropic parameter(s) that are indeed consistent with the resolution of Hubble tension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15273v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Priyanka Adhikary, Sudipta Das, Sergei D. Odintsov, Tanmoy Paul</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eternal inflation near inflection points: a challenge to primordial black hole models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15522v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Inflation with an inflection point potential is a popular model for producing primordial black holes. The potential near the inflection point is approximately flat, with a local maximum next to a local minimum, prone to eternal inflation. We show that a sufficient condition for eternal inflation is $\lambda_1 \leq 3$, where $\lambda_1$ is the index of the `exponential tail,' the lowest eigenvalue of the Fokker--Planck equation over a bounded region. We write $\lambda_1$ in terms of the model parameters for linear and quadratic regions. Wide quadratic regions inflate eternally if the second slow-roll parameter $\eta_V \geq -6$. We test example models from the literature and show this condition is satisfied; we argue eternal inflation is difficult to avoid in inflection point PBH models. Eternally inflating regions correspond to type II perturbations and form baby universes, hidden behind black hole horizons. These baby universes are inhomogeneous on large scales and dominate the multiverse's total volume. We argue that, if volume weighting is used, eternal inflation makes inflection point primordial black hole models incompatible with large-scale structure observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15522v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eemeli Tomberg, Konstantinos Dimopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Static Black Holes in Massive Gravity Serve as Candidates for Aschenbach-Like Phenomena?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15563</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15563v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Aschenbach effect is widely regarded as a manifestation of two quintessential relativistic features: frame dragging and extreme spacetime curvature. Traditionally associated with rotating geometries, this non-monotonic behavior in orbital angular velocity challenges Newtonian intuition. In our previous work, however, we demonstrated that this velocity irregularity is not exclusive to spinning spacetimes. Specifically, we showed that the presence of a stable minimum in the gravitational potential, corresponding to a stable photon sphere, can reproduce Aschenbach-like behavior in static black holes as well. This observation suggests that, even in the absence of rotational frame dragging, curvature alone (if encoded through appropriate geometric extrema) may be sufficient to induce non-monotonic velocity profiles.
  In this study, we build upon that foundation to investigate whether black hole architectures in theories of Massive Gravity can inherently support the emergence of Aschenbach-like phenomena. Furthermore, can this Aschenbach-like phenomenon in static configurations be considered as an observable signature in the dynamics of general relativity, similar to the original Aschenbach effect in rotating spacetimes?</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15563v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Ali S. Afshar, Jafar Sadeghi, Tahereh Azizi, A. S. Sefiedgar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A comprehensive approach to the physics of mesons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15646</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15646v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a novel approach for the self-consistent solution of coupled sets of Bethe-Salpeter and Schwinger-Dyson equations in QCD. This framework allows us to maintain the axial Ward-Takahashi identities of the theory within advanced approximation schemes, such as the skeleton or three-particle irreducible expansions. For this purpose we reformulate the Schwinger-Dyson equation of the axial-vector vertex such that the bulk of its quantum corrections is expressed in terms of a novel vertex. Crucially, this vertex satisfies a symmetry-induced relation of its own, which involves the full quark-gluon vertex. As a result, the Schwinger-Dyson equation reproduces the standard Ward-Takahashi identity satisfied by the axial-vector vertex. Consequently, the known relation between the quark mass function and the wave function of the pion in the chiral limit is duly fulfilled. The present approach offers valuable insights into the interplay between symmetry and dynamics, and provides a practical path towards computations of hadron physics within sophisticated approximations. In particular, the one-loop dressed truncation of the key dynamical equations, including that of the quark-gluon vertex, is shown to be completely compatible with the required symmetry relations. Further extensions and potential phenomenological applications of the developed framework are briefly discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15646v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Angel. S. Miramontes, Jose M. Morgado Chavez, Joannis Papavassiliou, Jan M. Pawlowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum gravity black holes as dark matter?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15795v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: One of the major problems in quantum gravity research is the lack of signals at the reach of present or near-future experimental facilities. In this paper, we show that this is not the case. Contrary to previous claims, the quantum decay of de Sitter space into black hole spacetimes can be significant even after inflation and can be observed on galactic scales. Using the instanton formalism within the no-boundary proposal for a class of short-scale, quantum-gravity-improved black holes, we show that de Sitter space decay would result in the production of $10^{60}$ stable Planck-size black hole remnants within the current Hubble horizon, which is the number required to explain dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15795v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bernard Carr, Piero Nicolini, Athanasios G. Tzikas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticality at absolute zero from Ising model on two-dimensional dynamical triangulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1710.03402</link>
      <description>arXiv:1710.03402v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We reconsider the criticality of the Ising model on two-dimensional dynamical triangulations based on the $N \times N$ hermitian two-matrix model with the introduction of a loop-counting parameter and linear terms in the potential. We show that in the large-N limit even though the Ising model is classical, the critical temperature can reach absolute zero by tuning the loop-counting parameter, and the corresponding continuum theory turns out to be the quantised theory of neither pure gravity nor gravity coupled to conformal matter with central charge being 1/2.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1710.03402v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.98.026026</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 98, 026026 (2018)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yuki Sato, Tomo Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards elucidation of zero-temperature criticality of Ising model on 2d DT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2003.08524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2003.08524v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the zero-temperature criticality of the Ising model on two-dimensional dynamical triangulations to contemplate its physics. As it turns out, an inhomogeneous nature of the system yields an interesting phase diagram and the physics at the zero temperature is quite sensitive about how we cool down the system. We show the existence of a continuous parameter that characterizes the way we approach the zero-temperature critical point and it may enter in a critical exponent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2003.08524v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.101.106019</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 101, 106019 (2020)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jan Ambj{\o}rn, Yuki Sato, Tomo Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Ubiquity of (Almost) Contact Structures in Hot MQCD at Intermediate Coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.13186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.13186v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Relevant to top-down ${\cal M}$-theory dual of large-$N$ thermal QCD-like theories at intermediate coupling, induced by the $G_2$ structure supported by the closed $M_7$ - a warped product of the ${\cal M}$-theory circle and a non-K\"{a}hler six-fold which is the warped product of the thermal circle with a non-Einsteinian deformation of $T^{1,1}$ - we obtain explicitly (Almost) Contact (3) (Metric)Structure(s) and a three-tuple of $SU(3)$ structures along the "transverse" six-fold induced by the AC(3)MS on $M_7$. A novel result in this context is that in the Infra-Red, within the parameter space of AC3S arising from G2 structures, the subspaces of C3S and AC3S are not mutually "N-path connected". Relevance of the results to staying out of the non-supersymmetric swampland, entanglement entropy of eternal black holes, chaos, bulk-to-shear viscosity ratio $\frac{\zeta}{\eta}$, paramagnetic plasma EoS and photoproduction in a strong magnetic field, in the context of top-down holographic thermal QCD at intermediate coupling, is highlighted/reiterated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.13186v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aalok Misra, Gopal Yadav</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic scattering and non-minimal RT surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15400v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the AdS/CFT correspondence, the causal structure of the bulk AdS spacetime is tied to entanglement in the dual CFT. This relationship is captured by the connected wedge theorem, which states that a bulk scattering process implies the existence of $O(1/G_N)$ entanglement between associated boundary subregions. In this paper, we study the connected wedge theorem in two asymptotically AdS$_{2+1}$ spacetimes: the conical defect and BTZ black hole geometries. In these settings, we find that bulk scattering processes require not just large entanglement, but also additional restrictions related to candidate RT surfaces which are non-minimal. We argue these extra relationships imply a certain CFT entanglement structure involving internal degrees of freedom. Because bulk scattering relies on sub-AdS scale physics, this supports the idea that sub-AdS scale locality emerges from internal degrees of freedom. While the new restriction that we identify on non-minimal surfaces is stronger than the initial statement of the connected wedge theorem, we find that it is necessary but still not sufficient to imply bulk scattering in mixed states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15400v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP10(2024)119</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 10 (2024) 119</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jacqueline Caminiti, Batia Friedman-Shaw, Alex May, Robert C. Myers, Olga Papadoulaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marginality from Leading Soft Gluons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.12521v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Marginal operators in a d-dimensional conformal field theory (CFT), those with conformal dimension $\Delta=d$, give us information about the space of related theories. This can be incredibly useful when trying to develop an intrinsic definition of a holographic CFT. Recent work has established that in the case of celestial CFTs, those dual to asymptotically flat spacetimes, marginal operators can be constructed as shadow transforms of soft scalars. In this work, rather than starting from a bulk theory of scalars, we start with Yang-Mills and construct marginal operators from soft gluons via light transforms. We obtain the local metric and connections for the associated conformal manifold by studying the two- and three-point functions of these marginal operators. We then discuss the implications of this for broadening our understanding of operator product expansions of soft operators in celestial CFTs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.12521v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sruthi A. Narayanan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pole-skipping in two-dimensional de Sitter spacetime and double-scaled SYK model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12330v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop the pole-skipping structure in de Sitter (dS) spacetime and find that their leading frequencies satisfy the relation $\omega_{dS}=i2\pi T_{dS}(1-s)$, where $T_{dS}=1/2\pi L$ and $s$ denotes spin. In the two-dimensional dS spacetime, the pole-skipping points near the cosmic horizon $r=L$ for the scalar field of spin-0 and the fermionic field of spin-$\frac{1}{2}$ correspond one-to-one with those in the classical limit as $\lambda\rightarrow 0$ in double-scaled Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model when the temperature is infinite (DSSYK$_\infty$). This provides a numerical correspondence between quantum gravity in the static patch of two-dimensional dS spacetime and a one-dimensional quantum system, which we consider as a realization of the DS/dS correspondence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12330v5</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/f3cb-kmnc</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 112, 026022 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Haiming Yuan, Xian-Hui Ge, Keun-Young Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bulk Reconstruction and Gauge Invariance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02534</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02534v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we discuss the concept of bulk reconstruction, which involves mapping bulk operators into CFT operators to understand the emergence of spacetime and gravity. We argue that the $N=\infty$ approximation fails to capture crucial aspects of gravity, as it does not respect gauge invariance and lacks direct connections between energy and boundary metrics. Key concepts such as entanglement wedge reconstruction and holographic error correction codes, which are based on the $N=\infty$ theory, may be incorrect or require significant revision when finite $N$ effects are considered. We present explicit examples demonstrating discrepancies in bulk reconstructions and suggest that a gauge-invariant approach is necessary for an accurate understanding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02534v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sotaro Sugishita, Seiji Terashima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hydrodynamics in the Carrollian regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18763v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Carroll hydrodynamics arises in the $c\to 0$ limit of relativistic hydrodynamics. Instances of its relevance include the Bjorken and Gubser flow models of heavy-ion collisions, where the ultrarelativistic nature of the flow makes the physics effectively Carrollian. In this paper, we explore the structure of hydrodynamics in what can be termed as the Carrollian regime, where instead of keeping only the leading terms in the $c\to 0$ limit of relativistic hydrodynamics, we perform a small-$c$ expansion and retain the subleading terms as well. We do so both for perfect fluids as well as viscous fluids incorporating first order derivative corrections. As apposite applications of the formalism, we utilize the subleading terms to compute modifications to the Bjorken and Gubser flow equations which bring in, in particular, dependence on rapidity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18763v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kedar S. Kolekar, Taniya Mandal, Ashish Shukla, Pushkar Soni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimal Models RG flows: non-invertible symmetries &amp; non-perturbative description</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07511</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07511v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this letter we continue the investigation of RG flows between minimal models that are protected by non-invertible symmetries. RG flows leaving unbroken a subcategory of non-invertible symmetries are associated with anomaly-matching conditions that we employ systematically to map the space of flows between Virasoro Minimal models beyond the $\mathbb{Z}_2$-symmetric proposed recently in the literature. We introduce a family of non-linear integral equations that appear to encode the exact finite-size, ground-state energies of these flows, including non-integrable cases, such as the recently proposed $\mathcal{M}(k q + I,q) \to \mathcal{M}(k q - I,q)$. Our family of NLIEs encompasses and generalises the integrable flows known in the literature: $\phi_{(1,3)}$, $\phi_{(1,5)}$, $\phi_{(1,2)}$ and $\phi_{(2,1)}$. This work uncovers a new interplay between exact solvability and non-invertible symmetries. Furthermore, our non-perturbative description provides a non-trivial test for all the flows conjectured by anomaly matching conditions, but so far not-observed by other means.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07511v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/dg1s-5vp6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.Lett. 135 (2025) 2, 021602</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Federico Ambrosino, Stefano Negro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamic stability from Lorentzian path integrals and codimension-two singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08409v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It has previously been shown how the gravitational thermal partition function can be obtained from a Lorentzian path integral. Unlike the Euclidean case, the integration contour over Lorentzian metrics is not immediately ruled out by the conformal factor problem. One can then ask whether this contour can be deformed to pick up nontrivial contributions from various saddle points. In Einstein-Maxwell theory, we argue that the relevance of each black hole saddle to the thermal partition function depends on its thermodynamic stability against variations in energy, angular momentum, and charge. The argument involves consideration of constrained saddles where area and quantities associated with angular momentum and charge are fixed on a codimension-two surface. Consequently, this surface possesses not only a conical singularity, but two other types of singularities. The latter are characterized by shifts along the surface and along the Maxwell gauge group acquired as one winds around near the surface in a metric-orthogonal and connection-horizontal manner. We first study this enlarged class of codimension-two singularities in generality and propose an action for singular configurations. We then incorporate these configurations into the path integral calculation of the partition function, focusing on three-dimensional spacetimes to simplify the treatment of angular momentum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08409v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP05(2025)180</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 05 (2025) 180</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hong Zhe Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Running Love Numbers and the Effective Field Theory of Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18684</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18684v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Massive states produce higher derivative corrections to Einstein gravity in the infrared, which are encoded into operators of the Effective Field Theory (EFT) of gravity. These EFT operators modify the geometry and affect the tidal properties of black holes, either neutral or charged. A thorough analysis of the perturbative tidal deformation problem leads us to introduce a tidal Green function, which we use to derive two universal formulae that efficiently provide the constant and running Love numbers induced by the EFT. We apply these formulae to determine the tidal response of EFT-corrected non-spinning black holes induced by vector and tensor fields, reproducing existing results where available and deriving new ones. We find that neutral black hole Love numbers run classically for $l\geq 3$ while charged ones run for $l\geq2$. Insights from the Frobenius method and from EFT principles confirm that the Love number renormalization flow is a well-defined physical effect. We find that extremal black holes can have Love numbers much larger than neutral ones, up to ${\cal O}(1)$ within the EFT validity regime, and that the EFT cutoff corresponds to the exponential suppression of the Schwinger effect. We discuss the possibility of probing an Abelian dark sector through gravitational waves, considering a scenario in which dark-charged extremal black holes exist in the present-day Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18684v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergio Barbosa, Philippe Brax, Sylvain Fichet, Lucas de Souza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement in Typical States of Chern-Simons Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21894v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We compute various averages over bulk geometries of quantum states prepared by the Chern-Simons path integral, for any level $k$ and compact simple gauge group $G$. We do so by carefully summing over all topologically distinct bulk geometries which have $n$ disjoint boundary tori and a decomposition into space$\times$time of fixed spatial topology. We find that to leading order in the complexity of the state, the typical state contains many types of multiparty entanglement, proving a conjecture of Balasubramanian et al. Additionally, we compute an averaged wave function which captures the leading order statistics of boundary observables in the $n$ torus Chern-Simons Hilbert space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21894v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charlie Cummings</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The spinning self-force EFT: 1SF waveform recursion relation and Compton scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02025v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Building on recent approaches, we develop an effective field theory for the interaction of spinning particles modeling Kerr black holes within the gravitational self-force expansion. To incorporate dimensional regularization into this framework, we analyze the higher-dimensional metric arising from the minimal coupling solution, comparing it against the Myers-Perry black hole and its particle description. We then derive the 1SF self-force effective action up to quadratic order in the spin expansion, identifying a new type of spinning recoil term that arises from integrating out the heavy dynamics. Next, we study the 1SF metric perturbation both from the traditional self-force perspective and through the diagrammatic background field expansion, making contact with the radiative waveform. This leads us to consider a novel recursion relation for the curved space 1SF Compton amplitude, which we study up to one-loop in the wave regime and compare with the flat space one-loop Compton for Kerr up to quadratic order in spin. Finally, we investigate the 1SF spinning Compton amplitude in the eikonal regime, clarifying how strong-field effect -- such as the location of the separatrix -- emerge from the resummation of the perturbative weak-field expansion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02025v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dogan Akpinar, Vittorio del Duca, Riccardo Gonzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>False and genuine decoherence in the early universe: a local observer and time-averaged observables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10472v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study quantum decoherence of curvature perturbations at superhorizon scales caused by the gravitational nonlinearities. We show that cubic gravitational couplings, constrained by the spatial diffeomorphism invariance, lead to infrared (IR) and ultraviolet (UV) divergences in the decoherence rate at one loop. These divergences arise from fluctuations of deep IR modes which look like a background mode for a local observer and violent zero-point fluctuations in the deep UV, respectively. We argue that these divergences are unobservable, as they vanish when considering proper observables. We consider correlators defined using the geodesic distance for IR divergences and time-averaged correlators for UV divergences. To account for these observer's perspectives, we propose to consider an effective quantum state, defined in terms of actual observables, as a more appropriate probe of the quantum coherence of the system measured by an observer. We then evaluate the finite decoherence rate induced by superhorizon environment during inflation and at late universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10472v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fumiya Sano, Junsei Tokuda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EFT strings and dualities in 4d $\mathcal{N}=1$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16984v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the global structure of the states becoming light at perturbative limits of 4d $\mathcal{N}=1$ string and M-theory compactifications, identifying the different duality frames that emerge asymptotically and how they fit together in moduli space. These limits are characterized by the presence of EFT strings - a special class of axionic BPS strings whose tension, derived from the IR K\"ahler potential, vanishes in Planck units at infinite field distance. An intriguing integer scaling relation, $m \sim \mathcal{T}^w$ with $w = \{1,2,3\}$ in Planck units, connects the tension $\mathcal{T}$ of these strings to the mass scale $m$ of the leading tower of states along the string flow. We show that this relation also holds for the subleading towers below the species scale that generate the tower convex hull, implying that their associated $\vec\zeta = -\vec{\nabla} \log m$ vectors lie in a lattice generated by those of the EFT strings. This reveals a striking UV/IR interplay and offers organizing principles for the parametric hierarchies among the relevant UV scales in a given perturbative limit and the web of dualities governing 4d string vacua.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16984v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandra Grieco, Ignacio Ruiz, Irene Valenzuela</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the Thermodynamic Phase Structure of Black Holes through Euler characteristic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06848v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we attempt to explore a possible connection between thermodynamic topology and the thermodynamic geometry formulation of black hole thermodynamics. We study the topological structure of black hole thermodynamic phase spaces by calculating the Euler characteristic (EC) using four well-known thermodynamic geometries: Weinhold, Ruppeiner, Geometrothermodynamics (GTD), and HPEM. We interpret the Euler characteristic as an indicator of the degree of microscopic interactions within the thermodynamic system. As the system approaches the spinoidal curve, the interaction strength increases significantly, eventually driving a phase transition. Beyond the spinoidal region, the interactions begin to weaken, and the system gradually stabilizes into a new phase configuration, reflected by a corresponding change in the topological structure of the thermodynamic state space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06848v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bidyut Hazarika, Prabwal Phukon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry Theories, Wigner's Function, Compactification, and Holography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.23887v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The global symmetry data of a $D$-dimensional absolute quantum field theory can sometimes be packaged in terms of a $(D+1)$-dimensional bulk system obtained by extending along an interval, with a relative QFT$_D$ at one end and suitable gapped / free boundary conditions at the other end. The partition function of the QFT$_D$ can then be interpreted as a wavefunction depending on background fields. However, in some cases, it is not possible or simply cumbersome to fix an absolute form of the symmetry data. Additionally, it is also of interest to consider entangled and mixed states of relative QFTs as well as entangled and mixed states of gapped / free boundary conditions. We argue that Wigner's quasi-probabilistic function on phase space provides a physical interpretation of the symmetry data in all such situations. We illustrate these considerations in the case of string compactifications and holographic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.23887v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan J. Heckman, Max H\"ubner, Chitraang Murdia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Non-Relativistic Strings Propagate Without Geometric Baggage?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12506v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a minimal and dynamically consistent formulation of non-relativistic bosonic string theory in a Newton-Cartan (NC) background. Starting from a reparametrization-invariant Nambu-Goto action, we develop the Hamiltonian framework and perform a complete Dirac constraint analysis. The resulting structure exhibits first-class constraints that generate worldsheet diffeomorphisms, confirming the internal gauge consistency of the model. Using an interpolating Lagrangian, we derive a Polyakov-type action that enables a direct comparison with symmetry-based constructions known as gauging the algebra (GTA) approaches, which promote non-relativistic symmetry algebras to local symmetries. In contrast to GTA formulations, which require additional background fields to achieve algebraic closure, our model derives all necessary geometric data dynamically from the string evolution itself. This establishes that standard Newton-Cartan geometry is sufficient to support consistent non-relativistic string dynamics. Our results provide a conceptually transparent and technically robust foundation for future studies of non-relativistic string theory in curved backgrounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12506v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Partha Nandi, Sk. Moinuddin, Abdus Sattar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbative unitarity bounds on field-space curvature in de Sitter spacetime: purity vs scattering amplitude</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.00850v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study perturbative unitarity bounds on the field-space curvature in de Sitter spacetime, using the momentum-space entanglement approach recently proposed by Pueyo, Goodhew, McCulloch, and Pajer. As an illustration, we perform a perturbative computation of the purity in two-scalar models and compare the resulting unitarity bounds with those obtained via a flat space approximation. In particular, we find that perturbative unitarity imposes an upper bound on the field-space curvature of the Hubble scale order, in addition to a bound analogous to the flat space result. This reflects the thermal nature of de Sitter spacetime. We also discuss generalizations to higher-dimensional field spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.00850v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qianhang Cai, Tomoya Inada, Masataka Ishikawa, Kanji Nishii, Toshifumi Noumi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An M-theory dS maximum from Casimir energies on Riemann-flat manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02037</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.02037v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We initiate the study of flux compactifications on non-supersymmetric Riemann-flat manifolds (RFM's) with Casimir energy. While curvature and other corrections are suppressed in RFM's, the inclusion of Casimir energies allows one to evade standard dS no-go theorems, and the absence of orientifolds or other singular sources means that the construction is completely captured by ten or eleven-dimensional supergravity. We obtain a fully explicit formula for the Casimir stress-energy in a general RFM, including its ten or eleven-dimensional profile. The Casimir energy localizes in particular loci of the RFM, which we call "Casimir branes". The tension of Casimir branes sometimes cancels exactly, due to a spacetime analog of worldsheet Atkin-Lehner symmetry. We use Casimir energies to construct an explicit $dS_5$ maximum solution of a flux compactification of M-theory on a specific 6-dimensional RFM. The resulting solution is scale-separated, has a vacuum energy of $10^{-15}$ in five-dimensional Planck units, the Hubble radius is $10^7$ Planck lengths, and the light fields have masses of order $H^2$. This is a fully explicit, top-down de Sitter maximum in M-theory, with precisely computable vacuum energy. While the solution is not parametric, it is under extraordinary control: higher derivative and loop corrections to the vacuum energy are suppressed in powers of a small parameter $\delta V/V\sim 10^{-10}$, and M2 and M5-brane instantons are negligible. In short, the solution survives all known corrections. Nevertheless, it might be sensitive to more exotic ones, such as e.g. loops of 11d Planckian virtual black holes if there were a large enough number of them. We also extend the Ewald numerical method for lattice sums to arbitrary dimensions and develop an efficient numerical implementation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.02037v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruno Valeixo Bento, Miguel Montero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact Confining Solution of the Planar QCD Loop Equation via a Matrix Ensemble</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05096v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct an exact solution to the planar QCD loop equation in four-dimensional Euclidean space using a novel matrix-valued momentum loop formalism. Central to this construction is a new loop calculus, in which functional derivatives act directly on the loop velocity \( \dot{C}(\theta) \). This framework yields finite, well-defined expressions for point and area derivatives in loop space and reveals the role of the loop-space Bianchi identity in ensuring gauge consistency.
  The Wilson loop is expressed as an average over matrix-valued momentum loops \( P(\theta) \) tracing closed paths in a compact complex manifold, constrained by self-duality and boundary conditions. Self-duality dynamically nullifies the classical Yang--Mills term in the loop equation, while the boundary constraints eliminate the contact terms in the planar (\( N \to \infty \)) limit. Thus, the full planar QCD loop equation is satisfied exactly and without modification.
  We further argue that these random walks define a self-dual minimal surface in an extended matrix space, and \textbf{prove} that the area of this matrix minimal surface scales proportionally to the Euclidean minimal area bounded by the same loop \( C \), thereby providing a sufficient condition for quark confinement. In the example of an elliptic loop, we construct the exact surface and compute its area analytically, finding that it equals the Euclidean area multiplied by a universal factor of \( 1/\sqrt{2} \), independent of the ellipse parameters.
  These results provide the first known explicit construction of a quark-confining minimal surface that solves the planar QCD loop equation exactly, and open a new path toward understanding gauge--string duality from first principles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05096v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Migdal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transition from weak to strong coupling in thermal gauge theories: Lessons from ${\cal N}=4$ SYM Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.06845v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the transition between weak and strong coupling in thermal ${\cal N}=4$ supersymmetric Yang-Mills (SYM) theory as a function of 't Hooft coupling $\lambda$ for several quantities of phenomenological interest for which next-to-leading order calculations are available in both regimes. We use Pad\'e approximants to interpolate between the weak and strong coupling expansions and determine the location and width of the transition between the asymptotic regimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.06845v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Berndt M\"uller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The thermal backreaction of a scalar field in de Sitter spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08774v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We argue that a scalar field in de Sitter spacetime should feel explicit thermal effects associated with its curvature. Starting from the Bunch-Davies vacuum and a scalar field with small mass compared to the de Sitter curvature, we use the thermo-field dynamics formalism in order to expose these thermal effects. We compute the thermal Wightman function connecting two spacetime points and from it, via the point-splitting regularization technique, the renormalized thermal energy-momentum tensor. We then examine how these corrections affect the de Sitter geometry by solving for the semi-classical backreaction and find that their sign depends on the initial conditions. In order to place our results in context, we compare them to the corresponding 2-loop quantum gravity correction to the cosmological constant derived in [1].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08774v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikos Irges, Antonis Kalogirou, Fotis Koutroulis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Angular Momentum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14931v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum states of a spin $\tfrac{1}{2}$ (a qubit) are parametrized by the space ${\mathbf {CP}}^1 \sim S^2$, the Bloch sphere. A spin $j$ for a generic $j$ (a $2j+1$-state system) is represented instead by a point of a larger space, ${\mathbf {CP}}^{2j}$. Here we study the state of a single angular momentum/spin in the limit, $j \to \infty$. The special class of states $ | j, {\mathbf n}\rangle \in {\mathbf {CP}}^{2j} $, with spin oriented towards definite spatial directions ${\mathbf n} \in S^2$, i.e., $({\mathbf J}\cdot {\mathbf n} ) \, | j, {\mathbf n}\rangle = j\, |j, {\mathbf n}\rangle $, are found to behave as classical angular momenta, $j \, {\mathbf n}$, in this limit. Vice versa, general spin states in ${\mathbf {CP}}^{2j}$ do not become classical, even at large $j$. We discuss these questions, by analysing the Stern-Gerlach processes, the angular-momentum composition rule, and the rotation matrix. Our observations help to clarify better how classical mechanics emerges from quantum mechanics in this context (e.g., with unique trajectories for a particle carrying a large spin), and to make the widespread idea that large spins somehow become classical, more precise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14931v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kenichi Konishi, Roberto Menta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Creation of domain-wall Skyrmions in chiral magnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19056</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19056v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the capture of a magnetic Skyrmion into a domain wall (DW) structure in chiral magnets and find that in the respective ground states of the DW and the Skyrmion, they repel each other. This means that an isolated magnetic Skyrmion cannot a priori enter the DW and become a DW-Skyrmion. However, rotating the DW's phase away from the stable phase may cause the successful capture and hence creation of a stable bound state of a magnetic Skyrmion and a DW: the DW-Skyrmion. At certain distances, the DW may also destroy the magnetic Skyrmion by inducing shrinkage of the latter. This happens as the isolated magnetic Skyrmion has negative DMI energy, whereas the DW-Skyrmion has positive DMI energy; in a finite range from the DW, the magnetic Skyrmion can be pushed to have vanishing DMI energy, for which it collapses to a point. En passant, we find the possibility of pair creation of a Skyrmion anti-DW-Skyrmion pair and a creation of more than one DW-Skyrmions by a Kibble-like mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19056v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sven Bjarke Gudnason, Yuki Amari, Muneto Nitta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breaking parity: the case of the trispectrum from chiral scalar-tensor theories of gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11801v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recently, possible hints of parity violation have been observed in the connected galaxy four-point correlation function. Although the true origin of the signal from the analysis has been debated, should they have a physical origin, they might point to primordial non-Gaussianity and would be evidence of new physics.
  In this work, we examine the single-field slow-roll model of inflation within chiral scalar-tensor theories of modified gravity. These theories, treated here as new Lorentz-breaking theories, extend the Chern-Simons one by including parity-violating operators containing first and second derivatives of the non-minimally coupled scalar (inflaton) field. This model is capable of imprinting parity-violating signatures in late-time observables, such as the galaxy four-point correlation function. We perform an analysis of the graviton-mediated scalar trispectrum of the gauge-invariant curvature perturbation $\zeta(t,\mathbf{x})$ using one of the parity-violating operators of these theories as a case study. We estimate that for a set of parameters of the theory it is possible to produce a signal-to-noise ratio for the parity-violating part of the trispectrum of order one without introducing modifications to the single-field slow-roll setup. Even if the signal found in the analysis turns out to be spurious or if no parity violation is ever detected in the galaxy four-point correlation function, our analysis can be used to constrain the free parameters of these theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11801v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/07/051</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 07 (2025) 051</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tommaso Moretti (Physics Dept., Naples, ITALY), Nicola Bartolo (Physics,Astronomy Dept.,INFN,INAF, Padova, ITALY), Alessandro Greco (Astronomy Dept., Gainesville, USA)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chaotic motion of the charged test particle in a Kerr-MOG black hole with explicit symplectic algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06122v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Kerr-MOG black hole has recently attracted significant research attention and has been extensively applied in various fields. To accurately characterize the long-term dynamical evolution of charged particles around Kerr-MOG black hole, it is essential to utilize numerical algorithms that are high-precision, stable, and capable of preserving the inherent physical structural properties. In this study, we employ explicit symplectic algorithms combined with the Hamiltonian splitting technique to numerically solve the equations of motion for charged particles. Initially, by decomposing the Hamiltonian into five integrable components, three distinct explicit symplectic algorithms ($S2$, $S4$, and $PR{K_6}4$) are constructed. Numerical experiments reveal that the $PR{K_6}4$ algorithm achieves superior accuracy. Subsequently, we utilize Poincar\'e sections and the Fast Lyapunov Indicator (FLI) to investigate the dynamic evolution of the particle. Our numerical results demonstrate that the energy $E$, angular momentum $L$, magnetic field parameter $\beta$, black hole spin parameter $a$, and MOG parameter $\alpha$ all significantly influence the particle's motion. Specifically, the chaotic region expands with increases in $E$, $\beta$, or $\alpha$, but contracts with increases in $a$ or $L$. Furthermore, when any two of these five parameters are varied simultaneously, it becomes evident that $a$ and $L$ predominantly dictate the system's behavior. This study not only offers novel insights into the chaotic dynamics associated with Kerr-MOG black holes but also extends the application of symplectic algorithms in strong gravitational field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06122v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhen-Meng Xu, Da-Zhu Ma, Wen-Fu Cao, Kai Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algorithmic construction of SSA-compatible extreme rays of the subadditivity cone and the ${\sf N}=6$ solution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15364v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We compute the set of all extreme rays of the 6-party subadditivity cone that are compatible with strong subadditivity. In total, we identify 208 new (genuine 6-party) orbits, 52 of which violate at least one known holographic entropy inequality. For the remaining 156 orbits, which do not violate any such inequalities, we construct holographic graph models for 150 of them. For the final 6 orbits, it remains an open question whether they are holographic. Consistent with the strong form of the conjecture in arXiv:2204.00075, 148 of these graph models are trees. However, 2 of the graphs contain a "bulk cycle", leaving open the question of whether equivalent models with tree topology exist, or if these extreme rays are counterexamples to the conjecture. The paper includes a detailed description of the algorithm used for the computation, which is presented in a general framework and can be applied to any situation involving a polyhedral cone defined by a set of linear inequalities and a partial order among them to find extreme rays corresponding to down-sets in this poset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15364v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP06(2025)055</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Temple He, Veronika E. Hubeny, Massimiliano Rota</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vacuum Polarization, Geodesic Equation and Sachs-Wolfe Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08748v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that the null geodesic equation for photons is modified in the presence of a charged scalar field, with quantum fluctuations acting as an effective mass term that changes the null paths to timelike curves. This effect can be interpreted as a vacuum polarization phenomenon in curved spacetime. The resulting contribution to the Sachs-Wolfe effect varies with photon frequency, leading to frequency-dependent corrections to the cosmic microwave background (CMB) blackbody spectrum in the form of a $\mu$-distortion, as well as modifications to the CMB power spectrum. We estimate these within a standard inflationary scenario and find that while the correction to the CMB power spectrum is significant when the scalar field is light, the magnitude of the $\mu$-distortion depends strongly on the regularization prescription.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08748v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Kaya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological observables and $\theta$ dependence in high temperature QCD from lattice simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15407v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study topology in Quantum Chromodynamics at high temperatures by means of lattice calculations. Simulations are performed with $N_f=2+1+1$ Wilson twisted mass fermions at maximal twist with physical quark masses, and temperatures $T~\gtrsim~180$ MeV. The results obtained with three lattice spacings ranging between $0.057$ and $0.080$ fm are extrapolated to the continuum limit. We compare the results for the topological susceptibility obtained with the field-theoretic definition with those obtained from an observable constructed with the disconnected part of the chiral susceptibility, and we confirm their agreement -- within the largish errors -- on our range of temperatures. We also study the topological charge distribution, the next order cumulant $b_2$ and, for the first time, the Free Energy as a function of the $\theta$ angle. We find a rapid crossover to the Dilute Instanton Gas behaviour above $ T \simeq 300$ MeV for all the observables we have considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15407v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Yu. Kotov, M. P. Lombardo, A. Trunin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure of center-vortex matter in SU(4) Yang-Mills theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19656v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The structure of center vortices is studied in SU(4) Yang-Mills theory for the first time to illuminate the interplay between elementary (center charge $\pm 1$) and doubly charged vortices. Unlike in SU(3), where charge $+2$ vortices are simply elementary vortices with reversed orientations in spacetime, these possibilities are physically distinct in SU(4). Visualizations of the vortex structure in three-dimensional slices reveal the various ways in which doubly charged objects manifest, as the convergence and matching of elementary vortices or as isolated doubly charged loops. An algorithm is described to classify every doubly charged chain as one of these three types. A collection of vortex statistics is considered to quantify the vortex structure. Many of these pertain to the novel doubly charged objects, including their relative proportions and chain lengths, which are analyzed to highlight the differences between each chain type. Three different lattice spacings are employed to investigate the approach to the continuum limit. Vortex matching chains are found to be shorter on average but also more prevalent than vortex convergences, ascribed to their interpretation as extended center monopoles. In addition, the lengths of both vortex convergences and vortex matchings are observed to follow an exponential distribution, allowing the introduction of a constant probability for a doubly charged chain to split into two elementary vortices as it propagates. Combined, these findings provide a characterization of the vortices that comprise center-vortex structures in SU(4) Yang-Mills theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19656v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/5d34-52zj</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 112, 014510 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jackson A. Mickley, Derek B. Leinweber, Luis E. Oxman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Color-magnetic correlations in SU(N) lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19874v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Motivated by color-magnetic instabilities in QCD, we investigate field-strength correlations in both SU(2) and SU(3) lattice QCD. In the Euclidean Landau gauge, we numerically calculate the perpendicular-type color-magnetic correlation, $C_{\perp}(r) \equiv g^2 \langle H_z^a(s)H_z^a(s + r\hat \perp)) \rangle$ with $\perp \equiv x, y$, and the parallel-type one, $C_{\parallel}(r) \equiv g^2 \langle H_z^a(s)H_z^a(s + r\hat \parallel) \rangle$ with $\parallel~\equiv z, t$. In the Landau gauge, all two-point field-strength correlations $g^2 \langle G^a_{\mu\nu}(s)G^b_{\alpha\beta}(s')\rangle$ are described by these two quantities, due to the Lorentz and global SU($N_c$) color symmetries. Curiously, the perpendicular-type color-magnetic correlation $C_{\perp}(r)$ is found to be always negative for arbitrary $r$, except for the same point of $r=0$. The parallel-type color-magnetic correlation $C_{\parallel}(r)$ is always positive. In the infrared region, $C_{\perp}(r)$ and $C_{\parallel}(r)$ strongly cancel each other, which leads to an approximate cancellation for the sum of the field-strength correlations as $\sum_{\mu, \nu} \langle G^a_{\mu\nu}(s)G^a_{\mu\nu}(s')\rangle \propto C_{\perp}(|s-s'|)+ C_{\parallel}(|s-s'|) \simeq 0$. Next, we decompose the perpendicular-type color-magnetic correlation $C_{\perp}(r)$ into quadratic, cubic and quartic terms of the gluon field $A_\mu$. The quadratic term is always negative, which is explained by the Yukawa-type gluon propagator $\langle A^a_\mu(s)A^a_\mu(s')\rangle \propto e^{-mr}/r$ with $r\equiv |s-s'|$ in the Landau gauge. The quartic term gives a relatively small contribution. In the infrared region, the cubic term is positive and tends to cancel with the quadratic term, resulting in a small value of $C_{\perp}(r)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19874v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PoS(QCHSC24) 045 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hideo Suganuma (Kyoto U.), Atsuya Tokutake (Kyoto U.), Kei Tohme (Kyoto U.)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gauging non-invertible symmetries on the lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02925</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02925v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We provide a general prescription for gauging finite non-invertible symmetries in 1+1d lattice Hamiltonian systems. Our primary example is the Rep(D$_8$) fusion category generated by the Kennedy-Tasaki transformation, which is the simplest anomaly-free non-invertible symmetry on a spin chain of qubits. We explicitly compute its lattice F-symbols and illustrate our prescription for a particular (non-maximal) gauging of this symmetry. In our gauging procedure, we introduce two qubits around each link, playing the role of "gauge fields" for the non-invertible symmetry, and impose novel Gauss's laws. Similar to the Kramers-Wannier transformation for gauging an ordinary $\mathbb{Z}_2$, our gauging can be summarized by a gauging map, which is part of a larger, continuous non-invertible cosine symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02925v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sahand Seifnashri, Shu-Heng Shao, Xinping Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The frozen vanilla model: Exploring dark sector interactions with delta effective theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21110v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce a new interacting mechanism within the dark sector, encompassing both dark energy and dark matter, while grounding our analysis in the familiar framework of the $\mathrm{\Lambda CDM}$ model augmented by baryons and radiation components, including photons and neutrinos. The interaction between dark energy and dark matter is confined to the perturbative level. One significant advantage of this proposal is that all geometric probes yield constraints consistent with the so-called vanilla model or the extended vanilla model, where dark energy has a constant equation of state, $w_{x}$. However, the introduction of this new interacting mechanism affects several theoretical signatures, involving contrast dark matter and dark energy densities. We perform an exploratory analysis of those effects in the CMB power spectra, matter-power spectra, and redshift space distortions. For instance, it allows for a decrease/increment in the integrated Sachs-Wolfe (ISW) effect depending on the value taken by the interaction coupling. This effect could be observationally detected by looking for a cross-correlation between the ISW temperature fluctuations and the distribution of galaxies or quasars. At late times, the interaction in the dark sector becomes very effective, affecting the non-linear scale of structure formation. We discuss how the estimators $f\sigma_{8}(z)$ and $S_{8}(z)$ are affected by different interacting couplings; indicating that $f\sigma_{8}(z)$ can show a relative change of up to $15\%$ compared to the concordance model at low redshifts. Finally, we show how the various terms in the dark energy pressure perturbation (both adiabatic and non-adiabatic) are relevant for different scales, demonstrating the absence of large-scale instabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21110v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mart\'in G. Richarte, Luiz F. Guimar\~aes, Susana J. Landau, J\'ulio C. Fabris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining Reheating Temperature, Inflaton-SM Coupling and Dark Matter Mass in Light of ACT DR6 Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13387</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13387v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We explore the phenomenological implications of the latest Atacama Cosmology Telescope (ACT) DR6 observations, in combination with Planck 2018, BICEP/Keck 2018, and DESI, on the physics of inflation and post-inflationary reheating. We focus on the $\alpha$-attractor class of inflationary models (both E- and T-models) and consider two reheating scenarios: perturbative inflaton ($\phi$) decay ($\phi \rightarrow bb$) and inflaton annihilation ($\phi \phi \rightarrow bb$) into Standard Model (SM) bosonic particles ($b$). By solving the Boltzmann equations, we derive bounds on key reheating parameters, including the reheating temperature, the inflaton equation of state (EoS), and the inflaton-SM coupling, in light of ACT data. To accurately constrain the coupling, we incorporate the Bose enhancement effect in the decay width. To ensure the validity of our perturbative approach, we also identify the regime where nonperturbative effects, such as parametric resonance, become significant. Additionally, we include indirect constraints from primordial gravitational waves (PGWs), which can impact the effective number of relativistic species, $\Delta N_{\rm eff}$. These constraints further bound the reheating temperature, particularly in scenarios with a stiff EoS. Finally, we analyze dark matter (DM) production through purely gravitational interactions during reheating and determine the allowed mass ranges consistent with the constrained reheating parameter space and recent ACT data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13387v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rajesh Mondal, Sourav Mondal, Ayan Chakraborty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error-resilient Reversal of Quantum Chaotic Dynamics Enabled by Scramblons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19915v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The emergence of the arrow of time in quantum many-body systems stems from the inherent tendency of Hamiltonian evolution to scramble quantum information and increase entanglement. While, in principle, one might counteract this temporal directionality by engineering a perfectly inverted Hamiltonian to reverse entanglement growth, such a scenario is fundamentally unstable because even minor imperfections in the backward evolution can be exponentially amplified, a hallmark of quantum many-body chaos. Therefore, successfully reversing quantum many-body dynamics demands a deep understanding of the underlying structure of quantum information scrambling and chaotic dynamics. Here, by using solid-state nuclear magnetic resonance on a macroscopic ensemble of randomly interacting spins, we measure the out-of-time-ordered correlator (OTOC) and validate key predictions of scramblon theory, a universal theoretical framework for information scrambling. Crucially, this theory enables us to isolate and mitigate errors in the OTOC caused by imperfections in the backward evolution. As a result, this protocol uncovers the anticipated exponential behavior of quantum many-body chaos and extracts the quantum Lyapunov exponent in a many-body experimental system for the first time. Our results push the fundamental limits of dynamical reversibility of complex quantum systems, with implications for quantum simulation and metrology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19915v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Chen Li, Tian-Gang Zhou, Shengyu Zhang, Ze Wu, Liqiang Zhao, Haochuan Yin, Xiaoxue An, Hui Zhai, Pengfei Zhang, Xinhua Peng, Jiangfeng Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Carrollian $\mathbb{R}^\times$-bundles II: Sigma Models on Event Horizons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00544</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.00544v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Carrollian field theories are usually understood as limits of relativistic theories. In this note, we use Carrollian $\mathbb{R}^\times$-bundles equipped with a principal connection to construct Carrollian sigma models intrinsically. The resulting theories are neither ``electric'' nor ``magnetic'' in the usual sense. As a physically suggestive example, we derive a Carrollian wave equation governing the dynamics of a scalar field on the event horizon of a Schwarzschild black hole.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.00544v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew James Bruce</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kerr black hole in a uniform magnetic field: An exact solution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05199</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05199v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A new class of exact spacetimes in Einstein's gravity, which are Kerr black holes immersed in an external magnetic (or electric) field that is asymptotically uniform and oriented along the rotational axis, is presented. These are axisymmetric stationary solutions to the Einstein-Maxwell equations such that (unlike in the Plebanski-Demianski spacetime) the null directions of the Faraday tensor are not aligned with neither of the two principal null directions of the Weyl tensor of algebraic type D (unlike the Kerr-Melvin spacetime). Three physical parameters are the black hole mass $m$, its rotation $a$, and the external field value $B$. For vanishing $B$ the metric directly reduces to standard Boyer-Lindquist form of the Kerr black hole, while for zero $m$ we recover conformally flat Bertotti-Robinson universe with a uniform Maxwell field. For zero $a$ the spacetime is contained in the Alekseev-Garcia and the Van den Bergh-Carminati solutions which can be understood as the Schwarzschild black hole in a magnetic field. Our family of black holes with non-aligned Maxwell hair - that can be called the Kerr-Bertotti-Robinson (Kerr-BR) black holes - may find application in various studies ranging from mathematical relativity to relativistic astrophysics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05199v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiri Podolsky, Hryhorii Ovcharenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grand-unification Theory Atlas: Standard Model and Beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.06368v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Under a reasonable set of ab-initio assumptions, we define and chart the atlas of simple gauge theories with families of fermions whose masses are forbidden by gauge invariance. We propose a compass to navigate the atlas based on counting degrees of freedom. When searching for Grand-unification Theories with three matter generations, the free energy singles out the SU(5) Georgi-Glashow model as the minimal one, closely followed by SO(10) with spinorial matter. The atlas also defines the dryland of grand-unifiable gauge extensions of the standard model. We further provide examples relevant for gauge dual completions of the standard model as well as extensions by an additional SU(N) gauge symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.06368v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giacomo Cacciapaglia, Aldo Deandrea, Konstantinos Kollias, Francesco Sannino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microcausality and Tunneling Times in Relativistic Quantum Field Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09066</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09066v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show, in the framework of a space-time resolved relativistic quantum field theory approach to tunneling, that microcausality precludes superluminal tunneling dynamics. More specifically in this work dealing with Dirac and Klein-Gordon fields, we first prove that microcausality holds for such fields in the presence of a background potential. We then use this result to show that an intervention performed on a localized region of an initial wave packet subsequently scattering on a potential barrier does not result in any effect outside the light cone emanating from that region. We illustrate these results with numerical computations for Dirac fermions and Klein-Gordon bosons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09066v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammed Alkhateeb, Alex Matzkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Infeasibility of Low-Energy Warp Drive via Metamaterial Gravitational Coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09724</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09724v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent ``low-energy'' warp-drive concepts propose replacing the constant gravitational coupling $\kappa_0$ with a spatially varying scalar field $\kappa(x)$ set by an engineered metamaterial's electromagnetic response. We show that the idea fails on both theoretical and experimental grounds. A prescribed, non-dynamical $\kappa(x)$ in the field equation $G^{\mu\nu} = \kappa(x)T^{\mu\nu}$ clashes with the contracted Bianchi identity, $\nabla_\mu G^{\mu\nu} \equiv 0$, forcing $\nabla_\mu T^{\mu\nu} \neq 0$ and thus violating local energy-momentum conservation. Making $\kappa(x)$ dynamical yields a scalar-tensor theory in which the scalar mediates a new long-range force that breaks the strong equivalence principle; Solar-System and pulsar-timing experiments already restrict $|\gamma - 1| \lesssim 10^{-5}$, excluding any technologically useful coupling. Junction-condition analysis further shows that any interface where $\kappa$ changes demands a $\delta$-function layer of stress-energy, while even steep continuous profiles are ruled out by torsion-balance, lunar-laser, and spacecraft Doppler measurements. Hence the concept is untenable: a non-dynamical scheme violates conservation laws, and its scalar-tensor completion is falsified by existing data..</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09724v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Rodal</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
