<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th</link>
    <description>hep-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 05:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Sasaki-Einstein Geometry, GK Geometry and the AdS/CFT correspondence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01950</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01950v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We review various aspects of Sasaki-Einstein and GK geometry, emphasising their similarities, interconnections and significance for the AdS/CFT correspondence. In particular, we highlight the key role that physical considerations have played in formulating geometric extremization principles, which have been instrumental in both understanding the geometry and identifying the corresponding dual field theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01950v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jerome P. Gauntlett, Dario Martelli, James Sparks</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deciphering Coupled Scalar Dark Sectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01961v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Coupled dark sector models have gained significant attention, motivated by recent advances in cosmology and the pressing need to address unresolved puzzles. In this work, we study coupled scalar dark sector models inspired by ultraviolet-complete frameworks such as supergravity and string theory. These models involve scalar couplings arising either from their kinetic terms, through a non-trivial field space metric, or from their scalar potential. We demonstrate how these couplings can be elegantly formulated in terms of an interacting vector, a standard tool in coupled dark sector studies, and analyse their distinct cosmological effects using a dynamical systems approach. Using this framework, we further investigate an axio-dilaton system recently explored in the literature, where the dilaton also couples to baryons. Intriguingly, we show that certain kinetic and potential interactions may mimic one another or even cancel out, making them observationally indistinguishable. If such a distinction becomes possible through observational constraints, it could provide valuable insights into the underlying field space metric and its connection to fundamental physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01961v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saba Rahimy, Elsa M. Teixeira, Ivonne Zavala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Kaluza-Klein AdS Virasoro-Shapiro Amplitude near Flat Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01964v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We bootstrap the first-order correction in the curvature expansion of the Virasoro-Shapiro amplitude in AdS spacetime, for arbitrary Kaluza-Klein charges of external operators. By constructing a universal ansatz based on single-valued multiple polylogarithms as well as an AdS$\times$S formalism, and matching it with the low-lying result, we derive a unified formula in terms of world-sheet integrals. Our result predicts an infinite number of Wilson coefficients that were not available in previous literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01964v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bo Wang, Di Wu, Ellis Ye Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cuscuton Bounce Beyond the Linear Regime: Bispectrum and Strong Coupling Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01992v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cuscuton Gravity is characterized as a scalar field that can be added to general relativity without introducing any new dynamical degrees of freedom on a cosmological background. Yet, it modifies gravity such that spacetime singularities can be avoided. This has led to the Cuscuton bounce, a nonsingular cosmology that has been shown to be linearly stable, which is a rare feat. Upon introducing mechanisms known to generate a near-scale-invariant power spectrum of isocurvature perturbations in the prebounce contracting phase, we perform an extensive linear analysis of all scalar perturbations as they evolve through the Cuscuton bounce, both analytically and numerically. Then, after deriving the third-order perturbed action for our theory, we compare the magnitude of its terms (on shell) to those in the second-order action. We show that perturbativity is maintained in the infrared throughout the evolution, including through the bounce. In the ultraviolet, we show that a hierarchy of scales is maintained, with the strong coupling scale well above the relevant background energy scale at all times. We reconfirm these results by computing the three-point functions in various limits and demonstrate that the models do not have any strong coupling problems and furthermore that there is negligible non-Gaussianities on observable scales. Consequently, the primary potential source of observable non-Gaussianities may only arise from the conversion of isocurvature perturbations to curvature perturbations. The whole scenario is thus a robust, stable, weakly coupled nonsingular cosmological model, consistent with observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01992v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amir Dehghani, Ghazal Geshnizjani, Jerome Quintin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large charge meets semiclassics in $\mathcal{N}=4$ super Yang-Mills</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02028v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the large-charge sector of $\mathcal{N}=4$ super Yang-Mills theory (SYM) with $SU(N)$ gauge group by constructing a special class of half-BPS heavy operators, termed "canonical operators". Such operators exhibit remarkable simplicity in the large-charge 't Hooft limit, where the dimension of the operators $\Delta \to \infty$ with $\Delta\, g_{\text{YM}}^2$ held finite. Canonical operator insertions in this regime map $\mathcal{N}=4$ SYM onto the Coulomb branch, by assigning a classical profile to the scalar fields with non-vanishing values along the diagonals given by the roots of unity. We follow a semiclassical approach to study two-point, three-point and Heavy-Heavy-Light-Light (HHLL) correlators. In particular we show that HHLL correlators in the large-charge 't Hooft limit are computed as two-point functions in a background determined by the classical profiles. We provide consistent evidence of our findings by computing the same observables via supersymmetric localization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02028v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Augustus Brown, Francesco Galvagno, Alba Grassi, Cristoforo Iossa, Congkao Wen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Following the state of an evaporating charged black hole into the quantum gravity regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02051</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02051v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the energy probability density function of an evaporating near-extremal charged black hole. At sufficiently low energies, such black holes experience large quantum metric fluctuations in the $AdS_{2}$ throat which are governed by a Schwarzian action. These fluctuations modify Hawking evaporation rates, and therefore also affect how the black hole state evolves over time. In previous work on Schwarzian-corrected Hawking radiation, the black hole was taken to be in the microcanonical or canonical ensemble [arXiv:2411.03447]. However, we find that an initially fixed-energy or fixed-temperature state does not remain so in the regime where Schwarzian corrections are important. We consider three decay channels: the emission of massless scalars, photons, and entangled pairs of photons in angular momentum singlet states. In each of the three cases, we find that in the very low energy, quantum dominated regime, the probability distribution of the black hole energy level occupation tends toward a particular attractor function that effectively depends on only one combination of time and energy. This function is independent of the initial state and gives new predictions for the energy fluxes and Hawking emission spectra of near-extremal charged black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02051v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna Biggs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>All-order solution of ladders and rainbows in Minimal Subtraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02079v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In dimensional regularization with $D=D_0-2\epsilon$, the minimal subtraction (MS) scheme is characterized by counterterms that only consist of singular terms in $\epsilon$. We develop a general method to compute the infinite sums of massless ladder or rainbow Feynman integrals in MS at $D_0$. Our method is based on relating the MS-solution to a kinematic solution at a coupling-dependent renormalization point. If the $\epsilon$-dependent Mellin transform of the kernel diagram of the insertions can be computed in closed form, we typically obtain a closed expression for the all-order solution in MS. As examples, we consider Yukawa theory and $\phi^4$ theory in $D_0=4$, and $\phi^3$ theory in $D_0=6$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02079v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul-Hermann Balduf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deriving motivic coactions and single-valued maps at genus zero from zeta generators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02096v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multiple polylogarithms are equipped with rich algebraic structures including the motivic coaction and the single-valued map which both found fruitful applications in high-energy physics. In recent work arXiv:2312.00697, the current authors presented a conjectural reformulation of the motivic coaction and the single-valued map via zeta generators, certain operations on non-commuting variables in suitable generating series of multiple polylogarithms. In this work, the conjectures of the reference will be proven for multiple polylogarithms that depend on any number of variables on the Riemann sphere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02096v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hadleigh Frost, Martijn Hidding, Deepak Kamlesh, Carlos Rodriguez, Oliver Schlotterer, Bram Verbeek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-split superstrings of dimension $(1|2)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02416</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02416v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Any supermanifold diffeomorphic to one whose structure sheaf is the sheaf of sections of a~vector bundle over the underlying manifold is called split. Gaw\c{e}dzki (1977) and Batchelor (1979) were the first to prove that any smooth supermanifold is split. In 1981, P.~Green, and Palamodov, found examples of non-split analytic supermanifolds and described obstructions to splitness that were further studied by Manin (resp. Onishchik with his students) following Palamodov's (resp. Green's) approach. Following Palamodov, Donagi and Witten demonstrated that some of the moduli supervarieties of superstring theories are non-split. None of the above-mentioned authors considered odd parameters of supervarieties of obstructions to non-splitness. Here, using Palamodov's approach, we classify and describe the even (degree-2) and the odd (degree-1) obstructions to splitness of $(1|2)$-dimensional superstrings. In particular, we correct calculations of degree-2 obstructions due to Bunegina and Onishchik and confirm Manin's answer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02416v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dimitry Leites, Alexander S. Tikhomirov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards $\mathcal{N}=2$ higher-spin supergravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02438v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We review the superfield formulation of $\mathcal{N}=2$ higher-spin supergravity theory in harmonic superspace. The analysis of both the hypermultiplet higher-spin supersymmetries and conformal supersymmetries is performed. The analytic superspace gauging of these symmetries gives rise to a set of unconstrained analytical prepotentials describing $\mathcal{N}=2$ higher-spin off-shell supermultiplets. This procedure naturally yields cubic interaction vertices of $\mathcal{N}=2$ higher spins with the hypermultiplet. Based on these results, the consistent interaction of an infinite tower of $\mathcal{N}=2$ superconformal higher spins with hypermultiplet is presented. Proceeding from this model, a method to construct a consistent interacting theory of $\mathcal{N}=2$ higher-spin supergravity by making use of the conformal compensators is proposed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02438v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ioseph Buchbinder, Evgeny Ivanov, Nikita Zaigraev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum work extraction of a moving battery as a witness to Unruh thermality in high-dimensional spacetimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02472v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We put forward a physical model of a uniformly accelerated Unruh-DeWitt battery and use quantum work extraction as a probe to witness the thermal nature of the Unruh effect in a high dimensional Minkowski spacetime. By means of the open quantum system approach, we investigate the maximal amount of quantum work extraction with respect to the acceleration-induced Unruh temperature, spacetime dimensionality and field mass. It has been found that the steady amount of quantum work extraction in the asymptotic condition is just determined by the Unruh temperature in arbitrary dimensional spacetimes. The asymptotic behavior can demonstrate the global feature of Unruh thermality dependent on the Kubo-Martin-Schwinger condition. From a local viewpoint of Unruh effect, we study the different ways for the dynamics of quantum work extraction when the battery gradually arrives at the same steady state. In the massless scalar field, the evolution with a small acceleration takes on a unique monotonicity in $D=3$ dimensional spacetime and changes to a decaying oscillation for other higher dimensions. The increase in spacetime dimensionality can increase the energy storage capacity of the moving battery. If the mass of the scalar field is considered, the related quantum work extraction is so robust against the Unruh decoherence that the high values can keep for a very long time. The persistence of quantum work extraction is strengthened in higher dimensional spacetime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02472v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan Chen, Wei-Wei Zhang, Tian-Xi Ren, Xiang Hao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonadiabatic quantum kinetic equations and Dirac-Heisenberg-Wigner formalism for Schwinger pair production in time-varying electric fields with multiple components</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02530</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02530v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The nonadiabatic quantum kinetic equations and Dirac-Heisenberg-Wigner formalism for Schwinger pair production in a spatially uniform and time-varying electric field with multiple components are derived and proven to be equivalent. The relation between nonadiabatic and adiabatic quantum kinetic equations is also established. By analyzing the time evolution of the distribution functions of particles created in a circularly polarized Gaussian pulse field with a subcycle structure, it is found that the nonadiabatic and adiabatic distribution functions are the same after the field, with a sufficient number of oscillation cycles, fades away. However, during the presence of the field, the two distribution functions typically differ. Nonetheless, the time evolution characteristics of the nonadiabatic and adiabatic momentum distributions are similar. For instance, the number of spirals is one less than the number of photons absorbed in both cases. Furthermore, for a rapidly oscillating electric field, the nonadiabatic quantum kinetic approaches may provide a more meaningful description of pair production at intermediate times. These findings deepen our understanding of the nonadiabatic quantum kinetic approaches and their application in pair production.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02530v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Z. L. Li, R. Z. Jiang, Y. J. Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Row and column detection complexities of character tables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02543v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Character tables of finite groups and closely related commutative algebras have been investigated recently using new perspectives arising from the AdS/CFT correspondence and low-dimensional topological quantum field theories. Two important elements in these new perspectives are physically motivated definitions of quantum complexity for the algebras and a notion of row-column duality. These elements are encoded in properties of the character table of a group G and the associated algebras, notably the centre of the group algebra and the fusion algebra of irreducible representations of the group. Motivated by these developments, we define row and column versions of detection complexities for character tables, and investigate the relation between these complexities under the exchange of rows and columns. We observe regularities that arise in the statistical averages over small character tables and propose corresponding conjectures for arbitrarily large character tables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02543v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrian Padellaro, Sanjaye Ramgoolam, Rak-Kyeong Seong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating (Non)-Integrability and Pulsating String in D3-Brane Background</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02548v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work explores the (non)-integrability and chaotic dynamics of classical strings in the background of a D3-brane with a non-commutative parameter, within the framework of the AdS/CFT correspondence. Using the Polyakov action, we derive the equations of motion and constraints for pulsating strings and analyze their stability through perturbation theory. In the large energy limit, the first-order perturbed equation simplifies to the P\"oschl-Teller equation, solvable via associated Legendre or hypergeometric functions, while numerical methods are employed for generic energy values. We demonstrate that the non-commutative parameter enhances chaotic behavior, as evidenced by the Largest Lyapunov Exponent (LLE). Furthermore, we investigate the integrability of geodesic motion and identify two distinct string modes: capture and escape to infinity. Finally, we study pulsating strings in the deformed $(AdS_{3} \times S^{2})_{\varkappa}$ background, deriving dispersion relations for both short and long strings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02548v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rashmi R. Nayak, Kamal L. Panigrahi, Manoranjan Samal, Balbeer Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Horndeski Genesis be Nonpathological?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02626v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a minimal setup within the framework of Horndeski gravity that can describe a nonpathological Genesis scenario. Our setup allows for a fully stable transition to the kination epoch, during which General Relativity (GR) is restored. This Genesis scenario circumvents the no-go theorem at the cost of encountering the risk of strong coupling in the past. Interestingly, our scenario admits two different regimes for the background solution for Hubble parameter at the Genesis stage: power-law behavior and manifestly non-power-law behavior. We explicitly show that, in both regimes, our model remains within unitarity bounds. In most cases, the tensor spectrum is blue-tilted. Then, we adopt a mechanism with a spectator field that allows for a red-tilted scalar power spectrum. We also suggest a deformation of the model that enables us to achieve sufficiently small values for the r ratio. Finally, we discuss the geodesic (in)completeness of the current model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02626v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Han Gil Choi, Pavel Petrov, Masahide Yamaguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vacua, Symmetries, and Higgsing of Chern-Simons Matter Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02744</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02744v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Three-dimensional supersymmetric Chern-Simons Matter (CSM) theories typically preserve $ \mathcal{N}=3$ supersymmetry but can exhibit enhanced $\mathcal{N}=4$ supersymmetry under special conditions. A detailed understanding of the moduli space of CSM theories, however, has remained elusive. This paper addresses this gap by systematically analysing the maximal branches of the moduli space of $\mathcal{N}=3$ and $\mathcal{N}=4$ CSM realised via Type IIB brane constructions. Firstly, for $\mathcal{N}=4$ theories with Chern-Simons levels equal $1$, the $\mathrm{SL}(2,\mathbb{Z})$ dualisation algorithm is employed to construct dual Lagrangian 3d $\mathcal{N}=4$ theories without CS terms. This allows the full moduli space to be determined using quiver algorithms that compute Higgs and Coulomb branch Hasse diagrams and associated RG flows. Secondly, for $\mathcal{N}=4$ theories with CS-levels greater $1$, where $\mathrm{SL}(2,\mathbb{Z})$ dualisation does not yield CS-free Lagrangians, a new prescription is introduced to derive two magnetic quivers, $\mathsf{MQ}_A $ and $\mathsf{MQ}_B$, whose Coulomb branches capture the maximal A and B branches of the original $\mathcal{N}=4$ CSM theory. Applying the decay and fission algorithm to $ \mathsf{MQ}_{A/B}$ then enables the systematic analysis of A/B branch RG flows and their geometric structures. Thirdly, for $\mathcal{N}=3$ CSM theories, one magnetic quiver for each maximal (hyper-K\"ahler) branch is derived from the brane system. This provides an efficient and comprehensive characterisation of these previously scarcely studied features.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02744v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabio Marino, Marcus Sperling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bosonizations and dualities in 2+1 dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02801v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss two methods for relating bosonic and fermionic relativistic field theories in 2+1 dimensions, the $Z_2^f$ gauging and the flux attachment. The first is primarily a correspondence between topological theories. It amounts to summing over fermionic spin structures, as is familiar in two-dimensional conformal theories. Its inverse map, fermionization, shows how spin structures and $Z_2^f$ fermion parity emerge from a bosonic theory equipped with a dual $Z_2^{(1)}$ generalized symmetry. The second method,flux attachment, gives spin and statistics to charged particles by coupling them to a Chern-Simons theory, and provides the basis for the Abelian dualities. We illustrate the two bosonizations with explicit results in a solvable semiclassical conformal theory, and show their differences and interplays with particle-vortex dualities. We employ the so-called loop model, which can describe general infrared critical points in 2+1 dimensions in the semiclassical limit. We also combine the two bosonizations to obtain further duality relations. By applying $Z_2^f$ gauging to the Dirac-boson and Majorana-boson flux-attachment dualities, we find new relations between bosonic theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02801v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Cappelli, Riccardo Villa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Four-point correlators with BPS bound states in AdS$_3$ and AdS$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02855</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02855v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider heavy-heavy-light-light (HHLL) correlators in AdS/CFT, focussing on the D1D5 CFT$_2$ and the ${\cal N}= 4$ super Yang-Mills theory. Out of the lightest $1/2$-BPS operator in the spectrum, $O$, we construct a particular heavy operator $O_H$ given by a coherent superposition of multi-particle operators $O^n$, and study the HHLL correlator. When $n$ is of order of the central charge, we show that the bulk equation that computes our boundary HHLL correlators is always a Heun equation. By assuming that the form of the correlator can be continued to the regime where $n$ is ${\mathcal O}(1)$, we first reproduce the known single-particle four-point correlators for $n=1$ and then predict new results for the multi-particle correlators $\langle O^n O^n O O\rangle$. Explicit expressions can be written entirely in terms of $n$-loop ladder integrals and their derivatives, and we provide them for $n=2$ and $n=3$ both in position and in Mellin space. Focussing on the AdS$_5$ case, we study the OPE expansion of these multi-particle correlators and show that several consistency relations with known CFT data are non-trivially satisfied. Finally, we extract new CFT data for double and triple-particle long operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02855v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Aprile, Stefano Giusto, Rodolfo Russo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conservative Dynamics of Relativistic Binaries Beyond Einstein Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02867v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the conservative dynamics of spinless compact objects in a general effective theory of gravity which includes a metric and an arbitrary number of scalar fields, through $\mathcal{O}(G^{3})$. Departures from Einstein gravity, which preserve general coordinate and local Lorentz invariance, are characterized by higher-derivative terms in a Lagrangian whose coupling constants scale as powers of a ``new-physics'' length scale, $\ell$. For a purely metric theory we compute the contributions from the the leading and subleading higher-curvature curvature corrections. In four dimensions these are cubic and quartic curvature terms, i.e. orders $\ell^4$ and $\ell^6$. We also study a general multi-scalar-tensor theory of gravity to order $\ell^{4}$, which includes both Einstein-dilaton-Gauss-Bonnet (EdGB) and dynamical Chern-Simons (dCS) higher-order couplings. Specifically, we compute the radial action in a post-Minkowskian approximation for scattering orbits, to two-loop order. The result encodes the fully relativistic dynamics of the compact objects, and serves as a generating function for gauge-invariant orbital observables for both bound and unbound binary systems. Where overlapping post-Newtonian results are available, we've verified agreement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02867v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jordan Wilson-Gerow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropy created when colliding particles fall into a black hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01934</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01934v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: If two particles collide in the vicinity of a black hole horizon, their center of mass energy is practically unlimited, so another black hole with a large mass and thus entropy can be created. The resulting black hole can then merge with the original one. If the black hole is created very close to the horizon, its energy will be highly redshifted for an asymptotic observer. However, its entropy is not redshifted. We demonstrated that the newly created entropy can be higher than the Bekenstein-Hawking entropy of the final black hole, though we neglect that a certain amount of energy can escape to infinity, carrying away part of the entropy produced in the process. This is a counter-example to the statement that the black hole thermal entropy counts all the states inside the black hole. Unlike similar examples, this colliding process does not involve exotic matter, alternative theories of gravity, nor artificial ad hoc gluing of two different spacetimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01934v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.044072</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review D, 111, 2025, 044072</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>De-Chang Dai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse bubbles from broken supersymmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01951v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Building upon the recent findings regarding inverse phase transitions in the early universe, we present the first natural realisation of this phenomenon within a supersymmetry-breaking sector. We demonstrate that inverse hydrodynamics, which is characterized by the fluid being aspired by the bubble wall rather than being pushed or dragged, is actually not limited to a phase of (re)heating but can also occur within the standard cooling cosmology. Through a numerical analysis of the phase transition, we establish a simple and generic criterion to determine its hydrodynamics based on the generalised pseudo-trace. Our results provide a proof of principle highlighting the need to account for these new fluid solutions when considering cosmological phase transitions and their phenomenological implications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01951v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giulio Barni, Simone Blasi, Miguel Vanvlasselaer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational wave cosmology in Einstein-scalar-Gauss-Bonnet gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01975v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the framework of Einstein-scalar-Gauss-Bonnet (EsGB) gravity, we systematically study gravitational waves (GWs), first produced by remote compact astrophysical sources and then propagating through the flat homogeneous and isotropic Universe at cosmic distances before arriving at detectors. Assuming that the speed $c_T$ of the spin-2 graviton is the same as that of photons, we find explicitly the stability conditions of the theory and then obtain the severest observational constraint found so far. In particular, all these conditions and constraints are satisfied, provided that $0 \leq \alpha\dot{f}(\phi_0) \lesssim 8.97 \times 10^{-24}$ (km), where $\alpha{f}(\phi)$ denotes the coupling strength between the scalar field $\phi$ and the Gauss-Bonnet term, an over-dot represents the derivative with respect to the cosmic time, and $\phi_0$ is the present value of $\phi$. The trajectories for both spin-2 and spin-0 gravitons and the amplitudes of GWs along the trajectories are explicitly obtained. The amplitude of a spin-2 GW is practically indistinguishable from that of GR, while the spin-0 GWs remain almost constant during radiation- and matter-dominated epochs, and in the dark energy-dominated epoch it is proportional to the physical distance between the source and the observer. A careful analysis shows that the latter is due to the assumption $c_T = 1$. When $c_T \not= 1$ to the extent that is consistent with the stability conditions and observational constraints, the above behavior disappears.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01975v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jared Fier, Henry Han, Bowen Li, Kai Lin, Shinji Mukohyama, Anzhong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schwinger Current in de Sitter Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01981v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study classical background electric fields and the Schwinger effect in de Sitter space. We show that having a constant electric field in de Sitter requires the photon to have a tachyonic mass proportional to the Hubble scale. This has physical implications for the induced Schwinger current which affect its IR behaviour. To study this we recompute the Schwinger current in de Sitter space for charged fermions and minimally coupled scalars imposing a physically consistent renormalization condition. We find a finite and positive Schwinger current even in the massless limit. This is in contrast to previous calculations in the literature which found a negative IR divergence. We also obtain the first result of the Schwinger current for a non-minimally coupled scalar, including for a conformally coupled scalar which we find has very similar behaviour to the fermion current. Our results may have physical implications for both magnetogenesis and inflationary dark matter production.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01981v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mar Bastero-Gil, Paulo B. Ferraz, Ant\'onio Torres Manso, Lorenzo Ubaldi, Roberto Vega-Morales</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time operator from parametrization invariance and implications for cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02055</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02055v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Motivated by the parametrization invariance of cosmological Lagrangians and their equivalence to systems describing the motion of particles in curved backgrounds, we identify the phase space analogue of the notion of proper time. We define the corresponding quantum operator, which results in being canonically conjugate to that of the vanishing Hamiltonian. In the context of particle dynamics, this leads to an uncertainty relation of the form $\Delta E_0 \,\Delta T \geq \hbar$, where $E_0$ is the rest energy of the particle. By studying the non-relativistic limit, we show that the action of the operator reduces to multiplication by the classical time coordinate. Finally, we derive the generic expression for the introduced time variable in the cosmological setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02055v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. Dimakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study of Null Geodesics and their Stability in Horndeski Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02083</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02083v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the motion of particles in the background of a scalar-tensor theory of gravity in which the scalar field is kinetically coupled to the Einstein tensor and we present the null geodesic structure for asymptotically flat, AdS, and dS Horndeski black holes, studying the effect of the cosmological constant on the orbits. Also, we consider three classical test of the gravity in the solar system, such as, the bending of the light, the gravitational redshift, and the Shapiro time delay in order to constraint the coupling parameters of the scalar field to gravity. Calculating the Lyapunov exponent we explore the stability of these geodesics for various values of the cosmological constant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02083v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. A. Carvajal, P. A. Gonz\'alez, Marco Olivares, Eleftherios Papantonopoulos, Yerko V\'asquez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shadows aspect of rotating black holes in the Einstein-AdS SU(N)-nonlinear sigma model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02179</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02179v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent observations of the supermassive black holes M87* and Sgr A* by the Event Horizon Telescope (EHT) have opened new avenues for testing gravity theories through black hole shadow observables. These observations offer a means to distinguish between general relativity and modified gravity theories while providing insights into the astrophysical properties of the observed black holes. In this work, we investigate photon orbits and shadow characteristics of rotating black holes within the Einstein-$\mathrm{SU(N)}$ nonlinear sigma model. We first analyze the static, spherically symmetric black hole solution, focusing on its asymptotically Anti-de Sitter behavior and causal structure. The Modified Newman-Janis Algorithm is then applied to obtain the rotating counterpart, followed by an examination of its geometric properties, ergoregions, and causal structure. Utilizing the Lagrangian formalism, we derive the equations of motion for photons and study the resulting black hole shadow on the celestial plane. We explore the dependence of the shadow's size and shape on the black hole parameters $K$ and $N$, imposing constraints using EHT observational data for M87* and Sgr A*. Finally, we analyze the black hole's evaporation rate under different scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02179v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohsen Fathi, Y. Sekhmani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deflection angle in the strong deflection limit: a perspective from local geometrical invariants and matter distributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02320v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the logarithmic divergence of the deflection angle in the strong deflection limit in static, spherically symmetric spacetimes. We propose a novel analytical framework that connects its physical origin to local, coordinate-invariant geometric quantities and properties of the matter distributions. Conventional approaches describe the divergence rate, characterized by the coefficient $\bar{a}$, in terms of coordinate-dependent metric functions. In contrast, our method relates $\bar{a}$ to the components of the Einstein tensor in an orthonormal tetrad adapted to the spacetime symmetry. By employing the Einstein equations, we express $\bar{a}$ in terms of the local values of energy density $\rho_{\mathrm{m}}$ and tangential pressure $\Pi_{\mathrm{m}}$ at the photon sphere with an areal radius $R_{\mathrm{m}}$: \begin{align*} \bar{a}=\frac{1}{\sqrt{1-8\pi R_{\mathrm{m}}^2\left(\rho_{\mathrm{m}}+\Pi_{\mathrm{m}}\right)}}. \end{align*} This formula clearly shows that, through the combination $\rho_{\mathrm{m}}+\Pi_{\mathrm{m}}$, the strong field limit coefficient $\bar{a}$ depends on the local matter distribution. In particular, if the matter fields satisfy $\rho+\Pi=0$, the universal result $\bar{a}=1$ emerges. This finding not only accounts for the behavior observed in the Schwarzschild spacetime but also provides a unified description applicable to a variety of spacetimes, including certain naked singularities and wormholes supported by a massless scalar field. Furthermore, these local properties are reflected in the frequencies of quasinormal modes, suggesting a profound connection between strong gravitational lensing and the dynamical response of gravitational wave signals. Our framework, independent of any specific gravitational theory, serves as a universal tool for testing gravitational theories and interpreting astrophysical observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02320v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takahisa Igata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charges in light cones and quenched infrared radiation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02342v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The creation of electrically charged states and the resulting electromagnetic fields are considered in space-time regions in which such experiments can actually be carried out, namely in future-directed light cones. Under the simplifying assumption of external charges, charged states are formed from neutral pairs of opposite charges, with one charge being shifted to light-like infinity. It thereby escapes observation. Despite the fact that this charge moves asymptotically at the speed of light, the resulting electromagnetic field has a well-defined energy operator that is bounded from below. Moreover, due to the spatiotemporal restrictions, the transverse electromagnetic field (the radiation) has no infrared singularities in the light cone. They are quenched and the observed radiation can be described by states in the Fock space of photons. The longitudinal field between the charges (giving rise to Gauss's law) disappears for inertial observers in an instant. This is consistent with the fact that there is no evidence for the existence of longitudinal photons. The results show that the restrictions of operations and observations to light cones, which are dictated by the arrow of time, amount to a Lorentz-invariant infrared cutoff.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02342v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Detlev Buchholz, Fabio Ciolli, Giuseppe Ruzzi, Ezio Vasselli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alternative Framework to Quantize Fermionic Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02362v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In quantum field theory, the quantization of classical fields is traditionally achieved through canonical quantization or the Feynman path integral formalism. In this work, we introduce an alternative approach based on the extended stationary action principle. This framework has been successfully applied to recover non-relativistic quantum mechanics and quantize scalar fields. Here, we extend it to fermionic fields by addressing the complexities associated with Grassmann-valued field variables. By recursively applying the extended stationary action principle, we derive a generalized Floreanini-Jackiw representation of the Schr\"{o}dinger equation for the wave functional of fermionic fields. The resulting Hamiltonian satisfies the symmetry constraints of special relativity by generating the Poincar\'{e} algebra. To highlight the distinctiveness of this quantization method, we apply it to the weak interaction theory of fermionic fields, which is non-renormalizable under standard canonical quantization. Our approach leads to a non-linear Schr\"{o}dinger equation for the wave functional, offering new insights into the quantization of non-renormalizable theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02362v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianhao M. Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmic Acceleration from Nothing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02380v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate that if the universe started as a vacuum fluctuation rather than from a singular Big Bang state, the universe must have a late-time cosmic acceleration. This is required by a ``cosmological sum rule'' derived using the Schwarzian form of the Friedmann equations. We discuss possible connections to conformal and M\"obius transformations, and also compute that the best fit present cosmic data is consistent with the necessary crossing of the Schwarzian through zero having occurred (while it would not yet have happened in a $\Lambda$CDM cosmology).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02380v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael R. R. Good, Eric V. Linder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Timelike Compton scattering on a spin-0 target with kinematic twist-4 precision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02461v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We calculate the kinematic twist-3 and 4 corrections to the leading order amplitude of timelike Compton scattering (TCS) on a (pseudo-)scalar target, in the recently developed framework based on the conformal operator-product expansion. This allows us to compute the complete set of helicity amplitudes of the process, in particular those that vanish at leading twist. We compare the effects of higher twist contributions to TCS with those in deeply virtual Compton scattering (DVCS). Our estimates, based on a $\pi$-meson GPD model, indicate that these contributions are sizeable and will play a crucial role in the interpretation of data from current and forthcoming experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02461v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Martinez-Fernandez, B. Pire, P. Sznajder, J. Wagner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Late Time Cosmic Acceleration in Modified Gravity and Gauss-Bonnet Cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02467v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This thesis focuses on late-time cosmic acceleration within modified theories of gravity, using various observational data sets and statistical analysis. The Universe is assumed to be spatially homogeneous and isotropic and is described by the Friedmann Lema\^{i}tre Robertson Walker metric. The late-time acceleration of the Universe has posed a significant challenge to contemporary cosmology. General relativity addresses this by introducing the cosmological constant, forming the basis of the standard cosmological model ($\Lambda$CDM). However, this model has limitations, leading cosmologists to explore alternative explanations for late-time acceleration. These alternatives range from models involving a dynamic dark fluid known as dark energy, to large-scale modifications of gravitational interaction, known as modified gravity. The formulation of general relativity fundamentally changed our understanding of gravitation, redefining gravity as a manifestation of the curvature of spacetime rather than a force as described by Newton. Despite its success, general relativity has shown incompatibilities with observations, necessitating the introduction of dark matter and dark energy....</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02467v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Santosh V. Lohakare</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New $\sim 5\sigma$ Tension at Characteristic Redshift from DESI DR1 and DES-SN5YR observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02880</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02880v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We perform a model-independent reconstruction of the angular diameter distance ($D_{A}$) using the Multi-Task Gaussian Process (MTGP) framework with DESI-DR1 BAO and DES-SN5YR datasets. We calibrate the comoving sound horizon at the baryon drag epoch $r_d$ to the Planck best-fit value, ensuring consistency with early-universe physics. With the reconstructed $D_A$ at two key redshifts, $z\sim 1.63$ (where $D_{A}^{\prime} =0$) and at $z\sim 0.512$ (where $D_{A}^{\prime} = D_{A}$), we derive the expansion rate of the Universe $H(z)$ at these redshifts. Our findings reveal that at $z\sim 1.63$, the $H(z)$ is fully consistent with the Planck-2018 $\Lambda$CDM prediction, confirming no new physics at that redshift. However, at $z \sim 0.512$, the derived $H(z)$ shows a more than $5\sigma$ discrepancy with the Planck-2018 $\Lambda$CDM prediction, suggesting a possible breakdown of the $\Lambda$CDM model as constrained by Planck-2018 at this lower redshift. This emerging $\sim 5\sigma$ tension at $z\sim 0.512$, distinct from the existing ``Hubble Tension'', may signal the first strong evidence for new physics at low redshifts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02880v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Purba Mukherjee, Anjan A Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fixing the AdS$_3$ metric from the pure state entanglement entropies of CFT$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1710.08448</link>
      <description>arXiv:1710.08448v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, based on RT formula, by identifying the pure state UV and IR entanglement entropies of a perturbed CFT$_2$ with geodesic lengths in the bulk, we demonstrate that the dual geometry is uniquely determined to be asymptotically AdS$_3$. The pure AdS$_3$ geometry is recovered by taking the massless limit of the system. Our derivations hold in both static and covariant scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1710.08448v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1674-1137/ada960</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chin.Phys.C 49 (2025) 4, 045105</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Peng Wang, Houwen Wu, Haitang Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cooling and heating regions of Joule-Thomson expansion for AdS black holes: Einstein-Maxwell-Power-Yang-Mills and Kerr Sen black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.02257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.02257v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the Joule-Thomson Expansion (JTE) process for two types of black holes: AdS-Einstein-Maxwell-Power-Yang-Mills (AEMPYM) and AdS-Kerr-Sen (AKS). Our study focuses on understanding how various parameters influence the Joule-Thomson Coefficient (JTC), the inversion curve, and the ratio of minimum inversion temperature to critical temperature. For the AKS black hole, we observe that the isenthalpic curves can exhibit either cooling or heating behavior. This behavior is determined by the inversion curve, which is affected by the black hole's mass and specific parameters such as $b$ (parameter signifies the ionic charge of the black hole) and $a$ (rotation parameter). In the case of the AEMPYM black hole, our findings reveal that the ratio of minimum inversion temperature to critical temperature approaches a specific value as Maxwell's charge increases. This ratio remains constant for certain parameter values, while it varies for others. Specifically, when the parameter $q$ (real positive parameter of AEMPYM black hole) is greater than 1, the ratio is almost equal to 1/2 as Maxwell's charge (C) increases. When q equals 1/2, the ratio is exactly 1/2 for all values of (C). For values of (q) between 1/2 and 1, the ratio is close to 1/2, and for values of (q) between 0 and 1/2, the ratio decreases, moving away from 1/2. For the AKS black hole, we find that specific parameter values, such as (a = 0.00951) and (b = 0.00475 ), yield a ratio of minimum inversion temperature to a critical temperature that is approximately 1/2. This consistency across different parameter values highlights the robustness of our findings. Finally, we compare our results with those reported in the existing literature, providing a comprehensive summary in detailed tables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.02257v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Reza Alipour, Saeed Noori Gashti, Mohammad Ali S. Afshar, Jafar Sadeghi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Orientable AdS$_3$ and its Holography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12546v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Known solutions to three-dimensional gravity with negative cosmological constant so far consist of either AdS$_3$ or its orbifolds (or orientifolds). We geometrically derive a novel non-orientable AdS$_3$ spacetime that is an orientifold of a spinor double cover of AdS$_3$, unlike existing solutions. This spacetime's universal cover contains a lightlike instead of spacelike compact direction. We show that its gravity theory possesses a simpler excited state spectrum and exhibits a Chern-Simons/Wess-Zumino-Witt (CS/WZW) correspondence between only one independent CS term and boundary chiral WZW term. This leads us to suggest that CS theory is able to more fully describe non-orientable pure gravity theory compared to orientable gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12546v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shivesh Pathak, Lucas Kocia Kovalsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resummation of Multi-Stress Tensors in Higher Dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.07458v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the context of holographic conformal field theories (CFTs), a system of linear partial differential equations was recently proposed to be the higher-dimensional analog of the null-state equations in $d=2$ CFTs at large central charge. Solving these equations in a near-lightcone expansion yields solutions that match the minimal-twist multi-stress tensor contributions to a heavy-light four-point correlator (or a thermal two-point correlator) computed using holography, the conformal bootstrap, and other methods. This paper explores the exact solutions to these equations. We begin by observing that, in an expansion in terms of the ratio between the heavy operator's dimension and the central charge, the $d=2$ correlator involving the level-two degenerate scalars at each order can be represented as a Bessel function; the resummation yields the Virasoro vacuum block. We next observe a relation between the $d=2$ correlator and the $d=4$ near-lightcone correlator involving light scalars with the same conformal dimension. The resummed $d=4$ correlator takes a simple form in the complex frequency domain. Unlike the Virasoro vacuum block, the resummation in $d=4$ leads to essential singularities. Similar expressions are also obtained when the light scalar's dimension takes other finite values. These CFT results correspond to a holographic computation with a spherical black hole. In addition, using the differential equations, we demonstrate that the correlators can be reconstructed via certain modes. In $d=2$, these modes are related to the Virasoro algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.07458v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.046016</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 111, 046016 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kuo-Wei Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embedding formalism for AdS superspaces in five dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10875v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The standard geometric description of $d$-dimensional anti-de Sitter (AdS) space is a quadric in ${\mathbb R}^{d-1,2}$ defined by $(X^0)^2 - (X^1)^2 - \dots - (X^{d-1})^2 + (X^d)^2 = \ell^2 = \text{const}$. In this paper we provide a supersymmetric generalisation of this embedding construction in the $d=5$ case. Specifically, a bi-supertwistor realisation is given for the ${\cal N}$-extended AdS superspace $\text{AdS}^{5|8\cal N}$, with ${\cal N}\geq 1$. The proposed formalism offers a simple construction of AdS super-invariants. As an example, we present a new model for a massive superparticle in $\text{AdS}^{5|8\cal N}$ which is manifestly invariant under the AdS isometry supergroup $\mathsf{SU}(2,2|{\cal N})$ and involves two independent two-derivative terms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10875v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nowar E. Koning, Sergei M. Kuzenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Every Poincar\'e gauge theory is conformal: a compelling case for dynamical vector torsion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12826v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Poincar\'e gauge theory (PGT) of gravity provides a viable formulation of general relativity (Einstein-Cartan theory), and a popular model-building framework for modified gravity with torsion. Notoriously, however, the PGT terms which propagate vector torsion lead to strongly-coupled ghosts: the modern view is that only scalar torsion can propagate. To fix this, we revisit the concept of embedding explicit mass scales in scale-invariant theories, showing how the Klein-Gordon theory naturally leads to a slowly-rolling inflaton. We then show that the unique scale-invariant embedding of PGT leads to two new terms, one of which is the Maxwell term for vector torsion. We provide the full spectrum of quantum particles in the resulting theory. Our result means that every PGT is conformal and - after a two-decade hiatus - vector torsion is back on the menu.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12826v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Will Barker, Michael Hobson, Anthony Lasenby, Yun-Cherng Lin, Zhiyuan Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Remarks on 2D quantum cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.15271v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider two-dimensional quantum gravity endowed with a positive cosmological constant and coupled to a conformal field theory of large and positive central charge. We study cosmological properties at the classical and quantum level. We provide a complete ADM analysis of the classical phase space, revealing a family of either bouncing or big bang/crunch type cosmologies. At the quantum level, we solve the Wheeler-DeWitt equation exactly. In the semiclassical limit, we link the Wheeler-DeWitt state space to the classical phase space. Wavefunctionals of the Hartle-Hawking and Vilenkin type are identified, and we uncover a quantum version of the bouncing spacetime. We retrieve the Hartle-Hawking wavefunction from the disk path integral of timelike Liouville theory. To do so, we must select a particular contour in the space of complexified fields. The quantum information content of the big bang cosmology is discussed, and contrasted with the de Sitter horizon entropy as computed by a gravitational path integral over the two-sphere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.15271v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dionysios Anninos, Chiara Baracco, Beatrix M\"uhlmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The enigmatic gravitational partition function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00267v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The saddle point approximation to formal quantum gravitational partition functions has yielded plausible computations of horizon entropy in various settings, but it stands on shaky ground. In this paper we visit some of that shaky ground, address some foundational questions, and describe efforts toward a more solid footing. We focus on the case of de Sitter horizon entropy which, it has been argued, corresponds to the dimension of the Hilbert space of a ball of space surrounded by the cosmological horizon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00267v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10714-024-03347-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Batoul Banihashemi, Ted Jacobson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On brane systems with O${}^+$ planes -- 5d and 6d SCFTs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02491v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study Higgs branches of field theories with 8 supercharges in 5 and 6 dimensions, focusing on theories realised on 5-brane webs in Type IIB with an O$7^+$ plane, or a D6-D8-NS5 brane system in Type IIA in the presence of an O$8^+$ plane. We find magnetic quivers for the Higgs branches of these theories. The main consequence of the presence of the orientifold is that it renders the magnetic quiver to be non-simply-laced. We propose a contribution of the O$7^+$ to the usual stable intersection number of 5-branes from tropical geometry, and show that it is consistent with Fayet-Iliopoulos deformations of magnetic quivers which represent mass deformations of 5d SQFTs. From the magnetic quivers, we compute phase diagrams and highest weight generating functions for the Higgs branches, enabling us to identify the global form of the flavour symmetry for several families of 5d SQFTs; among them Bhardwaj's rank-1 theory. For 6d theories realised on a $-4$ curve, we observe the appearance of an additional $D_4$ slice on top of the phase diagram as one goes to the tensionless limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02491v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Akhond, Guillermo Arias-Tamargo, Federico Carta, Julius F. Grimminger, Amihay Hanany</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractal Spacetime Effects on Charged AdS Black Hole Thermodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06271v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the emergent thermodynamic phenomena arising from spacetime foam and its impact on black hole behavior, as described by the Barrow model. In this framework, the structure of spacetime at small scales is modeled using fractal geometry, implying that black hole surfaces exhibit a fractal structure due to quantum deformations induced by quantum gravity effects. Our analysis, performed within the extended phase space formalism, reveals that the fractal correction to black hole entropy significantly modifies the equation of state, critical parameters, and phase transition behavior of charged AdS black holes. An increase in the fractal parameter leads to higher critical pressure and temperature, which diverge at maximal fractal deformation. Moreover, while the fractal structure has a negligible effect on small black holes with low entropy, it clearly influences the thermal evolution of medium and large event horizon black holes. Notably, for large black holes, the fractal nature of spacetime manifests as a resistance to evaporation, effectively slowing down their evaporation process. Additionally, the impact of fractal corrections is further reflected in the Joule-Thomson expansion, where it modifies the cooling and heating regions in the pressure-temperature plane. These findings provide new insights into the interplay between quantum gravitational effects and macroscopic black hole thermodynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06271v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yahya Ladghami, Aatifa Bargach, Amine Bouali, Touafik Ouali, Ghulam Mustafa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BPS Fivebrane Stars III: Effective Actions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16630v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: An effective action for NS5-branes coupled to supergravity is used to derive the full 10d form of horizon-free BPS solutions of fivebranes carrying momentum waves, including both transverse scalar and internal gauge excitations of the branes. When internal modes are highly excited, we find solutions that plausibly mediate the transition between the Coulomb phase of NS5-branes and the black hole phase. We also compute the two-point functions of fivebrane density fluctuations and of gravitons absorbed by the branes. Finally, we begin an exploration of near-BPS perturbations of the fivebrane ensemble, and propose the use of the brane+bulk effective action as a tool to explore the black hole phase, even in the AdS decoupling limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16630v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emil J. Martinec, Yoav Zigdon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Something Anomalies can tell about SM and Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07470</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07470v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This ia a review/research paper on anomalies applied to a bottom-up approach to standard model and gravity. It is divided in two parts. The first consists in a review proper of anomalies in quantum field theories. Anomalies are analyzed according to three different methods: a perturbative one based on Feynman diagram, a non-perturbative one relying on the Schwinger-DeWitt approach and, third, the one hinging on the Atiyah-Singer family's index theorem. The three methods are applied both to chiral gauge anomalies and trace anomalies. The fundamental distinction that our presentation leads to is between obstructive (O) and non-obstructive (NO) anomalies. The former are tied to the non-existence of fermion propagators, which fatally maim the corresponding theory. In the second part we apply this analysis to the SM and various of its extensions immersed in a gravitational background, and find that they all are plagued by a residual chiral trace anomaly. To completely eliminate all kind of dangerous anomalies in SM-like theories we propose a somewhat unconventional scheme, and exemplify it by means of an explicit model. The latter is a left-right symmetric model. We embed it in a Weyl geometry to render it conformal invariant. We then deal with some of its quantum aspects, in particular its even (NO) trace anomalies and the means to preserve its confomal invariance at the quantum level. We briefly review renormalization and unitarity in the framework of similar models discussed in the existing literature. Finally we present a possible (conjectural) application of the model to describe the junction between cosmology and quantum field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07470v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Loriano Bonora, Stefano G. Giaccari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stringy scaling of multi-tensor hard string scattering amplitudes and the K-identities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19640v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We calculate n-point hard string scattering amplitudes (HSSA) with n-2 tachyons and 2 tensor states at arbitrary mass levels. We discover the stringy scaling behavior of these HSSA. It is found that for HSSA with more than 2 transverse directions, the degree of stringy scaling dimM2 decreases comparing to the degree of stringy scaling dimM1 of the n-1 tachyons and 1 tensor HSSA calculated previously. Moreover, we propose a set of K-identities which is the key to demonstrate the stringy scaling behavior of HSSA. We explicitly prove both the diagonal and off-diagonal K-identities for the 4-point HSSA and give numerical proofs of these K-identities for some higher point HSSA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19640v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sheng-Hong Lai, Jen-Chi Lee, Yi Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Remarks on ghost resonances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04097v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we study various aspects of ghost resonances: the resummation that leads to the dressed propagator, the poles locations, the analytic continuation into the second Riemann sheet and the spectral representations in both first and second sheets. In particular, we show that for real masses above the multiparticle threshold the ghost propagator has a pair of complex conjugate poles in the first sheet, unlike the case of an ordinary unstable resonance which has no pole in the first sheet but a complex conjugate pair in the second sheet. Mathematical and physical implications of this feature are discussed. We also clarify an important point regarding the two absorptive contributions of a ghost propagator in the narrow-width approximation. Furthermore, we argue that finite-time quantum field theories are needed to consistently derive the dressed ghost propagator and capture the true physical properties of ghost resonances. Throughout the work, different prescriptions to define the ghost propagator on the real axis are considered: Feynman, anti-Feynman and fakeon prescriptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04097v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 02 (2025) 186</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Luca Buoninfante</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variant dilaton Weyl Multiplet for N=3 conformal supergravity in four dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13683v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct a new dilaton Weyl multiplet for $\mathcal{N}=3$ conformal supergravity in four dimensions. The R-symmetry realized on this dilaton Weyl multiplet is $SU(2) \times U(1) \times U(1)$. The construction follows a two-step procedure. Firstly, two on-shell vector multiplets are coupled to the standard Weyl multiplet. Secondly, using the field equations of the vector multiplets, some of the auxiliary fields of the standard Weyl multiplet are solved in terms of the fields belonging to the vector multiplets and some dual gauge fields. The remaining fields of the standard Weyl multiplet combine with the vector multiplet fields and the dual gauge fields to constitute the new dilaton Weyl multiplet.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13683v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soumya Adhikari, Aravind Aikot, Bindusar Sahoo, Madhu Mishra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causal Structure of Higher Curvature Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.16527v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we analyze the causal structure of Generalized Quadratic Gravity (GQG) and Einsteinian Cubic Gravity (ECG). It is well known that gravitons in higher-curvature theories can exhibit superluminal propagation, rendering the conventional definition of causal structures based on null curves inadequate. Instead, the causal structure must be defined using the fastest propagating modes, which travel along characteristic surfaces. The superluminal propagation in higher-curvature theories has significant implications for black holes. Specifically, if the Killing horizon of a black hole is not a characteristic surface corresponding to the fastest propagating mode, the horizon can no longer function as a causal barrier. Our analysis demonstrates that GQG with a genuine fourth-order equation of motion possesses only null characteristics, implying that the horizon is a characteristic surface. Furthermore, we perform a detailed characteristic analysis of ECG. We show that while all null surfaces are characteristic surfaces in ECG, the converse is not true - there exist non-null characteristic surfaces. In particular, we identify a non-null characteristic surface in a Type N spacetime in the algebraic classification of spacetimes. Despite the existence of multiple characteristic surfaces in ECG, we establish that the black hole horizon remains a characteristic surface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.16527v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohd Ali, Vardarajan Suneeta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The ordinary surface universality class of the three-dimensional O($N$) model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.16683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.16683v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the critical behavior at the ordinary surface universality class of the three-dimensional O($N$) model, bounded by a two-dimensional surface. Using high-precision Monte Carlo simulations of an improved lattice model, where the leading bulk scaling correction is suppressed, and finite-size scaling analysis of the fourth cumulant of the surface magnetization, we obtain precise estimates of the scaling dimension of the surface field operator for $N=2,3,4$. We also determine the fixed-point values of two renormalization-group invariant observables, which characterize the finite-size scaling behavior at the ordinary transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.16683v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.108.L020404</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 108, L020404 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Parisen Toldin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Field Theory in Curved Spacetime (2nd Edition)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.14517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.14517v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The 2023 second edition of a 2006 encyclopedia article on mathematical aspects of quantum field theory in curved spacetimes (QFTCST). Section-titles (with new sections indicated with stars) are: Introduction and preliminaries, Construction of a $*$-algebra for a real linear scalar field on globally hyperbolic spacetimes and some general theorems, *More about (quasifree) Hadamard states, Particle creation and the limitations of the particle concept, Theory of the stress-energy tensor, *More about the intersection of QFTCST with AQFT and the Fewster-Verch No-Go Theorem, Hawking and Unruh effects, *More about (classical and) quantum fields on black hole backgrounds, Non-globally hyperbolic spacetimes and the time-machine question, *More about QFT on non-globally hyperbolic spacetimes, Other related topics and some warnings. The article contains many references. It also includes a review of, and also compares and contrasts, recent results on the implications of QFTCST for the question of the instability of three sorts of Cauchy horizon -- first those inside black holes such as especially Reissner-Nordstr\"om-de Sitter and Kerr-de Sitter, second the compactly generated Cauchy horizons of spacetimes in which time-machines get manufactured, and third the Cauchy horizon of the spacetime which is believed to describe evaporating black holes and which underlies (one version of) the black hole information-loss puzzle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.14517v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/B978-0-323-95703-8.00085-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Elsevier Encyclopedia of Mathematical Physics (Second Edition) 5 357-381 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bernard S. Kay (York)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial Black Holes from Conformal Higgs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.13640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.13640v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Scale-invariant extensions of the electroweak theory are not only attractive because they can dynamically generate the weak scale, but also due to their role in facilitating supercooled first-order phase transitions. We study the minimal scale-invariant $U(1)_{\rm D}$ extension of the standard model and show that Primordial Black Holes (PBHs) can be abundantly produced. The mass of these PBHs is bounded from above by that of the moon due to QCD catalysis limiting the amount of supercooling. Lunar-mass PBHs, which are produced for dark Higgs vev $v_\phi\simeq 20~\rm TeV$, correspond to the best likelihood to explain the HSC lensing anomaly. For $v_\phi\gtrsim 400~\rm TeV$, the model can explain hundred per cent of dark matter. At even larger hierarchy of scales, it can contribute to the $511~\rm keV$ line. While the gravitational wave (GW) signal produced by the HSC anomaly interpretation is large and detectable by LISA above astrophysical foreground, the dark matter interpretation in terms of PBHs can not be entirely probed by future GW detection. This is due to the dilution of the signal by the entropy injected during the decay of the long-lived $U(1)_{\rm D}$ scalar. This extended lifetime is a natural consequence of the large hierarchy of scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.13640v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2024.138800</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Lett.B 855 (2024) 138800</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yann Gouttenoire</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GKZ hypergeometric systems of the four-loop vacuum Feynman integrals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13025v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Basing on Mellin-Barnes representations and Miller's transformation, we present the Gel'fand-Kapranov-Zelevinsky (GKZ) hypergeometric systems of 4-loop vacuum Feynman integrals with arbitrary masses. Through the GKZ hypergeometric systems, the analytical hypergeometric solutions of 4-loop vacuum Feynman integrals with arbitrary masses can be obtained in neighborhoods of origin including infinity. The analytical expressions of Feynman integrals can be formulated as a linear combination of the fundamental solution systems in certain convergent region, which the combination coefficients can be determined by the integral at some regular singularities, the Mellin-Barnes representation of the integral, or some mathematical methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13025v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP03(2025)013</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 03 (2025) 013</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hai-Bin Zhang, Tai-Fu Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast multilabel classification of HEP constraints with deep learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05453v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The shortcomings of the Standard Model (SM) motivate its extension to accommodate new expected phenomena, such as dark matter and neutrino masses. However, such extensions are generally more complex due to the presence of a large number of free parameters and additional phenomenology. Understanding how theoretical and experimental limits affect the parameter spaces of new models, individually and collectively, is of utmost importance for conducting model status analysis, motivating precise computations, or model-building aimed at solving certain issues. However, checking the constraints usually require a large amount of time using a chain of physics tools. We demonstrate, for the first time, the application of deep learning (DL) for the multilabel classification (MLC) of a group of theoretical and experimental constraints in the dark doublet phase of the next-to-two-Higgs-doublet model (DDP-N2HDM), as a representative 9-dimensional parameter space. We analyze the issue of class imbalance and the ability of the classifier to learn joint class distributions. We demonstrate the time advantage compared to physics tools, with the classifier achieving orders of magnitude faster checks on groups of constraints and strong performance. The classifier performed strongly in terms of identifying regions where all constraints are valid or invalid, as well as regions where one or more of the constraints are valid or invalid simultaneously. This approach can be applied to any extension beyond the SM with the potential to aid HEP tools or act as a surrogate for fast model status checks. To that end, we provide a python tool \texttt{HEPMLC} for generating and investigating multilabel classifiers for SM extensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05453v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maien Binjonaid</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Looking for traces of Hawking radiation in correlation functions of BEC acoustic black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02700v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Renaud Parentani was one of the leading figures in Quantum Field Theory in curved spacetime, in particular concerning its applications to Hawking-like radiation in analogue models. In this paper dedicated to him, we discuss the characteristic features appearing in the correlation functions in an acoustic black hole formed by a Bose-Einstein condensate, considered as signature of the presence of Hawking radiation in this system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02700v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.5802/crphys.241</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Published online: 4 March 2025. Comptes Rendus Physique</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Paul R. Anderson, Roberto Balbinot, Richard A. Dudley, Alessandro Fabbri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unearthing Neutrino Decoherence from Quantum Spacetime: An Open Quantum Systems Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.03808v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigated the influence of \(\kappa\) Minkowski-type quantum spacetime on neutrino oscillations, revealing that spacetime fluctuations introduce a unique energy-dependent power law, \(E^{-4}\), in the decoherence effect for relic neutrinos. This effect is particularly pronounced for low-energy neutrinos, such as those from the cosmic neutrino background ($C\nu B$). Our results indicate the potential for new models of low-energy quantum gravity-induced decoherence, which could pave the way for future experiments, such as IceCube-Gen2 and KM3NeT, to further constrain the deformation parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.03808v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Partha Nandi, Tiasha Bhattacharyya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$2+1$ dimensional Floquet systems and lattice fermions: Exact bulk spectral equivalence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18226v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A connection has recently been proposed between periodically driven systems known as Floquet insulators in continuous time and static fermion theories in discrete time. This connection has been established in a $(1+1)$-dimensional free theory, where an explicit mapping between the spectra of a Floquet insulator and a discrete-time Dirac fermion theory has been formulated. Here we investigate the potential of static discrete-time theories to capture Floquet physics in higher dimensions, where so-called anomalous Floquet topological insulators can emerge that feature chiral edge states despite having bulk bands with zero Chern number. Starting from a particular model of an anomalous Floquet system, we provide an example of a static discrete-time theory whose bulk spectrum is an exact analytic match for the Floquet spectrum. The spectra with open boundary conditions in a particular strip geometry also match up to finite-size corrections. However, the models differ in several important respects. The discrete-time theory is spatially anisotropic, so that the spectra do not agree for all lattice terminations, e.g. other strip geometries or on half spaces. This difference can be attributed to the fact that the static discrete-time model is quasi-one-dimensional in nature and therefore has a different bulk-boundary correspondence than the Floquet model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18226v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Iadecola, Srimoyee Sen, Lars Sivertsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New rotating Lorentzian wormhole spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09202v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A rotating version of a known static, spherically symmetric, zero Ricci scalar Lorentzian wormhole is constructed. It turns out that for this given non-rotating geometry, the standard Newman-Janis algorithm does not produce a rotating wormhole and, therefore, the method pioneered by Azreg-A\"inou has to be used. The rotating spacetime thus obtained is shown to be regular with wormhole features, though it is no longer a $R=0$ spacetime. The required matter is found to violate the energy conditions, as expected. A few other characteristic properties of this new rotating spacetime are mentioned. Finally, we calculate the shadow for this geometry and discuss its features {\em vis-a-vis} the Kerr geometry and available event horizon telescope observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09202v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.064010</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Anjan Kar, Soumya Jana, Sayan Kar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Traversable Wormholes with Spontaneous Symmetry Breaking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09236</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09236v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We argue that a spherically symmetric traversable wormhole solution of the Einstein field equations can be supported by minimally coupled self-interacting scalar field which allows a spontaneous symmetry breaking of the field around the wormhole throat. We study two cases : (i) the phantom wormhole solution of Bronnikov and (ii) a generalized Kiselev wormhole. We study the property of radial null geodesics and show that the metric can describe either a two-way or a one-way traversable wormhole depending on certain parameter ranges. The scalar field exhibits spontaneous symmetry breaking within the coordinate range where a wormhole throat forms and helps one suggest that spontaneous symmetry breaking may act as a threshold for wormhole throat formation. We also compute the radius of the photon sphere, the Lyapunov exponent, the shadow radius, and the innermost stable circular orbits for the geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09236v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soumya Chakrabarti, Chiranjeeb Singha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Krylov space approach to Singular Value Decomposition in non-Hermitian systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09309v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a tridiagonalization approach for non-Hermitian random matrices and Hamiltonians using singular value decomposition (SVD). This technique leverages the real and non-negative nature of singular values, bypassing the complex eigenvalues typically found in non-Hermitian systems. We analyze the tridiagonal elements, namely the Lanczos coefficients and the associated Krylov (spread) complexity, appropriately defined through the SVD, across several examples, including Ginibre ensembles and the non-Hermitian Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model. We demonstrate that in chaotic cases, the complexity exhibits a distinct peak due to the repulsion between singular values, a feature absent in integrable cases. Using our approach, we analytically compute the Krylov complexity for two-dimensional non-Hermitian random matrices within a subset of non-Hermitian symmetry classes including time-reversal, time-reversal$^{\dagger}$, chiral, and sublattice symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09309v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.064203</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 064203 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pratik Nandy, Tanay Pathak, Zhuo-Yu Xian, Johanna Erdmenger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meson spectroscopy in the $Sp(4)$ gauge theory with three antisymmetric fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.01170v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We report the results of an extensive numerical study of the $Sp(4)$ lattice gauge theory with three (Dirac) flavors of fermion in the two-index antisymmetric representation. In the presence of (degenerate) fermion masses, the theory has an enhanced global $SU(6)$ symmetry, broken explicitly and spontaneously to its $SO(6)$ subgroup. This symmetry breaking pattern makes the theory interesting for applications in the context of composite Higgs models, as well as for the implementation of top partial compositeness. It can also provide a dynamical realisation of the strongly interacting massive particle paradigm for the origin of dark matter. We adopt the standard plaquette gauge action with the Wilson-Dirac formulation for the fermions and apply the (rational) hybrid Monte Carlo algorithm in our ensemble generation process. We monitor the autocorrelation and topology of the ensembles. We explore the bare parameter space, and identify the weak and strong coupling regimes separated by a line of first-order bulk phase transitions.
  We measure two-point correlation functions between meson operators that transform as non-trivial representations of $SO(6)$, and extract the ground-state masses and the decay constants, in all accessible spin and parity channels. In addition, we measure the mass of the first excited state for the vector meson by solving a generalised eigenvalue problem. Spectral quantities show a mass dependence that is compatible with the expectation that, at long distances, the theory undergoes confinement, accompanied by the spontaneous breaking of the approximate global symmetries acting on the matter fields. Finally, we discuss the continuum and massless extrapolations, after setting the physical scale using the gradient flow method, and compare the results to those of existing studies in the quenched approximation, as well as to the literature on closely related theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.01170v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ed Bennett, Deog Ki Hong, Ho Hsiao, Jong-Wan Lee, C. -J. David Lin, Biagio Lucini, Maurizio Piai, Davide Vadacchino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Field Theoretical Description of an Alternative Model to Generalized Chaplygin Gas and its Thermodynamic Behaviour</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12200v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates a newly proposed fluid description of dark energy within the framework of the late-time accelerated expansion of the universe. Our primary objective is to explore the theoretical foundation of the proposed equation of state by establishing its correspondence with well-known scalar field models such as quintessence, k-essence, and DBI-essence. Through this correspondence, we reconstruct key field parameters, including the scalar field $\phi$ and scalar potential $V(\phi)$, and analyze their evolutionary behavior across cosmic time. The study also evaluates the model's physical consistency and cosmological implications by examining fundamental energy conditions - Null Energy Condition (NEC), Dominant Energy Condition (DEC), and Strong Energy Condition (SEC). Furthermore, we conduct a comprehensive stability analysis to ensure the robustness of the model and investigate its thermodynamic properties, including possible phase transitions using entropy and Gibbs free energy. To assess the observational viability of the model, we compare its predictions against recent datasets, including Cosmic Chronometers (CC), Baryon Acoustic Oscillation (BAO), and Supernova Type Ia from the Pantheon+SH0ES compilation and Union 2.1, as well as recent DESI and DESY5 data. Our analysis demonstrates that the proposed fluid model aligns well with observational constraints, reproduces the late-time acceleration of the universe, and offers a compelling alternative to the standard $\Lambda$-CDM model while maintaining consistency with current data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12200v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.dark.2025.101878</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physics of the Dark Universe (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tamal Mukhopadhyay, Banadipa Chakraborty, Ujjal Debnath, Anirudh Pradhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological Non-Gaussianity from Neutrino Seesaw Mechanism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16033v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The neutrino mass generation via conventional seesaw mechanism is realized at high scales around $O(10^{14})$GeV, making the test of neutrino seesaw a great challenge. A striking fact is that the neutrino seesaw scale is typically around the cosmological inflation scale. In this work, we propose a framework incorporating inflation and neutrino seesaw in which the inflaton primarily decays into right-handed neutrinos after inflation. This decay process is governed by the inflaton interaction with the right-handed neutrinos that respects the shift symmetry. Through the neutrino seesaw mechanism, fluctuations of the Higgs field can modulate the inflaton decays, contributing to the curvature perturbation. We investigate the induced non-Gaussian signatures and demonstrate that such signatures provides an important means to probe the high-scale neutrino seesaw mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16033v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingtao You, Linghao Song, Hong-Jian He, Chengcheng Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological Signatures of Neutrino Seesaw Mechanism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21045</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21045v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The tiny neutrino masses are most naturally explained by the seesaw mechanism through singlet right-handed neutrinos, which can further explain the matter-antimatter asymmetry in the universe. In this work, we propose a new approach to study cosmological signatures of neutrino seesaw through the interaction between inflaton and right-handed neutrinos. After inflation the inflaton predominantly decays into right-handed neutrinos and its decay rate is modulated by the fluctuations of Higgs field which act as the source of curvature perturbations. We demonstrate that this modulation produces primordial non-Gaussian signatures, which can be measured by the forthcoming large-scale structure surveys. We find that these surveys have the potential to probe a large portion of the neutrino seesaw parameter space, opening up a new window for testing the high scale seesaw mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21045v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengcheng Han, Hong-Jian He, Linghao Song, Jingtao You</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The foot, the fan, and the cuprate phase diagram: Fermi-volume-changing quantum phase transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16417</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16417v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A Fermi liquid with a 'large' Fermi surface (FL) can have a quantum phase transition to a spin density wave state (SDW) with reconstructed 'small' Fermi pockets. Both FL and SDW phases obey the Luttinger constraints on the volume enclosed by the Fermi surfaces. Critical spin fluctuations lead to spin-singlet $d$-wave pairing, as observed in the cuprates. Studies of the influence of spatial disorder on the FL-SDW quantum phase transition predict an extended quantum-critical Griffiths-type phase at low temperatures on the large Fermi surface side. These computations agree with the 'foot' of strange metal transport, and recent low temperature neutron scattering observations on La$_{2-x}$Sr$_x$CuO$_4$.
  However, this theory cannot explain the higher temperature pseudogap and the 'fan' of strange metal behavior of the hole-doped cuprates. Here we need to consider underlying Fermi-volume-changing quantum phase transitions without symmetry breaking. Then the small Fermi surface phase does not obey the Luttinger constraint, and the pseudogap metal is described by thermal fluctuations above a 'fractionalized Fermi liquid' (FL*) or a 'holon metal', with the descriptions related by a duality on a background spin liquid. The quantum critical fan is described using a field theory for an underlying FL-FL* quantum phase transition in the presence of spatial disorder. This field theory can be mapped to a form which can be analyzed using the methods of the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model. Such an analysis successfully models linear-in-temperature resistivity, optical conductivity and thermopower observations in the quantum critical fan.
  The confinement crossover connecting these lower and higher temperature descriptions is also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16417v5</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subir Sachdev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological phase-space analysis of $f(G)$-theories of gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01620v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The impact of topological terms that modify the Hilbert-Einstein action is here explored by virtue of a further $f(G)$ contribution. In particular, we investigate the phase-space stability and critical points of an equivalent scalar field representation that makes use of a massive field, whose potential is function of the topological correction. To do so, we introduce to the gravitational Action Integral a Lagrange multiplier and model the modified Friedmann equations by virtue of new non-dimensional variables. We single out dimensionless variables that permit \emph{a priori} the Hubble rate change of sign, enabling regions in which the Hubble parameter either vanishes or becomes negative. In this respect, we thus analyze the various possibilities associated with a universe characterized by such topological contributions and find the attractors, saddle points and regions of stability, in general. The overall analysis is carried out considering the exponential potential first and then shifting to more complicated cases, where the underlying variables do not simplify. We compute the eigenvalues of our coupled differential equations and, accordingly, the stability of the system, in both a spatially-flat and non-flat universe. Quite remarkably, regardless of the spatial curvature, we show that a stable de Sitter-like phase that can model current time appears only a small fraction of the entire phase-space, suggesting that the model under exam is unlikely in describing the whole universe dynamics, i.e., the topological terms appear disfavored in framing the entire evolution of the universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01620v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giannis Papagiannopoulos, Orlando Luongo, Genly Leon, Andronikos Paliathanasis</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
