<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th</link>
    <description>hep-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 02:23:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Elementary Classical and Quantum Lifshitz Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04522v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We classify the elementary classical and quantum Lifshitz systems. Lifshitz systems are systems where space and time scale anisotropically. That is, there is a constant $z$ such that under scaling by a factor of $\lambda$,
  \begin{equation*}
  \boldsymbol{x}\rightarrow \lambda \boldsymbol{x} \text{ and } t\rightarrow \lambda^{z}t
  \end{equation*}
  There are seven Lie groups, called the Lifshitz groups, which characterise all Lifshitz symmetries.
  Elementary classical Lifshitz systems are the symplectic manifolds with a transitive Lifshitz action, which turn out to be coadjoint orbits of the Lifshitz groups and their one-dimensional central extensions up to covering. Elementary quantum Lifshitz systems are the projective unitary irreducible representations of the Lifshitz groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04522v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jarah Fluxman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A measure on the space of CFTs and pure 3D gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04554v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We define a normalizable measure on the space of two-dimensional conformal field theories, which we interpret as a maximum ignorance ensemble. We test whether pure quantum gravity in AdS$_3$ is dual to the average over this ensemble. We find a negative answer, which implies that CFTs with a primary gap of order the central charge are highly atypical in our ensemble. We provide evidence that more generally, holographic CFTs are atypical in the space of all CFTs by finding similar results for permutation orbifolds: subgroups of $S_N$ with a good large $N$ limit are very sparse in the space of all subgroups. Along the way, we derive several new results on the space of CFTs. Notably we derive an upper bound on the spacing in central charge between CFTs, which is doubly exponentially small in the large central charge limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04554v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Belin, Alexander Maloney, Florian Seefeld</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large N Chern-Simons-matter fixed points with multiple flavors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04565v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we analyze the $2+1$d conformal fixed points arising from $SU(N_c)$ Chern-Simons-matter theories with multiple flavors $N_f &gt; 1$ in the 't Hooft large $N_c$ limit. The multi-flavor generalization of quasi-fermionic theories (fermions or critical scalars coupled to Chern-Simons gauge fields) is straightforward, but this is not true for quasi-bosonic theories (scalars or critical fermions coupled to Chern-Simons gauge fields). The latter theories have three flavor-singlet relevant operators and also three marginal operators, that become exactly marginal for infinite $N_c$, but have a non-zero beta function at order $1/N_c$. We compute the beta functions of these couplings in various weak coupling limits, and discuss also their general structure, generalizing previous computations for $N_f=1$. We find that IR-stable fixed points of the marginal couplings exist for some values of $N_f$ and of the 't Hooft coupling $\lambda$, but not for other values, and in one case we can explicitly follow how two pairs of fixed points merge and disappear as $\lambda$ is increased. We also analyze the ``Semi-Critical'' conformal field theories that arise when fine-tuning two (rather than three) relevant operators, and compute the beta function for their (single) marginal coupling constant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04565v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ofer Aharony, Ronny Frumkin, Jonathan Mehl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do null defects dream of conformal symmetry?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04578</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04578v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We initiate the study of null line defects in Lorentzian conformal field theories in various dimensions. We show that null lines geometrically preserve a larger set of conformal isometries than their timelike and spacelike counterparts, explain a connection to non-relativistic systems, and constrain correlation functions using conformal Ward identities. We argue that having conformal symmetry, and especially maximal conformal symmetry, is extremely constraining -- nearly trivializing systems. We consider the (3+1)d scalar pinning field and null Wilson line examples in depth, compare their results to ultraboosted limits of timelike and spacelike systems, and argue that shockwave-type solutions are generic. A number of physical consistency conditions compel us to consider defect correlators as distributions on a restricted subspace of Schwartz test functions. Consequently, we provide a resolution to the longstanding problem of ultraboosted limits of gauge potentials in classical electromagnetism. We briefly analyze semi-infinite sources for the scalar in ($4-\epsilon$)-dimensions, consider solutions on the Lorentzian cylinder, and introduce the ''perfect null polygon'' which emerges for compatibility between Gauss' law and ultraboosted limits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04578v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rajeev S. Erramilli, Justin Kulp, Fedor K. Popov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spontaneous collapse effects on relativistic fermionic matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04585</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04585v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study expands the spontaneous collapse assumptions into the relativistic quantum field theory framework for Dirac fields. By solving Lindblad's master equation using the Keldysh formalism, the effective action is derived, which captures the dynamics of fermions with spontaneous collapse represented as an imaginary self-interaction term. Utilizing the corresponding Dyson-Schwinger equations at 1-loop approximation, the effective mass induced by the nonlinearity is computed. The findings indicate the presence of a new mechanism that introduces a qualitative change in the mass spectrum, where the particle's mass becomes complex. This mechanism, which generates a Lorentz invariance violation in the infrared regime, recovers the Lorentz invariance in the ultraviolet regime. The corresponding hydrodynamics of the system is analyzed through the Keldysh component of the propagator, and a conserved charge is found. In contrast, the energy-momentum tensor is shown to be non-conserving. This phenomenon represents a new contribution to the understanding of the spontaneous collapse and the transition from quantum to the classical realm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04585v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. M. P. Gomes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gauged Extended Field Theory and Generalised Cartan Geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04595</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04595v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cartan geometry provides a unifying algebraic construction of curvature and torsion, based on an underlying model Lie algebra -- a viewpoint that can be extended naturally to the higher algebraic structures underlying supergravity. We present a Cartan-geometric framework for generalised geometries governed by a differential graded Lie algebra, extending previous results. The extended tangent bundle admits the action of both a global duality group $\mathcal{G}$ and a local gauge group $H$. This algebraic structure is implemented via a brane current algebra -- the phase space Poisson structure of $p$-branes. Within this Cartan-inspired framework, we define a hierarchy of generalised connections and compute their linearised torsion and curvature tensors, including the higher curvatures required by the tensor hierarchy. This provides a systematic construction of curvature and torsion tensors in generic generalised geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04595v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Falk Hassler, David Osten, Alex Swash</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A systematic search for conformal field theories in very small spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04596</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04596v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Groundstates of 1+1d conformal field theories (CFTs) satisfy a local entropic condition called the vector fixed point equation. This condition is surprisingly well satisfied by groundstates of quantum critical lattice models even at small system sizes. We perform a search in the space of states of very small systems (four qubits and four qutrits) and examine the states that satisfy this condition. By reconstructing a local Hamiltonian from each state, we are able to identify many of these solutions with known CFTs; others are gapped fixed points, or involve large relevant perturbations, and others are CFTs we have not yet identified. These ideas are also useful for identifying continuous quantum phase transitions in a given family of Hamiltonians, and for identifying the nature of the critical theory in small systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04596v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiang Li, Ting-Chun Lin, John McGreevy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New phases in QCD at finite temperature and chemical potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04671v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the phases of quantum chromodynamics (QCD) at finite temperature and baryon density is crucial for describing matter in heavy-ion collisions and the interior of neutron stars. While the transition from the confined phase to the deconfined phase has been extensively studied at vanishing chemical potential, recent theoretical work suggests the existence of intermediate phases with partial deconfinement, where only a subset of the color degrees of freedom is deconfined. In this paper, we study the generalization of partial deconfinement in QCD in the Veneziano large-$N_{\rm c}$ limit ($N_{\rm f}/N_{\rm c}$ fixed) to finite baryon chemical potential. We find that the partially deconfined phase has finer structure, and hence that there are four phases in QCD at finite temperature and moderately large chemical potential: complete confinement, complete deconfinement, and two kinds of partial deconfinement. A key ingredient is the refined understanding of the meaning of the 'Gross-Witten-Wadia point', i.e., the opening of a gap in the distribution of Polyakov line phases: either string condensation or baryon condensation causes the GWW transition. As a by-product, we observe the emergence of the QCD critical point from the interplay between baryon condensation and partial deconfinement. While our approach is necessarily qualitative due to the fermion sign problem, it provides a unified theoretical framework for understanding the rich phase structure of dense QCD matter and offers new perspectives on the location and nature of the QCD critical point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04671v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masanori Hanada, Jack Holden, Hiromasa Watanabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Maxwell--Born--Infeld Theory: Presence of Finite-Energy Electric Point Charge and Absence of Monopole and Dyon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04765v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We formulate a nonlinear electrodynamic theory which may be viewed as a weighted theory minimally interpolating the classical Maxwell and Born--Infeld theories. We show that, in contrast to the Born--Infeld theory, this new theory accommodates a finite-energy electric point charge, like that in the Born--Infeld theory, but does not accommodate a finite-energy magnetic point charge, known as the monopole, thereby exhibiting an electromagnetic asymmetry property, unlike that in the Born--Infeld theory. We estimate the radius of the electron within the formalism of such a theory. We also show that an electric point charge carries a finite energy in the Maxwell theory limit. Furthermore, we demonstrate that the theory does not accommodate a finite-energy monopole nor a dyon either in its most general setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04765v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tengyang Liu, Yisong Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minkowski Space holography and Radon transform</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04974</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04974v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We relate a free scalar field in the Minkowski spacetime with a scalar field with a certain scaling dimension on a sphere of codimension two. This is realised by first performing a Radon transform of the ``bulk" field on the Minkowski space to a field on a hyperplane identified with a de Sitter or Euclidean anti-de Sitter slice. The Radon transform is identified in turn with a scalar field obtained from a sphere of one further lower dimension through the so-called bulk reconstruction programme. We write down the Mellin modes of the bulk field as generalised hypergeometric functions using the Lee-Pomeransky method developed for evaluation of Feynman loop diagrams.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04974v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samrat Bhowmick, Koushik Ray</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semi-classical spacetime thermodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05052v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We derive the semi-classical gravitational dynamics from thermodynamics of local stretched light cones in 2-dimensional dilaton gravity, explicitly treating the backreaction of quantum matter through the conformal anomaly's effect on the generalized entropy. We also sketch the extension of this analysis to the conformal anomaly in 4-dimensional semi-classical gravity. In direct connection to this problem, we also tackle the appropriate definition of Wald entropy in thermodynamic derivation of equations of motion for classical scalar-tensor theories. For the class of Brans-Dicke theories, including 2-dimensional dilaton gravity, we show that the equations of motion follow from the dynamical Wald entropy associated with local causal horizons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05052v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ana Alonso-Serrano, Marek Li\v{s}ka, Micha{\l} Piotrak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The octonionic phase space Hopf map</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05073</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05073v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The octonionic Hopf map, expressing $S^{15}$ as an $S^7$ bundle over $S^8$, appears in the twistor transform in 10 dimensions, $S^8$ playing the r\^ole of the celestial sphere. A symplectic lift to twistor space manifests $Spin(2,10)$ symmetry. The 25-dimensional spinor orbit of $Spin(2,10)$ is an $S^7$ bundle over the phase space of a massless particle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05073v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Cederwall</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soliton Surfaces and the Geometry of Integrable Deformations of the $\mathbb{CP}^{N-1}$ Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05081</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05081v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The $\mathbb{CP}^{N-1}$ model is an analytically tractable $2d$ quantum field theory which shares several properties with $4d$ Yang-Mills theory. By virtue of its classical integrability, this model also admits a family of integrable higher-spin auxiliary field deformations, including the $T \overline{T}$ deformation as a special case. We study the $\mathbb{CP}^{N-1}$ model and its deformations from a geometrical perspective, constructing their soliton surfaces and recasting physical properties of these theories as statements about surface geometry. We examine how the $T \overline{T}$ flow affects the unit constraint in the $\mathbb{CP}^{N-1}$ model and prove that any solution of this theory with vanishing energy-momentum tensor remains a solution under analytic stress tensor deformations -- an argument that extends to generic dimensions and instanton-like solutions in stress tensor flows including the non-analytic, $2d$, root-$T \overline{T}$ case and classes of higher-spin, Smirnov-Zamolodchikov-type, deformations. Finally, we give two geometric interpretations for general $T \overline{T}$-like deformations of symmetric space sigma models, showing that such flows can be viewed as coupling the undeformed theory to a unit-determinant field-dependent metric, or using a particular choice of moving frame on the soliton surface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05081v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Ferko, Michele Galli, Zejun Huang, Gabriele Tartaglino-Mazzucchelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A strong-weak duality for the 1d long-range Ising model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05250</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05250v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the one-dimensional Ising model with long-range interactions decaying as $1/r^{1+s}$. In the critical regime, for $1/2 \leq s \leq 1$, this system realizes a family of nontrivial one-dimensional conformal field theories (CFTs), whose data vary continuously with $s$. For $s&gt;1$ the model has instead no phase transition at finite temperature, as in the short-range case. In the standard field-theoretic description, involving a generalized free field with quartic interactions, the critical model is weakly coupled near $s=1/2$ but strongly coupled in the vicinity of the short-range crossover at $s=1$. We introduce a dual formulation that becomes weakly coupled as $s \to 1$. Precisely at $s=1$, the dual description becomes an exactly solvable conformal boundary condition of the two-dimensional free scalar. We present a detailed study of the dual model and demonstrate its effectiveness by computing perturbatively the CFT data near $s=1$, up to next-to-next-to-leading order in $1-s$, by two independent approaches: (i) standard renormalization of our dual field-theoretic description and (ii) the analytic conformal bootstrap. The two methods yield complete agreement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05250v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dario Benedetti, Edoardo Lauria, Dalimil Mazac, Philine van Vliet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flat connections at infinity on knot surgery manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05270v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: $\rm SL(2,\mathbb{C})$ Chern-Simons theory on a closed 3-manifold is one of the most interesting, yet tractable examples of a QFT. On one hand, its non-perturbative structure is not yet fully understood; on the other, the mathematical structure turns out to be very rich. In this work we explore the new phenomenon of flat connections at infinity on various knot surgery manifolds. Such flat connections can be understood as asymptotic ends in the non-compact moduli space of flat $\rm SL(2,\mathbb{C})$ connections. We focus on the examples of $\pm 1/r$-surgeries on torus, twist and some double twist knot complements in $S^3$. Surprisingly, our findings suggest that flat connections at infinity are abundant even for simple low-crossing knot surgeries. We therefore believe that their presence would shed light on the resurgent nature of the path integral.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05270v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aditya Dwivedi, Archana Maji, Dmitry Noshchenko, Ramadevi Pichai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characteristic tensors for almost Finsler manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21744</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.21744v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Almost Finsler manifolds and partial Finsler manifolds are introduced, extending the standard definition of a Finsler manifold to allow for a nontrivial slit containing points fixed under homogeneous scaling and for metrics where the fundamental tensor has nonpositive eigenvalues. The bipartite spaces offer examples of comparatively simple almost Finsler manifolds and partial Finsler manifolds with physics applications. Special cases are the $\bf{a}$ and $\bf{b}$ spaces, which have almost Finsler norms and partial Finsler norms formed from a Riemannian norm and a 1-form. The indicatrix union of the almost Finsler $\bf{a}$ manifolds equals the indicatrix union of Randers spaces. Characteristic tensors that vanish for bipartite spaces and $\bf{b}$ spaces are obtained and expressed using geometric quantities. These tensors are generalizations of the Matsumoto tensor, which vanishes on Randers and $\bf{a}$ spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.21744v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James F. Davis, Benjamin R. Edwards, Alan Kostelecky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Faraday and Maxwell to Quantum Physics. The later story of the Electromagnetic Vector Potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04486v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: With the advent of quantum mechanics by Heisenberg in 1925 exactly a century ago, the quantization of the electromagnetic field became an important goal for our founding fathers, whom we are here to celebrate. It was realized very soon that a consistent picture of quantum electrodynamics (QED) requires the quantization of not just the electromagnetic field ${\bf A}({\bf r},t)$, but the electron field ${\bf \psi}({\bf r},t)$ as well. The electron field is now a Dirac spinor field and it becomes a major partner for the vector potential. Together these two fields form a duet which yearns for a unification which is not often emphasized in text books, but no one knows how to do this yet. The underlying structure appears to be a super-symmetric one where bosons and fermions live comfortably as a single field that could by some yet unknown process produce QED. This area is still at the forefront of current research with names like Super-symmetric Quantum Electrodynamics (SQED), strings and others. Ironically for a variety of reasons, the number of fields in SQED has to be increased and not decreased, defying the objective of an economical unification. Furthermore it is now known that Maxwell's theory is incomplete and that there are situations due to boundaries or topology that demand the vector potential must itself be gauge invariant.
  (This paper is dedicated to the celebration of 100 years of quantum mechanics, on the anniversary of Heisenberg's founding paper on the subject in July 1925, delivered by Miguel Ortu\~no at the IQSA 2025 Conference at Tropea in Calabria, Italy from 30 June to 4th July 2025. The proceedings will be published as a celebratory volume by World Scientific Publications, Singapore in 2026).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04486v1</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tuck Choy, Miguel Ortuno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Structure and Interpretation of Quantum Programs I: Foundations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04527v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Qubits are a great way to build a quantum computer, but a limited way to program one. We replace the usual "states and gates" formalism with a "props and ops" (propositions and operators) model in which (a) the C*-algebra of observables supplies the syntax; (b) states, viewed as linear functionals, give the semantics; and (c) a novel diagrammatic calculus unifies the two. The first part develops the basic objects of the framework, encoding consistent patterns of operator correlation, recovering Hilbert space via the GNS construction, and re-deriving the Bloch sphere as the set of all consistent correlations of operators in the Pauli algebra.
  We then turn to intervention, showing how measurement modifies state, proving an operator-algebraic version of the Knill-Laflamme conditions, and expressing stabilizer codes with the same diagrammatic machinery. This provides a concise, representation-agnostic account of quantum error correction. The result is a self-contained foundation in which C*-algebras, and their dual Hilbert spaces, offer a rich and universal substrate for quantum programming; forthcoming papers will build a high-level language and quantum software applications on top of this substrate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04527v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Wakeham</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing the roles of transitory obscured phases and inner torus in shaping the fractions of obscured AGN at cosmic noon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04553v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The origin of obscuration in Active Galactic Nuclei (AGN) is still a matter of contention. It is unclear whether obscured AGN are primarily due to line-of-sight effects, a transitory, dust-enshrouded phase in galaxy evolution, or a combination of both. The role of an inner torus around the central SMBH also remains unclear in pure Evolution models. We use cosmological semi-analytic models and semi-empirical prescriptions to explore obscuration effects in AGN at 1&lt;z&lt;3. We consider a realistic object-by-object modelling of AGN evolution including different light curves (LCs) composed of phases of varying levels of obscuration, mimicking the possible clearing effects of strong AGN feedback. Evolution models characterized by AGN LCs with relatively short pre-peak obscured phases followed by more extended optical/UV visible post-peak phases, struggle to reproduce the high fraction of obscured AGN at z~2-3 inferred from X-ray surveys. Evolution models characterised by LCs with sharp post-peak declines or persistent or multiple obscuration phases are more successful, although they still face challenges in reproducing the steady drop in the fractions of obscured AGN with increasing luminosity measured by some groups. Invoking a fine-tuning in the input LCs, with more luminous AGN defined by longer optical/UV visible windows, can improve the match to the decreasing fractions of obscured AGN with luminosity. Alternatively, a long-lived central torus-like component, with thickness decreasing with increasing AGN power, naturally boosts the luminosity-dependent fractions of obscured AGN, suggesting that small-scale orientation effects may still represent a key component even in Evolution models. We also find that in our models major mergers and starbursts, when considered in isolation, fall short in accounting for the large fractions of highly obscured faint AGN detected at cosmic noon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04553v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/staf1485</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Alba V. Alonso-Tetilla, Francesco Shankar, Fabio Fontanot, Andrea Lapi, Milena Valentini, Annagrazia Puglisi, Nicola Menci, Hao Fu, Lumen Boco, Johannes Buchner, Michaela Hirschmann, Cristina Ramos Almeida, Carolin Villforth, Lizhi Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dirac quantum criticality in twisted double bilayer transition metal dichalcogenides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04561</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04561v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the phase diagram of moir\'e double bilayer transition metal dichalcogenides with ABBA stacking as a function of twist angle and applied pressure. At hole filling $\nu = 2$ per moir\'e unit cell, the noninteracting system hosts a Dirac semimetal with graphene-like low-energy bands in the moir\'e Brillouin zone. At small twist angles, the Fermi velocity is reduced and interactions dominate the low-temperature behavior. A strong-coupling analysis identifies insulating ferromagnetic and antiferromagnetic ground-state candidates, characterized by spin-density modulations set by the moir\'e scale. Using a realistic continuum model with long-range Coulomb interactions, we perform self-consistent Hartree-Fock calculations to study the competition between these states. Varying the twist angle or pressure drives a transition from a Dirac semimetal to an antiferromagnetic insulator, which breaks SU(2) spin rotation and two-fold lattice rotation symmetries. This semimetal-to-insulator transition is continuous and belongs to the (2+1)D relativistic Gross-Neveu-Heisenberg universality class with $N = 2$ four-component Dirac fermions. Finite heterostrain, relevant in realistic samples, induces a crossover from Gross-Neveu-Heisenberg universality at intermediate temperatures to conventional (2+1)D Heisenberg criticality at the lowest temperatures. Further decreasing the twist angle can cause a level crossing from the antiferromagnetic insulator into a ferromagnetic insulator with spin-split bands. Our results provide a comprehensive theoretical framework that complements and elucidates recent experiments in twisted double bilayer WSe$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04561v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Biedermann, Lukas Janssen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter in a Three-Brane Randall-Sundrum Scenario out of the Evanescent Limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04580v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Nature of Dark Matter (DM), that constitutes approximately 25\% of the energy density in the Universe, is still eluding us. An intriguing possibility is that DM does indeed interacts with SM particles only gravitationally (the only mean by which we have detected it so far), albeit in an extra-dimensional scenario yet it has not been possible to detect it by some non-gravitational means. In a three-brane Randall-Sundrum setup, with DM located on a Deep Infra-Red GeV-TeV brane, and the SM on an Infra-Red TeV-PeV one, it was shown to be possible to recover the observed DM relic abundance and somewhat relax the hierarchy problem, whilst avoiding LHC stringent bounds on DM and KK graviton masses that constrain severely similar two-brane setups. The phenomenological results, however, has been obtained under the assumption that the bulk curvatures on the left ($k_1$) and the right ($k_2$) of the intermediate IR-brane are identical, $k_2 \to k_1$. Since the brane tension $\sigma_{\rm IR}$ of the intermediate brane is proportional to $k_2 - k_1$ and, therefore, vanishes, it is clear that this limit (for which the IR-brane becomes {\em evanescent}) is unphysical. We could say that this is {\em no brane}: if the brane tension of a brane vanishes, there is no brane in the bulk (pun intended). In this paper, therefore, we study in detail the theoretical framework needed to explore this interesting phenomenological possibility, {\em out of the evanescent brane limit}. We show that most of the formul\ae $\,$used in the {\em evanescent limit} are still valid for ${\cal O}(1)$ differences between $k_1$ and $k_2$ (thus, introducing no new unjustified hierarchy in the bulk). Once the relevant couplings of radions and KK gravitons are computed, we study the (enlarged) parameter space of the model looking for the region in which the relic DM abundance is recovered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04580v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Donini, Miguel G. Folgado, Alejandro Mu\~noz-Ovalle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetric entanglers for non-invertible SPT phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04581v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It has been suggested that non-invertible symmetry protected topological phases (SPT), due to the lack of a stacking structure, do not have symmetric entanglers (globally symmetric finite-depth quantum circuits) connecting them. Using topological holography, we argue that a symmetric entangler should in fact exist for $1+1$d systems whenever the non-invertible symmetry has SPT phases connected by fixed-charge dualities (FCD). Moreover, we construct an explicit example of a symmetric entangler for the two SPT phases with $\mathrm{Rep}(A_4)$-symmetry, as a matrix product unitary (MPU).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04581v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minyoung You</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chaos in Horndeski cosmologies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04590v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyze how a scalar field can affect the chaotic behaviour of homogeneous and isotropic Bianchi IX cosmologies. It is known that a massless, minimally coupled scalar field removes the chaos. However, in more general Horndeski theories, the situation is more complex. We find that in shift-symmetric $K$-essence theories, chaos persists if the scalar field contribution to the initial-value constraint is {\it subleading} compared to that of the anisotropies. In this case, solutions oscillate as they approach the singularity, just as in the vacuum case, and a similar behaviour is found when a non-minimal coupling is included. If the scalar field contribution is not subleading, then chaos is removed and the singularity is approached smoothly.
  An unusual and entirely new result appears when changing the sign in front of the scalar kinetic term, yielding the theory of a phantom scalar. If the scalar field is subleading, then solutions remain chaotic and oscillate when approaching the singularity, as before. However, if the scalar field is not subleading, solutions are also chaotic, but the spacetime singularity disappears, and the universe behaves as an apparently infinite sequence of anisotropic bounces. The spatial volume then oscillates within finite bounds, never reaching zero, while the amplitudes and positions of these oscillations appear completely random. To the best of our knowledge, this type of chaos has never been described.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04590v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail S. Volkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The principal W-algebra of $\mathfrak{psl}_{2|2}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04795v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the structure and representation theory of the principal W-algebra $\mathsf{W}^{\mathsf{k}}_{\mathrm{pr}}$ of $\mathsf{V}^{\mathsf{k}}(\mathfrak{psl}_{2|2})$. The defining operator product expansions are computed, as is the Zhu algebra, and these results are used to classify irreducible highest-weight modules. In particular, for $\mathsf{k} = \pm \frac{1}{2}$, $\mathsf{W}^{\mathsf{k}}_{\mathrm{pr}}$ is not simple and the corresponding simple quotient is the symplectic fermion vertex algebra. We use this fact, along with inverse hamiltonian reduction, to study relaxed highest-weight and logarithmic modules for the small $N=4$ superconformal algebra at central charges $-9$ and $-3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04795v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zachary Fehily, Christopher Raymond, David Ridout</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flavour from Fractal Mass Chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04811</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04811v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explore the possibility that the underlying flavour structure of the Standard Model could be determined by mass chains on a fractal geometry. We consider, as an example, the theory space on a Sierpinski-like geometry. The fermion mass chains on a Sierpinski-like geometry with three decorations (iterations) lead to three zero modes, which can be identified with the three generations of the Standard Model. This framework also reproduces the measured charged and neutral lepton masses and mixing angles with very few parameters. We also briefly discuss the possible extension to the quark sector.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04811v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alejandro Ibarra, Aadarsh Singh, Sudhir K Vempati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Genesis--Starobinsky inflation can explain the ACT data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04832v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a novel non-singular cosmological scenario within the framework of Horndeski gravity, consisting of three successive stages: (i) a Genesis phase, in which the Universe slowly expands from an asymptotically flat spacetime; (ii) a brief transition stage restoring General Relativity; and (iii) a Starobinsky inflationary phase. This construction is fully consistent within a viable parameter space: it remains weakly coupled, free from ghost and gradient instabilities, with luminal tensor and subluminal scalar perturbations throughout the entire evolution. Importantly, the Genesis phase induces characteristic corrections to the Starobinsky potential, which cannot be captured by simple $\sum_i c_i R^i$-type modifications. These corrections robustly enhance the scalar spectral index, thereby improving the agreement of Starobinsky inflation with recent CMB measurements, in particular the data from the Atacama Cosmology Telescope (ACT).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04832v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Han Gil Choi, Pavel Petrov, Seong Chan Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Note on searching for critical lattice models as entropy critical points from strange correlator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04947v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: An entropy function is proposed in [Phys. Rev. Lett. 131, 251602] as a way to detect criticality even when the system size is small. In this note we apply this strategy in the search for criticality of lattice transfer matrices constructed based on the topological holographic principle. We find that the combination of strategy is indeed a cost-effective and efficient way of identifying critical boundary conditions, estimating central charges and moreover, plotting entire phase diagrams in a multi-dimensional phase space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04947v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anran Jin, Ling-Yan Hung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unique gravitational wave signatures of GLPV scalar-tensor theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05027v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study gravitational waves induced by scalar primordial fluctuations in Gleyzes-Langlois-Piazza-Vernizzi (GLPV), beyond Horndeski, scalar-tensor theories. We uncover, at the level of the action, a new scalar-scalar-tensor interaction, unique to GLPV models disconnected from Horndeski via disformal transformation. The new interaction leads to third derivatives in the source for scalar-induced tensor modes, which are absent in Horndeski-related theories. Such new higher-derivative terms lead to a further enhanced production of induced gravitational waves. We predict that for a scale-invariant primordial spectrum, the induced gravitational wave spectral density has a characteristic frequency dependence proportional to $f^5$. Such a fast-rising spectrum offers a potential unique signature of modified gravity in the early universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05027v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillem Dom\`enech, Alexander Ganz, Mohammad Ali Gorji, Masahide Yamaguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Overcharging Extremal Rotating Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05087</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05087v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we use the weak cosmic censorship conjecture(WCC) to constrain black hole solutions in modified gravity theories. While Wald showed that extremal Kerr-Newman black holes in general relativity cannot be overcharged by test charged particles, this protection may fail in theories beyond general relativity. We have considered generic rotating black hole solutions beyond the Kerr-Newman family and examine particle absorption processes that could lead to overcharging and the emergence of naked singularities. Identifying regions of parameter space where WCC is violated allows us to place direct, physically motivated bounds on deviations from general relativity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05087v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shauvik Biswas, Amruta Sadhu, Sudipta Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gaussian curvature and Lyapunov exponent as probes of black hole phase transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05103</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05103v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the Gaussian curvature of unstable null orbits. The Gaussian curvature exhibits multivaluedness near the phase transition point of a first-order phase transition. Numerical investigations of Reissner-Nordstrom Anti-de Sitter (RN-AdS), Hayward-AdS, and Hayward-Letelier-AdS black holes demonstrate that this geometric multivalued region coincides precisely with the spinodal region calculated by black hole thermodynamics. Using the known relation $K=-\lambda^2$ linking orbital geometry to chaotic dynamics, we show that this geometric feature also satisfies the critical exponents predicted by mean-field theory, consistent with those derived from Lyapunov exponents. Our work demonstrates that Gaussian curvature can serve as an alternative effective tool to study the phase structure of black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05103v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shi-Hao Zhang, Zi-Qiang Zhao, Zi-Yuan Li, Jing-Fei Zhang, Xin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 3d mixed BF Lagrangian 1-form: a variational formulation of Hitchin's integrable system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05127v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the concept of gauged Lagrangian $1$-forms, extending the notion of Lagrangian $1$-forms to the setting of gauge theories. This general formalism is applied to a natural geometric Lagrangian $1$-form on the cotangent bundle of the space of holomorphic structures on a smooth principal $G$-bundle $\mathcal{P}$ over a compact Riemann surface $C$ of arbitrary genus $g$, with or without marked points, in order to gauge the symmetry group of smooth bundle automorphisms of $\mathcal{P}$. The resulting construction yields a multiform version of the $3$d mixed BF action with so-called type A and B defects, providing a variational formulation of Hitchin's completely integrable system over $C$. By passing to holomorphic local trivialisations and going partially on-shell, we obtain a unifying action for a hierarchy of Lax equations describing the Hitchin system in terms of meromorphic Lax matrices. The cases of genus $0$ and $1$ with marked points are treated in greater detail, producing explicit Lagrangian $1$-forms for the rational Gaudin hierarchy and the elliptic Gaudin hierarchy, respectively, with the elliptic spin Calogero-Moser hierarchy arising as a special subcase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05127v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincent Caudrelier, Derek Harland, Anup Anand Singh, Benoit Vicedo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bulk viscosity from early-time thermalization of cosmic fluids in light of DESI DR2 data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05148</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05148v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: If nonrelativistic dark matter and radiation are allowed to interact, reaching an approximate thermal equilibrium, this interaction induces a bulk viscous pressure changing the effective one-fluid description of the universe dynamics. By modeling such components as perfect fluids, a cosmologically relevant bulk viscous pressure emerges for dark matter particle masses in the range of $1\,\text{eV} - 10\,\text{eV}$ keeping thermal equilibrium with the radiation. Such a transient bulk viscosity introduces significant effects in the expansion rate near the matter-radiation equality (redshift $z_{\text{eq}} \sim 3400$) and at late times (leading to a higher inferred value of the Hubble constant $H_0$). We use the recent DESI DR2 BAO data to place an upper bound on the free parameter of the model $\tau_\text{eq}$ which represents the time scale in which each component follows its own internal perfect fluid dynamics until thermalization occurs. Our main result is encoded in the bound $\tau_\text{eq} &lt; 1.84 \times 10^{-10} $ s (2$\sigma$), with the corresponding dimensionless bulk coefficient $\tilde{\xi} H_0/H_{eq}&lt;5.94\times10^{-4}$ (2$\sigma$). In practice, this rules out any possible interaction between radiation and dark matter prior to the recombination epoch.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05148v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hermano Velten, William Iania</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Near-horizon Instabilities and Anomalous Decay Rate of Quasinormal Modes in Weyl Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05164v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the stability of the Weyl geometry considering an exact black hole solution. By calculating the geodesics of massless and massive scalar fields orbiting outside the Weyl black hole background and using the Lyapunov exponent, we show that chaotic instabilities appear in the asymptotically de Siter-like spacetime. Calculating the photon sphere's quasinormal modes (QNMs) of a scalar field perturbing the Weyl black hole, we find a relation connecting the QNMs with the Lyapunov exponent in the asymptotically de Siter-like spacetime. Furthermore, we study the anomalous decay rate of the QNMs connecting their behavior with the Lyapunov exponent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05164v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gerasimos Kouniatalis, P. A. Gonz\'alez, Eleftherios Papantonopoulos, Yerko V\'asquez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for a Dark Dimension Right-handed Neutrino in KATRIN</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05233v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the possibility that the Right-handed neutrino is a five-dimensional state propagating along a micron size extra dimension, as required in the dark dimension proposal. We work out the signatures of R-neutrino production in KATRIN experiment and compare them with those of a sterile neutrino which manifests by a kink in the electron energy spectrum of the beta-decay at a value corresponding to the sterile neutrino mass. We explore the allowed parameter space of the compactification scale and the R-neutrino bulk mass versus the Yukawa coupling, and show that a large part of it is within KATRIN's sensitivity. When the bulk mass is much smaller than the compactification scale, several kinks could be observed corresponding to the positions of the R-neutrino Kaluza-Klein excitations, while for large bulk mass there will be effectively one kink at the position of the bulk mass.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05233v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ignatios Antoniadis, Auttakit Chatrabhuti, Hiroshi Isono</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marginal IR running of Gravity as a Natural Explanation for Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05246v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose that the infrared (IR) running of Newton's coupling provides a simple and universal explanation for large--distance modifications of gravity relevant to dark matter phenomenology. Within the effective field theory (EFT) framework, we model $G(k)$ as a scale--dependent coupling governed by an anomalous dimension $\eta$. We show that the marginal case $\eta = 1$ is singled out by renormalization group (RG) and dimensional arguments, leading to a logarithmic potential and a $1/r$ force law at large distances, while smoothly recovering Newtonian gravity at short scales. The logarithmic correction is universal and regulator independent, indicating that the $1/r$ force arises as the robust IR imprint of quantum--field--theoretic scaling. This provides a principled alternative to particle dark matter, suggesting that galactic rotation curves and related anomalies may be understood as manifestations of the IR running of Newton's constant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05246v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naman Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magic for Hybrid Boson-Fermion Systems: A Grassmann Phase-Space Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05264v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Non-stabilizerness enables universality beyond Gaussian/Clifford dynamics, yet no resource theory exists for systems combining bosonic and fermionic modes. Using the Grassmann approach of Cahill and Glauber, we develop a phase-space framework defining hybrid magic via the $L_p$ norm of a hybrid Wigner function. We demonstrate it in the Holstein polaron, where phonon-electron coupling enhances magic growth, and in the fermionic Jaynes-Cummings model, examining dependence on atomic and cavity states. At the gate level, we define the non-stabilizer power of hybrid operations and derive a closed-form result for the conditional displacement gate. This establishes a unified quantification of non-stabilizerness in realistic hybrid systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05264v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthieu Sarkis, Pablo Martinez-Azcona, Alexandre Tkatchenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scrambling in charged hairy black holes and the Kasner interior</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01680</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01680v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We analyze how the axion parameter, the Einstein-Maxwell-Scalar (EMS) coupling constant, and the charge density affect the chaotic properties of a charged hairy black hole, as characterized by the quantum Lyapunov exponent. We inject charged shock waves from the asymptotic boundary and compute the out-of-time-ordered correlators (OTOCs). Due to the relevant deformation in the boundary theory induced by a bulk scalar field, the bulk solution flows to a more general Kasner spacetime near the black hole singularity. We examine the behavior of chaotic parameters, including the Lyapunov exponent, butterfly velocity, and scrambling time delay, under this deformation. We find that as the deformation parameter increases, the ratio of the quantum Lyapunov exponent to the surface gravity decreases. For sufficiently large deformation, the Lyapunov exponent in the deformed geometry can exceed that of the axion Reissner-Nordstrom case. We observe that boundary deformation generally reduces the scrambling time delay, with the EMS coupling having a significant effect on the delay. These results provide further insight into the role of boundary deformations in modifying chaotic properties in charged hairy black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01680v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-025-14625-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. C (2025) 85:946</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hadyan Luthfan Prihadi, Donny Dwiputra, Fitria Khairunnisa, Freddy Permana Zen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black Hole Entropy, Quantum Corrections and EFT Transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02655</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02655v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We revisit and study quantum corrections to the supersymmetric entropy of BPS black holes in 4d $\mathcal{N}=2$ effective field theories (EFTs), which can be obtained from Type IIA string theory compactified on a Calabi-Yau threefold. Macroscopically, these corrections arise from an infinite series of higher-derivative F-terms that encode certain modifications to the two-derivative supergravity effective action. Within the large volume regime, we analyze in detail the moduli dependence of these semi-classical contributions and explore their implications for the black hole entropy. As a byproduct, we show that the entropy captures, in a rather intricate way, the transition between four- and five-dimensional dual EFT descriptions. In fact, the expansion parameter $\alpha$ controlling the relevant asymptotic series can be related to the ratio of the black hole horizon and the Kaluza-Klein scale, given here by the inverse D0-brane mass. Furthermore, we are able to resum the series into a well-behaved convergent expression for all values of $\alpha$. This demonstrates, in turn, that (stable) black holes can, indeed, probe scales besides the quantum gravity cutoff. More precisely, by examining two representative BPS systems -- the D0-D2-D4 and D2-D6 black hole solutions -- we explicitly illustrate how highly non-local (perturbative) quantum effects resolve the divergences, ultimately leading to a well-defined entropy function. Additionally, in certain cases, we show that one can take a suitable decompactification limit to 5d and verify that the corrected entropy function reproduces the exact microstate counting of the underlying five-dimensional black string. Our results also clarify the role of non-perturbative quantum corrections, which, remarkably, do not modify any of our prior conclusions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02655v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP08(2025)112</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 08 (2025) 112</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Castellano, Matteo Zatti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact Three-Point Functions in $\mathcal{N}=2$ Superconformal Field Theories: Integrability vs. Localization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07295v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose an integrability approach for planar three-point functions at finite coupling in $\mathcal{N}=2$ superconformal field theories obtained as $\mathbb{Z}_K$ orbifolds of $\mathcal{N}=4$ super Yang-Mills (SYM). Generalizing the hexagon formalism for $\mathcal{N}=4$ SYM, we reproduce the structure constants of Coulomb branch operators, previously obtained by supersymmetric localization, as exact functions of the 't Hooft coupling. Our analysis explains the common physical origin of Fredholm kernels in integrability and localization, and hints at structures after the resummation in the hexagon formalism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07295v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gwena\"el Ferrando, Shota Komatsu, Gabriel Lefundes, Didina Serban</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sparsity in the numerical six-point bootstrap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00124</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.00124v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The paper contributes to an ongoing effort to extend the conformal bootstrap beyond its traditional focus on systems of four-point correlation functions. Recently, it was demonstrated that semidefinite programming can be used to formulate a six-point generalisation of the numerical bootstrap, yielding qualitatively new, rigorous bounds on CFT data. However, the numerical six-point bootstrap requires solving SDPs involving infinite-dimensional matrices, which has so far limited its applicability and hindered scalability in early implementations. This work overcomes the challenges by using sparse matrix decompositions to exploit the banded structure of the underlying SDP. The result is a rewriting of one-dimensional six-point bootstrap problems as effectively two-dimensional standard mixed correlator four-point bootstrap computations. As application, novel bounds whose extremal correlators interpolate between the six-point functions of the generalised free fermion and boson are derived. The extremal interpolations are matched with perturbative deformations of the massive free boson in AdS$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.00124v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Harris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Five-loop Anomalous Dimensions of Cubic Scalar Theory from Operator Product Expansion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13620v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, an Operator Product Expansion method has been proposed for renormalization in quantum field theories. This method extracts UV divergences from two-point propagator-type integrals, and it is believed to be applicable to generic QFTs. In the present work, we apply the OPE method to the renormalization of scalar theory with cubic interactions in six-dimensions. We have successfully computed the 5-loop corrections to the anomalous dimensions of the $\phi^Q$ operator, as well as the large $N$ expansion of scaling dimensions at the Wilson-Fisher fixed point to $1/N^5$ order. This computation sets a new loop-order record for the anomalous dimension of the $\phi^Q$ operator in cubic scalar theory, and further demonstrates the efficiency and capacity of the OPE method in renormalization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13620v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rijun Huang, Qingjun Jin, Yi Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kac-Moody algebras from M5-giants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20663</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20663v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We examine the giant graviton expansions of the Higgs indices for the 3d $\mathcal{N}=4$ $U(N)$ ADHM theories with $l$ fundamental hypermultiplets. The indices for the M5-brane giant gravitons of wrapping number $m$ appearing in the expansions consist of the contributions that generalize the characters of the W-algebra $\mathcal{W}(\mathfrak{gl}(m))$ and those which realize the characters of the affine Kac-Moody algebras of type $A_{l-1}$. Also we confirm that the inverse giant graviton expansions of the resulting M5-brane indices consistently reproduce the Higgs indices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20663v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hirotaka Hayashi, Tomoki Nosaka, Tadashi Okazaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soft Theorems in Chern-Simons Matter Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02542</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02542v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: I will describe tree level soft theorems for Chern-Simons QED and QCD in 4+1 dimensions. Soft theorems have been studied in various context in the past. Recently, there has been renewed interest in these theorems due to their connection with asymptotic symmetries and gauge invariance. Chern-Simons theories are gauge invariant only up to a boundary term. Hence, they make for an interesting case to study the relationship between gauge invariance and soft theorems. The aim of this work is to include corrections due to the addition of Chern-Simons terms in the gauge field action. I will start with an overview of Chern-Simons theories in 4+1 dimensions. Then I will move on to a discussion on soft theorems in gauge invariant QFT at the sub-leading order using Sen's covariantisation procedure. Finally, I will calculate the correction due to the addition of a Chern-Simons term for both QED and QCD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02542v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Avi Wadhwa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adams spectral sequences for non-vector-bundle Thom spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.01678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.01678v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: When $R$ is one of the spectra $\mathit{ku}$, $\mathit{ko}$, $\mathit{tmf}$, $\mathit{MTSpin}^c$, $\mathit{MTSpin}$, or $\mathit{MTString}$, there is a standard approach to computing twisted $R$-homology groups of a space $X$ with the Adams spectral sequence, by using a change-of-rings isomorphism to simplify the $E_2$-page. This approach requires the assumption that the twist comes from a vector bundle, i.e. the twist map $X\to B\mathrm{GL}_1(R)$ factors through $B\mathrm{O}$. We show this assumption is unnecessary by working with Baker-Lazarev's Adams spectral sequence of $R$-modules and computing its $E_2$-page for a large class of twists of these spectra. We then work through two example computations motivated by anomaly cancellation for supergravity theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.01678v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arun Debray, Matthew Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Harmonic $1$-forms on real loci of Calabi-Yau manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19402v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We numerically study whether there exist nowhere vanishing harmonic $1$-forms on the real locus of some carefully constructed examples of Calabi-Yau manifolds, which would then give rise to potentially new examples of $G_2$-manifolds and an explicit description of their metrics. We do this in two steps: first, we use a neural network to compute an approximate Calabi-Yau metric on each manifold. Second, we use another neural network to compute an approximately harmonic $1$-form with respect to the approximate metric, and then inspect the found solution. On two manifolds existence of a nowhere vanishing harmonic $1$-form can be ruled out using differential geometry. The real locus of a third manifold is diffeomorphic to $S^1 \times S^2$, and our numerics suggest that when the Calabi-Yau metric is close to a singular limit, then it admits a nowhere vanishing harmonic $1$-form. We explain how such an approximate solution could potentially be used in a numerically verified proof for the fact that our example manifold must admit a nowhere vanishing harmonic $1$-form.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19402v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael R. Douglas, Daniel Platt, Yidi Qi, Rodrigo Barbosa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial Black Holes and Second-order Gravitational Waves in Axion-like Hybrid Inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00764v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the possibility that primordial black holes (PBHs) can be formed from large curvature perturbations generated during the waterfall phase transition in a hybrid inflation model driven by an axion-like particle (ALP) $\phi$. The model predicts a spectral index $n_s \simeq 0.964$ and a tensor-to-scalar ratio $r \simeq 0.003$, in agreement with Planck data and potentially testable by next generation cosmic microwave background (CMB) experiments such as CMB-S4 and LiteBIRD. We find that the PBH mass and the peak of the associated scalar-induced gravitational wave (SIGW) spectrum are correlated with the ALP mass. In particular, PBHs in the mass range $10^{-13}\, M_\odot$ can constitute either the entire dark matter (DM) content of the universe or a significant fraction of it. The predicted second-order GWs from this mechanism are within the sensitivity reach of future observatories like LISA and ET. The typical reheating temperature in the model is around $10^6 - 10^7$ GeV is consistent with Big Bang Nucleosynthesis (BBN) constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00764v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Waqas Ahmed, Anish Ghoshal, Umer Zubair</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear stability of charged warm holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03421v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Charged black holes are known to suffer from an interior instability associated with the presence of the Cauchy horizon. Recently, a hairy charged black hole was proposed that avoids the formation of a Cauchy horizon. It is natural to question whether this instability might manifest in the exterior solution. In this paper, we have analyzed the stability of this black hole. Our results show that vector perturbations are stable, along with the scalar sector for $l=0$. We have also computed the corresponding quasinormal modes (QNMs) and quasibound states (QBSs).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03421v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-025-14661-5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Gannouji, R., Guzm\'an Antonucci, A. Linear stability of charged warm holes. Eur. Phys. J. C 85, 941 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Radouane Gannouji, Alejandro Guzm\'an Antonucci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring gravitational impulse via quantum Boltzmann equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13678v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the gravitational impulse by using the generalized formulation of the quantum Boltzmann equation (QBE), wherein the initial states are taken as wave packets rather than plane waves. The QBE operates within an open quantum system framework. Using this approach, we can analyze the two-body gravitational scattering by considering one body as part of the environment and the other as the system. Through this procedure, we obtain the system's impulse up to the second order for two massive objects. Similarly, we apply the forward scattering of the QBE to the gravitational impulse of a photon due to a massive object, during which we consider the photon as the system and the massive object as the environment. In this methodology, we use the QBE to compute the time evolution of the momentum operator associated with the system. While the forward scattering term vanishes when considering point particles, we demonstrate its persistence when using wave packets to describe both massive particles and the photon field. The results reported here are entirely consistent with the previous approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13678v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/td49-w7pz</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Sharifian, Moslem Zarei, Nicola Bartolo, Sabino Matarrese</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Barrow and Tsallis entropies after the DESI DR2 BAO data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12205</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12205v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Modified cosmology based on Barrow entropy arises from the gravity-thermodynamics conjecture, in which the standard Bekenstein-Hawking entropy is replaced by the Barrow entropy of quantum-gravitational origin, characterized by the Barrow parameter $\Delta$. Interestingly, this framework exhibits similarities with cosmology based on Tsallis $\delta$-entropy, which, although rooted in a non-extensive generalization of Boltzmann-Gibbs statistics, features the same power-law deformation of the holographic scaling present in the Barrow case. We use observational data from Supernova Type Ia (SNIa), Cosmic Chronometers (CC), and Baryonic acoustic oscillations (BAO), including the recently released DESI DR2 data, in order to extract constraints on such scenarios. As we show, the best-fit value for the Barrow exponent $\Delta$ is found to be negative, while the zero value, which corresponds to $\Lambda$CDM paradigm, is allowed only in the range of $2\sigma $ for three out of four datasets. Additionally, for the case of the SN$_{0}$+OHD+BAO dataset, for the current Hubble function we obtain a value of $H_0= 72.2_{-0.9}^{+0.9}$, which may potentially alleviate the $H_0$ tension. Moreover, we compare our results with the Gaussian Process reconstruction of the dark-energy equation of state for the DESI + Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) + Union3 datasets. Finally, by applying information criteria such as the Akaike Information Criterion and the Bayes evidence, we compare the fitting efficiency of the scenario at hand with $\Lambda$CDM cosmology, showing that the latter is slightly favoured.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12205v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/09/013</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 09, 013 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Gaetano Luciano, Andronikos Paliathanasis, Emmanuel N. Saridakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Cosmology Without Singularities: A New Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02616v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The article is dedicated to a discussion regarding the role of Barrow's ''Zero Universes'' in quantum cosmology. In particular, we demonstrate that if quantum gravity effects are modeled by the quantum potential method associated with the ''many interacting universes'' (MIU) model, then the mere presence of the universes with a zero scale factor (the ``Zero universes'') produces a veritably remarkable outcome: the classical cosmological singularities of Big Bang, Big Crunch and Big Rip all fail to arise. In other words, those universes that are considered ill-posed at the classical level may turn out to be a necessary and sought-after ingredient in a future internally consistent quantum theory of gravity. Finally, we argue that the MIU quantization method might shed light on a number of other cosmological mysteries; for example, it might account for a decoherence which preceded the eternal inflation, and elucidate how the quantum superposition of vacuum decays occurring at different places might give birth to actual bubble universes there. In addition, the new method might help explain why our universe was born in an extremely low-entropy initial state required to trigger the initial inflation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02616v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valerian A. Yurov, Artyom V. Yurov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher symmetries and anomalies in quantum lattice systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.04719v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We define an 't Hooft anomaly index for a group acting on a 2d quantum lattice system by finite-depth circuits. It takes values in the degree-4 cohomology of the group and is an obstruction to on-siteability of the group action. We introduce a 3-group (modeled as a crossed square) describing higher symmetries of a 2d lattice system and show that the 2d anomaly index is an obstruction for promoting a symmetry action to a morphism of 3-groups. This demonstrates that 't Hooft anomalies are a consequence of a mixing between ordinary symmetries and higher symmetries. Similarly, to any 1d lattice system we attach a 2-group (modeled as a crossed module) and interpret the Nayak-Else anomaly index as an obstruction for promoting a group action to a morphism of 2-groups. The meaning of indices of Symmetry Protected Topological states is also illuminated by higher group symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.04719v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Kapustin, Shixiong Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identification of gapless phases by a twisting operator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02496v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a general necessary condition for a spin chain with SO(3) spin-rotation symmetry to be gapped. Specifically, we prove that the ground state(s) of an SO(3)-symmetric gapped spin chain must be spin singlet(s), and the expectation value of a twisting operator asymptotically approaches unity in the thermodynamic limit, where finite-size corrections are inversely proportional to the system size. This theorem provides (i) supporting evidence for various conjectured gapped phases, and (ii) a sufficient criterion for identifying gapless spin chains. We verify our theorem by numerical simulations for a variety of spin models and show that it offers a novel efficient way to identify gapless phases in spin chains with spin-rotation symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02496v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/29j7-ltfn</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Hang Su, Tengzhou Zhang, Yuan Yao, Akira Furusaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GW200208_222617 as an eccentric black-hole binary merger: properties and astrophysical implications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.17105v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Detecting orbital eccentricity in a stellar-mass black-hole merger would point to a non-isolated formation channel. Eccentric binaries can form in dense stellar environments such as globular clusters or active galactic nuclei, or from triple stellar systems in the Galactic field. However, confidently measuring eccentricity is challenging -- short signals from high-mass eccentric mergers can mimic spin-induced precession, making the two effects hard to disentangle. This degeneracy weakens considerably for longer-duration signals. Here, GW200208_222617 provides a rare opportunity. Originating from a relatively low-mass binary with source-frame chirp mass $\sim20$ M$_\odot$, its gravitational-wave signal spanned $\sim14$ orbital cycles in band, with no indication of data quality issues. Previous analyses for quasi-circular binaries found no evidence for spin precession and, multiple subsequent studies found the data to favour an eccentric merger despite notable technical differences. All in all, we believe GW200208_222617 is the black-hole merger event from GWTC-3 with the least ambiguous detection of eccentricity. We present a critical discussion of properties and astrophysical interpretation of GW200208_222617 as an eccentric black-hole merger using models of field triples, globular clusters, and active galactic nuclei. We find that if GW200208_222617 was indeed eccentric, its origin is consistent with a field triple or globular cluster. Formation in the inner regions of an active galactic nucleus is disfavoured. The outer regions of such a disk remain a viable origin for GW200208_222617; we demonstrate how future detections of eccentric mergers formed in such environments could be powerful tools for constraining the disk geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.17105v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Isobel Romero-Shaw, Jakob Stegmann, Hiromichi Tagawa, Davide Gerosa, Johan Samsing, Nihar Gupte, Stephen R. Green</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropy from scattering in weakly interacting systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19127v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Perturbation theory is used to investigate the evolution of the von Neumann entropy of a subsystem of a bipartite quantum system under the action of a unitary matrix, in the limit where that matrix is close to the unit matrix. The physical context for such process would be scattering with weak short-ranged interactions where the unitary matrix is the S matrix. We find surprisingly simple criteria for the initial state and the S matrix that guarantee that the subsystem entropy increases. The class of initial states that meet these criteria are more correlated than simple product states of the subsystems. They form a subclass of the set of all separable states, and they can therefore be assembled by classical processes alone.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19127v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Duncan MacIntyre, Gordon W. Semenoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topology of Fermi seas and geometry of their boundaries for free particles in one and two-dimensional lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00590v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Free gases of spinless fermions moving on a geometric background with lattice symmetries are considered. Their Fermi seas and corresponding boundaries may be classified according to their topological properties at zero temperature. This is accomplished by considering the flat orbifolds $R^{d}/\Gamma$, with $\Gamma$ being the crystallographic group of symmetry in $d$-dimensional momentum space. For $d=1$, there are 2 topological classes: a circumference, corresponding to an insulator and an interval, identified as a conductor. For $d=2$, the number of topological classes extends to 17: there are 8 with the topology of a disk identified as conductors and 4 corresponding to a 2-sphere matching insulators, both sets eventually including finite numbers of conical singularities and reflection corners at the boundaries. The rest of the listing includes single cases corresponding to insulators (2-torus, real projective plane, Klein bottle) and conductors (annulus, M\"obius strip). Physical interpretations of the singularities are provided, as well as examples that fit within this listing. Given the topological nature of this classification, its results are expected to be robust against small perturbative interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00590v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillermo R. Zemba</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
