<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th</link>
    <description>hep-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 01:47:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Notes on the double Wick rotated BTZ black hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10562v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We analyze the double Wick rotated BTZ black hole with the Euclidean signature, which is a Riemannian manifold. We calculate thermodynamics, total energy of spacetime, and holographic two point functions in the double Wick rotated background. Results agree with those of a rotating BTZ with the same periodicity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10562v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hua-Yu Dai, Xi-Hao Fang, Mitsutoshi Fujita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sakai-Sugimoto Model in an Off-Shell: Chiral Lagrangian to All Orders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10575v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Sakai-Sugimoto holographic model is famous for implementing the approximate chiral symmetry of QCD and reproducing the Chiral Lagrangian in a top-down approach. Off-shell holography is a formalism most suitable for derivation of boundary effective actions. In this manuscript, we revisit the original Sakai-Sugimoto model using the off-shell formalism. Thus derived effective action is very rich in physics: it contains an $U(N_f)$ multiplet of massless pseudoscalars interacting (via trilinear and higher terms) with towers of massive (axial-) vector mesons. In contrast to the previous studies, our effective action is non-local. The original Chiral Lagrangian is recovered as its local expansion in small $\pi$-meson momenta (derivative expansion). We particularly zoom in on the values of four derivative terms couplings, the low energy constants, and compare those with the ones reported in the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10575v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Lublinsky, Timofey Solomko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soft theorems and spontaneous symmetry breaking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10577v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The soft photon and soft graviton theorems of Weinberg are known to derive from conservation laws associated with asymptotic symmetries. Within the corresponding classical theories, one often speaks of spontaneous symmetry breaking and vacuum degeneracy, but a genuine quantum description of this phenomenon has largely been lacking. Here we establish spontaneous symmetry breaking of asymptotic symmetries and the existence of Goldstone `particles' using exclusively the language of quantum field theory. This is made possible through the reformulation of massless scattering theory in terms of carrollian conformal field theory, and the observation that soft theorems correspond to Ward identities of broken symmetries. A suitable version of Goldstone theorem shows that there must exist zero-momentum particles described by conformal fields on the celestial sphere. We discuss the relevance of these observations to the problem of infrared divergences that scattering amplitudes suffer from.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10577v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shreyansh Agrawal, Kevin Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black Hole Critical Collapse in Infinite Dimensions: Continuous Self-Similar Solutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10590v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the dynamics of black hole critical collapse in the limit of a large number of spacetime dimensions, $D$. In particular, we study the spherical gravitational collapse of a massless, scale-invariant scalar field with continuous self-similarity (CSS). The large number of dimensions provides a natural separation of scales, simplifying the equations of motion at each scale where different effects dominate. With this approximation scheme, we construct matched asymptotic solutions for this family, including the critical solution. We then compute the mass critical exponent of the black hole for linear perturbations that break CSS, finding that it asymptotes to a constant value in infinite dimensions. Additionally, we present a link between these solutions and closed Friedmann--Lema\^itre--Robertson--Walker (FLRW) cosmologies with a dimension-dependent equation of state and cosmological constant. The critical solution corresponds to an unstable Einstein-like universe, while subcritical and supercritical solutions correspond to bouncing and crunching cosmologies respectively. Our results provide a proof of concept for the large-$D$ expansion as a powerful analytic tool in gravitational collapse and suggest potential extensions to other self-similar systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10590v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Craig R. Clark, Guilherme L. Pimentel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On five-dimensional curvature squared supergravity and holography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10856v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we report the recent progress in obtaining new curvature-squared invariants in 5D, N=1 gauged minimal supergravity. We exhibit the structure of various composite multiplets that are pivotal in the construction. We also present the form of the gauged Riemann-squared and Gauss-Bonnet superinvariants in a dilaton-Weyl multiplet. As a first application of the new curvature squared invariants, we compute their corrections to holographic central charges and the Euclidean action of supersymmetric charged rotating black holes, exhibiting exact matching between the gravity and CFT results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10856v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gregory Gold, Peng-Ju Hu, Jessica Hutomo, Saurish Khandelwal, Mehmet Ozkan, Yi Pang, Gabriele Tartaglino-Mazzucchelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal thermodynamic topological classes of three-dimensional BTZ black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10858v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish a universal thermodynamic topological classification for three-dimensional static neutral Ba\~{n}ados-Teitelboim-Zanelli (BTZ), charged BTZ, and rotating BTZ black holes. We demonstrate that in all three cases (static neutral BTZ, charged BTZ, and rotating BTZ black holes), both the innermost small black hole states and the outermost large black hole states exhibit stable thermodynamic behavior. In the low-temperature limit, all three cases exhibit a thermodynamically stable small black hole state. Conversely, in the high-temperature limit, each system admits a thermodynamically stable large black hole state. Through this analysis, we have rigorously shown that static neutral, charged, and rotating BTZ black holes are consistently classified within the $W^{1+}$ category. Our results demonstrate that neither the charge parameter nor the rotation parameter exerts significant influence on the universal thermodynamic topological classification of three-dimensional static neutral BTZ black holes. This reveals a fundamental dichotomy: while angular momentum and electric charge dominate the thermodynamic topology of four-dimensional static black holes, their effects become negligible in the three-dimensional static BTZ case, highlighting a dimension-driven divergence in black hole thermodynamic behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10858v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ying Chen, Xiao-Dan Zhu, Di Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AdS3 axion wormholes as stable contributions to the Euclidean gravitational path integral</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10868</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10868v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent work has demonstrated that Euclidean Giddings-Strominger axion wormholes are stable in asymptotically flat 4D Minkowski spacetime, suggesting that they should, at least naively, be included as contributions in the quantum gravitational path integral. Such inclusion appears to lead to known wormhole paradoxes, such as the factorization problem. In this paper, we generalize these results to AdS3 spacetime, where the axion is equivalent to a U(1) gauge field. We explicitly construct the classical wormhole solutions, show their regularity and stability, and compute their actions for arbitrary ratios of the wormhole mouth radius to the AdS radius and across various topologies. Finally, We discuss potential implications of these findings for the 3D gravitational path integral.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10868v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Loveridge, Hao-Yu Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On deformations of AdS$_3$ solutions, supersymmetry and $G$-structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11207v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct new families of supersymmetric AdS$_3$ solutions in both massive and massless Type IIA supergravity via deformations to known backgrounds preserving $\mathcal{N} = (4,0)$ and $\mathcal{N} = (6,0)$ supersymmetry. These deformations are performed along internal isometries and lead to backgrounds with fully preserved or reduced supersymmetry. Using the formalism of $G$-structures, we systematically characterise the resulting geometries and track the evolution of their supersymmetric properties under the deformation. In particular, we identify transitions among SU(3), SU(2), and identity structures, and demonstrate the preservation of Killing spinors through explicit spinor bilinear constructions. Additionally, we investigate D-brane embeddings in the deformed geometries, uncovering stable and supersymmetric configurations supported by the new backgrounds. Our results offer new insights into the classification of AdS$_3$ flux vacua and provide a concrete framework for understanding their potential holographic duals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11207v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anayeli Ramirez, Salomon Zacarias</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large deformations of Tr($\Phi^3$) and the world at infinity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11253v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The amplitudes of the non-linear sigma model can be obtained from those of Tr($\Phi^3$) theory by sending the kinematic (Mandelstam) variables to infinity in a certain direction. In this paper we characterize the behavior of Tr($\Phi^3$) amplitudes under a general class of large kinematic shifts called $g$-vector shifts. The objects that live in this world at infinity retain certain key amplitude-like properties, most notably factorization, and admit descriptions in terms of polytopes, but they are not generally amplitudes of any cognizable theory. We identify particular $g$-vector shifts that lead at infinity to mixed amplitudes involving two pions and any number of scalars, allowing us to provide polytopal descriptions of these amplitudes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11253v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shruti Paranjape, Marcos Skowronek, Marcus Spradlin, Anastasia Volovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 2D Lorentz-violating fermionic Casimir effect under thermal conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11430v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the present work, we explore the dimensional projection method applied to a fermionic Lorentz invariance violation (LIV) theory with the CPT-even dimension-six extension. Due to the dimensional reduction of a fermionic system from $4D$ to $2D$, it is possible to study the influence of LIV on the Casimir effect under the MIT bag boundary condition model in a low-dimensional setting, where results are obtained without any approximations for a null-temperature system. Moreover, the Matsubara formalism is applied to derive closed expressions for the influence of temperature on the physical observables: Casimir energy, Casimir force, and entropy associated with the system in a LIV context. For each thermal observable, the influence of the LIV correction term is considered in the analysis of both low- and high-temperature regimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11430v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. E. L. de Farias, M. A. Anacleto, Iver Brevik, F. A. Brito, E. Passos, Amilcar Queiroz, Jo\~ao R. L. Santos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ghostly interactions in (1+1) dimensional classical field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11437</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11437v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the classical stability of two coupled scalar fields with opposite-sign kinetic terms evolving in 1+1 dimensional Minkowski spacetime. In the first part, we characterise unquenched ghostly interactions and present numerical solutions that support the following statements. First, the classical instability is not instantaneous and can even be benign, i.e., free of finite-time singularities. Second, while the classical instability can cascade towards higher frequency excitations, it is not driven by high frequency modes: At fixed amplitude, high-frequency modes are more stable than low-frequency modes. In the second part, we demonstrate that the classical instability can be quenched by mass terms. In particular, we exemplify that heavy high-frequency ghost fields seem to not violate the decoupling theorem and can be integrated out classically. In the third part, we demonstrate how self-interactions can quench the instability, for instance, by postponing its onset to parametrically large times. Extrapolating numerical results at large but finite evolution time to infinite evolution time, we demonstrate that classical fluctuations around trivial and nontrivial field-theory vacua are increasingly long-lived with (i) smaller initial amplitude of fluctuations, (ii) higher initial frequency of fluctuations, (iii) larger masses of the fields, or (iv) weaker interaction coupling. Moreover, our numerical simulations for field-theoretical generalisations of some globally-stable ghostly mechanical models do not feature any instability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11437v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\'edric Deffayet, Aaron Held, Shinji Mukohyama, Alexander Vikman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Independent connection in ACTion during inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10488v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Atacama Cosmology Telescope (ATC) has recently released new measurements and constraints on inflationary observables. In this paper it is shown that a component of a dynamical affine connection, which is independent of the metric, can easily drive inflation in agreement with these observations. Such geometrical explanation of inflation is analysed in detail here in the minimal model, including the predictions for the scalar spectral index $n_s$ and its running $\alpha_s$, the amplitude of the scalar perturbations and the tensor-to-scalar ratio $r$. Furthermore, this minimal model is shown to provide an inflationary attractor: arbitrary initial values of the kinetic energy density are dynamically attracted down to negligible values compared to the potential energy density in homogeneous and isotropic metrics. The role of the Higgs boson during and after inflation is also briefly discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10488v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Salvio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ray geodesics and wave propagation on the Beltrami surface: Optics of an optical wormhole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10518</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10518v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study investigates ray geodesics and wave propagation on the Beltrami surface, with a particular emphasis on the effective potentials governing photon dynamics. We derive the geodesic equations and analyze the Helmholtz equation within this curved geometry, revealing that the resulting potentials are purely repulsive. For ray trajectories, the potential is determined by wormhole parameters such as the throat radius ($\ell$), radial optical distance ($u$), scale parameter ($R$), and the angular momentum of the test field. Near the wormhole throat, the potential remains constant, preventing inward motion below a critical energy threshold, whereas at larger radial distances, it decays exponentially, allowing free propagation. In the context of wave propagation, the potential exhibits a centrifugal barrier along with a constant repulsive term at large $u$. The Beltrami surface, characterized by constant negative Gaussian curvature, serves as a model for graphene sheets and optical wormholes in condensed matter systems. These results allow us to determine the space- and frequency-dependent refractive index of the medium, providing a coherent framework for understanding photon behavior in such systems, with promising implications for material applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10518v1</guid>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Semra Gurtas Dogan, Abdullah Guvendi, Omar Mustafa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Effects of Generalized Entropy onto Bardeen Black Hole Surrounded by Cloud of Strings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10528v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work explores the thermodynamic characteristics and geothermodynamics of a Bardeen black hole (BH) that interacts with a string cloud and is minimally connected to nonlinear electrodynamics. To avoid the singularities throughout the cosmic evolution, we consider an entropy function which comprises five parameters. In addition, by employing this entropy function for the specific range of parameters, we obtain the representations of BH entropy based on the holographic principle. Moreover, we employ this entropy function to investigate its impact on the thermodynamics of the BH by studying various thermodynamic properties like mass, temperature, heat capacity, and Gibbs free energy for numerous scalar charge and string cloud values. To support our investigation, we use various geothermodynamics formalisms to evaluate the stable behavior and identify different physical scenarios. Furthermore, in this analysis, we observe that only one entropy formalism provides us with better results regarding the thermodynamic behavior of the BH. Moreover, it is shown that one of the entropy models provides a thermodynamic geometric behavior compared to the other entropy models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10528v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hamza Tariq, Usman Zafar, Shahid Chaudhary, Kazuharu Bamba, Abdul Jawad, Sanjar Shaymatov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Poincar\'{e} Stresses: A Modern Quantum Field Theory Take on Hydrogen's Electromagnetic Mass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10547v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We revisit the longstanding electromagnetic mass problem from a modern quantum field theory perspective. Focusing on a system of two widely separated hydrogen atoms, one in an excited $nS$ state and the other in the ground $1S$ state, we isolate the electromagnetic contribution to the electron's total linear momentum by comparing the full energy-momentum tensor with the predictions of a point-like bound state model. Our analysis reveals that the leading perturbative correction introduces a factor $4/3$, which, along with subsequent corrections, indicates that the effective electromagnetic mass deviates from the conventional relation $E/c^2$. This discrepancy is attributed to the intrinsic nonlocality of the electromagnetic field, rather than to additional compensating mechanisms such as Poincar\'e stresses. We further contrast our quantum field theory results with the highly accurate predictions of the Schr\"odinger equation, which, despite neglecting higher-order terms, achieves an average error on the order of $10^{-5}\%$. Attempts to improve this accuracy via perturbative inclusion of the self-interaction of the electron's wave function instead increase the error, prompting a re-examination of the underlying perturbative assumptions. Our findings suggest that a non-perturbative treatment of the tree-level action may be required to fully capture the dynamics of bound states in quantum field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10547v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qasem Exirifard, Alessio D'Errico, Ebrahim Karimi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher-Form Anomalies Imply Intrinsic Long-Range Entanglement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10569</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10569v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that generic gapped quantum many-body states which respect an anomalous finite higher-form symmetry have an exponentially small overlap with any short-range entangled (SRE) state. Hence, anomalies of higher-form symmetries enforce $intrinsic$ long-range entanglement, which is in contrast with anomalies of ordinary (0-form) symmetries which are compatible with symmetric SRE states (specifically, symmetric cat states). As an application, we show that the anomalies of strong higher-form symmetries provide a diagnostic for mixed-state topological order in $d \geq 2$ spatial dimensions. We also identify a new (3+1)D intrinsic mixed-state topological order that does not obey remote-detectability by local decoherence of the (3+1)D Toric Code with fermionic loop excitations. This breakdown of remote detectability, as encoded in anomalies of strong higher-form symmetries, provides a partial characterization of intrinsically mixed-state topological order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10569v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Po-Shen Hsin, Ryohei Kobayashi, Abhinav Prem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RVV$\times$V: Interference contributions to inclusive Higgs boson and Drell-Yan production at N$^4$LO in QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10574v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present partonic contributions to the inclusive gluon-fusion Higgs boson and Drell-Yan production cross sections at Hadron colliders at next-to-next-to-next-to-next-to leading order (N$^4$LO). Specifically, we compute contributions due to the interference of one-loop amplitudes with two-loop amplitudes with three QCD partons and the Higgs boson or a virtual photon. Our result is in the form of a Laurent expansion in the dimensional regulator $\epsilon$, the coefficients of which are analytic functions in the ratio of the Higgs boson or virtual photon mass to the partonic center of mass energy. Furthermore, we introduce and deploy a new package implemented in Mathematica, CIFAR ("Color Invariant Feynman Amplitude Reducer"), to express color factors in terms of general Casimir invariants of simple compact Lie algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10574v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bernhard Mistlberger, Adi Suresh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating lattice fermion doubling with a Floquet drive</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10601v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a recently discovered mathematical correspondence between the spectra of a naively discretized lattice fermion and that of a periodically driven (i.e., Floquet) quantum system and turn it into an infrared equivalence between the two systems. The equivalence can be framed as a duality relation, allowing us to simulate a two-flavor discrete-time fermion theory on the lattice side, where the two flavors arise from time discretization, using a single-flavor fermion theory on the Floquet side. Our demonstration establishes an equivalence between (i) the fermion content, (ii) the correlation functions, and consequently (iii) observables of the two theories in the infrared. We also show how interactions may be incorporated into this equivalence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10601v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ra\'ul A. Brice\~no, William Gyory, Thomas Iadecola, Srimoyee Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A glimpse into the magical world of quantum gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10638v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this essay it is proved that, in a self-consistent semiclassical theory of gravity, the asymptotically measured orbital periods of test particles around central compact objects are fundamentally bounded from below by the compact universal relation $T_{\infty}\geq{{2\pi e\hbar}\over{\sqrt{G}c^2 m^2_{e}}}$ [here $\{m_e,e\}$ are respectively the proper mass and the electric charge of the electron, the lightest charged particle]. The explicit dependence of the lower bound on the fundamental constants $\{G,c,\hbar\}$ of gravity, special relativity, and quantum theory suggests that it provides a rare glimpse into the yet unknown quantum theory of gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10638v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Journal of Modern Physics D 33, 2441005 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shahar Hod</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new perspective on modulus stabilization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10668v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the original Randall-Sundrum (RS) two-brane model, the radion potential was fine-tuned to zero, leaving the extra-dimensional modulus undetermined. Goldberger and Wise (GW) introduced a stabilization mechanism by incorporating a massive bulk scalar field, leading to a radion potential with a stable minimum. In this work, we examine the impact of the intrinsic stability of the GW scalar field on the modulus stabilization procedure. To elucidate this relationship, we test the stabilization scheme across several relevant scenarios using methods of singular perturbation theory. Our analysis consistently indicates a one-to-one correspondence between the stability of the GW scalar and successful modulus stabilization. Additionally, we highlight that certain classes of GW bulk potentials elevate the possibility of such a correspondence, and provide checks which any GW bulk potential must satisfy in order to ensure modulus stabilization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10668v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soham Bhattacharyya, Soumitra SenGupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytic semigroups approaching a Schr\"{o}dinger group on real foliated metric manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10718</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10718v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: On real metric manifolds admitting a co-dimension one foliation, sectorial operators are introduced that interpolate between the generalized Laplacian and the d'Alembertian. This is used to construct a one-parameter family of analytic semigroups that remains well-defined into the near Lorentzian regime. In the strict Lorentzian limit we identify a sense in which a well-defined Schr\"{o}dinger evolution group arises. For the analytic semigroups we show in addition that: (i) they act as integral operators with kernels that are jointly smooth in the semigroup time and both spacetime arguments. (ii) the diagonal of the kernels admits an asymptotic expansion in (shifted) powers of the semigroup time whose coefficients are the Seeley-DeWitt coefficients evaluated on the complex metrics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10718v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jfa.2025.110898</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Functional Analysis 289 (2025) 110898</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Rudrajit Banerjee, Max Niedermaier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Geometry of the Light Cone: Fock representation and Spectrum of Radiated Power</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10802v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Starting from the symplectic potential for the $\gamma$-Palatini--Holst action on a null hypersurface, we identify an auxiliary conformal field theory (CFT), which carries a representation of the constraint algebra of general relativity on a null surface. The radiative data, which is encoded into the shear of each null generator, is mapped into an $SU(1,1)$ current algebra on each light ray. We study the resulting quantum theory for both bosonic and fermionic representations. In the fermionic representation, the central charge on each null ray is positive, for bosons it is negative. A negative central charge implies a non-unitary CFT, which has negative norm states. In the model, there is a natural $SU(1,1)$ Casimir. For the bosonic representations, the $SU(1,1)$ Casimir can have either sign. For the fermionic representations, the $SU(1,1)$ Casimir is always greater or equal to zero. To exclude negative norm states, we restrict ourselves to the fermionic case. To understand the physical implications of this restriction, we express the $SU(1,1)$ Casimir in terms of the geometric data. In this way, the positivity bound on the $SU(1,1)$ Casimir translates into an upper bound for the shear of each null generator. In the model, this bound must be satisfied for all three-dimensional null hypersurfaces. This in turn suggests to apply it to an entire null foliation in an asymptotically flat spacetime. In this way, we obtain a bound on the radiated power of gravitational waves in the model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10802v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wolfgang Wieland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gapless Foliated-Exotic Duality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10835</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10835v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we construct a new foliated quantum field theory equivalent to the exotic $\phi$-theory -- a fractonic gapless scalar field theory described by tensor gauge fields and exhibiting $U(1) \times U(1)$ subsystem global symmetry. This subsystem symmetry has an 't Hooft anomaly, which is captured by a subsystem symmetry-protected topological (SSPT) phase in one dimension higher via the anomaly inflow mechanism. By analyzing both the anomaly inflow structure and the foliated-exotic duality in the SSPT phases, we establish the foliated-exotic duality in the $\phi$-theories. Furthermore, we also investigate the foliated-exotic duality in the $\hat\phi$-theory, which is dual to the $\phi$-theory, and construct the foliated $\hat\phi$-theory. These are the first examples of the foliated-exotic duality in gapless theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10835v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kantaro Ohmori, Shutaro Shimamura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Minimal RT Coupling and its Impact on Inflationary Evolution in f(R, T) Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10876v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We examine inflationary models in the $f(R, T)$ gravity framework where we have a conformal constant and an $RT$-mixing term apart from an R term. The RT-mixing term introduces non-minimal coupling between gravity and matter. We consider the exponential SUSY potential $V(\p)=M^4 \lt(1-e^{-\l \p/\mp}\rt)$ and a novel potential $V(\p)=\l \mp^{4-2\a} \p^{2\a} \sin^2\lt(\frac{\b \mp^\a}{\p^\a}\rt)$. With the help of COBE normalization, we constrain values of different parameters and extract the field value at the time of Hubble crossing. The end of inflation is marked by $\tep(\p_i)=1$ where $\p_i$ is the field value at the end of inflation. Equipped with these values, we then move on to calculate values of spectral index $n_s$ and tensor-to-scalar ratio $r$. Our predicted values of $n_s$ and $r$ fall within their observed values from the Planck 2018 survey and BICEP/Keck array measurement for both potential, making them plausible candidates for the inflationary model. We also display the variation of the tensor-to-scalar ratio and spectral index with the coefficient of RT-mixing term for fixed values of e-fold number. There, we find the existence of two local maxima of $n_s$, which occur at a negative and a positive value of $\x$, the coefficient of $RT$-mixing term. Our analysis finds a significant impact of $\x$ on values of observables</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10876v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sohan Kumar Jha, Anisur Rahaman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytical coordinate time at the second post-Newtonian order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11029</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11029v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We derive the analytical expression of the coordinate time $t$ in terms of the eccentric anomaly $u$ at the second post-Newtonian order in General Relativity for a compact binary system moving on eccentric orbits. The parametrization of $t$ with $u$ permits to reduce at the minimum the presence of discontinuous trigonometric functions. This is helpful as they must be properly connected via accumulation functions to finally have a smooth coordinate time $t(u)$. Another difficulty relies on the presence of an infinite sum, about which we derive a compact form. This effort reveals to be extremely useful for application purposes. Indeed, we need to truncate the aforementioned sum to a certain finite threshold, which strongly depends on the selected parameter values and the accuracy error we would like to achieve. Thanks to our work, this analysis can be easily carried out.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11029v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vittorio De Falco, Marco Gallo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hints for a Geon from Causal Dynamic Triangulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11047v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The existence of geons, physical states of self-bound gravitons, has long been proposed. In the context of four-dimensional causal dynamical triangulation simulations we investigate this possibility by measuring curvature-curvature correlators of different gravitational operators. We find a behavior consistent with a massive state, independent of the operators considered, over a certain distance window. While at most a hint, this is tantalizing due to its possible implications for dark matter or (primordial) black holes. We also find indications that the phase of rapid expansion of the obtained de Sitter universe impacts the mass, and relates to quantum fluctuations of space-time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11047v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Axel Maas, Simon Pl\"atzer, Felix Pressler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lorentzian homogeneous Ricci-flat metrics on almost abelian Lie groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11077</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11077v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study Lorentzian homogeneous metrics on almost abelian Lie groups of dimensions larger than three. An almost abelian Lie group is a Lie group whose Lie algebra has a codimension one abelian ideal. Ricci-flat and non-flat conditions on the Lie algebra are derived. In particular, we generalize the four-dimensional Petrov solution to arbitrarily higher dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11077v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuichiro Sato, Takanao Tsuyuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More fields are different: Stochastic view of multi-field inflationary scenario</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11158v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: High-energy physics often motivates multi-field inflationary scenarios where stochastic effects play a crucial role. Peculiar to multi-field models, the noise-induced centrifugal force results in a longer duration of inflation depending on the number of fields, even when the stochastic noises themselves are small. We show that, in such small-noise regimes, the number of fields generically discriminates whether inflation successfully terminates or lasts forever. Our results indicate that inflation with an extremely large number of fields may fail to realise our observable Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11158v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomo Takahashi, Koki Tokeshi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Quasi Periodic Oscillations Encode Traces of Black Hole Phase Transitions ?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11205</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11205v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Finding observational evidence or imprints of black hole phase transitions is a promising and active area of research. Aiming to contribute to this direction, in this work, we probe the well-known thermodynamic phase structure of the Reissner Nordstr\"om Anti de Sitter (RN-AdS) black hole through the lens of its quasi-periodic oscillations (QPOs). Can QPOs be influenced by black hole phase transitions? Do they carry any signature of such transitions in their observational patterns? These were the central questions guiding our study. By analyzing the upper and lower QPO frequencies within the Relativistic Precession (RP) model, we observe that the frequency-temperature relationship reflects distinguishing features corresponding to the small, intermediate, and large black hole phases, offering insights into their stability properties. The analysis is further extended to other QPO models, including the Warped Disk (WD) and Epicyclic Resonance (ER) models. The presence of distinct phase structures remains evident across all models which is an encouraging outcome that may be worth exploring further in the context of other black hole systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11205v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bidyut Hazarika, Prabwal Phukon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Lorentz Invariance Violation in Z Boson Mass Measurements at High-Energy Colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11248</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11248v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a minimal extension to the Standard Model by introducing a Lorentz Invariance Violation (LIV) term into the Z boson's dispersion relation, expressed as $p_\mu p^\mu = M_Z^2 + \delta_{LIV} (p_\mu n^\mu)^2$, where $\delta_{LIV}$ defines the violation scale and $n^\mu$ is a unit Lorentz vector specifying the direction. This modification alters the Z boson propagator and decay rate, impacting the Drell-Yan process cross-section at high-energy colliders. Observable effects are most pronounced near the resonance region at high rapidities ($|Y| &gt; 4$), potentially shifting the perceived Z boson mass and inducing sidereal-time modulations for spacelike and lightlike LIV due to Earth's rotation. We outline a targeted search strategy for ATLAS and CMS, achieving sensitivity to LIV signatures down to $|\delta_{LIV}| \approx 10^{-8}$ (or $10^{-9}$ optimistically), offering new insights into historical and future collider data. Our model predicts systematic shifts in weak boson masses at higher collision energies, relevant to past Tevatron and LHC discrepancies, though current data are now consistent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11248v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juansher Jejelava, Zurab Kepuladze</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$QQ$-systems and tropical geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11260v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the system of polynomial equations, known as $QQ$-systems, which are closely related to the so-called Bethe ansatz equations of the XXZ spin chain, using the methods of tropical geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11260v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rahul Singh, Anton M. Zeitlin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Symmetry to Supersymmetry to Supergravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11311v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The theoretical developments that led to supersymmetry, first global and then local, over roughly six years (1970-1976) arose from a convergence of physical insights and mathematical methods stemming from diverse, and sometimes independent, research directions. This contribution aims to illustrate the interplay of ideas, methods, and motivations that informed the entire process and concludes with a reflection on the scientific modality of these developments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11311v1</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elena Castellani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Second Law of Black Holes Thermodynamics in Non-Quasi-Static Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11314v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Bekenstein-Hawking entropy satisfies the generalized second law of black hole thermodynamics for arbitrary thermodynamic evolution within Einstein-Maxwell theory. In contrast, the black hole entropy that satisfies the second law in low-energy effective modified gravity theories related to quantum gravity is derived solely by considering linear perturbations within quasi-static processes. Since astrophysical processes are typically non-quasi-static, deriving a rigorous expression for entropy within the quasi-static framework is not feasible. By treating the effective quantum corrections as first-order perturbations, the black hole entropy in Einstein-Maxwell gravity with generalized quadratic corrections for arbitrary dynamical processes is derived. This entropy is distinct from the Iyer-Wald and Dong-Wald entropies and is applicable to non-quasi-static processes. Furthermore, it is shown that the black hole entropy is consistent with the generalized covariant entropy boundary. This work establishes a framework for examining the generalized second law of black hole thermodynamics in non-static processes within modified gravity theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11314v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin-Yang Wang, Jie Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$27 \otimes 27$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11362v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the decomposition into $SU(N)$ irreducible representations (irreps) of the tensor product $27 \otimes 27$, where $27$ is the highest-dimensional $SU(N)$ irrep present in a two-gluon system, and explicitly construct all Hermitian projectors on these irreps, as well as transition operators between them. This yields an explicit basis of the complete $27\otimes 27$ color space (defined as the space of $27\otimes 27\to 27 \otimes 27$ color maps) in terms of orthogonal multiplets. This study shows that even complex color structures can be addressed, with the help of the birdtrack pictorial technique, using only elementary tools. In particular, we highlight the usefulness of the quadratic Casimir operator, whose eigenspaces allow efficient filtering of all projectors and transition operators, and of the permutation operators that further improve this filtering. The product $27\otimes 27$ also has an interesting feature: three equivalent irreps $27$ appear in the decomposition, two of which are symmetric and can therefore be distinguished neither by the quadratic Casimir operator nor by their symmetry under permutation. In this case, it is convenient to use Clebsch-Gordan coefficients to derive the two associated, symmetric projectors. The latter are not uniquely determined (only their sum is), and we give the set of all solutions. Finally, we explicitly derive the soft anomalous dimension matrix associated with $27\otimes 27\to 27\otimes 27$, whose block-diagonal main structure is easy to understand, but whose detailed spectrum properties remain intriguing. The approach presented for $27 \otimes 27 \to 27 \otimes 27$ could in principle be applied to any product of $SU(N)$ irreps, and eventually automated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11362v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Florian Cougoulic, St\'ephane Peign\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational waves in massive Horndeski theory with a cosmological constant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11378v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study gravitational waves in a de-Sitter background in linearized Horndeski theory. This background can be obtained in different ways in this theory. We first consider an arbitrary potential to implement an effective cosmological constant. The scalar field has long range whereas its potential can induce a mass term, rendering its range to short distances. A second effect of the potential is the possibility to induce a background curvature or an effective cosmological constant via the minimum of the potential. The latter is usually ignored in the literature to have an asymptotically flat background for the gravitational waves. In order to fill this gap, we consider the effects of the scalar potential in the framework of gravitational waves in the theories having such scalar couplings, and compare its effects with other approaches such as the presence of a vacuum energy density filling the spacetime or a linear potential which leads to an effective cosmological constant but now with a massless scalar field. We discuss properties of the gravitational waves, their propagation and interaction with the medium in which they propagate. The minimum of the scalar potential term mimics a cosmological constant and leads to separate redshifts in the effective frequency and wave number, which also discriminates the tensorial and massive scalar waves. We see that, depending on the implementation to have a cosmological constant, the propagation speeds and polarization properties of scalar modes of these waves is different, as summarized in the paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11378v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hatice \"Ozer, \"Ozg\"ur Delice</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SymTFT construction of gapless exotic-foliated dual models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11449</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11449v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct Symmetry Topological Field Theories (SymTFTs) for continuous subsystem symmetries, which are inherently non-Lorentz-invariant. Our framework produces dual bulk descriptions -- gapped foliated and exotic SymTFTs -- that generates gapless boundary theories with spontaneous subsystem symmetry breaking via interval compactification. In analogy with the sandwich construction of SymTFT, we call this Mille-feuille. This is done by specifying gapped and symmetry-breaking boundary conditions. In this way we obtain the foliated dual realizations of various models, including the XY plaquette, XYZ cube, and $\phi$, $\hat{\phi}$ theories. This also captures self-duality symmetries as condensation defects and provides a systematic method for generating free theories that non-linearly realize subsystem symmetries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11449v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabio Apruzzi, Francesco Bedogna, Salvo Mancani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A relativistic non-perturbative local model of fractons and its non-local perturbative hidden sector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.08663</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.08663v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct, from first principles, a covariant local model for scalar fractonic matter coupled to a symmetric tensor gauge field. The free gauge field action is just the one of the Blasi-Maggiore model. The scalar sector, describing fracton charges, is a non-trivial covariant generalization of Pretko's quartic model. Because the model has no quadratic term in the scalar field, a direct perturbative treatment fails. Remarkably, by performing a suitable change of variables, we demonstrate that the action can be driven to a perturbative effective action. However, at the price of carrying non-local interacting terms. We study the perturbative regime of the model first by analyzing the classical field equations and some possible simple solutions, which are in accordance with the expected immobile behavior of fractons. We also derive the fracton dispersion relation and, by playing with the parameters of the model, show that there are at least six distinct phases: one with two massive fractonic modes, one of them being tachyonic; one with massless states associated with a long-range attractive potential; a mixed phase with one massive and one massless state; another one where physical states of the scalar field cannot occur at all in the physical spectrum; a massive phase with states of two different masses; and second phase where the scalar field cannot be associated with physical particles, in spite of its mass being real. Moreover, we find evidence that fractonic bound states emerge in the model for some of these phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.08663v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rodrigo F. Sobreiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational back-reaction is magical</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07056</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07056v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the interplay between magic and entanglement in quantum many-body systems. We show that non-local magic, which is supported by the quantum correlations is lower bounded by the non-flatness of entanglement spectrum and upper bounded by the amount of entanglement in the system. We then argue that a smoothed version of non-local magic bounds the hardness of classical simulations for incompressible states. In conformal field theories, we conjecture that the non-local magic should scale linearly with entanglement entropy but sublinearly when an approximation of the state is allowed. We support the conjectures using both analytical arguments based on unitary distillation and numerical data from an Ising CFT. If the CFT has a holographic dual, then we prove that the non-local magic vanishes if and only if there is no gravitational back-reaction. Furthermore, we show that non-local magic is approximately equal to the rate of change of the minimal surface area in response to the change of cosmic brane tension in the bulk.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07056v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>ChunJun Cao, Gong Cheng, Alioscia Hamma, Lorenzo Leone, William Munizzi, Savatore F. E. Oliviero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark energy due to quantum corrections to effective potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18818v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we calculate quantum corrections to the effective potential in different models of inflationary cosmology. We show that quantum corrections lead to a modification of the initial potential uplifting its value at the minimum, which can be interpreted as a cosmological constant/dark energy. We concentrate on the models of $\alpha$-attractors and show that one can naturally get small values of the cosmological constant. In the model of quintessence, the same mechanism modifies the value of dark energy at the present time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18818v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. A. Filippov, R. M. Iakhibbaev, D. I. Kazakov, D. M. Tolkachev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conic Sections on the Sky: Shadows of Linearly Superrotated Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20181v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Soft hairs are an intrinsic infrared feature of a black hole, which may also affect near-horizon physics. In this work, we study some of the subtleties surrounding one of the primary observables with which we can study their effects in the context of Einstein's gravity: the black hole shadow. First, we clarify the singular pathology associated with black holes with soft hairs and demonstrate that the metrics of linearly superrotated black holes are free of near-zone pathologies due to appropriate asymptotic falloff conditions being imposed on the event horizon. We then analytically construct the photon orbits around such black holes, derive the shadow equation for near-zone observers, and find that the linear superrotation hairs deform the circular shadow of a bald Schwarzchild black hole into an ellipse. This is in sharp contrast to their supertranslated counterparts, which only shift the position of the center of the circular shadow but do not change its shape. Our results suggest a richness to the observable effects due to the infrared structures of Einstein's gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20181v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.024054</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 111, 024054 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Feng-Li Lin, Avani Patel, Jason Payne</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative AI for Brane Configurations and Coamoeba</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16033v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a generative AI model to obtain Type IIB brane configurations that realize toric phases of a family of 4d N=1 supersymmetric gauge theories. These 4d N=1 quiver gauge theories are worldvolume theories of a D3-brane probing a toric Calabi-Yau 3-fold. The Type IIB brane configurations are given by the coamoeba projection of the mirror curve associated with the toric Calabi-Yau 3-fold. The shape of the mirror curve and its coamoeba projection, as well as the corresponding Type IIB brane configuration and the toric phase of the 4d N=1 theory, all depend on the complex structure moduli parameterizing the mirror curve. We train a generative AI model, a conditional variational autoencoder (CVAE), that takes a choice of complex structure moduli as input and generates the corresponding coamoeba. This enables us not only to obtain a high-resolution representation of the entire phase space for a family of 4d N=1 theories corresponding to the same toric Calabi-Yau 3-fold, but also to continuously track the movements of the mirror curve and the branes wrapping the curve in the corresponding Type IIB brane configurations during phase transitions associated with Seiberg duality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16033v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.086013</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 111, 086013 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Rak-Kyeong Seong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-Corrected Holographic Wilson Loop Expectation Values and Super-Yang-Mills Confinement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11107</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11107v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Confinement is a well-known phenomenon in the infrared regime of (supersymmetric) Yang-Mills theory. While both experimental observations and numerical simulations have robustly confirmed its existence, the underlying physical mechanism remains elusive. Unraveling the theoretical origin of confinement continues to be a profound and longstanding challenge in both physics and mathematics. Motivated by recent advances in quantum Jackiw-Teitelboim gravity, we investigate the Wilson loop expectation values in the large-$N$ limit of $\mathscr{N}=4$ super-Yang-Mills theory at finite chemical potential, employing a holographic approach within the background of an extremal AdS$_5$ Reissner-Nordstr\"om black brane. Our results reveal that quantum gravitational fluctuations in the near-horizon region significantly modify the holographic Wilson loop expectation values. These values exhibit an area-law behavior, indicative of a confining quark-antiquark potential. Within this framework, our findings suggest that confinement in the super-Yang-Mills theory arises as a consequence of near-horizon quantum gravity fluctuations in the bulk extremal AdS$_5$ black brane geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11107v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-Long Liu, Cong-Yuan Yue, Jun Nian, Wenni Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brickwall One-Loop Determinant: Spectral Statistics &amp; Krylov Complexity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12301v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate quantum chaotic features of the brickwall model, which is obtained by introducing a stretched horizon - a Dirichlet wall placed outside the event horizon - within the BTZ geometry. This simple yet effective model has been shown to capture key properties of quantum black holes and is motivated by the stringy fuzzball proposal. We analyze the dynamics of both scalar and fermionic probe fields, deriving their normal mode spectra with Gaussian-distributed boundary conditions on the stretched horizon. By interpreting these normal modes as energy eigenvalues, we examine spectral statistics, including level spacing distributions, the spectral form factor, and Krylov state complexity as diagnostics for quantum chaos. Our results show that the brickwall model exhibits features consistent with random matrix theory across various ensembles as the standard deviation of the Gaussian distribution is varied. Specifically, we observe Wigner-Dyson distributions, a linear ramp in the spectral form factor, and a characteristic peak in Krylov complexity, all without the need for a classical interior geometry. We also demonstrate that non-vanishing spectral rigidity alone is sufficient to produce a peak in Krylov complexity, without requiring Wigner-Dyson level repulsion. Finally, we identify signatures of integrability at extreme values of the Dirichlet boundary condition parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12301v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hyun-Sik Jeong, Arnab Kundu, Juan F. Pedraza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Background subtraction method is not only much simpler, but also as applicable as covariant counterterm method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08214v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: As the criterion for the applicability of the background subtraction method, not only the finiteness condition of the resulting Hamiltonian but also the condition for the validity of the first law of black hole thermodynamics can be reduced to the form amenable to much simpler analysis at infinity by using the covariant phase space formalism. With this, we further establish that the background subtraction method is as applicable as the covariant counterterm method not only to Einstein's gravity, but also to its higher derivative corrections for black hole thermodynamics in both asymptotically flat and AdS spacetimes. In addition, our framework also provides us with the first derivation of the universal expression of the Gibbs free energy in terms of the Euclidean on-shell action beyond Einstein's gravity. Among others, our findings have a far reaching impact on the shift in methodology for the Euclidean approach to black hole thermodynamics, where the well justified background subtraction method by our wieldy criterion is supposed to be the favored choice compared to the covariant counterterm method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08214v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Guo, Xiyao Guo, Xin Lan, Hongbao Zhang, Wei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unitary Categorical Symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04440v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Global invertible symmetries act unitarily on local observables or states of a quantum system. In this note, we aim to generalise this statement to non-invertible symmetries by considering unitary actions of higher fusion category symmetries $\mathcal{C}$ on twisted sector local operators. We propose that the latter transform in $\ast$-representations of the tube algebra associated to $\mathcal{C}$, which we introduce and classify using the notion of higher $S$-matrices of higher braided fusion categories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04440v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Bartsch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Axion Stabilization in Modular Cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14904v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The $SL(2,\mathbb{Z})$ invariant $\alpha$-attractor models have plateau potentials with respect to the inflaton and axion fields. The potential in the axion direction is almost exactly flat during inflation, hence, the axion field remains nearly massless. In this paper, we develop a generalized class of such models, where the $SL(2,\mathbb{Z})$ symmetry is preserved, but the axion acquires a large mass and becomes strongly stabilized during inflation, which eliminates isocurvature perturbations in this scenario. Inflation in such two-field models occurs as in the single-field $\alpha$-attractors and leads to the same cosmological predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14904v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John Joseph Carrasco, Renata Kallosh, Andrei Linde, Diederik Roest</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards the Double Copy Formulation for the Abelian Sector of Heterotic Double Field Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23425v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It has been shown that double field theory (DFT) action can be constructed in a perturbative manner up to cubic order by using double copy of Yang-Mills. This construction can also be extended by starting with higher-derivative Yang-Mills theory to obtain higher-derivative DFT action. In this work, I try to use this classical double copy formulation for Abelian subsector of heterotic DFT, starting with a Yang-Mills theory including a charged scalar field, namely (Y M + \phi^3) theory. Although the methods I used do not give an exact match, they give some promising results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23425v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rasim Y{\i}lmaz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On an approach to canonicalizing elliptic Feynman integrals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23720v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a systematic approach to systematically constructing canonical bases for univariate elliptic Feynman integrals with multiple kinematic scales, which frequently arise in phenomenologically relevant scattering processes. The construction is performed in the Legendre normal form of elliptic curves, where the geometric properties of the curves are simple and explicit, and further kinematic singularities are present as marked points. The simplicity of the normal form facilitates the construction of universal canonical bases with an arbitrary number of marked points, which can be mapped to generic univariate elliptic integral families via an appropriate M\"obius transformation. Therefore, our result can be readily applied to these cases straightforwardly. As a demonstration, we discuss the application of our method to several concrete examples, where we show that the $\varepsilon$-factorization of sub-sector dependence can also be simply done.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23720v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaqi Chen, Li Lin Yang, Yiyang Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$K$-theoretic computation of the Atiyah(-Patodi)-Singer index of lattice Dirac operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23921v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that the Wilson Dirac operator in lattice gauge theory can be identified as a mathematical object in $K$-theory and that its associated spectral flow is equal to the index. In comparison to the standard lattice Dirac operator index, our formulation does not require the Ginsparg-Wilson relation and has broader applicability to systems with boundaries and to the mod-two version of the indices in general dimensions. We numerically verify that the $K$ and $KO$ group formulas reproduce the known index theorems in continuum theory. We examine the Atiyah-Singer index on a flat two-dimensional torus and, for the first time, demonstrate that the Atiyah-Patodi-Singer index with nontrivial curved boundaries, as well as the mod-two versions, can be computed on a lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23921v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shoto Aoki, Hidenori Fukaya, Mikio Furuta, Shinichiroh Matsuo, Tetsuya Onogi, Satoshi Yamaguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantization of Lie-Poisson algebra and Lie algebra solutions of mass-deformed type IIB matrix model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24060v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A quantization of Lie-Poisson algebras is studied. Classical solutions of the mass-deformed IKKT matrix model can be constructed from semisimple Lie algebras whose dimension matches the number of matrices in the model. We consider the geometry described by the classical solutions of the Lie algebras in the limit where the mass vanishes and the matrix size tends to infinity. Lie-Poisson varieties are regarded as such geometric objects.We provide a quantization called ``weak matrix regularization''of Lie-Poisson algebras (linear Poisson algebras) on the algebraic varieties defined by their Casimir polynomials. Casimir polynomials correspond with Casimir operators of the Lie algebra by the quantization. This quantization is a generalization of the method for constructing the fuzzy sphere. In order to define the weak matrix regularization of the quotient space by the ideal generated by the Casimir polynomials, we take a fixed reduced Gr\"obner basis of the ideal. The Gr\"obner basis determines remainders of polynomials. The operation of replacing this remainders with representation matrices of a Lie algebra roughly corresponds to a weak matrix regularization. As concrete examples, we construct weak matrix regularization for $\mathfrak{su}(2)$ and $\mathfrak{su}(3)$. In the case of $\mathfrak{su}(3)$, we not only construct weak matrix regularization for the quadratic Casimir polynomial, but also construct weak matrix regularization for the cubic Casimir polynomial.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24060v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jumpei Gohara, Akifumi Sako</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>False and genuine decoherence in the early universe: a local observer and time-averaged observables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10472v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study quantum decoherence of curvature perturbations at superhorizon scales caused by the gravitational nonlinearities. We show that cubic gravitational couplings, constrained by the spatial diffeomorphism invariance, lead to infrared (IR) and ultraviolet (UV) divergences in the decoherence rate at one loop. These divergences arise from fluctuations of deep IR modes which look like a background mode for a local observer and violent zero-point fluctuations in the deep UV, respectively. We argue that these divergences are unobservable, as they vanish when considering proper observables. We consider correlators defined using the geodesic distance for IR divergences and time-averaged correlators for UV divergences. To account for these observer's perspectives, we propose to consider an effective quantum state, defined in terms of actual observables, as a more appropriate probe of the quantum coherence of the system measured by an observer. We then evaluate the finite decoherence rate induced by superhorizon environment during inflation and at late universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10472v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fumiya Sano, Junsei Tokuda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic complexity and the Hubble tension: a quantum gravity portrayal for the large scale structure of the cosmos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.05267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.05267v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this letter, we propose a relationship between the so-called Hubble-Lema\^{i}tre constant $H_{0}$ and holographic complexity related to the emergence of spacetime in quantum gravity. Such a result can represent an important step to understanding the Hubble tension by introducing a quantum gravity perspective for cosmological observations: regarding the degree of quantum complexity we measure around us.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.05267v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The renormalized stress-energy tensor for scalar fields in the Boulware state with applications to extremal black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04528v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We provide a mode-sum prescription to directly compute the renormalized stress-energy tensor (RSET) for scalar fields in the Boulware vacuum. The method generalizes the recently developed extended coordinate method which was previously only applicable to Hartle-Hawking states. We exhibit the accuracy and efficiency of the method by calculating the RSET in sub-extremal and extremal Reissner-Nordstr\"om spacetimes. We find numerical evidence for the regularity of the RSET at the extremal horizon regardless of the field mass and its coupling. We employ our numerical results of the RSET to source the semi-classical Einstein equations, demonstrating that if the RSET is considered as a static perturbation, it will either de-extremalize the black hole, or convert it into a horizonless object.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04528v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.085009</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Julio Arrechea, Cormac Breen, Adrian Ottewill, Lorenzo Pisani, Peter Taylor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Procedure g5anchor to Anchor $\gamma_5$ in Feynman Diagrams for the Standard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08099v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a procedure g5anchor to anchor $\gamma_5$ in the definition of a Dirac trace with $\gamma_5$ in Dimensional Regularization (DR) in Feynman diagrams for the Standard Model, based on a recent revision of the works by Kreimer, Gottlieb and Donohue. For each closed fermion chain with an odd number of primitive (i.e.~not-yet-clearly-defined) $\gamma_5$ in a given Feynman diagram, g5anchor returns a definite set of anchor points for $\gamma_5$, in terms of pairs of ordered fermion propagators; at each of these $\gamma_5$ anchor points a fixed expression in terms of the Levi-Civita tensor and elementary Dirac matrices will be inserted together with a sign determined by anticommutatively shifting all $\gamma_5$ from their original places (dictated by the Feynman rules) to this anchor point. The defining expressions for the cyclic $\gamma_5$-odd Dirac traces in DR associated with closed fermion chains in amplitudes, or more generally squared amplitudes, thus follow from this procedure, where the Levi-Civita tensors are not necessarily treated strictly in 4-dimensions. We propose utilizing this definition in practical perturbative calculations in the Standard Model at least to two-loop orders with the current implementation. Certain limitations and modifications of the KKS and/or the Kreimer scheme are addressed, as well as the possible caveats with g5anchor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08099v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Long Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singularity resolution in spherically reduced 2D semiclassical gravity with negative central charge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10523v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We analyze the semiclassical Schwarzschild geometry in the Boulware quantum state in the framework of two-dimensional (2D) dilaton gravity. The classical model is defined by the spherical reduction of Einstein's gravity sourced with conformal scalar fields. The expectation value of the stress-energy tensor in the Boulware state is singular at the classical horizon of the Schwarzschild spacetime, but when backreaction effects are considered, previous results have shown that the 2D geometry is horizonless and described by a non-symmetric wormhole with a curvature singularity on the other side of the throat. In this work we show that reversing the sign of the central charge of the conformal matter removes the curvature singularity of the 2D backreacted geometry, which happens to be horizonless and asymptotically flat. This result is consistent with a similar analysis recently performed for the CGHS model. We also argue the physical significance of negative central charges in conformal anomalies from a four-dimensional perspective.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10523v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.045025</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 111, 045025 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Adri\'an del R\'io, F. Javier Mara\~n\'on-Gonz\'alez, Jos\'e Navarro-Salas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravity from (A)dS Yang-Mills: a natural reduction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17574v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the relationship between a one-parameter family of (anti)-de Sitter Yang-Mills models and Einstein-Palatini gravity with matter, realized through In\"o\"nu-Wigner contraction of the (A)dS algebra. By setting the gauge group parameter $\alpha$ to zero, the gauge transformation of the potential becomes consistent with the transformation properties of the tetrad form and spin connection. We show that a sector of the Yang-Mills dynamics exists where the gauge fields acquire a geometric interpretation, and the full Yang-Mills symmetry gives rise to diffeomorphisms and local Lorentz transformations. Finally, the corresponding dynamics is consistent with unimodular gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17574v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Goffredo Chirco, Alfonso Lamberti, Lucio Vacchiano, Patrizia Vitale</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum integrable model for the quantum cohomology/K-theory of flag varieties and the double $\beta$-Grothendieck polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03768</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.03768v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A GL$(n)$ quantum integrable system generalizing the asymmetric five vertex spin chain is shown to encode the ring relations of the equivariant quantum cohomology and equivariant quantum K-theory ring of flag varieties. We also show that the Bethe ansatz states of this system generate the double $\beta$-Grothendieck polynomials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.03768v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jirui Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The sinusoidal valley: a recipe for high peaks in the scalar and induced tensor spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12015</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12015v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Adding a sine-type interaction to inflationary models with two fields can evoke a classical trajectory with many turns in field space. Under conditions we discuss, the enhancement of the spectrum of adiabatic fluctuations resulting from each turn adds up. A special range of scales away from the CMB-constrained region can then be enhanced by several orders of magnitude, allowing for interesting phenomenological possibilities, such as induced gravitational waves or primordial black holes. A localized version of this interaction can also be used as an add-on to conventional inflationary models, thus allowing the injection of the large peak in their power spectra. The intuition and the conclusions drawn from this simple model remain relevant for more complicated applications that usually include extra terms that obscure the simplicity of the mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12015v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aris Katsis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Preference for evolving dark energy in light of the galaxy bispectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04602v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We analyse pre-DESI clustering data using a dark energy equation of state $w(z)$ parametrised by $(w_0, w_a)$, finding a $2.8-3.9\sigma$ preference for evolving dark energy over the cosmological constant $\Lambda$ when combined with cosmic microwave background data from Planck and supernova data from Pantheon+, Union3, or DESY5. Our constraints, consistent with DESI Y1 results, are derived from the power spectrum and bispectrum of SDSS/BOSS galaxies using the Effective Field Theory of Large Scale Structure (EFTofLSS) at one loop. The evidence remains robust across analysis variations but disappears without the one-loop bispectrum. When combining DESI baryon acoustic oscillations with BOSS full-shape data, while marginalising over the sound horizon in the latter to prevent unaccounted correlations, the significance increases to $3.7-4.4\sigma$, depending on the supernova dataset. Using a data-driven reconstruction of $w(z)$, we show that the evidence arises from deviations from $\Lambda$ at multiple redshifts. In addition, our findings are interpreted within the Effective Field Theory of Dark Energy (EFTofDE), from which we explicitly track the non-standard time evolution in EFTofLSS predictions. For perturbatively stable theories in the $w &lt; -1$ regime, the evidence persists in the clustering limit $(c_s^2 \rightarrow 0)$ when higher-derivative corrections are present, as well as in the quasi-static limit $(c_s^2 \rightarrow 1)$ when additional EFTofDE parameters are considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04602v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyu Lu, Th\'eo Simon, Pierre Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Axial perturbations of black holes with primary scalar hair</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.22348v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study axial perturbations of static black holes with primary hair in a family of degenerate higher-order scalar-tensor (DHOST) theories. These solutions possess a scalar charge, fully independent of the mass, leading to a continuous one-parameter deformation of the standard Schwarzschild black hole. Starting from these solutions, we also construct new black holes, solutions of other DHOST theories, obtained via disformal transformations of the metric. In particular, we investigate two specific types of disformal transformations: the first leading to a theory where gravitational waves propagate at the speed of light, the second to a Horndeski theory, where the equations of motion remain second order. The dynamics of axial perturbations can be formally related to the general relativistic equations of motion of axial perturbations in an effective metric. The causal structure of the effective metric differs from that of the background metric, leading to distinct gravitational and luminous horizons. Using a WKB approximation, we compute the quasi-normal modes for the Schr\"odinger-like equation associated with the effective metric outside the gravitational horizon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.22348v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christos Charmousis, Simon Iteanu, David Langlois, Karim Noui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rigorous results for timelike Liouville field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02348v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Liouville field theory has long been a cornerstone of two-dimensional quantum field theory and quantum gravity, which has attracted much recent attention in the mathematics literature. Timelike Liouville field theory is a version of Liouville field theory where the kinetic term in the action appears with a negative sign, which makes it closer to a theory of quantum gravity than ordinary (spacelike) Liouville field theory. Making sense of this "wrong sign" requires a theory of Gaussian random variables with negative variance. Such a theory is developed in this paper, and is used to prove the timelike DOZZ formula for the $3$-point correlation function when the parameters satisfy the so-called "charge neutrality condition". Expressions are derived also for the $k$-point correlation functions for all $k\ge 3$, and it is shown that these functions approach the correct semiclassical limits as the coupling constant is sent to zero.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02348v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sourav Chatterjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Notes on color reductions and $\gamma$ traces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.05853v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present efficient algorithms to calculate the color factors for the $SU(N)$ gauge group and to evaluate $\gamma$ traces. The aim of these notes is to give a self-contained, proved account of the basic results with particular emphasis on color reductions. We fine tune existing algorithms to make calculations at high loop orders possible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.05853v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oliver Schnetz</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
