<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th</link>
    <description>hep-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 02:47:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Quadratic Curvature Correction to the Euclidean Action of Rotating AdS Black Holes in General Dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10184v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We adopt the improved Reall-Santos method to obtain the leading-order perturbative correction of the quadratic curvature invariants to the on-shell Euclidean action of rotating anti-de Sitter (AdS) black holes in general $D$ dimensions. The corresponding Gibbs free energy is a function of thermodynamic variables, temperature and angular velocities, which are unperturbed in this approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10184v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Si-Yue Lu, H. Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal Killing Tensors, Noether Currents and Higher-Spin Shift Symmetries in (A)dS Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10188v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For certain mass values, shift symmetries appear among massive higher spin fields propagating on (anti-) de Sitter spacetime. On the one hand, Noether's theorem assigns a set of conserved currents for each shift symmetric field, one current for each of the independent shift symmetries. On the other hand, each shift symmetric field comes with a higher-rank conserved field strength that can be contracted with a conformal Killing tensor (CKT) to form another set of conserved currents, one for each independent CKT. This second set is naively much larger than the first. We conjecture, and prove in the first few cases, that these two sets are the same once we account for the redundancy due to trivial currents that is implicit in Noether's theorem. For each field, only one branch of the CKTs is non-trivial. As we range over all the mass values and spins of the shift symmetric fields, each kind of CKT gets used exactly once in a non-trivial current.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10188v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kurt Hinterbichler, Samanta Saha, Thomas Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disturbing news about the $d=2+\epsilon$ expansion II. Assessing the recombination scenario</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10194v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In [De Cesare, Rychkov (2025)], we revisited the $d=2+\epsilon$ expansion in the $O(N)$ Non-Linear Sigma Model (NLSM), emphasizing the existence of a protected operator which is a closed form with $N-1$ indices. The scaling dimension of this operator stays exactly equal to $N-1$, independently of $\epsilon$. Its existence is problematic for the identification of the NLSM fixed point in $d=2+\epsilon$ with the Wilson-Fisher fixed point family obtained by analytically continuing from near $d=4$, which does not possess such a protected operator. Multiplet recombination is one scenario discussed in [De Cesare, Rychkov (2025)], which could allow to connect the two families continuously (although not analytically). In this scenario, the protected dimension is lifted at some critical value of $\epsilon$, thanks to the short conformal multiplet of scaling dimension $N-1$ eating a long conformal multiplet of higher scaling dimension. In this followup work, we assess this scenario for the cases $N=3$ and $N=4$. We identify the lowest candidates for the long multiplet which could be eaten, and compute their one-loop anomalous dimensions. We find that at one loop, scaling dimensions of these candidates grow with $\epsilon$, while it should decrease down to $N$ for the recombination to occur. We conclude that multiplet recombination is unlikely.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10194v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabiana De Cesare, Slava Rychkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bootstrapping ABJM theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10196v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Supersymmetric localization reduces the computation of protected observables in ABJM theory to finite-dimensional matrix integrals. Building on the techniques introduced in arXiv:2512.02119, we develop a bootstrap framework for the systematic calculation of instanton corrections to the free energy and to supersymmetric Wilson loops. Exploiting exact functional relations and consistency conditions satisfied by grand-canonical observables, in the Fermi-gas formulation of the ABJM matrix model, we provide analytic derivations of several relations for the free energy that were previously known only conjecturally, either from refined topological string theory or from high-precision numerical studies. We apply the same framework to determine the nonperturbative corrections to $1/2$ and $1/6$ BPS Wilson loops, elucidating their qualitative differences and uncovering novel structural features of the instanton effects. These results further highlight the intricate nonperturbative structure and network of dualities underlying ABJM theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10196v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bercel Boldis, Gregory P. Korchemsky, Alessandro Testa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Excited String States and D-branes from Infinite Width Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10214v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore recent proposal to represent worldsheet string path integrals by integrating over parameters of a wide random-feature neural network whose output is identified with the embedding field $X^\mu$. In this paper we extend it focusing on scattering with excited states insertions and for worldsheets with boundaries introducing fixed-feature Gaussian normal-ordering prescription for derivative composites (removing the neural contact term at finite width), and propose realization of mixed Neumann/Dirichlet boundary conditions interpreted as a neural D$p$-brane. As concrete outputs, we derive the sphere four-point integrand with a single $(1,1)$ insertion and the disk four-tachyon amplitude on a D$p$-brane, recovering the expected derivative prefactors, boundary exponents, and momentum-conservation limits after renormalization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10214v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dmitry S. Ageev, Yulia A. Ageeva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic metals at finite volume</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10460v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct the electron star solution in asymptotically global AdS spacetime, and investigate its stability properties, both locally under perturbations and globally with respect to the Reissner-Nordstr\"om black hole and thermal AdS metrics. We interpret the resulting phase diagram as that of a holographic metal confined to a finite volume. We identify a quantum critical point at finite chemical potential, around which the different phases are organized.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10460v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Acito, Nicolas Grandi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving integration-by-parts and differential equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10651</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10651v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this talk, we discuss how ideas from geometry help to improve Feynman integral reduction and the construction of $\varepsilon$-factorised differential equations. In particular, we outline a systematic procedure to obtain an $\varepsilon$-factorised differential equation for any Feynman integral.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10651v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Iris Bree, Federico Gasparotto, Antonela Matija\v{s}i\'c, Pouria Mazloumi, Dmytro Melnichenko, Sebastian P\"ogel, Toni Teschke, Xing Wang, Stefan Weinzierl, Konglong Wu, Xiaofeng Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A QFT information protocol for charged black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10733</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10733v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A generalization for the quantum information retrieval protocol recently illustrated by Verlinde and van der Heijden for evaporating black holes is provided to inclusions of type III von Neumann factors. The physical interest of such scenario arises in Quantum Field Theory, where local algebras are type III von Neumann algebras. The formula obtained can be easily interpreted in terms of the statistical dimension of superselection sectors in the case of black holes undergoing charge evaporation, thanks to the index-statistics theorem, leading to a thermodynamic interpretation. A constraint on the values of the index leads to a final remark about the quantization of the charge emitted by the black hole during the evaporation process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10733v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Palumbo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $\sigma_-$ Cohomology Analysis for Coxeter HS $B_2$ model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10788v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The dynamical content of equations resulting from rank-two covariant derivatives in $B_2$ Coxeter theory in $AdS_4$ are analyzed in terms of $\sigma_-$-complexes. Primary fields and gauge-invariant differential operators on primary fields are classified for $(adj \otimes adj)$ one-form fields $\omega$ and $(tw\otimes adj)$ zero-form fields $C$. It is shown that one-forms $\omega$ in the $(adj \otimes adj)$ sector encode symmetric massless fields and partially massless fields of all spins and depth of masslessness. Gluing of the one-form module to the zero-form modules at the linear vertices is studied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10788v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. A. Tarusov, K. A. Ushakov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classical strings and the double copy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10907v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The double copy is by now a well-established relationship between scattering amplitudes and classical solutions in gauge and gravity (field) theories, and is itself inspired by amplitude relations in string theory. In this paper, we generalise the classical double copy to the motion of strings, taking as a case study the motion of an open string in a background abelian gauge field. We argue that the double copy of this situation is a closed string moving in a spacetime background arising as the double copy of the gauge theory background. The gauge theory background we consider is that of a constant electric field, which has a critical value beyond which the open string motion is pathological. We find no counterpart of this behaviour in the double copy, and interpret this result. We then examine how the closed string nevertheless still knows about the single copy gauge theory. Our results pave the way for more systematic study of the double copy in a classical string context, thus going beyond the KLT relations for amplitudes in flat space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10907v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riccardo Morieri, Igor Pesando, Michael L. Reichenberg Ashby, Chris D. White</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sigma model approach to string theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10977v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A review of the $\sigma$-model approach to derivation of effective string equations of motion for the massless fields is presented. We limit our consideration to the case of the tree approximation in the closed bosonic string theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10977v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Int. J. Mod. Phys. A 4 (1989) 1257-1318</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Arkady A. Tseytlin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlators in the theory of Integral Discriminants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10981v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Integral discriminants provide a simple and fundamental model for non-Gaussian integrals, associated with homogeneous polynomials of degree r in n variables. We argue that, in this context, the study of correlators is equally if not more important. In this paper, we study a natural class of correlators in this model -- the invariant correlators. We suggest a general method to compute invariant correlators using differential operators that act on the partition function. This method allows to compute general invariant correlators in terms of the fundamental invariants. Moreover, in some cases the correlators appear to be simply polynomials in the invariants. This could be an interesting manifestation of superintegrability phenomenon in the theory of integral discriminants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10981v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Morozov, Sh. Shakirov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement Entropy of Yukawa-Coupled Fields Across a Rindler Horizon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11038v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We compute the entanglement entropy across a Rindler horizon in scalar field theory with Yukawa interaction. Starting from a microscopic scalar-mediator theory in flat spacetime, we integrate out the massive mediator to obtain a quadratic but nonlocal effective kernel that determines the ground-state wavefunctional. The reduced density matrix for a single Rindler wedge is constructed explicitly by tracing over the complementary wedge, allowing the entanglement entropy to be evaluated directly from the kernel without replica or geometric methods. Exploiting translational invariance parallel to the horizon, the problem decomposes into independent transverse momentum sectors that reduce effectively to one-dimensional nonlocal systems and can be diagonalized analytically in the weak-coupling regime. The interaction-induced entropy obeys an area law, with leading corrections controlled by the Yukawa screening mass and logarithmically sensitive to the transverse ultraviolet cutoff, reflecting the localization of correlations near the horizon. Although the modular Hamiltonian depends on the Rindler acceleration, the entanglement spectrum and entropy are independent of this choice, demonstrating the observer-independent nature of vacuum entanglement. Our framework provides a direct and microscopically transparent approach to computing interaction-induced corrections to horizon entanglement using nonlocal effective kernels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11038v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akshay Kulkarni, Rahul Nigam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical isotropy of the universe and the look-elsewhere effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10178</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10178v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently, Jones et al. [arXiv:2310.12859] claimed strong evidence for the statistical anisotropy of the universe. The claim is based on a joint analysis of four different anomaly tests of the cosmic microwave background data, each of which is known to be anomalous, with a lower level of significance. They reported a combined $p$-value of about $3\times 10^{-8}$, which is more than a $5\sigma$ level of significance. We observe that statistical anisotropy is not even relevant for two of the four considered tests, which seems sufficient to invalidate the authors' claim. Furthermore, even if one reinterprets the claim as evidence against $\Lambda$CDM rather than statistical anisotropy, we argue that this result significantly suffers from the look-elsewhere effect. Assuming a set of independent (i.e., uncorrelated) tests, we show that if the four tests with the smallest $p$-values are cherry-picked from 10 independent tests, the $p$-value reported by Jones et al. corresponds to only $3\sigma$ significance. If there are 27 independent tests, the significance falls to $2\sigma$. These numbers, however, overstate our argument, since the four tests used by Jones et al. are slightly correlated. Determining the correlation of Jones et al.'s tests by comparing their joint $p$-value with the product of the four separate $p$-values, we find that about 16 or 50 tests are sufficient to reduce the significance of Jones et al.'s results to 3$\sigma$ or 2$\sigma$ significance, respectively. We also provide a list of anomaly tests discussed in the literature (and propose a few generalizations), suggesting that very plausibly 16 (or even 50) independent tests have been published, and possibly many more have been considered but not published. We conclude that the current data is consistent with the $\Lambda$CDM model and, in particular, with statistical isotropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10178v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alan H. Guth, Mohammad Hossein Namjoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Kramers-Wannier Self-Duality in Hopf-Ising Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10183v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Kramers-Wannier transformation of the 1+1d transverse-field Ising model exchanges the paramagnetic and ferromagnetic phases and, at criticality, manifests as a non-invertible symmetry. Extending such self-duality symmetries beyond gauging of abelian groups in tensor-product Hilbert spaces has, however, remained challenging. In this work, we construct a generalized 1+1d Ising model based on a finite-dimensional semisimple Hopf algebra $H$ that enjoys an anomaly-free non-invertible symmetry $\mathrm{Rep}(H)$. We provide an intuitive diagrammatic formulation of both the Hamiltonian and the symmetry operators using a non-(co)commutative generalization of ZX-calculus built from Hopf-algebraic data. When $H$ is self-dual, we further construct a generalized Kramers-Wannier duality operator that exchanges the paramagnetic and ferromagnetic phases and becomes a non-invertible symmetry at the self-dual point. This enlarged symmetry mixes with lattice translation and, in the infrared, flows to a weakly integral fusion category given by a $\mathbb{Z}_2$ extension of $\mathrm{Rep}(H)$. Specializing to the Kac-Paljutkin algebra $H_8$, the smallest self-dual Hopf algebra beyond abelian group algebras, we numerically study the phase diagram and identify four of the six $\mathrm{Rep}(H_8)$-symmetric gapped phases, separated by Ising critical lines and meeting at a multicritical point. We also realize all six $\mathrm{Rep}(H_8)$-symmetric gapped phases on the lattice via the $H$-comodule algebra formalism, in agreement with the module-category classification of $\mathrm{Rep}(H_8)$. Our results provide a unified Hopf-algebraic framework for non-invertible symmetries, dualities, and the tensor product lattice models that realize them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10183v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Da-Chuan Lu, Arkya Chatterjee, Nathanan Tantivasadakarn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical spacetime crystals in continuous dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10185</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10185v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We numerically construct a one-parameter family of critical spacetimes in arbitrary continuous dimensions D&gt;3. This generalizes Choptuik's D=4 solution to spherically symmetric massless scalar-field collapse at the threshold of D-dimensional Schwarzschild-Tangherlini black hole formation. We refer to these solutions, which share the discrete self-similarity of their four-dimensional counterpart, as critical spacetime crystals. Our main results are the echoing period and Choptuik exponent of the crystals as continuous functions of D, with detailed data for the interval 3.05&lt;D&lt;5.5. Notably, the echoing period has a maximum near D=3.76. As a by-product, we recover the echoing periods and Choptuik exponents in D=4 (5): Delta=3.445453 (3.22176) and gamma=0.373961 (0.41322). We support these numerical results with analytical expansions in 1/D and D-3. They suggest that both the echoing period and Choptuik exponent vanish as D approaches 3 from above. This paves the way for a small-(D-3) expansion, paralleling the large-$D$ expansion of general relativity. We also extend our results to two-dimensional dilaton gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10185v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Ecker, Florian Ecker, Daniel Grumiller, Tobias Jechtl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Versor: A Geometric Sequence Architecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10195v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A novel sequence architecture design is introduced, Versor, which uses Conformal Geometric Algebra (CGA) in place of the traditional fundamental non-linear operations to achieve structural generalization and significant performance improvements on a variety of tasks, while offering improved interpretability and efficiency. By embedding states in the $Cl_{4,1}$ manifold and evolving them via geometric transformations (rotors), Versor natively represents $SE(3)$-equivariant relationships without requiring explicit structural encoding. Versor is validated on chaotic N-body dynamics, topological reasoning, and standard multimodal benchmarks (CIFAR-10, WikiText-103), consistently outperforming Transformers, Graph Networks, and geometric baselines (GATr, EGNN). Key results include: orders of magnitude fewer parameters ($200\times$ vs. Transformers); interpretable attention decomposing into proximity and orientational components; zero-shot scale generalization (99.3% MCC on topology vs. 50.4% for ViT); and $O(L)$ linear complexity via the novel Recursive Rotor Accumulator. In out-of-distribution tests, Versor maintains stable predictions while Transformers fail catastrophically. Custom Clifford kernels achieve up to $78\times$ speedup, providing a scalable foundation for geometrically-aware scientific modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10195v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Truong Minh Huy, Edward Hirst</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological Expansion Induces Interference Between Communication and Entanglement Harvesting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10203v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the interplay between genuine entanglement harvesting and communication mediated correlations for local particle detectors in expanding cosmological spacetimes. Focusing on a conformally coupled scalar field in de Sitter spacetime, we analyze how spacetime expansion induces interference between these two sources of entanglement when the detectors are in causal contact. We compare two physically distinct detector models: detectors whose spatial profile expands with the Universe, and detectors whose proper size remains fixed despite cosmological expansion. We find that the lack of time-reversal symmetry in cosmological settings generically leads to constructive or destructive interference between communication mediated correlations and harvested field correlations, dramatically affecting the entanglement that detectors can acquire. In particular, rapid expansion can suppress entanglement entirely for expanding detectors through destructive interference, even when both communication and field correlations are individually large, whereas detectors that maintain a fixed proper size remain capable of acquiring significant entanglement. Our results show that cosmological expansion qualitatively reshapes the balance between communication and harvesting, and that the detector internal cohesion (whether it expands with the Universe or not) plays a crucial role in determining whether detectors' entanglement can survive in rapidly expanding universes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10203v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matheus H. Zambianco, Adam Teixid\'o-Bonfill, Eduardo Mart\'in-Mart\'inez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Network Quantum Field Theory from Transformer Architectures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10209v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a neural-network construction of Euclidean scalar quantum field theories from transformer attention heads, defining $n$-point correlators by averaging over random network parameters in the NN-QFT framework. For a single attention head, shared random softmax weights couple different width coordinates and induce non-Gaussian field statistics that persist in the infinite-width limit $d_k\to\infty$. We compute the two-point function in an attention-weight representation and show how Euclidean-invariant kernels can be engineered via random-feature token embeddings. We then analyze the connected four-point function and identify an "independence-breaking" contribution, expressible as a covariance over query-key weights, which remains finite at infinite width. Finally, we show that summing many independent heads with standard $1/N_h$ normalization suppresses connected non-Gaussian correlators as $1/N_h$, yielding a Gaussian NN-QFT in the large-head limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10209v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dmitry S. Ageev, Yulia A. Ageeva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerated expansion of the universe purely driven by scalar field fluctuations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10223v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that scalar field fluctuations alone can drive cosmic acceleration, provided the universe is spatially closed and the Compton wavelength of the field exceeds the radius of curvature. This mechanism may open new perspectives on inflation and dark energy, which could arise from a gas of sufficiently light bosons in a closed universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10223v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Jim\'enez-Aguilar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological production of dark matter in the Universe and in the laboratory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10331v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This thesis investigates cosmological particle production within Quantum Field Theory in Curved Spacetimes, both as a dark matter mechanism and through analog simulations using Bose-Einstein condensates. While a full theory of Quantum Gravity remains elusive, studying quantum fields on curved backgrounds provides essential insights into the early Universe. We focus on how dynamical spacetimes, particularly during inflation, generate particles from spectator fields influenced solely by geometry.
  The work is divided into four parts. Part I establishes the theoretical framework, covering cosmology, inflation, and the principles of analog gravity. Part II analyzes particle production in various inflationary models, showing that scalar and vector fields can account for observed dark matter abundance, especially through tachyonic instabilities. Part III explores BEC experiments, mapping phonons to scalar fields in expanding universes. We demonstrate the reconstruction of expansion histories, reinterpret production as a scattering problem, and propose methods to measure entanglement between produced pairs. Finally, Part IV addresses quantum vacuum ambiguities and the impact of non-adiabatic transitions during the "switch-on" and "switch-off" of expansion.
  Ultimately, this work highlights the viability of cosmological particle production for dark matter and the power of analog experiments to enhance our understanding of quantum effects in curved spacetimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10331v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\'Alvaro Parra-L\'opez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Brownian motion with non-Gaussian noises: Fluctuation-Dissipation Relation and nonlinear Langevin equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10421v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Building upon the work of Hu, Paz, and Zhang [1,2] on open quantum systems we consider the quantum Brownian motion (QBM) model with one oscillator (position variable $x$) as the system, {\it nonlinearly} coupled to an environment of $N$ harmonic oscillators (with mass $m_n$, natural frequency $\omega_n$, position $q_n$ and momentum $p_n$ variables) in the form $\sum_{n}\left(v_{n1}(x)q_{n}^{k}+v_{n2}(x)p_{n}^{l}\right)$ where $k, l$ are integers (the present work only considers the $k=l=2$ cases). The vertex functions $v_{n1}, v_{n2} $ are of the form $v_{n1}=\lambda C_{n1} f(x), v_{n2}(x)=-\lambda\,C_{n2}m_{n}^{-2}\omega_{n}^{-2}f(x)$ where $C_{n1,2}$ are the coupling constants with the $n$th oscillator, $f(x)$ is any arbitrary function of $x$, and $\lambda$ is a dimensionless constant. Employing the closed-time-path formalism the influence action $S_{IF}$ is calculated using a perturbative expansion in $\lambda$. It is possible to identify the terms in $S_{IF}$ quadratic or higher in $\Delta(s)\equiv f(x_{+}(s))-f(x_{-}(s))$ to constitute the noise kernel, while terms linear in $\Delta$ to that of the dissipation kernel. The non-Gaussian noise kernel gives rise to non-zero three-point correlation function of the corresponding stochastic force. The pathway presented here should be useful for the exploration of \textit{non-Gaussian properties of systems nonlinearly coupled with their environments}; examples in early universe cosmology and in quantum optomechanics (QOM) are mentioned. A modified fluctuation-dissipation relation (FDR) is also established, which ensures the consistency of the model and the accuracy of results even at higher perturbative orders. Another result of significance is the derivation of a nonlinear Langevin equation which is expected to be useful for many open quantum system applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10421v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hing-Tong Cho, Bei-Lok Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric properties of slowly rotating black holes embedded in matter environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10579v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Astrophysical black holes are embedded in surrounding dark and baryonic matter that can measurably perturb the spacetime. We construct a self-consistent spacetime describing a slowly rotating black hole embedded in an external matter distribution, modeling the surrounding dark matter halo as an anisotropic fluid. Working within the slow-rotation approximation, we capture leading-order spin and frame-dragging effects while retaining analytic transparency. We show that the presence and rotation of the halo induce distinct deviations from the vacuum black hole geometry, modifying inertial frame dragging, equatorial circular geodesics, the light ring, the innermost stable circular orbit, and radial and vertical epicyclic frequencies. These effects produce systematic shifts in orbital constants of motion and the locations of epicyclic resonances. In particular, the epicyclic frequency ratios develop nonmonotonic behavior, such as local minima. We further demonstrate that these features depend on the angular velocity of the surrounding fluid, reflecting the interplay between environmental gravity and frame dragging. Our results demonstrate that environmental and rotational effects can leave observable imprints on precision strong-field probes, particularly extreme mass-ratio inspirals, where small corrections accumulate over many orbital cycles. This work provides a minimal and extensible framework for incorporating realistic astrophysical environments into strong-field tests of gravity with future space-based gravitational-wave detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10579v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sayak Datta, Chiranjeeb Singha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three-loop helicity amplitudes of four-lepton scattering in QED</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10807v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the analytic expressions of the three-loop virtual corrections to the helicity amplitudes of 2 -&gt; 2 four-fermion scattering processes in massless QED. The contributing Feynman diagrams are grouped into integrand families characterised by independent Symanzik polynomials and decomposed in terms of master integrals using an optimised integration-by-parts strategy. Upon the renormalisation of the ultraviolet divergences and the extraction of the universal infrared pole structure, the finite results are expressed in terms of generalised polylogarithms up to transcendental weight six. Amplitudes for dimuon production in electron-positron annihilations, electron-muon scattering, and Bhabha scattering are explicitly derived.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10807v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giulio Crisanti, Thomas Dave, Pierpaolo Mastrolia, Jonathan Ronca, Sid Smith, William J. Torres Bobadilla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vacuum polarization in the Schwarzschild black hole with a global monopole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10899v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate vacuum polarization on the event horizon of a Schwarzschild black hole carrying a global monopole. For a massless scalar field $\Psi$ in the Hartle-Hawking state and with arbitrary curvature coupling, we compute the renormalized vacuum expectation value $\langle \Psi^2 \rangle_{\textrm{ren}}$. The monopole produces a solid-angle deficit and makes the spacetime non-Ricci-flat. Working perturbatively in the monopole parameter $\eta$ and retaining terms through $O(\eta^2)$, we find that $\langle \Psi^2 \rangle_{\textrm{ren}}$ on the horizon splits into two contributions: a genuinely monopole-induced term evaluated at the horizon and the usual Schwarzschild result - with the event horizon radius modified by the presence of $\eta$. Our result parallels earlier analyses for Schwarzschild black holes pierced by a cosmic string.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10899v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonardo G. Barbosa, Victor H. M. Ramos, Jo\~ao Paulo M. Pitelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dirac mode localization in QCD near the crossover temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10921v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the localization properties of the low-lying Dirac eigenmodes in QCD near the crossover temperature, using staggered fermions on the lattice. We find that localized low modes, absent at low temperature, appear at a temperature $T_{\mathrm{loc}}$ in the range $155\,\mathrm{MeV}\le T_{\mathrm{loc}}\le 158\,\mathrm{MeV}$, in excellent agreement with the pseudocritical crossover temperature as determined from the chiral condensate and from the light-quark susceptibility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10921v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Giordano, Tamas G. Kovacs, Ferenc Pittler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian inference for tidal heating with extreme mass ratio inspirals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11039</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11039v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Extreme mass ratio inspirals (EMRIs) provide unique probes of near-horizon dissipation through the tidal heating. We present a full Bayesian analysis of tidal heating in equatorial eccentric EMRIs by performing injection-recovery studies and inferring posterior constraints on the reflectivity parameter $|\mathcal{R}|^2$ while sampling in the full EMRI parameter space. We find that in the strong-field regime the posterior uncertainties are smaller, indicating a stronger constraining capability on the tidal heating. Using two-year signals with an optimal signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) of $\rho=50$, EMRIs can put bounds on $|\mathcal{R}|^2$ at the level of $10^{-3}$--$ 10^{-4}$ for a rapidly spinning central object. Moreover, we show that neglecting the tidal heating can induce clear systematic biases in the intrinsic parameters of the EMRI system. These results establish EMRIs as promising precision probes for detecting and constraining black hole event horizons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11039v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhong-Wu Xia, Sheng Long, Qiyuan Pan, Jiliang Jing, Wei-Liang Qian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New constraints on cosmic anisotropy from galaxy clusters using an improved dipole fitting method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11093v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we attempted to apply the dipole fitting (DF) method to galaxy clusters to search for cosmic anisotropic signals, and to construct a statistical isotropic analysis scheme for them. Compared to Type Ia supernova (SNe Ia), the galaxy clusters offer a significant advantage in terms of spatial distribution. This advantage makes the anisotropic signals obtained from them more reliable. From 313 galaxy clusters (Chandra + XMM-Newton), we find two preferred directions (l, b) = (${257.82^{\circ}}_{-52.88}^{+58.01}$, $-31.30{^{\circ}}_{-39.46}^{+35.92}$) and ($80.89{^{\circ}}_{-52.46}^{+60.97}$, $31.75{^{\circ}}_{-40.16}^{+35.19}$). The former to a direction where the universe is expanding at a faster rate than the surrounding area, while the latter to a slower rate of expansion. The corresponding magnitude of anisotropy is $|A|$ = 5.2 $\sim$ 5.4 $\times$ 10$^{-4}$. The results of statistical isotropy analyses give $\sim$1.0$\sigma$ confidence level. From the reanalyses based on the subsamples including Chandra, XMM-Newton, low reshift (LR, $z &lt; 0.10$), high redshift (HR, $z &gt; 0.10$) datasets, we find that the observation equipment and sample redshift can affect the preferred direction, anisotropic magnitude, and statistical significance of anisotropy. The XMM-Newton dataset gives a statistical significance of 2.26$\sigma$ (Mock) and 2.86$\sigma$ (Iso) which are much higher than that from Chandra and the total datasets. The magnitude of anisotropy $|A|$ from HR dataset is larger than that from LR dataset. Overall, our results indicate the presence of anisotropic signals in galaxy clusters, which must be taken seriously. Further test is still needed to better understand these signals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11093v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianping Hu, Chao Geng, Xuandong Jia, Zhaoyu Zuo, Taozhi Yang, Fayin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cryptographic Censorship</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.03425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.03425v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We formulate and take two large strides towards proving a quantum version of the weak cosmic censorship conjecture. We first prove "Cryptographic Censorship": a theorem showing that when the time evolution operator of a holographic CFT is approximately pseudorandom (or Haar random) on some code subspace, then there must be an event horizon in the corresponding bulk dual. This result provides a general condition that guarantees (in finite time) event horizon formation, with minimal assumptions about the global spacetime structure. Our theorem relies on an extension of a recent quantum learning no-go theorem and is proved using new techniques of pseudorandom measure concentration. To apply this result to cosmic censorship, we separate singularities into classical, semi-Planckian, and Planckian types. We illustrate that classical and semi-Planckian singularities are compatible with approximately pseudorandom CFT time evolution; thus, if such singularities are indeed approximately pseudorandom, by Cryptographic Censorship, they cannot exist in the absence of event horizons. This result provides a sufficient condition guaranteeing that seminal holographic results on quantum chaos and thermalization, whose general applicability relies on typicality of horizons, will not be invalidated by the formation of naked singularities in AdS/CFT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.03425v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Netta Engelhardt, {\AA}smund Folkestad, Adam Levine, Evita Verheijden, Lisa Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interacting massive/massless continuous-spin fields and integer-spin fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02817</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02817v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the framework of light-cone gauge approach, interacting continuous-spin fields and integer-spin fields propagating in flat space are studied. The continuous-spin fields are considered by using a light-cone gauge vector superspace formulation. Description of massive continuous-spin fields associated with the principal, complementary and discrete series is presented. For the massive continuous-spin fields of the principal and complementary series and massless continuous-spin fields, all parity-even cubic vertices realized as functions on the light-cone gauge vector superspace are obtained. Cubic vertices for a cross-interaction of massive/massless continuous spin fields and massive/massless integer-spin fields are also derived. These results for cubic vertices are complete for the dimensions of space-time greater than four. The use of the light-cone gauge vector superspace formulation considerably simplifies the cubic vertices as compared to the ones of oscillator formulation. Some cubic vertices realized as distributions are also found. Map between the oscillator formulation and the vector superspace formulation of the continuous-spin fields is explicitly described. An equivalence of the light-cone gauge and Lorentz covariant formulations of the free continuous-spin fields is also demonstrated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02817v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. R. Metsaev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Krylov operator complexity in holographic CFTs: Smeared boundary reconstruction and the dual proper radial momentum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03273v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Motivated by bulk reconstruction of smeared boundary operators, we study the Krylov complexity of local and non-local primary CFT$_d$ operators from the local bulk-to-bulk propagator of a minimally-coupled massive scalar field in Rindler-AdS$_{d+1}$ space. We derive analytic and numerical evidence on how the degree of non-locality in the dual CFT$_d$ observable affects the evolution of Krylov complexity and the Lanczos coefficients. Curiously, the near-horizon limit matches with the same observable for conformally-coupled probe scalar fields inserted at the asymptotic boundary of AdS$_{d+1}$ space. Our results also show that the evolution of the growth rate of Krylov operator complexity in the CFT$_d$ takes the same form as to the proper radial momentum of a probe particle inside the bulk to a good approximation. The exact equality only occurs when the probe particle is inserted in the asymptotic boundary or in the horizon limit. Our results capture a prosperous interplay between Krylov complexity in the CFT, thermal ensembles at finite bulk locations and their role in the holographic dictionary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03273v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/6bgg-vglp</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 112 (2025) 12, 126014</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sergio E. Aguilar-Gutierrez, Hugo A. Camargo, Viktor Jahnke, Keun-Young Kim, Mitsuhiro Nishida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infrared Divergence in QED and the Fluctuation of Electromagnetic Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08269v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish a no-go result for the infrared sector of quantum electrodynamics. Using the standard Fock-space formulation, we show that gauge invariance enforces coherent soft-photon phases that guarantee the Bloch--Nordsieck/Kinoshita--Lee--Nauenberg cancellation for all inclusive observables. The infrared divergences of perturbative amplitudes therefore do not signal any physical instability of the theory, but reflect the universal quantum dressing cloud inseparably accompanying charged particles.
  We further demonstrate that the stochastic interpretation suggested by the Schwinger--Keldysh effective action does not apply to four-dimensional Maxwell theory. Although infrared-sensitive imaginary terms appear in the SK effective action and can be rewritten via a Hubbard--Stratonovich transformation, we prove that conformal invariance forbids any infrared growth of these terms. As a consequence, the associated auxiliary field cannot be interpreted as a Langevin force, even in de~Sitter spacetime.
  These results exclude infrared-induced classical stochastic dynamics for gauge fields and clarify the physical distinction between QED and nearly massless scalar fields in de~Sitter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08269v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takeshi Fukuyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Index from a point</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12510v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose an algebro-geometric interpretation of the Schur and Macdonald indices of four-dimensional $\mathcal{N}=2$ superconformal field theories (SCFTs). We conjecture that there exists an affine scheme $X$, which reduces to the Higgs branch as a variety, such that the Hilbert series of the (appropriately-graded) arc space of its polynomial ring $J_\infty(\mathbb{C}[X])$ encodes the indices. Distinct local descriptions of a (singular) point correspond to distinct choices of $X$, giving rise to families of $\mathcal{N}=2$ SCFTs each without a Higgs branch. These local descriptions directly translate into nilpotency relations in the operator product expansions. We test our conjecture across a variety of (generalized) Argyres--Douglas theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12510v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Monica Jinwoo Kang, Craig Lawrie, Jaewon Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropic force in matrix</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12921v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the entropic force in matrix theory. We find the gravity in bulk can be emergent from the entropic force.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12921v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei-shui Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Chaos Diagnostics for non-Hermitian Systems from Bi-Lanczos Krylov Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13956</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13956v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In Hermitian systems, Krylov complexity has emerged as a powerful diagnostic of quantum dynamics, capable of distinguishing chaotic from integrable phases, in agreement with established probes such as spectral statistics and out-of-time-order correlators. By contrast, its role in non-Hermitian settings, relevant for modeling open quantum systems, remains less understood due to the challenges posed by complex eigenvalues and the limitations of standard approaches based on orthogonality, such as singular value decomposition. Here we demonstrate that Krylov complexity, computed via the bi-Lanczos algorithm, provides a reliable probe of quantum chaos in non-Hermitian systems, clearly discriminating chaotic and integrable regimes. Our results agree with complex spectral statistics and complex spacing ratios, underscoring the robustness of the method. Universality is supported by extensive tests in both the non-Hermitian Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model and non-Hermitian random-matrix ensembles across multiple non-Hermitian symmetry classes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13956v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Baggioli, Kyoung-Bum Huh, Hyun-Sik Jeong, Xuhao Jiang, Keun-Young Kim, Juan F. Pedraza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>O(16)$\times$O(16) heterotic theory on $AdS_3\times S^3\times T^4$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20915v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study non-supersymmetric $AdS_{3}\times S^{3}$ vacuua of $O(16)\times O(16)$ heterotic theory on a string scale $T^{4}$ background, which are parameterized by a pair of flux integers. Adding the one-loop scalar potential to the effective theory contributes positively to the cosmological constant, but we find that there is no uplift to de Sitter for any values of the fluxes. We study the fluctuations around these vacua and show that all scalar and tensor modes from the six-dimensional effective theory lie above the Breitenlohner-Freedman bound. The moduli coming from the torus compactification will also be above the bound, at least for a large range of fluxes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20915v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Robbins, Hassaan Saleem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complex Saddles of Charged-AdS Gravitational partition function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25396v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the Euclidean partition function of uncharged and charged $AdS_{d+1}$ black hole geometries in canonical and grand canonical ensemble for $d\geq3$. It is seen that the partition function can be reduced to a one-dimensional integral, which can be investigated using methods of Picard-Lefschetz. The saddles of the system correspond to either naked-singular geometry, thermal-AdS, small-, intermediate- or large-sized black hole for different ranges of parameter space. These are solutions of Einstein's equation, which are dominant saddles of the partition function in various regimes of parameter space. A naive analysis of the partition function involving these saddles would lead to conflicts with the standard understanding of black hole thermodynamics and also with AdS/CFT. However, when the partition function is analysed using Picard-Lefschetz, it is seen that naked-singular geometries turn out to be irrelevant and therefore do not contribute. This also aligns well with the Cosmic Censorship hypothesis. Depending on the ensemble, saddles corresponding to negative specific heat are either small- or intermediate-sized black holes. Although they are relevant in the partition function but are sub-dominant. They drop out under homology averaging. Only saddles corresponding to non-negative specific heat contribute to the Euclidean partition function. Finally, we analyze the allowability of these complex geometries using the KSW criterion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25396v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP02(2026)054</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 02 (2026) 054</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Manishankar Ailiga, Shubhashis Mallik, Gaurav Narain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Weyl anomaly for chiral fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05545v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We compute the parity-odd part of the Weyl anomaly for chiral fermions in a background gravitational field. We start from a manifestly real form of the Lagrangian (that is, not only real up to a total derivative), and we regularize it by means of Pauli-Villars fermions. All parity-odd terms in the anomaly cancel in the integrand, so that the result of the anomaly is necessarily parity-even.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05545v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrique Alvarez, Luis Alvarez-Gaume, Jesus Anero, Carmelo P Martin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On theta function expressions of cyclic products of fermion correlation functions in genus two</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.08664v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In arXiv:2211.09069, significant progress was made in decomposing simple products of fermion correlation functions, and in summing over spin structures of superstring amplitudes in genus two under cyclic constraints. In this manuscript we consider part of the same subject using a framework in which one of the branch points of the genus two curve is fixed at infinity. This framework is a direct generalization of the popular one in the case of genus one. We address some of the issues that remained unresolved in our previous paper arXiv:2209.14633. We show that the spin structures of the simple products of fermion correlation functions with cyclic conditions depend only on the Pe-function values at the half-periods of the genus two surface, for any number of factors in the products. Similar to the genus one case, we can provide basis functions to decompose the product. Consequently, the trilinear relations found in arXiv:2211.09069 can be derived from the known set of differential equations of genus two Pe-functions by simply setting the variables equal to the half-periods of the non-singular and even spin structures, as is the case for genus one. The focus of this manuscript is on the procedures for expressing the results of decomposed formulae in terms of the unique genus two theta function. At present we cannot provide a procedure for deriving the general form of the decomposed formula totally expressed in terms of the theta functions for an arbitrary number of the fermion correlation functions in the product, by the reason described in the text. We present some general results and demonstrate that concrete expressions of both the spin structure dependent and independent parts will be derived and simplified to analyze using the logic of the derivations of the classical solutions to Jacobi inversion problem and their modifications which will be given in this manuscript.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.08664v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. G. Tsuchiya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observers, $\alpha$-parameters, and the Hartle-Hawking state</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.03835</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.03835v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we extend recent ideas about observers and closed universes to theories where observers can be fluctuated into existence in the Hartle-Hawking state. This introduces a phenomenon that was not considered in these earlier discussions: the dominant transition from one cosmological state to another can go through a fluctuation that annihilates the universe and creates a new one. We nonetheless argue that the observer decoherence rule allows for the third-quantized description of such a theory to emerge from a factorizing holographic theory with a one-dimensional Hilbert space, without any need for $\alpha$-parameters. We also point out a close analogy between the observer rule in this context and the coarse-graining of the spectral form factor at late times for AdS black holes. Along the way we clarify several aspects of the relationship between holography, the gravitational path integral, and $\alpha$-parameters. We also explain why string theory scattering amplitudes do not lead to a one-dimensional Hilbert space on the worldsheet, despite being computed by a gravitational path integral with a sum over topology. Finally we point out that using the path integral to compute integrated local operators conditioned on an observer in the context of a theory with a landscape can lead to rather surprising conclusions. For example we argue that in a landscape with one AdS minimum and one dS minimum, both of which can support observers, an observer almost surely finds themself in dS and not AdS even if the boundary conditions are dual to a state with an observer in AdS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.03835v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Harlow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Realization of Carrollian Conformal Symmetry through Deformed Light-Cone Null Reduction of Complex Vector Field Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06280v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Inspired by Saha et al. (2025) [1], we utilize the deformed light-cone formalism to investigate the Carrollian version of a complex vector field theory. We find that after applying the null-reduction procedure and the Carrollian limit c $\to$ 0, the "-" null-direction and spatial components of the parent vector field decouple completely into independent scalar fields, while the "+" null-direction component vanishes. We carefully derive and demonstrate the process by which the energy-momentum tensor degrades from the Lorentzian symmetry case to the non-relativistic scenario, and point out that the secondary constraint of the original parent theory will play a crucial role in the derivation of the Carrollian generators. Finally, as expected, the resulting generators produce the known kinematic Carrollian conformal algebraic commutation relations. This work represents an extension of the application of the deformed light-cone null reduction formalism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06280v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Limin Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lindblad many-body scars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06665v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum many-body scars have received much recent attention for being both intriguing non-ergodic states in otherwise quantum chaotic systems and promising candidates to encode quantum information efficiently. So far, these studies have mostly been restricted to Hermitian systems. Here, we study many-body scars in many-body quantum chaotic systems coupled to a Markovian bath, which we term Lindblad many-body scars. They are defined as simultaneous eigenvectors of the Hamiltonian and dissipative parts of the vectorized Liouvillian. Importantly, because their eigenvalues are purely real, they are not related to revivals. The number and nature of the scars depend on both the symmetry of the Hamiltonian and the choice of jump operators. For a dissipative four-body Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) model with $N$ fermions, either Majorana or complex, we construct analytically some of these Lindblad scars while others could only be obtained numerically. As an example of the former, we identify $N/2+1$ scars for complex fermions due to the $U(1)$ symmetry of the model and two scars for Majorana fermions as a consequence of the parity symmetry. Similar results are obtained for a dissipative XXZ spin chain. We also characterize the physical properties of Lindblad scars. First, the operator size is independent of the disorder realization and has a vanishing variance. By contrast, the operator size for non-scarred states, believed to be quantum chaotic, is well described by a distribution centered around a specific size and a finite variance, which could be relevant for a precise definition of the eigenstate thermalization hypothesis in dissipative quantum chaos. Moreover, the entanglement entropy of these scars has distinct features such as a strong dependence on the partition choice and, in certain cases, a large entanglement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06665v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/x15w-zchv</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. E 113, 024116 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Antonio M. Garc\'ia-Garc\'ia, Zhongling Lu, Lucas S\'a, Jacobus J. M. Verbaarschot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum gravitational corrections to Reissner-Nordstr\"om black hole thermodynamics and their implications for the weak gravity conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.08459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.08459v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the quantum gravitational corrections to the thermodynamical quantities of Reissner-Nordstr\"om black holes within the framework of effective field theory. The effective action originates from integrating out massless particles, including gravitons, at the one-loop level. We perform a complete thermodynamic analysis for both non-extremal and extremal black holes, and are mainly concerned about the shift in the charge-to-mass ratio $q/M$ that plays an important role in analyzing the weak gravity conjuecture. For non-extremal black holes, we identify a relationship between the shift in the charge-to-mass ratio and the thermodynamic stability of the black holes. For extremal black holes, we show that quantum gravity effects naturally lead to the super-extremality $q/M&gt;1$ of charged black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.08459v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yong Xiao, Qiang Wang, Aonan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring R\'enyi entropy using a projected Loschmidt echo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.05237v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present efficient and practical protocols to measure the second R\'enyi entropy (RE), whose exponential is known as the purity. We achieve this by establishing a direct connection to a Loschmidt echo (LE) type measurement sequence, applicable to quantum many-body systems. Notably, our approach does not rely on random-noise averaging, a feature that can be extended to protocols to measure out-of-time-order correlation functions (OTOCs), as we demonstrate. By way of example, we show that our protocols can be practically implemented in superconducting qubit-based platforms, as well as in cavity-QED trapped ultra-cold gases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.05237v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi-Neng Zhou, Robin L\"owenberg, Julian Sonner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the structure of compact strong HKT manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06058</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06058v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the geometry of compact strong HKT and, more generally, compact BHE manifolds. We prove that any compact BHE manifold with full holonomy must be K\"ahler and we establish a similar result for strong HKT manifolds. Additionally, we demonstrate a rigidity theorem for strong HKT structures on solvmanifolds and we completely classify those with parallel Bismut torsion. Finally, we introduce the Ricci foliation for hypercomplex manifolds and analyze its properties for compact, simply connected, 8-dimensional strong HKT manifolds, proving that they are always Hopf fibrations over a compact $4$-dimensional orbifold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06058v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beatrice Brienza, Anna Fino, Gueo Grantcharov, Misha Verbitsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SO(n) Affleck-Kennedy-Lieb-Tasaki states as conformal boundary states of integrable SU(n) spin chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13114v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct a class of conformal boundary states in the $\mathrm{SU}(n)_1$ Wess-Zumino-Witten (WZW) conformal field theory (CFT) using the symmetry embedding $\mathrm{Spin}(n)_2 \subset \mathrm{SU}(n)_1$. These boundary states are beyond the standard Cardy construction and possess $\mathrm{SO}(n)$ symmetry. The $\mathrm{SU}(n)$ Uimin-Lai-Sutherland (ULS) spin chains, which realize the $\mathrm{SU}(n)_1$ WZW model on the lattice, allow us to identify these boundary states as the ground states of the $\mathrm{SO}(n)$ Affleck-Kennedy-Lieb-Tasaki spin chains. Using the integrability of the $\mathrm{SU}(n)$ ULS model, we analytically compute the corresponding Affleck-Ludwig boundary entropy using exact overlap formulas. Our results unveil intriguing connections between exotic boundary states in CFT and integrable lattice models, thus providing deep insights into the interplay of symmetry, integrability, and boundary critical phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13114v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yueshui Zhang, Ying-Hai Wu, Meng Cheng, Hong-Hao Tu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vectorlike lepton imprints at lepton $g-2$ measurements and $e^+e^-$ colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20873v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A fermion can be chiral or vectorlike with respect to a given symmetry, depending on its coupling to the corresponding gauge boson. Vectorlike fermions have a distinct property that their left-handed and right-handed components behave in the same way under the gauge symmetry. In this paper, we investigate an extension of the standard model with an $SU(2)$ doublet of vectorlike leptons and two complex scalars. The new physics effects on the lepton anomalous magnetic moment, as well as the electron and muon pair production processes at $e^+e^-$ colliders are analyzed. Taking into account the updated measurement results of the electron and muon $g-2$, the LEP and the LHC data, the viable parameter space of the model is identified. We also examine the prospect of testing the model using $\mu^+\mu^-$ signals from electron-position annihilation at the Future Circular Collider (FCC-ee). The analysis shows that the FCC-ee will be able to exclude a significant part of the parameter space, pinpointing exiguous viable regions to be tested in the future due to its high precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20873v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/w45p-zqx4</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Sang Quang Dinh, Hieu Minh Tran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Softening holographic nuclear matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02216</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02216v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Baryons in the holographic Witten-Sakai-Sugimoto model are described by instanton solutions on the flavor branes. A commonly used approximation for dense baryonic matter replaces the many-instanton solution by a simpler, spatially homogeneous, ansatz, which requires a discontinuity in the holographic direction of the non-abelian gauge field in order to account for topological baryon number. We point out that the simplest configuration with a single jump - often used in previous studies - results in matter at saturation density that is much stiffer than real-world nuclear matter. This is improved, although not completely remedied, by adding a second jump. We present a systematic discussion of all possible configurations up to four jumps, dynamically computing locations of and behavior at the discontinuities. We find solutions that continuously connect to those based on pointlike baryons, thus, for the first time, establishing a concrete link between the instantonic and homogeneous pictures. This is supported by translating the multi-jump profiles of the gauge field into gauge invariant multi-layer charge distributions. The most important of our novel configurations has a block-like structure in the bulk, becomes pointlike at low density and/or large coupling, and is energetically preferred over all previously studied configurations. Therefore, our work lays the ground for improved predictions from holography for dense nuclear matter in neutron stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02216v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Ecker, Nicolas Kovensky, Orestis Papadopoulos, Andreas Schmitt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clifford quantum cellular automata from topological quantum field theories and invertible subalgebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07099v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a general framework for constructing quantum cellular automata (QCA) from topological quantum field theories (TQFT) and invertible subalgebras (ISA) using the cup-product formalism. This approach explicitly realizes all $\mathbb{Z}_2$ and $\mathbb{Z}_p$ Clifford QCAs (for prime $p$) in all admissible dimensions, in precise agreement with the classification predicted by algebraic $L$-theory. We determine the orders of these QCAs by explicitly showing that finite powers reduce to the identity up to finite-depth quantum circuits (FDQC) and lattice translations. In particular, we demonstrate that the $\mathbb{Z}_2$ Clifford QCAs in $(4l{+}1)$ spatial dimensions can be disentangled by non-Clifford FDQCs. Our construction applies beyond cubic lattices, allowing $\mathbb{Z}_2$ QCAs to be defined on arbitrary cellulations. Furthermore, we explicitly construct invertible subalgebras in higher dimensions, obtaining $\mathbb{Z}_2$ ISAs in $2l$ spatial dimensions and $\mathbb{Z}_p$ ISAs in $(4l{-}2)$ spatial dimensions. These ISAs give rise to $\mathbb{Z}_2$ QCAs in $(2l{+}1)$ dimensions and $\mathbb{Z}_p$ QCAs in $(4l{-}1)$ dimensions. We further prove that the QCAs in $3$ spatial dimensions constructed via TQFTs and ISAs are equivalent by identifying their boundary algebras, and show that this approach extends to higher dimensions. Together, these results establish a unified and dimension-periodic framework for Clifford QCAs, connecting their explicit lattice realizations to field theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07099v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meng Sun, Bowen Yang, Zongyuan Wang, Nathanan Tantivasadakarn, Yu-An Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of Out-of-Time-Ordered Transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.11198v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct an effective field theory (EFT) that captures the universal behavior of out-of-time-order correlators (OTOCs) at late times in generic quantum many-body systems with conservation laws. The EFT hinges on a generalization of the strong-to-weak spontaneous symmetry breaking pattern adapted to out-of-time-order observables, and reduces to conventional fluctuating hydrodynamics when time-ordered observables are probed. We use the EFT to explain different power-law behavior observed in OTOCs at late times, and show that many OTOCs are entirely fixed by conventional transport data. Nevertheless, we show that a specific combination of OTOCs is sensitive to novel transport parameters, not visible in regular time-ordered correlators. We test our predictions in Hamiltonian and Floquet spin chains in one dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.11198v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruchira Mishra, Jiaozi Wang, Silvia Pappalardi, Luca V. Delacr\'etaz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Realization of quintom dark energy after DESI DR2 in Nieh-Yan modified teleparallel gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.00506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.00506v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent observations from the DESI Collaboration indicate a preference for quintom dark energy, i.e., its equation of state evolves across the cosmological constant boundary $w=-1$. It is well known that models with single perfect fluid or single scalar field minimally coupled to Einstein gravity develop perturbative instabilities around the crossing, thereby cannot realize the quintom scenario. In this paper, we propose a method to circumvent the instability problem of these models by considering the coupling of dark energy to the Nieh-Yan density within the framework of teleparallel gravity. We show that with this coupling the background evolution is not affected, but the dark energy perturbation is removed from the menu of dynamical degrees of freedom, thus avoiding the inherent difficulties in the old models. Furthermore, the Nieh-Yan coupling causes parity violation in gravitational waves, and this can be considered as a clear prediction of this mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.00506v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxuan Kang, Mingzhe Li, Changzhi Yi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
