<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ao-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ao-ph</link>
    <description>physics.ao-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ao-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 04:02:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking Turbulence Models to Represent Cloud-Edge Mixing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03789</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.03789v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Considering turbulence is crucial to understanding clouds. However, covering all scales involved in the turbulent mixing of clouds with their environment is computationally challenging, urging the development of simpler models to represent some of the processes involved. By using full direct numerical simulations as a reference, this study compares several statistical approaches for representing small-scale turbulent mixing. All models use a comparable Lagrangian representation of cloud microphysics, and simulate the same cases of cloud-edge mixing, covering different ambient humidities and turbulence intensities. It is demonstrated that all statistical models represent the evolution of thermodynamics successfully, but not all models capture the changes in cloud microphysics (cloud droplet number concentration, droplet mean radius, and spectral width). Implications of these results for using the presented models as subgrid-scale schemes are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.03789v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Kainz, Nikitabahen N. Makwana, Bipin Kumar, S. Ravichandran, Johan Fries, Gaetano Sardina, Bernhard Mehlig, Fabian Hoffmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IceCloudNet: 3D reconstruction of cloud ice from Meteosat SEVIRI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04135v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: IceCloudNet is a novel method based on machine learning able to predict high-quality vertically resolved cloud ice water contents (IWC) and ice crystal number concentrations (N$_\textrm{ice}$). The predictions come at the spatio-temporal coverage and resolution of geostationary satellite observations (SEVIRI) and the vertical resolution of active satellite retrievals (DARDAR). IceCloudNet consists of a ConvNeXt-based U-Net and a 3D PatchGAN discriminator model and is trained by predicting DARDAR profiles from co-located SEVIRI images. Despite the sparse availability of DARDAR data due to its narrow overpass, IceCloudNet is able to predict cloud occurrence, spatial structure, and microphysical properties with high precision. The model has been applied to ten years of SEVIRI data, producing a dataset of vertically resolved IWC and N$_\textrm{ice}$ of clouds containing ice with a 3 kmx3 kmx240 mx15 minute resolution in a spatial domain of 30{\deg}W to 30{\deg}E and 30{\deg}S to 30{\deg}N. The produced dataset increases the availability of vertical cloud profiles, for the period when DARDAR is available, by more than six orders of magnitude and moreover, IceCloudNet is able to produce vertical cloud profiles beyond the lifetime of the recently ended satellite missions underlying DARDAR.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04135v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kai Jeggle, Mikolaj Czerkawski, Federico Serva, Bertrand Le Saux, David Neubauer, Ulrike Lohmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>YanTian: An Application Platform for AI Global Weather Forecasting Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04539v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To promote the practical application of AI Global Weather Forecasting Models (AIGWFM), we have developed an adaptable application platform named 'YanTian'. This platform enhances existing open-source AIGWFM with a suite of capability-enhancing modules and is constructed by a "loosely coupled" plug-in architecture. The goal of 'YanTian' is to address the limitations of current open-source AIGWFM in operational application, including improving local forecast accuracy, providing spatial high-resolution forecasts, increasing density of forecast intervals, and generating diverse products with the provision of AIGC capabilities. 'YianTian' also provides a simple, visualized user interface, allowing meteorologists easily access both basic and extended capabilities of the platform by simply configuring the platform UI. Users do not need to possess the complex artificial intelligence knowledge and the coding techniques. Additionally, 'YianTian' can be deployed on a PC with GPUs. We hope 'YianTian' can facilitate the operational widespread adoption of AIGWFMs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04539v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wencong Cheng, Jiangjiang Xia, Chang Qu, Zhigang Wang, Xinyi Zeng, Fang Huang, Tianye Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The absolute seawater entropy: Part~I. Definition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04821v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The absolute entropy of seawater is defined as an improved version of the relationship defined by Franck Millero in 1976 and 1983. The first improvements concern the complex non-linear dependence of entropy on pressure, temperature and salinity, with the use of the standard TEOS10 formulation based on a fit of the oceanic Gibbs function to more recent observations. On the other hand, more recent thermodynamic tables have been used to increase the accuracy of the Millero's salinity increment to this standard formulation, to deduce the absolute version of entropy with new values for the pure-water and sea-salts absolute reference entropies. The differences between the values of the seawater entropy calculated with the Millero and TEOS10 formulations (standard and absolute) are documented, before a more complete study shown in the second part of the paper of the absolute seawater entropy computed from observed vertical profiles and analysed surface datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04821v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pascal Marquet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The absolute seawater entropy: Part~II. Case studies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04822</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04822v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The aim of this second part of the article is to study with several concrete cases the absolute definition of the seawater entropy described in Part I. Observed vertical profiles and polar transects, as well as analysed surface data, show that very different temperature and salinity values can organise to create new isentropic regions that can only be revealed by the absolute formulation of the entropy of seawater (Arctic Ocean; Bay of Bengal; Mediterranean, Black and Caspian Seas). Existing hypotheses to explain these results include the possible impact of turbulent processes that must be applied to the entropies of the atmosphere and oceans.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04822v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pascal Marquet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UFLUX v2.0: A Process-Informed Machine Learning Framework for Efficient and Explainable Modelling of Terrestrial Carbon Uptake</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.03951v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Gross Primary Productivity (GPP), the amount of carbon plants fixed by photosynthesis, is pivotal for understanding the global carbon cycle and ecosystem functioning. Process-based models built on the knowledge of ecological processes are susceptible to biases stemming from their assumptions and approximations. These limitations potentially result in considerable uncertainties in global GPP estimation, which may pose significant challenges to our Net Zero goals. This study presents UFLUX v2.0, a process-informed model that integrates state-of-art ecological knowledge and advanced machine learning techniques to reduce uncertainties in GPP estimation by learning the biases between process-based models and eddy covariance (EC) measurements. In our findings, UFLUX v2.0 demonstrated a substantial improvement in model accuracy, achieving an R^2 of 0.79 with a reduced RMSE of 1.60 g C m^-2 d^-1, compared to the process-based model's R^2 of 0.51 and RMSE of 3.09 g C m^-2 d^-1. Our global GPP distribution analysis indicates that while UFLUX v2.0 and the process-based model achieved similar global total GPP (137.47 Pg C and 132.23 Pg C, respectively), they exhibited large differences in spatial distribution, particularly in latitudinal gradients. These differences are very likely due to systematic biases in the process-based model and differing sensitivities to climate and environmental conditions. This study offers improved adaptability for GPP modelling across diverse ecosystems, and further enhances our understanding of global carbon cycles and its responses to environmental changes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.03951v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenquan Dong, Songyan Zhu, Jian Xu, Casey M. Ryan, Man Chen, Jingya Zeng, Hao Yu, Congfeng Cao, Jiancheng Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radiative cooling capacity on Earth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04109</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04109v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: By passively dissipating thermal emission into the ultracold deep space, radiative cooling (RC) is an environment-friendly means for gaining cooling capacity, paving a bright future for global energy saving and carbon dioxide reduction. However, assessing the global RC capacity at the day-to-annual scale remains challenging as the RC capacity significantly depends on geographic and environmental conditions. To our knowledge, no analysis of global RC capacity has been reported. Herein, we show the distribution of RC capacity on Earth by establishing a precise assessment model for evaluating the performance of a radiative cooler. Our assessment is comprehensively validated against experimental data and extended to elucidate the capacity of representative broadband and selective cooler. We also categorize the global RC capacity into five representative regions based on the year-round cooling power. Our assessment can inform trade-offs between design and practical application for the RC systems, alongside promoting RC-based technologies to tackle worldwide energy and environment challenges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04109v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cunhai Wang, Hao Chen, Yanyan Feng, Ziming Cheng, Jingchong Liu, Fuqiang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atmospheres of Solar System Moons and Pluto</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04595</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04595v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The atmospheres within our Solar System can be categorized into four distinct climate regimes: "terrestrial", "Jovian", "condensable", and "exosphere". Beyond the three terrestrial planets (excluding Mercury) and the four giant planets, collisional atmospheres are also found on smaller celestial bodies such as Jupiter's moon Io, Saturn's moon Titan, Neptune's moon Triton, and Pluto. This article reviews the key characteristics of these atmospheres and the underlying physical and chemical processes that govern them. I focus on their thermal structures, chemical constituents, wind patterns, and the origins and losses of the atmospheres, and highlight the critical roles of surface ices and liquids, atmospheric hazes, and the space environments of their host planets in shaping these atmospheres. I dedicated this article to Prof. Zuo Xiao (1936-2024) at Peking University.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04595v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xi Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compact Cavity-Enhanced Aerosol Detector using Incoherent Light Sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05150v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We have realized a compact optical particle counter utilizing enhancement of light scattering within a high finesse Fabry-Perot optical cavity. In contrast to laser-based approaches such as cavity ringdown spectroscopy we use the light stream from both superluminescent and light-emitting diodes that have no longitudinal coherence. This eliminates the vibration sensitivity that is typical of laser-based cavity methods. The use of the transmission mode of detection allows us to reduce the cavity mirror separation to below 1 cm, with no obvious limit to miniaturization. Typical light scattering instruments are larger, in part due to their sensitivity to background signals from the light source. Our approach paves the way toward a new generation of compact and portable instruments. A simultaneous comparison of the scattering signals with a commercial particle counter shows that our cavity is also sensitive to ultrafine particles below 300 nm diameter that are typically not recorded in such counters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05150v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacob Williamson, Pranav Chamakkad Muthukrishnan, Srushti Nandanwar, Shuaifeng Guo, Chandra Raman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparing the influence of Atlantic Multidecadal Variability and spring soil moisture on European summer heat waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10821v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we study and compare the influence of the Atlantic Multidecadal Variability (AMV) and of spring soil moisture in Southern Europe on the duration and intensity of European summer heat waves. We study common heat waves with return times of a few years like in previous studies, but we also propose a new methodological approach, return time maps, that allows us to study rare heat waves with return times from 10 to 50 years. We use the outputs from three climate models, namely IPSL-CM6A-LR, EC-Earth3, and CNRM-CM6-1, in which North Atlantic sea surface temperatures are restored towards the observed AMV anomalies. The three models give consistent results, with the exception of EC-Earth simulating a much greater influence of soil moisture. Typical AMV or spring soil moisture anomalies induce changes in the temperature and duration of heat waves that are of comparable amplitude, but follow different regional patterns. As might be expected, a positive AMV phase or low soil moisture induces hotter and longer typical heat waves over most of Europe. However, counter-intuitively, they also induce less heat wave days and cooler heat waves over part of Northeast Europe. For more extreme events, the influence of the AMV and soil moisture increase, according to rather similar regional patterns as for typical heat waves. However, while the amplitude of the influence is greater, the regions with decreased heat wave temperature and less heat wave days extend in size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10821v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valeria Mascolo, Cl\'ement Le Priol, Fabio D'Andrea, Freddy Bouchet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calculating radio emissions of positive streamer phenomena using 3D simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09772v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study radio emissions from positive streamers in air using 3D simulations, from which the radiated electric field is computed by solving Jefimenko's equations. The simulations are performed at 0.5 bar using two photoionization methods: the Helmholtz approximation for a photon density and a Monte Carlo method using discrete photons, with the latter being the most realistic. We consider cases with single streamers, streamer branching, streamers interacting with preionization and streamer-streamer encounters. We do not observe a strong VHF radio signal during or after branching, which is confirmed by lab experiments. This indicates that the current inside a streamer discharges evolves approximately continuously during branching. On the other hand, stochastic fluctuations in streamer propagation due to Monte Carlo photoionization lead to more radio emission being emitted at frequencies of 100 MHz and above. Another process that leads to such high-frequency emission is the interaction of a streamer with a weakly preionized region, which can be present due to a previous discharge. In agreement with previous work, we observe the strongest and highest-frequency emission from streamer encounters. The amount of total energy that is radiated seems to depend primarily on the background electric field, and less on the particular streamer evolution. Finally, we present approximations for the maximal current along a streamer channel and a fit formula for a streamer's current moment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09772v4</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1029/2024JD041385</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Hemaditya Malla, Brian M. Hare, Steven Cummer, Yihao Guo, Alejandro Malag\'on-Romero, Sander Nijdam, Ute Ebert, Jannis Teunissen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Effect of Tornadic Supercell Thunderstorms on the Atmospheric Muon Flux</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19311v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Tornadoes are severe weather phenomena characterized by a violently rotating column of air connecting the ground to a parent storm. Within the United States, hundreds of tornadoes occur every year. Despite this, the dynamics of tornado formation and propagation are not particularly well understood, in part due to the challenge of instrumentation: many existing instruments for measuring atmospheric properties are in-situ detectors, making deployment in or near an active or developing tornado difficult. Here, we combine local atmospheric and cosmic ray air shower simulation to explore the potential for remote measurement of the pressure field within tornado-producing supercell thunderstorms by examining directional variations of the atmospheric muon flux.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19311v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William Luszczak, Leigh Orf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bridging the Rossby number gap in rapidly rotating thermal convection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08536v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Geophysical and astrophysical fluid flows are typically driven by buoyancy and strongly constrained at large scales by planetary rotation. Rapidly rotating Rayleigh-B\'enard convection (RRRBC) provides a paradigm for experiments and direct numerical simulations (DNS) of such flows, but the accessible parameter space remains restricted to moderately fast rotation rates (Ekman numbers $Ek \gtrsim 10^{-8}$), while realistic $Ek$ for astro-/geophysical applications are orders of magnitude smaller. On the other hand, previously derived reduced equations of motion describing the leading-order behaviour in the limit of very rapid rotation ($Ek\to 0$) cannot capture finite rotation effects, and the physically most relevant part of parameter space with small but finite $Ek$ has remained elusive. Here, we employ the rescaled incompressible Navier-Stokes equations (RiNSE) -- a reformulation of the Navier-Stokes-Boussinesq equations informed by the scalings valid for $Ek\to 0$, recently introduced by Julien et al. (2024) -- to provide full DNS of RRRBC at unprecedented rotation strengths down to $Ek=10^{-15}$ and below, revealing the disappearance of cyclone-anticyclone asymmetry at previously unattainable Ekman numbers ($Ek \approx 10^{-9}$). We also identify an overshoot in the heat transport as $Ek$ is varied at fixed $\widetilde{Ra}= Ra Ek^{4/3}$, associated with dissipation due to ageostrophic motions in the boundary layers. The simulations validate theoretical predictions based on thermal boundary layer theory for RRRBC and show that the solutions of RiNSE agree with the reduced equations at very small $Ek$. These results represent a first foray into the vast, largely unexplored parameter space of very rapidly rotating convection rendered accessible by RiNSE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08536v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrian van Kan, Keith Julien, Benjamin Miquel, Edgar Knobloch</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
