<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ao-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ao-ph</link>
    <description>physics.ao-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ao-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 05:00:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Advancing global aerosol forecasting with artificial intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02498v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Aerosol forecasting is essential for air quality warnings, health risk assessment, and climate change mitigation. However, it is more complex than weather forecasting due to the intricate interactions between aerosol physicochemical processes and atmospheric dynamics, resulting in significant uncertainty and high computational costs. Here, we develop an artificial intelligence-driven global aerosol-meteorology forecasting system (AI-GAMFS), which provides reliable 5-day, 3-hourly forecasts of aerosol optical components and surface concentrations at a 0.5{\deg} x 0.625{\deg} resolution. AI-GAMFS combines Vision Transformer and U-Net in a backbone network, robustly capturing the complex aerosol-meteorology interactions via global attention and spatiotemporal encoding. Trained on 42 years of advanced aerosol reanalysis data and initialized with GEOS Forward Processing (GEOS-FP) analyses, AI-GAMFS delivers operational 5-day forecasts in one minute. It outperforms the Copernicus Atmosphere Monitoring Service (CAMS) global forecasting system, GEOS-FP forecasts, and several regional dust forecasting systems in forecasting most aerosol variables including aerosol optical depth and dust components. Our results mark a significant step forward in leveraging AI to refine physics-based aerosol forecasting, facilitating more accurate global warnings for aerosol pollution events, such as dust storms and wildfires.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02498v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ke Gui, Xutao Zhang, Huizheng Che, Lei Li, Yu Zheng, Linchang An, Yucong Miao, Hujia Zhao, Oleg Dubovik, Brent Holben, Jun Wang, Pawan Gupta, Elena S. Lind, Carlos Toledano, Hong Wang, Zhili Wang, Yaqiang Wang, Xiaomeng Huang, Kan Dai, Xiangao Xia, Xiaofeng Xu, Xiaoye Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convective environments within Mediterranean cyclones</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02590v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding convective processes leading to severe weather hazards within Mediterranean cyclones is relevant for operational forecasters, insurance industry, and enhancing societal preparedness. In this work we examine the climatological link between Mediterranean cyclones and atmospheric conditions conducive to the formation of severe convection and convective hazards (convective precipitation, lightning and hail potential). Using ATDnet lightning detections we find that, from autumn to spring, 20 to 60% of lightning hours over the Mediterranean basin and adjacent land regions are associated with the presence of a nearby cyclone. Based on reanalysis data, severe convective environments, deep, moist convection (i.e., lightning potential) and related hazards are frequent in the warm sector of Mediterranean cyclones and to the north-east of their centres. In agreement with previous literature, convective processes and hazards peak approximately six hours prior to the time of minimum pressure of the cyclone centre. Moreover, severe convective environments are often detected in cyclone categories typical of transition seasons (especially autumn) and summer, while they are rarer in deep baroclinic cyclones with peak occurrence during winter. Finally, we show that dynamical cyclone features distinguish regions favourable to deep, moist convection. Warm conveyor belts of Mediterranean cyclones, characterised by large-scale ascent and located in regions of high thermodynamic instability, have the largest lightning potential. The potential is only half as intense along the cyclones' cold fronts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02590v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alice Portal, Andrea Angelidou, Raphael Rousseau-Rizzi, Shira Raveh-Rubin, Yonatan Givon, Jennifer L Catto, Francesco Battaglioli, Mateusz Taszarek, Emmanouil Flaounas, Olivia Martius</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CA-MoE: Channel-Adapted MoE for Incremental Weather Forecasting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02503v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Atmospheric science is intricately connected with other fields, e.g., geography and aerospace. Most existing approaches involve training a joint atmospheric and geographic model from scratch, which incurs significant computational costs and overlooks the potential for incremental learning of weather variables across different domains. In this paper, we introduce incremental learning to weather forecasting and propose a novel structure that allows for the flexible expansion of variables within the model. Specifically, our method presents a Channel-Adapted MoE (CA-MoE) that employs a divide-and-conquer strategy. This strategy assigns variable training tasks to different experts by index embedding and reduces computational complexity through a channel-wise Top-K strategy. Experiments conducted on the widely utilized ERA5 dataset reveal that our method, utilizing only approximately 15\% of trainable parameters during the incremental stage, attains performance that is on par with state-of-the-art competitors. Notably, in the context of variable incremental experiments, our method demonstrates negligible issues with catastrophic forgetting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02503v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Chen, Han Tao, Guo Song, Jie Zhang, Yunlong Yu, Yonghan Dong, Chuang Yang, Lei Bai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OceanCastNet: A Deep Learning Ocean Wave Model with Energy Conservation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.03848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.03848v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Traditional wave forecasting models, although based on energy conservation equations, are computationally expensive. On the other hand, existing deep learning geophysical fluid models, while computationally efficient, often suffer from issues such as energy dissipation in long-term forecasts. This paper proposes a novel energy-balanced deep learning wave forecasting model called OceanCastNet (OCN). By incorporating wind fields at the current, previous, and future time steps, as well as wave fields at the current and previous time steps as input variables, OCN maintains energy balance within the model. Furthermore, the model employs adaptive Fourier operators as its core components and designs a masked loss function to better handle the impact of land-sea boundaries. A series of experiments on the ERA5 dataset demonstrate that OCN can achieve short-term forecast accuracy comparable to traditional models while exhibiting an understanding of the wave generation process. In comparative experiments under both normal and extreme conditions, OCN consistently outperforms the widely used WaveWatch III model in the industry. Even after long-term forecasting, OCN maintains a stable and energy-rich state. By further constructing a simple meteorological model, OCN-wind, which considers energy balance, this paper confirms the importance of energy constraints for improving the long-term forecast performance of deep learning meteorological models. This finding provides new ideas for future research on deep learning geophysical fluid models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.03848v3</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziliang Zhang, Huaming Yu, Danqin Ren</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
