<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ao-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ao-ph</link>
    <description>physics.ao-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ao-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 04:02:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On the impact of initial conditions in the forecast of Hurricane Leslie extratropical transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12363v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hurricane Leslie (2018) was a non-tropical system that lasted for a long time undergoing several transitions between tropical and extratropical states. Its trajectory was highly uncertain and difficult to predict. Here the extratropical transition of Leslie is simulated using the Model for Prediction Across Scales (MPAS) with two different sets of initial conditions (IC): the operational analysis of the Integrate Forecast System (IFS) and the Global Forecast System (GFS).
  Discrepancies in Leslie position are found in the IC patterns, and in the intensity and amplitude of the dorsal-trough system in which Leslie is found. Differences are identified both in the geopotential height at 300 hPa and the geopotential thickness. Potential temperature in the dynamic tropopause shows a broader, more intense trough displaced western when using the IC-IFS. The IC-IFS simulation shows lesser trajectory errors but wind speed overestimation than the IC-GFS one. The complex situation of the extratropical transition, where Leslie interacts with a trough, increases the uncertainty associated with the intensification process.
  The disparities observed in the simulations are attributed to inaccuracies in generating the ICs. Both ICs generate different atmospheric configurations when propagated in time. Results suggest that during an extratropical transition in a highly baroclinic atmosphere, the IFS model's data assimilation method produced a more precise analysis than GFS due to the greater number of observations assimilated by the IFS, the greater spatial resolution of the model and the continuous adjustment of the simulations with the field of observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12363v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.atmosres.2023.107020</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Mauricio L\'opez-Reyes, J. J. Gonz\'alez-Alem\'an, M. Sastre, D. Insua-Costa, P. Bolgiani, M. L. Mart\'in</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graph Convolutional Neural Networks as Surrogate Models for Climate Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12815v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many climate processes are characterized using large systems of nonlinear differential equations; this, along with the immense amount of data required to parameterize complex interactions, means that Earth-System Model (ESM) simulations may take weeks to run on large clusters. Uncertainty quantification may require thousands of runs, making ESM simulations impractical for preliminary assessment. Alternatives may include simplifying the processes in the model, but recent efforts have focused on using machine learning to complement these models or even act as full surrogates. \textit{We leverage machine learning, specifically fully-connected neural networks (FCNNs) and graph convolutional neural networks (GCNNs), to enable rapid simulation and uncertainty quantification in order to inform more extensive ESM simulations.} Our surrogate simulated 80 years in approximately 310 seconds on a single A100 GPU, compared to weeks for the ESM model while having mean temperature errors below $0.1^{\circ}C$ and maximum errors below $2^{\circ}C$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12815v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Potter, Carianne Martinez, Reina Pradhan, Samantha Brozak, Steven Sleder, Lauren Wheeler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cool Pavements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12242</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12242v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cool pavements designate alternative pavements designed to reduce their contribution to urban heating. Urban heating generally refers to the sensible heat exchanged with the atmosphere by urban materials but can also include the radiative load they impose on pedestrians. In either case, pavement surface temperature is a very important parameter, which cool pavements seek to decrease compared with standard pavement designs. The energy balance of a pavement surface or very thin pavement slab helps identify the outbound flows which cool pavements attempt to promote and fundamental physical principles which govern them. On this basis, cool pavements can be classified as reflective pavements, green and evaporative pavements, high inertia or phase changing pavements as well as conductive or heatharvesting pavements. This chapter presents the urban heat island and the urban heating phenomena and provides an overview of cool pavement technologies, detailing areas which require further scientific investigation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12242v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/B978-0-12-818981-8.00006-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eco-Efficient Pavement Construction Materials, Elsevier, pp.97-125, 2020, 9780128189818</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Martin Hendel (LIED)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconstruction of the Total Solar Irradiance during the last Millenium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12648</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12648v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Solar irradiance variations across various timescales, from minutes to centuries, represents a potential natural driver of past regional and global climate cold phases. To accurately assess the Sun's effect on climate, particularly during periods of exceptionally low solar activity known as grand minima, an accurate reconstruction of solar forcing is essential. While direct measurements of Total Solar Irradiance (TSI) only began in the late 1970s with the advent of space radiometers, indirect evidence from various historical proxies suggests that the Sun's magnetic activity has undergone possible significant fluctuations over much longer timescales. Employing diverse and independent methods for TSI reconstruction is essential to gaining a comprehensive understanding of this issue. This study employs a semi-empirical model to reconstruct TSI over the past millennium. Our approach uses an estimated open solar magnetic field ($F_{o}$), derived from cosmogenic isotope data, as a proxy for solar activity. We reconstruct the cyclic variations of TSI, due to the solar surface magnetic features, by correlating $F_{o}$ with the parameter of active region functional form. Instead, we obtain the long-term TSI trend by applying the Empirical Mode Decomposition (EMD) algorithm to the reconstructed $F_{o}$ to filter out the 11-year and 22-year solar variability. We prepare a reconstructed TSI record, spanning 971 to 2020 CE. The estimated departure from modern TSI values occurred during the Sp\"{o}rer Minimum (around 1400 CE), with a decrease of approximately 2.3 $W m^{-2}$. A slightly smaller decline of 2.2 $W m^{-2}$ is reported during the Maunder Minimum, between 1645 and 1715 CE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12648v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valentina Penza, Luca Bertello, Matteo Cantoresi, Serena Criscuoli, Lorenza Lucaferri, Raffaele Reda, Simone Ulzega, Francesco Berrilli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpretable multiscale Machine Learning-Based Parameterizations of Convection for ICON</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.03251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.03251v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Machine learning (ML)-based parameterizations have been developed for Earth System Models (ESMs) with the goal to better represent subgrid-scale processes or to accelerate computations. ML-based parameterizations within hybrid ESMs have successfully learned subgrid-scale processes from short high-resolution simulations. However, most studies used a particular ML method to parameterize the subgrid tendencies or fluxes originating from the compound effect of various small-scale processes (e.g., radiation, convection, gravity waves) in mostly idealized settings or from superparameterizations. Here, we use a filtering technique to explicitly separate convection from these processes in simulations with the Icosahedral Non-hydrostatic modelling framework (ICON) in a realistic setting and benchmark various ML algorithms against each other offline. We discover that an unablated U-Net, while showing the best offline performance, learns reverse causal relations between convective precipitation and subgrid fluxes. While we were able to connect the learned relations of the U-Net to physical processes this was not possible for the non-deep learning-based Gradient Boosted Trees. The ML algorithms are then coupled online to the host ICON model. Our best online performing model, an ablated U-Net excluding precipitating tracer species, indicates higher agreement for simulated precipitation extremes and mean with the high-resolution simulation compared to the traditional scheme. However, a smoothing bias is introduced both in water vapor path and mean precipitation. Online, the ablated U-Net significantly improves stability compared to the non-ablated U-Net and runs stable for the full simulation period of 180 days. Our results hint to the potential to significantly reduce systematic errors with hybrid ESMs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.03251v4</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1029/2024MS004398</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Helge Heuer, Mierk Schwabe, Pierre Gentine, Marco A. Giorgetta, Veronika Eyring</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Super Resolution On Global Weather Forecasts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11502v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Weather forecasting is a vitally important tool for tasks ranging from planning day to day activities to disaster response planning. However, modeling weather has proven to be challenging task due to its chaotic and unpredictable nature. Each variable, from temperature to precipitation to wind, all influence the path the environment will take. As a result, all models tend to rapidly lose accuracy as the temporal range of their forecasts increase. Classical forecasting methods use a myriad of physics-based, numerical, and stochastic techniques to predict the change in weather variables over time. However, such forecasts often require a very large amount of data and are extremely computationally expensive. Furthermore, as climate and global weather patterns change, classical models are substantially more difficult and time-consuming to update for changing environments. Fortunately, with recent advances in deep learning and publicly available high quality weather datasets, deploying learning methods for estimating these complex systems has become feasible. The current state-of-the-art deep learning models have comparable accuracy to the industry standard numerical models and are becoming more ubiquitous in practice due to their adaptability. Our group seeks to improve upon existing deep learning based forecasting methods by increasing spatial resolutions of global weather predictions. Specifically, we are interested in performing super resolution (SR) on GraphCast temperature predictions by increasing the global precision from 1 degree of accuracy to 0.5 degrees, which is approximately 111km and 55km respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11502v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lawrence Zhang, Adam Yang, Rodz Andrie Amor, Bryan Zhang, Dhruv Rao</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
