<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ao-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ao-ph</link>
    <description>physics.ao-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ao-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 04:03:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On the relative humidity of the atmosphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08824v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Water vapour is highly subsaturated in much of the Earth's atmosphere. This has important consequences for water vapour feedback, and also for general phenomena such as the runaway greenhouse. In this chapter, we discuss the processes that create subsaturation, with reference to both observations, general circulation models, and a range of idealized theoretical models which produce subsaturation. While this chapter focuses on subsaturation of water vapour in Earth's atmosphere, the processes discussed are generic to condensible substances in all planetary atmospheres.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08824v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raymond T. Pierrehumbert, Helene Brogniez, Remy Roca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating the Robustness of Extreme Precipitation Super-Resolution Across Climates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09166</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09166v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The coarse spatial resolution of gridded climate models, such as general circulation models, limits their direct use in projecting socially relevant variables like extreme precipitation. Most downscaling methods estimate the conditional distributions of extremes by generating large ensembles, complicating the assessment of robustness under distributional shifts, such as those induced by climate change. To better understand and potentially improve robustness, we propose super-resolving the parameters of the target variable's probability distribution directly using analytically tractable mappings. Within a perfect-model framework over Switzerland, we demonstrate that vector generalized linear and additive models can super-resolve the generalized extreme value distribution of summer hourly precipitation extremes from coarse precipitation fields and topography. We introduce the notion of a "robustness gap", defined as the difference in predictive error between present-trained and future-trained models, and use it to diagnose how model structure affects the generalization of each quantile to a pseudo-global warming scenario. By evaluating multiple model configurations, we also identify an upper limit on the super-resolution factor based on the spatial auto- and cross-correlation of precipitation and elevation, beyond which coarse precipitation loses predictive value. Our framework is broadly applicable to variables governed by parametric distributions and offers a model-agnostic diagnostic for understanding when and why empirical downscaling generalizes to climate change and extremes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09166v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louise Largeau, Erwan Koch, David Leutwyler, Gregoire Mariethoz, Valerie Chavez-Demoulin, Tom Beucler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Systematic Review of Passive Cooling Strategies Integrating Traditional Wisdom and Modern Innovations for Sustainable Development in Arid Urban Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09365v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Urban environments in hot-arid regions are increasingly challenged by rising temperatures, rapid urban expansion, and reliance on energy intensive mechanical cooling systems. This study presents a systematic review of peer reviewed literature from 1980 to 2025 to assess both traditional and contemporary passive cooling strategies tailored for arid urban settings. Following PRISMA 2020 guidelines, 30 high-quality studies were selected from databases including Scopus, Web of Science, ScienceDirect, and Google Scholar. These works span diverse geographical contexts from the Middle East and North Africa to parts of South Asia, and apply methods including field experiments, computer-based simulations, and qualitative analyses. Findings highlight strong consensus around passive principles such as solar control, natural ventilation, and the use of thermal mass. Vernacular solutions like courtyards, wind towers, and thick masonry walls remain effective, while innovations such as cool roofs, phase change materials, and parametric optimization techniques expand the design toolkit. Implementation is often limited by climate variability, cultural shifts, regulations, and economic feasibility. The review concludes that context-sensitive, hybrid solutions combining traditional knowledge with modern technology hold the greatest potential for achieving sustainable thermal comfort. These approaches must be supported by adaptive urban planning, user centered design, and updated building codes. The study offers practical insights for architects, planners, and policymakers aiming to create resilient, low-carbon cities that harmonize cultural identity with environmental responsibility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09365v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiva Manshour, Steffen Lehmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>XiChen: An observation-scalable fully AI-driven global weather forecasting system with 4D variational knowledge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09202v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent advancements in Artificial Intelligence (AI) demonstrate significant potential to revolutionize weather forecasting. However, most AI-driven models rely on Numerical Weather Prediction (NWP) systems for initial condition preparation, which often consumes hours on supercomputers. Here we introduce XiChen, the first observation-scalable fully AI-driven global weather forecasting system, whose entire pipeline, from Data Assimilation (DA) to medium-range forecasting, can be accomplished within only 17 seconds. XiChen is built upon a foundation model that is pre-trained for weather forecasting. Meanwhile, this model is subsequently fine-tuned to serve as both observation operators and DA models, thereby scalably assimilating conventional and raw satellite observations. Furthermore, the integration of four-dimensional variational knowledge ensures that XiChen's DA and medium-range forecasting accuracy rivals that of operational NWP systems, amazingly achieving a skillful forecasting lead time exceeding 8.25 days. These findings demonstrate that XiChen holds strong potential toward fully AI-driven weather forecasting independent of NWP systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09202v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wuxin Wang, Weicheng Ni, Lilan Huang, Tao Hao, Ben Fei, Shuo Ma, Taikang Yuan, Yanlai Zhao, Kefeng Deng, Xiaoyong Li, Boheng Duan, Lei Bai, Kaijun Ren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capturing Unseen Spatial Extremes Through Knowledge-Informed Generative Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09211</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09211v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Observed records of climate extremes provide an incomplete picture of risk, missing "unseen" extremes that exceed historical bounds. In parallel, neglecting spatial dependence undervalues the risk of synchronized hazards that amplify impacts. To address these challenges, we develop DeepX-GAN (Dependence-Enhanced Embedding for Physical eXtremes - Generative Adversarial Network), a knowledge-informed deep generative model designed to better capture the spatial structure of rare extremes. The zero-shot generalizability of DeepX-GAN enables simulation of unseen extremes that fall outside historical experience yet remain statistically plausible. We define two types of unseen extremes: "checkmate" extremes that directly hit targets, and "stalemate" extremes that narrowly miss. These unrealized scenarios expose latent risks in fragile systems and may reinforce a false sense of resilience if overlooked. Near misses, in particular, can prompt either proactive adaptation or dangerous complacency, depending on how they are interpreted. Applying DeepX-GAN to the Middle East and North Africa (MENA), we find that these unseen extremes disproportionately affect regions with high vulnerability and low socioeconomic readiness, but differ in urgency and interpretation. Future warming could expand and redistribute these unseen extremes, with emerging exposure hotspots in Indo-Pakistan and Central Africa. This distributional shift highlights critical blind spots in conventional hazard planning and underscores the need to develop spatially adaptive policies that anticipate emergent risk hotspots rather than simply extrapolating from historical patterns.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09211v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinyue Liu, Xiao Peng, Shuyue Yan, Yuntian Chen, Dongxiao Zhang, Zhixiao Niu, Hui-Min Wang, Xiaogang He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistics of stochastic entropy for recorded transitions between ENSO states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10516</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10516v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyse the transitions between established phases of the El Ni\~no Southern Oscillation (ENSO) by surveying the daily data of the Southern Oscillation Index from an entropic viewpoint using the framework of stochastic Statistical Physics. We evaluate the variation of entropy produced due to each recorded path of that index during each transition as well as taking only into consideration the beginning and the end of the change between phases and verified both integral fluctuation relations. The statistical results show that these entropy variations have not been extreme entropic events; only the transition between the strong $1999-2000$ La Ni\~na to the moderate $2002-2003$ El Ni\~no is at the edge of being so. With that, the present work opens a long and winding avenue of research over the application of stochastic Statistical Physics to Climate Dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10516v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.094201</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 133, 094201 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>S\'ilvio M. Duarte Queir\'os</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Questioning whether seasonal advance of intense tropical cyclones since the 1980s truly exists</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00330v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Shan et al. (2023) recently reported significant seasonal advances of intense tropical cyclones (TCs) in both the Northern Hemisphere (NH) and Southern Hemisphere (SH) since the 1980s, and emphasized the data insensitivity of this conclusion, based on the Advanced Dvorak Technique-Hurricane Satellite (ADT-HURSAT) and the International Best Track Archive for Climate Stewardship (IBTrACS) datasets. However, this conclusion contradicts our recent findings. Following the procedures outlined in Shan et al., our analysis reveals that the seasonal advancing trend of intense TCs does not pass the significance test in the SH. Meanwhile, for the NH, the trend is statistically significant only when using the ADT-HURSAT, but not when using the IBTrACS. These discrepancies may be due to flaws in the calculations performed by Shan et al. The above findings raise doubts about the reproducibility and validity of Shan et al.'s conclusions regarding the global seasonal advance of intense TCs. We argue that the reported seasonal advance of intense TCs since the 1980s is inconclusive, and further investigations are needed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00330v4</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jimin Liu, Jeremy Cheuk-Hin Leung, Wenshou Tian, Hong Huang, Daosheng Xu, Weijing Li, Weihong Qian, Banglin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constructing Extreme Heatwave Storylines with Differentiable Climate Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.10660v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding the plausible upper bounds of extreme weather events is essential for risk assessment in a warming climate. Existing methods, based on large ensembles of physics-based models, are often computationally expensive or lack the fidelity needed to simulate rare, high-impact extremes. Here, we present a novel framework that leverages a differentiable hybrid climate model, NeuralGCM, to optimize initial conditions and generate physically consistent worst-case heatwave trajectories. Applied to the 2021 Pacific Northwest heatwave, our method produces heatwave intensity up to 3.7 $^\circ$C above the most extreme member of a 75-member ensemble. These trajectories feature intensified atmospheric blocking and amplified Rossby wave patterns-hallmarks of severe heat events. Our results demonstrate that differentiable climate models can efficiently explore the upper tails of event likelihoods, providing a powerful new approach for constructing targeted storylines of extreme weather under climate change.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.10660v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tim Whittaker, Alejandro Di Luca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying the Dunkelflaute: An analysis of variable renewable energy droughts in Europe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00244</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00244v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Variable renewable energy droughts, also called "Dunkelflaute", emerge as a challenge for climate-neutral energy systems based on variable renewables. Drawing on 38 historic weather years and an advanced identification method, we characterize European drought events for on- and offshore wind power, solar photovoltaics, and renewable technology portfolios. We show that their characteristics heavily depend on the chosen drought threshold, questioning the usefulness of single-threshold analyses. Applying a multi-threshold framework, we quantify how the complementarity of wind and solar power temporally and spatially alleviates drought frequency, duration, and severity within (portfolio effect) and across countries (balancing effect). We identify the most extreme droughts and show how these drive major discharging periods of long-duration storage in a fully renewable European energy system, based on a policy-relevant decarbonization scenario. Such events comprise sequences of shorter droughts of varying severity. The most extreme event occurred in winter 1996/97 and lasted 55 days in a perfectly interconnected setting. While the average renewable availability during this period was still 47% of its long-run mean, we argue that system planners must consider such events when planning for storage and other flexibility technologies. Methodologically, we conclude that using single calendar years is not suitable for modeling weather-resilient energy scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00244v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Kittel, Wolf-Peter Schill</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-attentive Transformer for Fast and Accurate Postprocessing of Temperature and Wind Speed Forecasts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13957</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13957v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Current postprocessing techniques often require separate models for each lead time and disregard possible inter-ensemble relationships by either correcting each member separately or by employing distributional approaches. In this work, we tackle these shortcomings with an innovative, fast and accurate Transformer which postprocesses each ensemble member individually while allowing information exchange across variables, spatial dimensions and lead times by means of multi-headed self-attention. Weather forecasts are postprocessed over 20 lead times simultaneously while including up to fifteen meteorological predictors. We use the EUPPBench dataset for training which contains ensemble predictions from the European Center for Medium-range Weather Forecasts' integrated forecasting system alongside corresponding observations. The work presented here is the first to postprocess the ten and one hundred-meter wind speed forecasts within this benchmark dataset, while also correcting two-meter temperature. Our approach significantly improves the original forecasts, as measured by the CRPS, with 16.5\% for two-meter temperature, 10\% for ten-meter wind speed and 9\% for one hundred-meter wind speed, outperforming a classical member-by-member approach employed as a competitive benchmark. Furthermore, being up to six times faster, it fulfills the demand for rapid operational weather forecasts in various downstream applications, including renewable energy forecasting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13957v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1175/AIES-D-24-0127.1</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Aaron Van Poecke, Tobias Sebastian Finn, Ruoke Meng, Joris Van den Bergh, Geert Smet, Jonathan Demaeyer, Piet Termonia, Hossein Tabari, Peter Hellinckx</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
