<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ao-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ao-ph</link>
    <description>physics.ao-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ao-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 05:01:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>beta plane corrections to nonlinear atmospheric flow patterns application to jupiters great red spot (GRS) drift dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.21928v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Great Red Spot (GRS) of Jupiter has been observed for over a century, with researchers studying its characteristics and dynamics, including its size, depth, movement, and interactions with its environment. Recently, the f-plane thin-shell asymptotic analysis was used to explain some of the GRS features, but the method failed to capture the observed westward drift of the GRS. In this study, the f-plane theory was extended by including the Rossby parameter in the \beta-plane approximation and using the dimensionless Rossby deformation parameter \gamma, to systematically apply perturbation theory. The westward drift velocity of 3.7 m/s was analytically predicted, which is 95% in agreement with the observed 3.9 m/s. The observed 90-day oscillation in drift rate was explained. Also explained is the north-south asymmetry in circulation patterns. The universality of the \b{eta}-plane theory was demonstrated by its application to the vortices on Saturn, Neptune and Earth, without free parameters. It was demonstrated in this study that for the understanding of long-lived atmospheric vortex dynamics, the planetary vorticity gradient is very critical.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.21928v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oladiran Johnson Abimbola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of the sodium and calcium chlorides uptake on the interfacial behavior of ice: premelting, structure, and dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.21929v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hypothesis: Seawater ice and frozen aqueous solutions in contact with air can exhibit a thin quasi-brine surface layer intruding between ice and vapor, but a detailed characterization of surface properties and its relation to three phase coexistence has been lacking. Using thermodynamic arguments we show how it is possible to characterize the surface layers by comparison to the three phase ice-brine-air bulk phase diagram, despite the difficulty to control or monitor all of the relevant thermodynamic fields of the two component system.
  Simulations: We performed computer simulations of surface briny layers of sodium and calcium chloride adsorbed on ice. Using suitable order parameters and a rigorous geometrical dividing surface, we are able to characterize the layer's thermodynamic state, measure its properties and relate them to the corresponding properties of the bulk solution.
  Results: Our results confirm that undersaturated briny surface layers can form down to the eutectic point, with a maximum concentration that is bound by the liquidus line of the ice-brine phase diagram. Such layers are distinct from finite size realizations of three phase coexistence, and can be regarded as genuine surface states, but their salt content can increase the premelting layer thickness by a factor of two or more. Owing to this significant thickness, these layers can be related to bulk electrolyte solutions of similar concentration, both as regards the structural organization of ions and the dynamical properties of the quasi-liquid film.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.21929v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>{\L}ukasz Baran, Luis G. MacDowell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating satellite and reanalysis rainfall estimates for climate services in agriculture: a comprehensive methodology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.20471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.20471v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High-resolution rainfall estimates from satellite and reanalysis sources (SRE) could play a major role in improving climate services for agriculture. This is particularly relevant in regions that rely on rain-fed farming but lack a dense network of ground-based measurements to provide localised historical climate information, as in most of the Global South. However, there is a need for a framework which practitioners can use to determine the suitability of these estimated data for specific agricultural applications. This paper presents a comprehensive methodology for evaluating the ability of SRE to provide historical rainfall information for agricultural applications, primarily through comparison with ground-based measurements. The methodology comprises five main steps: data selection and pre-processing, spatial and temporal consistency checks, quantitative SRE-gauge comparisons, bias correction, and application specific summaries. The methodology makes use of graphical summaries, standard comparison metrics, and Markov chain models. We describe how users can apply this methodology to evaluate rainfall estimates for specific applications, complementing existing validation studies. Evaluation cases are presented to demonstrate the methodology using five widely used satellite and reanalysis rainfall products and ground-based measurements from 12 stations in Africa and the Caribbean. The case studies demonstrate how the methodology can be applied to examine multiple aspects of the rainfall estimates. While previous validation studies ask "Does the SRE estimate the true rainfall well?", this methodology provides means of establishing "To what extent can an SRE be used for this specific purpose?" and a comprehensive framework for this. This meets a major need for location specific rainfall information to improve climate information services for millions of small-holder farming households.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.20471v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Danny Parsons, David Stern, Denis Ndanguza, Mouhamadou Bamba Sylla, James Musyoka, John Bagiliko, Graham Clarkson, Peter Dorward</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probabilistic Link Budget Analysis for Low Earth Orbit Satellites in the Optical Regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.20908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.20908v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Low Earth Orbit (LEO) optical satellite communication systems face performance challenges due to atmospheric effects such as scintillation, turbulence, wavefront distortion, beam spread, and jitter. This paper presents a comprehensive mathematical model to characterize these effects and their impact on signal propagation. We develop a methodology for dynamically calculating link budgets at any location and time by integrating these models into a probabilistic framework. The approach accounts for spatial and temporal variations in atmospheric conditions, enabling accurate estimation of link loss probabilities. Simulations validate the model's accuracy and applicability to real-world LEO satellite systems. This work offers a robust tool for optimizing link performance and enhancing the reliability of satellite networks, providing valuable insights for system designers and operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.20908v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dhruv Shivkant, Shreyaans Jain, Rohit K Ramakrishnan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
