<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ao-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ao-ph</link>
    <description>physics.ao-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ao-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 04:04:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Energy Spectra of Secondary Particles Induced by Solar Energetic Proton Events and Magnetospheric Effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16269v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the energy spectra of secondary cosmic ray particles associated with two distinct solar events: the magnetospheric effect (ME) of 5 November 2023 and ground-level enhancement (GLE 74) of 11 May 2024. Using data from the SEVAN and Neutron Monitor networks and energy release histograms from particle spectrometers, we reconstruct spectra and identify key differences between ME and GLE. CORSIKA-based simulations reveal that MEs are caused by galactic protons below geomagnetic cutoff rigidities (Rc = 7.1 GV at Aragats) penetrating the magnetosphere during geomagnetic storms, leading to localized flux enhancements at mountain altitudes but not at sea level. In contrast, SEP events initiated by GLEs can involve high-energy solar protons (&gt;10 GeV), producing secondaries that reach sea level at middle latitudes. We present integral energy spectra and spatial correlation of detector responses, demonstrating that SEVAN's energy-resolved data offer new diagnostic tools for identifying hard-spectrum SERs. Our results refine the definition of ME and suggest a strategy for early warning of hazardous solar particle events based on real-time ground-based observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16269v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Chilingarian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variations of the Near-Surface Electric field measured at Aragats during Geomagnetic Storms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16271v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: At least two mechanisms effectively transfer interplanetary magnetic field (IMF) disturbances into the atmosphere. First, the inflow of solar wind into the ionosphere at low latitudes significantly enhances the total vertical electron content, increasing atmospheric conductivity. Second, Forbush decreases (FD) reduce the cosmic ray flux by a few percent, lowering ionization levels at middle latitudes and decreasing conductivity. Changes in atmospheric conductivity affect the global electric circuit and atmospheric electric field (AEF). However, to study the response of AEF to geomagnetic storms (GMS), it is necessary to carefully monitor atmospheric conditions before and during storms, as meteorological influences can be much stronger than those of GMS. Charged clouds above detectors, lightning flashes, and abrupt weather changes significantly impact near-surface electric field (NSEF) variations, which serve as a proxy for AEF measured at the Earth's surface. The facilities at Aragats station monitor all environmental parameters on a one-minute timescale. We analyze four GMS events described in previous studies, detailing the corresponding weather conditions to isolate the genuine influence of GMS on NSEF. The GMS of June 22, 2015, and September 8, 2017, occurred under fair-weather conditions, providing clear evidence of GMS influence on NSEF. These events were long-lasting, positive, and modest, ranging from 0.2 to 0.3 kV/m, and coincided with the depletion phase of FD. The sky was clear, no rain was detected, and lightning flashes from previous thunderstorms were more than 20 km from the station. The other two events did not meet favorable weather criteria, and their occurrence during GMS seemed incidental. We identify a feature that may indicate the solar (FD) origin of NSEF enhancement: a dip in the enhanced NSEF during the daytime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16271v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Chilingarian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast-wave slow-wave spectral deferred correction methods applied to the compressible Euler equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.15985v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates the application of a fast-wave slow-wave spectral deferred correction time-stepping method (FWSW-SDC) to the compressible Euler equations. The resulting model achieves arbitrary order accuracy in time, demonstrating robust performance in standard benchmark idealised test cases for dynamical cores used for numerical weather prediction. The model uses a compatible finite element spatial discretisation, achieving good linear wave dispersion properties without spurious computational modes. A convergence test confirms the model's high temporal accuracy. Arbitrarily high spatial-temporal convergence is demonstrated using a gravity wave test case. The model is further extended to include the parametrisation of a simple physics process by adding two phases of moisture and its validity is demonstrated for a rising thermal problem. Finally, a baroclinic wave in simulated in a Cartesian domain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.15985v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Brown, Joscha Fregin, Thomas Bendall, Thomas Melvin, Daniel Ruprecht, Jemma Shipton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electric field effects on the collision efficiency of uncharged water droplets in a linear flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16010v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the dynamics of collisions between a pair of uncharged conducting droplets under the influence of a uniaxial compressional flow and an external electric field. The near-field asymptotic expression for the electric-field-induced attractive force demonstrate that surface-to-surface contact in finite time is facilitated by overcoming lubrication resistance. We demonstrate the significant role of the external electric field on the relative trajectories of two droplets in a compressional flow and provide estimates of the correlation between collision efficiency and the forces induced by the electric field. For droplet collisions in clouds, continuum lubrication approximations become inadequate to capture collision dynamics, and thus we incorporate non-continuum lubrication interactions into our analysis to address this complexity. Our findings reveal the dependence of collision efficiency on the strength of the electric field, geometry of the two interacting droplets, non-continuum effects, and van der Waals forces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16010v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pijush Patra, Anubhab Roy, J. S. Wettlaufer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Increased hydrogen escape from Mars atmosphere during periods of high obliquity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16692v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It is still unknown how much water has escaped from Mars during its history. Hydrogen escape from Mars's atmosphere probably played a major role in drying the planet, but present-day Hloss rates (about 3x10^26 atoms per second on average) cannot explain the geological evidence for the large volumes of liquid water on ancient Mars. Here we used the three-dimensional Mars-Planetary Climate Model to show that H loss rates could have increased by more than one order of magnitude (6x10^27 atoms per second) during higher spin axis obliquity periods, notably in the last few million years when Mars's obliquity was about 35 deg on average. The resulting accumulated H escape over Mars's history translates into an approx. 80 m global equivalent layer, which is close to the lower limit of geological estimates, assessing the major role of atmospheric escape in drying Mars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16692v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41550-025-02561-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nat Astron (2025), published on-line on 21 May 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gabriella Gilli, Francisco Gonz\'alez-Galindo, Jean-Yves Chaufray, Ehouarn Millour, Fran\c{c}ois Forget, Franck Montmessin, Franck Lef\`evre, Joseph Naar, Yangcheng Luo, Margaux Vals, Lo\"ic Rossi, Miguel \'Angel L\'opez-Valverde, Adri\'an Brines</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatiotemporal spectral transfers in fluid dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02259</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02259v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Motivated by previous work on kinetic energy cascades in the ocean and atmosphere, we develop a spatio-temporal spectral transfer tool that can be used to study scales of variability in generalized dynamical systems. In particular, we use generalized time-frequency methods from signal analysis to broaden the applicability of frequency transfers from theoretical to practical applications such as the study of ocean or atmosphere data or simulation output. We also show that triad interactions in wavenumber used to study kinetic energy and enstrophy cascades can be generalized to study triad interactions in frequency or wavenumber-frequency. We study the effects of sweeping on the locality of frequency transfers and frequency triad interactions to better understand the locality of spatio-temporal frequency transfers. As an illustrative example, we use the spatio-temporal spectral transfer tool to study the results of a simulation of two-dimensional homogeneous isotropic turbulence. This simulated fluid is forced at a well-defined wavenumber and frequency with dissipation occurring at both large and small scales, making this one of the first studies of "modulated turbulence" in two dimensions. Our results show that the spatio-temporal transfers we develop in this paper are robust to potential practical problems such as low sampling rates or nonstationarity in time series of interest. We anticipate that this method will be a useful tool in studying scales of spatio-temporal variability in a wide range of fluids applications as higher resolution data and simulations become more widely available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02259v3</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevFluids.00.004600</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Avik Mondal, Andrew J. Morten, Brian K. Arbic, Glenn R. Flierl, Robert B. Scott, Joseph Skitka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Harnessing natural and mechanical airflows for surface-based atmospheric pollutant removal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11803v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Removal strategies for atmospheric pollutants are increasingly being considered to mitigate global warming and improve public health. However, surface-based removal techniques, such as sorption, catalysis and filtration, are often limited by pollutant transport and removal rate constraints. We evaluate the atmospheric pollutant transport to surfaces and assess the potential of surface-based removal technologies for applications in airflow through cities, HVAC systems and over vehicles. If these removal technologies are applied to their surfaces, cities, solar farms, HVAC systems and filters can achieve atmospheric pollutant removal rates that exceed 1 GtCO$_2$e annually (20-year GWP). Cities have the highest atmospheric pollutant removal potential, with estimates averaging 30 GtCO$_2$, 0.06 GtCH$_4$, 0.0001 GtPM$_{2.5}$, 0.007 GtNO$_\text{x}$ annually. HVAC filters can achieve atmospheric pollutant removal costs as low as \$300 per tCO$_2$e removed when sorption or catalyst technologies are incorporated into their fibre sheets, outperforming the \$2000 per tCO$_2$e removal cost when these technologies are applied to city surfaces. This estimate is based on the literature values for these technologies' costs per square meter. However, our calculations indicate that optimising catalyst properties and surface coverage could lower the cost estimates to below \$100 per tCO$_2$e across these applications. These findings demonstrate that integrating surface-based pollutant removal technologies into infrastructure may offer a scalable pathway to advance climate and health objectives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11803v4</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel D. Tomlinson, Aliki M. Tsopelakou, Tzia M. Onn, Steven R. H. Barrett, Adam M. Boies, Shaun D. Fitzgerald</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
