<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ao-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ao-ph</link>
    <description>physics.ao-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ao-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 02:53:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Year-to-Decadal Temperature Prediction using a Machine Learning Model-Analog Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17583v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multi-year-to-decadal climate prediction is a key tool in understanding the range of potential regional and global climate futures. Here, we present a framework that combines machine learning and analog forecasting for predictions on these timescales. A neural network is used to learn a mask, specific to a region and lead time, with global weights based on relative importance as precursors to the evolution of that prediction target. A library of mask-weighted model states, or potential analogs, are then compared to a single mask-weighted observational state. The known future of the best matching potential analogs serve as the prediction for the future of the observational state. We match and predict 2-meter temperature using the Berkeley Earth Surface Temperature dataset for observations, and a set of CMIP6 models as the analog library. We find improved performance over traditional analog methods and initialized decadal predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17583v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. A. Fernandez, Elizabeth A. Barnes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatiotemporal Forecasting in Climate Data Using EOFs and Machine Learning Models: A Case Study in Chile</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17495v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Effective resource management and environmental planning in regions with high climatic variability, such as Chile, demand advanced predictive tools. This study addresses this challenge by employing an innovative and computationally efficient hybrid methodology that integrates machine learning (ML) methods for time series forecasting with established statistical techniques. The spatiotemporal data undergo decomposition using time-dependent Empirical Orthogonal Functions (EOFs), denoted as \(\phi_{k}(t)\), and their corresponding spatial coefficients, \(\alpha_{k}(s)\), to reduce dimensionality. Wavelet analysis provides high-resolution time and frequency information from the \(\phi_{k}(t)\) functions, while neural networks forecast these functions within a medium-range horizon \(h\). By utilizing various ML models, particularly a Wavelet - ANN hybrid model, we forecast \(\phi_{k}(t+h)\) up to a time horizon \(h\), and subsequently reconstruct the spatiotemporal data using these extended EOFs. This methodology is applied to a grid of climate data covering the territory of Chile. It transitions from a high-dimensional multivariate spatiotemporal data forecasting problem to a low-dimensional univariate forecasting problem. Additionally, cluster analysis with Dynamic Time Warping for defining similarities between rainfall time series, along with spatial coherence and predictability assessments, has been instrumental in identifying geographic areas where model performance is enhanced. This approach also elucidates the reasons behind poor forecast performance in regions or clusters with low spatial coherence and predictability. By utilizing cluster medoids, the forecasting process becomes more practical and efficient. This compound approach significantly reduces computational complexity while generating forecasts of reasonable accuracy and utility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17495v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mauricio Herrera, Francisca Kleisinger, Andr\'es Wils\'on</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MARFA: an Effective Line-by-line Tool For Calculating Molecular Absorption in Planetary Atmospheres</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03418v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present MARFA (Molecular atmospheric Absorption with Rapid and Flexible Analysis) -- an open-source line-by-line tool for calculating absorption coefficients and cross-sections in planetary atmospheres, particularly under conditions of uncertain spectroscopic data and missing continuum functions. MARFA employs an eleven-grid interpolation technique, enabling accurate and efficient computation of far-wing contributions for large line cut-offs. The tool supports flexible parameterization, including line shape functions, wing corrections, user-defined atmospheric profiles, thus, facilitating rapid sensitivity studies for sparse datasets. Spectra are calculated at a high-resolution of about 5E-4 cm-1, optimized for infrared and visible spectral regions where HITRAN-formatted line data is available, yet adaptable to other datasets with available line parameters. Output is represented either in a form of binary lookup tables files, directly compatible with radiative transfer codes or in a human-readable format for data analysis and distribution. The MARFA tool is provided in two ways: through a web application accessible at marfa.app for onboarding and educational usage, and as an open-source code available in a public repository for advanced utilization, development and contributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03418v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail Razumovskiy, Boris Fomin, Denis Astanin</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
