<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CY updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CY</link>
    <description>cs.CY updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CY" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 04:00:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Working with Color: How Color Quantization Can Aid Researchers of Problematic Information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03424v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Analyzing large sets of visual media remains a challenging task, particularly in mixed-method studies dealing with problematic information and human subjects. Using AI tools in such analyses risks reifying and exacerbating biases, as well as untenable computational and cost limitations. As such, we turn to adopting geometric computer graphics and vision methods towards analyzing a large set of images from a problematic information campaign, in conjunction with human-in-the-loop qualitative analysis. We illustrate an effective case of this approach with the implementation of color quantization towards analyzing online hate image at the US-Mexico border, along with a historicist trace of the history of color quantization and skin tone scales, to inform our usage and reclamation of these methodologies from their racist origins. To that end, we scaffold motivations and the need for more researchers to consider the advantages and risks of reclaiming such methodologies in their own work, situated in our case study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03424v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3687019</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Nina Lutz, Jordyn W. Padzensky, Joseph S. Schafer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prioritising Response-able IP Practices in Digitization of Electoral Processes in Africa</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03690v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Globally, people widely regard technology as a solution to global social problems. In a democratic society, its citizens view technology as a way to ensure commitment and sustaining the nation's democracy by allowing them to participate actively in the democratic process. However, despite the hype surrounding technology and development, many developing countries still experience democratic challenges. The democratic challenges have further led to barriers that shape the political landscape, resulting in delusion, disappointment, and failures in the democratic and public good processes, such as the electoral process. This paper explores the relationship between intellectual property (IP) practices and the adoption of digital technologies used in democratic electoral processes. Specifically, it examines how the prioritisation of IP by technology service providers can disrupt socio-material relationships in democratic electoral processes and outcomes. Because of the hard boundaries associated with IP it creates an environment where the systems are controlled solely by technology IP owners, while the consequences of electoral processes are borne by citizens. This questions the response-ability and trust-ability of digital technologies in running democratic processes. Drawing from the parallels in Kenya's general elections of 2017 and 2022, this paper illustrates how IP practices form a hard boundary that impels technology owners to micromanage electoral processes, leading to tensions that potentially create conflict. This finding can be used by decision-makers to adopt digital technologies and protect IP without compromising electoral processes and disrupting relationships in the wider society.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03690v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Angella Ndaka, Samwel Oando, Eucabeth Majiwa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PsyDI: Towards a Personalized and Progressively In-depth Chatbot for Psychological Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03337v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the field of psychology, the static nature and lack of customization of psychological test scales, along with the challenge of quantifying psychological indicators, have long been critical issues. Despite numerous attempts to use AI to address psychological challenges, a dynamically interactive psychological test has yet to emerge. In contrast to traditional psychological assessment methods, we propose PsyDI, a multi-modal, interactive, and customized chatbot for psychological assessments, using the Myers-Briggs Type Indicator (MBTI) as an example. PsyDI initiates with user-related multi-modal information, then engaging in customized interaction to discern the user's MBTI type based on their multiple rounds of responses. Despite these advancements, accurately quantifying absolute value of psychological indicators remains challenging. To tackle such difficulty, we introduce the PsyDI framework that trains LLMs to discern the relative magnitude of psychological traits rather than their absolute values. Through various experiments, we demonstrate the effectiveness of the training techniques proposed in PsyDI on various datasets, and we have also launched its web version, reaching about ~3k accesses. Additionally, comprehensive post-deployment data analysis has provided profound insights into the implications and applications of PsyDI, demonstrating its potential to serve as a general framework for psychological assessment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03337v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xueyan Li, Xinyan Chen, Yazhe Niu, Shuai Hu, Yu Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transit Rider Heat Stress in Atlanta, GA under Current and Future Climate Scenarios</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03457</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03457v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Transit is a crucial mode of transportation, especially in urban areas and for urban and rural disadvantaged communities. Because extreme temperatures often pose threats to the elderly, members of the disability community, and other vulnerable populations, this study seeks to understand the level of influence that extreme temperatures may have on transit users across different demographic groups. In this case study for Atlanta, GA, heat stress is predicted for 2019 transit riders (using transit rider activity survey data) and for three future climate scenarios, SSP245, SSP370, and SSP585, into the year 2100. The HeatPath Analyzer and TransitSim 4.0 models were applied to predict cumulative heat exposure and trip-level risk for 35,999 trip equivalents for an average Atlanta area weekday in the summer of 2019. The analyses show that under 2019 weather conditions, 8.33% of summer trips were estimated to be conducted under extreme heat. With the projected future climate conditions, the percentage of trips under extreme heat risk grows steadily. By 2100, 37.1%, 56.1%, and 76.4% are projected to be under extreme heat risk for scenarios SSP245, SSP370, and SSP585, respectively. Under current weather conditions, Atlanta transit riders that own no vehicles and transit riders that are African American are disproportionately influenced by extreme heat. The disparity between these two groups and other groups of transit riders becomes wider as climate change continues to exacerbate. The findings of the study highlight an urgent need to implement heat mitigation and adaptation strategies in urban transit networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03457v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huiying Fan, Geyu Lyu, Hongyu Lu, Angshuman Guin, Randall Guensler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrating HCI Datasets in Project-Based Machine Learning Courses: A College-Level Review and Case Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03472v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study explores the integration of real-world machine learning (ML) projects using human-computer interfaces (HCI) datasets in college-level courses to enhance both teaching and learning experiences. Employing a comprehensive literature review, course websites analysis, and a detailed case study, the research identifies best practices for incorporating HCI datasets into project-based ML education. Key f indings demonstrate increased student engagement, motivation, and skill development through hands-on projects, while instructors benefit from effective tools for teaching complex concepts. The study also addresses challenges such as data complexity and resource allocation, offering recommendations for future improvements. These insights provide a valuable framework for educators aiming to bridge the gap between</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03472v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction (HCII 2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiaodong Qu, Matthew Key, Eric Luo, Chuhui Qiu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simplifying Scholarly Abstracts for Accessible Digital Libraries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03899v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Standing at the forefront of knowledge dissemination, digital libraries curate vast collections of scientific literature. However, these scholarly writings are often laden with jargon and tailored for domain experts rather than the general public. As librarians, we strive to offer services to a diverse audience, including those with lower reading levels. To extend our services beyond mere access, we propose fine-tuning a language model to rewrite scholarly abstracts into more comprehensible versions, thereby making scholarly literature more accessible when requested. We began by introducing a corpus specifically designed for training models to simplify scholarly abstracts. This corpus consists of over three thousand pairs of abstracts and significance statements from diverse disciplines. We then fine-tuned four language models using this corpus. The outputs from the models were subsequently examined both quantitatively for accessibility and semantic coherence, and qualitatively for language quality, faithfulness, and completeness. Our findings show that the resulting models can improve readability by over three grade levels, while maintaining fidelity to the original content. Although commercial state-of-the-art models still hold an edge, our models are much more compact, can be deployed locally in an affordable manner, and alleviate the privacy concerns associated with using commercial models. We envision this work as a step toward more inclusive and accessible libraries, improving our services for young readers and those without a college degree.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03899v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haining Wang, Jason Clark</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Face of Populism: Examining Differences in Facial Emotional Expressions of Political Leaders Using Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.09914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.09914v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Populist rhetoric employed on online media is characterized as deeply impassioned and often imbued with strong emotions. The aim of this paper is to empirically investigate the differences in affective nonverbal communication of political leaders. We use a deep-learning approach to process a sample of 220 YouTube videos of political leaders from 15 different countries, analyze their facial expressions of emotion and then examine differences in average emotion scores representing the relative presence of 6 emotional states (anger, disgust, fear, happiness, sadness, and surprise) and a neutral expression for each frame of the YouTube video. Based on a sample of manually coded images, we find that this deep-learning approach has 53-60\% agreement with human labels. We observe statistically significant differences in the average score of negative emotions between groups of leaders with varying degrees of populist rhetoric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.09914v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sara Major, Aleksandar Toma\v{s}evi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VoteLab: A Modular and Adaptive Experimentation Platform for Online Collective Decision Making</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.10903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.10903v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Digital democracy and new forms for direct digital participation in policy making gain unprecedented momentum. This is particularly the case for preferential voting methods and decision-support systems designed to promote fairer, more inclusive and legitimate collective decision-making processes in citizens assemblies, participatory budgeting and elections. However, a systematic human experimentation with different voting methods is cumbersome and costly. This paper introduces VoteLab, an open-source and thoroughly-documented platform for modular and adaptive design of voting experiments. It supports to visually and interactively build reusable campaigns with a choice of different voting methods, while voters can easily respond to subscribed voting questions on a smartphone. A proof-of-concept with four voting methods and questions on COVID-19 in an online lab experiment have been used to study the consistency of voting outcomes. It demonstrates the capability of VoteLab to support rigorous experimentation of complex voting scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.10903v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renato Kunz, Fatemeh Banaie, Abhinav Sharma, Carina I. Hausladen, Dirk Helbing, Evangelos Pournaras</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Perceptions and Behaviors of Google Personal Account Holders in Saudi Arabia</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.10148</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.10148v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: While privacy perceptions and behaviors have been investigated in Western societies, little is known about these issues in non-Western societies. To bridge this gap, we interviewed 30 Google personal account holders in Saudi Arabia about their privacy perceptions and behaviors regarding the activity data that Google saves about them. Our study focuses on Google's Activity Controls, which enable users to control whether, and how, Google saves their Web \&amp; App Activity, Location History, and YouTube History. Our results show that although most participants have some level of awareness about Google's data practices and the Activity Controls, many have only vague awareness, and the majority have not used the available controls. When participants viewed their saved activity data, many were surprised by what had been saved. While many participants find Google's use of their data to improve the services provided to them acceptable, the majority find the use of their data for ad purposes unacceptable. We observe that our Saudi participants exhibit similar trends and patterns in privacy awareness, attitudes, preferences, concerns, and behaviors to what has been found in studies in the US. Our results emphasize the need for: 1) improved techniques to inform users about privacy settings during account sign-up, to remind users about their settings, and to raise awareness about privacy settings; 2) improved privacy setting interfaces to reduce the costs that deter many users from changing the settings; and 3) further research to explore privacy concerns in non-Western cultures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.10148v5</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eman Alashwali, Lorrie Faith Cranor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AI, insurance, discrimination and unfair differentiation. An overview and research agenda</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.11892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.11892v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Insurers underwrite risks: they calculate risks and decide on the insurance premium. Insurers seem captivated by two trends. (i) First, insurers could use AI for analysing more and new types of data to assess risks more precisely: data-intensive underwriting. (ii) Second, insurers could use AI to monitor the behaviour of individual consumers in real-time: behaviour-based insurance. For example, some car insurers offer a discount if the consumer agrees to being tracked by the insurer and drives safely. While the two trends bring many advantages, they may also have discriminatory effects on society. This paper focuses on the following question. Which effects related to discrimination and unfair differentiation may occur if insurers follow data-intensive underwriting and behaviour-based insurance?</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.11892v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marvin S. L. van Bekkum, Frederik J. Zuiderveen Borgesius, Tom Heskes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Practical Guide for Causal Pathways and Sub-group Disparity Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02702v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study, we introduce the application of causal disparity analysis to unveil intricate relationships and causal pathways between sensitive attributes and the targeted outcomes within real-world observational data. Our methodology involves employing causal decomposition analysis to quantify and examine the causal interplay between sensitive attributes and outcomes. We also emphasize the significance of integrating heterogeneity assessment in causal disparity analysis to gain deeper insights into the impact of sensitive attributes within specific sub-groups on outcomes. Our two-step investigation focuses on datasets where race serves as the sensitive attribute. The results on two datasets indicate the benefit of leveraging causal analysis and heterogeneity assessment not only for quantifying biases in the data but also for disentangling their influences on outcomes. We demonstrate that the sub-groups identified by our approach to be affected the most by disparities are the ones with the largest ML classification errors. We also show that grouping the data only based on a sensitive attribute is not enough, and through these analyses, we can find sub-groups that are directly affected by disparities. We hope that our findings will encourage the adoption of such methodologies in future ethical AI practices and bias audits, fostering a more equitable and fair technological landscape.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02702v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Farnaz Kohankhaki, Shaina Raza, Oluwanifemi Bamgbose, Deval Pandya, Elham Dolatabadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of Moral Behavior in Heterogeneous Populations of Learning Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04202v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Growing concerns about safety and alignment of AI systems highlight the importance of embedding moral capabilities in artificial agents: a promising solution is the use of learning from experience, i.e., Reinforcement Learning. In multi-agent (social) environments, complex population-level phenomena may emerge from interactions between individual learning agents. Many of the existing studies rely on simulated social dilemma environments to study the interactions of independent learning agents; however, they tend to ignore the moral heterogeneity that is likely to be present in societies of agents in practice. For example, at different points in time a single learning agent may face opponents who are consequentialist (i.e., focused on maximizing outcomes over time), norm-based (i.e., conforming to specific norms), or virtue-based (i.e., considering a combination of different virtues). The extent to which agents' co-development may be impacted by such moral heterogeneity in populations is not well understood. In this paper, we present a study of the learning dynamics of morally heterogeneous populations interacting in a social dilemma setting. Using an Iterated Prisoner's Dilemma environment with a partner selection mechanism, we investigate the extent to which the prevalence of diverse moral agents in populations affects individual agents' learning behaviors and emergent population-level outcomes. We observe several types of non-trivial interactions between pro-social and anti-social agents, and find that certain types of moral agents are able to steer selfish agents towards more cooperative behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04202v5</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elizaveta Tennant, Stephen Hailes, Mirco Musolesi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PraFFL: A Preference-Aware Scheme in Fair Federated Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08973</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.08973v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Fairness in federated learning has emerged as a critical concern, aiming to develop an unbiased model for any special group (e.g., male or female) of sensitive features. However, there is a trade-off between model performance and fairness, i.e., improving model fairness will decrease model performance. Existing approaches have characterized such a trade-off by introducing hyperparameters to quantify client's preferences for model fairness and model performance. Nevertheless, these approaches are limited to scenarios where each client has only a single pre-defined preference, and fail to work in practical systems where each client generally have multiple preferences. The key challenge is to design a method that allows the model to adapt to diverse preferences of each client in real time. To this end, we propose a Preference-aware scheme in Fair Federated Learning paradigm (called PraFFL) to generate preference-wise model in real time. PraFFL can adaptively adjust the model based on each client's preferences to meet their needs. We theoretically prove that PraFFL can offer the optimal model tailored to an arbitrary preference of each client, and show its linear convergence. Experimental results show that our proposed PraFFL outperforms five fair federated learning algorithms in terms of the model's capability of adapting to clients' different preferences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.08973v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rongguang Ye, Wei-Bin Kou, Ming Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SoK: Attacks on DAOs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.15071v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Decentralized Autonomous Organizations (DAOs) are blockchain-based organizations that facilitate decentralized governance. Today, DAOs not only hold billions of dollars in their treasury but also govern many of the most popular Decentralized Finance (DeFi) protocols. This paper systematically analyses security threats to DAOs, focusing on the types of attacks they face. We study attacks on DAOs that took place in the past, attacks that have been theorized to be possible, and potential attacks that were uncovered and prevented in audits. For each of these (potential) attacks, we describe and categorize the attack vectors utilized into four categories. This reveals that while many attacks on DAOs take advantage of the less tangible and more complex human nature involved in governance, audits tend to focus on code and protocol vulnerabilities. Thus, additionally, the paper examines empirical data on DAO vulnerabilities, outlines risk factors contributing to these attacks, and suggests mitigation strategies to safeguard against such vulnerabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.15071v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rainer Feichtinger, Robin Fritsch, Lioba Heimbach, Yann Vonlanthen, Roger Wattenhofer</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
