<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CY updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CY</link>
    <description>cs.CY updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CY" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 02:05:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Testing GPT-4-o1-preview on math and science problems: A follow-up study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22340</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22340v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In August 2023, Scott Aaronson and I reported the results of testing GPT4 with the Wolfram Alpha and Code Interpreter plug-ins over a collection of 105 original high-school level and college-level science and math problems (Davis and Aaronson, 2023). In September 2024, I tested the recently released model GPT-4o1-preview on the same collection. Overall I found that performance had significantly improved, but was still considerably short of perfect. In particular, problems that involve spatial reasoning are often stumbling blocks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22340v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ernest Davis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving the accuracy of food security predictions by integrating conflict data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22342v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Violence and armed conflicts have emerged as prominent factors driving food crises. However, the extent of their impact remains largely unexplored. This paper provides an in-depth analysis of the impact of violent conflicts on food security in Africa. We performed a comprehensive correlation analysis using data from the Famine Early Warning Systems Network (FEWSNET) and the Armed Conflict Location Event Data (ACLED). Our results show that using conflict data to train machine learning models leads to a 1.5% increase in accuracy compared to models that do not incorporate conflict-related information. The key contribution of this study is the quantitative analysis of the impact of conflicts on food security predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22342v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Bertetti, Paolo Agnolucci, Alvaro Calzadilla, Licia Capra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The State of Data Curation at NeurIPS: An Assessment of Dataset Development Practices in the Datasets and Benchmarks Track</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22473</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22473v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Data curation is a field with origins in librarianship and archives, whose scholarship and thinking on data issues go back centuries, if not millennia. The field of machine learning is increasingly observing the importance of data curation to the advancement of both applications and fundamental understanding of machine learning models - evidenced not least by the creation of the Datasets and Benchmarks track itself. This work provides an analysis of dataset development practices at NeurIPS through the lens of data curation. We present an evaluation framework for dataset documentation, consisting of a rubric and toolkit developed through a literature review of data curation principles. We use the framework to assess the strengths and weaknesses in current dataset development practices of 60 datasets published in the NeurIPS Datasets and Benchmarks track from 2021-2023. We summarize key findings and trends. Results indicate greater need for documentation about environmental footprint, ethical considerations, and data management. We suggest targeted strategies and resources to improve documentation in these areas and provide recommendations for the NeurIPS peer-review process that prioritize rigorous data curation in ML. Finally, we provide results in the format of a dataset that showcases aspects of recommended data curation practices. Our rubric and results are of interest for improving data curation practices broadly in the field of ML as well as to data curation and science and technology studies scholars studying practices in ML. Our aim is to support continued improvement in interdisciplinary research on dataset practices, ultimately improving the reusability and reproducibility of new datasets and benchmarks, enabling standardized and informed human oversight, and strengthening the foundation of rigorous and responsible ML research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22473v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eshta Bhardwaj, Harshit Gujral, Siyi Wu, Ciara Zogheib, Tegan Maharaj, Christoph Becker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Evolution Of The Digital Inheritance: Legal, Technical, And Practical Dimensions Of Cryptocurrency Transfer Through Succession In French-Inspired Legal Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22907v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In recent years, cryptocurrencies have enjoyed increased popularity in all domains. Thus, in this context, it is important to understand how these digital assets can be transmitted, both legally and efficiently, in the event of the death of their owner. The present paper analyses the mechanisms of cryptocurrencies, analysing from a technical point of view aspects related to blockchain technology, virtual wallets or cryptographic keys, as well as various types of operations regarding this type of virtual currencies. The study also examines the legal aspects related to cryptocurrencies, with an emphasis on the diversity of their status in different global jurisdictions as well as the impact on inheritance planning. The case studies present tangible examples related to successions with cryptocurrencies as the main object, thus completing the exposition related to the main challenges faced by the heirs in the transfer process. In this way, this paper offers possible solutions and recommendations related to inheritance planning with cryptocurrencies as its main object, including the legal and fiscal aspects that must be taken into account when planning a digital succession.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22907v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cristina Carata, Ana-Luisa Chelaru</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The SPORT-C Intervention: An Integration of Sports, Case-Based Pedagogy and Systems Thinking Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.11755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.11755v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The STEM field is unrepresentative of the population it serves. Due to a lack of cultural relevance in STEM courses, there is a dissociation between the lived experience of students from underrepresented racial groups (URG) and STEM course material. The SPORT-C intervention is a framework that combines sports, systems thinking learning, and a case-based pedagogy into an activity that can be used in any STEM course. A pilot study was conducted to determine the viability of the SPORT-C intervention in a classroom setting and determine if it was worth further investigating and if any impact differed by racial identity. The findings from this study implicate that the SPORT-C intervention has an impact on the motivation levels of students to participate in STEM courses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.11755v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ed-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeffrey Basoah, William Scherer, Karis Boyd-Sinkler, Reid Bailey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search Engines in an AI Era: The False Promise of Factual and Verifiable Source-Cited Responses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22349v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Large Language Model (LLM)-based applications are graduating from research prototypes to products serving millions of users, influencing how people write and consume information. A prominent example is the appearance of Answer Engines: LLM-based generative search engines supplanting traditional search engines. Answer engines not only retrieve relevant sources to a user query but synthesize answer summaries that cite the sources. To understand these systems' limitations, we first conducted a study with 21 participants, evaluating interactions with answer vs. traditional search engines and identifying 16 answer engine limitations. From these insights, we propose 16 answer engine design recommendations, linked to 8 metrics. An automated evaluation implementing our metrics on three popular engines (You.com, Perplexity.ai, BingChat) quantifies common limitations (e.g., frequent hallucination, inaccurate citation) and unique features (e.g., variation in answer confidence), with results mirroring user study insights. We release our Answer Engine Evaluation benchmark (AEE) to facilitate transparent evaluation of LLM-based applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22349v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pranav Narayanan Venkit, Philippe Laban, Yilun Zhou, Yixin Mao, Chien-Sheng Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FNDEX: Fake News and Doxxing Detection with Explainable AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22390v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The widespread and diverse online media platforms and other internet-driven communication technologies have presented significant challenges in defining the boundaries of freedom of expression. Consequently, the internet has been transformed into a potential cyber weapon. Within this evolving landscape, two particularly hazardous phenomena have emerged: fake news and doxxing. Although these threats have been subjects of extensive scholarly analysis, the crossroads where they intersect remain unexplored. This research addresses this convergence by introducing a novel system. The Fake News and Doxxing Detection with Explainable Artificial Intelligence (FNDEX) system leverages the capabilities of three distinct transformer models to achieve high-performance detection for both fake news and doxxing. To enhance data security, a rigorous three-step anonymization process is employed, rooted in a pattern-based approach for anonymizing personally identifiable information. Finally, this research emphasizes the importance of generating coherent explanations for the outcomes produced by both detection models. Our experiments on realistic datasets demonstrate that our system significantly outperforms the existing baselines</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22390v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dorsaf Sallami, Esma A\"imeur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ethical Statistical Practice and Ethical AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22475</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22475v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Artificial Intelligence (AI) is a field that utilizes computing and often, data and statistics, intensively together to solve problems or make predictions. AI has been evolving with literally unbelievable speed over the past few years, and this has led to an increase in social, cultural, industrial, scientific, and governmental concerns about the ethical development and use of AI systems worldwide. The ASA has issued a statement on ethical statistical practice and AI (ASA, 2024), which echoes similar statements from other groups. Here we discuss the support for ethical statistical practice and ethical AI that has been established in long-standing human rights law and ethical practice standards for computing and statistics. There are multiple sources of support for ethical statistical practice and ethical AI deriving from these source documents, which are critical for strengthening the operationalization of the "Statement on Ethical AI for Statistics Practitioners". These resources are explicated for interested readers to utilize to guide their development and use of AI in, and through, their statistical practice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22475v1</guid>
      <category>stat.OT</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rochelle E. Tractenberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Graph-Based Model for Vehicle-Centric Data Sharing Ecosystem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22897</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22897v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The development of technologies has prompted a paradigm shift in the automotive industry, with an increasing focus on connected services and autonomous driving capabilities. This transformation allows vehicles to collect and share vast amounts of vehicle-specific and personal data. While these technological advancements offer enhanced user experiences, they also raise privacy concerns. To understand the ecosystem of data collection and sharing in modern vehicles, we adopted the ontology 101 methodology to incorporate information extracted from different sources, including analysis of privacy policies using GPT-4, a small-scale systematic literature review, and an existing ontology, to develop a high-level conceptual graph-based model, aiming to get insights into how modern vehicles handle data exchange among different parties. This serves as a foundational model with the flexibility and scalability to further expand for modelling and analysing data sharing practices across diverse contexts. Two realistic examples were developed to demonstrate the usefulness and effectiveness of discovering insights into privacy regarding vehicle-related data sharing. We also recommend several future research directions, such as exploring advanced ontology languages for reasoning tasks, supporting topological analysis for discovering data privacy risks/concerns, and developing useful tools for comparative analysis, to strengthen the understanding of the vehicle-centric data sharing ecosystem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22897v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haiyue Yuan, Ali Raza, Nikolay Matyunin, Jibesh Patra, Shujun Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Good, the Bad, and the Ugly: The Role of AI Quality Disclosure in Lie Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23143v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate how low-quality AI advisors, lacking quality disclosures, can help spread text-based lies while seeming to help people detect lies. Participants in our experiment discern truth from lies by evaluating transcripts from a game show that mimicked deceptive social media exchanges on topics with objective truths. We find that when relying on low-quality advisors without disclosures, participants' truth-detection rates fall below their own abilities, which recovered once the AI's true effectiveness was revealed. Conversely, high-quality advisor enhances truth detection, regardless of disclosure. We discover that participants' expectations about AI capabilities contribute to their undue reliance on opaque, low-quality advisors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23143v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haimanti Bhattacharya, Subhasish Dugar, Sanchaita Hazra, Bodhisattwa Prasad Majumder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CRAFT@Large: Building Community Through Co-Making</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23239v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: CRAFT@Large (C@L) is an initiative launched by the MakerLAB at Cornell Tech to create an inclusive environment for the intercultural and intergenerational exchange of ideas through making. With our approach, we challenge the traditional definition of community outreach performed by academic makerspaces. Existing academic makerspaces often perform community engagement by only offering hourly, one-time workshops or by having community members provide a problem that is then used by students as a project assignment. These approaches position community members as occasional visitors and non-equal contributors, which not only conflict with the core values of co-creation but also limit the makerspaces' impact on connecting the universities and the communities. C@L explored an alternative approach in which we invited community members as long-term and equal co-makers into the academic makerspaces. In this article, we showcase two sets of collaborations that illustrate the continuity of people through co-making. We present how academic makerspaces can function as a hub that connects community members and partner organizations with the campus community in a long-term relationship.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23239v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Symposium on Academic Makerspaces. 6 (2021)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yiran Zhao, Maria Alinea-Bravo, Niti Parikh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AI, insurance, discrimination and unfair differentiation. An overview and research agenda</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.11892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.11892v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Insurers underwrite risks: they calculate risks and decide on the insurance premium. Insurers seem captivated by two trends enabled by Artificial Intelligence (AI). (i) First, insurers could use AI for analysing more and new types of data to assess risks more precisely: data-intensive underwriting. (ii) Second, insurers could use AI to monitor the behaviour of individual consumers in real-time: behaviour-based insurance. For example, some car insurers offer a discount if the consumer agrees to being tracked by the insurer and drives safely. While the two trends bring many advantages, they may also have discriminatory effects on society. This paper focuses on the following question. Which effects related to discrimination and unfair differentiation may occur if insurers follow data-intensive underwriting and behaviour-based insurance? Researchers and policymakers working in other sectors may also find the paper useful, as the insurance sector has decades of experience with statistics and forms of AI. Moreover, some questions that arise in the insurance sector are important in other sectors too.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.11892v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marvin van Bekkum, Frederik Zuiderveen Borgesius, Tom Heskes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charting the Landscape of Nefarious Uses of Generative Artificial Intelligence for Online Election Interference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01862v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Generative Artificial Intelligence (GenAI) and Large Language Models (LLMs) pose significant risks, particularly in the realm of online election interference. This paper explores the nefarious applications of GenAI, highlighting their potential to disrupt democratic processes through deepfakes, botnets, targeted misinformation campaigns, and synthetic identities. By examining recent case studies and public incidents, we illustrate how malicious actors exploit these technologies to try influencing voter behavior, spread disinformation, and undermine public trust in electoral systems. The paper also discusses the societal implications of these threats, emphasizing the urgent need for robust mitigation strategies and international cooperation to safeguard democratic integrity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01862v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emilio Ferrara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Adopt Generative AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19806v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent advancements in generative AI, exemplified by ChatGPT, have dramatically transformed how people access information. Despite its powerful capabilities, the benefits it provides may not be equally distributed among individuals - a phenomenon referred to as the digital divide. Building upon prior literature, we propose two forms of digital divide in the generative AI adoption process: (i) the learning divide, capturing individuals' heterogeneous abilities to update their perceived utility of ChatGPT; and (ii) the utility divide, representing differences in individuals' actual utility derived from per use of ChatGPT. To evaluate these two divides, we develop a Bayesian learning model that incorporates demographic heterogeneities in both the utility and signal functions. Leveraging a six-month clickstream dataset, we estimate the model and find significant learning and utility divides across various demographic attributes. Interestingly, lower-educated and non-white individuals derive higher utility gains from ChatGPT but learn about its utility at a slower rate. Furthermore, males, younger individuals, and those with an IT background not only derive higher utility per use from ChatGPT but also learn about its utility more rapidly. Besides, we document a phenomenon termed the belief trap, wherein users underestimate ChatGPT's utility, opt not to use the tool, and consequently lack new experiences to update their perceptions, leading to continued underutilization. Our simulation further demonstrates that the learning divide can significantly affect the probability of falling into the belief trap, another form of the digital divide in adoption outcomes (i.e., outcome divide); however, offering training programs can alleviate the belief trap and mitigate the divide.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19806v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lijia Ma, Xingchen Xu, Yumei He, Yong Tan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intelligent Environmental Empathy (IEE): A new power and platform to fostering green obligation for climate peace and justice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21536v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose Intelligent Environmental Empathy (IEE) as a new driver for climate peace and justice, as an emerging issue in the age of big data. We first show that the authoritarian top-down intergovernmental cooperation, through international organizations (e.g., UNEP) for climate justice, could not overcome environmental issues and crevices so far. We elaborate on four grounds of climate injustice (i.e., teleological origin, axiological origin, formation cause, and social epistemic cause), and explain how the lack of empathy and environmental motivation on a global scale causes the failure of all the authoritarian top-down intergovernmental cooperation. Addressing all these issues requires a new button-up approach to climate peace and justice. Secondly, focusing on the intersection of AI, environmental empathy, and climate justice, we propose a model of Intelligent Environmental Empathy (IEE) for climate peace and justice at the operational level. IEE is empowered by the new power of environmental empathy (as a driver of green obligation for climate justice) and putative decentralized platform of AI (as an operative system against free riders), which Initially, impact citizens and some middle-class decision makers, such as city planners and local administrators, but will eventually affect global decision-makers as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21536v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saleh Afroogh, Ali Mostafavi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fairness in Ranking under Disparate Uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.01610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.01610v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Ranking is a ubiquitous method for focusing the attention of human evaluators on a manageable subset of options. Its use as part of human decision-making processes ranges from surfacing potentially relevant products on an e-commerce site to prioritizing college applications for human review. While ranking can make human evaluation more effective by focusing attention on the most promising options, we argue that it can introduce unfairness if the uncertainty of the underlying relevance model differs between groups of options. Unfortunately, such disparity in uncertainty appears widespread, often to the detriment of minority groups for which relevance estimates can have higher uncertainty due to a lack of data or appropriate features. To address this fairness issue, we propose Equal-Opportunity Ranking (EOR) as a new fairness criterion for ranking and show that it corresponds to a group-wise fair lottery among the relevant options even in the presence of disparate uncertainty. EOR optimizes for an even cost burden on all groups, unlike the conventional Probability Ranking Principle, and is fundamentally different from existing notions of fairness in rankings, such as demographic parity and proportional Rooney rule constraints that are motivated by proportional representation relative to group size. To make EOR ranking practical, we present an efficient algorithm for computing it in time $O(n \log(n))$ and prove its close approximation guarantee to the globally optimal solution. In a comprehensive empirical evaluation on synthetic data, a US Census dataset, and a real-world audit of Amazon search queries, we find that the algorithm reliably guarantees EOR fairness while providing effective rankings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.01610v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3689904.3694703</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Richa Rastogi, Thorsten Joachims</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping the DeFi Crime Landscape: An Evidence-based Picture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.04356</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.04356v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Decentralized finance (DeFi) has been the target of numerous profit-driven crimes, but the prevalence and cumulative impact of these crimes have not yet been assessed. This study provides a comprehensive assessment of profit-driven crimes targeting the DeFi sector. We collected data on 1153 crime events from 2017 to 2022. Of these, 1,048 were related to DeFi (the main focus of this study) and 105 to centralized finance (CeFi). The findings show that the entire cryptoasset industry has suffered a minimum loss of US$30B, with two thirds related to CeFi and one third to DeFi. Focusing on DeFi, a taxonomy was developed to clarify the similarities and differences among these crimes. All events were mapped onto the DeFi stack to assess the impacted technical layers, and the financial damages were quantified to gauge their scale. The results highlight that during an attack, a DeFi actor (an entity developing a DeFi technology) can serve as a direct target (due to technical vulnerabilities or exploitation of human risks), as a perpetrator (through malicious uses of contracts or market manipulations), or as an intermediary (by being imitated through, for example, phishing scams). The findings also show that DeFi actors are the first victims of crimes targeting the DeFi industry: 52.2% of events targeted them, primarily due to technical vulnerabilities at the protocol layer, and these events accounted for 83% of all financial damages. Alternatively, in 40.7% of events, DeFi actors were themselves malicious perpetrators, predominantly misusing contracts at the cryptoasset layer (e.g., rug pull scams). However, these events accounted for only 17% of all financial damages. The study offers a preliminary assessment of the size and scope of crime events within the DeFi sector and highlights the vulnerable position of DeFi actors in the ecosystem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.04356v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Catherine Carpentier-Desjardins, Masarah Paquet-Clouston, Stefan Kitzler, Bernhard Haslhofer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fair Wasserstein Coresets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.05436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.05436v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Data distillation and coresets have emerged as popular approaches to generate a smaller representative set of samples for downstream learning tasks to handle large-scale datasets. At the same time, machine learning is being increasingly applied to decision-making processes at a societal level, making it imperative for modelers to address inherent biases towards subgroups present in the data. While current approaches focus on creating fair synthetic representative samples by optimizing local properties relative to the original samples, their impact on downstream learning processes has yet to be explored. In this work, we present fair Wasserstein coresets (FWC), a novel coreset approach which generates fair synthetic representative samples along with sample-level weights to be used in downstream learning tasks. FWC uses an efficient majority minimization algorithm to minimize the Wasserstein distance between the original dataset and the weighted synthetic samples while enforcing demographic parity. We show that an unconstrained version of FWC is equivalent to Lloyd's algorithm for k-medians and k-means clustering. Experiments conducted on both synthetic and real datasets show that FWC: (i) achieves a competitive fairness-utility tradeoff in downstream models compared to existing approaches, (ii) improves downstream fairness when added to the existing training data and (iii) can be used to reduce biases in predictions from large language models (GPT-3.5 and GPT-4).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.05436v4</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zikai Xiong, Niccol\`o Dalmasso, Shubham Sharma, Freddy Lecue, Daniele Magazzeni, Vamsi K. Potluru, Tucker Balch, Manuela Veloso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aequitas Flow: Streamlining Fair ML Experimentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05809v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Aequitas Flow is an open-source framework and toolkit for end-to-end Fair Machine Learning (ML) experimentation, and benchmarking in Python. This package fills integration gaps that exist in other fair ML packages. In addition to the existing audit capabilities in Aequitas, the Aequitas Flow module provides a pipeline for fairness-aware model training, hyperparameter optimization, and evaluation, enabling easy-to-use and rapid experiments and analysis of results. Aimed at ML practitioners and researchers, the framework offers implementations of methods, datasets, metrics, and standard interfaces for these components to improve extensibility. By facilitating the development of fair ML practices, Aequitas Flow hopes to enhance the incorporation of fairness concepts in AI systems making AI systems more robust and fair.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05809v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S\'ergio Jesus, Pedro Saleiro, In\^es Oliveira e Silva, Beatriz M. Jorge, Rita P. Ribeiro, Jo\~ao Gama, Pedro Bizarro, Rayid Ghani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting and Mitigating Bias in Algorithms Used to Disseminate Information in Social Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12764v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Social connections are conduits through which individuals communicate, information propagates, and diseases spread. Identifying individuals who are more likely to adopt ideas and spread them is essential in order to develop effective information campaigns, maximize the reach of resources, and fight epidemics. Influence maximization algorithms are used to identify sets of influencers. Based on extensive computer simulations on synthetic and ten diverse real-world social networks we show that seeding information using these methods creates information gaps. Our results show that these algorithms select influencers who do not disseminate information equitably, threatening to create an increasingly unequal society. To overcome this issue we devise a multi-objective algorithm which maximizes influence and information equity. Our results demonstrate it is possible to reduce vulnerability at a relatively low trade-off with respect to spread. This highlights that in our search for maximizing information we do not need to compromise on information equality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12764v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vedran Sekara, Ivan Dotu, Manuel Cebrian, Esteban Moro, Manuel Garcia-Herranz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CARES: A Comprehensive Benchmark of Trustworthiness in Medical Vision Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06007</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06007v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Artificial intelligence has significantly impacted medical applications, particularly with the advent of Medical Large Vision Language Models (Med-LVLMs), sparking optimism for the future of automated and personalized healthcare. However, the trustworthiness of Med-LVLMs remains unverified, posing significant risks for future model deployment. In this paper, we introduce CARES and aim to comprehensively evaluate the Trustworthiness of Med-LVLMs across the medical domain. We assess the trustworthiness of Med-LVLMs across five dimensions, including trustfulness, fairness, safety, privacy, and robustness. CARES comprises about 41K question-answer pairs in both closed and open-ended formats, covering 16 medical image modalities and 27 anatomical regions. Our analysis reveals that the models consistently exhibit concerns regarding trustworthiness, often displaying factual inaccuracies and failing to maintain fairness across different demographic groups. Furthermore, they are vulnerable to attacks and demonstrate a lack of privacy awareness. We publicly release our benchmark and code in https://cares-ai.github.io/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06007v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peng Xia, Ze Chen, Juanxi Tian, Yangrui Gong, Ruibo Hou, Yue Xu, Zhenbang Wu, Zhiyuan Fan, Yiyang Zhou, Kangyu Zhu, Wenhao Zheng, Zhaoyang Wang, Xiao Wang, Xuchao Zhang, Chetan Bansal, Marc Niethammer, Junzhou Huang, Hongtu Zhu, Yun Li, Jimeng Sun, Zongyuan Ge, Gang Li, James Zou, Huaxiu Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breach By A Thousand Leaks: Unsafe Information Leakage in `Safe' AI Responses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02551v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Vulnerability of Frontier language models to misuse and jailbreaks has prompted the development of safety measures like filters and alignment training in an effort to ensure safety through robustness to adversarially crafted prompts. We assert that robustness is fundamentally insufficient for ensuring safety goals, and current defenses and evaluation methods fail to account for risks of dual-intent queries and their composition for malicious goals. To quantify these risks, we introduce a new safety evaluation framework based on impermissible information leakage of model outputs and demonstrate how our proposed question-decomposition attack can extract dangerous knowledge from a censored LLM more effectively than traditional jailbreaking. Underlying our proposed evaluation method is a novel information-theoretic threat model of inferential adversaries, distinguished from security adversaries, such as jailbreaks, in that success is measured by inferring impermissible knowledge from victim outputs as opposed to forcing explicitly impermissible outputs from the victim. Through our information-theoretic framework, we show that to ensure safety against inferential adversaries, defense mechanisms must ensure information censorship, bounding the leakage of impermissible information. However, we prove that such defenses inevitably incur a safety-utility trade-off.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02551v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Glukhov, Ziwen Han, Ilia Shumailov, Vardan Papyan, Nicolas Papernot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Questionable practices in machine learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12220</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.12220v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Evaluating modern ML models is hard. The strong incentive for researchers and companies to report a state-of-the-art result on some metric often leads to questionable research practices (QRPs): bad practices which fall short of outright research fraud. We describe 44 such practices which can undermine reported results, giving examples where possible. Our list emphasises the evaluation of large language models (LLMs) on public benchmarks. We also discuss "irreproducible research practices", i.e. decisions that make it difficult or impossible for other researchers to reproduce, build on or audit previous research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.12220v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gavin Leech, Juan J. Vazquez, Niclas Kupper, Misha Yagudin, Laurence Aitchison</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Still More Shades of Null: An Evaluation Suite for Responsible Missing Value Imputation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07510v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Data missingness is a practical challenge of sustained interest to the scientific community. In this paper, we present Shades-of-Null, an evaluation suite for responsible missing value imputation. Our work is novel in two ways (i) we model realistic and socially-salient missingness scenarios that go beyond Rubin's classic Missing Completely at Random (MCAR), Missing At Random (MAR) and Missing Not At Random (MNAR) settings, to include multi-mechanism missingness (when different missingness patterns co-exist in the data) and missingness shift (when the missingness mechanism changes between training and test) (ii) we evaluate imputers holistically, based on imputation quality, as well as on the predictive performance, fairness and stability of the models that are trained and tested on the data post-imputation.
  We use Shades-of-Null to conduct a large-scale empirical study involving 23,940 experimental pipelines, and find that while there is no single best-performing imputation approach for all missingness types, interesting trade-offs arise between predictive performance, fairness and stability, based on the combination of missingness scenario, imputer choice, and the architecture of the predictive model. We make Shades-of-Null publicly available, to enable researchers to rigorously evaluate missing value imputation methods on a wide range of metrics in plausible and socially meaningful scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07510v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Falaah Arif Khan, Denys Herasymuk, Nazar Protsiv, Julia Stoyanovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Instigating Cooperation among LLM Agents Using Adaptive Information Modulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10372v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel framework combining LLM agents as proxies for human strategic behavior with reinforcement learning (RL) to engage these agents in evolving strategic interactions within team environments. Our approach extends traditional agent-based simulations by using strategic LLM agents (SLA) and introducing dynamic and adaptive governance through a pro-social promoting RL agent (PPA) that modulates information access across agents in a network, optimizing social welfare and promoting pro-social behavior. Through validation in iterative games, including the prisoner dilemma, we demonstrate that SLA agents exhibit nuanced strategic adaptations. The PPA agent effectively learns to adjust information transparency, resulting in enhanced cooperation rates. This framework offers significant insights into AI-mediated social dynamics, contributing to the deployment of AI in real-world team settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10372v3</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiliang Chen, Sepehr Ilami, Nunzio Lore, Babak Heydari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncovering Coordinated Cross-Platform Information Operations Threatening the Integrity of the 2024 U.S. Presidential Election Online Discussion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.15402v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Information Operations (IOs) pose a significant threat to the integrity of democratic processes, with the potential to influence election-related online discourse. In anticipation of the 2024 U.S. presidential election, we present a study aimed at uncovering the digital traces of coordinated IOs on $\mathbb{X}$ (formerly Twitter). Using our machine learning framework for detecting online coordination, we analyze a dataset comprising election-related conversations on $\mathbb{X}$ from May 2024. This reveals a network of coordinated inauthentic actors, displaying notable similarities in their link-sharing behaviors. Our analysis shows concerted efforts by these accounts to disseminate misleading, redundant, and biased information across the Web through a coordinated cross-platform information operation: The links shared by this network frequently direct users to other social media platforms or suspicious websites featuring low-quality political content and, in turn, promoting the same $\mathbb{X}$ and YouTube accounts. Members of this network also shared deceptive images generated by AI, accompanied by language attacking political figures and symbolic imagery intended to convey power and dominance. While $\mathbb{X}$ has suspended a subset of these accounts, more than 75% of the coordinated network remains active. Our findings underscore the critical role of developing computational models to scale up the detection of threats on large social media platforms, and emphasize the broader implications of these techniques to detect IOs across the wider Web.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.15402v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Minici, Luca Luceri, Federico Cinus, Emilio Ferrara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GPT-4o reads the mind in the eyes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22309v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Large Language Models (LLMs) are capable of reproducing human-like inferences, including inferences about emotions and mental states, from text. Whether this capability extends beyond text to other modalities remains unclear. Humans possess a sophisticated ability to read the mind in the eyes of other people. Here we tested whether this ability is also present in GPT-4o, a multimodal LLM. Using two versions of a widely used theory of mind test, the Reading the Mind in Eyes Test and the Multiracial Reading the Mind in the Eyes Test, we found that GPT-4o outperformed humans in interpreting mental states from upright faces but underperformed humans when faces were inverted. While humans in our sample showed no difference between White and Non-white faces, GPT-4o's accuracy was higher for White than for Non-white faces. GPT-4o's errors were not random but revealed a highly consistent, yet incorrect, processing of mental-state information across trials, with an orientation-dependent error structure that qualitatively differed from that of humans for inverted faces but not for upright faces. These findings highlight how advanced mental state inference abilities and human-like face processing signatures, such as inversion effects, coexist in GPT-4o alongside substantial differences in information processing compared to humans.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22309v2</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James W. A. Strachan, Oriana Pansardi, Eugenio Scaliti, Marco Celotto, Krati Saxena, Chunzhi Yi, Fabio Manzi, Alessandro Rufo, Guido Manzi, Michael S. A. Graziano, Stefano Panzeri, Cristina Becchio</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
