<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CY updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CY</link>
    <description>cs.CY updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CY" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 01:20:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>PAPPL: Personalized AI-Powered Progressive Learning Platform</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14109</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14109v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Engineering education has historically been constrained by rigid, standardized frameworks, often neglecting students' diverse learning needs and interests. While significant advancements have been made in online and personalized education within K-12 and foundational sciences, engineering education at both undergraduate and graduate levels continues to lag in adopting similar innovations. Traditional evaluation methods, such as exams and homework assignments, frequently overlook individual student requirements, impeding personalized educational experiences. To address these limitations, this paper introduces the Personalized AI-Powered Progressive Learning (PAPPL) platform, an advanced Intelligent Tutoring System (ITS) designed specifically for engineering education. It highlights the development of a scalable, data-driven tutoring environment leveraging cutting-edge AI technology to enhance personalized learning across diverse academic disciplines, particularly in STEM fields. PAPPL integrates core ITS components including the expert module, student module, tutor module, and user interface, and utilizes GPT-4o, a sophisticated large language model (LLM), to deliver context-sensitive and pedagogically sound hints based on students' interactions. The system uniquely records student attempts, detects recurring misconceptions, and generates progressively targeted feedback, providing personalized assistance that adapts dynamically to each student's learning profile. Additionally, PAPPL offers instructors detailed analytics, empowering evidence-based adjustments to teaching strategies. This study provides a fundamental framework for the progression of Generative ITSs scalable to all education levels, delivering important perspectives on personalized progressive learning and the wider possibilities of Generative AI in the field of education.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14109v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shayan Bafandkar, Sungyong Chung, Homa Khosravian, Alireza Talebpour</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enriching Moral Perspectives on AI: Concepts of Trust amongst Africans</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14116v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The trustworthiness of AI is considered essential to the adoption and application of AI systems. However, the meaning of trust varies across industry, research and policy spaces. Studies suggest that professionals who develop and use AI regard an AI system as trustworthy based on their personal experiences and social relations at work. Studies about trust in AI and the constructs that aim to operationalise trust in AI (e.g., consistency, reliability, explainability and accountability). However, the majority of existing studies about trust in AI are situated in Western, Educated, Industrialised, Rich and Democratic (WEIRD) societies. The few studies about trust and AI in Africa do not include the views of people who develop, study or use AI in their work. In this study, we surveyed 157 people with professional and/or educational interests in AI from 25 African countries, to explore how they conceptualised trust in AI. Most respondents had links with workshops about trust and AI in Africa in Namibia and Ghana. Respondents' educational background, transnational mobility, and country of origin influenced their concerns about AI systems. These factors also affected their levels of distrust in certain AI applications and their emphasis on specific principles designed to foster trust. Respondents often expressed that their values are guided by the communities in which they grew up and emphasised communal relations over individual freedoms. They described trust in many ways, including applying nuances of Afro-relationalism to constructs in international discourse, such as reliability and reliance. Thus, our exploratory study motivates more empirical research about the ways trust is practically enacted and experienced in African social realities of AI design, use and governance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14116v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lameck Mbangula Amugongo, Nicola J Bidwell, Joseph Mwatukange</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Documenting Deployment with Fabric: A Repository of Real-World AI Governance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14119</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14119v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Artificial intelligence (AI) is increasingly integrated into society, from financial services and traffic management to creative writing. Academic literature on the deployment of AI has mostly focused on the risks and harms that result from the use of AI. We introduce Fabric, a publicly available repository of deployed AI use cases to outline their governance mechanisms. Through semi-structured interviews with practitioners, we collect an initial set of 20 AI use cases. In addition, we co-design diagrams of the AI workflow with the practitioners. We discuss the oversight mechanisms and guardrails used in practice to safeguard AI use. The Fabric repository includes visual diagrams of AI use cases and descriptions of the deployed systems. Using the repository, we surface gaps in governance and find common patterns in human oversight of deployed AI systems. We intend for Fabric to serve as an extendable, evolving tool for researchers to study the effectiveness of AI governance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14119v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mackenzie Jorgensen, Kendall Brogle, Katherine M. Collins, Lujain Ibrahim, Arina Shah, Petra Ivanovic, Noah Broestl, Gabriel Piles, Paul Dongha, Hatim Abdulhussein, Adrian Weller, Jillian Powers, Umang Bhatt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Algorithms Infer Gender: Revisiting Computational Phenotyping with Electronic Health Records Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14150v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Computational phenotyping has emerged as a practical solution to the incomplete collection of data on gender in electronic health records (EHRs). This approach relies on algorithms to infer a patient's gender using the available data in their health record, such as diagnosis codes, medication histories, and information in clinical notes. Although intended to improve the visibility of trans and gender-expansive populations in EHR-based biomedical research, computational phenotyping raises significant methodological and ethical concerns related to the potential misuse of algorithm outputs. In this paper, we review current practices for computational phenotyping of gender and examine its challenges through a critical lens. We also highlight existing recommendations for biomedical researchers and propose priorities for future work in this domain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14150v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jessica Gronsbell, Hilary Thurston, Lillian Dong, Vanessa Ferguson, Diksha Sen Chaudhury, Braden O'Neill, Katrina S. Sha, Rebecca Bonneville</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breakable Machine: A K-12 Classroom Game for Transformative AI Literacy Through Spoofing and eXplainable AI (XAI)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14201v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper, submitted to the special track on resources for teaching AI in K-12, presents an eXplainable AI (XAI)-based classroom game "Breakable Machine" for teaching critical, transformative AI literacy through adversarial play and interrogation of AI systems. Designed for learners aged 10-15, the game invites students to spoof an image classifier by manipulating their appearance or environment in order to trigger high-confidence misclassifications. Rather than focusing on building AI models, this activity centers on breaking them-exposing their brittleness, bias, and vulnerability through hands-on, embodied experimentation. The game includes an XAI view to help students visualize feature saliency, revealing how models attend to specific visual cues. A shared classroom leaderboard fosters collaborative inquiry and comparison of strategies, turning the classroom into a site for collective sensemaking. This approach reframes AI education by treating model failure and misclassification not as problems to be debugged, but as pedagogically rich opportunities to interrogate AI as a sociotechnical system. In doing so, the game supports students in developing data agency, ethical awareness, and a critical stance toward AI systems increasingly embedded in everyday life. The game and its source code are freely available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14201v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olli Hilke, Nicolas Pope, Juho Kahila, Henriikka Vartiainen, Teemu Roos, Tuomo Parkki, Matti Tedre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Incident Analysis for AI Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14231</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14231v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As AI agents become more widely deployed, we are likely to see an increasing number of incidents: events involving AI agent use that directly or indirectly cause harm. For example, agents could be prompt-injected to exfiltrate private information or make unauthorized purchases. Structured information about such incidents (e.g., user prompts) can help us understand their causes and prevent future occurrences. However, existing incident reporting processes are not sufficient for understanding agent incidents. In particular, such processes are largely based on publicly available data, which excludes useful, but potentially sensitive, information such as an agent's chain of thought or browser history. To inform the development of new, emerging incident reporting processes, we propose an incident analysis framework for agents. Drawing on systems safety approaches, our framework proposes three types of factors that can cause incidents: system-related (e.g., CBRN training data), contextual (e.g., prompt injections), and cognitive (e.g., misunderstanding a user request). We also identify specific information that could help clarify which factors are relevant to a given incident: activity logs, system documentation and access, and information about the tools an agent uses. We provide recommendations for 1) what information incident reports should include and 2) what information developers and deployers should retain and make available to incident investigators upon request. As we transition to a world with more agents, understanding agent incidents will become increasingly crucial for managing risks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14231v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carson Ezell, Xavier Roberts-Gaal, Alan Chan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sociotechnical Imaginaries of ChatGPT in Higher Education: The Evolving Media Discourse</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14692v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study investigates how U.S. news media framed the use of ChatGPT in higher education from November 2022 to October 2024. Employing Framing Theory and combining temporal and sentiment analysis of 198 news articles, we trace the evolving narratives surrounding generative AI. We found that the media discourse largely centered on institutional responses; policy changes and teaching practices showed the most consistent presence and positive sentiment over time. Conversely, coverage of topics such as human-centered learning, the job market, and skill development appeared more sporadically, with initially uncertain portrayals gradually shifting toward cautious optimism. Importantly, media sentiment toward ChatGPT's role in college admissions remained predominantly negative. Our findings suggest that media narratives prioritize institutional responses to generative AI over long-term, broader ethical, social, and labor-related implications, shaping an emerging sociotechnical imaginary that frames generative AI in education primarily through the lens of adaptation and innovation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14692v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yinan Sun, Ali Unlu, Aditya Johri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Investigation Into Secondary School Students' Debugging Behaviour in Python</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14833v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Background and context: Debugging is a common and often frustrating challenge for beginner programmers. Understanding students' debugging processes can help us identify the difficulties and misunderstandings they possess. However, we currently have limited knowledge of how secondary students debug in a text-based language, a medium through which millions of students will learn to program in the future. Objectives: In this paper, we investigate the debugging behaviour of K-12 students learning a text-based programming language, as part of an effort to shape how to effectively teach debugging to these students. Method: We collected log data from 73 students attempting a set of debugging exercises using an online code editor. We inductively analysed these logs using qualitative content analysis, generating a categorisation of the debugging behaviours observed. Findings: A range of behaviours were exhibited by students, skewed towards being ineffective. Most students were able to partially locate errors but often struggled to resolve them, sometimes introducing additional errors in the process. We argue that students struggling to debug possess fragile knowledge, a lens through which we view the results. Implications: This paper highlights some of the difficulties K-12 learners have when debugging in a text-based programming language. We argue, like much related work, that effective debugging strategies should be explicitly taught, while ineffective strategies should be discouraged.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14833v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laurie Gale, Sue Sentance</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking Sociolinguistic Diversity in Swahili NLP: A Taxonomy-Guided Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14051</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14051v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the first taxonomy-guided evaluation of Swahili NLP, addressing gaps in sociolinguistic diversity. Drawing on health-related psychometric tasks, we collect a dataset of 2,170 free-text responses from Kenyan speakers. The data exhibits tribal influences, urban vernacular, code-mixing, and loanwords. We develop a structured taxonomy and use it as a lens for examining model prediction errors across pre-trained and instruction-tuned language models. Our findings advance culturally grounded evaluation frameworks and highlight the role of sociolinguistic variation in shaping model performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14051v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kezia Oketch, John P. Lalor, Ahmed Abbasi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparing energy consumption and accuracy in text classification inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14170v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The increasing deployment of large language models (LLMs) in natural language processing (NLP) tasks raises concerns about energy efficiency and sustainability. While prior research has largely focused on energy consumption during model training, the inference phase has received comparatively less attention. This study systematically evaluates the trade-offs between model accuracy and energy consumption in text classification inference across various model architectures and hardware configurations. Our empirical analysis shows that the best-performing model in terms of accuracy can also be energy-efficient, while larger LLMs tend to consume significantly more energy with lower classification accuracy. We observe substantial variability in inference energy consumption ($&lt;$mWh to $&gt;$kWh), influenced by model type, model size, and hardware specifications. Additionally, we find a strong correlation between inference energy consumption and model runtime, indicating that execution time can serve as a practical proxy for energy usage in settings where direct measurement is not feasible. These findings have implications for sustainable AI development, providing actionable insights for researchers, industry practitioners, and policymakers seeking to balance performance and resource efficiency in NLP applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14170v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Zschache, Tilman Hartwig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GRILE: A Benchmark for Grammar Reasoning and Explanation in Romanian LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14279v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: LLMs (Large language models) have revolutionized NLP (Natural Language Processing), yet their pedagogical value for low-resource languages remains unclear. We present GRILE (Grammar Romanian Inference and Language Explanations) , the first open benchmark of 1,151 multiple-choice questions harvested from Romanian high-stakes exams (National Evaluation, Baccalaureate, university admissions). GRILE enables us to probe two complementary abilities of seven state-of-the-art multilingual and Romanian-specific LLMs: (i) selecting the correct answer, and (ii) producing linguistically accurate explanations. While Gemini 2.5 Pro reaches 83% accuracy, most open-weight models stay below 65%, and 48% of their explanations contain factual or pedagogical flaws according to expert review. A detailed error analysis pinpoints systematic weaknesses in morphology and in applying the latest DOOM3 orthographic norms. All data, code and a public web demo are released to catalyze future research. Our findings expose open challenges for trustworthy educational NLP in low-resource settings and establish GRILE as a new test-bed for controllable explanation generation and evaluation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14279v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrian-Marius Dumitran, Alexandra-Mihaela Danila, Angela-Liliana Dumitran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ZPD-SCA: Unveiling the Blind Spots of LLMs in Assessing Students' Cognitive Abilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14377v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated potential in educational applications, yet their capacity to accurately assess the cognitive alignment of reading materials with students' developmental stages remains insufficiently explored. This gap is particularly critical given the foundational educational principle of the Zone of Proximal Development (ZPD), which emphasizes the need to match learning resources with Students' Cognitive Abilities (SCA). Despite the importance of this alignment, there is a notable absence of comprehensive studies investigating LLMs' ability to evaluate reading comprehension difficulty across different student age groups, especially in the context of Chinese language education. To fill this gap, we introduce ZPD-SCA, a novel benchmark specifically designed to assess stage-level Chinese reading comprehension difficulty. The benchmark is annotated by 60 Special Grade teachers, a group that represents the top 0.15% of all in-service teachers nationwide. Experimental results reveal that LLMs perform poorly in zero-shot learning scenarios, with Qwen-max and GLM even falling below the probability of random guessing. When provided with in-context examples, LLMs performance improves substantially, with some models achieving nearly double the accuracy of their zero-shot baselines. These results reveal that LLMs possess emerging abilities to assess reading difficulty, while also exposing limitations in their current training for educationally aligned judgment. Notably, even the best-performing models display systematic directional biases, suggesting difficulties in accurately aligning material difficulty with SCA. Furthermore, significant variations in model performance across different genres underscore the complexity of task. We envision that ZPD-SCA can provide a foundation for evaluating and improving LLMs in cognitively aligned educational applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14377v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenhan Dong, Zhen Sun, Yuemeng Zhao, Zifan Peng, Jun Wu, Jingyi Zheng, Yule Liu, Xinlei He, Yu Wang, Ruiming Wang, Xinyi Huang, Lei Mo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Challenges and Opportunities for Participatory Design of Conversational Agents for Young People's Wellbeing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14787</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14787v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper outlines the challenges and opportunities of research on conversational agents with children and young people across four countries, exploring the ways AI technologies can support children's well-being across social and cultural contexts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14787v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Natalia Kucirkova, Alexis Hiniker, Megumi Ishikawa, Sho Tsuji, Aayushi Dangol, Robert Wolfe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative AI in K-12 Education: The CyberScholar Initiative</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19422v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper focuses on the piloting of CyberScholar, a Generative AI assistant tool that aims to provide formative feedback on writing in K-12 contexts. Specifically, this study explores how students worked with CyberScholar in diverse subject areas, including English Language Arts, Social Studies, and Modern World History classes in Grades 7, 8, 10, and 11 in three schools in the Midwest and one in the Northwest of the United States. This paper focuses on CyberScholar's potential to support K-12 students' writing in diverse subject areas requiring written assignments. Data were collected through implementation observations, surveys, and interviews by participating 121 students and 4 teachers. Thematic qualitative analysis revealed that the feedback tool was perceived as a valuable tool for supporting student writing through detailed feedback, enhanced interactivity, and alignment with rubric criteria. Students appreciated the tool's guidance in refining their writing. For the students, the assistant tool suggests restructuring feedback as a dynamic, dialogic process rather than a static evaluation, a shift that aligns with the cyber-social learning idea, self-regulation, and metacognition. For the teaching side, the findings indicate a shift in teachers' roles, from serving primarily as evaluators to guiding AI feedback processes that foster better student writing and critical thinking.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19422v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vania Castro, Ana Karina de Oliveira Nascimento, Raigul Zheldibayeva, Duane Searsmith, Akash Saini, Bill Cope, Mary Kalantzis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Conceptual Framework for AI-based Decision Systems in Critical Infrastructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16133v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The interaction between humans and AI in safety-critical systems presents a unique set of challenges that remain partially addressed by existing frameworks. These challenges stem from the complex interplay of requirements for transparency, trust, and explainability, coupled with the necessity for robust and safe decision-making. A framework that holistically integrates human and AI capabilities while addressing these concerns is notably required, bridging the critical gaps in designing, deploying, and maintaining safe and effective systems. This paper proposes a holistic conceptual framework for critical infrastructures by adopting an interdisciplinary approach. It integrates traditionally distinct fields such as mathematics, decision theory, computer science, philosophy, psychology, and cognitive engineering and draws on specialized engineering domains, particularly energy, mobility, and aeronautics. Its flexibility is further demonstrated through a case study on power grid management.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16133v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2025 IEEE International Conference on Systems, Man, and Cybernetics (SMC)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Milad Leyli-abadi, Ricardo J. Bessa, Jan Viebahn, Daniel Boos, Clark Borst, Alberto Castagna, Ricardo Chavarriaga, Mohamed Hassouna, Bruno Lemetayer, Giulia Leto, Antoine Marot, Maroua Meddeb, Manuel Meyer, Viola Schiaffonati, Manuel Schneider, Toni Waefler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Autonomy to Agency: Agentic Vehicles for Human-Centered Mobility Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04996v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Autonomy, from the Greek autos (self) and nomos (law), refers to the capacity to operate according to internal rules without external control. Accordingly, autonomous vehicles (AuVs) are viewed as vehicular systems capable of perceiving their environment and executing pre-programmed tasks independently of external input. However, both research and real-world deployments increasingly showcase vehicles that demonstrate behaviors beyond this definition (including the SAE levels 0 to 5); Examples of this outpace include the interaction with humans with natural language, goal adaptation, contextual reasoning, external tool use, and unseen ethical dilemma handling, largely empowered by multi-modal large language models (LLMs). These developments reveal a conceptual gap between technical autonomy and the broader cognitive and social capabilities needed for future human-centered mobility systems. To address this gap, this paper introduces the concept of agentic vehicles (AgVs), referring to vehicles that integrate agentic AI systems to reason, adapt, and interact within complex environments. This paper proposes the term AgVs and their distinguishing characteristics from conventional AuVs. It synthesizes relevant advances in integrating LLMs and AuVs and highlights how AgVs might transform future mobility systems and ensure the systems are human-centered. The paper concludes by identifying key challenges in the development and governance of AgVs, and how they can play a significant role in future agentic transportation systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04996v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiangbo Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Depression-Diagnosis-Oriented Chat with Psychological State Tracking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09717</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09717v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Depression-diagnosis-oriented chat aims to guide patients in self-expression to collect key symptoms for depression detection. Recent work focuses on combining task-oriented dialogue and chitchat to simulate the interview-based depression diagnosis. Whereas, these methods can not well capture the changing information, feelings, or symptoms of the patient during dialogues. Moreover, no explicit framework has been explored to guide the dialogue, which results in some useless communications that affect the experience. In this paper, we propose to integrate Psychological State Tracking (POST) within the large language model (LLM) to explicitly guide depression-diagnosis-oriented chat. Specifically, the state is adapted from a psychological theoretical model, which consists of four components, namely Stage, Information, Summary and Next. We fine-tune an LLM model to generate the dynamic psychological state, which is further used to assist response generation at each turn to simulate the psychiatrist. Experimental results on the existing benchmark show that our proposed method boosts the performance of all subtasks in depression-diagnosis-oriented chat.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09717v2</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiyang Gu, Yougen Zhou, Qin Chen, Ningning Zhou, Jie Zhou, Aimin Zhou, Liang He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Biased AI improves human decision-making but reduces trust</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09297</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09297v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Current AI systems minimize risk by enforcing ideological neutrality, yet this may introduce automation bias by suppressing cognitive engagement in human decision-making. We conducted randomized trials with 2,500 participants to test whether culturally biased AI enhances human decision-making. Participants interacted with politically diverse GPT-4o variants on information evaluation tasks. Partisan AI assistants enhanced human performance, increased engagement, and reduced evaluative bias compared to non-biased counterparts, with amplified benefits when participants encountered opposing views. These gains carried a trust penalty: participants underappreciated biased AI and overcredited neutral systems. Exposing participants to two AIs whose biases flanked human perspectives closed the perception-performance gap. These findings complicate conventional wisdom about AI neutrality, suggesting that strategic integration of diverse cultural biases may foster improved and resilient human decision-making.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09297v3</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiyang Lai, Junsol Kim, Nadav Kunievsky, Yujin Potter, James Evans</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
