<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.GT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.GT</link>
    <description>cs.GT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.GT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 01:56:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Strategic and Fair Aggregator Interactions in Energy Markets: Mutli-agent Dynamics and Quasiconcave Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11296v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The introduction of aggregator structures has proven effective in bringing fairness to energy resource allocation by negotiating for more resources and economic surplus on behalf of users. This paper extends the fair energy resource allocation problem to a multi-agent setting, focusing on interactions among multiple aggregators in an electricity market.
  We prove that the strategic optimization problems faced by the aggregators form a quasiconcave game, ensuring the existence of a Nash equilibrium. This resolves complexities related to market price dependencies on total purchases and balancing fairness and efficiency in energy allocation. In addition, we design simulations to characterize the equilibrium points of the induced game, demonstrating how aggregators stabilize market outcomes, ensure fair resource distribution, and optimize user surplus. Our findings offer a robust framework for understanding strategic interactions among aggregators, contributing to more efficient and equitable energy markets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11296v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiayi Li, Matt Motoki, Baosen Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Mediation Mechanisms in Bilateral Trade</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11683v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Consider a bilateral trade scenario where a seller seeks to sell an item to a buyer through a trusted mediator. The item's quality is the seller's private information, and the buyer's valuation of the item depends on both the quality and the buyer's type. The mediator, who is uninformed about the private information of both the seller and buyer, aims to design a mechanism that elicits and reveals information to facilitate communication between two agents. The mediator can also charge a fee for providing such services.
  In this work, we study the problem of designing mechanisms that maximize revenue for the mediator. We formulate this mechanism design problem as an optimization problem that involves non-linear constraints. Interestingly, under the monotone hazard rate assumption, we can bypass this issue by considering a relaxed problem and showing that the solution to the relaxed problem remains optimal to the original one. In optimal mechanisms, the mediator directly recommends whether to trade after eliciting the agents' types. The mediator privately offers a price to each agent if a trade is recommended. The optimal mechanism adopts a threshold information structure, i.e., it only reveals to the agent whether the other agent's type exceeds a certain threshold. The optimal payment function of buyer is monotone decreasing to their type, which differs from most existing works. Finally, we discuss some interesting observations revealed by the optimal mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11683v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhikang Fan, Weiran Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Majorized Bayesian Persuasion and Fair Selection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11798v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We address the fundamental problem of selection under uncertainty by modeling it from the perspective of Bayesian persuasion. In our model, a decision maker with imperfect information always selects the option with the highest expected value. We seek to achieve fairness among the options by revealing additional information to the decision maker and hence influencing its subsequent selection. To measure fairness, we adopt the notion of majorization, aiming at simultaneously approximately maximizing all symmetric, monotone, concave functions over the utilities of the options. As our main result, we design a novel information revelation policy that achieves a logarithmic-approximation to majorization in polynomial time. On the other hand, no policy, regardless of its running time, can achieve a constant-approximation to majorization. Our work is the first non-trivial majorization result in the Bayesian persuasion literature with multi-dimensional information sets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11798v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siddhartha Banerjee, Kamesh Munagala, Yiheng Shen, Kangning Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Simplicity of Optimal Dynamic Mechanisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11738v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A fundamental economic question is that of designing revenue-maximizing mechanisms in dynamic environments. This paper considers a simple yet compelling market model to tackle this question, where forward-looking buyers arrive at the market over discrete time periods, and a monopolistic seller is endowed with a limited supply of a single good. In the case of i.i.d. and regular valuations for the buyers, Board and Skrzypacz (2016) characterized the optimal mechanism and proved the optimality of posted prices in the continuous-time limit. Our main result considers the limit case of a continuum of buyers, establishing that for arbitrary independent buyers' valuations, posted prices and capacity rationing can implement the optimal anonymous mechanism. Our result departs from the literature in three ways: It does not make any regularity assumptions, it considers the case of general, not necessarily i.i.d., arrivals, and finally, not only posted prices but also capacity rationing takes part in the optimal mechanism. Additionally, if supply is unlimited, we show that the rationing effect vanishes, and the optimal mechanism can be implemented using posted prices only, \`a la Board (2008).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11738v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose Correa, Andres Cristi, Laura Vargas Koch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Differentially Private Approval-Based Committee Voting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.10122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.10122v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate tradeoffs among differential privacy (DP) and several representative axioms for approval-based committee voting, including justified representation, proportional justified representation, extended justified representation, Pareto efficiency, and Condorcet criterion. Without surprise, we demonstrate that all of these axioms are incompatible with DP, and thus establish both upper and lower bounds for their two-way tradeoffs with DP. Furthermore, we provide upper and lower bounds for three-way tradeoffs among DP and every pairwise combination of such axioms, revealing that although these axioms are compatible without DP, their optimal levels under DP cannot be simultaneously achieved. Our results quantify the effect of DP on the satisfaction and compatibility of the axioms in approval-based committee voting, which can provide insights for designing voting rules that possess both privacy and axiomatic properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.10122v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhechen Li, Zimai Guo, Lirong Xia, Yongzhi Cao, Hanpin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Serial Monopoly on Blockchains with Quasi-patient Users</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17334</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17334v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the face of limited block size, miners (e.g., in Bitcoin) prioritize high-bid transactions, forming a large part of their revenue. If the block size were to expand significantly, meeting all transaction demand due to infrastructure or protocol improvements, bids could drop to zero or to a minimum fee, reducing mining incentives and potentially affecting security. To address this, Lavi et al. (2022) introduced a monopolistic pricing mechanism where miners only include transactions paying a minimum price, ensuring some revenue but resulting in an unbounded loss in welfare. Nisan (2023) expands this by modeling bidders as patient, who wait indefinitely long for lower prices, causing price fluctuations even with stable demand. In order to capture users' diminishing interest in having their transactions added to the ledger over time, we consider a more realistic setting with quasi-patient users, where only a fraction $\delta \in [0,1]$ of pending transactions remains in the next round. This richer model encompasses both Lavi et al.'s impatient users ($\delta=0$) and Nisan's patient users ($\delta=1$) as special cases. We demonstrate that Nisan's fluctuating dynamics persist for $\delta$ close to 1, while for $\delta$ close to 0, the dynamics resemble the impatient case. For $\delta \in (0,1)$, we establish new bounds on price dynamics, revealing unexpected effects. Unlike the fully patient case, the bounds of the dynamics for $\delta&lt;1$ depend on the demand curve and undergo a "transition phase". For some $\delta$, the model mirrors the fully patient setting, and for smaller $\delta' &lt; \delta$, it stabilizes at the highest monopolist price, thus collapsing to the impatient case. We provide quantitative bounds and analytical results, showing that the bounds for $\delta=1$ are generally not tight for $\delta&lt;1$, and we give guarantees on the minimum ("admission") price for transactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17334v3</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Penna, Manvir Schneider</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast Revenue Maximization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07316v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Problem definition: We study a data-driven pricing problem in which a seller offers a price for a single item based on demand observed at a small number of historical prices. Our goal is to derive precise evaluation procedures of the value of the historical information gathered by the seller, along with prescriptions for more efficient price experimentation. Methodology/results: Our main methodological result is an exact characterization of the maximin ratio (defined as the worst-case revenue garnered by a seller who only relies on past data divided by the optimal revenue achievable with full knowledge of the distribution of values). This result allows to measure the value of any historical data consisting of prices and corresponding conversion rates. We leverage this central reduction to provide new insights about price experimentation. Managerial implications: Motivated by practical constraints that impede the seller from changing prices abruptly, we first illustrate our framework by evaluating the value of local information and show that the mere sign of the gradient of the revenue curve at a single point can provide significant information to the seller. We then showcase how our framework can be used to run efficient price experiments. On the one hand, we develop a method to select the next price experiment that the seller should use to maximize the future robust performance. On the other hand, we demonstrate that our result allows to considerably reduce the number of price experiments needed to reach preset revenue guarantees through dynamic pricing algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07316v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Achraf Bahamou, Omar Besbes, Omar Mouchtaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Putting Gale &amp; Shapley to Work: Guaranteeing Stability Through Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04376v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Two-sided matching markets describe a large class of problems wherein participants from one side of the market must be matched to those from the other side according to their preferences. In many real-world applications (e.g. content matching or online labor markets), the knowledge about preferences may not be readily available and must be learned, i.e., one side of the market (aka agents) may not know their preferences over the other side (aka arms). Recent research on online settings has focused primarily on welfare optimization aspects (i.e. minimizing the overall regret) while paying little attention to the game-theoretic properties such as the stability of the final matching. In this paper, we exploit the structure of stable solutions to devise algorithms that improve the likelihood of finding stable solutions. We initiate the study of the sample complexity of finding a stable matching, and provide theoretical bounds on the number of samples needed to reach a stable matching with high probability. Finally, our empirical results demonstrate intriguing tradeoffs between stability and optimality of the proposed algorithms, further complementing our theoretical findings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04376v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hadi Hosseini, Sanjukta Roy, Duohan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stackelberg vs. Nash in the Lottery Colonel Blotto Game</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07690v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Resource competition problems are often modeled using Colonel Blotto games. However, Colonel Blotto games only simulate scenarios where players act simultaneously. In many real-life scenarios, competition is sequential, such as cybersecurity, cloud services, Web investments, and more. To model such sequential competition, we model the Lottery Colonel Blotto game as a Stackelberg game. We solve the Stackelberg equilibrium in the Lottery Colonel Blotto game in which the first mover's strategy is actually a solution to a bi-level optimization problem. We develop a constructive method that allows for a series of game reductions. This method enables us to compute the leader's optimal commitment strategy in a polynomial number of iterations. Furthermore, we identify the conditions under which the Stackelberg equilibrium aligns with the Nash equilibria. Finally, we show that by making the optimal first move, the leader can improve utility by an infinite factor compared to its utility in the Nash equilibria. We find that the player with a smaller budget has a greater incentive to become the leader in the game. Surprisingly, even when the leader adopts the optimal commitment strategy, the follower's utility may improve compared to that in Nash equilibria.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07690v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan Liu, Bonan Ni, Weiran Shen, Zihe Wang, Jie Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Multi-BMBY Mechanism: Proportionality-Preserving and Strategyproof Ownership Restructuring in Private Companies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.06780</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.06780v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In privately held startups, restructuring ownership is challenging due to diverse and uncertain valuations among owners. Traditional approaches, including the BMBY mechanism for equal partnerships, fail to address the complexities of multi-owner settings and don't elicit true valuations. We propose a novel mechanism that extends the BMBY rationale to accommodate these complex scenarios. Our mechanism ensures truthful valuation elicitation while offering several advantages: it is easy to implement, budget balanced, resistant to collusion, individually rational, and allocates shares to those who value them most. Crucially, it preserves proportionality among remaining owners, maintaining existing power dynamics. The mechanism allows for adaptive control of the eventual number of owners, addressing unique startup needs such as incentivizing employee ownership. This paper contributes to the field of ownership restructuring by providing a practical, theoretically-grounded solution for the complex dynamics of startup recapitalization, potentially improving decision-making processes and stakeholder relationships in these pivotal business transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.06780v3</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gal Danino, Moran Koren, Omer Madmon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are Large Language Models Strategic Decision Makers? A Study of Performance and Bias in Two-Player Non-Zero-Sum Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04467v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Large Language Models (LLMs) have been increasingly used in real-world settings, yet their strategic decision-making abilities remain largely unexplored. To fully benefit from the potential of LLMs, it's essential to understand their ability to function in complex social scenarios. Game theory, which is already used to understand real-world interactions, provides a good framework for assessing these abilities. This work investigates the performance and merits of LLMs in canonical game-theoretic two-player non-zero-sum games, Stag Hunt and Prisoner Dilemma. Our structured evaluation of GPT-3.5, GPT-4-Turbo, GPT-4o, and Llama-3-8B shows that these models, when making decisions in these games, are affected by at least one of the following systematic biases: positional bias, payoff bias, or behavioural bias. This indicates that LLMs do not fully rely on logical reasoning when making these strategic decisions. As a result, it was found that the LLMs' performance drops when the game configuration is misaligned with the affecting biases. When misaligned, GPT-3.5, GPT-4-Turbo, GPT-4o, and Llama-3-8B show an average performance drop of 32\%, 25\%, 34\%, and 29\% respectively in Stag Hunt, and 28\%, 16\%, 34\%, and 24\% respectively in Prisoner's Dilemma. Surprisingly, GPT-4o (a top-performing LLM across standard benchmarks) suffers the most substantial performance drop, suggesting that newer models are not addressing these issues. Interestingly, we found that a commonly used method of improving the reasoning capabilities of LLMs, chain-of-thought (CoT) prompting, reduces the biases in GPT-3.5, GPT-4o, and Llama-3-8B but increases the effect of the bias in GPT-4-Turbo, indicating that CoT alone cannot fully serve as a robust solution to this problem. We perform several additional experiments, which provide further insight into these observed behaviours.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04467v3</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathan Herr, Fernando Acero, Roberta Raileanu, Mar\'ia P\'erez-Ortiz, Zhibin Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
