<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.GT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.GT</link>
    <description>cs.GT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.GT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 04:00:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Stability in Online Assignment Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09814v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The assignment game models a housing market where buyers and sellers are matched, and transaction prices are set so that the resulting allocation is stable. Shapley and Shubik showed that every stable allocation is necessarily built on a maximum social welfare matching. In practice, however, stable allocations are rarely attainable, as matchings are often sub-optimal, particularly in online settings where eagents arrive sequentially to the market. In this paper, we introduce and compare two complementary measures of instability for allocations with sub-optimal matchings, establish their connections to the optimality ratio of the underlying matching, and use this framework to study the stability performances of randomized algorithms in online assignment games.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09814v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emile Martinez, Felipe Garrido-Lucero, Umberto Grandi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proportional and Pareto-Optimal Allocation of Chores with Subsidy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10335v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the problem of allocating $m$ indivisible chores among $n$ agents with possibly different weights, aiming for a solution that is both fair and efficient. Specifically, we focus on the classic fairness notion of proportionality and efficiency notion of Pareto-optimality. Since proportional allocations may not always exist in this setting, we allow the use of subsidies (monetary compensation to agents) to ensure agents are proportionally-satisfied, and aim to minimize the total subsidy required. Wu and Zhou (WINE 2024) showed that when each chore has disutility at most 1, a total subsidy of at most $n/3 - 1/6$ is sufficient to guarantee proportionality. However, their approach is based on a complex technique, which does not guarantee economic efficiency - a key desideratum in fair division.
  In this work, we give a polynomial-time algorithm that achieves the same subsidy bound while also ensuring Pareto-optimality. Moreover, both our algorithm and its analysis are significantly simpler than those of Wu and Zhou (WINE 2024). Our approach first computes a proportionally-fair competitive equilibrium, and then applies a rounding procedure guided by minimum-pain-per-buck edges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10335v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jugal Garg, Eklavya Sharma, Xiaowei Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved Maximin Share Guarantee for Additive Valuations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10423</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10423v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The maximin share ($\textsf{MMS}$) is the most prominent share-based fairness notion in the fair allocation of indivisible goods. Recent years have seen significant efforts to improve the approximation guarantees for $\textsf{MMS}$ for different valuation classes, particularly for additive valuations. For the additive setting, it has been shown that for some instances, no allocation can guarantee a factor better than $1-\tfrac{1}{n^4}$ of maximin share value to all agents. However, the best currently known algorithm achieves an approximation guarantee of $\tfrac{3}{4} + \tfrac{3}{3836}$ for $\textsf{MMS}$. In this work, we narrow this gap and improve the best-known approximation guarantee for $\textsf{MMS}$ to $\tfrac{10}{13}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10423v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ehsan Heidari, Alireza Kaviani, Masoud Seddighin, AmirMohammad Shahrezaei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fair Assignment of Indivisible Chores to Asymmetric Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10698v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the problem of assigning indivisible chores to agents with different entitlements in the maximin share value (\MMS) context. While constant-\MMS\ allocations/assignments are guaranteed to exist for both goods and chores in the symmetric setting, the situation becomes much more complex when agents have different entitlements. For the allocation of indivisible goods, it has been proven that an $n$-\WMMS\ (weighted \MMS) guarantee is the best one can hope for. For indivisible chores, however, it was recently discovered that an $O(\log n)$-\WMMS\ assignment is guaranteed to exist. In this work, we improve this upper bound to a constant-\WMMS\ guarantee.\footnote{We prove the existence of a 20-\WMMS\ assignment, but we did not attempt to optimize the constant factor. We believe our methods already yield a slightly better bound with a tighter analysis.}</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10698v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masoud Seddighin, Saeed Seddighin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Achieving Coordination in Non-Cooperative Joint Replenishment Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10929v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We analyze an infinite-horizon deterministic joint replenishment model from a non-cooperative game-theoretical approach. In this model, a group of retailers can choose to jointly place an order, which incurs a major setup cost independent of the group, and a minor setup cost for each retailer. Additionally, each retailer is associated with a holding cost. Our objective is to design cost allocation rules that minimize the long-run average system cost while accounting for the fact that each retailer independently selects its replenishment interval to minimize its own cost. We introduce a class of cost allocation rules that distribute the major setup cost among the associated retailers in proportion to their predefined weights. For these rules, we establish a monotonicity property of agent better responses, which enables us to prove the existence of a payoff dominant pure Nash equilibrium that can also be computed efficiently. We then analyze the efficiency of these equilibria by examining the price of stability (PoS), the ratio of the best Nash equilibrium's system cost to the social optimum, across different information settings. In particular, our analysis reveals that one rule, which leverages retailers' own holding cost rates, achieves a near-optimal PoS of 1.25, while another rule that does not require access to retailers' private information also yields a favorable PoS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10929v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junjie Luo, Changjun Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Likes, Budgets, and Equilibria: Designing Contests for Socially Optimal Advertising</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11253v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Firms (businesses, service providers, entertainment organizations, political parties, etc.) advertise on social networks to draw people's attention and improve their awareness of the brands of the firms. In all such cases, the competitive nature of their engagements gives rise to a game where the firms need to decide how to distribute their budget over the agents on a network to maximize their brand's awareness. The firms (players) therefore need to optimize how much budget they should put on the vertices of the network so that the spread improves via direct (via advertisements or free promotional offers) and indirect marketing (words-of-mouth). We propose a two-timescale model of decisions where the communication between the vertices happen in a faster timescale and the strategy update of the firms happen in a slower timescale. We show that under fairly standard conditions, the best response dynamics of the firms converge to a pure strategy Nash equilibrium. However, such equilibria can be away from a socially optimal one. We provide a characterization of the contest success functions and provide examples for the designers of such contests (e.g., regulators, social network providers, etc.) such that the Nash equilibrium becomes unique and social welfare maximizing. Our experiments show that for realistic scenarios, such contest success functions perform fairly well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11253v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sayantika Mandal, Harman Agrawal, Swaprava Nath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temporal Cooperative Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11255v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Classical cooperative game theory assumes that the worth of a coalition depends only on the set of agents involved, but in practice, it may also depend on the order in which agents arrive. Motivated by such scenarios, we introduce temporal cooperative games (TCG), where the worth $v$ becomes a function of the sequence of agents $\pi$ rather than just the set $S$. This shift calls for rethinking the underlying axioms. A key property in this temporal framework is the incentive for optimal arrival (I4OA), which encourages agents to join in the order maximizing total worth. Alongside, we define two additional properties: online individual rationality (OIR), incentivizing earlier agents to invite more participants, and sequential efficiency (SE), ensuring that the total worth of any sequence is fully distributed among its agents. We identify a class of reward-sharing mechanisms uniquely characterized by these three properties. The classical Shapley value does not directly apply here, so we construct its natural analogs in two variants: the sequential world, where rewards are defined for each sequence-player pair, and the extended world, where rewards are defined for each player alone. Properties of efficiency, additivity, and null player uniquely determine these Shapley analogs in both worlds. Importantly, the Shapley analogs are disjoint from mechanisms satisfying I4OA, OIR, and SE, and this conflict persists even for restricted classes such as convex and simple TCGs. Our findings thus uncover a fundamental tension: when players arrive sequentially, reward-sharing mechanisms satisfying desirable temporal properties must inherently differ from Shapley-inspired ones, opening new questions for defining fair and efficient solution concepts in TCGs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11255v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashwin Goyal, Drashthi Doshi, Swaprava Nath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Complexity of Stationary Nash Equilibria in Discounted Perfect Information Stochastic Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11550v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the problem of computing stationary Nash equilibria in discounted perfect information stochastic games from the viewpoint of computational complexity. For two-player games we prove the problem to be in PPAD, which together with a previous PPAD-hardness result precisely classifies the problem as PPAD-complete. In addition to this we give an improved and simpler PPAD-hardness proof for computing a stationary epsilon-Nash equilibrium. For 3-player games we construct games showing that rational-valued stationary Nash equilibria are not guaranteed to exist, and we use these to prove SqrtSum-hardness of computing a stationary Nash equilibrium in 4-player games.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11550v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kristoffer Arnsfelt Hansen, Xinhao Nie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiwinner Voting with Interval Preferences under Incomplete Information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11625v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In multiwinner approval elections with many candidates, voters may struggle to determine their preferences over the entire slate of candidates. It is therefore of interest to explore which (if any) fairness guarantees can be provided under reduced communication. In this paper, we consider voters with one-dimensional preferences: voters and candidates are associated with points in $\mathbb R$, and each voter's approval set forms an interval of $\mathbb R$. We put forward a probabilistic preference model, where the voter set consists of $\sigma$ different groups; each group is associated with a distribution over an interval of $\mathbb R$, so that each voter draws the endpoints of her approval interval from the distribution associated with her group. We present an algorithm for computing committees that provide Proportional Justified Representation + (PJR+), which proceeds by querying voters' preferences, and show that, in expectation, it makes $\mathcal{O}(\log( \sigma\cdot k))$ queries per voter, where $k$ is the desired committee size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11625v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Drew Springham, Edith Elkind, Bart de Keijzer, Maria Polukarov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLMs as Strategic Agents: Beliefs, Best Response Behavior, and Emergent Heuristics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10813v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Large Language Models (LLMs) are increasingly applied to domains that require reasoning about other agents' behavior, such as negotiation, policy design, and market simulation, yet existing research has mostly evaluated their adherence to equilibrium play or their exhibited depth of reasoning. Whether they display genuine strategic thinking, understood as the coherent formation of beliefs about other agents, evaluation of possible actions, and choice based on those beliefs, remains unexplored. We develop a framework to identify this ability by disentangling beliefs, evaluation, and choice in static, complete-information games, and apply it across a series of non-cooperative environments. By jointly analyzing models' revealed choices and reasoning traces, and introducing a new context-free game to rule out imitation from memorization, we show that current frontier models exhibit belief-coherent best-response behavior at targeted reasoning depths. When unconstrained, they self-limit their depth of reasoning and form differentiated conjectures about human and synthetic opponents, revealing an emergent form of meta-reasoning. Under increasing complexity, explicit recursion gives way to internally generated heuristic rules of choice that are stable, model-specific, and distinct from known human biases. These findings indicate that belief coherence, meta-reasoning, and novel heuristic formation can emerge jointly from language modeling objectives, providing a structured basis for the study of strategic cognition in artificial agents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10813v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enric Junque de Fortuny, Veronica Roberta Cappelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast and the Furious: Hot Starts in Pursuit-Evasion Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10830</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10830v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Effectively positioning pursuers in pursuit-evasion games without prior knowledge of evader locations remains a significant challenge. A novel approach that combines game-theoretic control theory with Graph Neural Networks is introduced in this work. By conceptualizing pursuer configurations as strategic arrangements and representing them as graphs, a Graph Characteristic Space is constructed via multi-objective optimization to identify Pareto-optimal configurations. A Graph Convolutional Network (GCN) is trained on these Pareto-optimal graphs to generate strategically effective initial configurations, termed "hot starts". Empirical evaluations demonstrate that the GCN-generated hot starts provide a significant advantage over random configurations. In scenarios considering multiple pursuers and evaders, this method hastens the decline in evader survival rates, reduces pursuer travel distances, and enhances containment, showcasing clear strategic benefits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10830v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel Smithline, Scott Nivison</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>People use fast, flat goal-directed simulation to reason about novel problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11503v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Games have long been a microcosm for studying planning and reasoning in both natural and artificial intelligence, especially with a focus on expert-level or even super-human play. But real life also pushes human intelligence along a different frontier, requiring people to flexibly navigate decision-making problems that they have never thought about before. Here, we use novice gameplay to study how people make decisions and form judgments in new problem settings. We show that people are systematic and adaptively rational in how they play a game for the first time, or evaluate a game (e.g., how fair or how fun it is likely to be) before they have played it even once. We explain these capacities via a computational cognitive model that we call the "Intuitive Gamer". The model is based on mechanisms of fast and flat (depth-limited) goal-directed probabilistic simulation--analogous to those used in Monte Carlo tree-search models of expert game-play, but scaled down to use very few stochastic samples, simple goal heuristics for evaluating actions, and no deep search. In a series of large-scale behavioral studies with over 1000 participants and 121 two-player strategic board games (almost all novel to our participants), our model quantitatively captures human judgments and decisions varying the amount and kind of experience people have with a game--from no experience at all ("just thinking"), to a single round of play, to indirect experience watching another person and predicting how they should play--and does so significantly better than much more compute-intensive expert-level models. More broadly, our work offers new insights into how people rapidly evaluate, act, and make suggestions when encountering novel problems, and could inform the design of more flexible and human-like AI systems that can determine not just how to solve new tasks, but whether a task is worth thinking about at all.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11503v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katherine M. Collins, Cedegao E. Zhang, Lionel Wong, Mauricio Barba da Costa, Graham Todd, Adrian Weller, Samuel J. Cheyette, Thomas L. Griffiths, Joshua B. Tenenbaum</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tight Regret Upper and Lower Bounds for Optimistic Hedge in Two-Player Zero-Sum Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11691v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In two-player zero-sum games, the learning dynamic based on optimistic Hedge achieves one of the best-known regret upper bounds among strongly-uncoupled learning dynamics. With an appropriately chosen learning rate, the social and individual regrets can be bounded by $O(\log(mn))$ in terms of the numbers of actions $m$ and $n$ of the two players. This study investigates the optimality of the dependence on $m$ and $n$ in the regret of optimistic Hedge. To this end, we begin by refining existing regret analysis and show that, in the strongly-uncoupled setting where the opponent's number of actions is known, both the social and individual regret bounds can be improved to $O(\sqrt{\log m \log n})$. In this analysis, we express the regret upper bound as an optimization problem with respect to the learning rates and the coefficients of certain negative terms, enabling refined analysis of the leading constants. We then show that the existing social regret bound as well as these new social and individual regret upper bounds cannot be further improved for optimistic Hedge by providing algorithm-dependent individual regret lower bounds. Importantly, these social regret upper and lower bounds match exactly including the constant factor in the leading term. Finally, building on these results, we improve the last-iterate convergence rate and the dynamic regret of a learning dynamic based on optimistic Hedge, and complement these bounds with algorithm-dependent dynamic regret lower bounds that match the improved bounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11691v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taira Tsuchiya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inspection Game with Location-Specific Detection Capabilities: Exact and Approximate Algorithms for Strategic Resource Coordination</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11545v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a zero-sum inspection game, in which a defender positions detectors across a critical system to detect multiple attacks caused by an attacker. We assume that detection is imperfect, and each detector location is associated with a probability of detecting attacks within its set of monitored system components. The objective of the defender (resp. attacker) is to minimize (resp. maximize) the expected number of undetected attacks. To compute Nash equilibria for this large-scale zero-sum game, we formulate a linear program with a small number of constraints that can be solved via column generation. We provide an exact mixed-integer program for the pricing problem and leverage its supermodular structure to design two efficient approaches for computing approximate Nash equilibria with theoretical guarantees: A column generation and a multiplicative weights update algorithm, both with approximate best responses. To address the computational challenges posed by combinatorial attacker strategies, each iteration of our multiplicative weights update algorithm computes a projection onto the polytope of marginal attack probabilities under the unnormalized relative entropy, for which we derive a closed-form expression and a linear-time algorithm. Computational results on real-world gas distribution networks illustrate the performance and scalability of our solution approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11545v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Basti\'an Bahamondes, Mathieu Dahan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online Auction Design Using Distribution-Free Uncertainty Quantification with Applications to E-Commerce</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.07038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.07038v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Online auction is a cornerstone of e-commerce, and a key challenge is designing incentive-compatible mechanisms that maximize expected revenue. Existing approaches often assume known bidder value distributions and fixed sets of bidders and items, but these assumptions rarely hold in real-world settings where bidder values are unknown, and the number of future participants is uncertain. In this paper, we introduce the Conformal Online Auction Design (COAD), a novel mechanism that maximizes revenue by quantifying uncertainty in bidder values without relying on known distributions. COAD incorporates both bidder and item features, using historical data to design an incentive-compatible mechanism for online auctions. Unlike traditional methods, COAD leverages distribution-free uncertainty quantification techniques and integrates machine learning methods, such as random forests, kernel methods, and deep neural networks, to predict bidder values while ensuring revenue guarantees. Moreover, COAD introduces bidder-specific reserve prices, based on the lower confidence bounds of bidder valuations, contrasting with the single reserve prices commonly used in the literature. We demonstrate the practical effectiveness of COAD through an application to real-world eBay auction data. Theoretical results and extensive simulation studies further validate the properties of our approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.07038v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiale Han, Xiaowu Dai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Apportionment with Weighted Seats</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18102</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18102v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Apportionment is the task of assigning resources to entities with different entitlements in a fair manner, and specifically a manner that is as proportional as possible. The best-known application is the assignment of parliamentary seats to political parties based on their share in the popular vote. Here we enrich the standard model of apportionment by associating each seat with a weight representing the (objective) value of that seat. A seat's weight reflects the fact that different seats might come with different roles, such as chair or treasurer. We define several apportionment methods and natural fairness requirements for this new setting, and we study the extent to which our methods satisfy these requirements. Our findings show that full fairness is harder to achieve than in the standard apportionment setting. Yet, for several natural relaxations of those requirements we can achieve stronger results than in the more expressive model of fair division with entitlements, where the values of objects are subjective.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18102v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julian Chingoma, Ulle Endriss, Ronald de Haan, Adrian Haret, Jan Maly</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective Two-Stage Double Auction for Dynamic Resource Provision over Edge Networks via Discovering The Power of Overbooking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04507</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04507v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: To facilitate responsive and cost-effective computing service delivery over edge networks, this paper investigates a novel two-stage double auction methodology via discovering an interesting idea of resource overbooking to overcome dynamic and uncertain nature of supply of edge servers (sellers) and demand generated from mobile devices (as buyers). The proposed auction integrates multiple essential goals such as maximizing social welfare as well as accelerating the decision-making process from both short-term and long-term views, (e.g., the time for determining winning seller-buyer pairs), by introducing a stagewise strategy: an overbooking-driven pre-double auction (OPDAuction) for determining long-term cooperations between sellers and buyers before practical resource transactions as Stage I, and a real-time backup double auction (RBDAuction) for quickly coping with residual resource demands during actual transactions. In particular, by embedding a proper overbooking rate, OPDAuction helps with facilitating trading contracts between appropriate sellers and buyers as guidance for future transactions, by allowing the booked resources to exceed theoretical supply. Then, since pre-auctions may cause risks, our RBDAuction adjusts to real-time market changes, further enhancing the overall social welfare. More importantly, we offer an interesting view to show that our proposed two-stage auction can support significant design properties such as truthfulness, individual rationality, and budget balance. Through extensive experiments, we demonstrate good performance in social welfare, time efficiency, and computational scalability, outstripping conventional methods in dynamic edge computing settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04507v4</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sicheng Wu, Minghui Liwang, Deqing Wang, Xianbin Wang, Chao Wu, Junyi Tang, Li Li, Xiaoyu Xia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Relations among Fairness Notions in Discrete Fair Division</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02815v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Fair allocation of indivisible items among agents is a fundamental and extensively studied problem. However, fairness does not have a single universally accepted definition, leading to a variety of competing fairness notions. Some of these notions are considered stronger or more desirable, but they are also more difficult to guarantee. In this work, we examine 22 different notions of fairness and organize them into a hierarchy. Formally, we say that a fairness notion $F_1$ implies another notion $F_2$ if every $F_1$-fair allocation is also $F_2$-fair. We give a near-complete picture of implications among fairness notions: for almost every pair of notions, we either prove an implication or give a counterexample demonstrating that the implication does not hold. Although some of these results are already known, many are new. We examine multiple settings, including the allocation of goods, chores, and mixed manna. We believe this work clarifies the relative strengths and applicability of these notions, providing a foundation for future research in fair division. Moreover, we developed an inference engine to automate part of our work. It is available as a user-friendly web application and may have broader applications beyond fair division.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02815v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jugal Garg, Eklavya Sharma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Auction Design using Value Prediction with Hallucinations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08792v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate a Bayesian mechanism design problem where a seller seeks to maximize revenue by selling an indivisible good to one of n buyers, incorporating potentially unreliable predictions (signals) of buyers' private values derived from a machine learning model. We propose a framework where these signals are sometimes reflective of buyers' true valuations but other times are hallucinations, which are uncorrelated with the buyers' true valuations. Our main contribution is a characterization of the optimal auction under this framework. Our characterization establishes a near-decomposition of how to treat types above and below the signal. For the one buyer case, the seller's optimal strategy is to post one of three fairly intuitive prices depending on the signal, which we call the "ignore", "follow" and "cap" actions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08792v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilan Lobel, Humberto Moreira, Omar Mouchtaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Incentivize Contribution and Learn Parameters Too: Federated Learning with Strategic Data Owners</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.12010v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Classical federated learning (FL) assumes that the clients have a limited amount of noisy data with which they voluntarily participate and contribute towards learning a global, more accurate model in a principled manner. The learning happens in a distributed fashion without sharing the data with the center. However, these methods do not consider the incentive of an agent for participating and contributing to the process, given that data collection and running a distributed algorithm is costly for the clients. The question of rationality of contribution has been asked recently in the literature and some results exist that consider this problem. This paper addresses the question of simultaneous parameter learning and incentivizing contribution in a truthful manner, which distinguishes it from the extant literature. Our first mechanism incentivizes each client to contribute to the FL process at a Nash equilibrium and simultaneously learn the model parameters. We also ensure that agents are incentivized to truthfully reveal information in the intermediate stages of the algorithm. However, this equilibrium outcome can be away from the optimal, where clients contribute with their full data and the algorithm learns the optimal parameters. We propose a second mechanism that enables the full data contribution along with optimal parameter learning. Large scale experiments with real (federated) datasets (CIFAR-10, FEMNIST, and Twitter) show that these algorithms converge quite fast in practice, yield good welfare guarantees and better model performance for all agents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.12010v3</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Drashthi Doshi, Aditya Vema Reddy Kesari, Avishek Ghosh, Swaprava Nath, Suhas S Kowshik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online MMS Allocation for Chores</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14039</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14039v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the problem of fair division of indivisible chores among $n$ agents in an online setting, where items arrive sequentially and must be allocated irrevocably upon arrival. The goal is to produce an $\alpha$-MMS allocation at the end. Several recent works have investigated this model, but have only succeeded in obtaining non-trivial algorithms under restrictive assumptions, such as the two-agent bi-valued special case (Wang and Wei, 2025), or by assuming knowledge of the total disutility of each agent (Zhou, Bai, and Wu, 2023). For the general case, the trivial $n$-MMS guarantee remains the best known, while the strongest lower bound is still only $2$.
  We close this gap on the negative side by proving that for any fixed $n$ and $\varepsilon$, no algorithm can guarantee an $(n - \varepsilon)$-MMS allocation. Notably, this lower bound holds precisely for every $n$, without hiding constants in big-$O$ notation, thereby exactly matching the trivial upper bound.
  Despite this strong impossibility result, we also present positive results. We provide an online algorithm that applies in the general case, guaranteeing a $\min\{n, O(k), O(\log D)\}$-MMS allocation, where $k$ is the maximum number of distinct disutilities across all agents and $D$ is the maximum ratio between the largest and smallest disutilities for any agent. This bound is reasonable across a broad range of scenarios and, for example, implies that we can achieve an $O(1)$-MMS allocation whenever $k$ is constant. Moreover, to optimize the constant in the important personalized bi-valued case, we show that if each agent has at most two distinct disutilities, our algorithm guarantees a $(2 + \sqrt{3}) \approx 3.7$-MMS allocation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14039v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaxin Song, Biaoshuai Tao, Wenqian Wang, Yuhao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What Do Agents Think One Another Want? Level-2 Inverse Games for Inferring Agents' Estimates of Others' Objectives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03824v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Effectively interpreting strategic interactions among multiple agents requires us to infer each agent's objective from limited information. Existing inverse game-theoretic approaches frame this challenge in terms of a "level-1" inference problem, in which we take the perspective of a third-party observer and assume that individual agents share complete knowledge of one another's objectives. However, this assumption breaks down in decentralized, real-world scenarios like urban driving and bargaining, in which agents may act based on conflicting views of one another's objectives. We demonstrate the necessity of inferring agents' different estimates of each other's objectives through empirical examples, and by theoretically characterizing the prediction error of level-1 inference on fictitious gameplay data from linear-quadratic games. To address this fundamental issue, we propose a framework for level-2 inference to address the question: "What does each agent believe about other agents' objectives?" We prove that the level-2 inference problem is non-convex even in benign settings like linear-quadratic games, and we develop an efficient gradient-based approach for identifying local solutions. Experiments on a synthetic urban driving example show that our approach uncovers nuanced misalignments that level-1 methods miss.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03824v4</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hamzah I. Khan, Jingqi Li, David Fridovich-Keil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Axiomatic and Probabilistic Foundations for the Hodge-Theoretic Shapley Value</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.15094</link>
      <description>arXiv:2106.15094v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper establishes a complete theoretical foundation for the Hodge-theoretic extension of the Shapley value introduced by Stern and Tettenhorst (2019). We show that a set of five axioms--efficiency, linearity, symmetry, a modified null-player condition, and an independency principle--uniquely characterize this value across all coalitions, not just the grand coalition. In parallel, we derive a probabilistic representation interpreting each player's value as the expected cumulative marginal contribution along a random walk on the coalition graph. These dual axiomatic and probabilistic results unify fairness and stochastic interpretation, positioning the Hodge-theoretic value as a canonical generalization of Shapley's framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2106.15094v4</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tongseok Lim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>So Long Sucker: Endgame Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17302</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17302v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: So Long Sucker is a strategy board game that requires 4 players, each with $c$ chips of their designated color, and a board made of $k$ empty piles. With a clear set-up comes intricate rules, such as: players taking turns but not in a fixed order, agreements made between some players broken at any time, or a player winning the game without any chips in hand.
  One of the main points of interest in studying this game is finding when a player has a winning strategy. The game begins with four players who get successively eliminated until only the winner is left. To study winning strategies, it is of interest to look at endgame situations. For that, we study the following game set-up: there are two players left in the game, Blue and Red, with only their respective chip colors. In this paper, we characterize Blue's winning scenarios and strategies for this game set-up through a delicate case analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17302v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Lou De Carufel, Marie Rose Jerade</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tight Lower Bound for Multicolor Discrepancy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.18489v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove the following asymptotically tight lower bound for $k$-color discrepancy: For any $k \geq 2$, there exists a hypergraph with $n$ hyperedges such that its $k$-color discrepancy is at least $\Omega(\sqrt{n})$. This improves on the previously known lower bound of $\Omega(\sqrt{n/\log k})$ due to Caragiannis et al. (arXiv:2502.10516). As an application, we show that our result implies improved lower bounds for group fair division.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.18489v3</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pasin Manurangsi, Raghu Meka</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
