<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.GT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.GT</link>
    <description>cs.GT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.GT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 04:01:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Aggregate Fictitious Play for Learning in Anonymous Polymatrix Games (Extended Version)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.19371v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fictitious play (FP) is a well-studied algorithm that enables agents to learn Nash equilibrium in games with certain reward structures. However, when agents have no prior knowledge of the reward functions, FP faces a major challenge: the joint action space grows exponentially with the number of agents, which slows down reward exploration. Anonymous games offer a structure that mitigates this issue. In these games, the rewards depend only on the actions taken; not on who is taking which action. Under such a structure, we introduce aggregate fictitious play (agg-FP), a variant of FP where each agent tracks the frequency of the number of other agents playing each action, rather than these agents' individual actions. We show that in anonymous polymatrix games, agg-FP converges to a Nash equilibrium under the same conditions as classical FP. In essence, by aggregating the agents' actions, we reduce the action space without losing the convergence guarantees. Using simulations, we provide empirical evidence on how this reduction accelerates convergence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.19371v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Semih Kara, Tamer Ba\c{s}ar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The generalized stochastic preference choice model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1803.04244</link>
      <description>arXiv:1803.04244v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a new discrete choice model, called the generalized stochastic preference (GSP) model, that incorporates non-rationality into the stochastic preference (SP) choice model, also known as the rank-based model. Our model can capture several context-dependent choice behaviors that cannot be represented by any SP model, such as the well-documented compromise and attraction effects, while still including the SP model as a special case. The GSP model is defined as a distribution over consumer types, where each type extends the choice behavior of rational types in the SP model. We build on existing methods for estimating the SP model and propose an iterative estimation algorithm for the GSP model that finds new types by solving an integer linear program in each iteration. We further show that our proposed notion of non-rationality can be incorporated into other choice models, like the random utility maximization (RUM) model class as well as any of its subclasses. As a concrete example, we introduce the non-rational extension of the classical MNL model, which we term the generalized MNL (GMNL) model and present an efficient expectation-maximization (EM) algorithm for estimating it. \av{For the GSP model, we demonstrate that the worst-case performance guarantee of revenue-ordered assortments is significantly worse than for the SP model. For the GMNL model, we establish that assortment optimization with totally unimodular constraints is NP-hard to approximate to within a factor of $O(n^{1-\epsilon})$ for any $\epsilon &gt; 0$, where $n$ is the number of products.} Finally, numerical evaluation on synthetic and real choice data shows that the GMNL and GSP models can outperform their rational counterparts in out-of-sample prediction accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1803.04244v4</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gerardo Berbeglia, Ashwin Venkataraman</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
