<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.GT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.GT</link>
    <description>cs.GT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.GT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 01:30:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Capacity Planning in Stable Matching with Truthful or Strategic Preference Uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.22560v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent studies on many-to-one matching markets have explored agents with flexible capacity and truthful preference reporting, focusing on mechanisms that jointly design capacities and select a matching. However, in real-world applications such as school choice and residency matching, preferences are revealed after capacity decisions are made, with matching occurring afterward; uncertainty about agents' preferences must be considered during capacity planning. Moreover, even under strategy-proof mechanisms, agents may strategically misreport preferences based on beliefs about admission chances. We introduce a two-stage stochastic matching problem with uncertain preferences, using school choice as a case study. In the first stage, the clearinghouse expands schools' capacities before observing students' reported preferences. Students either report their true preferences, producing exogenous uncertainty, or act strategically, submitting reported preferences based on their true preferences and admission chances (which depend on capacities), introducing endogenous uncertainty. In the second stage, the clearinghouse computes the student-optimal stable matching based on schools' priorities and students' reported preferences. In strategic cases, endogenous reported preferences are utility-maximizing transformations of capacity decisions and exogenous true preferences; we handle uncertainty using sample average approximation(SAA). We develop behavior-based mathematical formulations and, due to problem complexity, propose Lagrangian- and local-search-based behavior-specific heuristics for near-optimal solutions. Our SAA-based approaches outperform the average scenario approach on students' matching preferences and admission outcomes, emphasizing the impact of stochastic preferences on capacity decisions. Student behavior notably influences capacity design, stressing the need to consider misreports.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.22560v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maria Bazotte, Margarida Carvalho, Thibaut Vidal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Truthful Mechanisms without Discretization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.22911v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces TEDI (Truthful, Expressive, and Dimension-Insensitive approach), a discretization-free algorithm to learn truthful and utility-maximizing mechanisms. Existing learning-based approaches often rely on discretization of outcome spaces to ensure truthfulness, which leads to inefficiency with increasing problem size. To address this limitation, we formalize the concept of pricing rules, defined as functions that map outcomes to prices. Based on this concept, we propose a novel menu mechanism, which can be equivalent to a truthful direct mechanism under specific conditions. The core idea of TEDI lies in its parameterization of pricing rules using Partial GroupMax Network, a new network architecture designed to universally approximate partial convex functions. To learn optimal pricing rules, we develop novel training techniques, including covariance trick and continuous sampling, to derive unbiased gradient estimators compatible with first-order optimization. Theoretical analysis establishes that TEDI guarantees truthfulness, full expressiveness, and dimension-insensitivity. Experimental evaluation in the studied auction setting demonstrates that TEDI achieves strong performance, competitive with or exceeding state-of-the-art methods.
  This work presents the first approaches to learn truthful mechanisms without outcome discretization, thereby enhancing algorithmic efficiency. The proposed concepts, network architecture, and learning techniques might offer potential value and provide new insights for automated mechanism design and differentiable economics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.22911v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunxuan Ma, Siqiang Wang, Zhijian Duan, Yukun Cheng, Xiaotie Deng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Markov Chains of Evolutionary Games with a Small Number of Players</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.23134v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct and study the transition probability matrix of evolutionary games in which the number of players is finite (and relatively small) of such games. We use a simplified version of the population games studied by Sandholm. After laying out a general framework we concentrate on specific examples, involving the Iterated Prisoner's Dilemma, the Iterated Stag Hunt, and the Rock-Paper-Scissors game. Also we consider several revision protocols: Best Response, Pairwise Comparison, Pairwise Proportional Comparison etc. For each of these we explicitly construct the MC transition probability matrix and study its properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.23134v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Athanasios Kehagias</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interdependent Bilateral Trade: Information vs Approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23896</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.23896v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Welfare maximization in bilateral trade has been extensively studied in recent years. Previous literature obtained incentive-compatible approximation mechanisms only for the private values case. In this paper, we study welfare maximization in bilateral trade with interdependent values. Designing mechanisms for interdependent settings is much more challenging because the values of the players depend on the private information of the others, requiring complex belief updates and strategic inference. We propose to classify information structures by quantifying the influence that a player's private signal has on their own valuation. We then paint a picture of where approximations are possible and impossible based on these information structures. Finally, we also study the possible approximation ratios for a natural family of information structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.23896v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shahar Dobzinski, Alon Eden, Kira Goldner, Ariel Shaulker, Thodoris Tsilivis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quickest Detection of Adversarial Attacks Against Correlated Equilibria</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.24040</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.24040v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider correlated equilibria in strategic games in an adversarial environment, where an adversary can compromise the public signal used by the players for choosing their strategies, while players aim at detecting a potential attack as soon as possible to avoid loss of utility. We model the interaction between the adversary and the players as a zero-sum game and we derive the maxmin strategies for both the defender and the attacker using the framework of quickest change detection. We define a class of adversarial strategies that achieve the optimal trade-off between attack impact and attack detectability and show that a generalized CUSUM scheme is asymptotically optimal for the detection of the attacks. Our numerical results on the Sioux-Falls benchmark traffic routing game show that the proposed detection scheme can effectively limit the utility loss by a potential adversary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.24040v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1609/aaai.v39i13.33527</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence, 39(13), 13961-13968 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kiarash Kazari, Aris Kanellopoulos, Gy\"orgy D\'an</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Static Nuel Games with Terminal Payoff</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.01681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.01681v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we study a variant of the Nuel game (a generalization of the duel) which is played in turns by $N$ players. In each turn a single player must fire at one of the other players and has a certain probability of hitting and killing his target. The players shoot in a fixed sequence and when a player is eliminated, the ``move'' passes to the next surviving player. The winner is the last surviving player. We prove that, for every $N\geq2$, the Nuel has a stationary Nash equilibrium and provide algorithms for its computation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.01681v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Mastrakoulis, Ath. Kehagias</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Highway toll allocation problem revisited: new methods and characterizations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22475</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.22475v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper considers the highway toll allocation problem (Wu, van den Brink, and Est\'evez-Fern\'andez in Transport Res B-Meth 180:10288, 2024). The aim is to allocate the tolls collected from the users of a highway across the various road sections. To this end, the authors propose, among others, the Segments Equal Sharing method, which is characterized and reinterpreted as a specific solution of a cooperative game associated with the problem. This paper presents two new allocation rules: the Segments Proportional Sharing method and the Segments Compensated Sharing method. We axiomatically characterize these new methods and compare their properties to those of the Segments Equal Sharing method. Furthermore, we also examine the relationship of these methods to the solution of the associated cooperative game. We conclude the methodological study by introducing a general family of segment allocation methods that includes the three aforementioned rules. Finally, we evaluate the performance of these methods using a real-world dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.22475v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Soto-Rodr\'iguez, B. Casas-M\'endez, A. Saavedra-Nieves</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marker Gene Method : Identifying Stable Solutions in a Dynamic Environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.23734v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Competitive Co-evolutionary Algorithms (CCEAs) are often hampered by complex dynamics like intransitivity and the Red Queen effect, leading to unstable convergence. To counter these challenges, this paper introduces the Marker Gene Method (MGM), a framework that establishes stability by using a 'marker gene' as a dynamic benchmark and an adaptive weighting mechanism to balance exploration and exploitation. We provide rigorous mathematical proofs demonstrating that MGM creates strong attractors near Nash Equilibria within the Strictly Competitive Game framework. Empirically, MGM demonstrates its efficacy across a spectrum of challenges: it stabilizes the canonical Rock-Paper-Scissors game, significantly improves the performance of C-RMOEA/D on ZDT benchmarks, and, when augmented with a Memory Pool (MP) extension, it successfully tames the notoriously pathological Shapley Biased Game. This work presents a theoretically sound and empirically validated framework that substantially enhances the stability and robustness of CCEAs in complex competitive environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.23734v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Shi, Xi Li, Fangfang Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayes correlated equilibria, no-regret dynamics in Bayesian games, and the price of anarchy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.05005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.05005v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates equilibrium computation and the price of anarchy for Bayesian games, which are the fundamental models of games with incomplete information. In normal-form games with complete information, it is known that efficiently computable no-regret dynamics converge to correlated equilibria, and the price of anarchy for correlated equilibria can be bounded for a broad class of games called smooth games. However, in Bayesian games, as surveyed by Forges (1993), several non-equivalent extensions of correlated equilibria exist, and it remains unclear whether they can be efficiently computed or whether their price of anarchy can be bounded.
  In this paper, we identify a natural extension of correlated equilibria that can be computed efficiently and is guaranteed to have bounds on the price of anarchy in various games. First, we propose a variant of regret called untruthful swap regret. If each player minimizes it in repeated play of Bayesian games, the empirical distribution of these dynamics is guaranteed to converge to communication equilibria, which is one of the extensions of correlated equilibria proposed by Myerson (1982). We present an efficient algorithm for minimizing untruthful swap regret with a sublinear upper bound, which we prove to be tight in terms of the number of types. As a result, by simulating the dynamics with our algorithm, we can approximately compute a communication equilibrium in polynomial time. Furthermore, we extend existing lower bounds on the price of anarchy based on the smoothness arguments from Bayes--Nash equilibria to equilibria obtained by the proposed dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.05005v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaito Fujii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Oracle Complexity of Simplex-based Matrix Games: Linear Separability and Nash Equilibria</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06990v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the problem of solving matrix games of the form $\max_{\mathbf{w}\in\mathcal{W}}\min_{\mathbf{p}\in\Delta}\mathbf{p}^{\top}A\mathbf{w}$, where $A$ is some matrix and $\Delta$ is the probability simplex. This problem encapsulates canonical tasks such as finding a linear separator and computing Nash equilibria in zero-sum games. However, perhaps surprisingly, its inherent complexity (as formalized in the standard framework of oracle complexity [Nemirovski and Yudin, 1983]) is not well-understood. In this work, we first identify different oracle models which are implicitly used by prior algorithms, amounting to multiplying the matrix $A$ by a vector from either one or both sides. We then prove complexity lower bounds for algorithms under both access models, which in particular imply a separation between them. Specifically, we start by showing that algorithms for linear separability based on one-sided multiplications must require $\Omega(\gamma_A^{-2})$ iterations, where $\gamma_A$ is the margin, as matched by the Perceptron algorithm. We then prove that accelerated algorithms for this task, which utilize multiplications from both sides, must require $\tilde{\Omega}(\gamma_{A}^{-2/3})$ iterations, establishing the first oracle complexity barrier for such algorithms. Finally, by adapting our lower bound to $\ell_1$ geometry, we prove that computing an $\epsilon$-approximate Nash equilibrium requires $\tilde{\Omega}(\epsilon^{-2/5})$ iterations, which is an exponential improvement over the previously best-known lower bound due to Hadiji et al. [2024].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06990v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guy Kornowski, Ohad Shamir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Convergence of Min-Max Langevin Dynamics and Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20471v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study zero-sum games in the space of probability distributions over the Euclidean space $\mathbb{R}^d$ with entropy regularization, in the setting when the interaction function between the players is smooth and strongly convex-strongly concave. We prove an exponential convergence guarantee for the mean-field min-max Langevin dynamics to compute the equilibrium distribution of the zero-sum game. We also study the finite-particle approximation of the mean-field min-max Langevin dynamics, both in continuous and discrete times. We prove biased convergence guarantees for the continuous-time finite-particle min-max Langevin dynamics to the stationary mean-field equilibrium distribution with an explicit bias term which does not scale with the number of particles. We also prove biased convergence guarantees for the discrete-time finite-particle min-max Langevin algorithm to the stationary mean-field equilibrium distribution with an additional bias term which scales with the step size and the number of particles. This provides an explicit iteration complexity for the average particle along the finite-particle algorithm to approximately compute the equilibrium distribution of the zero-sum game.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20471v3</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Cai, Siddharth Mitra, Xiuyuan Wang, Andre Wibisono</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The residual maximin share</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19961v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider fair allocations of indivisible goods to agents with general monotone valuations. We observe that it is useful to introduce a new share-based fairness notion, the {\em residual maximin share} (RMMS). This share is {\em feasible} and {\em self maximizing}. Its value is at least as large as the MXS for monotone valuations, and at least as large as $\frac{2}{3}$-MMS for additive valuations. Known techniques easily imply the existence of partial allocations that are both RMMS and EFX, and complete allocations that are both RMMS and EFL. This unifies and somewhat improves upon several different results from previous papers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19961v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Uriel Feige</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A few good choices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.22133v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A Condorcet winning set addresses the Condorcet paradox by selecting a few candidates--rather than a single winner--such that no unselected alternative is preferred to all of them by a majority of voters. This idea extends to $\alpha$-undominated sets, which ensure the same property for any $\alpha$-fraction of voters and are guaranteed to exist in constant size for any $\alpha$. However, the requirement that an outsider be preferred to every member of the set can be overly restrictive and difficult to justify in many applications. Motivated by this, we introduce a more flexible notion: $(t, \alpha)$-undominated sets. Here, each voter compares an outsider to their $t$-th most preferred member of the set, and the set is undominated if no outsider is preferred by more than an $\alpha$-fraction of voters. This framework subsumes prior definitions, recovering Condorcet winning sets when $(t = 1, \alpha = 1/2)$ and $\alpha$-undominated sets when $t = 1$, and introduces a new, tunable notion of collective acceptability for $t &gt; 1$. We establish three main results:
  1. We prove that a $(t, \alpha)$-undominated set of size $O(t/\alpha)$ exists for all values of $t$ and $\alpha$.
  2. We show that as $t$ becomes large, the minimum size of such a set approaches $t/\alpha$, which is asymptotically optimal.
  3. In the special case $t = 1$, we improve the bound on the size of an $\alpha$-undominated set given by Charikar, Lassota, Ramakrishnan, Vetta, and Wang (STOC 2025). As a consequence, we show that a Condorcet winning set of five candidates exists, improving their bound of six.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.22133v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thanh Nguyen, Haoyu Song, Young-San Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating Agents using Social Choice Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.03121</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.03121v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We argue that many general evaluation problems can be viewed through the lens of voting theory. Each task is interpreted as a separate voter, which requires only ordinal rankings or pairwise comparisons of agents to produce an overall evaluation. By viewing the aggregator as a social welfare function, we are able to leverage centuries of research in social choice theory to derive principled evaluation frameworks with axiomatic foundations. These evaluations are interpretable and flexible, while avoiding many of the problems currently facing cross-task evaluation. We apply this Voting-as-Evaluation (VasE) framework across multiple settings, including reinforcement learning, large language models, and humans. In practice, we observe that VasE can be more robust than popular evaluation frameworks (Elo and Nash averaging), discovers properties in the evaluation data not evident from scores alone, and can predict outcomes better than Elo in a complex seven-player game. We identify one particular approach, maximal lotteries, that satisfies important consistency properties relevant to evaluation, is computationally efficient (polynomial in the size of the evaluation data), and identifies game-theoretic cycles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.03121v4</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marc Lanctot, Kate Larson, Yoram Bachrach, Luke Marris, Zun Li, Avishkar Bhoopchand, Thomas Anthony, Brian Tanner, Anna Koop</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding and Reducing the Class-Dependent Effects of Data Augmentation with A Two-Player Game Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03146v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Data augmentation is widely applied and has shown its benefits in different machine learning tasks. However, as recently observed, it may have an unfair effect in multi-class classification. While data augmentation generally improves the overall performance (and therefore is beneficial for many classes), it can actually be detrimental for other classes, which can be problematic in some application domains. In this paper, to counteract this phenomenon, we propose CLAM, a CLAss-dependent Multiplicative-weights method. To derive it, we first formulate the training of a classifier as a non-linear optimization problem that aims at simultaneously maximizing the individual class performances and balancing them. By rewriting this optimization problem as an adversarial two-player game, we propose a novel multiplicative weight algorithm, for which we prove the convergence. Interestingly, our formulation also reveals that the class-dependent effects of data augmentation is not due to data augmentation only, but is in fact a general phenomenon. Our empirical results over six datasets demonstrate that the performance of learned classifiers is indeed more fairly distributed over classes, with only limited impact on the average accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03146v5</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunpeng Jiang, Yutong Ban, Paul Weng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Games with $\omega$-Automatic Preference Relations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04759v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates Nash equilibria (NEs) in multi-player turn-based games on graphs, where player preferences are modeled as $\omega$-automatic relations via deterministic parity automata. Unlike much of the existing literature, which focuses on specific reward functions, our results apply to any preference relation definable by an $\omega$-automatic relation. We analyze the computational complexity of determining the existence of an NE (possibly under some constraints), verifying whether a given strategy profile forms an NE, and checking whether a specific outcome can be realized by an NE. When a (constrained) NE exists, we show that there always exists one with finite-memory strategies. Finally, we explore fundamental properties of $\omega$-automatic relations and their implications in the existence of equilibria.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04759v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V\'eronique Bruy\`ere, Christophe Grandmont, Jean-Fran\c{c}ois Raskin</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
