<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NE</link>
    <description>cs.NE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2024 02:57:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>An Inverse Modeling Constrained Multi-Objective Evolutionary Algorithm Based on Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19203v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces the inverse modeling constrained multi-objective evolutionary algorithm based on decomposition (IM-C-MOEA/D) for addressing constrained real-world optimization problems. Our research builds upon the advancements made in evolutionary computing-based inverse modeling, and it strategically bridges the gaps in applying inverse models based on decomposition to problem domains with constraints. The proposed approach is experimentally evaluated on diverse real-world problems (RWMOP1-35), showing superior performance to state-of-the-art constrained multi-objective evolutionary algorithms (CMOEAs). The experimental results highlight the robustness of the algorithm and its applicability in real-world constrained optimization scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19203v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas R. C. Farias, Aluizio F. R. Ara\'ujo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Genetic Motifs as a Blueprint for Mismatch-Tolerant Neuromorphic Computing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19403</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19403v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mixed-signal implementations of SNNs offer a promising solution to edge computing applications that require low-power and compact embedded processing systems. However, device mismatch in the analog circuits of these neuromorphic processors poses a significant challenge to the deployment of robust processing in these systems. Here we introduce a novel architectural solution inspired by biological development to address this issue. Specifically we propose to implement architectures that incorporate network motifs found in developed brains through a differentiable re-parameterization of weight matrices based on gene expression patterns and genetic rules. Thanks to the gradient descent optimization compatibility of the method proposed, we can apply the robustness of biological neural development to neuromorphic computing.
  To validate this approach we benchmark it using the Yin-Yang classification dataset, and compare its performance with that of standard multilayer perceptrons trained with state-of-the-art hardware-aware training method. Our results demonstrate that the proposed method mitigates mismatch-induced noise without requiring precise device mismatch measurements, effectively outperforming alternative hardware-aware techniques proposed in the literature, and providing a more general solution for improving the robustness of SNNs in neuromorphic hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19403v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tommaso Boccato, Dmitrii Zendrikov, Nicola Toschi, Giacomo Indiveri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolving choice hysteresis in reinforcement learning: comparing the adaptive value of positivity bias and gradual perseveration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19434</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19434v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The tendency of repeating past choices more often than expected from the history of outcomes has been repeatedly empirically observed in reinforcement learning experiments. It can be explained by at least two computational processes: asymmetric update and (gradual) choice perseveration. A recent meta-analysis showed that both mechanisms are detectable in human reinforcement learning. However, while their descriptive value seems to be well established, they have not been compared regarding their possible adaptive value. In this study, we address this gap by simulating reinforcement learning agents in a variety of environments with a new variant of an evolutionary algorithm. Our results show that positivity bias (in the form of asymmetric update) is evolutionary stable in many situations, while the emergence of gradual perseveration is less systematic and robust. Overall, our results illustrate that biases can be adaptive and selected by evolution, in an environment-specific manner.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19434v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Isabelle Hoxha, Leo Sperber, Stefano Palminteri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Dominated Sorting Bidirectional Differential Coevolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19439v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Constrained multiobjective optimization problems (CMOPs) are commonly found in real-world applications. CMOP is a complex problem that needs to satisfy a set of equality or inequality constraints. This paper proposes a variant of the bidirectional coevolution algorithm (BiCo) with differential evolution (DE). The novelties in the model include the DE differential mutation and crossover operators as the main search engine and a non-dominated sorting selection scheme. Experimental results on two benchmark test suites and eight real-world CMOPs suggested that the proposed model reached better overall performance than the original model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19439v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cicero S. R. Mendes, Aluizio F. R. Ara\'ujo, Lucas R. C. Farias</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Memetic Search for Electric Vehicle Routing with Time Windows, Simultaneous Pickup-Delivery, and Partial Recharges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19580v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With growing environmental concerns, electric vehicles for logistics have gained significant attention within the computational intelligence community in recent years. This work addresses an emerging and significant extension of the electric vehicle routing problem (EVRP), namely EVRP with time windows, simultaneous pickup-delivery, and partial recharges (EVRP-TW-SPD), which has wide real-world applications. We propose a hybrid memetic algorithm (HMA) for solving EVRP-TW-SPD. HMA incorporates two novel components: a parallel-sequential station insertion procedure for handling partial recharges that can better avoid local optima compared to purely sequential insertion, and a cross-domain neighborhood search that explores solution spaces of both electric and non-electric problem domains simultaneously. These components can also be easily applied to various EVRP variants. To bridge the gap between existing benchmarks and real-world scenarios, we introduce a new, large-scale EVRP-TW-SPD benchmark set derived from real-world applications, containing instances with many more customers and charging stations than existing benchmark instances. Extensive experiments demonstrate the significant performance advantages of HMA over existing algorithms across a wide range of problem instances. Both the benchmark set and HMA will be open-sourced to facilitate further research in this area.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19580v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zubin Zheng, Shengcai Liu, Yew-Soon Ong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Hearthstone Agents using an Evolutionary Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19681v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Digital collectible card games are not only a growing part of the video game industry, but also an interesting research area for the field of computational intelligence. This game genre allows researchers to deal with hidden information, uncertainty and planning, among other aspects. This paper proposes the use of evolutionary algorithms (EAs) to develop agents who play a card game, Hearthstone, by optimizing a data-driven decision-making mechanism that takes into account all the elements currently in play. Agents feature self-learning by means of a competitive coevolutionary training approach, whereby no external sparring element defined by the user is required for the optimization process. One of the agents developed through the proposed approach was runner-up (best 6%) in an international Hearthstone Artificial Intelligence (AI) competition. Our proposal performed remarkably well, even when it faced state-of-the-art techniques that attempted to take into account future game states, such as Monte-Carlo Tree search. This outcome shows how evolutionary computation could represent a considerable advantage in developing AIs for collectible card games such as Hearthstone.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19681v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.knosys.2019.105032</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Knowledge-Based Systems 188:105032, 2020</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pablo Garc\'ia-S\'anchez, Alberto Tonda, Antonio J. Fern\'andez-Leiva, Carlos Cotta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In-Simulation Testing of Deep Learning Vision Models in Autonomous Robotic Manipulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19277v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Testing autonomous robotic manipulators is challenging due to the complex software interactions between vision and control components. A crucial element of modern robotic manipulators is the deep learning based object detection model. The creation and assessment of this model requires real world data, which can be hard to label and collect, especially when the hardware setup is not available. The current techniques primarily focus on using synthetic data to train deep neural networks (DDNs) and identifying failures through offline or online simulation-based testing. However, the process of exploiting the identified failures to uncover design flaws early on, and leveraging the optimized DNN within the simulation to accelerate the engineering of the DNN for real-world tasks remains unclear. To address these challenges, we propose the MARTENS (Manipulator Robot Testing and Enhancement in Simulation) framework, which integrates a photorealistic NVIDIA Isaac Sim simulator with evolutionary search to identify critical scenarios aiming at improving the deep learning vision model and uncovering system design flaws. Evaluation of two industrial case studies demonstrated that MARTENS effectively reveals robotic manipulator system failures, detecting 25 % to 50 % more failures with greater diversity compared to random test generation. The model trained and repaired using the MARTENS approach achieved mean average precision (mAP) scores of 0.91 and 0.82 on real-world images with no prior retraining. Further fine-tuning on real-world images for a few epochs (less than 10) increased the mAP to 0.95 and 0.89 for the first and second use cases, respectively. In contrast, a model trained solely on real-world data achieved mAPs of 0.8 and 0.75 for use case 1 and use case 2 after more than 25 epochs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19277v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3691620.3695281</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Dmytro Humeniuk, Houssem Ben Braiek, Thomas Reid, Foutse Khomh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How high dimensional neural dynamics are confined in phase space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19348v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: High dimensional dynamics play a vital role in brain function, ecological systems, and neuro-inspired machine learning. Where and how these dynamics are confined in the phase space remains challenging to solve. Here, we provide an analytic argument that the confinement region is an M-shape when the neural dynamics show a diversity, with two sharp boundaries and a flat low-density region in between. Despite increasing synaptic strengths in a neural circuit, the shape remains qualitatively the same, while the left boundary is continuously pushed away. However, in deep chaotic regions, an arch-shaped confinement gradually emerges. Our theory is supported by numerical simulations on finite-sized networks. This analytic theory opens up a geometric route towards addressing fundamental questions about high dimensional non-equilibrium dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19348v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shishe Wang, Haiping Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Understanding the Link Between Modularity and Performance in Neural Networks for Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.06451</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.06451v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Modularity has been widely studied as a mechanism to improve the capabilities of neural networks through various techniques such as hand-crafted modular architectures and automatic approaches. While these methods have sometimes shown improvements towards generalisation ability, robustness, and efficiency, the mechanisms that enable modularity to give performance advantages are unclear. In this paper, we investigate this issue and find that the amount of network modularity for optimal performance is likely entangled in complex relationships between many other features of the network and problem environment. Therefore, direct optimisation or arbitrary designation of a suitable amount of modularity in neural networks may not be beneficial. We used a classic neuroevolutionary algorithm which enables rich, automatic optimisation and exploration of neural network architectures and weights with varying levels of modularity. The structural modularity and performance of networks generated by the NeuroEvolution of Augmenting Topologies algorithm was assessed on three reinforcement learning tasks, with and without an additional modularity objective. The results of the quality-diversity optimisation algorithm, MAP-Elites, suggest intricate conditional relationships between modularity, performance, and other predefined network features.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.06451v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Humphrey Munn, Marcus Gallagher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contrastive-Signal-Dependent Plasticity: Self-Supervised Learning in Spiking Neural Circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.18187</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.18187v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Brain-inspired machine intelligence research seeks to develop computational models that emulate the information processing and adaptability that distinguishes biological systems of neurons. This has led to the development of spiking neural networks, a class of models that promisingly addresses the biological implausibility and {the lack of energy efficiency} inherent to modern-day deep neural networks. In this work, we address the challenge of designing neurobiologically-motivated schemes for adjusting the synapses of spiking networks and propose contrastive-signal-dependent plasticity, a process which generalizes ideas behind self-supervised learning to facilitate local adaptation in architectures of event-based neuronal layers that operate in parallel. Our experimental simulations demonstrate a consistent advantage over other biologically-plausible approaches when training recurrent spiking networks, crucially side-stepping the need for extra structure such as feedback synapses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.18187v3</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1126/sciadv.adn6076</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Ororbia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MC-QDSNN: Quantized Deep evolutionary SNN with Multi-Dendritic Compartment Neurons for Stress Detection using Physiological Signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04992v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Long short-term memory (LSTM) has emerged as a definitive network for analyzing and inferring time series data. LSTM has the capability to extract spectral features and a mixture of temporal features. Due to this benefit, a similar feature extraction method is explored for the spiking counterparts targeting time-series data. Though LSTMs perform well in their spiking form, they tend to be compute and power intensive. Addressing this issue, this work proposes Multi-Compartment Leaky (MCLeaky) neuron as a viable alternative for efficient processing of time series data. The MCLeaky neuron, derived from the Leaky Integrate and Fire (LIF) neuron model, contains multiple memristive synapses interlinked to form a memory component, which emulates the human brain's Hippocampus region. The proposed MCLeaky neuron based Spiking Neural Network model and its quantized variant were benchmarked against state-of-the-art (SOTA) Spiking LSTMs to perform human stress detection, by comparing compute requirements, latency and real-world performances on unseen data with models derived through Neural Architecture Search (NAS). Results show that networks with MCLeaky activation neuron managed a superior accuracy of 98.8% to detect stress based on Electrodermal Activity (EDA) signals, better than any other investigated models, while using 20% less parameters on average. MCLeaky neuron was also tested for various signals including EDA Wrist and Chest, Temperature, ECG, and combinations of them. Quantized MCLeaky model was also derived and validated to forecast their performance on hardware architectures, which resulted in 91.84% accuracy. The neurons were evaluated for multiple modalities of data towards stress detection, which resulted in energy savings of 25.12x to 39.20x and EDP gains of 52.37x to 81.9x over ANNs, while offering a best accuracy of 98.8% when compared with the rest of the SOTA implementations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04992v3</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TCAD.2024.3484353</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ajay B S, Phani Pavan K, Madhav Rao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparative Analysis of Indicators for Multiobjective Diversity Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18900</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18900v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Indicator-based (multiobjective) diversity optimization aims at finding a set of near (Pareto-)optimal solutions that maximizes a diversity indicator, where diversity is typically interpreted as the number of essentially different solutions. Whereas, in the first diversity-oriented evolutionary multiobjective optimization algorithm, the NOAH algorithm by Ulrich and Thiele, the Solow Polasky Diversity (also related to Magnitude) served as a metric, other diversity indicators might be considered, such as the parameter-free Max-Min Diversity, and the Riesz s-Energy, which features uniformly distributed solution sets. In this paper, focusing on multiobjective diversity optimization, we discuss different diversity indicators from the perspective of indicator-based evolutionary algorithms (IBEA) with multiple objectives. We examine theoretical, computational, and practical properties of these indicators, such as monotonicity in species, twinning, monotonicity in distance, strict monotonicity in distance, uniformity of maximizing point sets, computational effort for a set of size~n, single-point contributions, subset selection, and submodularity. We present new theorems -- including a proof of the NP-hardness of the Riesz s-Energy Subset Selection Problem -- and consolidate existing results from the literature. In the second part, we apply these indicators in the NOAH algorithm and analyze search dynamics through an example. We examine how optimizing with one indicator affects the performance of others and propose NOAH adaptations specific to the Max-Min indicator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18900v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ksenia Pereverdieva, Andr\'e Deutz, Tessa Ezendam, Thomas B\"ack, H\`erm Hofmeyer, Michael T. M. Emmerich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EVOTER: Evolution of Transparent Explainable Rule-sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.10438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2204.10438v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Most AI systems are black boxes generating reasonable outputs for given inputs. Some domains, however, have explainability and trustworthiness requirements that cannot be directly met by these approaches. Various methods have therefore been developed to interpret black-box models after training. This paper advocates an alternative approach where the models are transparent and explainable to begin with. This approach, EVOTER, evolves rule-sets based on simple logical expressions. The approach is evaluated in several prediction/classification and prescription/policy search domains with and without a surrogate. It is shown to discover meaningful rule sets that perform similarly to black-box models. The rules can provide insight into the domain, and make biases hidden in the data explicit. It may also be possible to edit them directly to remove biases and add constraints. EVOTER thus forms a promising foundation for building trustworthy AI systems for real-world applications in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2204.10438v5</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hormoz Shahrzad, Babak Hodjat, Risto Miikkulainen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relational Concept Bottleneck Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.11991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.11991v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The design of interpretable deep learning models working in relational domains poses an open challenge: interpretable deep learning methods, such as Concept Bottleneck Models (CBMs), are not designed to solve relational problems, while relational deep learning models, such as Graph Neural Networks (GNNs), are not as interpretable as CBMs. To overcome these limitations, we propose Relational Concept Bottleneck Models (R-CBMs), a family of relational deep learning methods providing interpretable task predictions. As special cases, we show that R-CBMs are capable of both representing standard CBMs and message-passing GNNs. To evaluate the effectiveness and versatility of these models, we designed a class of experimental problems, ranging from image classification to link prediction in knowledge graphs. In particular we show that R-CBMs (i) match generalization performance of existing relational black-boxes, (ii) support the generation of quantified concept-based explanations, (iii) effectively respond to test-time interventions, and (iv) withstand demanding settings including out-of-distribution scenarios, limited training data regimes, and scarce concept supervisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.11991v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pietro Barbiero, Francesco Giannini, Gabriele Ciravegna, Michelangelo Diligenti, Giuseppe Marra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Heuristics for Transit Network Design and Improvement with Deep Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05894v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Transit agencies world-wide face tightening budgets. To maintain quality of service while cutting costs, efficient transit network design is essential. But planning a network of public transit routes is a challenging optimization problem. The most successful approaches to date use metaheuristic algorithms to search through the space of possible transit networks by applying low-level heuristics that randomly alter routes in a network. The design of these low-level heuristics has a major impact on the quality of the result. In this paper we use deep reinforcement learning with graph neural nets to learn low-level heuristics for an evolutionary algorithm, instead of designing them manually. These learned heuristics improve the algorithm's results on benchmark synthetic cities with 70 nodes or more, and obtain state-of-the-art results when optimizing operating costs. They also improve upon a simulation of the real transit network in the city of Laval, Canada, by as much as 54% and 18% on two key metrics, and offer cost savings of up to 12% over the city's existing transit network.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05894v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Holliday, Ahmed El-Geneidy, Gregory Dudek</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
