<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NE</link>
    <description>cs.NE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 04:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>An Artificial Neural Network for Image Classification Inspired by Aversive Olfactory Learning Circuits in Caenorhabditis Elegans</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07466v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study introduces an artificial neural network (ANN) for image classification task, inspired by the aversive olfactory learning circuits of the nematode Caenorhabditis elegans (C. elegans). Despite the remarkable performance of ANNs in a variety of tasks, they face challenges such as excessive parameterization, high training costs and limited generalization capabilities. C. elegans, with its simple nervous system comprising only 302 neurons, serves as a paradigm in neurobiological research and is capable of complex behaviors including learning. This research identifies key neural circuits associated with aversive olfactory learning in C. elegans through behavioral experiments and high-throughput gene sequencing, translating them into an image classification ANN architecture. Additionally, two other image classification ANNs with distinct architectures were constructed for comparative performance analysis to highlight the advantages of bio-inspired design. The results indicate that the ANN inspired by the aversive olfactory learning circuits of C. elegans achieves higher accuracy, better consistency and faster convergence rates in image classification task, especially when tackling more complex classification challenges. This study not only showcases the potential of bio-inspired design in enhancing ANN capabilities but also provides a novel perspective and methodology for future ANN design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07466v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuebin Wang, Chunxiuzi Liu, Meng Zhao, Ke Zhang, Zengru Di, He Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Training Spiking Neural Networks via Augmented Direct Feedback Alignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07776v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spiking neural networks (SNNs), the models inspired by the mechanisms of real neurons in the brain, transmit and represent information by employing discrete action potentials or spikes. The sparse, asynchronous properties of information processing make SNNs highly energy efficient, leading to SNNs being promising solutions for implementing neural networks in neuromorphic devices. However, the nondifferentiable nature of SNN neurons makes it a challenge to train them. The current training methods of SNNs that are based on error backpropagation (BP) and precisely designing surrogate gradient are difficult to implement and biologically implausible, hindering the implementation of SNNs on neuromorphic devices. Thus, it is important to train SNNs with a method that is both physically implementatable and biologically plausible. In this paper, we propose using augmented direct feedback alignment (aDFA), a gradient-free approach based on random projection, to train SNNs. This method requires only partial information of the forward process during training, so it is easy to implement and biologically plausible. We systematically demonstrate the feasibility of the proposed aDFA-SNNs scheme, propose its effective working range, and analyze its well-performing settings by employing genetic algorithm. We also analyze the impact of crucial features of SNNs on the scheme, thus demonstrating its superiority and stability over BP and conventional direct feedback alignment. Our scheme can achieve competitive performance without accurate prior knowledge about the utilized system, thus providing a valuable reference for physically training SNNs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07776v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongbo Zhang, Katsuma Inoue, Mitsumasa Nakajima, Toshikazu Hashimoto, Yasuo Kuniyoshi, Kohei Nakajima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classifying Images with CoLaNET Spiking Neural Network -- the MNIST Example</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07833v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the present paper, it is shown how the columnar/layered CoLaNET spiking neural network (SNN) architecture can be used in supervised learning image classification tasks. Image pixel brightness is coded by the spike count during image presentation period. Image class label is indicated by activity of special SNN input nodes (one node per class). The CoLaNET classification accuracy is evaluated on the MNIST benchmark. It is demonstrated that CoLaNET is almost as accurate as the most advanced machine learning algorithms (not using convolutional approach).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07833v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail Kiselev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning of Nonlinear Dynamical Systems with Control Parameters Using Feedforward Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07468v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Several authors have reported that the echo state network reproduces bifurcation diagrams of some nonlinear differential equations using the data for a few control parameters. We demonstrate that a simpler feedforward neural network can also reproduce the bifurcation diagram of the logistics map and synchronization transition in globally coupled Stuart-Landau equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07468v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hidetsugu Sakaguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MToP: A MATLAB Optimization Platform for Evolutionary Multitasking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.08134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.08134v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Evolutionary multitasking (EMT) has emerged as a popular topic of evolutionary computation over the past years. It aims to concurrently address multiple optimization tasks within limited computing resources, leveraging inter-task knowledge transfer techniques. Despite the abundance of multitask evolutionary algorithms (MTEAs) proposed for multitask optimization (MTO), there remains a comprehensive software platform to help researchers evaluate MTEA performance on benchmark MTO problems as well as explore real-world applications. To bridge this gap, we introduce the first open-source optimization platform, named MTO-Platform (MToP), for EMT. MToP incorporates over 40 MTEAs, more than 150 MTO problem cases with real-world applications, and over 20 performance metrics. Moreover, to facilitate comparative analyses between MTEAs and traditional evolutionary algorithms, we adapted over 40 popular single-task evolutionary algorithms to address MTO problems. MToP boasts a user-friendly graphical interface, facilitating results analysis, data export, and schematics visualization. More importantly, MToP is designed with extensibility in mind, allowing users to develop new algorithms and tackle emerging problem domains. The source code of MToP is available at https://github.com/intLyc/MTO-Platform.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.08134v3</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanchi Li, Wenyin Gong, Fei Ming, Tingyu Zhang, Shuijia Li, Qiong Gu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CoLaNET -- A Spiking Neural Network with Columnar Layered Architecture for Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.01230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.01230v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the present paper, I describe a spiking neural network (SNN) architecture which, can be used in wide range of supervised learning classification tasks. It is assumed, that all participating signals (the classified object description, correct class label and SNN decision) have spiking nature. The distinctive feature of this architecture is a combination of prototypical network structures corresponding to different classes and significantly distinctive instances of one class (=columns) and functionally differing populations of neurons inside columns (=layers). The other distinctive feature is a novel combination of anti-Hebbian and dopamine-modulated plasticity. The plasticity rules are local and do not use the backpropagation principle. Besides that, as in my previous studies, I was guided by the requirement that the all neuron/plasticity models should be easily implemented on modern neurochips. I illustrate the high performance of my network on a task related to model-based reinforcement learning, namely, evaluation of proximity of an external world state to the target state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.01230v4</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail Kiselev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contrastive Learning and the Emergence of Attributes Associations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.10763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.10763v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In response to an object presentation, supervised learning schemes generally respond with a parsimonious label. Upon a similar presentation we humans respond again with a label, but are flooded, in addition, by a myriad of associations. A significant portion of these consist of the presented object attributes. Contrastive learning is a semi-supervised learning scheme based on the application of identity preserving transformations on the object input representations. It is conjectured in this work that these same applied transformations preserve, in addition to the identity of the presented object, also the identity of its semantically meaningful attributes. The corollary of this is that the output representations of such a contrastive learning scheme contain valuable information not only for the classification of the presented object, but also for the presence or absence decision of any attribute of interest. Simulation results which demonstrate this idea and the feasibility of this conjecture are presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.10763v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel N. Nissani (Nissensohn)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embodied Neuromorphic Artificial Intelligence for Robotics: Perspectives, Challenges, and Research Development Stack</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03325v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Robotic technologies have been an indispensable part for improving human productivity since they have been helping humans in completing diverse, complex, and intensive tasks in a fast yet accurate and efficient way. Therefore, robotic technologies have been deployed in a wide range of applications, ranging from personal to industrial use-cases. However, current robotic technologies and their computing paradigm still lack embodied intelligence to efficiently interact with operational environments, respond with correct/expected actions, and adapt to changes in the environments. Toward this, recent advances in neuromorphic computing with Spiking Neural Networks (SNN) have demonstrated the potential to enable the embodied intelligence for robotics through bio-plausible computing paradigm that mimics how the biological brain works, known as "neuromorphic artificial intelligence (AI)". However, the field of neuromorphic AI-based robotics is still at an early stage, therefore its development and deployment for solving real-world problems expose new challenges in different design aspects, such as accuracy, adaptability, efficiency, reliability, and security. To address these challenges, this paper will discuss how we can enable embodied neuromorphic AI for robotic systems through our perspectives: (P1) Embodied intelligence based on effective learning rule, training mechanism, and adaptability; (P2) Cross-layer optimizations for energy-efficient neuromorphic computing; (P3) Representative and fair benchmarks; (P4) Low-cost reliability and safety enhancements; (P5) Security and privacy for neuromorphic computing; and (P6) A synergistic development for energy-efficient and robust neuromorphic-based robotics. Furthermore, this paper identifies research challenges and opportunities, as well as elaborates our vision for future research development toward embodied neuromorphic AI for robotics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03325v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rachmad Vidya Wicaksana Putra, Alberto Marchisio, Fakhreddine Zayer, Jorge Dias, Muhammad Shafique</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Walk model that continuously generates Brownian walks to L\'evy walks depending on destination attractiveness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.07541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.07541v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The L\'evy walk, a type of random walk characterized by linear step lengths that follow a power-law distribution, is observed in the migratory behaviors of various organisms, ranging from bacteria to humans. Notably, L\'evy walks with power exponents close to two, also known as Cauchy walks, are frequently observed, though their underlying causes remain elusive. This study proposes a walk model in which agents move toward a destination in multi-dimensional space and their movement strategy is parameterized by the extent to which they pursue the shortest path to the destination. This parameter is taken to represent the attractiveness of the destination to the agents. Our findings reveal that if the destination is very attractive, agents intensively search the area around it using Brownian walks, whereas if the destination is unattractive, they explore a distant region away from the point using L\'evy walks with power exponents less than two. In the case where agents are unable to determine whether the destination is attractive or unattractive, Cauchy walks emerge. The Cauchy walker searches the region with a probability inversely proportional to the distance from the destination. This suggests that it preferentially searches the area close to the destination, while concurrently having the potential to extend the search area much further. Our model, which can change the search method and search area depending on the attractiveness of the destination, has the potential to be utilized for exploring the parameter space of optimization problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.07541v4</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuji Shinohara, Daiki Morita, Hayato Hirai, Ryosuke Kuribayashi, Nobuhito Manome, Toru Moriyama, Hiroshi Okamoto, Yoshihiro Nakajima, Yukio-Pegio Gunji, Ung-il Chung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Element-wise Multiplication Based Deeper Physics-Informed Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04170v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: As a promising framework for resolving partial differential equations (PDEs), Physics-Informed Neural Networks (PINNs) have received widespread attention from industrial and scientific fields. However, lack of expressive ability and initialization pathology issues are found to prevent the application of PINNs in complex PDEs. In this work, we propose Deeper Physics-Informed Neural Network (Deeper-PINN) to resolve these issues. The element-wise multiplication operation is adopted to transform features into high-dimensional, non-linear spaces. Benefiting from element-wise multiplication operation, Deeper-PINNs can alleviate the initialization pathologies of PINNs and enhance the expressive capability of PINNs. The proposed structure is verified on various benchmarks. The results show that Deeper-PINNs can effectively resolve the initialization pathology and exhibit strong expressive ability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04170v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Feilong Jiang, Xiaonan Hou, Min Xia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NITRO-D: Native Integer-only Training of Deep Convolutional Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11698v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantization has become increasingly pivotal in addressing the steadily increasing computational and memory requirements of Deep Neural Networks (DNNs). By reducing the number of bits used to represent weights and activations (typically from 32-bit floating-point to 16-bit or 8-bit integers), quantization reduces the memory footprint, energy consumption, and execution time of DNN models. However, traditional quantization methods typically focus on the inference of DNNs, while the training process still relies on floating-point operations. To date, only one work in the literature has addressed integer-only training for Multi-Layer Perceptron (MLP) architectures. This work introduces NITRO-D, a new framework for training arbitrarily deep integer-only Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs) that operate entirely in the integer-only domain for both training and inference. NITRO-D is the first framework in the literature enabling the training of integer-only CNNs without the need to introduce a quantization scheme. Specifically, NITRO-D introduces a novel architecture integrating multiple integer local-loss blocks, which include the proposed NITRO Scaling Layer and the NITRO-ReLU activation function. Additionally, it introduces a novel integer-only learning algorithm derived from Local Error Signals (LES), utilizing IntegerSGD, an optimizer specifically designed to operate in an integer-only context. NITRO-D is implemented in an open-source Python library. Extensive experimental evaluations demonstrate its effectiveness across several state-of-the-art image recognition datasets. Results show significant performance improvements from 2.47% to 5.96% for integer-only MLP architectures over the state-of-the-art solution, and the capability of training integer-only CNN architectures with minimal accuracy degradation from -0.15% to -4.22% compared to floating-point LES.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11698v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Pirillo, Luca Colombo, Manuel Roveri</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
