<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NE</link>
    <description>cs.NE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 02:49:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution imposes an inductive bias that alters and accelerates learning dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10651</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10651v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The learning dynamics of biological brains and artificial neural networks are of interest to both neuroscience and machine learning. A key difference between them is that neural networks are often trained from a randomly initialized state whereas each brain is the product of generations of evolutionary optimization, yielding innate structures that enable few-shot learning and inbuilt reflexes. Artificial neural networks, by contrast, require non-ethological quantities of training data to attain comparable performance. To investigate the effect of evolutionary optimization on the learning dynamics of neural networks, we combined algorithms simulating natural selection and online learning to produce a method for evolutionarily conditioning artificial neural networks, and applied it to both reinforcement and supervised learning contexts. We found the evolutionary conditioning algorithm, by itself, performs comparably to an unoptimized baseline. However, evolutionarily conditioned networks show signs of unique and latent learning dynamics, and can be rapidly fine-tuned to optimal performance. These results suggest evolution constitutes an inductive bias that tunes neural systems to enable rapid learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10651v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Midler, Alejandro Pan Vazquez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolutionary training-free guidance in diffusion model for 3D multi-objective molecular generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11037</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11037v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Discovering novel 3D molecular structures that simultaneously satisfy multiple property targets remains a central challenge in materials and drug design. Although recent diffusion-based models can generate 3D conformations, they require expensive retraining for each new property or property-combination and lack flexibility in enforcing structural constraints. We introduce EGD (Evolutionary Guidance in Diffusion), a training-free framework that embeds evolutionary operators directly into the diffusion sampling process. By performing crossover on noise-perturbed samples and then denoising them with a pretrained Unconditional diffusion model, EGD seamlessly blends structural fragments and steers generation toward user-specified objectives without any additional model updates. On both single- and multi-target 3D conditional generation tasks-and on multi-objective optimization of quantum properties EGD outperforms state-of-the-art conditional diffusion methods in accuracy and runs up to five times faster per generation. In the single-objective optimization of protein ligands, EGD enables customized ligand generation. Moreover, EGD can embed arbitrary 3D fragments into the generated molecules while optimizing multiple conflicting properties in one unified process. This combination of efficiency, flexibility, and controllable structure makes EGD a powerful tool for rapid, guided exploration of chemical space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11037v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruiqing Sun, Dawei Feng, Sen Yang, Yijie Wang, Huaimin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>STEP: A Unified Spiking Transformer Evaluation Platform for Fair and Reproducible Benchmarking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11151v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spiking Transformers have recently emerged as promising architectures for combining the efficiency of spiking neural networks with the representational power of self-attention. However, the lack of standardized implementations, evaluation pipelines, and consistent design choices has hindered fair comparison and principled analysis. In this paper, we introduce \textbf{STEP}, a unified benchmark framework for Spiking Transformers that supports a wide range of tasks, including classification, segmentation, and detection across static, event-based, and sequential datasets. STEP provides modular support for diverse components such as spiking neurons, input encodings, surrogate gradients, and multiple backends (e.g., SpikingJelly, BrainCog). Using STEP, we reproduce and evaluate several representative models, and conduct systematic ablation studies on attention design, neuron types, encoding schemes, and temporal modeling capabilities. We also propose a unified analytical model for energy estimation, accounting for spike sparsity, bitwidth, and memory access, and show that quantized ANNs may offer comparable or better energy efficiency. Our results suggest that current Spiking Transformers rely heavily on convolutional frontends and lack strong temporal modeling, underscoring the need for spike-native architectural innovations. The full code is available at: https://github.com/Fancyssc/STEP</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11151v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sicheng Shen, Dongcheng Zhao, Linghao Feng, Zeyang Yue, Jindong Li, Tenglong Li, Guobin Shen, Yi Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lightweight LIF-only SNN accelerator using differential time encoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11252v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spiking Neural Networks (SNNs) offer a promising solution to the problem of increasing computational and energy requirements for modern Machine Learning (ML) applications. Due to their unique data representation choice of using spikes and spike trains, they mostly rely on additions and thresholding operations to achieve results approaching state-of-the-art (SOTA) Artificial Neural Networks (ANNs). This advantage is hindered by the fact that their temporal characteristic does not map well to already existing accelerator hardware like GPUs. Therefore, this work will introduce a hardware accelerator architecture capable of computing feedforward LIF-only SNNs, as well as an accompanying encoding method to efficiently encode already existing data into spike trains. Together, this leads to a design capable of &gt;99% accuracy on the MNIST dataset, with ~0.29ms inference times on a Xilinx Ultrascale+ FPGA, as well as ~0.17ms on a custom ASIC using the open-source predictive 7nm ASAP7 PDK. Furthermore, this work will showcase the advantages of the previously presented differential time encoding for spikes, as well as provide proof that merging spikes from different synapses given in differential time encoding can be done efficiently in hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11252v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Windhager, Lothar Ratschbacher, Bernhard A. Moser, Michael Lunglmayr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Step towards Interpretable Multimodal AI Models with MultiFIX</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11262v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Real-world problems are often dependent on multiple data modalities, making multimodal fusion essential for leveraging diverse information sources. In high-stakes domains, such as in healthcare, understanding how each modality contributes to the prediction is critical to ensure trustworthy and interpretable AI models. We present MultiFIX, an interpretability-driven multimodal data fusion pipeline that explicitly engineers distinct features from different modalities and combines them to make the final prediction. Initially, only deep learning components are used to train a model from data. The black-box (deep learning) components are subsequently either explained using post-hoc methods such as Grad-CAM for images or fully replaced by interpretable blocks, namely symbolic expressions for tabular data, resulting in an explainable model. We study the use of MultiFIX using several training strategies for feature extraction and predictive modeling. Besides highlighting strengths and weaknesses of MultiFIX, experiments on a variety of synthetic datasets with varying degrees of interaction between modalities demonstrate that MultiFIX can generate multimodal models that can be used to accurately explain both the extracted features and their integration without compromising predictive performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11262v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mafalda Malafaia, Thalea Schlender, Tanja Alderliesten, Peter A. N. Bosman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MID-L: Matrix-Interpolated Dropout Layer with Layer-wise Neuron Selection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11416</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11416v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Modern neural networks often activate all neurons for every input, leading to unnecessary computation and inefficiency. We introduce Matrix-Interpolated Dropout Layer (MID-L), a novel module that dynamically selects and activates only the most informative neurons by interpolating between two transformation paths via a learned, input-dependent gating vector. Unlike conventional dropout or static sparsity methods, MID-L employs a differentiable Top-k masking strategy, enabling per-input adaptive computation while maintaining end-to-end differentiability. MID-L is model-agnostic and integrates seamlessly into existing architectures. Extensive experiments on six benchmarks, including MNIST, CIFAR-10, CIFAR-100, SVHN, UCI Adult, and IMDB, show that MID-L achieves up to average 55\% reduction in active neurons, 1.7$\times$ FLOPs savings, and maintains or exceeds baseline accuracy. We further validate the informativeness and selectivity of the learned neurons via Sliced Mutual Information (SMI) and observe improved robustness under overfitting and noisy data conditions. Additionally, MID-L demonstrates favorable inference latency and memory usage profiles, making it suitable for both research exploration and deployment on compute-constrained systems. These results position MID-L as a general-purpose, plug-and-play dynamic computation layer, bridging the gap between dropout regularization and efficient inference.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11416v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pouya Shaeri, Ariane Middel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy efficiency analysis of Spiking Neural Networks for space applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11418v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: While the exponential growth of the space sector and new operative concepts ask for higher spacecraft autonomy, the development of AI-assisted space systems was so far hindered by the low availability of power and energy typical of space applications. In this context, Spiking Neural Networks (SNN) are highly attractive due to their theoretically superior energy efficiency due to their inherently sparse activity induced by neurons communicating by means of binary spikes. Nevertheless, the ability of SNN to reach such efficiency on real world tasks is still to be demonstrated in practice. To evaluate the feasibility of utilizing SNN onboard spacecraft, this work presents a numerical analysis and comparison of different SNN techniques applied to scene classification for the EuroSAT dataset. Such tasks are of primary importance for space applications and constitute a valuable test case given the abundance of competitive methods available to establish a benchmark. Particular emphasis is placed on models based on temporal coding, where crucial information is encoded in the timing of neuron spikes. These models promise even greater efficiency of resulting networks, as they maximize the sparsity properties inherent in SNN. A reliable metric capable of comparing different architectures in a hardware-agnostic way is developed to establish a clear theoretical dependence between architecture parameters and the energy consumption that can be expected onboard the spacecraft. The potential of this novel method and his flexibility to describe specific hardware platforms is demonstrated by its application to predicting the energy consumption of a BrainChip Akida AKD1000 neuromorphic processor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11418v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Lunghi, Stefano Silvestrini, Dominik Dold, Gabriele Meoni, Alexander Hadjiivanov, Dario Izzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ASRC-SNN: Adaptive Skip Recurrent Connection Spiking Neural Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11455</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11455v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In recent years, Recurrent Spiking Neural Networks (RSNNs) have shown promising potential in long-term temporal modeling. Many studies focus on improving neuron models and also integrate recurrent structures, leveraging their synergistic effects to improve the long-term temporal modeling capabilities of Spiking Neural Networks (SNNs). However, these studies often place an excessive emphasis on the role of neurons, overlooking the importance of analyzing neurons and recurrent structures as an integrated framework. In this work, we consider neurons and recurrent structures as an integrated system and conduct a systematic analysis of gradient propagation along the temporal dimension, revealing a challenging gradient vanishing problem. To address this issue, we propose the Skip Recurrent Connection (SRC) as a replacement for the vanilla recurrent structure, effectively mitigating the gradient vanishing problem and enhancing long-term temporal modeling performance. Additionally, we propose the Adaptive Skip Recurrent Connection (ASRC), a method that can learn the skip span of skip recurrent connection in each layer of the network. Experiments show that replacing the vanilla recurrent structure in RSNN with SRC significantly improves the model's performance on temporal benchmark datasets. Moreover, ASRC-SNN outperforms SRC-SNN in terms of temporal modeling capabilities and robustness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11455v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shang Xu, Jiayu Zhang, Ziming Wang, Runhao Jiang, Rui Yan, Huajin Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embodied AI in Machine Learning -- is it Really Embodied?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10705v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Embodied Artificial Intelligence (Embodied AI) is gaining momentum in the machine learning communities with the goal of leveraging current progress in AI (deep learning, transformers, large language and visual-language models) to empower robots. In this chapter we put this work in the context of "Good Old-Fashioned Artificial Intelligence" (GOFAI) (Haugeland, 1989) and the behavior-based or embodied alternatives (R. A. Brooks 1991; Pfeifer and Scheier 2001). We claim that the AI-powered robots are only weakly embodied and inherit some of the problems of GOFAI. Moreover, we review and critically discuss the possibility of cross-embodiment learning (Padalkar et al. 2024). We identify fundamental roadblocks and propose directions on how to make progress.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10705v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matej Hoffmann, Shubhan Parag Patni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Symbolic Optimization: Reinforcement Learning for Symbolic Mathematics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10762v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Deep Symbolic Optimization (DSO) is a novel computational framework that enables symbolic optimization for scientific discovery, particularly in applications involving the search for intricate symbolic structures. One notable example is equation discovery, which aims to automatically derive mathematical models expressed in symbolic form. In DSO, the discovery process is formulated as a sequential decision-making task. A generative neural network learns a probabilistic model over a vast space of candidate symbolic expressions, while reinforcement learning strategies guide the search toward the most promising regions. This approach integrates gradient-based optimization with evolutionary and local search techniques, and it incorporates in-situ constraints, domain-specific priors, and advanced policy optimization methods. The result is a robust framework capable of efficiently exploring extensive search spaces to identify interpretable and physically meaningful models. Extensive evaluations on benchmark problems have demonstrated that DSO achieves state-of-the-art performance in both accuracy and interpretability. In this chapter, we provide a comprehensive overview of the DSO framework and illustrate its transformative potential for automating symbolic optimization in scientific discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10762v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Conor F. Hayes, Felipe Leno Da Silva, Jiachen Yang, T. Nathan Mundhenk, Chak Shing Lee, Jacob F. Pettit, Claudio Santiago, Sookyung Kim, Joanne T. Kim, Ignacio Aravena Solis, Ruben Glatt, Andre R. Goncalves, Alexander Ladd, Ahmet Can Solak, Thomas Desautels, Daniel Faissol, Brenden K. Petersen, Mikel Landajuela</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pipelining Kruskal's: A Neuromorphic Approach for Minimum Spanning Tree</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10771v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neuromorphic computing, characterized by its event-driven computation and massive parallelism, is particularly effective for handling data-intensive tasks in low-power environments, such as computing the minimum spanning tree (MST) for large-scale graphs. The introduction of dynamic synaptic modifications provides new design opportunities for neuromorphic algorithms. Building on this foundation, we propose an SNN-based union-sort routine and a pipelined version of Kruskal's algorithm for MST computation. The event-driven nature of our method allows for the concurrent execution of two completely decoupled stages: neuromorphic sorting and union-find. Our approach demonstrates superior performance compared to state-of-the-art Prim 's-based methods on large-scale graphs from the DIMACS10 dataset, achieving speedups by 269.67x to 1283.80x, with a median speedup of 540.76x. We further evaluate the pipelined implementation against two serial variants of Kruskal's algorithm, which rely on neuromorphic sorting and neuromorphic radix sort, showing significant performance advantages in most scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10771v2</guid>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yee Hin Chong, Peng Qu, Yuchen Li, Youhui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Superlinearly Convergent Evolution Strategy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10987</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10987v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a hybrid algorithm between an evolution strategy and a quasi Newton method. The design is based on the Hessian Estimation Evolution Strategy, which iteratively estimates the inverse square root of the Hessian matrix of the problem. This is akin to a quasi-Newton method and corresponding derivative-free trust-region algorithms like NEWUOA. The proposed method therefore replaces the global recombination step commonly found in non-elitist evolution strategies with a quasi-Newton step. Numerical results show superlinear convergence, resulting in improved performance in particular on smooth convex problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10987v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Glasmachers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Assessing the Performance of Analog Training for Transfer Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11067</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11067v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Analog in-memory computing is a next-generation computing paradigm that promises fast, parallel, and energy-efficient deep learning training and transfer learning (TL). However, achieving this promise has remained elusive due to a lack of suitable training algorithms. Analog memory devices exhibit asymmetric and non-linear switching behavior in addition to device-to-device variation, meaning that most, if not all, of the current off-the-shelf training algorithms cannot achieve good training outcomes. Also, recently introduced algorithms have enjoyed limited attention, as they require bi-directionally switching devices of unrealistically high symmetry and precision and are highly sensitive. A new algorithm chopped TTv2 (c-TTv2), has been introduced, which leverages the chopped technique to address many of the challenges mentioned above. In this paper, we assess the performance of the c-TTv2 algorithm for analog TL using a Swin-ViT model on a subset of the CIFAR100 dataset. We also investigate the robustness of our algorithm to changes in some device specifications, including weight transfer noise, symmetry point skew, and symmetry point variability</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11067v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Omobayode Fagbohungbe, Corey Lammie, Malte J. Rasch, Takashi Ando, Tayfun Gokmen, Vijay Narayanan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalability of Reinforcement Learning Methods for Dispatching in Semiconductor Frontend Fabs: A Comparison of Open-Source Models with Real Industry Datasets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11135v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Benchmark datasets are crucial for evaluating approaches to scheduling or dispatching in the semiconductor industry during the development and deployment phases. However, commonly used benchmark datasets like the Minifab or SMT2020 lack the complex details and constraints found in real-world scenarios. To mitigate this shortcoming, we compare open-source simulation models with a real industry dataset to evaluate how optimization methods scale with different levels of complexity. Specifically, we focus on Reinforcement Learning methods, performing optimization based on policy-gradient and Evolution Strategies. Our research provides insights into the effectiveness of these optimization methods and their applicability to realistic semiconductor frontend fab simulations. We show that our proposed Evolution Strategies-based method scales much better than a comparable policy-gradient-based approach. Moreover, we identify the selection and combination of relevant bottleneck tools to control by the agent as crucial for an efficient optimization. For the generalization across different loading scenarios and stochastic tool failure patterns, we achieve advantages when utilizing a diverse training dataset. While the overall approach is computationally expensive, it manages to scale well with the number of CPU cores used for training. For the real industry dataset, we achieve an improvement of up to 4% regarding tardiness and up to 1% regarding throughput. For the less complex open-source models Minifab and SMT2020, we observe double-digit percentage improvement in tardiness and single digit percentage improvement in throughput by use of Evolution Strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11135v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick St\"ockermann, Henning S\"udfeld, Alessandro Immordino, Thomas Altenm\"uller, Marc Wegmann, Martin Gebser, Konstantin Schekotihin, Georg Seidel, Chew Wye Chan, Fei Fei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mergenetic: a Simple Evolutionary Model Merging Library</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11427v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Model merging allows combining the capabilities of existing models into a new one - post hoc, without additional training. This has made it increasingly popular thanks to its low cost and the availability of libraries that support merging on consumer GPUs. Recent work shows that pairing merging with evolutionary algorithms can boost performance, but no framework currently supports flexible experimentation with such strategies in language models. We introduce Mergenetic, an open-source library for evolutionary model merging. Mergenetic enables easy composition of merging methods and evolutionary algorithms while incorporating lightweight fitness estimators to reduce evaluation costs. We describe its design and demonstrate that Mergenetic produces competitive results across tasks and languages using modest hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11427v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrian Robert Minut, Tommaso Mencattini, Andrea Santilli, Donato Crisostomi, Emanuele Rodol\`a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding trade-offs in classifier bias with quality-diversity optimization: an application to talent management</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16965v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Fairness,the impartial treatment towards individuals or groups regardless of their inherent or acquired characteristics [20], is a critical challenge for the successful implementation of Artificial Intelligence (AI) in multiple fields like finances, human capital, and housing. A major struggle for the development of fair AI models lies in the bias implicit in the data available to train such models. Filtering or sampling the dataset before training can help ameliorate model bias but can also reduce model performance and the bias impact can be opaque. In this paper, we propose a method for visualizing the biases inherent in a dataset and understanding the potential trade-offs between fairness and accuracy. Our method builds on quality-diversity optimization, in particular Covariance Matrix Adaptation Multi-dimensional Archive of Phenotypic Elites (MAP-Elites). Our method provides a visual representation of bias in models, allows users to identify models within a minimal threshold of fairness, and determines the trade-off between fairness and accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16965v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-031-90062-4_15</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Catalina M Jaramillo, Paul Squires, Julian Togelius</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TS-SNN: Temporal Shift Module for Spiking Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04165</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.04165v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Spiking Neural Networks (SNNs) are increasingly recognized for their biological plausibility and energy efficiency, positioning them as strong alternatives to Artificial Neural Networks (ANNs) in neuromorphic computing applications. SNNs inherently process temporal information by leveraging the precise timing of spikes, but balancing temporal feature utilization with low energy consumption remains a challenge. In this work, we introduce Temporal Shift module for Spiking Neural Networks (TS-SNN), which incorporates a novel Temporal Shift (TS) module to integrate past, present, and future spike features within a single timestep via a simple yet effective shift operation. A residual combination method prevents information loss by integrating shifted and original features. The TS module is lightweight, requiring only one additional learnable parameter, and can be seamlessly integrated into existing architectures with minimal additional computational cost. TS-SNN achieves state-of-the-art performance on benchmarks like CIFAR-10 (96.72\%), CIFAR-100 (80.28\%), and ImageNet (70.61\%) with fewer timesteps, while maintaining low energy consumption. This work marks a significant step forward in developing efficient and accurate SNN architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.04165v4</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kairong Yu, Tianqing Zhang, Qi Xu, Gang Pan, Hongwei Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Why Adam Outperforms SGD: Gradient Heterogeneity in Transformers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00213</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00213v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Transformers are challenging to optimize with SGD and typically require adaptive optimizers such as Adam. However, the reasons behind the superior performance of Adam over SGD remain unclear. In this study, we investigate the optimization of transformers by focusing on gradient heterogeneity, defined as the disparity in gradient norms among parameters. Our analysis shows that gradient heterogeneity hinders gradient-based optimization, including SGD, while sign-based optimization, a simplified variant of Adam, is less affected. We further examine gradient heterogeneity in transformers and show that it is influenced by the placement of layer normalization. Experimental results from fine-tuning transformers in both NLP and vision domains validate our theoretical analyses. This study provides insights into the optimization challenges of transformers and offers guidance for designing future optimization algorithms. Code is available at https://github.com/tom4649/gradient-heterogeneity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00213v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akiyoshi Tomihari, Issei Sato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion Recommender Models and the Illusion of Progress: A Concerning Study of Reproducibility and a Conceptual Mismatch</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09364v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Countless new machine learning models are published every year and are reported to significantly advance the state-of-the-art in \emph{top-n} recommendation. However, earlier reproducibility studies indicate that progress in this area may be quite limited. Specifically, various widespread methodological issues, e.g., comparisons with untuned baseline models, have led to an \emph{illusion of progress}. In this work, our goal is to examine whether these problems persist in today's research. To this end, we aim to reproduce the latest advancements reported from applying modern Denoising Diffusion Probabilistic Models to recommender systems, focusing on four models published at the top-ranked SIGIR conference in 2023 and 2024. Our findings are concerning, revealing persistent methodological problems. Alarmingly, through experiments, we find that the latest recommendation techniques based on diffusion models, despite their computational complexity and substantial carbon footprint, are consistently outperformed by simpler existing models. Furthermore, we identify key mismatches between the characteristics of diffusion models and those of the traditional \emph{top-n} recommendation task, raising doubts about their suitability for recommendation. We also note that, in the papers we analyze, the generative capabilities of these models are constrained to a minimum. Overall, our results and continued methodological issues call for greater scientific rigor and a disruptive change in the research and publication culture in this area.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09364v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Benigni, Maurizio Ferrari Dacrema, Dietmar Jannach</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
