<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NE</link>
    <description>cs.NE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 05:00:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluation and Efficiency Comparison of Evolutionary Algorithms for Service Placement Optimization in Fog Architectures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09958v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study compares three evolutionary algorithms for the problem of fog service placement: weighted sum genetic algorithm (WSGA), non-dominated sorting genetic algorithm II (NSGA-II), and multiobjective evolutionary algorithm based on decomposition (MOEA/D). A model for the problem domain (fog architecture and fog applications) and for the optimization (objective functions and solutions) is presented. Our main concerns are related to optimize the network latency, the service spread and the use of the resources. The algorithms are evaluated with a random Barabasi-Albert network topology with 100 devices and with two experiment sizes of 100 and 200 application services. The results showed that NSGA-II obtained the highest optimizations of the objectives and the highest diversity of the solution space. On the contrary, MOEA/D was better to reduce the execution times. The WSGA algorithm did not show any benefit with regard to the other two algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09958v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.future.2019.02.056</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Evaluation and efficiency comparison of evolutionary algorithms for service placement optimization in fog architectures, Future Generation Computer Systems, Volume 97, 2019, Pages 131-144, ISSN 0167-739X</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Guerrero, Isaac Lera, Carlos Juiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dendritic Localized Learning: Toward Biologically Plausible Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09976</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09976v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Backpropagation is the foundational algorithm for training neural networks and a key driver of deep learning's success. However, its biological plausibility has been challenged due to three primary limitations: weight symmetry, reliance on global error signals, and the dual-phase nature of training, as highlighted by the existing literature. Although various alternative learning approaches have been proposed to address these issues, most either fail to satisfy all three criteria simultaneously or yield suboptimal results. Inspired by the dynamics and plasticity of pyramidal neurons, we propose Dendritic Localized Learning (DLL), a novel learning algorithm designed to overcome these challenges. Extensive empirical experiments demonstrate that DLL satisfies all three criteria of biological plausibility while achieving state-of-the-art performance among algorithms that meet these requirements. Furthermore, DLL exhibits strong generalization across a range of architectures, including MLPs, CNNs, and RNNs. These results, benchmarked against existing biologically plausible learning algorithms, offer valuable empirical insights for future research. We hope this study can inspire the development of new biologically plausible algorithms for training multilayer networks and advancing progress in both neuroscience and machine learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09976v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Changze Lv, Jingwen Xu, Yiyang Lu, Xiaohua Wang, Zhenghua Wang, Zhibo Xu, Di Yu, Xin Du, Xiaoqing Zheng, Xuanjing Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast energy-aware OLSR routing in VANETs by means of a parallel evolutionary algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09996v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work tackles the problem of reducing the power consumption of the OLSR routing protocol in vehicular networks. Nowadays, energy-aware and green communication protocols are important research topics, specially when deploying wireless mobile networks. This article introduces a fast automatic methodology to search for energy-efficient OLSR configurations by using a parallel evolutionary algorithm. The experimental analysis demonstrates that significant improvements over the standard configuration can be attained in terms of power consumption, with no noteworthy loss in the QoS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09996v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10586-012-0208-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Cluster computing, 16, 435-450 (2013)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jamal Toutouh, Sergio Nesmachnow, Enrique Alba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A swarm algorithm for collaborative traffic in vehicular networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10007</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10007v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Vehicular ad hoc networks (VANETs) allow vehicles to exchange warning messages with each other. These specific kinds of networks help reduce hazardous traffic situations and improve safety, which are two of the main objectives in developing Intelligent Transportation Systems (ITS). For this, the performance of VANETs should guarantee the delivery of messages in a required time. An obstacle to this is that the data traffic generated may cause network congestion. Data congestion control is used to enhance network capabilities, increasing the reliability of the VANET by decreasing packet losses and communication delays. In this study, we propose a swarm intelligence based distributed congestion control strategy to maintain the channel usage level under the threshold of network malfunction, while keeping the quality-of-service of the VANET high. An exhaustive experimentation shows that the proposed strategy improves the throughput of the network, the channel usage, and the stability of the communications in comparison with other competing congestion control strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10007v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.vehcom.2018.04.003</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Vehicular Communications, 12, 127-137 (2018)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jamal Toutouh, Enrique Alba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infrastructure Deployment in Vehicular Communication Networks Using a Parallel Multiobjective Evolutionary Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10016v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article describes the application of a multiobjective evolutionary algorithm for locating roadside infrastructure for vehicular communication networks over realistic urban areas. A multiobjective formulation of the problem is introduced, considering quality-of-service and cost objectives. The experimental analysis is performed over a real map of M\'alaga, using real traffic information and antennas, and scenarios that model different combinations of traffic patterns and applications (text/audio/video) in the communications. The proposed multiobjective evolutionary algorithm computes accurate trade-off solutions, significantly improving over state-of-the-art algorithms previously applied to the problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10016v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/int.21890</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IJIS, 32(8), 801-829 (2017)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Renzo Massobrio, Jamal Toutouh, Sergio Nesmachniw, Enrique Alba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random-Key Algorithms for Optimizing Integrated Operating Room Scheduling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10243v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Efficient surgery room scheduling is essential for hospital efficiency, patient satisfaction, and resource utilization. This study addresses this challenge by introducing a novel concept of Random-Key Optimizer (RKO), rigorously tested on literature and new, real-world inspired instances. Our combinatorial optimization problem incorporates multi-room scheduling, equipment scheduling, and complex availability constraints for rooms, patients, and surgeons, facilitating rescheduling and enhancing operational flexibility. The RKO approach represents solutions as points in a continuous space, which are then mapped in the problem solution space via a deterministic function known as a decoder. The core idea is to operate metaheuristics and heuristics in the random-key space, unaware of the original solution space. We design the Biased Random-Key Genetic Algorithm with $Q$-Learning, Simulated Annealing, and Iterated Local Search for use within an RKO framework, employing a single decoder function. The proposed metaheuristics are complemented by lower-bound formulations, providing optimal gaps for evaluating the effectiveness of the heuristic results. Our results demonstrate significant lower and upper bounds improvements for the literature instances, notably proving one optimal result. Furthermore, the best-proposed metaheuristic efficiently generates schedules for the newly introduced instances, even in highly constrained scenarios. This research offers valuable insights and practical solutions for improving surgery scheduling processes, offering tangible benefits to hospitals by optimising resource allocation, reducing patient wait times, and enhancing overall operational efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10243v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruno Salezze Vieira, Eduardo Machado Silva, Antonio Augusto Chaves</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Restart Strategies for Parameter-dependent Optimization Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10173</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10173v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper examines restart strategies for algorithms whose successful termination depends on an unknown parameter $\lambda$. After each restart, $\lambda$ is increased, until the algorithm terminates successfully. It is assumed that there is a unique, unknown, optimal value for $\lambda$. For the algorithm to run successfully, this value must be reached or surpassed. The key question is whether there exists an optimal strategy for selecting $\lambda$ after each restart taking into account that the computational costs (runtime) increases with $\lambda$. In this work, potential restart strategies are classified into parameter-dependent strategy types. A loss function is introduced to quantify the wasted computational cost relative to the optimal strategy. A crucial requirement for any efficient restart strategy is that its loss, relative to the optimal $\lambda$, remains bounded. To this end, upper and lower bounds of the loss are derived. Using these bounds it will be shown that not all strategy types are bounded. However, for a particular strategy type, where $\lambda$ is increased multiplicatively by a constant factor $\lambda$, the relative loss function is bounded. Furthermore, it will be demonstrated that within this strategy type, there exists an optimal value for $\lambda$ that minimizes the maximum relative loss. In the asymptotic limit, this optimal choice of $\lambda$ does not depend on the unknown optimal $\lambda$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10173v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lisa Sch\"onenberger, Hans-Georg Beyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Octopus Inspired Optimization Algorithm: Multi-Level Structures and Parallel Computing Strategies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07968v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel bionic intelligent optimisation algorithm, Octopus Inspired Optimization (OIO) algorithm, which is inspired by the neural structure of octopus, especially its hierarchical and decentralised interaction properties. By simulating the sensory, decision-making, and executive abilities of octopuses, the OIO algorithm adopts a multi-level hierarchical strategy, including tentacles, suckers, individuals and groups, to achieve an effective combination of global and local search. This hierarchical design not only enhances the flexibility and efficiency of the algorithm, but also significantly improves its search efficiency and adaptability. In performance evaluations, including comparisons with existing mainstream intelligent optimisation algorithms, OIO shows faster convergence and higher accuracy, especially when dealing with multimodal functions and high-dimensional optimisation problems. This advantage is even more pronounced as the required minimum accuracy is higher, with the OIO algorithm showing an average speedup of 2.27 times that of conventional particle swarm optimisation (PSO) and 9.63 times that of differential evolution (DE) on multimodal functions. In particular, when dealing with high-dimensional optimisation problems, OIO achieves an average speed of 10.39 times that of DE, demonstrating its superior computational efficiency. In addition, the OIO algorithm also shows a reduction of about 5\% in CPU usage efficiency compared to PSO, which is reflected in the efficiency of CPU resource usage also shows its efficiency. These features make the OIO algorithm show great potential in complex optimisation problems, and it is especially suitable for application scenarios that require fast, efficient and robust optimisation methods, such as robot path planning, supply chain management optimisation, and energy system management.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07968v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xu Wang, Longji Xu, Yiquan Wang, Yuhua Dong, Xiang Li, Jia Deng, Rui He</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
