<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NE</link>
    <description>cs.NE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 04:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Spiking Neural Networks with Random Network Architecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13622v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The spiking neural network, known as the third generation neural network, is an important network paradigm. Due to its mode of information propagation that follows biological rationality, the spiking neural network has strong energy efficiency and has advantages in complex high-energy application scenarios. However, unlike the artificial neural network (ANN) which has a mature and unified framework, the SNN models and training methods have not yet been widely unified due to the discontinuous and non-differentiable property of the firing mechanism. Although several algorithms for training spiking neural networks have been proposed in the subsequent development process, some fundamental issues remain unsolved. Inspired by random network design, this work proposes a new architecture for spiking neural networks, RanSNN, where only part of the network weights need training and all the classic training methods can be adopted. Compared with traditional training methods for spiking neural networks, it greatly improves the training efficiency while ensuring the training performance, and also has good versatility and stability as validated by benchmark tests.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13622v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zihan Dai, Huanfei Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking MOEAs for solving continuous multi-objective RL problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13726v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multi-objective reinforcement learning (MORL) addresses the challenge of simultaneously optimizing multiple, often conflicting, rewards, moving beyond the single-reward focus of conventional reinforcement learning (RL). This approach is essential for applications where agents must balance trade-offs between diverse goals, such as speed, energy efficiency, or stability, as a series of sequential decisions. This paper investigates the applicability and limitations of multi-objective evolutionary algorithms (MOEAs) in solving complex MORL problems. We assess whether these algorithms can effectively address the unique challenges posed by MORL and how MORL instances can serve as benchmarks to evaluate and improve MOEA performance. In particular, we propose a framework to characterize the features influencing MORL instance complexity, select representative MORL problems from the literature, and benchmark a suite of MOEAs alongside single-objective EAs using scalarized MORL formulations. Additionally, we evaluate the utility of existing multi-objective quality indicators in MORL scenarios, such as hypervolume conducting a comparison of the algorithms supported by statistical analysis. Our findings provide insights into the interplay between MORL problem characteristics and algorithmic effectiveness, highlighting opportunities for advancing both MORL research and the design of evolutionary algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13726v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Hern\'andez, Roberto Santana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RAG/LLM Augmented Switching Driven Polymorphic Metaheuristic Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13808v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Metaheuristic algorithms are widely used for solving complex optimization problems, yet their effectiveness is often constrained by fixed structures and the need for extensive tuning. The Polymorphic Metaheuristic Framework (PMF) addresses this limitation by introducing a self-adaptive metaheuristic switching mechanism driven by real-time performance feedback and dynamic algorithmic selection. PMF leverages the Polymorphic Metaheuristic Agent (PMA) and the Polymorphic Metaheuristic Selection Agent (PMSA) to dynamically select and transition between metaheuristic algorithms based on key performance indicators, ensuring continuous adaptation. This approach enhances convergence speed, adaptability, and solution quality, outperforming traditional metaheuristics in high-dimensional, dynamic, and multimodal environments. Experimental results on benchmark functions demonstrate that PMF significantly improves optimization efficiency by mitigating stagnation and balancing exploration-exploitation strategies across various problem landscapes. By integrating AI-driven decision-making and self-correcting mechanisms, PMF paves the way for scalable, intelligent, and autonomous optimization frameworks, with promising applications in engineering, logistics, and complex decision-making systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13808v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Faramarz Safi Esfahani, Ghassan Beydoun, Morteza Saberi, Brad McCusker, Biswajeet Pradhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weak Pareto Boundary: The Achilles' Heel of Evolutionary Multi-Objective Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13854</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13854v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The weak Pareto boundary ($WPB$) refers to a boundary in the objective space of a multi-objective optimization problem, characterized by weak Pareto optimality rather than Pareto optimality. The $WPB$ brings severe challenges to multi-objective evolutionary algorithms (MOEAs), as it may mislead the algorithms into finding dominance-resistant solutions (DRSs), i.e., solutions that excel on some objectives but severely underperform on the others, thereby missing Pareto-optimal solutions. Although the severe impact of the $WPB$ on MOEAs has been recognized, a systematic and detailed analysis remains lacking. To fill this gap, this paper studies the attributes of the $WPB$. In particular, the category of a $WPB$, as an attribute derived from its weakly Pareto-optimal property, is theoretically analyzed. The analysis reveals that the dominance resistance degrees of DRSs induced by different categories of $WPB$s exhibit distinct asymptotic growth rates as the DRSs in the objective space approach the $WPB$s, where a steeper asymptotic growth rate indicates a greater hindrance to MOEAs. Beyond that, experimental studies are conducted on various new test problems to investigate the impact of $WPB$'s attributes. The experimental results demonstrate consistency with our theoretical findings. Experiments on other attributes show that the performance of an MOEA is highly sensitive to some attributes. Overall, no existing MOEAs can comprehensively address challenges brought by these attributes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13854v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruihao Zheng, Jingda Deng, Zhenkun Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Program Quantum Measurements for Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13525</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13525v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The rapid advancements in quantum computing (QC) and machine learning (ML) have sparked significant interest, driving extensive exploration of quantum machine learning (QML) algorithms to address a wide range of complex challenges. The development of high-performance QML models requires expert-level expertise, presenting a key challenge to the widespread adoption of QML. Critical obstacles include the design of effective data encoding strategies and parameterized quantum circuits, both of which are vital for the performance of QML models. Furthermore, the measurement process is often neglected-most existing QML models employ predefined measurement schemes that may not align with the specific requirements of the targeted problem. We propose an innovative framework that renders the observable of a quantum system-specifically, the Hermitian matrix-trainable. This approach employs an end-to-end differentiable learning framework, enabling simultaneous optimization of the neural network used to program the parameterized observables and the standard quantum circuit parameters. Notably, the quantum observable parameters are dynamically programmed by the neural network, allowing the observables to adapt in real time based on the input data stream. Through numerical simulations, we demonstrate that the proposed method effectively programs observables dynamically within variational quantum circuits, achieving superior results compared to existing approaches. Notably, it delivers enhanced performance metrics, such as higher classification accuracy, thereby significantly improving the overall effectiveness of QML models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13525v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samual Yen-Chi Chen, Huan-Hsin Tseng, Hsin-Yi Lin, Shinjae Yoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Counter-Inferential Behavior in Natural and Artificial Cognitive Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13551v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study explores the emergence of counter-inferential behavior in natural and artificial cognitive systems, that is, patterns in which agents misattribute empirical success or suppress adaptation, leading to epistemic rigidity or maladaptive stability. We analyze archetypal scenarios in which such behavior arises: reinforcement of stability through reward imbalance, meta-cognitive attribution of success to internal superiority, and protective reframing under perceived model fragility. Rather than arising from noise or flawed design, these behaviors emerge through structured interactions between internal information models, empirical feedback, and higher-order evaluation mechanisms. Drawing on evidence from artificial systems, biological cognition, human psychology, and social dynamics, we identify counter-inferential behavior as a general cognitive vulnerability that can manifest even in otherwise well-adapted systems. The findings highlight the importance of preserving minimal adaptive activation under stable conditions and suggest design principles for cognitive architectures that can resist rigidity under informational stress.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13551v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Serge Dolgikh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Randomised Optimism via Competitive Co-Evolution for Matrix Games with Bandit Feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13562v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Learning in games is a fundamental problem in machine learning and artificial intelligence, with numerous applications~\citep{silver2016mastering,schrittwieser2020mastering}. This work investigates two-player zero-sum matrix games with an unknown payoff matrix and bandit feedback, where each player observes their actions and the corresponding noisy payoff. Prior studies have proposed algorithms for this setting~\citep{o2021matrix,maiti2023query,cai2024uncoupled}, with \citet{o2021matrix} demonstrating the effectiveness of deterministic optimism (e.g., \ucb) in achieving sublinear regret. However, the potential of randomised optimism in matrix games remains theoretically unexplored.
  We propose Competitive Co-evolutionary Bandit Learning (\coebl), a novel algorithm that integrates evolutionary algorithms (EAs) into the bandit framework to implement randomised optimism through EA variation operators. We prove that \coebl achieves sublinear regret, matching the performance of deterministic optimism-based methods. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first theoretical regret analysis of an evolutionary bandit learning algorithm in matrix games.
  Empirical evaluations on diverse matrix game benchmarks demonstrate that \coebl not only achieves sublinear regret but also consistently outperforms classical bandit algorithms, including \exptr~\citep{auer2002nonstochastic}, the variant \exptrni~\citep{cai2024uncoupled}, and \ucb~\citep{o2021matrix}. These results highlight the potential of evolutionary bandit learning, particularly the efficacy of randomised optimism via evolutionary algorithms in game-theoretic settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13562v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shishen Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frozen Backpropagation: Relaxing Weight Symmetry in Temporally-Coded Deep Spiking Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13741</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13741v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Direct training of Spiking Neural Networks (SNNs) on neuromorphic hardware can greatly reduce energy costs compared to GPU-based training. However, implementing Backpropagation (BP) on such hardware is challenging because forward and backward passes are typically performed by separate networks with distinct weights. To compute correct gradients, forward and feedback weights must remain symmetric during training, necessitating weight transport between the two networks. This symmetry requirement imposes hardware overhead and increases energy costs. To address this issue, we introduce Frozen Backpropagation (fBP), a BP-based training algorithm relaxing weight symmetry in settings with separate networks. fBP updates forward weights by computing gradients with periodically frozen feedback weights, reducing weight transports during training and minimizing synchronization overhead. To further improve transport efficiency, we propose three partial weight transport schemes of varying computational complexity, where only a subset of weights is transported at a time. We evaluate our methods on image recognition tasks and compare them to existing approaches addressing the weight symmetry requirement. Our results show that fBP outperforms these methods and achieves accuracy comparable to BP. With partial weight transport, fBP can substantially lower transport costs by 1,000x with an accuracy drop of only 0.5pp on CIFAR-10 and 1.1pp on CIFAR-100, or by up to 10,000x at the expense of moderated accuracy loss. This work provides insights for guiding the design of neuromorphic hardware incorporating BP-based on-chip learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13741v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaspard Goupy, Pierre Tirilly, Ioan Marius Bilasco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do Language Models Use Their Depth Efficiently?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13898v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Modern LLMs are increasingly deep, and depth correlates with performance, albeit with diminishing returns. However, do these models use their depth efficiently? Do they compose more features to create higher-order computations that are impossible in shallow models, or do they merely spread the same kinds of computation out over more layers? To address these questions, we analyze the residual stream of the Llama 3.1 and Qwen 3 family of models. We find: First, comparing the output of the sublayers to the residual stream reveals that layers in the second half contribute much less than those in the first half, with a clear phase transition between the two halves. Second, skipping layers in the second half has a much smaller effect on future computations and output predictions. Third, for multihop tasks, we are unable to find evidence that models are using increased depth to compose subresults in examples involving many hops. Fourth, we seek to directly address whether deeper models are using their additional layers to perform new kinds of computation. To do this, we train linear maps from the residual stream of a shallow model to a deeper one. We find that layers with the same relative depth map best to each other, suggesting that the larger model simply spreads the same computations out over its many layers. All this evidence suggests that deeper models are not using their depth to learn new kinds of computation, but only using the greater depth to perform more fine-grained adjustments to the residual. This may help explain why increasing scale leads to diminishing returns for stacked Transformer architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13898v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R\'obert Csord\'as, Christopher D. Manning, Christopher Potts</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>X-KAN: Optimizing Local Kolmogorov-Arnold Networks via Evolutionary Rule-Based Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14273v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Function approximation is a critical task in various fields. However, existing neural network approaches struggle with locally complex or discontinuous functions due to their reliance on a single global model covering the entire problem space. We propose X-KAN, a novel method that optimizes multiple local Kolmogorov-Arnold Networks (KANs) through an evolutionary rule-based machine learning framework called XCSF. X-KAN combines KAN's high expressiveness with XCSF's adaptive partitioning capability by implementing local KAN models as rule consequents and defining local regions via rule antecedents. Our experimental results on artificial test functions and real-world datasets demonstrate that X-KAN significantly outperforms conventional methods, including XCSF, Multi-Layer Perceptron, and KAN, in terms of approximation accuracy. Notably, X-KAN effectively handles functions with locally complex or discontinuous structures that are challenging for conventional KAN, using a compact set of rules (average 7.2 $\pm$ 2.3 rules). These results validate the effectiveness of using KAN as a local model in XCSF, which evaluates the rule fitness based on both accuracy and generality. Our X-KAN implementation is available at https://github.com/YNU-NakataLab/X-KAN.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14273v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>34th International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI 2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hiroki Shiraishi, Hisao Ishibuchi, Masaya Nakata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Better Neural Network Expressivity: Subdividing the Simplex</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14338v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work studies the expressivity of ReLU neural networks with a focus on their depth. A sequence of previous works showed that $\lceil \log_2(n+1) \rceil$ hidden layers are sufficient to compute all continuous piecewise linear (CPWL) functions on $\mathbb{R}^n$. Hertrich, Basu, Di Summa, and Skutella (NeurIPS'21) conjectured that this result is optimal in the sense that there are CPWL functions on $\mathbb{R}^n$, like the maximum function, that require this depth. We disprove the conjecture and show that $\lceil\log_3(n-1)\rceil+1$ hidden layers are sufficient to compute all CPWL functions on $\mathbb{R}^n$.
  A key step in the proof is that ReLU neural networks with two hidden layers can exactly represent the maximum function of five inputs. More generally, we show that $\lceil\log_3(n-2)\rceil+1$ hidden layers are sufficient to compute the maximum of $n\geq 4$ numbers. Our constructions almost match the $\lceil\log_3(n)\rceil$ lower bound of Averkov, Hojny, and Merkert (ICLR'25) in the special case of ReLU networks with weights that are decimal fractions. The constructions have a geometric interpretation via polyhedral subdivisions of the simplex into ``easier'' polytopes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14338v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Egor Bakaev, Florestan Brunck, Christoph Hertrich, Jack Stade, Amir Yehudayoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A General Upper Bound for the Runtime of a Coevolutionary Algorithm on Impartial Combinatorial Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04177</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04177v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Due to their complex dynamics, combinatorial games are a key test case and application for algorithms that train game playing agents. Among those algorithms that train using self-play are coevolutionary algorithms (CoEAs). However, the successful application of CoEAs for game playing is difficult due to pathological behaviours such as cycling, an issue especially critical for games with intransitive payoff landscapes.
  Insight into how to design CoEAs to avoid such behaviours can be provided by runtime analysis. In this paper, we push the scope of runtime analysis for CoEAs to combinatorial games, proving a general upper bound for the number of simulated games needed for UMDA to discover (with high probability) an optimal strategy. This result applies to any impartial combinatorial game, and for many games the implied bound is polynomial or quasipolynomial as a function of the number of game positions. After proving the main result, we provide several applications to simple well-known games: Nim, Chomp, Silver Dollar, and Turning Turtles. As the first runtime analysis for CoEAs on combinatorial games, this result is a critical step towards a comprehensive theoretical framework for coevolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04177v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alistair Benford, Per Kristian Lehre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gated Recurrent Neural Networks with Weighted Time-Delay Feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.00228</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.00228v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a novel approach to modeling long-term dependencies in sequential data by introducing a gated recurrent unit (GRU) with a weighted time-delay feedback mechanism. Our proposed model, named $\tau$-GRU, is a discretized version of a continuous-time formulation of a recurrent unit, where the dynamics are governed by delay differential equations (DDEs). We prove the existence and uniqueness of solutions for the continuous-time model and show that the proposed feedback mechanism can significantly improve the modeling of long-term dependencies. Our empirical results indicate that $\tau$-GRU outperforms state-of-the-art recurrent units and gated recurrent architectures on a range of tasks, achieving faster convergence and better generalization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.00228v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. Benjamin Erichson, Soon Hoe Lim, Michael W. Mahoney</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Core Placement Optimization of Many-core Brain-Inspired Near-Storage Systems for Spiking Neural Network Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19430v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: With the increasing application scope of spiking neural networks (SNN), the complexity of SNN models has surged, leading to an exponential growth in demand for AI computility. As the new generation computing architecture of the neural networks, the efficiency and power consumption of distributed storage and parallel computing in the many-core near-memory computing system have attracted much attention. Among them, the mapping problem from logical cores to physical cores is one of the research hotspots. In order to improve the computing parallelism and system throughput of the many-core near-memory computing system, and to reduce power consumption, we propose a SNN training many-core deployment optimization method based on Off-policy Deterministic Actor-Critic. We utilize deep reinforcement learning as a nonlinear optimizer, treating the many-core topology as network graph features and using graph convolution to input the many-core structure into the policy network. We update the parameters of the policy network through near-end policy optimization to achieve deployment optimization of SNN models in the many-core near-memory computing architecture to reduce chip power consumption. To handle large-dimensional action spaces, we use continuous values matching the number of cores as the output of the policy network and then discretize them again to obtain new deployment schemes. Furthermore, to further balance inter-core computation latency and improve system throughput, we propose a model partitioning method with a balanced storage and computation strategy. Our method overcomes the problems such as uneven computation and storage loads between cores, and the formation of local communication hotspots, significantly reducing model training time, communication costs, and average flow load between cores in the many-core near-memory computing architecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19430v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xueke Zhu (Pengcheng Laboratory), Wenjie Lin (Pengcheng Laboratory), Yanyu Lin (Pengcheng Laboratory), Yunhao Ma (Pengcheng Laboratory), Wenxiang Cheng (Pengcheng Laboratory), Zhengyu Ma (Pengcheng Laboratory), Yonghong Tian (Pengcheng Laboratory, Peking University), Huihui Zhou (Pengcheng Laboratory)</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
