<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.NE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NE</link>
    <description>cs.NE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.NE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 01:39:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Random-key genetic algorithms: Principles and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02120</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02120v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A random-key genetic algorithm is an evolutionary metaheuristic for discrete and global optimization. Each solution is encoded as a vector of N random keys, where a random key is a real number randomly generated in the continuous interval [0, 1). A decoder maps each vector of random keys to a solution of the optimization problem being solved and computes its cost. The benefit of this approach is that all genetic operators and transformations can be maintained within the unitary hypercube, regardless of the problem being addressed. This enhances the productivity and maintainability of the core framework. The algorithm starts with a population of P vectors of random keys. At each iteration, the vectors are partitioned into two sets: a smaller set of high-valued elite solutions and the remaining non-elite solutions. All elite elements are copied, without change, to the next population. A small number of random-key vectors (the mutants) is added to the population of the next iteration. The remaining elements of the population of the next iteration are generated by combining, with the parametrized uniform crossover of Spears and DeJong (1991), pairs of solutions. This chapter reviews random-key genetic algorithms and describes an effective variant called biased random-key genetic algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02120v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mariana A. Londe, Luciana S. Pessoa, Carlos E. Andrade, Jos\'e F. Gon\c{c}alves, Mauricio G. C. Resende</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimal Neuron Circuits -- Part I: Resonators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02341</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02341v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spiking Neural Networks have earned increased recognition in recent years owing to their biological plausibility and event-driven computation. Spiking neurons are the fundamental building components of Spiking Neural Networks. Those neurons act as computational units that determine the decision to fire an action potential. This work presents a methodology to implement biologically plausible yet scalable spiking neurons in hardware. We show that it is more efficient to design neurons that mimic the $I_{Na,p}+I_{K}$ model rather than the more complicated Hodgkin-Huxley model. We demonstrate our methodology by presenting eleven novel minimal spiking neuron circuits in Parts I and II of the paper. We categorize the neuron circuits presented into two types: Resonators and Integrators. We discuss the methodology employed in designing neurons of the resonator type in Part I, while we discuss neurons of the integrator type in Part II. In part I, we postulate that Sodium channels exhibit type-N negative differential resistance. Consequently, we present three novel minimal neuron circuits that use type-N negative differential resistance circuits or devices as the Sodium channel. Nevertheless, the aim of the paper is not to present a set of minimal neuron circuits but rather the methodology utilized to construct those circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02341v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amr Nabil, T. Nandha Kumar, Haider Abbas F. Almurib</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GANORM: Lifespan Normative Modeling of EEG Network Topology based on Multinational Cross-Spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02566v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Charting the lifespan evolutionary trajectory of brain function serves as the normative standard for preventing mental disorders during brain development and aging. Although numerous MRI studies have mapped the structural connectome for young cohorts, the EEG-based functional connectome is unknown to characterize human lifespan, limiting its practical applications for the early detection of brain dysfunctions at the community level. This work aimed to undertake normative modeling from the perspective of EEG network topology. Frequency-dependent scalp EEG functional networks were constructed based on EEG cross-spectra aged 5-97 years from 9 countries and network characteristics were quantified. First, GAMLSS were applied to describe the normative curves of the network characteristics in different frequency bands. Subsequently, addressing the limitations of existing regression approaches for whole brain network analysis, this paper proposed an interpretable encoder-decoder framework, Generative Age-dependent brain Network nORmative Model (GANORM). Building upon this framework, we established an age-dependent normative trajectory of the complete brain network for the entire lifespan. Finally, we validated the effectiveness of the norm using EEG datasets from multiple sites. Subsequently, we evaluated the effectiveness of GANORM, and the tested performances of BPNN showed the R^2 was 0.796, the MAE was 0.081, and the RMSE was 0.013. Following established lifespan brain network norm, GANORM also exhibited good results upon verification using healthy and disease data from various sites. The deviation scores from the normative mean for the healthy control group were significantly smaller than those of the disease group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02566v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiang Hu, Xiaolong Huang, Yifan Hu, Xue Xiang, Xiaoliang Sheng, Debin Zhou, Pedro A. Valdes-Sosa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Exploration in Lenia with Intrinsic Multi-Objective Ranking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02990v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Artificial life aims to understand the fundamental principles of biological life by creating computational models that exhibit life-like properties. Although artificial life systems show promise for simulating biological evolution, achieving open-endedness remains a central challenge. This work investigates mechanisms to promote exploration and unbounded innovation within evolving populations of Lenia continuous cellular automata by evaluating individuals against each other with respect to distinctiveness, population sparsity, and homeostatic regulation. Multi-objective ranking of these intrinsic fitness objectives encourages the perpetual selection of novel and explorative individuals in sparse regions of the descriptor space without restricting the scope of emergent behaviors. We present experiments demonstrating the effectiveness of our multi-objective approach and emphasize that intrinsic evolution allows diverse expressions of artificial life to emerge. We argue that adaptive exploration improves evolutionary dynamics and serves as an important step toward achieving open-ended evolution in artificial systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02990v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niko Lorantos, Lee Spector</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient ANN-SNN Conversion with Error Compensation Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.01968v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Artificial neural networks (ANNs) have demonstrated outstanding performance in numerous tasks, but deployment in resource-constrained environments remains a challenge due to their high computational and memory requirements. Spiking neural networks (SNNs) operate through discrete spike events and offer superior energy efficiency, providing a bio-inspired alternative. However, current ANN-to-SNN conversion often results in significant accuracy loss and increased inference time due to conversion errors such as clipping, quantization, and uneven activation. This paper proposes a novel ANN-to-SNN conversion framework based on error compensation learning. We introduce a learnable threshold clipping function, dual-threshold neurons, and an optimized membrane potential initialization strategy to mitigate the conversion error. Together, these techniques address the clipping error through adaptive thresholds, dynamically reduce the quantization error through dual-threshold neurons, and minimize the non-uniformity error by effectively managing the membrane potential. Experimental results on CIFAR-10, CIFAR-100, ImageNet datasets show that our method achieves high-precision and ultra-low latency among existing conversion methods. Using only two time steps, our method significantly reduces the inference time while maintains competitive accuracy of 94.75% on CIFAR-10 dataset under ResNet-18 structure. This research promotes the practical application of SNNs on low-power hardware, making efficient real-time processing possible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.01968v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chang Liu, Jiangrong Shen, Xuming Ran, Mingkun Xu, Qi Xu, Yi Xu, Gang Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EvoGit: Decentralized Code Evolution via Git-Based Multi-Agent Collaboration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02049</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02049v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce EvoGit, a decentralized multi-agent framework for collaborative software development driven by autonomous code evolution. EvoGit deploys a population of independent coding agents, each proposing edits to a shared codebase without centralized coordination, explicit message passing, or shared memory. Instead, all coordination emerges through a Git-based phylogenetic graph that tracks the full version lineage and enables agents to asynchronously read from and write to the evolving code repository. This graph-based structure supports fine-grained branching, implicit concurrency, and scalable agent interaction while preserving a consistent historical record. Human involvement is minimal but strategic: users define high-level goals, periodically review the graph, and provide lightweight feedback to promote promising directions or prune unproductive ones. Experiments demonstrate EvoGit's ability to autonomously produce functional and modular software artifacts across two real-world tasks: (1) building a web application from scratch using modern frameworks, and (2) constructing a meta-level system that evolves its own language-model-guided solver for the bin-packing optimization problem. Our results underscore EvoGit's potential to establish a new paradigm for decentralized, automated, and continual software development. EvoGit is open-sourced at https://github.com/BillHuang2001/evogit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02049v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beichen Huang, Ran Cheng, Kay Chen Tan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brain-Like Processing Pathways Form in Models With Heterogeneous Experts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02813v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The brain is made up of a vast set of heterogeneous regions that dynamically organize into pathways as a function of task demands. Examples of such pathways can be seen in the interactions between cortical and subcortical networks during learning. This raises the question of how exactly brain regions organize into these dynamic groups. In this work, we use an extension of the Heterogeneous Mixture-of-Experts architecture, to show that heterogeneous regions do not form processing pathways by themselves, implying that the brain likely implements specific constraints which result in reliable formation of pathways. We identify three biologically relevant inductive biases that encourage pathway formation: a routing cost imposed on the use of more complex regions, a scaling factor that reduces this cost when task performance is low, and randomized expert dropout. When comparing our resulting Mixture-of-Pathways model with the brain, we observe that the artificial pathways match how the brain uses cortical and subcortical systems to learn and solve tasks of varying difficulty. In summary, we introduce a novel framework for investigating how the brain forms task-specific pathways through inductive biases which may make Mixture-of-Experts architectures in general more adaptive.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02813v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jack Cook, Danyal Akarca, Rui Ponte Costa, Jascha Achterberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Adaptive Re-evaluation Method for Evolution Strategy under Additive Noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.16757v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Covariance Matrix Adaptation Evolutionary Strategy (CMA-ES) is one of the most advanced algorithms in numerical black-box optimization. For noisy objective functions, several approaches were proposed to mitigate the noise, e.g., re-evaluations of the same solution or adapting the population size.
  In this paper, we devise a novel method to adaptively choose the optimal re-evaluation number for function values corrupted by additive Gaussian white noise. We derive a theoretical lower bound of the expected improvement achieved in one iteration of CMA-ES, given an estimation of the noise level and the Lipschitz constant of the function's gradient. Solving for the maximum of the lower bound, we obtain a simple expression of the optimal re-evaluation number.
  We experimentally compare our method to the state-of-the-art noise-handling methods for CMA-ES on a set of artificial test functions across various noise levels, optimization budgets, and dimensionality. Our method demonstrates significant advantages in terms of the probability of hitting near-optimal function values.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.16757v3</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Catalin-Viorel Dinu, Yash J. Patel, Xavier Bonet-Monroig, Hao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learnable Activation Functions in Physics-Informed Neural Networks for Solving Partial Differential Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.15111</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.15111v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate learnable activation functions in Physics-Informed Neural Networks (PINNs) for solving Partial Differential Equations (PDEs), comparing traditional Multilayer Perceptrons (MLPs) with fixed and trainable activations against Kolmogorov-Arnold Networks (KANs) that employ learnable basis functions. While PINNs effectively incorporate physical laws into the learning process, they suffer from convergence and spectral bias problems, which limit their applicability to problems with rapid oscillations or sharp transitions. In this work, we study and evaluate various activation and basis functions across diverse PDEs, including oscillatory, nonlinear wave, mixed-physics, and fluid dynamics problems. Using empirical Neural Tangent Kernel (NTK) analysis and Hessian eigenvalue decomposition, we assess convergence behavior, stability, and high-frequency approximation capacity. While KANs offer improved expressivity for capturing complex, high-frequency PDE solutions, they introduce new optimization challenges, especially in deeper networks. Our findings show that KANs face a curse of functional dimensionality, creating intractable optimization landscapes in deeper networks. Low spectral bias alone does not guarantee good performance; adaptive spectral bias approaches such as B-splines achieve optimal results by balancing global stability with local high-frequency resolution. Different PDE types require tailored strategies: smooth global activation functions excel for wave phenomena, while local adaptive activation functions suit problems with sharp transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.15111v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Afrah Farea, Mustafa Serdar Celebi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLM-Driven Instance-Specific Heuristic Generation and Selection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00490v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Combinatorial optimization problems are widely encountered in real-world applications. Designing high-quality heuristic algorithms that efficiently approximate optimal solutions within reasonable time is a critical research challenge. In recent years, many works have explored integrating Large Language Models (LLMs) with Evolutionary Algorithms to automate heuristic algorithm design through prompt engineering. However, these approaches generally adopt a problem-specific paradigm, applying a single algorithm across all problem instances, failing to account for the heterogeneity across instances. In this paper, we propose InstSpecHH, a novel framework that introduces the concept of instance-specific heuristic generation. InstSpecHH partitions the overall problem class into sub-classes based on instance features and performs differentiated, automated heuristic design for each problem subclass. By tailoring heuristics to the unique features of different sub-classes, InstSpecHH achieves better performance at the problem class level while avoiding redundant heuristic generation for similar instances, thus reducing computational overhead. This approach effectively balances the trade-off between the cost of automatic heuristic design and the quality of the obtained solutions. To evaluate the performance of InstSpecHH, we conduct experiments on 4,500 subclasses of the Online Bin Packing Problem (OBPP) and 365 subclasses of the Capacitated Vehicle Routing Problem (CVRP). Experimental results show that InstSpecHH demonstrates strong intra-subclass and inter-subclass generalization capabilities. Compared to previous problem-specific methods, InstSpecHH reduces the average optimality gap by more than 5.6\% for OBPP and 0.9\% for CVRP. These results highlight the potential of instance-aware automatic heuristic design to further enhance solution quality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00490v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shaofeng Zhang, Shengcai Liu, Ning Lu, Jiahao Wu, Ji Liu, Yew-Soon Ong, Ke Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-time respiratory motion forecasting with online learning of recurrent neural networks for accurate targeting in externally guided radiotherapy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01607v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In lung radiotherapy, infrared cameras can track reflective objects on the chest to estimate tumor motion due to breathing, but treatment system latencies hinder radiation beam precision. Real-time recurrent learning (RTRL) is a potential solution that can learn patterns within non-stationary respiratory data but has high complexity. This study assesses the capabilities of resource-efficient online RNN algorithms, namely unbiased online recurrent optimization (UORO), sparse-1 step approximation (SnAp-1), and decoupled neural interfaces (DNI) to forecast respiratory motion during radiotherapy treatment accurately. We use time series containing the 3D positions of external markers on the chest of healthy subjects. We propose efficient implementations for SnAp-1 and DNI that compress the influence and immediate Jacobian matrices and accurately update the linear coefficients used in credit assignment estimation, respectively. Data was originally sampled at 10Hz; we resampled it at 3.33Hz and 30Hz to analyze the effect of the sampling rate on performance. We use UORO, SnAp-1, and DNI to forecast each marker's 3D position with horizons h&lt;=2.1s (the time interval in advance for which the prediction is made) and compare them with RTRL, least mean squares, kernel support vector regression, and linear regression. RNNs trained online achieved similar or better accuracy than most previous works using larger training databases and deep learning, even though we used only the first minute of each sequence to predict motion within that exact sequence. SnAp-1 had the lowest normalized root mean square errors (nRMSEs) averaged over the horizon values considered, equal to 0.335 and 0.157, at 3.33Hz and 10.0Hz, respectively. Similarly, UORO had the lowest nRMSE at 30Hz, equal to 0.086. DNI's inference time (6.8ms per time step at 30Hz, Intel Core i7-13700 CPU) was the lowest among the RNN methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01607v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.cmpb.2025.108828</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Michel Pohl, Mitsuru Uesaka, Hiroyuki Takahashi, Kazuyuki Demachi, Ritu Bhusal Chhatkuli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structured and Balanced Multi-Component and Multi-Layer Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00765v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we propose a balanced multi-component and multi-layer neural network (MMNN) structure to accurately and efficiently approximate functions with complex features, in terms of both degrees of freedom and computational cost. The main idea is inspired by a multi-component approach, in which each component can be effectively approximated by a single-layer network, combined with a multi-layer decomposition strategy to capture the complexity of the target function. Although MMNNs can be viewed as a simple modification of fully connected neural networks (FCNNs) or multi-layer perceptrons (MLPs) by introducing balanced multi-component structures, they achieve a significant reduction in training parameters, a much more efficient training process, and improved accuracy compared to FCNNs or MLPs. Extensive numerical experiments demonstrate the effectiveness of MMNNs in approximating highly oscillatory functions and their ability to automatically adapt to localized features.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00765v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shijun Zhang, Hongkai Zhao, Yimin Zhong, Haomin Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatio-Temporal Fuzzy-oriented Multi-Modal Meta-Learning for Fine-grained Emotion Recognition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13541v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Fine-grained emotion recognition (FER) plays a vital role in various fields, such as disease diagnosis, personalized recommendations, and multimedia mining. However, existing FER methods face three key challenges in real-world applications: (i) they rely on large amounts of continuously annotated data to ensure accuracy since emotions are complex and ambiguous in reality, which is costly and time-consuming; (ii) they cannot capture the temporal heterogeneity caused by changing emotion patterns, because they usually assume that the temporal correlation within sampling periods is the same; (iii) they do not consider the spatial heterogeneity of different FER scenarios, that is, the distribution of emotion information in different data may have bias or interference. To address these challenges, we propose a Spatio-Temporal Fuzzy-oriented Multi-modal Meta-learning framework (ST-F2M). Specifically, ST-F2M first divides the multi-modal videos into multiple views, and each view corresponds to one modality of one emotion. Multiple randomly selected views for the same emotion form a meta-training task. Next, ST-F2M uses an integrated module with spatial and temporal convolutions to encode the data of each task, reflecting the spatial and temporal heterogeneity. Then it adds fuzzy semantic information to each task based on generalized fuzzy rules, which helps handle the complexity and ambiguity of emotions. Finally, ST-F2M learns emotion-related general meta-knowledge through meta-recurrent neural networks to achieve fast and robust fine-grained emotion recognition. Extensive experiments show that ST-F2M outperforms various state-of-the-art methods in terms of accuracy and model efficiency. In addition, we construct ablation studies and further analysis to explore why ST-F2M performs well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13541v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingyao Wang, Wenwen Qiang, Changwen Zheng, Fuchun Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolving Hard Maximum Cut Instances for Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12012v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Variational quantum algorithms, such as the Recursive Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (RQAOA), have become increasingly popular, offering promising avenues for employing Noisy Intermediate-Scale Quantum devices to address challenging combinatorial optimization tasks like the maximum cut problem. In this study, we utilize an evolutionary algorithm equipped with a unique fitness function. This approach targets hard maximum cut instances within the latent space of a Graph Autoencoder, identifying those that pose significant challenges or are particularly tractable for RQAOA, in contrast to the classic Goemans and Williamson algorithm. Our findings not only delineate the distinct capabilities and limitations of each algorithm but also expand our understanding of RQAOA's operational limits. Furthermore, the diverse set of graphs we have generated serves as a crucial benchmarking asset, emphasizing the need for more advanced algorithms to tackle combinatorial optimization challenges. Additionally, our results pave the way for new avenues in graph generation research, offering exciting opportunities for future explorations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12012v3</guid>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuaiqun Pan, Yash J. Patel, Aneta Neumann, Frank Neumann, Thomas B\"ack, Hao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Systematic Review of Metaheuristics-Based and Machine Learning-Driven Intrusion Detection Systems in IoT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00377v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The widespread adoption of the Internet of Things (IoT) has raised a new challenge for developers since it is prone to known and unknown cyberattacks due to its heterogeneity, flexibility, and close connectivity. To defend against such security breaches, researchers have focused on building sophisticated intrusion detection systems (IDSs) using machine learning (ML) techniques. Although these algorithms notably improve detection performance, they require excessive computing power and resources, which are crucial issues in IoT networks considering the recent trends of decentralized data processing and computing systems. Consequently, many optimization techniques have been incorporated with these ML models. Specifically, a special category of optimizer adopted from the behavior of living creatures and different aspects of natural phenomena, known as metaheuristic algorithms, has been a central focus in recent years and brought about remarkable results. Considering this vital significance, we present a comprehensive and systematic review of various applications of metaheuristics algorithms in developing a machine learning-based IDS, especially for IoT. A significant contribution of this study is the discovery of hidden correlations between these optimization techniques and machine learning models integrated with state-of-the-art IoT-IDSs. In addition, the effectiveness of these metaheuristic algorithms in different applications, such as feature selection, parameter or hyperparameter tuning, and hybrid usages are separately analyzed. Moreover, a taxonomy of existing IoT-IDSs is proposed. Furthermore, we investigate several critical issues related to such integration. Our extensive exploration ends with a discussion of promising optimization algorithms and technologies that can enhance the efficiency of IoT-IDSs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00377v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.swevo.2025.101984</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Shamim Ahsan, Salekul Islam, Swakkhar Shatabda</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
