<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.QM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.QM</link>
    <description>q-bio.QM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.QM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 05:00:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A quantum inspired predictor of Parkinsons disease built on a diverse, multimodal dataset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18640v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Parkinsons disease, the fastest growing neurodegenerative disorder globally, has seen a 50 percent increase in cases within just two years. As speech, memory, and motor symptoms worsen over time, early diagnosis is crucial for preserving patients quality of life. While machine-learning-based detection has shown promise, relying on a single feature for classification can be error-prone due to the variability of symptoms between patients. To address this limitation we utilized the mPower database, which includes 150,000 samples across four key biomarkers: voice, gait, tapping, and demographic data. From these measurements, we extracted 64 features and trained a baseline Random Forest model to select the features above the 80th percentile. For classification, we designed a simulatable quantum support vector machine (qSVM) that detects high-dimensional patterns, leveraging recent advancements in quantum machine learning. With a novel, simulatable architecture that can be run on standard hardware rather than resource-intensive quantum computers, our model achieves an accuracy of 90 percent and an AUC of 0.98, surpassing benchmark models. By utilizing an innovative classification framework built on a diverse set of features, our model offers a pathway for accessible global Parkinsons screening.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18640v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diya Vatsavai, Anya Iyer, Ashwin A. Nair</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparative analysis of whole-body center-of-mass estimation methods in dynamic and static activities using marker-based systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18774v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate estimation of the whole-body center of mass (CoM) is essential for assessing human stability and postural control. However, selecting the most accurate estimation method is challenging due to the complexity of human movement, diverse nature of activities, and varying availability of equipment, such as marker-based systems and ground reaction force (GRF) sensors. This study compares three CoM estimation methods -- "Pelvis Markerset", "Whole-Body Markerset", and "Whole-Body Markerset &amp; GRFs" -- across static activities, such as standing with eyes closed, and dynamic activities, such as picking up an object from the ground. Using the root mean square (RMS) of "external force residual" (the difference between measured ground reaction forces and estimated CoM accelerations multiplied by total body mass) as a performance metric, we found that while all methods performed similarly under static conditions, the "Pelvis Markerset" method showed 96% to 104% higher RMS external force residual values during dynamic activities compared to the two whole-body methods ($p&lt;0.001$, Cohen's $d$:2.90-3.04). The accuracy of "Whole-Body Markerset &amp; GRFs" (i.e., Kalman filter) was similar to "Whole-Body Markerset", suggesting that incorporating the GRFs through the presented Kalman filter does not improve the estimates from whole-body kinematics. Based on these findings, we recommend the "Whole-Body Markerset" as it performs well and does not require information from GRFs. The "Pelvis Markerset" method can be used in static activities or when markersets around the pelvis reflect whole-body kinematics. This method is not recommended for CoM state estimation in highly dynamic scenarios and when whole-body markersets are available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18774v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingshu Peng, Mohsen Alizadeh Noghani, Edgar Bol\'ivar-Nieto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Per-event Uncertainty Quantification for Flow Cytometry using Calibration Beads</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19191v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Flow cytometry measurements are widely used in diagnostics and medical decision making. Incomplete understanding of sources of measurement uncertainty can make it difficult to distinguish autofluorescence and background sources from signals of interest. Moreover, established methods for modeling uncertainty overlook the fact that the apparent distribution of measurements is a convolution of the inherent the population variability (e.g., associated with calibration beads or cells) and instrument induced-effects. Such issues make it difficult, for example, to identify signals from small objects such as extracellular vesicles. To overcome such limitations, we formulate an explicit probabilistic measurement model that accounts for volume and labeling variation, background signals and fluorescence shot noise. Using raw data from routine per-event calibration measurements, we use this model to separate the aforementioned sources of uncertainty and demonstrate how such information can be used to facilitate decision-making and instrument characterization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19191v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prajakta Bedekar, Megan A. Catterton, Matthew DiSalvo, Gregory A. Cooksey, Anthony J. Kearsley, Paul N. Patrone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graph-Based Biomarker Discovery and Interpretation for Alzheimer's Disease</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18796</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18796v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Early diagnosis and discovery of therapeutic drug targets are crucial objectives for the effective management of Alzheimer's Disease (AD). Current approaches for AD diagnosis and treatment planning are based on radiological imaging and largely inaccessible for population-level screening due to prohibitive costs and limited availability. Recently, blood tests have shown promise in diagnosing AD and highlighting possible biomarkers that can be used as drug targets for AD management. Blood tests are significantly more accessible to disadvantaged populations, cost-effective, and minimally invasive. However, biomarker discovery in the context of AD diagnosis is complex as there exist important associations between various biomarkers. Here, we introduce BRAIN (Biomarker Representation, Analysis, and Interpretation Network), a novel machine learning (ML) framework to jointly optimize the diagnostic accuracy and biomarker discovery processes to identify all relevant biomarkers that contribute to AD diagnosis. Using a holistic graph-based representation for biomarkers, we highlight their inter-dependencies and explain why different ML models identify different discriminative biomarkers. We apply BRAIN to a publicly available blood biomarker dataset, revealing three novel biomarker sub-networks whose interactions vary between the control and AD groups, offering a new paradigm for drug discovery and biomarker analysis for AD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18796v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maryam Khalid, Fadeel Sher Khan, John Broussard, Arko Barman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncertainty quantification of receptor ligand binding sites prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.11312</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.11312v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent advancements in protein docking site prediction have highlighted the limitations of traditional rigid docking algorithms, like PIPER, which often neglect critical stochastic elements such as solvent-induced fluctuations. These oversights can lead to inaccuracies in identifying viable docking sites due to the complexity of high-dimensional, stochastic energy manifolds with low regularity. To address this issue, our research introduces a novel model where the molecular shapes of ligands and receptors are represented using multi-variate Karhunen-Lo `eve (KL) expansions. This method effectively captures the stochastic nature of energy manifolds, allowing for a more accurate representation of molecular interactions.Developed as a plugin for PIPER, our scientific computing software enhances the platform, delivering robust uncertainty measures for the energy manifolds of ranked binding sites. Our results demonstrate that top-ranked binding sites, characterized by lower uncertainty in the stochastic energy manifold, align closely with actual docking sites. Conversely, sites with higher uncertainty correlate with less optimal docking positions. This distinction not only validates our approach but also sets a new standard in protein docking predictions, offering substantial implications for future molecular interaction research and drug development.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.11312v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nanjie Chen, Dongliang Yu, Dmitri Beglov, Mark Kon, Julio Enrique Castrillon-Candas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ApisTox: a new benchmark dataset for the classification of small molecules toxicity on honey bees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16196v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The global decline in bee populations poses significant risks to agriculture, biodiversity, and environmental stability. To bridge the gap in existing data, we introduce ApisTox, a comprehensive dataset focusing on the toxicity of pesticides to honey bees (Apis mellifera). This dataset combines and leverages data from existing sources such as ECOTOX and PPDB, providing an extensive, consistent, and curated collection that surpasses the previous datasets. ApisTox incorporates a wide array of data, including toxicity levels for chemicals, details such as time of their publication in literature, and identifiers linking them to external chemical databases. This dataset may serve as an important tool for environmental and agricultural research, but also can support the development of policies and practices aimed at minimizing harm to bee populations. Finally, ApisTox offers a unique resource for benchmarking molecular property prediction methods on agrochemical compounds, facilitating advancements in both environmental science and cheminformatics. This makes it a valuable tool for both academic research and practical applications in bee conservation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16196v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jakub Adamczyk, Jakub Poziemski, Pawel Siedlecki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Image segmentation of treated and untreated tumor spheroids by Fully Convolutional Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01105v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Multicellular tumor spheroids (MCTS) are advanced cell culture systems for assessing the impact of combinatorial radio(chemo)therapy. They exhibit therapeutically relevant in-vivo-like characteristics from 3D cell-cell and cell-matrix interactions to radial pathophysiological gradients related to proliferative activity and nutrient/oxygen supply, altering cellular radioresponse. State-of-the-art assays quantify long-term curative endpoints based on collected brightfield image time series from large treated spheroid populations per irradiation dose and treatment arm. Here, spheroid control probabilities are documented analogous to in-vivo tumor control probabilities based on Kaplan-Meier curves. This analyses require laborious spheroid segmentation of up to 100.000 images per treatment arm to extract relevant structural information from the images, e.g., diameter, area, volume and circularity. While several image analysis algorithms are available for spheroid segmentation, they all focus on compact MCTS with clearly distinguishable outer rim throughout growth. However, treated MCTS may partly be detached and destroyed and are usually obscured by dead cell debris. We successfully train two Fully Convolutional Networks, UNet and HRNet, and optimize their hyperparameters to develop an automatic segmentation for both untreated and treated MCTS. We systematically validate the automatic segmentation on larger, independent data sets of spheroids derived from two human head-and-neck cancer cell lines. We find an excellent overlap between manual and automatic segmentation for most images, quantified by Jaccard indices at around 90%. For images with smaller overlap of the segmentations, we demonstrate that this error is comparable to the variations across segmentations from different biological experts, suggesting that these images represent biologically unclear or ambiguous cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01105v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>q-bio.TO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthias Streller, So\v{n}a Michl\'ikov\'a, Willy Ciecior, Katharina L\"onnecke, Leoni A. Kunz-Schughart, Steffen Lange, Anja Voss-B\"ohme</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modelling the Stochastic Importation Dynamics and Establishment of Novel Pathogenic Strains using a General Branching Processes Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02379v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The importation and subsequent establishment of novel pathogenic strains in a population is subject to a large degree of uncertainty due to the stochastic nature of the disease dynamics. Mathematical models need to take this stochasticity in the early phase of an outbreak in order to adequately capture the uncertainty in disease forecasts. We propose a general branching process model of disease spread that includes host-level heterogeneity, and that can be straightforwardly tailored to capture the salient aspects of a particular disease outbreak. We combine this with a model of case importation that occurs via an independent marked Poisson process. We use this framework to investigate the impact of different control strategies, particularly on the time to establishment of an invading, exogenous strain, using parameters taken from the literature for COVID-19 as an example. We also demonstrate how to combine our model with a deterministic approximation, such that longer term projections can be generated that still incorporate the uncertainty from the early growth phase of the epidemic. Our approach produces meaningful short- and medium-term projections of the course of a disease outbreak when model parameters are still uncertain and when stochasticity still has a large effect on the population dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02379v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacob Curran-Sebastian, Frederik M{\o}lkj{\ae}r Andersen, Samir Bhatt</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
