<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.QM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.QM</link>
    <description>q-bio.QM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.QM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 04:02:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Unraveling the Autism spectrum heterogeneity: Insights from ABIDE I Database using data/model-driven permutation testing approaches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12225v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Autism Spectrum Condition (ASC) is a neurodevelopmental condition characterized by impairments in communication, social interaction and restricted or repetitive behaviors. Extensive research has been conducted to identify distinctions between individuals with ASC and neurotypical individuals. However, limited attention has been given to comprehensively evaluating how variations in image acquisition protocols across different centers influence these observed differences. This analysis focuses on structural magnetic resonance imaging (sMRI) data from the Autism Brain Imaging Data Exchange I (ABIDE I) database, evaluating subjects' condition and individual centers to identify disparities between ASC and control groups. Statistical analysis, employing permutation tests, utilizes two distinct statistical mapping methods: Statistical Agnostic Mapping (SAM) and Statistical Parametric Mapping (SPM). Results reveal the absence of statistically significant differences in any brain region, attributed to factors such as limited sample sizes within certain centers, noise effects and the problem of multicentrism in a heterogeneous condition such as autism. This study indicates limitations in using the ABIDE I database to detect structural differences in the brain between neurotypical individuals and those diagnosed with ASC. Furthermore, results from the SAM mapping method show greater consistency with existing literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12225v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. J. Alcaide, I. A. Illan, J. Ramirez, J. M. Gorriz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scientific Hypothesis Generation by a Large Language Model: Laboratory Validation in Breast Cancer Treatment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12258</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12258v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Large language models (LLMs) have transformed AI and achieved breakthrough performance on a wide range of tasks that require human intelligence. In science, perhaps the most interesting application of LLMs is for hypothesis formation. A feature of LLMs, which results from their probabilistic structure, is that the output text is not necessarily a valid inference from the training text. These are 'hallucinations', and are a serious problem in many applications. However, in science, hallucinations may be useful: they are novel hypotheses whose validity may be tested by laboratory experiments. Here we experimentally test the use of LLMs as a source of scientific hypotheses using the domain of breast cancer treatment. We applied the LLM GPT4 to hypothesize novel pairs of FDA-approved non-cancer drugs that target the MCF7 breast cancer cell line relative to the non-tumorigenic breast cell line MCF10A. In the first round of laboratory experiments GPT4 succeeded in discovering three drug combinations (out of 12 tested) with synergy scores above the positive controls. These combinations were itraconazole + atenolol, disulfiram + simvastatin and dipyridamole + mebendazole. GPT4 was then asked to generate new combinations after considering its initial results. It then discovered three more combinations with positive synergy scores (out of four tested), these were disulfiram + fulvestrant, mebendazole + quinacrine and disulfiram + quinacrine. A limitation of GPT4 as a generator of hypotheses was that its explanations for them were formulaic and unconvincing. We conclude that LLMs are an exciting novel source of scientific hypotheses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12258v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abbi Abdel-Rehim, Hector Zenil, Oghenejokpeme Orhobor, Marie Fisher, Ross J. Collins, Elizabeth Bourne, Gareth W. Fearnley, Emma Tate, Holly X. Smith, Larisa N. Soldatova, Ross D. King</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extraction of Human DNA from Soil: Protocol Adaptations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12422v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: PCR-based analysis of DNA is utilized in a wide variety of fields, including Forensic Science. Aside from the more common ample sources, material analyzed here can refer to specimen excavated from a soil environment, or a sampling of the soil itself to recover DNA leached into the soil from decomposing human remains or from body fluids intermingled with the soil in an outdoor crime scene. The common problematic of these types of sample is the presence of humic acids, which are a component of any soil environment, and when the co-extracted with the DNA, lead to inhibition of enzyme-based procedures including PCR.
  While a variety of methods exist for the extraction of DNA from excavated skeletal remains, protocols for extraction of DNA from the soil directly are usually targeting soil microorganism. To address the need for methodology suitable for extraction of human DNA from soil, a selection of three published protocols were adapted for this purpose, to be tested and evaluated using standardized samples. The resulting protocols are presented here.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12422v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wera M Schmerer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ProtT3: Protein-to-Text Generation for Text-based Protein Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12564v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Language Models (LMs) excel in understanding textual descriptions of proteins, as evident in biomedical question-answering tasks. However, their capability falters with raw protein data, such as amino acid sequences, due to a deficit in pretraining on such data. Conversely, Protein Language Models (PLMs) can understand and convert protein data into high-quality representations, but struggle to process texts. To address their limitations, we introduce ProtT3, a framework for Protein-to-Text Generation for Text-based Protein Understanding. ProtT3 empowers an LM to understand protein sequences of amino acids by incorporating a PLM as its protein understanding module, enabling effective protein-to-text generation. This collaboration between PLM and LM is facilitated by a cross-modal projector (i.e., Q-Former) that bridges the modality gap between the PLM's representation space and the LM's input space. Unlike previous studies focusing on protein property prediction and protein-text retrieval, we delve into the largely unexplored field of protein-to-text generation. To facilitate comprehensive benchmarks and promote future research, we establish quantitative evaluations for protein-text modeling tasks, including protein captioning, protein question-answering, and protein-text retrieval. Our experiments show that ProtT3 substantially surpasses current baselines, with ablation studies further highlighting the efficacy of its core components. Our code is available at https://github.com/acharkq/ProtT3.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12564v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyuan Liu, An Zhang, Hao Fei, Enzhi Zhang, Xiang Wang, Kenji Kawaguchi, Tat-Seng Chua</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hypergraph: A Unified and Uniform Definition with Application to Chemical Hypergraph</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12235v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The conventional definition of hypergraph has two major issues: (1) there is not a standard definition of directed hypergraph and (2) there is not a formal definition of nested hypergraph. To resolve these issues, we propose a new definition of hypergraph that unifies the concepts of undirected, directed and nested hypergraphs, and that is uniform in using hyperedge as a single construct for representing high-order correlations among things, i.e., nodes and hyperedges. Specifically, we define a hyperedge to be a simple hyperedge, a nesting hyperedge, or a directed hyperedge. With this new definition, a hypergraph is nested if it has nesting hyperedge(s), and is directed if it has directed hyperedge(s). Otherwise, a hypergraph is a simple hypergraph. The uniformity and power of this new definition should facilitate the use of hypergraph for representing (hierarchical) high-order correlations in general and chemical systems in particular. Graph has been widely used as a mathematical structure for machine learning on molecular structures and 3D molecular geometries. However, graph has a major limitation: it can represent only pairwise correlations between nodes. Hypergraph extends graph with high-order correlations among nodes. This extension is significant or essential for machine learning on chemical systems. For molecules, this is significant as it allows the direct, explicit representation of multicenter bonds and molecular substructures. For chemical reactions, this is essential since most chemical reactions involve multiple participants. We propose the use of chemical hypergraph, a multilevel hypergraph with simple, nesting and directed hyperedges, as a single mathematical structure for representing chemical systems. We apply the new definition of hypergraph to chemical hypergraph and, as simplified versions, molecular hypergraph and chemical reaction hypergraph.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12235v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel T. Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MAGE: Model-Level Graph Neural Networks Explanations via Motif-based Graph Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12519v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) have shown remarkable success in molecular tasks, yet their interpretability remains challenging. Traditional model-level explanation methods like XGNN and GNNInterpreter often fail to identify valid substructures like rings, leading to questionable interpretability. This limitation stems from XGNN's atom-by-atom approach and GNNInterpreter's reliance on average graph embeddings, which overlook the essential structural elements crucial for molecules. To address these gaps, we introduce an innovative \textbf{M}otif-b\textbf{A}sed \textbf{G}NN \textbf{E}xplainer (MAGE) that uses motifs as fundamental units for generating explanations. Our approach begins with extracting potential motifs through a motif decomposition technique. Then, we utilize an attention-based learning method to identify class-specific motifs. Finally, we employ a motif-based graph generator for each class to create molecular graph explanations based on these class-specific motifs. This novel method not only incorporates critical substructures into the explanations but also guarantees their validity, yielding results that are human-understandable. Our proposed method's effectiveness is demonstrated through quantitative and qualitative assessments conducted on six real-world molecular datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12519v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhaoning Yu, Hongyang Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy Rank Alignment: Using Preference Optimization to Search Chemical Space at Scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12961v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Searching through chemical space is an exceptionally challenging problem because the number of possible molecules grows combinatorially with the number of atoms. Large, autoregressive models trained on databases of chemical compounds have yielded powerful generators, but we still lack robust strategies for generating molecules with desired properties. This molecular search problem closely resembles the "alignment" problem for large language models, though for many chemical tasks we have a specific and easily evaluable reward function. Here, we introduce an algorithm called energy rank alignment (ERA) that leverages an explicit reward function to produce a gradient-based objective that we use to optimize autoregressive policies. We show theoretically that this algorithm is closely related to proximal policy optimization (PPO) and direct preference optimization (DPO), but has a minimizer that converges to an ideal Gibbs-Boltzmann distribution with the reward playing the role of an energy function. Furthermore, this algorithm is highly scalable, does not require reinforcement learning, and performs well relative to DPO when the number of preference observations per pairing is small. We deploy this approach to align molecular transformers to generate molecules with externally specified properties and find that it does so robustly, searching through diverse parts of chemical space. While our focus here is on chemical search, we also obtain excellent results on an AI supervised task for LLM alignment, showing that the method is scalable and general.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12961v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shriram Chennakesavalu, Frank Hu, Sebastian Ibarraran, Grant M. Rotskoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-omics Prediction from High-content Cellular Imaging with Deep Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.09391</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.09391v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High-content cellular imaging, transcriptomics, and proteomics data provide rich and complementary views on the molecular layers of biology that influence cellular states and function. However, the biological determinants through which changes in multi-omics measurements influence cellular morphology have not yet been systematically explored, and the degree to which cell imaging could potentially enable the prediction of multi-omics directly from cell imaging data is therefore currently unclear. Here, we address the question of whether it is possible to predict bulk multi-omics measurements directly from cell images using Image2Omics - a deep learning approach that predicts multi-omics in a cell population directly from high-content images of cells stained with multiplexed fluorescent dyes. We perform an experimental evaluation in gene-edited macrophages derived from human induced pluripotent stem cells (hiPSC) under multiple stimulation conditions and demonstrate that Image2Omics achieves significantly better performance in predicting transcriptomics and proteomics measurements directly from cell images than predictions based on the mean observed training set abundance. We observed significant predictability of abundances for 4927 (18.72%; 95% CI: 6.52%, 35.52%) and 3521 (13.38%; 95% CI: 4.10%, 32.21%) transcripts out of 26137 in M1 and M2-stimulated macrophages respectively and for 422 (8.46%; 95% CI: 0.58%, 25.83%) and 697 (13.98%; 95% CI: 2.41%, 32.83%) proteins out of 4986 in M1 and M2-stimulated macrophages respectively. Our results show that some transcript and protein abundances are predictable from cell imaging and that cell imaging may potentially, in some settings and depending on the mechanisms of interest and desired performance threshold, even be a scalable and resource-efficient substitute for multi-omics measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.09391v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rahil Mehrizi, Arash Mehrjou, Maryana Alegro, Yi Zhao, Benedetta Carbone, Carl Fishwick, Johanna Vappiani, Jing Bi, Siobhan Sanford, Hakan Keles, Marcus Bantscheff, Cuong Nguyen, Patrick Schwab</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Molecular techniques employed in CTG(Ser1) and CTG(Ala) D-xylose metabolizing yeast clades for strain design and industrial applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.11010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.11010v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: D-xylose is the second most abundant monosaccharide found in lignocellulose and is of biotechnological importance for producing second-generation ethanol and other high-value chemical compounds. D-xylose conversion to ethanol is promoted by microbial fermentation, mainly by bacteria, yeasts, or filamentous fungi. Considering yeasts, species belonging to the CTG(Ser1) or CTG(Ala) clade display a remarkable ability to ferment D-xylose to ethanol and other compounds; however, these yeasts are not employed on an industrial scale due to the poor fermentative performance compared to conventional yeasts, like Saccharomyces cerevisiae, and also due to the lack of a molecular toolbox for development of new strains tailored to fermentation stress tolerance and performance. Thus, the purpose of this review is to evaluate the major molecular tools (e.g., transformation markers and techniques, vectors, regulatory sequences, and gene editing techniques) available for the most studied yeasts of CTG(Ser1) clade, like Scheffersomyces, Spathaspora, Candida and Yamadazyma species, and the CTG(Ala) clade representative Pachysolen tannophilus. Furthermore, we synthesized the current state-of-the-art molecular developments and perspectives for D-xylose fermenting yeast strain design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.11010v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ana Paula Wives, Isabelli Seiler de Medeiros Mendes, Sofia Turatti dos Santos, Diego Bonatto</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
