<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.QM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.QM</link>
    <description>q-bio.QM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.QM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 02:00:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>BEACON: Benchmark for Comprehensive RNA Tasks and Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10391</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10391v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: RNA plays a pivotal role in translating genetic instructions into functional outcomes, underscoring its importance in biological processes and disease mechanisms. Despite the emergence of numerous deep learning approaches for RNA, particularly universal RNA language models, there remains a significant lack of standardized benchmarks to assess the effectiveness of these methods. In this study, we introduce the first comprehensive RNA benchmark BEACON (\textbf{BE}nchm\textbf{A}rk for \textbf{CO}mprehensive R\textbf{N}A Task and Language Models). First, BEACON comprises 13 distinct tasks derived from extensive previous work covering structural analysis, functional studies, and engineering applications, enabling a comprehensive assessment of the performance of methods on various RNA understanding tasks. Second, we examine a range of models, including traditional approaches like CNNs, as well as advanced RNA foundation models based on language models, offering valuable insights into the task-specific performances of these models. Third, we investigate the vital RNA language model components from the tokenizer and positional encoding aspects. Notably, our findings emphasize the superiority of single nucleotide tokenization and the effectiveness of Attention with Linear Biases (ALiBi) over traditional positional encoding methods. Based on these insights, a simple yet strong baseline called BEACON-B is proposed, which can achieve outstanding performance with limited data and computational resources. The datasets and source code of our benchmark are available at https://github.com/terry-r123/RNABenchmark.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10391v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuchen Ren, Zhiyuan Chen, Lifeng Qiao, Hongtai Jing, Yuchen Cai, Sheng Xu, Peng Ye, Xinzhu Ma, Siqi Sun, Hongliang Yan, Dong Yuan, Wanli Ouyang, Xihui Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved absolute abundance estimates from spatial count data with simulation and microfossil case studies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10921v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many fundamental parameters of biological systems -- eg. productivity, population sizes and biomass -- are most effectively expressed in absolute terms. In contrast to proportional data (eg. percentages), absolute values provide standardised metrics on the functioning of biological entities (eg. organisism, species, ecosystems). These are particularly valuable when comparing assemblages across time and space. Since it is almost always impractical to count entire populations, estimates of population abundances require a sampling method that is both accurate and precise. Such absolute abundance estimates typically entail more "sampling effort" (data collection time) than proportional data. Here we refined a method of absolute abundance estimates -- the "exotic marker technique" -- by producing a variant that is more efficient without losing accuracy. This new method, the "field-of-view subsampling method" (FOVS method) is based on area subsampling, from which large samples can be quickly extrapolated.
  Two case studies of the exotic marker technique were employed: 1, computer simulations; and 2, an observational "real world" data set of terrestrial organic microfossils from the Permian- and Triassic-aged rock strata of southeastern Australia, spiked with marker grains of known quantity and variance. We compared the FOVS method against the traditional "linear method" method using three metrics: 1, concentration (specimens/gram of sediment); 2, precision and 3, data collection effort. In almost all cases, the FOVS method delivers higher precision than the linear method, with equivalent effort, and our computer simulations suggest that the FOVS method more accurately estimates the true error for large target-to-marker ratios. Since we predict that these conditions are typically common, we recommend the new FOVS method in almost every "real world" case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10921v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chris Mays, Marcos Amores, Anthony Mays</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Increasing certainty in systems biology models using Bayesian multimodel inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11178</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11178v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mathematical models are indispensable to the system biology toolkit for studying the structure and behavior of intracellular signaling networks. A common approach to modeling is to develop a system of equations that encode the known biology using approximations and simplifying assumptions. As a result, the same signaling pathway can be represented by multiple models, each with its set of underlying assumptions, which opens up challenges for model selection and decreases certainty in model predictions. Here, we use Bayesian multimodel inference to develop a framework to increase certainty in systems biology models. Using models of the extracellular regulated kinase (ERK) pathway, we first show that multimodel inference increases predictive certainty and yields predictors that are robust to changes in the set of available models. We then show that predictions made with multimodel inference are robust to data uncertainties introduced by decreasing the measurement duration and reducing the sample size. Finally, we use multimodel inference to identify a new model to explain experimentally measured sub-cellular location-specific ERK activity dynamics. In summary, our framework highlights multimodel inference as a disciplined approach to increasing the certainty of intracellular signaling activity predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11178v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathaniel Linden-Santangeli, Jin Zhang, Boris Kramer, Padmini Rangamani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information-theoretic evaluation of covariate distributions models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10611</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10611v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Statistical modelling of covariate distributions allows to generate virtual populations or to impute missing values in a covariate dataset. Covariate distributions typically have non-Gaussian margins and show nonlinear correlation structures, which simple multivariate Gaussian distributions fail to represent. Prominent non-Gaussian frameworks for covariate distribution modelling are copula-based models and models based on multiple imputation by chained equations (MICE). While both frameworks have already found applications in the life sciences, a systematic investigation of their goodness-of-fit to the theoretical underlying distribution, indicating strengths and weaknesses under different conditions, is still lacking. To bridge this gap, we thoroughly evaluated covariate distribution models in terms of Kullback-Leibler divergence (KL-D), a scale-invariant information-theoretic goodness-of-fit criterion for distributions. Methodologically, we proposed a new approach to construct confidence intervals for KL-D by combining nearest neighbour-based KL-D estimators with subsampling-based uncertainty quantification. In relevant data sets of different sizes and dimensionalities with both continuous and discrete covariates, non-Gaussian models showed consistent improvements in KL-D, compared to simpler Gaussian or scale transform approximations. KL-D estimates were also robust to the inclusion of latent variables and large fractions of missing values. While good generalization behaviour to new data could be seen in copula-based models, MICE shows a trend for overfitting and its performance should always be evaluated on separate test data. Parametric copula models and MICE were found to scale much better with the dataset dimension than nonparametric copula models. These findings corroborate the potential of non-Gaussian models for modelling realistic life science covariate distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10611v1</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niklas Hartung, Aleksandra Khatova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Development and Validation of Fully Automatic Deep Learning-Based Algorithms for Immunohistochemistry Reporting of Invasive Breast Ductal Carcinoma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10893</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10893v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Immunohistochemistry (IHC) analysis is a well-accepted and widely used method for molecular subtyping, a procedure for prognosis and targeted therapy of breast carcinoma, the most common type of tumor affecting women. There are four molecular biomarkers namely progesterone receptor (PR), estrogen receptor (ER), antigen Ki67, and human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2) whose assessment is needed under IHC procedure to decide prognosis as well as predictors of response to therapy. However, IHC scoring is based on subjective microscopic examination of tumor morphology and suffers from poor reproducibility, high subjectivity, and often incorrect scoring in low-score cases. In this paper, we present, a deep learning-based semi-supervised trained, fully automatic, decision support system (DSS) for IHC scoring of invasive ductal carcinoma. Our system automatically detects the tumor region removing artifacts and scores based on Allred standard. The system is developed using 3 million pathologist-annotated image patches from 300 slides, fifty thousand in-house cell annotations, and forty thousand pixels marking of HER2 membrane. We have conducted multicentric trials at four centers with three different types of digital scanners in terms of percentage agreement with doctors. And achieved agreements of 95, 92, 88 and 82 percent for Ki67, HER2, ER, and PR stain categories, respectively. In addition to overall accuracy, we found that there is 5 percent of cases where pathologist have changed their score in favor of algorithm score while reviewing with detailed algorithmic analysis. Our approach could improve the accuracy of IHC scoring and subsequent therapy decisions, particularly where specialist expertise is unavailable. Our system is highly modular. The proposed algorithm modules can be used to develop DSS for other cancer types.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10893v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>q-bio.TO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sumit Kumar Jha, Purnendu Mishra, Shubham Mathur, Gursewak Singh, Rajiv Kumar, Kiran Aatre, Suraj Rengarajan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computing the Frequency Response of Biochemical Networks: A Python module</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11140</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11140v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, a set of Python methods is described that can be used to compute the frequency response of an arbitrary biochemical network given any input and output. Models can be provided in standard SBML or Antimony format. The code takes into account any conserved moieties so that this software can be used to also study signaling networks where moiety cycles are common. A utility method is also provided to make it easy to plot standard Bode plots from the generated results. The code also takes into account the possibility that the phase shift could exceed 180 degrees which can result in ugly discontinues in the Bode plot. In the paper, some of the theory behind the method is provided as well as some commentary on the code and several illustrative examples to show the code in operation. Illustrative examples include linear reaction chains of varying lengths and the effect of negative feedback on the frequency response.
  Software License: MIT Open Source
  Availability: The code is available from https://github.com/sys-bio/frequencyResponse.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11140v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.MN</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Herbert M Sauro</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
