<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.QM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.QM</link>
    <description>q-bio.QM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.QM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2024 04:00:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Projecting Molecules into Synthesizable Chemical Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04628v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Discovering new drug molecules is a pivotal yet challenging process due to the near-infinitely large chemical space and notorious demands on time and resources. Numerous generative models have recently been introduced to accelerate the drug discovery process, but their progression to experimental validation remains limited, largely due to a lack of consideration for synthetic accessibility in practical settings. In this work, we introduce a novel framework that is capable of generating new chemical structures while ensuring synthetic accessibility. Specifically, we introduce a postfix notation of synthetic pathways to represent molecules in chemical space. Then, we design a transformer-based model to translate molecular graphs into postfix notations of synthesis. We highlight the model's ability to: (a) perform bottom-up synthesis planning more accurately, (b) generate structurally similar, synthesizable analogs for unsynthesizable molecules proposed by generative models with their properties preserved, and (c) explore the local synthesizable chemical space around hit molecules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04628v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shitong Luo, Wenhao Gao, Zuofan Wu, Jian Peng, Connor W. Coley, Jianzhu Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting local perturbations of networks in a latent hyperbolic embedding space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.13495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.13495v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Graph theoretical approaches have been proven to be effective in the characterization of connected systems, as well as in quantifying their dysfunction due to perturbation. In this paper, we show the advantage of a non-Euclidean (hyperbolic) representation of networks to identify local connectivity perturbations and to characterize the induced effects on a large scale. We propose two perturbation scores based on representations of the networks in a latent geometric space, obtained through an embedding onto the hyperbolic Poincar\'e disk. We numerically demonstrate that these methods are able to localize perturbations in networks with homogeneous or heterogeneous degree connectivity. We apply this framework to identify the most perturbed brain areas in epileptic patients following surgery. This study is conceived in the effort of developing more powerful tools to represent and analyze brain networks, and it is the first to apply geometric network embedding techniques to the case of epilepsy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.13495v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0199546</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chaos 1 June 2024; 34 (6): 063117</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alice Longhena, Martin Guillemaud, Mario Chavez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faster Gr\"obner bases for Lie derivatives of ODE systems via monomial orderings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.06297</link>
      <description>arXiv:2202.06297v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Symbolic computation for systems of differential equations is often computationally expensive. Many practical differential models have a form of polynomial or rational ODE system with specified outputs. A basic symbolic approach to analyze these models is to compute and then symbolically process the polynomial system obtained by sufficiently many Lie derivatives of the output functions with respect to the vector field given by the ODE system.
  In this paper, we present a method for speeding up Gr\"obner basis computation for such a class of polynomial systems by using specific monomial ordering, including weights for the variables, coming from the structure of the ODE model. We provide empirical results that show improvement across different symbolic computing frameworks and apply the method to speed up structural identifiability analysis of ODE models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2202.06297v3</guid>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <category>cs.MS</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3666000.3669695</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Mariya Bessonov, Ilia Ilmer, Tatiana Konstantinova, Alexey Ovchinnikov, Gleb Pogudin, Pedro Soto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A picture guide to cancer progression and monotonic accumulation models: evolutionary assumptions, plausible interpretations, and alternative uses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.06824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.06824v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Cancer progression and monotonic accumulation models were developed to discover dependencies in the irreversible acquisition of binary traits from cross-sectional data. They have been used in computational oncology and virology to understand dependencies in the accumulation of mutations but also in widely different problems such as malaria progression.
  These tools have been used to make predictions about future and unobserved states of the system, identify different routes of feature acquisition in subsets of the data, and improve patient stratification based on the evolutionary trajectories.
  But these methods have shortcomings, in particular with respect to key evolutionary assumptions and interpretations. After an overview of the available methods, we focus on how and why the methods can fail and why their inferences might not be about the process we intend. The discussion embraces fitness landscapes and highlights the difficulties that arise from bulk sequencing and reciprocal sign epistasis, from the conflation of lines of descent, path of the maximum, and mutational profiles, and from the ambiguous use of the concepts of exclusivity and alternative evolutionary paths. Next, we suggest that users recognize the limitations that arise from their sampling designs, and we examine how the previous concerns are modified when bulk sequencing is accounted for. We also highlight how bulk sequencing can create an opportunity for addressing dependencies that arise from frequency-dependent selection. This review should help identify major standing issues and research opportunities, and encourage the use of these methods in other areas with a possibly better fit between entities and model assumptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.06824v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ramon Diaz-Uriarte, Iain G. Johnston</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rene: A Pre-trained Multi-modal Architecture for Auscultation of Respiratory Diseases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.07442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.07442v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Compared with invasive examinations that require tissue sampling, respiratory sound testing is a non-invasive examination method that is safer and easier for patients to accept. In this study, we introduce Rene, a pioneering large-scale model tailored for respiratory sound recognition. Rene has been rigorously fine-tuned with an extensive dataset featuring a broad array of respiratory audio samples, targeting disease detection, sound pattern classification, and event identification. Our innovative approach applies a pre-trained speech recognition model to process respiratory sounds, augmented with patient medical records. The resulting multi-modal deep-learning framework addresses interpretability and real-time diagnostic challenges that have hindered previous respiratory-focused models. Benchmark comparisons reveal that Rene significantly outperforms existing models, achieving improvements of 10.27%, 16.15%, 15.29%, and 18.90% in respiratory event detection and audio classification on the SPRSound database. Disease prediction accuracy on the ICBHI database improved by 23% over the baseline in both mean average and harmonic scores. Moreover, we have developed a real-time respiratory sound discrimination system utilizing the Rene architecture. Employing state-of-the-art Edge AI technology, this system enables rapid and accurate responses for respiratory sound auscultation(https://github.com/zpforlove/Rene).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.07442v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pengfei Zhang, Zhihang Zheng, Shichen Zhang, Minghao Yang, Shaojun Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
