<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.QM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.QM</link>
    <description>q-bio.QM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.QM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 04:01:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Topological and Graph Theoretical Analysis of Dynamic Functional Connectivity for Autism Spectrum Disorder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16874v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD) is a prevalent neurological disorder. However, the multi-faceted symptoms and large individual differences among ASD patients are hindering the diagnosis process, which largely relies on subject descriptions and lacks quantitative biomarkers. To remediate such problems, this paper explores the use of graph theory and topological data analysis (TDA) to study brain activity in ASD patients and normal controls. We employ the Mapper algorithm in TDA and the distance correlation graphical model (DCGM) in graph theory to create brain state networks, then innovatively adopt complex network metrics in Graph signal processing (GSP) and physical quantities to analyze brain activities over time. Our findings reveal statistical differences in network characteristics between ASD and control groups. Compared to normal subjects, brain state networks of ASD patients tend to have decreased modularity, higher von Neumann entropy, increased Betti-0 numbers, and decreased Betti-1 numbers. These findings attest to the biological traits of ASD, suggesting less transitioning in brain dynamics. These findings offer potential biomarkers for ASD diagnosis and deepen our understanding of its neural correlations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16874v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuzhe Chen, Dayu Qin, Ercan Engin Kuruoglu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational autoencoders stabilise TCN performance when classifying weakly labelled bioacoustics data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17006</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17006v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Passive acoustic monitoring (PAM) data is often weakly labelled, audited at the scale of detection presence or absence on timescales of minutes to hours. Moreover, this data exhibits great variability from one deployment to the next, due to differences in ambient noise and the signals across sources and geographies. This study proposes a two-step solution to leverage weakly annotated data for training Deep Learning (DL) detection models. Our case study involves binary classification of the presence/absence of sperm whale (\textit{Physeter macrocephalus}) click trains in 4-minute-long recordings from a dataset comprising diverse sources and deployment conditions to maximise generalisability. We tested methods for extracting acoustic features from lengthy audio segments and integrated Temporal Convolutional Networks (TCNs) trained on the extracted features for sequence classification. For feature extraction, we introduced a new approach using Variational AutoEncoders (VAEs) to extract information from both waveforms and spectrograms, which eliminates the necessity for manual threshold setting or time-consuming strong labelling. For classification, TCNs were trained separately on sequences of either VAE embeddings or handpicked acoustic features extracted from the waveform and spectrogram representations using classical methods, to compare the efficacy of the two approaches. The TCN demonstrated robust classification capabilities on a validation set, achieving accuracies exceeding 85\% when applied to 4-minute acoustic recordings. Notably, TCNs trained on handpicked acoustic features exhibited greater variability in performance across recordings from diverse deployment conditions, whereas those trained on VAEs showed a more consistent performance, highlighting the robust transferability of VAEs for feature extraction across different deployment conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17006v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laia Garrob\'e Fonollosa, Douglas Gillespie, Lina Stankovic, Vladimir Stankovic, Luke Rendell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transfer Learning Bayesian Optimization to Design Competitor DNA Molecules for Use in Diagnostic Assays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17704</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.17704v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: With the rise in engineered biomolecular devices, there is an increased need for tailor-made biological sequences. Often, many similar biological sequences need to be made for a specific application meaning numerous, sometimes prohibitively expensive, lab experiments are necessary for their optimization. This paper presents a transfer learning design of experiments workflow to make this development feasible. By combining a transfer learning surrogate model with Bayesian optimization, we show how the total number of experiments can be reduced by sharing information between optimization tasks. We demonstrate the reduction in the number of experiments using data from the development of DNA competitors for use in an amplification-based diagnostic assay. We use cross-validation to compare the predictive accuracy of different transfer learning models, and then compare the performance of the models for both single objective and penalized optimization tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.17704v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruby Sedgwick, John P. Goertz, Molly M. Stevens, Ruth Misener, Mark van der Wilk</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
