<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.QM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.QM</link>
    <description>q-bio.QM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.QM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 14:40:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Implementation of an AI-based MRD evaluation and prediction model for multiple myeloma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00842</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00842v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With the application of hematopoietic stem cell transplantation and new drugs, the progression-free survival rate and overall survival rate of multiple myeloma have been greatly improved, but it is still considered as a kind of disease that cannot be completely cured. Many patients have disease recurrence after complete remission, which is rooted in the presence of minimal residual disease MRD in patients. Studies have shown that positive MRD is an independent adverse prognostic factor affecting survival, so MRD detection is an important indicator to judge the prognosis of patients and guide clinical treatment. At present, multipa-rameter flow cytometry (MFC), polymerase chain reaction (PCR), positron emission tomography (positron emission) Several techniques, such as PET/computer tomography (CT), have been used for MRD detection of multiple myeloma.However, there is still no cure for the disease. "IFM2013-04" four clinical studies confirmed for the first time that proteasome inhibitors (PIs) and immunomodulatory drugs, The synergism and importance of the combination of IMiDs in the treatment of MM, the large Phase 3 clinical study SWOG SO777 compared the combination of bortezomib plus lenalidomide and dexamethasone. The efficacy of VRD and D established the status of VRD first-line treatment of MM, and due to the good efficacy of CD38 monoclonal antibody in large clinical studies, combination therapy with VRD has been recommended as the first-line treatment of MM. However, to explore the clinical value and problems of applying artificial intelligence bone marrow cell recognition system Morphogo in the detection of multiple myeloma minimal residual disease (MRD)</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00842v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianfeng Chen, Jize Xiong, Yixu Wang, Qi Xin, Hong Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Protein Predictive Models via Proteins Data Augmentation: A Benchmark and New Directions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00875v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Augmentation is an effective alternative to utilize the small amount of labeled protein data. However, most of the existing work focuses on design-ing new architectures or pre-training tasks, and relatively little work has studied data augmentation for proteins. This paper extends data augmentation techniques previously used for images and texts to proteins and then benchmarks these techniques on a variety of protein-related tasks, providing the first comprehensive evaluation of protein augmentation. Furthermore, we propose two novel semantic-level protein augmentation methods, namely Integrated Gradients Substitution and Back Translation Substitution, which enable protein semantic-aware augmentation through saliency detection and biological knowledge. Finally, we integrate extended and proposed augmentations into an augmentation pool and propose a simple but effective framework, namely Automated Protein Augmentation (APA), which can adaptively select the most suitable augmentation combinations for different tasks. Extensive experiments have shown that APA enhances the performance of five protein related tasks by an average of 10.55% across three architectures compared to vanilla implementations without augmentation, highlighting its potential to make a great impact on the field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00875v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rui Sun, Lirong Wu, Haitao Lin, Yufei Huang, Stan Z. Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chaining thoughts and LLMs to learn DNA structural biophysics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01332v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The future development of an AI scientist, a tool that is capable of integrating a variety of experimental data and generating testable hypotheses, holds immense potential. So far, bespoke machine learning models have been created to specialize in singular scientific tasks, but otherwise lack the flexibility of a general purpose model. Here, we show that a general purpose large language model, chatGPT 3.5-turbo, can be fine-tuned to learn the structural biophysics of DNA. We find that both fine-tuning models to return chain-of-thought responses and chaining together models fine-tuned for subtasks have an enhanced ability to analyze and design DNA sequences and their structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01332v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tyler D. Ross, Ashwin Gopinath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structured methods for parameter inference and uncertainty quantification for mechanistic models in the life sciences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01678v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Parameter inference and uncertainty quantification are important steps when relating mathematical models to real-world observations, and when estimating uncertainty in model predictions. However, methods for doing this can be computationally expensive, particularly when the number of unknown model parameters is large. The aim of this study is to develop and test an efficient profile likelihood-based method, which takes advantage of the structure of the mathematical model being used. We do this by identifying specific parameters that affect model output in a known way, such as a linear scaling. We illustrate the method by applying it to three caricature models from different areas of the life sciences: (i) a predator-prey model from ecology; (ii) a compartment-based epidemic model from health sciences; and, (iii) an advection-diffusion-reaction model describing transport of dissolved solutes from environmental science. We show that the new method produces results of comparable accuracy to existing profile likelihood methods, but with substantially fewer evaluations of the forward model. We conclude that our method could provide a much more efficient approach to parameter inference for models where a structure approach is feasible. Code to apply the new method to user-supplied models and data is provided via a publicly accessible repository.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01678v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael J. Plank, Matthew J. Simpson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Piezoelectricity and flexoelectricity in biological cells: The role of cell structure and organelles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02050v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Living tissues experience various external forces on cells, influencing their behaviour, physiology, shape, gene expression, and destiny through interactions with their environment. Despite much research done in this area, challenges remain in our better understanding of the behaviour of the cell in response to external stimuli, including the arrangement, quantity, and shape of organelles within the cell. This study explores the electromechanical behaviour of biological cells, including organelles like microtubules, mitochondria, nuclei, and cell membranes. Two distinct cell structures have been developed to explore the cell responses to mechanical displacement, resembling actual cell shapes. The finite element method has been utilized to integrate the linear piezoelectric and non-local flexoelectric effects accurately. It is found that the longitudinal stress is absent and only the transverse stress plays a crucial role when the mechanical load is imposed on the top side of the cell through compressive displacement. The impact of flexoelectricity is elucidated by introducing a new parameter called the maximum electric potential ratio ($V_{\text{R,max}}$). It has been found that $V_{\text{R,max}}$ depends upon the orientation angle and shape of the microtubules. Further, the study reveals that the number of microtubules significantly impacts effective elastic and piezoelectric coefficients, affecting cell behaviour based on structure, microtubule orientation, and mechanical stress direction. The insight obtained from the current study can assist in advancements in medical therapies such as tissue engineering and regenerative medicine.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02050v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akepogu Venkateshwarlu,  Akshayveer, Sundeep Singh, Roderick Melnik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tractography derived quantitative estimates of tissue microstructure depend on streamline length: A characterization and method of adjustment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02102</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02102v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Tractography algorithms are used extensively to delineate white matter structures, by operating on the voxel-wise information generated through the application of diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) or other models to diffusion weighted (DW) magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) data. We demonstrate that these methods commonly yield systematic streamline length dependent distortions of tractography derived tissue microstructure parameters, such as fractional anisotropy (FA). This dependency may be described as piecewise linear. For streamlines shorter than an inflection point (determined for a group of tracts delineated for each individual brain), estimates of tissue microstructure exhibit a positive linear relation with streamline length. For streamlines longer than the point of inflection, the association is weaker, with the slope of the relationship between streamline length and tissue microstructure differing only marginally from zero. As the dependency is most pronounced for a range of streamline lengths encountered typically in DW imaging of the human brain (less than ~100 mm), our results suggest that some previous estimates of tissue microstructure should be treated with considerable caution. A method is described, whereby an Akaike information weighted average of linear, Blackman and piecewise linear model predictions, may be used to compensate effectively for the dependence of FA (and other estimates of tissue microstructure) on streamline length, across the entire range of streamline lengths present in each specimen.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02102v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Richard G. Carson, Alexander Leemans</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search via Parallel L{\'e}vy Walks on ${\mathbb Z}^2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.01562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2004.01562v5 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Motivated by the \emph{L{\'e}vy foraging hypothesis} -- the premise that various animal species have adapted to follow \emph{L{\'e}vy walks} to optimize their search efficiency -- we study the parallel hitting time of L{\'e}vy walks on the infinite two-dimensional grid.We consider $k$ independent discrete-time L{\'e}vy walks, with the same exponent $\alpha \in(1,\infty)$, that start from the same node, and analyze the number of steps until the first walk visits a given target at distance $\ell$.We show that for any choice of $k$ and $\ell$ from a large range, there is a unique optimal exponent $\alpha_{k,\ell} \in (2,3)$, for which the hitting time is $\tilde O(\ell^2/k)$ w.h.p., while modifying the exponent by an $\epsilon$ term increases the hitting time by a polynomial factor, or the walks fail to hit the target almost surely.Based on that, we propose a surprisingly simple and effective parallel search strategy, for the setting where $k$ and $\ell$ are unknown: the exponent of each L{\'e}vy walk is just chosen independently and uniformly at random from the interval $(2,3)$.This strategy achieves optimal search time (modulo polylogarithmic factors) among all possible algorithms (even centralized ones that know $k$).Our results should be contrasted with a line of previous work showing that the exponent $\alpha = 2$ is optimal for various search problems.In our setting of $k$ parallel walks, we show that the optimal exponent depends on $k$ and $\ell$, and that randomizing the choice of the exponents works simultaneously for all $k$ and $\ell$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2004.01562v5</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3465084.3467921</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PODC 2021 - ACM Symposium on Principles of Distributed Computing, Jul 2021, Salerno, Italy. pp.81-91</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andrea ClementiCOATI, Francesco d'AmoreCOATI, George GiakkoupisWIDE, Emanuele NataleCOATI</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\textit{L+M-24}$: Building a Dataset for Language + Molecules @ ACL 2024</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00791v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Language-molecule models have emerged as an exciting direction for molecular discovery and understanding. However, training these models is challenging due to the scarcity of molecule-language pair datasets. At this point, datasets have been released which are 1) small and scraped from existing databases, 2) large but noisy and constructed by performing entity linking on the scientific literature, and 3) built by converting property prediction datasets to natural language using templates. In this document, we detail the $\textit{L+M-24}$ dataset, which has been created for the Language + Molecules Workshop shared task at ACL 2024. In particular, $\textit{L+M-24}$ is designed to focus on three key benefits of natural language in molecule design: compositionality, functionality, and abstraction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00791v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carl Edwards, Qingyun Wang, Lawrence Zhao, Heng Ji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>History-dependence shapes causal inference of brain-behaviour relationships</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00947v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Behavioural and neural time series are often correlated with the past. This history-dependence may represent a fundamental property of the measured variables, or may arise from how confounding variables change over time. Here we argue that undecidability about the ground-truth of history-dependence is a general computational property of systems that exchange information with its environment, and show that the resulting uncertainty has a direct impact on causal inference. We first argue that uncertainty in the ground truth of history-dependence is an inherent property of open systems that cannot be explicitly falsified. Simple model systems are then simulated to show how different assumptions about history-dependence can lead to spurious correlations and statistical properties of data distributions that are typically unaccounted for. We then consider this problem from an interventionist perspective, showing that interventions can only be guaranteed to remedy the spurious correlation problem when the latent dynamics between the intervention and measured processes are known a priori, and the effect of the intervention is invariant at the chosen level of analysis. We conclude that uncertainty about history-dependence is a fundamental property of the study of neural systems, and in light of this discuss how causality should be assessed in neuroscience.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00947v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brandon Caie, Gunnar Blohm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MetaCompass: Reference-guided Assembly of Metagenomes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01578</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01578v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Metagenomic studies have primarily relied on de novo assembly for reconstructing genes and genomes from microbial mixtures. While reference-guided approaches have been employed in the assembly of single organisms, they have not been used in a metagenomic context. Here we describe the first effective approach for reference-guided metagenomic assembly that can complement and improve upon de novo metagenomic assembly methods for certain organisms. Such approaches will be increasingly useful as more genomes are sequenced and made publicly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01578v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tu Luan, Victoria Cepeda, Bo Liu, Zac Bowen, Ujjwal Ayyangar, Mathieu Almeida, Christopher M. Hill, Sergey Koren, Todd J. Treangen, Adam Porter, Mihai Pop</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advancing Gene Selection in Oncology: A Fusion of Deep Learning and Sparsity for Precision Gene Selection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01927v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Gene selection plays a pivotal role in oncology research for improving outcome prediction accuracy and facilitating cost-effective genomic profiling for cancer patients. This paper introduces two gene selection strategies for deep learning-based survival prediction models. The first strategy uses a sparsity-inducing method while the second one uses importance based gene selection for identifying relevant genes. Our overall approach leverages the power of deep learning to model complex biological data structures, while sparsity-inducing methods ensure the selection process focuses on the most informative genes, minimizing noise and redundancy. Through comprehensive experimentation on diverse genomic and survival datasets, we demonstrate that our strategy not only identifies gene signatures with high predictive power for survival outcomes but can also streamlines the process for low-cost genomic profiling. The implications of this research are profound as it offers a scalable and effective tool for advancing personalized medicine and targeted cancer therapies. By pushing the boundaries of gene selection methodologies, our work contributes significantly to the ongoing efforts in cancer genomics, promising improved diagnostic and prognostic capabilities in clinical settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01927v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>q-bio.TO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akhila Krishna, Ravi Kant Gupta, Pranav Jeevan, Amit Sethi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Double trouble: Predicting new variant counts across two heterogeneous populations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02154</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02154v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Collecting genomics data across multiple heterogeneous populations (e.g., across different cancer types) has the potential to improve our understanding of disease. Despite sequencing advances, though, resources often remain a constraint when gathering data. So it would be useful for experimental design if experimenters with access to a pilot study could predict the number of new variants they might expect to find in a follow-up study: both the number of new variants shared between the populations and the total across the populations. While many authors have developed prediction methods for the single-population case, we show that these predictions can fare poorly across multiple populations that are heterogeneous. We prove that, surprisingly, a natural extension of a state-of-the-art single-population predictor to multiple populations fails for fundamental reasons. We provide the first predictor for the number of new shared variants and new total variants that can handle heterogeneity in multiple populations. We show that our proposed method works well empirically using real cancer and population genetics data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02154v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunyi Shen, Lorenzo Masoero, Joshua G. Schraiber, Tamara Broderick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mol-Instructions: A Large-Scale Biomolecular Instruction Dataset for Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.08018</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.08018v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Large Language Models (LLMs), with their remarkable task-handling capabilities and innovative outputs, have catalyzed significant advancements across a spectrum of fields. However, their proficiency within specialized domains such as biomolecular studies remains limited. To address this challenge, we introduce Mol-Instructions, a comprehensive instruction dataset designed for the biomolecular domain. Mol-Instructions encompasses three key components: molecule-oriented instructions, protein-oriented instructions, and biomolecular text instructions. Each component aims to improve the understanding and prediction capabilities of LLMs concerning biomolecular features and behaviors. Through extensive instruction tuning experiments on LLMs, we demonstrate the effectiveness of Mol-Instructions in enhancing large models' performance in the intricate realm of biomolecular studies, thus fostering progress in the biomolecular research community. Mol-Instructions is publicly available for ongoing research and will undergo regular updates to enhance its applicability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.08018v5</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yin Fang, Xiaozhuan Liang, Ningyu Zhang, Kangwei Liu, Rui Huang, Zhuo Chen, Xiaohui Fan, Huajun Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parameter identifiability in PDE models of fluorescence recovery after photobleaching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.15857</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.15857v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Identifying unique parameters for mathematical models describing biological data can be challenging and often impossible. Parameter identifiability for partial differential equations models in cell biology is especially difficult given that many established \textit{in vivo} measurements of protein dynamics average out the spatial dimensions. Here, we are motivated by recent experiments on the binding dynamics of the RNA-binding protein PTBP3 in RNP granules of frog oocytes based on fluorescence recovery after photobleaching (FRAP) measurements. FRAP is a widely-used experimental technique for probing protein dynamics in living cells, and is often modeled using simple reaction-diffusion models of the protein dynamics. We show that current methods of structural and practical parameter identifiability provide limited insights into identifiability of kinetic parameters for these PDE models and spatially-averaged FRAP data. We thus propose a pipeline for assessing parameter identifiability and for learning parameter combinations based on re-parametrization and profile likelihoods analysis. We show that this method is able to recover parameter combinations for synthetic FRAP datasets and investigate its application to real experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.15857v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11538-024-01266-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Maria-Veronica Ciocanel, Lee Ding, Lucas Mastromatteo, Sarah Reichheld, Sarah Cabral, Kimberly Mowry, Bjorn Sandstede</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prediction of Cellular Identities from Trajectory and Cell Fate Information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.06182</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.06182v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Determining cell identities in imaging sequences is an important yet challenging task. The conventional method for cell identification is via cell tracking, which is complex and can be time-consuming. In this study, we propose an innovative approach to cell identification during early $\textit{C. elegans}$ embryogenesis using machine learning. Cell identification during $\textit{C. elegans}$ embryogenesis would provide insights into neural development with implications for higher organisms including humans. We employed random forest, MLP, and LSTM models, and tested cell classification accuracy on 3D time-lapse confocal datasets spanning the first 4 hours of embryogenesis. By leveraging a small number of spatial-temporal features of individual cells, including cell trajectory and cell fate information, our models achieve an accuracy of over 91%, even with limited data. We also determine the most important feature contributions and can interpret these features in the context of biological knowledge. Our research demonstrates the success of predicting cell identities in time-lapse imaging sequences directly from simple spatio-temporal features.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.06182v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baiyang Dai, Jiamin Yang, Hari Shroff, Patrick La Riviere</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving Protein Optimization with Smoothed Fitness Landscapes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.00494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.00494v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The ability to engineer novel proteins with higher fitness for a desired property would be revolutionary for biotechnology and medicine. Modeling the combinatorially large space of sequences is infeasible; prior methods often constrain optimization to a small mutational radius, but this drastically limits the design space. Instead of heuristics, we propose smoothing the fitness landscape to facilitate protein optimization. First, we formulate protein fitness as a graph signal then use Tikunov regularization to smooth the fitness landscape. We find optimizing in this smoothed landscape leads to improved performance across multiple methods in the GFP and AAV benchmarks. Second, we achieve state-of-the-art results utilizing discrete energy-based models and MCMC in the smoothed landscape. Our method, called Gibbs sampling with Graph-based Smoothing (GGS), demonstrates a unique ability to achieve 2.5 fold fitness improvement (with in-silico evaluation) over its training set. GGS demonstrates potential to optimize proteins in the limited data regime. Code: https://github.com/kirjner/GGS</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.00494v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Kirjner, Jason Yim, Raman Samusevich, Shahar Bracha, Tommi Jaakkola, Regina Barzilay, Ila Fiete</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
