<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.QM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.QM</link>
    <description>q-bio.QM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.QM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 04:00:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Histo-Miner: Deep Learning based Tissue Features Extraction Pipeline from H&amp;E Whole Slide Images of Cutaneous Squamous Cell Carcinoma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.04672v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent advancements in digital pathology have enabled comprehensive analysis of Whole-Slide Images (WSI) from tissue samples, leveraging high-resolution microscopy and computational capabilities. Despite this progress, there is a lack of labeled datasets and open source pipelines specifically tailored for analysis of skin tissue. Here we propose Histo-Miner, a deep learning-based pipeline for analysis of skin WSIs and generate two datasets with labeled nuclei and tumor regions. We develop our pipeline for the analysis of patient samples of cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma (cSCC), a frequent non-melanoma skin cancer. Utilizing the two datasets, comprising 47,392 annotated cell nuclei and 144 tumor-segmented WSIs respectively, both from cSCC patients, Histo-Miner employs convolutional neural networks and vision transformers for nucleus segmentation and classification as well as tumor region segmentation. Performance of trained models positively compares to state of the art with multi-class Panoptic Quality (mPQ) of 0.569 for nucleus segmentation, macro-averaged F1 of 0.832 for nucleus classification and mean Intersection over Union (mIoU) of 0.884 for tumor region segmentation. From these predictions we generate a compact feature vector summarizing tissue morphology and cellular interactions, which can be used for various downstream tasks. Here, we use Histo-Miner to predict cSCC patient response to immunotherapy based on pre-treatment WSIs from 45 patients. Histo-Miner identifies percentages of lymphocytes, the granulocyte to lymphocyte ratio in tumor vicinity and the distances between granulocytes and plasma cells in tumors as predictive features for therapy response. This highlights the applicability of Histo-Miner to clinically relevant scenarios, providing direct interpretation of the classification and insights into the underlying biology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.04672v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Sanc\'er\'e, Carina Lorenz, Doris Helbig, Oana-Diana Persa, Sonja Dengler, Alexander Kreuter, Martim Laimer, Anne Fr\"ohlich, Jennifer Landsberg, Johannes Br\"agelmann, Katarzyna Bozek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scientific Hypothesis Generation by a Large Language Model: Laboratory Validation in Breast Cancer Treatment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12258</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12258v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Large language models LLMs have transformed AI and achieved breakthrough performance on a wide range of tasks In science the most interesting application of LLMs is for hypothesis formation A feature of LLMs which results from their probabilistic structure is that the output text is not necessarily a valid inference from the training text These are termed hallucinations and are harmful in many applications In science some hallucinations may be useful novel hypotheses whose validity may be tested by laboratory experiments Here we experimentally test the application of LLMs as a source of scientific hypotheses using the domain of breast cancer treatment We applied the LLM GPT4 to hypothesize novel synergistic pairs of FDA-approved noncancer drugs that target the MCF7 breast cancer cell line relative to the nontumorigenic breast cell line MCF10A In the first round of laboratory experiments GPT4 succeeded in discovering three drug combinations out of twelve tested with synergy scores above the positive controls GPT4 then generated new combinations based on its initial results this generated three more combinations with positive synergy scores out of four tested We conclude that LLMs are a valuable source of scientific hypotheses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12258v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abbi Abdel-Rehim, Hector Zenil, Oghenejokpeme Orhobor, Marie Fisher, Ross J. Collins, Elizabeth Bourne, Gareth W. Fearnley, Emma Tate, Holly X. Smith, Larisa N. Soldatova, Ross D. King</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NaFM: Pre-training a Foundation Model for Small-Molecule Natural Products</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17656v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Natural products, as metabolites from microorganisms, animals, or plants, exhibit diverse biological activities, making them crucial for drug discovery. Nowadays, existing deep learning methods for natural products research primarily rely on supervised learning approaches designed for specific downstream tasks. However, such one-model-for-a-task paradigm often lacks generalizability and leaves significant room for performance improvement. Additionally, existing molecular characterization methods are not well-suited for the unique tasks associated with natural products. To address these limitations, we have pre-trained a foundation model for natural products based on their unique properties. Our approach employs a novel pretraining strategy that is especially tailored to natural products. By incorporating contrastive learning and masked graph learning objectives, we emphasize evolutional information from molecular scaffolds while capturing side-chain information. Our framework achieves state-of-the-art (SOTA) results in various downstream tasks related to natural product mining and drug discovery. We first compare taxonomy classification with synthesized molecule-focused baselines to demonstrate that current models are inadequate for understanding natural synthesis. Furthermore, by diving into a fine-grained analysis at both the gene and microbial levels, NaFM demonstrates the ability to capture evolutionary information. Eventually, our method is experimented with virtual screening, illustrating informative natural product representations that can lead to more effective identification of potential drug candidates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17656v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuheng Ding, Yusong Wang, Bo Qiang, Jie Yu, Qi Li, Yiran Zhou, Zhenmin Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital Pathway Curation (DPC): a pipeline able to assess the reproducibility, consensus and accuracy in biomedical search retrieval by comparing Gemini, PubMed, and Scientific Reviewers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01259</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01259v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A scientific study begins with a central question, and search engines like PubMed are the first tools for retrieving knowledge and understanding the current state of the art. Large Language Models (LLMs) have been used in research, promising acceleration and deeper results. However, besides caution, they demand rigorous validation. Assessing complex biological relationships remains challenging for SQL-based tools and LLM models. Here, we introduce the Digital Pathway Curation (DPC) pipeline to evaluate the reproducibility and accuracy of the Gemini models against PubMed search and human expert curation. Using two omics experiments, we created a large dataset (Ensemble) based on determining pathway-disease associations. With the Ensemble dataset, we demonstrate that Gemini achieves high run-to-run reproducibility of approximately 99% and inter-model reproducibility of around 75%. Next, we calculate the crowdsourced consensus using a smaller dataset. The CSC allows us to calculate accuracies, and the Gemini multi-model consensus reached a significant accuracy of about 87%. Our findings demonstrate that LLMs are reproducible, reliable, and valuable tools for navigating complex biomedical knowledge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01259v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Flavio Lichtenstein, Daniel Alexandre de Souza, Carlos Eduardo Madureira Trufen, Victor Wendel da Silva Gon\c{c}alves, Juliana de Paula Bernardes, Vinicius Miranda Baroni, Carlos DeOcesano-Pereira, Leonardo Fontoura Ormundo, Fabio Augusto Labre de Souza, Olga Celia Martinez Iba\~nez, Nancy Starobinas, Luciano Rodrigo Lopes, Aparecida Maria Fontes, Sonia Aparecida de Andrade, Ana Marisa Chudzinski-Tavassi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning stochastic dynamics from snapshots through regularized unbalanced optimal transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00844v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Reconstructing dynamics using samples from sparsely time-resolved snapshots is an important problem in both natural sciences and machine learning. Here, we introduce a new deep learning approach for solving regularized unbalanced optimal transport (RUOT) and inferring continuous unbalanced stochastic dynamics from observed snapshots. Based on the RUOT form, our method models these dynamics without requiring prior knowledge of growth and death processes or additional information, allowing them to be learned directly from data. Theoretically, we explore the connections between the RUOT and Schr\"odinger bridge problem and discuss the key challenges and potential solutions. The effectiveness of our method is demonstrated with a synthetic gene regulatory network, high-dimensional Gaussian Mixture Model, and single-cell RNA-seq data from blood development. Compared with other methods, our approach accurately identifies growth and transition patterns, eliminates false transitions, and constructs the Waddington developmental landscape. Our code is available at: https://github.com/zhenyiizhang/DeepRUOT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00844v5</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenyi Zhang, Tiejun Li, Peijie Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
