<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.QM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.QM</link>
    <description>q-bio.QM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.QM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 01:28:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Using PyBioNetFit to Leverage Qualitative and Quantitative Data in Biological Model Parameterization and Uncertainty Quantification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.19420v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Data generated in studies of cellular regulatory systems are often qualitative. For example, measurements of signaling readouts in the presence and absence of mutations may reveal a rank ordering of responses across conditions but not the precise extents of mutation-induced differences. Qualitative data are often ignored by mathematical modelers or are considered in an ad hoc manner, as in the study of Kocieniewski and Lipniacki (2013) [Phys Biol 10: 035006], which was focused on the roles of MEK isoforms in ERK activation. In this earlier study, model parameter values were tuned manually to obtain consistency with a combination of qualitative and quantitative data. This approach is not reproducible, nor does it provide insights into parametric or prediction uncertainties. Here, starting from the same data and the same ordinary differential equation (ODE) model structure, we generate formalized statements of qualitative observations, making these observations more reusable, and we improve the model parameterization procedure by applying a systematic and automated approach enabled by the software package PyBioNetFit. We also demonstrate uncertainty quantification (UQ), which was absent in the original study. Our results show that PyBioNetFit enables qualitative data to be leveraged, together with quantitative data, in parameterization of systems biology models and facilitates UQ. These capabilities are important for reliable estimation of model parameters and model analyses in studies of cellular regulatory systems and reproducibility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.19420v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ely F. Miller, Abhishek Mallela, Jacob Neumann, Yen Ting Lin, William S. Hlavacek, Richard G. Posner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Next Layer: Augmenting Foundation Models with Structure-Preserving and Attention-Guided Learning for Local Patches to Global Context Awareness in Computational Pathology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.19914v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Foundation models have recently emerged as powerful feature extractors in computational pathology, yet they typically omit mechanisms for leveraging the global spatial structure of tissues and the local contextual relationships among diagnostically relevant regions - key elements for understanding the tumor microenvironment. Multiple instance learning (MIL) remains an essential next step following foundation model, designing a framework to aggregate patch-level features into slide-level predictions. We present EAGLE-Net, a structure-preserving, attention-guided MIL architecture designed to augment prediction and interpretability. EAGLE-Net integrates multi-scale absolute spatial encoding to capture global tissue architecture, a top-K neighborhood-aware loss to focus attention on local microenvironments, and background suppression loss to minimize false positives. We benchmarked EAGLE-Net on large pan-cancer datasets, including three cancer types for classification (10,260 slides) and seven cancer types for survival prediction (4,172 slides), using three distinct histology foundation backbones (REMEDIES, Uni-V1, Uni2-h). Across tasks, EAGLE-Net achieved up to 3% higher classification accuracy and the top concordance indices in 6 of 7 cancer types, producing smooth, biologically coherent attention maps that aligned with expert annotations and highlighted invasive fronts, necrosis, and immune infiltration. These results position EAGLE-Net as a generalizable, interpretable framework that complements foundation models, enabling improved biomarker discovery, prognostic modeling, and clinical decision support</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.19914v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Waqas, Rukhmini Bandyopadhyay, Eman Showkatian, Amgad Muneer, Anas Zafar, Frank Rojas Alvarez, Maricel Corredor Marin, Wentao Li, David Jaffray, Cara Haymaker, John Heymach, Natalie I Vokes, Luisa Maren Solis Soto, Jianjun Zhang, Jia Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepAtlas: a tool for effective manifold learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.19479v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Manifold learning builds on the "manifold hypothesis," which posits that data in high-dimensional datasets are drawn from lower-dimensional manifolds. Current tools generate global embeddings of data, rather than the local maps used to define manifolds mathematically. These tools also cannot assess whether the manifold hypothesis holds true for a dataset. Here, we describe DeepAtlas, an algorithm that generates lower-dimensional representations of the data's local neighborhoods, then trains deep neural networks that map between these local embeddings and the original data. Topological distortion is used to determine whether a dataset is drawn from a manifold and, if so, its dimensionality. Application to test datasets indicates that DeepAtlas can successfully learn manifold structures. Interestingly, many real datasets, including single-cell RNA-sequencing, do not conform to the manifold hypothesis. In cases where data is drawn from a manifold, DeepAtlas builds a model that can be used generatively and promises to allow the application of powerful tools from differential geometry to a variety of datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.19479v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Serena Hughes, Timothy Hamilton, Tom Kolokotrones, Eric J. Deeds</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
