<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.space-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.space-ph</link>
    <description>physics.space-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.space-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 19:11:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Exoplanet Magnetic Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15429v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Planetary magnetic fields are important indicators of planetary processes and evolution, from a planet's outer core to its surface (if it possesses one) to its atmosphere and near-space environment. Magnetic fields are most directly measured in situ, and determining whether distant planetary objects possess magnetic fields can be challenging. At present we have no unambiguous measurements of magnetic fields on exoplanets. Nevertheless, it would be surprising if at least some exoplanets did not generate a magnetic field, like many planetary bodies in the solar system. This chapter provides an overview of the current understanding of exoplanetary magnetic fields and their consequences. In the next section we review the current understanding of planetary dynamo generation as it applies to solar system objects and discuss the implications for exoplanetary magnetic field generation. Following this, we describe seven methods for determining the existence and strength of an exoplanetary magnetic field and discuss the near-term prospects for each method. We close by highlighting four main consequences of exoplanetary magnetic fields for a planet and its evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15429v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David A. Brain, Melodie M. Kao, Joseph G. O'Rourke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magneto-inertial range dominated by magnetic helicity in space plasmas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.03524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2204.03524v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magneto-inertial range dominated by magnetic helicity has been studied using results of the numerical simulations, laboratory measurements, solar, solar wind, and the Earth's and planets' magnetosphere observations (spacecraft measurements). The spectral data have been compared with the theoretical results based on the distributed chaos notion in the frames of the Kolmogorov-Iroshnikov phenomenology. The transition from magnetohydrodynamics to kinetics in the electron and Hall magnetohydrodynamics, and in a fully kinetic 3D approach, as well as in the solar wind, solar photosphere, and at the special events (reconnections, Kelvin-Helmholtz instability, isolated flux tube interchanges, etc.) in the magnetosphere of Earth, Saturn, Jupiter, and Mercury has been also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2204.03524v3</guid>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Bershadskii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identification of the weak-to-strong transition in Alfv\'enic turbulence from space plasma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.06709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.06709v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Plasma turbulence is a ubiquitous dynamical process that transfers energy across many spatial and temporal scales in astrophysical and space plasma systems. Although the theory of anisotropic magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) turbulence has successfully described phenomena in nature, its core prediction of an Alfvenic transition from weak to strong MHD turbulence when energy cascades from large to small scales has not been observationally confirmed. Here we report the first observational evidence for the Alfvenic weak-to-strong transition in MHD turbulence in the terrestrial magnetosheath using the four Cluster spacecraft. The observed transition indicates the universal existence of strong turbulence regardless of the initial level of MHD fluctuations. Moreover, the observations demonstrate that the nonlinear interactions of MHD turbulence play a crucial role in the energy cascade, widening the directions of the energy cascade and broadening the fluctuating frequencies. Our work takes a critical step toward understanding the complete picture of turbulence cascade, connecting the weak and strong MHD turbulence systems. It will have broad implications in star formation, energetic particle transport, turbulent dynamo, and solar corona or solar wind heating.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.06709v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41550-024-02249-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Siqi Zhao, Huirong Yan, Terry Z. Liu, Ka Ho Yuen, Huizi Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Radio Emissions from Confirmed Exoplanets Using SKA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14468v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Currently, our understanding of magnetic fields in exoplanets remains limited compared to those within our solar system. Planets with magnetic fields emit radio signals primarily due to the Electron Cyclotron Maser Instability mechanism. In this study, we explore the feasibility of detecting radio emissions from exoplanets using the Square Kilometre Array (SKA) radio telescope. Utilizing data from the NASA Exoplanet Archive, we compile information on confirmed exoplanets and estimate their radio emissions using the RBL model. Our analysis reveals that three exoplanets- Qatar-4 b, TOI-1278 b, and WASP-173 A b- exhibit detectable radio signals suitable for observation with the SKA telescope.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14468v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fatemeh Bagheri, Anshuman Garga, Ramon E. Lopez</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
