<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.space-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.space-ph</link>
    <description>physics.space-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.space-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 02:20:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>BLADE: An Automated Framework for Classifying Light Curves from the Center for Near-Earth Object Studies (CNEOS) Fireball Database</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16099v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fireballs (bolides) are high-energy luminous phenomena produced when meteoroids and small asteroids enter Earth's atmosphere at hypersonic speeds, often resulting in fragmentation or complete disintegration accompanied by significant energy release. The resulting bolide light curves capture temporal brightness variations as these objects traverse increasingly dense atmospheric layers, providing essential information on meteoroid entry dynamics, fragmentation behavior, and atmospheric energy deposition processes. The Center for Near-Earth Object Studies' (CNEOS) continuously expanding fireball database offers a globally comprehensive archive of bolide events, including light curves and associated metadata. Events associated with infrasound detections allow direct correlations between acoustic signatures and light-curve features, therefore enabling detailed analyses of fragmentation dynamics and energy deposition. Here, we introduce BLADE (Bolide Light-curve Analysis and Discrimination Explorer), a robust and high-fidelity framework specifically designed to analyze bolide light curves for objects detected from space. BLADE incorporates a processing pipeline integrating Savitzky-Golay filtering, prominence-based peak detection, and gradient analysis, enabling systematic identification and classification of fragmentation events and their associated energy release characteristics. Preliminary results demonstrate that BLADE reliably distinguishes distinct bolide behaviors, providing an objective, scalable methodology for characterization and analysis of large bolide light curve datasets. This foundational work establishes a novel pathway for advanced bolide research, with promising applications in planetary defense and global atmospheric monitoring.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16099v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elizabeth A. Silber, Vedant Sawal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy conversion and scaling analysis of relativistic magnetic reconnection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16227</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16227v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Relativistic magnetic reconnection is a key process for accelerating charged particles and producing high-energy radiation. We study this process using relativistic resistive magnetohydrodynamics simulations. Starting with Harris sheet configuration, we study time evolution of reconnection rate and the Alfven four Mach number for outflow. These measurements validate the Sweet-Parker scaling, consistent with previous studies. To study energy conversion processes, we calculate Ohmic dissipation, crucial for understanding how energy is converted between plasma and electromagnetic fields. Decomposing electric field components relative to velocity field, we find that energy conversion is initially dominated by the resistive electric field, but convective electric fields take over as reconnection progresses. Plasma primarily gains energy within the current sheet and near the separatrix. We perform a scan of magnetization for mildly relativistic plasma to examine scaling laws previously derived for non-relativistic inflow. We find the inflow is slower than predicted, due to conversion of magnetic energy mostly into thermal energy, causing strong compressibility. We calculate and verify the scaling of the compressibility factor, providing a more accurate representation of inflow dynamics. We analyze the impact of a guide field on reconnection and energy partition, finding that a stronger guide field reduces the reconnection rate but has minimal effect on the relative distribution of kinetic, magnetic, and thermal energy. Addition of rotating guide field and variations in initial pressure and density have little effect on the energy composition of the outflow, with thermal energy consistently dominating at nearly 90%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16227v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harihar Pradhan, Kirit D Makwana, Bart Ripperda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frequency Differences between Clocks on the Earth and the Moon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16377v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Based on general relativity, clock comparisons enable the determination of the gravity potential relative to a stable reference. Lunar surface clocks, owing to the Moon's low-noise conditions, high orbital stability, and broad Earth visibility, are promising reference clocks for global-scale comparisons between terrestrial clocks. Meanwhile, the need for an independent lunar time system-driven by future lunar navigation-requires maintaining links to terrestrial standards. This Letter simulates fractional frequency differences between Earth (E) and Moon (L) clocks by modeling three key time transformations: proper-to-coordinate time for E-clocks and for L-clocks (both linked to the local gravity potential), and the coordinate time relation between Earth and Moon. Signal propagation effects are not addressed. Gravity potential differences impact observations at the 10^-10 level, and the coordinate time ratio at 10^-11. Contributions from static, tidal, and non-tidal potentials, body self-rotation, and different celestial bodies are evaluated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16377v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingyue Zhang, J\"urgen M\"uller, Sergei M. Kopeikin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmology on the Generalized Proca Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03483</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.03483v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This thesis employs the dynamical systems approach to explore two cosmological models: an anisotropic dark energy scenario in a Bianchi-I background and the Generalized SU(2) Proca (GSU2P) theory in a flat FLRW background. In the first case, a numerical framework is developed to analyze the interaction between a scalar tachyon field and a vector field, identifying parameter regions that allow anisotropic accelerated attractors. The second case examines the viability of GSU2P as a driver of inflation and late-time acceleration. Our analysis reveals fundamental limitations, including the absence of stable attractors and smooth cosmological transitions, ultimately ruling out the model as a complete description of the Universe's expansion. This work highlights the effectiveness of dynamical systems techniques in assessing alternative cosmological scenarios and underscores the need for refined theoretical frameworks aligned with observational constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.03483v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Santiago Garc\'ia-Serna</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
