<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.space-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.space-ph</link>
    <description>physics.space-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.space-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 02:26:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Occurrence of Non-Stationarity at Earth's Quasi-Perpendicular Bow Shock</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13817</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13817v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Collisionless shocks can exhibit non-stationary behavior even under steady upstream conditions, forming a complex transition region. Ion phase-space holes, linked to shock self-reformation and surface ripples, are a signature of this non-stationarity. We statistically analyze their occurrence using 521 crossings of Earth's quasi-perpendicular bow shock. Phase-space holes appear in 65% of cases, though the actual rate may be higher as the holes may not be resolved during fast shock crossings. The occurrence rate peaks at 70% for shocks with Alfv\'en Mach numbers $M_A&gt;7$. These findings suggest that Earth's quasi-perpendicular bow shock is predominantly non-stationary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13817v1</guid>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ajay Lotekar, Yuri V. Khotyaintsev, Daniel B. Graham, Andrew Dimmock, Andreas Johlander, Ahmad Lalti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A novel scheme for measuring the growth of Alfven wave parametric decay instability using counter-propagating waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13590v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The parametric decay instability (PDI) of Alfven waves -- where a pump Alfven wave decays into a backward-propagating child Alfven wave and a forward ion acoustic wave -- is a fundamental nonlinear wave-wave interaction and holds significant implications for space and laboratory plasmas. However, to date there has been no direct experimental measurement of PDI. Here, we propose a novel and experimentally viable scheme to quantify the growth of Alfven wave PDI on a linear device using a large pump Alfven wave and a small counter-propagating seed Alfven wave, with the seed wave frequency tuned to match the backward Alfven wave generated by standard PDI. Using hybrid simulations, we show that energy transfer from the pump to the seed reduces the latter's spatial damping. By comparing seed wave amplitudes with and without the pump wave, this damping reduction can be used as a direct and reliable proxy for PDI growth. The method is validated in our simulations across a range of plasma and wave parameters and agrees well with theoretical predictions. Notably, the scheme exhibits no threshold for PDI excitation and is, in principle, readily implementable under current laboratory conditions. This scheme is a critical step toward solving the challenge of experimentally accessing Alfven wave PDI and provides an elegant method that may be used to validate fundamental theories of parametric instabilities in controlled laboratory settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13590v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Feiyu Li, Seth Dorfman, Xiangrong Fu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling HMI observables for the study of solar oscillations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13756v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Context: Helioseismology aims to infer the properties of the solar interior by analyzing observations of acoustic oscillations. The interpretation of the helioseismic data is however complicated by the non-trivial relationship between helioseismic observables and the physical perturbations associated with acoustic modes, as well as by various instrumental effects. Aims: We aim to improve our understanding of the signature of acoustic modes measured in the Helioseismic and Magnetic Imager (HMI) continuum intensity and Doppler velocity observables by accounting for radiative transfer, solar background rotation, and spacecraft velocity. Methods: We start with a background model atmosphere that accurately reproduces solar limb darkening and the Fe I 6173{\AA} spectral line profile. We employ first-order perturbation theory to model the effect of acoustic oscillations on inferred intensity and velocity. By solving the radiative transfer equation in the atmosphere, we synthesize the spectral line, convolve it with the six HMI spectral windows, and deduce continuum intensity (hmi.Ic_45s) and Doppler velocity (hmi.V_45s) according to the HMI algorithm. Results: We analytically derive the relationship between mode displacement in the atmosphere and the HMI observables, and show that both intensity and velocity deviate significantly from simple approximations. Specifically, the continuum intensity does not simply reflect the true continuum value, while the line-of-sight velocity does not correspond to a straightforward projection of the velocity at a fixed height in the atmosphere. Our results indicate that these deviations are substantial, with amplitudes of approximately 10% and phase shifts of around 10 degrees across the detector for both observables. Moreover, these effects are highly dependent on the acoustic mode under consideration and the position on the solar disk.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13756v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Fournier, N. M. Kostogryz, L. Gizon, J. Schou, V. Witzke, A. I. Shapiro, I. Milic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alfv\'en wave propagation, reflection and trapping in the solar wind</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13809v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Alfv\'en waves are known to be important carriers of magnetic energy that could play a role in coronal heating and/or solar wind acceleration. As these waves are efficient energy carriers, how they are dissipated still remains one of the key challenges. Using a series of 1.5-D magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) simulations, we explore wave energy trapping associated with field-aligned density enhancements. We examine the parameters which govern the wave reflection and trapping. The goal of our simulations is to find optimal conditions for wave trapping, which would ultimately promote the energisation of the solar atmosphere. In agreement with previous studies, we find that maximum wave reflections happen only for a narrow range of density enhancement widths, namely when it is comparable to the Alfv\'en wave wavelength. In our paper, we explain this scale-selectivity using a semi-analytical model that demonstrates the importance of wave interference effects. As expected, we find that spatially extended regions of density inhomogeneities favour enhanced wave reflection and trapping. However, wave interference causes saturation of the reflected energy for very extended regions of varying density.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13809v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/staf1189</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Anmol Kumar, Thomas A. Howson, Paolo Pagano, Ineke De Moortel</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
