<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.space-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.space-ph</link>
    <description>physics.space-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.space-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 04:03:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Heat-flux Instabilities of Regularized Kappa Distributed Strahl Electrons Resolved with ALPS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03084</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03084v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The fluid behavior of the solar wind is affected by the heat flux carried by the suprathermal electron populations, especially the electron strahl (or beam) that propagates along the magnetic field. In turn, the electron strahl cannot be stable, and in the absence of collisions, its properties are regulated mainly by self-generated instabilities. This paper approaches the description of these heat-flux instabilities in a novel manner using regularized Kappa distributions (RKDs) to characterize the electron strahl. RKDs conform to the velocity distributions with suprathermal tails observed in situ, and at the same time allow for consistent macromodeling, based on their singularity-free moments. In contrast, the complexity of RKD models makes the analytical kinetic formalism complicated and still inaccessible, and therefore, here heat-flux instabilities are resolved using the advanced solver ALPS. Two primary types of instabilities emerge depending on plasma conditions: the whistler and firehose heat-flux instabilities. The solver is successfully tested for the first time for such instabilities by comparison with previous results for standard distributions, such as Maxwellian and Kappa. Moreover, the new RKD results show that idealized Maxwellian models can overrate or underestimate the effects of these instabilities, and also show differences from those obtained for the standard Kappa, which, for instance, underestimate the firehose heat-flux growth rates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03084v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ade0c0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The Astrophysical Journal, 987:110, 2025 July 10</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Dustin L. Schr\"oder, Marian Lazar, Rodrigo A. L\'opez, Horst Fichtner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Background in Low Earth Orbiting Cherenkov Detectors, and Mitigation Strategies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03838v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cherenkov detectors have been used in space missions for many decades, and for a variety of purposes, including for example, for Galactic Cosmic Ray (GCR) and Solar Energetic Particle (SEP) measurements. Cherenkov detectors are sensitive to many types of particles that are present in the environment of space, including gamma rays, trapped particles and cosmic particles, and each particle component acts as essentially a background when trying to view another specific particle component. In this research, GRAS/Geant4 simulations were performed to characterise the count rates that a simple Cherenkov detector design would experience in a low Earth orbit, and we find that Cherenkov count rates due to most particle components vary significantly depending on many different factors, including the location in the orbit, the date of the orbit, whether or not the detector is within the van Allen belts, and whether or not a solar particle event is occurring. We find that a small Cherenkov detector is readily able to gather detailed data on both trapped particles and spectral information during Ground-Level Enhancements. We also investigate the use of coincidence as a method to remove count rates due to trapped particles and delta electrons, finding that this method is generally very effective for resolving count rates due to GLEs amongst intense trapped particle environments, but that some Cherenkov count rates due to trapped particles are still observed in the simulated south Atlantic anomaly region.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03838v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher S. W. Davis, Fan Lei, Keith Ryden, Clive Dyer, Giovanni Santin, Piers Jiggens, Melanie Heil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inertial-range Turbulence Anisotropy of the Young Solar Wind from Different Source Regions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04288v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the wavevector and variance anisotropies in the inertial range of the young solar wind observed by the Parker Solar Probe (PSP). Using the first 19 encounters of PSP measurements, we identify the young solar wind from different source regions: coronal hole (CH) interiors, streamers, and low Mach-number boundary layers (LMBLs), i.e., the peripheral region inside CHs. We assess the wavevector anisotropy with the 2D and slab turbulence model for the CH wind and the streamer wind, and the nearly incompressible (NI) MHD turbulence model for the LMBL wind where Taylor's hypothesis becomes questionable. Unlike the $\sim80\%$ 2D contribution typically reported at 1 au, our results show that only $26\%$ of the inertial range energy is associated with 2D fluctuations in the CH wind, and this fraction increases to $45\%$ in the streamer wind. As a representation of the LMBL wind, similarly, the oblique sub-Alfv\'enic intervals and the near-subsonic intervals are characterized by the dominance of slab fluctuations. All the results suggest that slab fluctuations are more abundant in the young solar wind below 0.3 au than at 1 au. Furthermore, we find a dependence of the variance anisotropy in the inertial range on proton plasma beta $\beta_p$. The variance anisotropy is the strongest in the LMBL wind with the lowest $\beta_p$, and the weakest in the streamer wind with the highest $\beta_p$. This contrast can be interpreted as the remnant of fluctuations from the coronal sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04288v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenshuai Cheng, Ming Xiong, Yiming Jiao, Hao Ran, Liping Yang, Huidong Hu, Rui Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
