<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.space-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.space-ph</link>
    <description>physics.space-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.space-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 05:01:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Angular dependence of third-order law in anisotropic MHD turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.16610v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In solar wind turbulence, the energy transfer/dissipation rate is typically estimated using MHD third-order structure functions calculated using spacecraft observations. However, the inherent anisotropy of solar wind turbulence leads to significant variations in structure functions along different observational directions, thereby affecting the accuracy of energy-dissipation rate estimation. An unresolved issue is how to optimise the selection of observation angles under limited directional sampling to improve estimation precision. We conduct a series of MHD turbulence simulations with different mean magnetic field strengths, $ B_0 $. Our analysis of the third-order structure functions reveals that the global energy dissipation rate estimated around a polar angle of $ \theta = 60^\circ$ agrees reasonably with the exact one for $ 0 \le B_0/b_{rms} \le 5 $, where $b_{rms}$ denotes the root-mean-square magnetic field fluctuation. The speciality of $60^\circ$ polar angle can be understood by the Mean Value Theorem of Integrals, since the spherical integral of the polar-angle component ($\widetilde{T_\theta}$) of the divergence of Yaglom flux is zero, and $\widetilde{T_\theta}$ changes sign around 60$^\circ$. Existing theory on the energy flux vector as a function of the polar angle is assessed, and supports the speciality of $60^\circ$ polar angle. The angular dependence of the third-order structure functions is further assessed with virtual spacecraft data analysis. The present results can be applied to measure the turbulent dissipation rates of energy in the solar wind, which are of potential importance to other areas in which turbulence takes place, such as laboratory plasmas and astrophysics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.16610v1</guid>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bin Jiang, Zhuoran Gao, Yan Yang, Francesco Pecora, Kai Gao, Cheng Li, Sean Oughton, William Matthaeus, Minping Wan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct calculation of steady-state hydrodynamic solar wind solutions with newtonian viscosity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.16028v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Steady-state solutions to the Navier-Stokes equations are known to admit solutions that are singular at the sonic point. Consequently, inviscid solar wind models require special treatment of the solution near the sonic points, and this has proven to be a significant impediment to efficient modeling of the solar wind. In this paper we revisit the governing hydrodynamic equations for the expanding solar wind, with the inclusion of the classical (Newtonian) viscous stress , and we show how this inclusion eliminates the singularities that emerge from the inviscid equations. This result has been previously reported and used to generate solar wind profiles from initial conditions in the asymptotic limit; however, those studies did not include realistic treatments of the inner corona, and generally rejected the prospect of extrapolating solutions outward from the Sun into the heliosphere. Here, we expand this method to include external heating and optically thin radiative losses and show that solutions can be computed from initial conditions near the solar surface, thereby capturing the entire range of scales from below the transition region to the outer heliosphere in a single solution. Our approach is to cast the steady-state Navier-Stokes equations as a system of five coupled, ordinary differential equations (ODEs), which we solve using conventional methods, without any special treatment of the governing equations in the vicinity of the sonic point. The representative solutions that we present here demonstrate the utility and efficiency of this extrapolation method, which is considerably more realistic than commonly used analytical or empirical models. This method provides a direct approach to generating accurate solar wind profiles subject to observationally motivated initial conditions near the solar surface, at a fraction of the computational cost of comparable relaxation-based models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.16028v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202555327</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Roger B. Scott, Stephen J. Bradshaw, Mark G. Linton, Chris Lowder, Leonard Strachan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-Informed Neural Networks for Modeling the Martian Induced Magnetosphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.16175v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Understanding the magnetic field environment around Mars and its response to upstream solar wind conditions provide key insights into the processes driving atmospheric ion escape. To date, global models of Martian induced magnetosphere have been exclusively physics-based, relying on computationally intensive simulations. For the first time, we develop a data-driven model of the Martian induced magnetospheric magnetic field using Physics-Informed Neural Network (PINN) combined with MAVEN observations and physical laws. Trained under varying solar wind conditions, including B_IMF, P_SW, and {\theta}_cone, the data-driven model accurately reconstructs the three-dimensional magnetic field configuration and its variability in response to upstream solar wind drivers. Based on the PINN results, we identify key dependencies of magnetic field configuration on solar wind parameters, including the hemispheric asymmetries of the draped field line strength in the Mars-Solar-Electric coordinates. These findings demonstrate the capability of PINNs to reconstruct complex magnetic field structures in the Martian induced magnetosphere, thereby offering a promising tool for advancing studies of solar wind-Mars interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.16175v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiawei Gao, Chuanfei Dong, Chi Zhang, Yilan Qin, Simin Shekarpaz, Xinmin Li, Liang Wang, Hongyang Zhou, Abigail Tadlock</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hypervelocity Impact Debris Cloud Trajectory-Planning based on Additive Manufactured Lattice Structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16611</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.16611v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Space debris and micrometeoroid (MMOD) impacts pose a serious threat to the safe operation of spacecraft. However, traditional protective structures typically suffer from limitations such as excessive thickness and inadequate load-bearing capacity. Guided by the design concepts of debris-cloud deflection and hierarchical energy dissipation, this study proposes a trajectory-planning lattice protective structure. First, the lattice parameters and geometry were designed according to the functional relationship between the incident angle and the transmitted/ricochet trajectory angles. Subsequently, multi-angle hypervelocity impact experiments were carried out to evaluate the proposed lattice protection structure. In combination with post-impact CT three-dimensional reconstruction and smoothed particle hydrodynamics (SPH) numerical simulations, the protective mechanisms of the lattice structure were systematically characterized and clarified. The results demonstrate that, for three oblique incidence conditions, the lattice structure remained intact and significantly deflected the debris-cloud momentum direction while effectively dissipating its kinetic energy. The angled plates with gradient designs enabled continuous changes in the momentum direction and stepwise kinetic energy dissipation through multiple cycles of debrisation, dispersion, and trajectory deflection. This research presents a novel, engineering-ready approach for spacecraft MMOD protection and validates the potential of trajectory-planning lattice structures for hypervelocity impact defense.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.16611v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bilin Zheng, Xiao Kang, Xiaoyu Zhang, Hao Zhou, Mengchuan Xu, Chang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
