<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.space-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.space-ph</link>
    <description>physics.space-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.space-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 04:30:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Conversion Layer Controls the Evolution of Magnetic Deflections Near the Alfven Surface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.22321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.22321v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We examine the statistics of Alfvenic deflections in both sub-Alfvenic and super-Alfvenic solar wind with particular focus on a common parameter that underlies the definition of switchbacks: the magnetic deflection angle. Our findings are in general agreement with earlier studies that suggest magnetic deflection angles &gt; 90 degrees are very unlikely to occur in sub-Alfvenic regimes. We find that their upper limit exhibits an identifiable trend with the Alfven Mach number Ma, suggesting that gradual steepening of Alfvenic deflections with increasing Ma is a plausible mechanism controlling deflection angles in the young solar wind. Further analysis reveals that large velocity fluctuations tend to be important in the largest sub-Alfvenic magnetic deflections with increasing contributions from the parallel component very close to Ma = 1, while virtually no magnetic deflections in the super-Alfvenic regime exhibit such large velocity perturbations. We also determine the local ratio of radial Poynting flux SR to kinetic energy flux KR and find that large sub-Alfvenic deflection angles tend to be dominated by SR, while super-Alfvenic deflections are eventually dominated by the KR associated with the radial solar wind flow. Our results show that within the vicinity of the Alfven surface (where Ma = 1), there is a critical region of parameter space within which velocity deflections approach the Alfven velocity and KR/SR is close to unity. We refer to this region (where | log10(Ma)| &lt; 0.2) as the conversion layer. The conversion layer may play a significant role in the evolution of magnetic defections by providing the medium for converting magnetic energy to particle energy and likely driving the formation of magnetic switchbacks in super-Alfvenic solar wind.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.22321v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dominic Payne, Mojtaba Akhavan-Tafti, Joshua Goodwill, Samuel Badman, Riddhi Bandyopadhyay, Subash Adhikari, William Matthaeus, Gary Zank, Chen Shi, Michael Stevens, Roberto Livi, Yeimy Rivera, Kristoff Paulson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ground Level Enhancement (GLE#77) in the gamma-ray component: First observation from Arctic and Antarctic stations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.22807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.22807v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This article presents the observations of the extreme ground-level enhancement (GLE #77) of Solar Cycle 25 that occurred on 11 November 2025, using ground-based NaI(Tl) gamma-ray detectors deployed at Arctic and Antarctic stations, together with neutron monitor data and particle measurements from the GOES-18 satellite. The event was associated with an intense X-class solar flare and a strong solar energetic proton event. This paper reports the first ground-based detection of a GLE using gamma-ray detectors operating simultaneously in both polar regions, which are concurrent with increases in neutron monitor counts. Thus highlights the capability of polar gamma-ray detectors to complement traditional neutron monitor observations during extreme solar proton events. A detailed analysis revealed distinct prompt and delayed responses during the event evolution. Interestingly, the signature of the prompt peak of GLE#77 (at 10:38 UT) was observed up to high-rigidity neutron monitors (low latitudes). However, the delayed peak (at 13:08 UT) was not seen at the stations with rigidity &gt; 6 GV. The timing of the prompt and delayed peaks coincided with the proton flux peaks observed by the GOES-18 satellite at energies &gt; 150 MeV and 12-99 MeV, respectively. It is observed that the GLE amplitude has a strong dependence on geomagnetic cutoff rigidity and has a weak solar zenith angle dependence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.22807v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pranali Thakur, Geeta Vichare, Selvaraj Chelliah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparing Simulated and Observed Particle Energy Distributions through Magnetic Reconnection in Earth's Magnetotail</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07621v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magnetic reconnection is an explosive process that accelerates particles to high energies in Earth's magnetosphere, offering a unique natural laboratory to study this phenomenon. This study investigates how well data-driven fully kinetic simulations can reproduce the ion and electron energy distributions observed during a reconnection event by the Magnetospheric Multiscale (MMS) mission.We performed fully kinetic 2D simulations initialized with plasma parameters derived from the MMS event and compared the resulting ion and electron energy distributions with observations. Key numerical and physical parameters were systematically varied to assess their influence on the resulting particle spectra. The simulations capture the overall shape and evolution of nonthermal energy distributions for both species, but generally underestimate the very high-energy tail of the electron spectrum. Variations in numerical parameters have negligible effects on the resulting spectra, while the initial upstream temperatures instead play a more pronounced role in reproducing the observed distributions.We present a novel analysis of data-driven fully kinetic simulations of MR, showing that key aspects of particle acceleration can be captured, while also highlighting the limitations of 2D simulations and the need for more realistic (e.g., 3D) setups to reproduce the observed particle energization accurately.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07621v2</guid>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202558575</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Nadja Reisinger, Fabio Bacchini</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
