<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.gen-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.gen-ph</link>
    <description>physics.gen-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.gen-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 04:05:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Dual Affine Connections, Legendre Transforms, and Black Hole Thermodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.08698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.08698v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Geometrical methods have become increasingly important in understanding both thermodynamics and information theory. In particular, dual affine (Hessian) geometry offers a powerful unification of concepts by recasting Legendre transformations as coordinate changes on a manifold endowed with a strictly convex potential. This viewpoint illuminates the mathematical basis of key thermodynamic relations, such as the mappings between internal energy U(S,V) and other potentials like Helmholtz or Gibbs free energies, and connects these ideas to the broader framework of information geometry, where dual coordinate systems naturally arise.
  In this paper, we present a concise treatment of how dual affine connections $(\nabla, \nabla^*)$ emerge from a single convex potential and are directly related through Legendre transforms. This emphasizes their physical significance and the geometric interpretation of entropy maximization. We then explore an energy gap integral constructed from the cubic form of the Hessian metric that measures how far a system deviates from the Levi Civita connection a self dual connection, and discuss how quantum-scale effects may render this gap infinite below the Planck length. Finally, we apply these concepts to black hole thermodynamics, showing how quantum or measurement uncertainties in (T,S,F,U) can be incorporated into the Hessian framework and interpreted via Hawking radiation in a stable black hole scenario. This unifying perspective underscores the natural extension from classical Riemannian geometry to dual-affine thermodynamics, with potential ramifications for quantum gravity and advanced thermodynamic modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.08698v1</guid>
      <category>physics.gen-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shoshauna Gauvin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear Einstein-Power-Yang-Mills AdS Black Holes: From Quantum Tunneling to Aschenbach Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.08713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.08713v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study investigates the thermodynamic and quantum properties of Einstein-Power-Yang-Mills (EPYM) black holes in an Anti-de Sitter background, focusing on the effects of the nonlinear Yang-Mills charge parameter $\gamma$. We derive the metric function, analyze Hawking radiation through boson tunneling, and calculate thermodynamic properties including temperature and phase transitions. The quantum tunneling of $W^+$ bosons is examined using the WKB approximation and Hamilton-Jacobi formalism, revealing how nonlinearity modifies the radiation spectrum. We compute the effective potential governing photon orbits and null geodesics, demonstrating significant alterations in light behavior in strong gravitational fields. Additionally, we explore the Aschenbach effect, showing that this phenomenon, which is typically associated with rotating black holes, can emerge in spherically symmetric EPYM spacetimes because of non-linear field interactions. Our results may yield observational markers that can be identified with instruments such as the Event Horizon Telescope and upcoming gravitational wave detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.08713v1</guid>
      <category>physics.gen-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erdem Sucu, \.Izzet Sakall{\i}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electric? Then it is geometric</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.08718</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.08718v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we revisit Kaluza-Klein theory from the perspective of the classification of elementary particles based on the coadjoint orbit method. We propose a symmetry group for which the electric charge is invariant and, on this basis, a cosmological scenario in which the three former spatial dimensions inflate quickly while the fifth one shrinks, leading to a 4D era where the particles correspond to the coadjoint orbits of this group. By this mechanism, the elementary particles can acquire electric charge as a by-product of the 4 + 1 symmetry breaking of the Universe. By pullback over the space-time, we construct the non-Riemannian connection corresponding to this symmetry group, allowing to recover conservation of the charge and the equation of motion with the Lorentz force. On this ground, we develop a five dimensional extension of the variational relativity allowing to deduce in the classical limit Maxwell's equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.08718v1</guid>
      <category>physics.gen-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G\'ery de Saxc\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
