<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.gen-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.gen-ph</link>
    <description>physics.gen-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.gen-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 04:00:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Simple and accurate complete elliptic integrals for the full range of modulus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.17159v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Complete elliptic integral of the first and second kind, K(k) and E(k), appear in multitudes of physics and engineering applications. Because there is no known closed-form, the exact values have to be computed numerically. Here, approximations for the integrals are proposed based on their asymptotic behaviors. An inverse of K is also presented. As a result, the proposed K(k) and E(k) reproduce the exact analytical forms both in the zero and asymptotic limits, while in the mid-range of modulus maintain average error of 0.06% and 0.01% respectively. The key finding is the ability to compute the integrals with exceptional accuracy on both limits of elliptical conditions. The accuracy of 1 in 1,000 should be sufficient for practical or prototyping engineering and architecture designs. The simplicity should facilitate discussions of advanced physics topics in introductory physics classes, and allow broader collaborations among researchers from other fields of expertise. For example, phase space of energy-conserving nonlinear pendulum using all elementary functions is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.17159v1</guid>
      <category>physics.gen-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Teepanis Chachiyo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the entropy of the massive conformal gravity universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17171</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.17171v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We find that the total entropy of the massive conformal gravity universe is an increasing function of time, and therefore the cosmological model of the theory passes the generalized second law of thermodynamics test.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.17171v1</guid>
      <category>physics.gen-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Modern Physics Letters A Vol. 40, No. 19n20, 2530005 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>F. F. Faria</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Hybrid Euclidean-Lorentzian Universe: Stability Considerations and the Point of Transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06635v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The limited velocity implied by Lorentzian signature, prevents the universe to reach thermodynamic equilibrium implied by the CMB. Rapid expansion can occur by following Hawking and assuming a primordial Euclidean metric, in which case velocity is not limited and thermalization and rapid expansion are derived without the need to assume an ad-hoc field. Moreover, a mathematical model was given regarding the development of current Lorentzian spacetime from the early Euclidean space-time in which problems such as initial singularity and the homogeneity of the CMB are solved. However, stability properties of the hybrid model were not discussed yet, nor was a mathematical criterion for the transition between the Euclidean and Lorentzian era's defined, those will be discussed here to some extent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06635v3</guid>
      <category>physics.gen-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1142/S0219887824400346</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Journal of Geometric Methods in Modern Physics, Vol. 21, No. 10, 2440034, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Asher Yahalom</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A DESI universe with time-dependent dark energy is 119 Myr younger than a LambdaCDM universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.06290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.06290v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: On the basis of their redshift and Lyman-alpha measurements, the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) collaboration suggest that dark energy varies with the scale factor $a$ as $ \rho_{de}(a)={} \, a^{-3(1 + w_0 + w_a)} e^{-3 w_a (1-a)}\rho_{de,0} $ in which $w_0 = - 0.752 \pm 0.057$ and $w_a ={} - 0.86^{+0.23}_{-0.20} $. Such a DESI universe is 119 Myr younger than the LambdaCDM universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.06290v3</guid>
      <category>physics.gen-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Cahill</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
