<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.gen-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.gen-ph</link>
    <description>physics.gen-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.gen-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 05:01:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Overlooked local interactions in the EPR Paradox</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.04230v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Five objections to the conventional arguments underlying the EPR \enquote{paradox} are presented. It is shown that for entangled subsystems the formation of the post-measurement state necessarily involves local interactions affecting both subsystems, contradicting standard EPR assumptions. Correlations between measurements by remote apparatuses are shown to be consistent with relativistic principles. For entangled eigenstates of total momentum or total spin, eliminating redundant degrees of freedom in analogy with generalized Hamiltonian dynamics prevents the emergence of the EPR \enquote{paradox}. A different paradox is identified for a quantum charged particle, whose electric field is shown to be determined by potential configurations encoded in the quantum state rather than by actual measurement events.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.04230v1</guid>
      <category>physics.gen-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. O. Chudak, O. S. Potiienko, I. V. Sharph, V. P. Smolyar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superposition of states in quantum theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04248</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.04248v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The most general mathematical law for summing bounded quantities is not the arithmetic law, but a composition law of which the summation law for velocities in special relativity is only one particular example. We believe that this composition law, should also be used in quantum theory. We present it with a few examples, we discuss its physical meaning and we show how it can be useful in quantum theory. We show in particular that its use may open the way for a new interpretation of the use of probabilities in quantum theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.04248v1</guid>
      <category>physics.gen-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. -M. Vigoureux</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signs of Possible High-Temperature Superconductivity in Graphite Intercalated with Lithium-Based Alloys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03256</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03256v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report experimental results indicating possible high-temperature superconductivity in graphite intercalation compounds synthesized with lithium-based alloys. Temperature-dependent measurements of magnetization, trapped magnetic flux, and electrical resistance reveal transitions with critical temperatures (Tc) in the range of 240-350 K at ambient pressure, depending on intercalation metals and conditions. The highest Tc values and largest high-Tc fractions (&lt; 0.1 %) were observed in graphite samples intercalated with ternary Sr-Ca-Li alloy. Our results and analyses suggest that the observed transitions originate from local superconductivity rather than intrinsic magnetic properties of the intercalated graphite, which may be an alternative explanation. Accordingly, we propose and intend to pursue further investigations to test and confirm the nature of the observed high-Tc transitions, and to obtain larger high-Tc fractions by optimizing the intercalation materials and methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03256v2</guid>
      <category>physics.gen-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vadim Ksenofontov, Vasily S. Minkov, Alexander P. Drozdov, Ulrich P\"oschl, Mikhail I. Eremets</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new understanding of Einstein-Rosen bridges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.20691v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The formulation of quantum field theory in Minkowski spacetime, which emerges from the unification of special relativity and quantum mechanics, is based on treating time as a parameter, assuming a fixed arrow of time, and requiring that field operators commute for spacelike distances. This procedure is questioned here in the context of quantum field theory in curved spacetime (QFTCS). In 1935, Einstein and Rosen (ER), in their seminal paper (Einstein and Rosen 1935 Phys. Rev. 48 73-77), proposed that "a particle in the physical Universe has to be described by mathematical bridges connecting two sheets of spacetime" which involved two arrows of time. Recently proposed direct-sum quantum theory reconciles this ER's vision by introducing geometric superselection sectors associated with the regions of spacetime related by discrete transformations. We further establish that the quantum effects at gravitational horizons involve the physics of quantum inverted harmonic oscillators that have phase space horizons. This new understanding of the ER bridges is not related to classical wormholes, it addresses the original ER puzzle and promises a unitary description of QFTCS, along with observer complementarity. Furthermore, we present compelling evidence for our new understanding of ER bridges in the form of large-scale parity asymmetric features in the cosmic microwave background, which is statistically 650 times stronger than the standard scale-invariant power spectrum from the typical understanding of inflationary quantum fluctuations when compared with the posterior probabilities associated with the model given the data. We finally discuss the implications of this new understanding in combining gravity and quantum mechanics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.20691v2</guid>
      <category>physics.gen-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6382/ae3044</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Class. Quantum Grav. (2026) 43 015023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Enrique Gazta\~naga, K. Sravan Kumar, Jo\~ao Marto</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
