<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.CB updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.CB</link>
    <description>q-bio.CB updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.CB" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 02:01:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Adoptive Cell Therapy in Bladder Cancer from Sparse Biological Data using PINNs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13431</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13431v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Physics-informed neural networks (PINNs) are neural networks that embed the laws of dynamical systems modeled by differential equations into their loss function as constraints. In this work, we present a PINN framework applied to oncology. Here, we seek to learn time-varying interactions due to a combination therapy in a tumor microenvironment. In oncology, experimental data are often sparse and composed of a few time points of tumor volume. By embedding inductive biases derived from prior information about a dynamical system, we extend the physics-informed neural networks (PINN) and incorporate observed biological constraints as regularization agents. The modified PINN algorithm is able to steer itself to a reasonable solution and can generalize well with only a few training examples. We demonstrate the merit of our approach by learning the dynamics of treatment applied intermittently in an ordinary differential equation (ODE) model of a combination therapy. The algorithm yields a solution to the ODE and time-varying forms of some of the ODE model parameters. We demonstrate a strong convergence using metrics such as the mean squared error (MSE), mean absolute error (MAE), and mean absolute percentage error (MAPE).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13431v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kayode Olumoyin, Katarzyna Rejniak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Software System for Low-Cost, GUI-Based Microscopy Segmentation: Algorithmic Implementation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11354v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This article presents a novel microscopy image analysis framework designed for low-budget labs equipped with a standard CPU desktop. The Python-based program enables cytometric analysis of live, unstained cells in culture through an advanced computer vision and machine learning pipeline. Crucially, the framework operates on label-free data, requiring no manually annotated training data or training phase. It is accessible via a user-friendly, cross-platform GUI that requires no programming skills, while also providing a scripting interface for programmatic control and integration by developers. The end-to-end workflow performs semantic and instance segmentation, feature extraction, analysis, evaluation, and automated report generation. Its modular architecture supports easy maintenance and flexible integration while supporting both single-image and batch processing. Validated on several unstained cell types from the public dataset of livecells, the framework demonstrates superior accuracy and reproducibility compared to contemporary tools like Cellpose and StarDist. Its competitive segmentation speed on a CPU-based platform highlights its significant potential for basic research and clinical application-particularly in cell transplantation for personalised medicine and muscle regeneration therapies. The access to the application is available for reproducibility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11354v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Surajit Das, Pavel Zun</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
