<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.CB updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.CB</link>
    <description>q-bio.CB updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.CB" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Apr 2025 04:09:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 28 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Parametrization of microbial survival models under UVC exposure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14724</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14724v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study aims to identify and parameterize the optimal survival curves for 33 fundamental microorganisms subject to UVC exposure through experimental measurements. We compile published data on UVC doses and corresponding survival fractions for these microorganisms to estimate parameters for four prominent survival models: Single-target (ST), Multi-target (MT), Linear Quadratic (LQ), and Two-Stage Decay (TSD). The best-fitting model for each microorganism is determined by selecting the one with the lowest mean squared error (MSE) compared to the experimental data. Our analysis indicates that the MT model is the most frequently appropriate, accurately fitting 21 of the 33 microorganisms. The TSD model is the best fit for only three, while the LQ model, though occasionally suitable at lower doses, is often excluded due to unreliable performance at higher doses. The assessed models, particularly the MT model, demonstrate strong predictive capabilities for UVC surface sterilization of microorganisms. However, caution is warranted with the LQ model at higher doses due to its potential limitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14724v2</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aikaterini A. Tsantari, Konstantinos K. Delibasis, Harilaos G. Sandalidis, Nestor D. Chatzidiamantis</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
