<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.CB updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.CB</link>
    <description>q-bio.CB updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.CB" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 02:53:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Morphogenesis of bacterial colonies in liquid crystalline environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12406v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Natural bacterial habitats are often complex fluids with viscoelastic and anisotropic responses to stress; for example, they can take the form of liquid crystals (LCs), with elongated microscopic constituents that collectively align while still retaining the ability to flow. However, laboratory studies typically focus on cells in simple liquids or complex fluids with randomly-oriented constituents. Here, we show how interactions with LCs shape bacterial proliferation in multicellular colonies. Using experiments, we find that in a nematic LC, cells generically form aligned single-cell-wide "chains" as they reproduce. As these chains lengthen, they eventually buckle in a highly localized manner. By combining our measurements with a continuum mechanical theory, we demonstrate that this distinctive morphogenetic program emerges because cells are kept in alignment due to the LC's elasticity; as each chain lengthens, growth-induced viscous stresses along its contour eventually overcome the elasticity of the surrounding nematic, leading to buckling. Our work thus reveals and provides mechanistic insight into the previously-overlooked role of LCs in sculpting bacterial life in complex environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12406v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Gonzalez La Corte, Thomas G. J. Chandler, Saverio E. Spagnolie, Ned S. Wingreen, Sujit S. Datta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FlowClass.jl: Classifying Dynamical Systems by Structural Properties in Julia</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13084</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13084v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: FlowClass.jl is a Julia package for classifying continuous-time dynamical systems into a hierarchy of structural classes: Gradient, Gradient-like, Morse-Smale, Structurally Stable, and General. Given a vector field \(\mathbf{F}(\mathbf{x})\) defining the system \(\mathrm{d}\mathbf{x}/\mathrm{d}t = \mathbf{F}(\mathbf{x})\), the package performs a battery of computational tests -- Jacobian symmetry analysis, curl magnitude estimation, fixed point detection and stability classification, periodic orbit detection, and stable/unstable manifold computation -- to determine where the system sits within the classification hierarchy. This classification has direct implications for qualitative behaviour: gradient systems cannot oscillate, Morse-Smale systems are structurally stable in less than 3 dimensions, and general systems may exhibit chaos. Much of classical developmental theory going back to Waddington's epigenetic landscape rests on an implicit assumption of gradient dynamics.
  The package is designed with applications in systems and developmental biology in mind, particularly the analysis of gene regulatory networks and cell fate decision models in the context of Waddington's epigenetic landscape. It provides tools to assess whether a landscape metaphor is appropriate for a given dynamical model, and to quantify the magnitude of non-gradient (curl) dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13084v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael P. H. Stumpf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A self-organized compression network arrests epithelial proliferation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.16661v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: As epithelial development or wound closure approaches completion, cell proliferation progressively slows via contact inhibition of proliferation (CIP) - a mechanism understood as being strictly local. Here we report the discovery of inhibition of proliferation through an unanticipated mechanism that is non-local. As a confluent epithelial layer becomes progressively more jammed, two interpenetrating networks emerge: islands of mechanically compressed non-cycling cells percolating within an ocean of mechanically tensed cycling cells. The evolution of the compression network was found to be susceptible to both specific molecular stimulus and to injury-induced unjamming. Yet, in all circumstances, the size of compressed islands followed a power-law distribution that was well-captured by preferential network theory. Together, these findings demonstrate the existence of a network-based inhibition of proliferation (NIP) that is self-organizing and poised in proximity to criticality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.16661v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.TO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liav Daraf, Yael Lavi, Areej Saleem, Daniel Sevilla Sanchez, Yuri Feldman, Lior Atia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active Force Dynamics in Red Blood Cells Under Non-Invasive Optical Tweezers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01417</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01417v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Red blood cells (RBCs) sustain mechanical stresses associated with microcirculatory flow through ATP-driven plasma membrane flickering. This is an active phenomenon driven by motor proteins that regulate interactions between the spectrin cytoskeleton and the lipid bilayer; it is manifested in RBC shape fluctuations reflecting the cell's mechanical and metabolic state. Yet, direct quantification of the forces and energetic costs underlying this non-equilibrium behavior remains challenging due to the invasiveness of existing techniques. Here, a minimally invasive method that combines bead-free, low-power optical tweezers with high-speed video microscopy was employed to track local membrane forces and displacements in single RBCs during the same time window. This independent dual-channel measurement enabled the construction of a mechano-dynamic phase space for RBCs under different chemical treatments, that allowed for differentiating between metabolic and structural states based on their fluctuation-force signatures. Quantification of mechanical work during flickering demonstrated that membrane softening enhanced fluctuations while elevating energy dissipation. The proposed optical tweezers methodology provides a robust framework for mapping the active mechanics of living cells, enabling precise probing of cellular physiology and detection of biomechanical dysfunction in diseases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01417v2</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <category>q-bio.SC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arnau Dorn, Clara Luque-Rioja, Macarena Calero, Diego Herr\'aez-Aguilar, Francisco Monroy, Niccol\`o Caselli</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
