<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.CB updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.CB</link>
    <description>q-bio.CB updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.CB" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 05:11:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Leveraging Pre-trained Neural Network Models for the Classification of Tumor Cells Analyzed by Label-free Phase Holotomographic Microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06808v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Can a single label-free image reveal whether cancer cells were exposed to chemotherapy? We present an innovative methodology on the label-free and high-resolution imaging properties of phase holotomographic microscopy coupled with neural network models for the classification of cancer cells. Using 3D phase holotomographic microscopy, we imaged live A549 lung cancer cells with and without paclitaxel, converted stacks to 2D maximum-intensity projections, and evaluated pre-trained convolutional networks (VGG16, ResNet18, DenseNet121, and EfficientNet-B0) for binary classification of treatment status. EfficientNet-B0 achieved 96.9 % accuracy on unsegmented images. Refractive index analysis revealed bimodal distribution in treated cells, reflecting heterogeneous biophysical responses to paclitaxel exposure and supporting the network's ability to detect subtle, label-free indicators of drug action. As further proof-of-concept, the same pipeline separated holotomographic images of label-free, high versus low-graded urothelial cancer cells with high accuracy (90.6 %). These findings highlight the potential of integrating label-free holotomographic imaging with deep learning techniques for rapid and efficient classification of tumor cells, paving the way for advancements in treatment optimization and personalized diagnostic strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06808v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonor V. C. Losa, Temple A. Douglas, Lia Santos, Raquel Monteiro, Isabel Calejo, Raphael F. Canadas, Jana B. Nieder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A mathematical model for smooth muscle cell phenotype switching in atherosclerotic plaque</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06170v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Smooth muscle cells (SMCs) play a fundamental role in the development of atherosclerotic plaques. They ingest lipids in a similar way to monocyte-derived macrophages (MDMs) in the plaque. This can stimulate SMCs to undergo a phenotypic switch to a macrophage-like phenotype. We formulate an ordinary differential equation (ODE) model for the populations of SMCs, MDMs and smooth muscle cell-derived macrophages (SDMs) and the internalised lipid load in each population. We use this model to explore the effect on plaque fate of SMC phenotype switching. We find that when SMCs switch to a macrophage-like phenotype, the total lipid contained in the model plaque that is internalised inside cells increases. Additionally, removal of SMCs from the plaque via phenotype switching reduces the number of SMCs in the plaque fibrous cap, increases the lipid in the necrotic core, and increases plaque inflammation. This makes the plaque more vulnerable to rupture, which can lead to heart attacks and strokes. When SDMs are highly proliferative or resistant to cell death, the plaque grows rapidly and becomes highly pathological. The model suggests that plaque dynamics, driven by the switch of SMCs to a macrophage-like phenotype, may drive the development of unstable, vulnerable and pathological plaques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06170v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joseph P. Ndenda, Michael G. Watson, Ashish Misra, Mary R. Myerscough</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
