<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.CB updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.CB</link>
    <description>q-bio.CB updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.CB" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 05:03:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Complexity reduction by symmetry: uncovering the minimal regulatory network for logical computation in bacteria</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.10895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.10895v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Symmetry principles play an important role in geometry, and physics, allowing for the reduction of complicated systems to simpler, more comprehensible models that preserve the system's features of interest. Biological systems are often highly complex and may consist of a large number of interacting parts. Using symmetry fibrations, the relevant symmetries for biological "message-passing" networks, we introduce a scheme, called Complexity Reduction by Symmetry or ComSym, to reduce the gene regulatory networks of Escherichia coli and Bacillus subtilis bacteria to core networks in a way that preserves the dynamics and uncovers the computational capabilities of the network. Gene nodes in the original network that share isomorphic input trees are collapsed by the fibration into equivalence classes called fibers, whereby nodes that receive signals with the same "history" belong to one fiber and synchronize. Then we reduce the networks to its minimal computational core via k-core decomposition. This computational core consists of a few strongly connected components or "signal vortices", in which signals can cycle through. While between them, these "signal vortices" transmit signals in a feedforward manner. These connected components perform signal processing and decision making in the bacterial cell by employing a series of genetic toggle-switch circuits that store memory, plus oscillator circuits. These circuits act as the central computation device of the network, whose output signals then spread to the rest of the network. Our reduction method opens the door to narrow the vast complexity of biological systems to their minimal parts in a systematic way by using fundamental theoretical principles of symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.10895v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <category>q-bio.MN</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luis A. \'Alvarez-Garc\'ia, Wolfram Liebermeister, Ian Leifer, Hern\'an A. Makse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active energy harvesting and work transduction by hair-cell bundles in bullfrog's inner ear</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14485</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.14485v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Hair cells actively drive oscillations of their mechanosensitive organelles--the hair bundles that enable hearing and balance sensing in vertebrates. Why and how some hair cells expend energy by sustaining this oscillatory motion in order to fulfill their function as signal sensors and others--as amplifiers, remains unknown. We develop a stochastic thermodynamic theory to describe energy flows in a periodically-driven hair bundle. Our analysis of thermodynamic fluxes associated with hair bundles' motion and external sinusoidal stimulus reveals that these organelles operate as thermodynamic work-to-work machines under different operational modes. One operational mode transduces the signal's power into the cell, whereas another allows the external stimulus to harvest the energy supplied by the cell. These two regimes might represent thermodynamic signatures of signal sensing and amplification respectively. In addition to work transduction and energy harvesting, our model also substantiates the capability of hair-cell bundles to operate as heaters and, at the expense of external driving, as active feedback refrigerators. We quantify the performance and robustness of the work-to-work conversion by hair bundles, whose efficiency in some conditions exceeds 80 % of the applied power.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.14485v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanathip Thipmaungprom, Laila Saliekh, Rodrigo Alonso, \'Edgar Rold\'an, Florian Berger, Roman Belousov</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
