<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.CB updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.CB</link>
    <description>q-bio.CB updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.CB" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 04:07:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Rosette formations as symmetry-breaking events: theory and experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20543v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multicellular rosettes are observed in different situations such as morphogenesis, wound healing, and cancer progression. While some molecular insights have been gained to explain the presence of these assemblies of five or more cells around a common center, what are the tunable, global features that favors/hinders their formation is still largely unknown. Here, we made use of a Voronoi dynamical model to investigate the ingredients driving the emergence of rosettes characterized by different degree of stability and organization. We found that (i) breaking the local spatial symmetry of the system, i.e., introducing curvature-inducing defects, allows for the formation of rosette-like structures (ii) whose probability of formation depends on the characteristic of the cellular layer. In particular, a trade-off between tissue fluidity and single cell deformability dictates the assembly of transient rosettes, that are strongly stabilized in the presence of cell alignment interactions. To test our model predictions, we performed fluorescence microscopy experiments on rosette-forming neural populations derived from induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs), finding significant agreement. Overall, our work may set the stage to gain an unifying understanding of the plethora of biophysical mechanisms involving the occurrence of rosette-like structure both in physiology and their altered formation in pathology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20543v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mattia Miotto, Giorgio Gosti, Maria Rosito, Michela Dell'Omo, Viola Folli, Valeria de Turris, Giancarlo Ruocco, Alessandro Rosa, Matteo Paoluzzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-invasive maturity assessment of iPSC-CMs based on optical maturity characteristics using interpretable AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20775</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20775v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Human induced pluripotent stem cell-derived cardiomyocytes (iPSC-CMs) are an important resource for the identification of new therapeutic targets and cardioprotective drugs. After differentiation iPSC-CMs show an immature, fetal-like phenotype. Cultivation of iPSC-CMs in lipid-supplemented maturation medium (MM) strongly enhances their structural, metabolic and functional phenotype. Nevertheless, assessing iPSC-CM maturation state remains challenging as most methods are time consuming and go in line with cell damage or loss of the sample. To address this issue, we developed a non-invasive approach for automated classification of iPSC-CM maturity through interpretable artificial intelligence (AI)-based analysis of beat characteristics derived from video-based motion analysis. In a prospective study, we evaluated 230 video recordings of early-state, immature iPSC-CMs on day 21 after differentiation (d21) and more mature iPSC-CMs cultured in MM (d42, MM). For each recording, 10 features were extracted using Maia motion analysis software and entered into a support vector machine (SVM). The hyperparameters of the SVM were optimized in a grid search on 80 % of the data using 5-fold cross-validation. The optimized model achieved an accuracy of 99.5 $\pm$ 1.1 % on a hold-out test set. Shapley Additive Explanations (SHAP) identified displacement, relaxation-rise time and beating duration as the most relevant features for assessing maturity level. Our results suggest the use of non-invasive, optical motion analysis combined with AI-based methods as a tool to assess iPSC-CMs maturity and could be applied before performing functional readouts or drug testing. This may potentially reduce the variability and improve the reproducibility of experimental studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20775v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabian Scheurer, Alexander Hammer, Mario Schubert, Robert-Patrick Steiner, Oliver Gamm, Kaomei Guan, Frank Sonntag, Hagen Malberg, Martin Schmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metabolic coordination and phase transitions in spatially distributed multi-cellular systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.13424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.13424v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: During overflow metabolism, cells excrete glycolytic byproducts when growing under aerobic conditions in a seemingly wasteful fashion. While potentially advantageous for microbes with finite oxidative capacity, its role in higher organisms is harder to assess. Recent single-cell experiments suggest overflow metabolism arises due to imbalances in inter-cellular exchange networks. We quantitatively characterize this scenario by integrating spatial metabolic modeling with tools from statistical physics and experimental single-cell flux data. Our results provide a theoretical demonstration of how diffusion-limited exchanges shape the space of accessible multi-cellular metabolic states. Specifically, a phase transition from a balanced network of exchanges to an unbalanced, overflow regime occurs as mean glucose and oxygen uptake rates vary. Heterogeneous single-cell metabolic phenotypes occur near this transition. Time-resolved tumor-stroma co-culture data support the idea that overflow metabolism stems from failure of inter-cellular metabolic coordination. In summary, environmental control is an emergent multi-cellular property, rather than a cell-autonomous effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.13424v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s42005-025-02133-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Commun Phys 8, 205 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Krishnadev Narayanankutty, Jos\'e Antonio Pereiro-Morejon, Ari\'an Ferrero-Fern\'andez, Valentina Onesto, Stefania Forciniti, Loretta L. del Mercato, Roberto Mulet, Andrea De Martino, David S. Tourigny, Daniele De Martino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sensitivity analysis-guided model reduction of a mathematical model of pembrolizumab therapy for de novo metastatic MSI-H/dMMR colorectal cancer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18920</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.18920v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Colorectal cancer (CRC) is the third most commonly diagnosed cancer worldwide and the leading cause of cancer-related deaths in adults under 55, involving a complex interplay of biological processes such as dendritic cell (DC) maturation and migration, T cell activation and proliferation, cytokine production, and T cell and natural killer (NK) cell-mediated cancer cell killing. Microsatellite instability-high (MSI-H) CRC and deficient mismatch repair (dMMR) CRC constitute 15% of all CRC, and 4% of metastatic CRC, and exhibit remarkable responsiveness to immunotherapy, especially with PD-1 inhibitors such as pembrolizumab. Mathematical models of the underlying immunobiology and the interactions underpinning immune checkpoint blockade offer mechanistic insights into tumour-immune dynamics and provide avenues for treatment optimisation and the identification of novel therapeutic targets. We used our data-driven model of de novo metastatic MSI-H/dMMR CRC (dnmMCRC) and performed sensitivity analysis-guided model reduction using the FAST and EFAST methods. In this work, we constructed two simplified models of dnmMCRC: one that faithfully reproduces all of the original model's trajectories, and a second, minimal model that accurately replicates the original dynamics while being highly extensible for future inclusion of additional components to explore various aspects of the anti-tumour immune response.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.18920v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georgio Hawi, Peter S. Kim, Peter P. Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
