<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.EP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.EP</link>
    <description>astro-ph.EP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.EP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2024 02:41:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Sulfur Dioxide and Other Molecular Species in the Atmosphere of the Sub-Neptune GJ 3470 b</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04450</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04450v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report observations of the atmospheric transmission spectrum of the sub-Neptune exoplanet GJ 3470 b taken using the Near-Infrared Camera (NIRCam) on JWST. Combined with two archival HST/WFC3 transit observations and fifteen archival Spitzer transit observations, we detect water, methane, sulfur dioxide, and carbon dioxide in the atmosphere of GJ 3470 b, each with a significance of &gt;3-sigma. GJ 3470 b is the lowest mass -- and coldest -- exoplanet known to show a substantial sulfur dioxide feature in its spectrum, at $M_{p}$=11.2${\,{\rm M}_{\oplus}}$ and $T_{eq}$=600$\,$K. This indicates disequilibrium photochemistry drives sulfur dioxide production in exoplanet atmospheres over a wider range of masses and temperatures than has been reported or expected. The water, carbon dioxide, and sulfur dioxide abundances we measure indicate an atmospheric metallicity of approximately $100\times$ Solar. We see further evidence for disequilibrium chemistry in our inferred methane abundance, which is significantly lower than expected from equilibrium models consistent with our measured water and carbon dioxide abundances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04450v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas G. Beatty, Luis Welbanks, Everett Schlawin, Taylor J. Bell, Michael R. Line, Matthew Murphy, Isaac Edelman, Thomas P. Greene, Jonathan J. Fortney, Gregory W. Henry, Sagnick Mukherjee, Kazumasa Ohno, Vivien Parmentier, Emily Rauscher, Lindsey S. Wiser, Kenneth E. Arnold</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cold water emission cannot be used to infer depletion of bulk elemental oxygen [O/H] in disks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04457</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04457v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We re-examine the constraints provided by Herschel Space Observatory data regarding cold water emission from protoplanetary disks. Previous disk models that were used to interpret observed water emission concluded that oxygen (O/H) is depleted by at least 2 orders of magnitude if a standard, interstellar gas/dust mass ratio is assumed in the disk. In this work, we use model results from a recent disk parameter survey and show that most of the \textit{Herschel} constraints obtained for cold water (i.e. for transitions with an upper energy level $E_\mathrm{up}&lt;200$ K, where the bulk of the disk water lies) can be explained with disk models adopting ISM-like oxygen elemental abundance (i.e. O/H=$3.2\times10^{-4}$) and the canonical gas/dust mass ratio of 100. We show that cold water vapor is mainly formed by photodesorption of water ice at the interface between the molecular layer and the midplane, and that its emission is relatively independent of the main disk properties like the disk gas mass and gas/dust mass ratio. We find that the abundance of water vapor in the outer disk is set by photoprocesses and depends on the (constant) vertical column density of water ice needed to attenuate the FUV photon flux, resulting in roughly constant emission for the parameters (gas mass, dust mass, disk radius) varied in our survey. Importantly, water line emission is found to be optically thick and hence sensitive to temperature more than abundance, possibly driving previous inferences of large scale oxygen depletion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04457v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxime Ruaud, Uma Gorti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shaking and Tumbling: Short- and Long-Timescale Mechanisms for Resurfacing of Near-Earth Asteroid Surfaces from Planetary Tides and Predictions for the 2029 Earth Encounter by (99942) Apophis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04864v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spectral characterization of near-Earth asteroids (NEAs) has revealed a continuum of space-weathered states for the surfaces of S-complex NEAs, with Q-class NEAs, an S-complex subclass, most closely matching the un-weathered surfaces of ordinary chondrite meteorites. Dynamical calculations of the orbital evolution of S-complex NEAs revealed that Q-class NEAs tend to have close encounters with terrestrial planets, suggesting that planetary tides may play a role in refreshing NEA surfaces. However, the exact physical mechanism(s) that drive resurfacing through tidal encounters and the encounter distance at which these mechanisms are effective, has remained unclear. Through the lens of the upcoming (99942) Apophis encounter with Earth in 2029, we investigate the potential for surface mobilization through tidally-driven seismic shaking over short-timescales during encounter and subsequent surface slope evolution over longer-timescales driven by tumbling. We perform multi-scale numerical modeling and find that the 2029 encounter will induce short-term tidally-driven discrete seismic events that lead to high-frequency (greater than 0.1 Hz) surface accelerations that reach magnitudes similar to Apophis' gravity, and that may be detectable by modern seismometers. It is still unclear if the shaking we model translates to widespread particle mobilization and/or lofting. We also find there will be a significant change in Apophis' tumbling spin state that could lead to longer-term surface refreshing in response to tumbling-induced surface slope changes. We propose that through these mechanisms, space-weathered S-class asteroid surfaces may become refreshed through the exposure of unweathered underlying material. These results will be tested by the future exploration of Apophis by NASA's OSIRIS-APEX.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04864v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. -L. Ballouz, H. Agrusa, O. S. Barnouin, K. J. Walsh, Y. Zhang, R. P. Binzel, V. J. Bray, D. N. DellaGiustina, E. R. Jawin, J. V. DeMartini, A. Marusiak, P. Michel, N. Murdoch, D. C. Richardson, E. Rivera-Valentin, A. S. Rivkin, Y. Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $\beta$ Pictoris b Hill sphere transit campaign. Paper II: Searching for the signatures of the $\beta$ Pictoris exoplanets through time delay analysis of the $\delta$ Scuti pulsations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04870v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The $\beta$ Pictoris system is the closest known stellar system with directly detected gas giant planets, an edge-on circumstellar disc, and evidence of falling sublimating bodies and transiting exocomets. The inner planet, $\beta$ Pictoris c, has also been indirectly detected with radial velocity (RV) measurements. The star is a known $\delta$ Scuti pulsator, and the long-term stability of these pulsations opens up the possibility of indirectly detecting the gas giant planets through time delays of the pulsations due to a varying light travel time. We search for phase shifts in the $\delta$ Scuti pulsations consistent with the known planets $\beta$ Pictoris b and c and carry out an analysis of the stellar pulsations of $\beta$ Pictoris over a multi-year timescale. We used photometric data collected by the BRITE-Constellation, bRing, ASTEP, and TESS to derive a list of the strongest and most significant $\delta$ Scuti pulsations. We carried out an analysis with the open-source python package maelstrom to study the stability of the pulsation modes of $\beta$ Pictoris in order to determine the long-term trends in the observed pulsations. We did not detect the expected signal for $\beta$ Pictoris b or $\beta$ Pictoris c. The expected time delay is 6 seconds for $\beta$ Pictoris c and 24 seconds for $\beta$ Pictoris b. With simulations, we determined that the photometric noise in all the combined data sets cannot reach the sensitivity needed to detect the expected timing drifts. An analysis of the pulsational modes of $\beta$ Pictoris using maelstrom showed that the modes themselves drift on the timescale of a year, fundamentally limiting our ability to detect exoplanets around $\beta$ Pictoris via pulsation timing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04870v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202347754</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Zieba, Konstanze Zwintz, Matthew Kenworthy, Daniel Hey, Simon J. Murphy, Rainer Kuschnig, Lyu Abe, Abdelkrim Agabi, Djamel Mekarnia, Tristan Guillot, Fran\c{c}ois-Xavier Schmider, Philippe Stee, Yuri De Pra, Marco Buttu, Nicolas Crouzet, Samuel Mellon, Jeb Bailey III, Remko Stuik, Patrick Dorval, Geert-Jan J. Talens, Steven Crawford, Eric Mamajek, Iva Laginja, Michael Ireland, Blaine Lomberg, Rudi Kuhn, Ignas Snellen, Paul Kalas, Jason J. Wang, Kevin B. Stevenson, Ernst de Mooij, Anne-Marie Lagrange, Sylvestre Lacour, Mathias Nowak, Paul A. Str{\o}m, Zhang Hui, Lifan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting astrophysical bounds on continuous spontaneous localization models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04463v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Among the open problems in fundamental physics, few are as conceptually significant as the measurement problem in Quantum Mechanics. One of the proposed solutions to this problem is the Continuous Spontaneous Localization (CSL) model, which introduces a non-linear and stochastic modification of the Schr\"odinger equation. This model incorporates two parameters that can be subjected to experimental constraints. One of the most notable consequences of this theory is the spontaneous heating of massive objects; this anomalous heating is dependent on the CSL parameters. In this work, we will revisit some astrophysical bounds previously found, and introduce new methods for testing the spontaneous heating in a variety of compact objects. Finally, we will compare our different bounds and discuss the benefits and shortcomings of each one.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04463v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Miguel Ocampo, Marcelo M. Miller Bertolami, Gabriel Le\'on</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of time-varying X-ray emission from stellar flares on the ionization of protoplanetary disks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04946v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: X-rays have significant impacts on cold, weakly ionized protoplanetary disks by increasing the ionization rate and driving chemical reactions. Stellar flares are explosions that emit intense X-rays and are the unique source of hard X-rays with an energy of $\gtrsim10$ keV in the protoplanetary disk systems. Hard X-rays should be carefully taken into account in models as they can reach the disk midplane as a result of scattering in the disk atmospheres. However, previous models are insufficient to predict the hard X-ray spectra because of the simplification in flare models. We develop a model of X-ray spectra of stellar flares based on observations and flare theories. The flare temperature and nonthermal electron emissions are modeled as functions of flare energy, which allows us to better predict the hard X-ray photon flux than before. Using our X-ray model, we conduct radiative transfer calculations to investigate the impact of flare hard X-rays on disk ionization, with a particular focus on the protoplanetary disk around a T Tauri star. We demonstrate that for a flare with an energy of $\geq 10^{33}$ erg, X-ray photons with $\gtrsim 10$ keV penetrate down to the midplane to increase the ionization rates more than galactic cosmic rays. We also find that the 10-year-averaged X-rays from multiple flares could certainly contribute to the ionization at the disk midplane. These results emphasize the importance of stellar flares on the disk evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04946v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haruka Washinoue, Shinsuke Takasao, Kenji Furuya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LHS 1140 b is a potentially habitable water world</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13265</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13265v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: LHS 1140 b is a small planet orbiting in the habitable zone of its M4.5V dwarf host. Recent mass and radius constraints have indicated that it has either a thick H$_2$-rich atmosphere or substantial water by mass. Here we present a transmission spectrum of LHS 1140 b between 1.7 and 5.2 $\mu$m, obtained using the NIRSpec instrument on JWST. By combining spectral retrievals and self-consistent atmospheric models, we show that the transmission spectrum is inconsistent with H$_2$-rich atmospheres with varied size and metallicity, leaving a water world as the remaining scenario to explain the planet's low density. Specifically, a H$_2$-rich atmosphere would result in prominent spectral features of CH$_4$ or CO$_2$ on this planet, but they are not seen in the transmission spectrum. Instead, the data favors a high-mean-molecular-weight atmosphere (possibly N$_2$-dominated with H$_2$O and CO$_2$) with a modest confidence. Forming the planet by accreting C- and N-bearing ices could naturally give rise to a CO$_2$- or N$_2$-dominated atmosphere, and if the planet evolves to or has the climate-stabilizing mechanism to maintain a moderate-size CO$_2$/N$_2$-dominated atmosphere, the planet could have liquid-water oceans. Our models suggest CO$_2$ absorption features with an expected signal of 20 ppm at 4.2 $\mu$m. As the existence of an atmosphere on TRAPPIST-1 planets is uncertain, LHS 1140 b may well present the best current opportunity to detect and characterize a habitable world.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13265v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mario Damiano, Aaron Bello-Arufe, Jeehyun Yang, Renyu Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
