<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.EP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.EP</link>
    <description>astro-ph.EP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.EP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 04:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Long-term double synchronization in close-in gas giant planets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10979v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hot Jupiters, orbiting their host stars at extremely close distances, undergo tidal evolution, with some being engulfed by their stars due to angular momentum exchanges induced by tidal forces. However, achieving double synchronization can prolong their survival. Using the MESA stellar evolution code, combined with the magnetic braking model of Matt et al. (2015), we calculate 25,000 models with different metallicity and study how to attain the conditions that trigger the long-term double synchronization. Our results indicate that massive planets orbiting stars with lower convective turnover time are easier to achieve long-term double synchronization. The rotation angular velocity at the equilibrium point ($\Omega_{\mathrm{sta}}$) is almost equal to orbital angular velocity of planet ($\mathrm{n}$) for the majority of the main sequence lifetime if a system has undergone a long-term double synchronization, regardless of their state at this moment. We further compared our results with known parameters of giant planetary systems and found that those systems with larger planetary masses and lower convective turnover time seem to be less sensitive to changes in the tidal quality factor $Q'_{_*}$. We suggest that for systems that fall on the state of $\Omega_{\mathrm{sta}} \approx n$, regardless of their current state, the synchronization will persist for a long time if orbital synchronization occurs at any stage of their evolution. Our results can be applied to estimate whether a system has experienced long-term double synchronization in the past or may experience it in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10979v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuaishuai Guo, Jianheng Guo, Jie Su, Dongdong Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The role of Ohmic dissipation of internal currents on Hot Jupiter radii</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11501v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The inflated radii observed in hundreds of Hot Jupiters represent a long-standing open issue. The observed correlation between radii and irradiation strength, and the occasional extreme cases, nearly double the size of Jupiter, remain without a comprehensive quantitative explanation. In this investigation, we delve into this issue within the framework of Ohmic dissipation, one of the most promising mechanisms for explaining the radius anomaly. Using the evolutionary code MESA, we simulate the evolution of irradiated giant planets, spanning the range 1 to 8 Jupiter masses, incorporating an internal source of Ohmic dissipation located beneath the radiative-convective boundary. Our modeling is based on physical parameters, and accounts for the approximated conductivity and the evolution of the magnetic fields, utilizing widely-used scaling laws. We compute the radius evolution across a spectrum of masses and equilibrium temperatures, considering varying amounts of Ohmic dissipation, calculated with the internal conductivity profile and an effective parametrization of the currents, based on the typical radius of curvature of the field lines. Our analysis reveals that this internal Ohmic dissipation can broadly reproduce the range of observed radii using values of radius of curvature up to about one order of magnitude lower than what we estimate from the Juno measurements of the Jovian magnetosphere and from MHD dynamo simulations presented herein. The observed trend with equilibrium temperature can be explained if the highly-irradiated planets have more intense and more small-scale magnetic fields. This suggests the possibility of an interplay between atmospherically induced currents and the interior, via turbulence, in agreement with recent box simulations of turbulent MHD in atmospheric columns.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11501v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taner Akg\"un, Cl\`audia Soriano-Guerrero, Albert Elias-L\'opez, Daniele Vigan\`o, Rosalba Perna, Fabio Del Sordo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Logistic regression to boost exoplanet detection performances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11571</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11571v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Direct imaging of exoplanets requires to separate the background noise from the exoplanet signals. Statistical methods have been recently proposed to avoid subtracting any signal of interest as opposed to initial self-subtracting methods based on Angular Differential Imaging (ADI). However, unless conservative thresholds are chosen to claim for a detection, such approaches tend to produce a list of candidates that include many false positives. Choosing high, conservative, thresholds leads to miss the faintest planets. We extend a statistical framework with a logistic regression to filter the list of candidates. Features with physical/optical meaning (in two wavelengths) are used, leading to a very fast and pragmatic approach. The overall method requires a simple edge detection (image processing) and clustering algorithm to work with sub-images. To estimate its efficiency, we apply our approach to targets observed with the ESO/SPHERE high contrast imager, that were previously used as tests for blind surveys. Experimental results with injected signals show that either the number of false detections is considerably reduced or faint exoplanets that would otherwise not be detected can be sometimes found. Typically, on the blind tests performed, we are now able to detect around 50% more of the injected planets with an SNR below 5, and with a very low number of additional candidates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11571v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hadrien Cambazard (G-SCOP), Nicolas Catusse (G-SCOP), A. Chomez, A. -M. Lagrange, Pierre Vieu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The fuzzy cores of Jupiter and Saturn</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11657v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: New interior models of Jupiter and Saturn suggest that both planets have "fuzzy cores". These cores should be viewed as central regions that are enriched with heavy elements but are not distinct from the rest of the deep interior. These cores may contain large amounts of hydrogen and helium though small pure-heavy element cores may also exist. New measurements along with advanced planetary modeling have revolutionized the way we think about the interiors of giant planets and provide important constraints for planet formation and evolution theories. These developments are also relevant for the characterization of giant exoplanets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11657v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ravit Helled, David J. Stevenson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Irradiation induced mineral changes of NWA10580 meteorite determined by infrared analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11725v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context. Identifying minerals on asteroid surfaces is difficult as space weathering modifies the minerals infrared spectra. This shouldbe better understood for proper interpretation.
  Aims. We simulated the space weathering effects on a meteorite and recorded the alterations of the crystalline structure, such as the change in peak positions and full width at half maximum values.
  Methods. We used proton irradiation to simulate the effects of solar wind on a sample of NWA 10580 CO3 chondrite meteorites. After irradiation in three gradually increased steps with 1 keV ion energy, we used infrared microscopic reflectance and diffuse reflectance infrared Fourier transform spectroscopy (DRIFTS) to identify and understand the consequences of irradiation.
  Results. We find negative peak shifts after the first and second irradiations at pyroxene and feldspar minerals, similarly to the literature, and this shift was attributed to Mg loss. However, after the third irradiation a positive change in values in wavenumber emerged for silicates, which could come from the distortion of SiO4 tetrahedra, resembling shock deformation. The full width at half maximum values of major bands show a positive (increasing) trend after irradiations in the case of feldspars, using IR reflection measurements. Comparing DRIFTS and reflection infrared data, the peak positions of major mineral bands were at similar wavenumbers, but differences can be observed in minor bands.
  Conclusions. We measured the spectral changes of meteorite minerals after high doses of proton irradiation for several minerals. We show the first of these measurements for feldspars; previous works only presented pyroxene, olivine, and phyllosilicates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11725v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202347467</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A, 683, A162 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>I. Gyollai, S. Biri, Z. Juh\'asz, Cs. Kir\'aly, B. D. P\'al, R. R\'acz, D. Rezes, B. Sulik, M. Szab\'o, Z. Szalai, P. Sz\'avai, T. Szklen\'ar, \'A. Kereszturi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Debris disks around main-sequence stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11804v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: 'Debris disks' are collections of small bodies around stars, such as the Asteroid Belt and Kuiper Belt in our Solar System. These disks are composed of objects smaller than planets, including asteroids, comets, dust, and dwarf planets. We detect debris disks around a significant fraction of stars, and these disks appear to be common components of planetary systems. Extrasolar debris disks have a broad range of locations, shapes and features. This chapter provides an introduction to debris disks around main-sequence stars. It summarises our understanding of the field, and covers a wide range of concepts from observations and theory. It describes how we detect extrasolar debris disks, what we see, and what these observations tell us. It also describes how debris disks evolve, and how they interact with planets. The chapter concludes by discussing several unsolved questions in debris-disk science.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11804v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tim D. Pearce</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cohesion and Shear Strength of Compacted Lunar and Martian Regolith Simulants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11029</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11029v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Shear strength and cohesion of granular materials are important geotechnical properties that play a crucial role in the stability and behavior of lunar and Martian regolith, as well as their terrestrial analog materials. To characterize and predict shear strength and cohesion for future space missions, it is also important to understand the effects of particle size distribution and density on these fundamental geotechnical properties. Generalized equations have been established using empirical data from direct shear measurements of lunar and Martian regolith simulants to quantify the effects of particle size distribution and density on cohesion and shear strength. Preliminary results are also presented highlighting the effects of atmospheric absorbed water on shear strength and cohesion when conducting experiments in atmospheric conditions on Earth. The results of this study show that cohesion increases exponentially with bulk density, while the exponential growth constant is also dependent on particle size distribution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11029v1</guid>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Dotson, D. Sanchez Valencia, C. Millwater, P. Easter, J. Long-Fox, D. Britt, P. Metzger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seven new triply eclipsing triple star systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.12041v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We have identified nearly a hundred close triply eclipsing hierarchical triple star systems from data taken with the space telescope TESS. These systems are noteworthy in that we can potentially determine their dynamical and astrophysical parameters with a high precision. In the present paper, we report the comprehensive study of seven new compact triply eclipsing triple star systems taken from this larger sample: TICs 133771812, 176713425, 185615681, 287756035, 321978218, 323486857, and 650024463. Most of the data for this study come from TESS observations, but two of them have Gaia measurements of their outer orbits, and we obtained supplemental radial velocity (RV) measurements for three of the systems. The eclipse timing variation curves extracted from the TESS data, the photometric light curves, the RV points, and the spectral energy distribution (SED) are combined in a complex photodynamical analysis to yield the stellar and orbital parameters of all seven systems. Four of the systems are quite compact with outer periods in the range of 41-56 days. All of the systems are substantially flat, with mutual inclination angles of &lt; ~2 degrees. Including the systems reported in this work, we have now studied in considerable detail some 30 triply eclipsing triples with TESS, and are accumulating a meaningful census of these systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.12041v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. A. Rappaport, T. Borkovits, T. Mitnyan, R. Gagliano, N. Eisner, T. Jacobs, A. Tokovinin, B. Powell, V. Kostov, M. Omohundro, M. H. Kristiansen, R. Jayaraman, I. Terentev, H. M. Schwengeler, D. LaCourse, Z. Gara, T. Pribulla, P. F. L. Maxted, I. B. B\'ir\'o, I. Cs\'anyi, A. P\'al, A. Vanderburg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Air-sea interactions on Titan: effect of radiative transfer on the lake evaporation and atmospheric circulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.03278</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.03278v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Titan's northern high latitudes host many large hydrocarbon lakes. Like water lakes on Earth, Titan's lakes are constantly subject to evaporation. This process strongly affects the atmospheric methane abundance, the atmospheric temperature, the lake mixed layer temperature, and the local wind circulation. In this work we use a 2D atmospheric mesoscale model coupled to a slab lake model to investigate the effect of solar and infrared radiation on the exchange of energy and methane between Titan's lakes and atmosphere. The magnitude of solar radiation reaching the surface of Titan through its thick atmosphere is only a few $Wm^{-2}$. However, we find that this small energy input is important and is comparable in absolute magnitude to the latent and sensible heat fluxes, as suggested in the prior study by Rafkin and Soto (2020). The implementation of a gray radiative scheme in the model confirms the importance of radiation when studying lakes at the surface of Titan. Solar and infrared radiation change the energy balance of the system leading to an enhancement of the methane evaporation rate, an increase of the equilibrium lake temperature almost completely determined by its environment (humidity, insolation, and background wind), and a strengthening of the local sea breeze, which undergoes diurnal variations. The sea breeze efficiently transports methane vapor horizontally, from the lake to the land, and vertically due to rising motion along the sea breeze front and due to radiation-induced turbulence over the land.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.03278v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/PSJ/ac8d0b</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Planet. Sci. J. 3 232 (2022)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Audrey Chatain, Scot C. R. Rafkin, Alejandro Soto, Ricardo Hueso, Aymeric Spiga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eccentric Gas Disk Orbiting the White Dwarf SDSS J1228+1040</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.01234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.01234v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Metal pollution onto white dwarfs is a wide-spread phenomenon that remains puzzling. Some of these white dwarfs also harbour gaseous debris disks. Emission lines from these disks open a unique window to the physical properties of the polluting material, lending insights to their origin. We model the emission line kinematics for the gas disk around SDSS J1228+1040, a system that has been monitored for over two decades. We show that the disk mass is strongly peaked at 1 solar radius (modulo the unknown inclination), and the disk eccentricity decreases from a value of 0.44 at the inner edge, to nearly zero at the outer edge. This eccentricity profile is exactly what one expects if the disk is in a global eccentric mode, precessing rigidly under general relativity and gas pressure. The precession period is about two decades. We infer that the mass of the gas disk is roughly equivalent to that of a 50-km rocky body, while the mass of the accompanying dust disk is likely insignificant. The disk eccentricity confirms an origin in tidal disruption, while the short disk diffusion time suggests that the disruption event happened a few centuries ago. Moreover, we argue that the initial orbit for the disrupted body, and that of its putative planetary perturber, fall within an AU around the white dwarf. The total mass of the source population is likely orders of magnitude more massive than our own Asteroid belt, and does not seem to exist around main-sequence stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.01234v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olcay Ates Goksu (Toronto), Taylor Kutra (Toronto), Yanqin Wu (Toronto)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The impact of lake shape and size on lake breezes and air-lake exchanges on Titan</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.07042</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.07042v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Titan, the largest moon of Saturn, has many lakes on its surface, formed mainly of liquid methane. Like water lakes on Earth, these methane lakes on Titan likely profoundly affect the local climate. Previous studies (Rafkin and Soto 2020, Chatain et al 2022) showed that Titan's lakes create lake breeze circulations with characteristic dimensions similar to the ones observed on Earth. However, such studies used a model in two dimensions; this work investigates the consequences of the addition of a third dimension to the model. Our results show that 2D simulations tend to overestimate the extension of the lake breeze over the land, and underestimate the strength of the subsidence over the lake, due to divergence/convergence geometrical effects in the mass conservation equations. In addition, 3D simulations including a large scale background wind show the formation of a pocket of accelerated wind behind the lake, which did not form in 2D simulations. An investigation of the effect of shoreline concavity on the resulting air circulation shows the formation of wind currents over peninsulas. Simulations with several lakes can either result in the formation of several individual lake breeze cells (during the day), or the emergence of a large merged cell with internal wind currents between lakes (during the night). Simulations of several real-shaped lakes located at a latitude of 74{\deg}N on Titan at the autumn equinox show that larger lakes trigger stronger winds, and that some sections of lakes might accumulate enough methane vapor to form a thin fog. The addition of a third dimension, along with adjustments in the parametrizations of turbulence and subsurface land temperature, results in a reduction in the magnitude of the average lake evaporate rate, namely to ~6 cm/Earth year.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.07042v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.icarus.2023.115925</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Icarus 411 (2024) 115925</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Audrey Chatain, Scot C. R. Rafkin, Alejandro Soto, Enora Moisan, Juan M. Lora, Alice Le Gall, Ricardo Hueso, Aymeric Spiga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The mass-radius relation of exoplanets, revisited</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.12593v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Determining the mass-radius ($M$-$R$) relation of exoplanets is important for exoplanet characterization. Here we present a re-analysis of the $M$-$R$ relations and their transitions using exoplanetary data from the PlanetS catalog which only includes planets with reliable mass and radius determinations. We find that "small planets" correspond to planets with masses of up to $\sim4.4 M_\oplus$ (within 17%) where $R \propto M^{0.27}$. Planets with masses between $\sim4.4$ and $127 M_\oplus$ (within 5%) can be viewed as "intermediate-mass" planets, where $R \propto M^{0.67}$. Massive planets, or gas giant planets, are found to have masses beyond $127 M_\oplus$ with an $M$-$R$ relation of $R \propto M^{-0.06}$. By analyzing the radius-density relation we also find that the transition between "small" to "intermediate-size" planets occurs at a planetary radius of $\sim1.6 R_\oplus$ (within 3%). Our results are consistent with previous studies and provide an ideal fit for the currently-measured planetary population.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.12593v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon M\"uller, Jana Baron, Ravit Helled, Fran\c{c}ois Bouchy, L\'ena Parc</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The POKEMON Speckle Survey of Nearby M Dwarfs. III. The Stellar Multiplicity Rate of M Dwarfs within 15 pc</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.14703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.14703v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: M dwarfs are ubiquitous in our galaxy, and the rate at which they host stellar companions, and the properties of these companions, provides a window into the formation and evolution of the star(s), and of any planets that they may host. The Pervasive Overview of 'Kompanions' of Every M dwarf in Our Neighborhood (POKEMON) speckle survey of nearby M dwarfs is volume-limited from M0V through M9V out to 15 pc, with additional targets at larger distances. In total, 1125 stars were observed, and 455 of these are within the volume-limited, 15-pc sample of M-dwarf primaries. When we combine the speckle observations with known companions from the literature, we find that the stellar multiplicity rate of M dwarfs within 15 pc is 23.5% plus or minus 2.0%, and that the companion rate is 28.8% plus or minus 2.1%. We also find that the projected separation distribution for multiples that are known to host planets peaks at 198 au, while the distribution for multiples that are not yet known to host planets peaks at 5.57 au. This result suggests that the presence of close-in stellar companions inhibits the formation of M-dwarf planetary systems, similar to what has been found for FGK stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.14703v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Catherine A. Clark, Gerard T. van Belle, Elliott P. Horch, David R. Ciardi, Kaspar von Braun, Brian A. Skiff, Jennifer G. Winters, Michael B. Lund, Mark E. Everett, Zachary D. Hartman, Joe Llama</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
