<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.EP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.EP</link>
    <description>astro-ph.EP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.EP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2024 04:00:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>PDS 70 unveiled by star-hopping: total intensity, polarimetry and mm-imaging modeled in concert</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11641v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context. Most ground-based planet search direct imaging campaigns use angular differential imaging, which distorts the signal from extended sources like protoplanetary disks. In the case PDS 70, a young system with two planets found within the cavity of a protoplanetary disk, obtaining a reliable image of both planets and disk is essential to understanding planet-disk interactions. Aims. Our goals are to reveal the true intensity of the planets and disk without self-subtraction effects for the first time, search for new giant planets beyond separations of 0.1" and to study the morphology of the disk shaped by two massive planets. Methods. We present YJHK-band imaging, polarimetry, and spatially resolved spectroscopy of PDS 70 using near-simultaneous reference star differential imaging, also known as star-hopping. We created a radiative transfer model of the system to match the near-infrared imaging and polarimetric data, along with sub-millimeter imaging from ALMA. Furthermore, we extracted the spectra of the planets and the disk and compared them. Results. We find that the disk is quite flared with a scale height of ~15% at the outer edge of the disk at ~90 au, similar to some disks in the literature. The gap inside of ~50 au is estimated to have ~1% of the dust density of the outer disk. The Northeast outer disk arc seen in previous observations is likely the outer lip of the flared disk. Abundance ratios of grains estimated by the modeling indicate a shallow grain-size index &gt; -2.7, instead of the canonical -3.5. There is both vertical and radial segregation of grains. Planet c is well separated from the disk and has a spectrum similar to planet b, clearly redder than the disk spectra. Planet c is possibly associated with the sudden flaring of the disk starting at ~50 au. No new planets &gt; 5 Mj were found.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11641v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Z. Wahhaj, M. Benisty, C. Ginski, C. Swastik, S. Arora, R. G. van Holstein, R. J. De Rosa, B. Yang, J. Bae, B. Ren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for Free-Floating Planets with TESS: I. Discovery of a First Terrestrial-Mass Candidate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11666v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Though free-floating planets (FFPs) that have been ejected from their natal star systems may outpopulate their bound counterparts in the terrestrial-mass range, they remain one of the least explored exoplanet demographics. Due to their negligible electromagnetic emission at all wavelengths, the only observational technique able to detect these worlds is gravitational microlensing. Microlensing by terrestrial-mass FFPs induces rare, short-duration magnifications of background stars, requiring high-cadence, wide-field surveys to detect these events. The Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS), though designed to detect close-bound exoplanets via the transit technique, boasts a cadence as short as 200 seconds and has monitored hundreds of millions of stars, making it well-suited to search for short-duration microlensing events as well. We have used existing data products from the TESS Quick-Look Pipeline (QLP) to perform a preliminary search for FFP microlensing candidates in 1.3 million light curves from TESS Sector 61. We find one compelling candidate associated with TIC-107150013, a source star at $d_s = 3.194$ kpc. The event has a duration $t_E = 0.074^{+0.002}_{-0.002}$ days and shows prominent finite-source features ($\rho = 4.55^{+0.08}_{-0.07}$), making it consistent with an FFP in the terrestrial-mass range. This exciting result indicates that our ongoing search through all TESS sectors has the opportunity to shed new light on this enigmatic population of worlds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11666v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michelle Kunimoto, William DeRocco, Nolan Smyth, Steve Bryson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Laser Irradiation of Carbonaceous Chondrite Simulants: Space Weathering Implications for C-complex Asteroids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11814v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Surfaces of carbonaceous asteroids (C-complex) have shown diverse contrasting spectral variations, which may be related to space weathering. We performed laser irradiation experiments on CI and CM simulant material under vacuum to mimic the spectral alteration induced by micrometeorite impacts. We used in situ ultraviolet-visible and near-infrared reflectance spectroscopy to analyze spectral alterations in response to pulsed laser irradiation, as well as scanning electron microscopy and x-ray photoelectron spectroscopy to search for microstructural and compositional changes. Laser irradiation causes an increase in spectral slope (reddening) and a decrease in the albedo (darkening), and these changes are stronger in the ultraviolet-visible region. These spectral changes are likely driven by the excess iron found in the altered surface region, although other factors, such as the observed structural changes, may also contribute. Additionally, while the 0.27~${\mu}m$ band appears relatively stable under laser irradiation, a broad feature at 0.6~${\mu}m$ rapidly disappears with laser irradiation, suggesting that space weathering may inhibit the detection of any feature in this spectral region, including the 0.7~${\mu}m$ band, which has typically been used an indicator of hydration. Comparing our laboratory results with optical spectrophotometry observations of C-complex asteroids, we find that the majority of objects are spectrally red and possess colors that are similar to our irradiated material rather than our fresh samples. Furthermore, we also find that ``younger'' and ``older'' C-complex families have similar colors, suggesting that the space weathering process is near-equal or faster than the time it takes to refresh the surfaces of these airless bodies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11814v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andy J. L\'opez-Oquendo, Mark J. Loeffler, David E. Trilling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Delivery of Dust Particles from Protoplanetary Disks onto Circumplanetary Disks of Giant Planets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11857</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11857v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Principal regular satellites of gas giants are thought to be formed by the accumulation of solid materials in circumplanetary disks (CPDs). While there has been significant progress in the study of satellite formation in CPDs, details of the supply of satellite building blocks to CPDs remain unclear. We performed orbital integration of solid particles in the protoplanetary disk (PPD) approaching a planet, considering the gas drag force using the results of three-dimensional hydrodynamical simulations of a local region around the planet. We investigated planetary-mass dependence of the capture positions and capture rates of dust particles accreting onto the CPD. We also examined the degree of dust retention in accreting gas onto the CPD, which is important for determining the ratio of dust-to-gas inflow rates, a key parameter in satellite formation. We found that the degree of dust retention increases with increasing planetary mass for a given dust scale height in the PPD. In the case of a small planet ($M_{\rm p}=0.2M_{\rm Jup}$), most particles with insufficient initial altitudes in the PPD are isolated from the gas in the accreting region. On the other hand, in the case of a massive planet ($M_{\rm p}=1M_{\rm Jup}$), dust particles can be coupled to the vertically accreting gas, even when the dust scale height is about $10-30$\% of the gas scale height. The results of this study can be used for models of dust delivery and satellite formation in the CPDs of gas giants of various masses, including exoplanets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11857v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Natsuho Maeda, Keiji Ohtsuki, Ryo Suetsugu, Yuhito Shibaike, Takayuki Tanigawa, Masahiro N. Machida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Fireball of November 24, 1970, as the Most Probable Source of the Ischgl Meteorite</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11989</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11989v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In June 1976, a pristine meteorite stone weighing approximately 1 kg, fully covered with a fresh black fusion crust, was collected on a mountain road in the high-altitude Alpine environment. The recovery took place while clearing the remnants of a snow avalanche, 2 km northwest of Ischgl in Austria. Subsequent to its retrieval, the specimen remained in the finder's private residence without undergoing any scientific examination or identification until 2008, when it was brought to the University of Innsbruck. The sample was classified as a well-preserved LL6 chondrite, with a W0 weathering grade, implying a relatively short time between the meteorite fall and its retrieval. To investigate the potential connection between the Ischgl meteorite and a recorded fireball event, we have reviewed all documented fireballs ever photographed by German fireball camera stations. This examination led us to identify the fireball EN241170 observed in Germany by ten different European Network stations on the night of November 23/24, 1970, as the most likely candidate. We employed state-of-the-art techniques to reconstruct the fireball's trajectory, and to reproduce both its luminous and dark flight phases in detail. We find that the determined strewn field and the generated heat map closely align with the recovery location of the Ischgl meteorite. Furthermore, the measured radionuclide data reported here indicate that the pre-atmospheric size of the Ischgl meteoroid is consistent with the mass estimate inferred from our deceleration analysis along the trajectory. Our findings strongly support the conclusion that the Ischgl meteorite originated from the EN241170 fireball, effectively establishing it as a confirmed meteorite fall. This discovery enables to determine, along with the physical properties, also the heliocentric orbit and cosmic history of the Ischgl meteorite.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11989v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1111/MAPS.14173</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Maria Gritsevich, Jarmo Moilanen, Jaakko Visuri, Matthias M. M. Meier, Colin Maden, J\"urgen Oberst, Dieter Heinlein, Joachim Flohrer, Alberto J. Castro-Tirado, Jorge Delgado-Garc\'ia, Christian Koeberl, Ludovic Ferri\`ere, Franz Brandst\"atter, Pavel P. Povinec, Ivan S\'ykora, Florian Schweidler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The formation of transiting circumplanetary debris discs from the disruption of satellite systems during planet-planet scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12239v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Several stars show deep transits consistent with discs of roughly 1 Solar radius seen at moderate inclinations, likely surrounding planets on eccentric orbits. We show that this configuration arises naturally as a result of planet-planet scattering when the planets possess satellite systems. Planet-planet scattering explains the orbital eccentricities of the discs' host bodies, while the close encounters during scattering lead to the exchange of satellites between planets and/or their destabilisation. This leads to collisions between satellites and their tidal disruption close to the planet. Both of these events lead to large quantities of debris being produced, which in time will settle into a disc such as those observed. The mass of debris required is comparable to a Ceres-sized satellite. Through N-body simulations of planets with clones of the Galilean satellite system undergoing scattering, we show that 90 percent of planets undergoing scattering will possess debris from satellite destruction. Extrapolating to smaller numbers of satellites suggests that tens of percent of such planets should still possess circumplanetary debris discs. The debris trails arising from these events are often tilted at tens of degrees to the planetary orbit, consistent with the inclinations of the observed discs. Disruption of satellite systems during scattering thus simultaneously explains the existence of debris, the tilt of the discs, and the eccentricity of the planets they orbit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12239v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander J. Mustill, Melvyn B. Davies, Matthew A. Kenworthy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radio Observations as an Extrasolar Planet Discovery and Characterization: Interior Structure and Habitability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12348v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Detection of radio emission from Jupiter was identified quickly as being due to its planetary-scale magnetic field. Subsequent spacecraft investigations have revealed that many of the planets, and even some moons, either have or have had large-scale magnetic fields. In the case of the Earth, Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus, and Neptune, the their magnetic fields are generated by dynamo processes within these planets, and an interaction between the solar wind and their magnetic fields generates intense radio emission via the electron cyclotron maser instability. In the case of Jupiter, its magnetic field interacts with the moon Io to result in radio emission as well.
  Extrasolar planets reasonably may be expected to generate large-scale magnetic fields and to sustain an electron cyclotron maser instability. Not only may these radio emissions be a means for discovering extrasolar planets, because magnetic fields are tied to the properties of planetary interiors, radio emissions may be a remote sensing means of constraining extrasolar planetary properties that will be otherwise difficult to access. In the case of terrestrial planets, the presence or absence of a magnetic field may be an indicator for habitability. Since the first edition of the Handbook, there have been a number of advances, albeit there remain no unambigous detection of radio emission from extrasolar planets. New ground-based telescopes and new possibilities for space-based telescopes provide promise for the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12348v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Joseph W. Lazio (Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CRIRES$^+$ transmission spectroscopy of WASP-127b. Detection of the resolved signatures of a supersonic equatorial jet and cool poles in a hot planet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12363v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: General circulation models of gas giant exoplanets predict equatorial jets that drive inhomogeneities across the planetary atmosphere. We studied the transmission spectrum of the hot Jupiter WASP-127b during one transit in the K band with CRIRES+. Telluric and stellar signals were removed from the data using SYSREM and the planetary signal was investigated using the cross-correlation (CCF) technique. After detecting a spectral signal indicative of atmospheric inhomogeneities, we employed a Bayesian retrieval framework with a 2D modelling approach tailored to address this scenario. We detected strong signals of H$_2$O and CO, which exhibited not one but two distinct CCF peaks. The double peaked signal can be explained by a supersonic equatorial jet and muted signals at the poles, with the two peaks representing the signals from the planet's morning and evening terminators, respectively. We calculated an equatorial jet velocity of $7.7\pm0.2$km/s from our retrieved overall equatorial velocity and the planet's tidally locked rotation, and derive distinct atmospheric properties for the two terminators as well as the polar region. The evening terminator is found to be hotter than the morning terminator by $175^{+116}_{-133}$K and the muted signals from the poles can be explained by significantly lower temperatures or a high cloud deck. Our retrieval yields a solar C/O ratio and metallicity and challenges previous studies of WASP-127b's atmosphere. The presence of a double peaked signal highlights the importance of accounting for planetary 3D structure during interpretation of atmospheric signals. The measured supersonic jet velocity and the lack of signal from the polar regions, representing a detection of latitudinal inhomogeneity in a spatially unresolved target, showcases the power of high-resolution transmission spectroscopy for the characterization of global circulation in exoplanets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12363v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Nortmann, F. Lesjak, F. Yan, D. Cont, S. Czesla, A. Lavail, A. D. Rains, E. Nagel, L. Boldt-Christmas, A. Hatzes, A. Reiners, N. Piskunov, O. Kochukhov, U. Heiter, D. Shulyak, M. Renge, U. Seemann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modelling stochastic and quasi-periodic behaviour in stellar time-series: Gaussian process regression versus power-spectrum fitting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11662</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11662v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: As the hunt for an Earth-like exoplanets has intensified in recent years, so has the effort to characterise and model the stellar signals that can hide or mimic small planetary signals. Stellar variability arises from a number of sources, including granulation, supergranulation, oscillations and activity, all of which result in quasi-periodic or stochastic behaviour in photometric and/or radial velocity observations. Traditionally, the characterisation of these signals has mostly been done in the frequency domain. However, the recent development of scalable Gaussian process regression methods makes direct time-domain modelling of stochastic processes a feasible and arguably preferable alternative, obviating the need to estimate the power spectral density of the data before modelling it. In this paper, we compare the two approaches using a series of experiments on simulated data. We show that frequency domain modelling can lead to inaccurate results, especially when the time sampling is irregular. By contrast, Gaussian process regression results are often more precise, and systematically more accurate, in both the regular and irregular time sampling regimes. While this work was motivated by the analysis of radial velocity and photometry observations of main sequence stars in the context of planet searches, we note that our results may also have applications for the study of other types of astrophysical variability such as quasi-periodic oscillations in X-ray binaries and active galactic nuclei variability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11662v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niamh K. O'Sullivan, Suzanne Aigrain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General non-linear fragmentation with discontinuous Galerkin methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11851v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Dust grains play a significant role in several astrophysical processes, including gas/dust dynamics, chemical reactions, and radiative transfer. Replenishment of small-grain populations is mainly governed by fragmentation during pair-wise collisions between grains. The wide spectrum of fragmentation outcomes, from complete disruption to erosion and/or mass transfer, can be modelled by the general non-linear fragmentation equation. Efficiently solving this equation is crucial for an accurate treatment of the dust fragmentation in numerical modelling. However, similar to dust coagulation, numerical errors in current fragmentation algorithms employed in astrophysics are dominated by the numerical over-diffusion problem -- particularly in 3D hydrodynamic simulations where the discrete resolution of the mass density distribution tends to be highly limited. With this in mind, we have derived the first conservative form of the general non-linear fragmentation with a mass flux highlighting the mass transfer phenomenon. Then, to address cases of limited mass density resolution, we applied a high-order discontinuous Galerkin scheme to efficiently solve the conservative fragmentation equation with a reduced number of dust bins. An accuracy of 0.1 -1% is reached with 20 dust bins spanning a mass range of 9 orders of magnitude.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11851v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxime Lombart, Charles-Edouard Br\'ehier, Mark Hutchison, Yueh-Ning Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MINDS: Mid-infrared atomic and molecular hydrogen lines in the inner disk around a low-mass star</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11942</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11942v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work aims to measure the mass accretion rate, the accretion luminosity, and more generally the physical conditions of the warm emitting gas in the inner disk of the very low-mass star 2MASS-J16053215-1933159. We investigate the source mid-infrared spectrum for atomic and molecular hydrogen line emission. We present the full James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) Mid-InfraRed Instrument (MIRI) Medium Resolution Spectrometer (MRS) spectrum of the protoplanetary disk around the very low-mass star 2MASS-J16053215-1933159 from the MINDS GTO program, previously shown to be abundant in hydrocarbon molecules. We analyzed the atomic and molecular hydrogen lines in this source by fitting one or multiple Gaussian profiles. We then built a rotational diagram for the H2 lines to constrain the rotational temperature and column density of the gas. Finally, we compared the observed atomic line fluxes to predictions from two standard emission models. We identify five molecular hydrogen pure rotational lines and 16 atomic hydrogen recombination lines. The spectrum indicates optically thin emission for both species. We use the molecular hydrogen lines to constrain the mass and temperature of the warm emitting gas. The HI (7-6) recombination line is used to measure the mass accretion rate and luminosity onto the central source. HI recombination lines can also be used to derive the physical properties of the gas using atomic recombination models. The JWST-MIRI MRS observations for the very low-mass star 2MASS-J16053215-1933159 reveal a large number of emission lines, many originating from atomic and molecular hydrogen because we are able to look into the disk warm molecular layer. Their analysis constrains the physical properties of the emitting gas and showcases the potential of JWST to deepen our understanding of the physical and chemical structure of protoplanetary disks</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11942v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riccardo Franceschi, Thomas Henning, Beno\^it Tabone, Giulia Perotti, Alessio Caratti o Garatti, Giulio Bettoni, Ewine F. van Dishoeck, Inga Kamp, Olivier Absil, Manuel G\"udel, G\"oran Olofsson, L. B. F. M. Waters, Aditya M. Arabhavi, Valentin Christiaens, Danny Gasman, Sierra L. Grant, Hyerin Jang, Donna Rodgers-Lee, Matthias Samland, Kamber Schwarz, Milou Temmink, David Barrado, Anthony Boccaletti, Vincent Geers, Pierre-Olivier Lagage, Eric Pantin, Tom P. Ray, Silvia Scheithauer, Bart Vandenbussche, Gillian Wright</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Multiwavelength Survey of Nearby M dwarfs: Optical and Near-Ultraviolet Flares and Activity with Contemporaneous TESS, Kepler/K2, \textit{Swift}, and HST Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12310</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12310v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive multiwavelength investigation into flares and activity in nearby M~dwarf stars. We leverage the most extensive contemporaneous dataset obtained through the Transiting Exoplanet Sky Survey (TESS), Kepler/K2, the Neil Gehrels Swift Observatory (\textit{Swift}), and the Hubble Space Telescope (HST), spanning the optical and near-ultraviolet (NUV) regimes. In total, we observed 213 NUV flares on 24 nearby M dwarfs, with $\sim$27\% of them having detected optical counterparts, and found that all optical flares had NUV counterparts. We explore NUV/optical energy fractionation in M dwarf flares. Our findings reveal a slight decrease in the ratio of optical to NUV energies with increasing NUV energies, a trend in agreement with prior investigations on G-K stars' flares at higher energies. Our analysis yields an average NUV fraction of flaring time for M0-M3 dwarfs of 2.1\%, while for M4-M6 dwarfs, it is 5\%. We present an empirical relationship between NUV and optical flare energies and compare to predictions from radiative-hydrodynamic and blackbody models. We conducted a comparison of the flare frequency distribution (FFDs) of NUV and optical flares, revealing the FFDs of both NUV and optical flares exhibit comparable slopes across all spectral subtypes. NUV flares on stars affect the atmospheric chemistry, the radiation environment, and the overall potential to sustain life on any exoplanets they host. We find that early and mid-M dwarfs (M0-M5) have the potential to generate NUV flares capable of initiating abiogenesis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12310v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rishi R. Paudel, Thomas Barclay, Allison Youngblood, Elisa V. Quintana, Joshua E. Schlieder, Laura D. Vega, Emily A. Gilbert, Rachel A. Osten, Sarah Peacock, Isaiah I. Tristan, Dax L. Feliz, Patricia T. Boyd, James R. A. Davenport, Daniel Huber, Adam F. Kowalski, Teresa A. Monsue, Michele L. Silverstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Kinematic and Chemical Properties of the Close-in Planet Host Star 8 UMi</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.05120</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.05120v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A recent study by Hon et al. reported that a close-in planet around the red clump star, 8 UMi, should have been engulfed during the expansion phase of its parent star's evolution. They explained the survival of this exoplanet through a binary-merger channel for 8 UMi. The key to testing this formation scenario is to derive the true age of this star: is it an old "imposter" resulting from a binary merger, or a genuinely young red clump giant? To accomplish this, we derive kinematic and chemical properties for 8 UMi using astrometric data from {\it Gaia} DR3 and the element-abundance pattern measured from a high-resolution ($R \sim 75,000$) spectrum taken by SOPHIE. Our analysis shows that 8 UMi is a normal thin-disk star with orbital rotation speed of $\it{V}_\mathrm{\phi}=\mathrm{244.96 km s^{-1}}$, and possesses a Solar metallicity ([Fe/H] $= -0.05 \pm 0.07$) and $\alpha$-element abundance ratio ([$\alpha$/Fe] $= +0.01 \pm 0.03$). By adopting well-established relationships between age and space velocities/elemental abundances, we estimate a kinematic age of $3.50^{+3.00}_{-2.00}$ Gyr, and a chemical age of $3.25^{+2.50}_{-1.50}$ Gyr from [C/N] and $3.47 \pm 1.96$ Gyr from [Y/Mg] for 8 UMi, respectively. These estimates are consistent with the isochrone-fitting age ($1.90^{+1.15}_{-0.30}$ Gyr) of 8 UMi, but are all much younger than the timescale required in a binary-merger scenario. This result challenges the binary-merger model; the existence of such a closely orbiting exoplanet around a giant star remains a mystery yet to be resolved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.05120v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huiling Chen, Yang Huang, Wei Zhu, Timothy C. Beers, Renjing Xie, Yutao Zhou, Sharon Xuesong Wang, Wei Wang, Sofya Alexeeva, Qikang Feng, Haozhu Fu, Haining Li, Lile Wang, Huawei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exoplanet Detection : A Detailed Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09143v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The exoplanet detection is the most exciting and challenging field of astronomy. The discovery of many exoplanets has revolutionized our understanding of the formation and evolution of planetary systems and has showed new ways to search for extra terrestrial life. In recent years, some primary methods of exoplanet detection like transit, radial velocity, gravitational microlensing, direct imaging and astrometry have played a important role for the discovery of exoplanets. In this paper we explored detection methodologies with all the implications and analytics of comparison between them. Here we also discussed on different machine learning algorithms for exoplanet detection and visualization. Finally, concluded with the significant discoveries made by some missions and their implications on our understanding for the properties, environmental conditions and importance of exoplanets in the universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09143v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahima Kaushik, Aditee Mattoo, Ritesh Rastogi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Missing Metals in DQ Stars; a Compelling Clue to their Origin</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.05990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.05990v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: White dwarf stars frequently experience external pollution by heavy elements, and yet the intrinsically carbon-enriched DQ spectral class members fail to exhibit this phenomenon, representing a decades-old conundrum. This study reports a high-resolution spectroscopic search for Ca II in classical DQ white dwarfs, finding that these stars are stunted both in pollution frequency and heavy element mass fractions, relative to the wider population. Compared to other white dwarf spectral classes, the average external accretion rate is found to be at least three orders of magnitude lower in the DQ stars. Several hypotheses are considered which need to simultaneously account for i) an apparent lack of accreted metals, ii) a dearth of circumstellar planetary material, iii) an observed deficit of unevolved companions in post-common envelope binaries, iv) relatively low helium mass fractions, and remnant masses that appear smaller than for other spectral classes, v) a high incidence of strong magnetism, and vi) modestly older disk kinematics. Only one hypothesis is consistent with all these constraints, suggesting DQ white dwarfs are the progeny of binary evolution that altered both their stellar structures and their circumstellar environments. A binary origin is already suspected for the warmer and more massive DQ stars, and is proposed here as an inclusive mechanism to expose core carbon material, in a potential evolutionary unification for the entire DQ spectral class. In this picture, DQ stars are not descended from DA or DB white dwarfs that commonly host dynamically-active planetary systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.05990v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Farihi, P. Dufour, T. G. Wilson</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
