<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.EP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.EP</link>
    <description>astro-ph.EP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.EP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2024 04:00:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>An atlas of resolved spectral features in the transmission spectrum of WASP-189 b with MAROON-X</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08863</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08863v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Exoplanets in the ultra-hot Jupiter regime provide an excellent laboratory for testing the impact of stellar irradiation on the dynamics and chemical composition of gas giant atmospheres. In this study, we observed two transits of the ultra-hot Jupiter WASP-189 b with MAROON-X/Gemini-North to probe its high-altitude atmospheric layers, using strong absorption lines. We derived posterior probability distributions for the planetary and stellar parameters by calculating the stellar spectrum behind the planet at every orbital phase during the transit. This was used to correct the Rossiter-McLaughlin imprint on the transmission spectra. Using differential transmission spectroscopy, we detect strong absorption lines of Ca+, Ba+, Na, H$\alpha$, Mg, Fe, and Fe+, providing an unprecedented and detailed view of the atmospheric chemical composition. Ca+ absorption is particularly well suited for analysis through time-resolved narrow-band spectroscopy, owing to its transition lines formed in high-altitude layers. The spectral absorption lines show no significant blueshifts that would indicate high-altitude day-to-night winds, and further analysis is needed to investigate the implications for atmospheric dynamics. These high signal-to-noise observations provide a benchmark data set for testing high-resolution retrievals and the assumptions of atmospheric models. We also simulate observations of WASP-189 b with ANDES/ELT, and show that ANDES will be highly sensitive to the individual absorption lines of a myriad of elements and molecules, including TiO and CO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08863v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202349125</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>B. Prinoth, H. J. Hoeijmakers, B. M. Morris, M. Lam, D. Kitzmann, E. Sedaghati, J. V. Seidel, E. K. H. Lee, B. Thorsbro, N. W. Borsato, Y. C. Damasceno, S. Pelletier, A. Seifahrt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HST astrometry of the closest Brown Dwarfs -- II. Improved parameters and constraints on a third body</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08865v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Located at less than 2pc away, Luhman16AB (WISE.J104915.57-531906.1) is the closest pair of brown dwarfs and third closest `stellar' system to Earth. An exoplanet candidate in the Luhman16 binary system was reported in 2017 based on a weak astrometric signature in the analysis of 12 HST epochs. An additional epoch collected in 2018 and re-analysis of the data with more advanced methods further increased the significance level of the candidate, consistent with a Neptune-mass exoplanet orbiting one of the Luhman16 brown dwarf components. We report the joint analysis of these previous data together with two new astrometric HST epochs we obtained to confirm or disprove this astrometric signature. Our new analysis rules out presence of a planet orbiting one component of the Luhman16AB system for masses M &gt; 1.5 M_Nep (Neptune masses) and periods between 400 and 5000 days. However, the presence of third bodies with masses M &lt; 3 M_Nep and periods between 2 and 400 days (~1.1yrs) can not be excluded. Our measurements make significant improvements to the characterization of this sub-stellar binary, including its mass-ratio 0.8305+/-0.0006, individual component masses 35.4+/-0.2 M_Jup and 29.4+/-0.2 M_Jup (Jupiter masses), and parallax distance 1.9960pc +/- 50AU. Comparison of the masses and luminosities of Luhman16AB to several evolutionary models shows persistent discrepancies in the ages of the two components, but strengthens the case that this system is a member of the 510+/-95 Myr Oceanus Moving Group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08865v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/asna.20230158</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>L. R. Bedin (INAF-OAPD), J. Dietrich (Univ.AZ, Az. State Univ), A. J. Burgasser (UCSD), D. Apai (Univ.AZ, Lunar and Planetary Lab. Az), M. Libralato (INAF-OAPD, AURA for ESA STScI), M. Griggio (INAF-OAPD, Univ. Ferrara, STScI), C. Fontanive (Trottier Ins. for Res. on Exoplanets Montreal), D. Pourbaix (IAAULB Bruxelles)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>White Dwarf Pollution; One Star or Two?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08870v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The accretion of tidally disrupted planetary bodies is the current consensus model for the presence of photospheric metals commonly detected in white dwarfs. While most dynamical studies have considered a single star and associated planetary instabilities, several investigations have instead considered the influence of widely-bound stellar companions as potential drivers of white dwarf pollution. This study examines the prevalence of wide binaries among polluted white dwarfs using Gaia DR3 astrometry, where three samples are investigated: 71 DAZ stars with metals detected in the ultraviolet using Hubble, and two groups of DZ stars identified via SDSS spectroscopy, comprised of 116 warmer and 101 cooler sources. Each sample was searched for spatially-resolved, co-moving companions, and compared to the same analysis of thousands of field white dwarfs within overlapping regions of the Gaia HR diagram. The wide binary fraction of the DAZ sample is $10.6_{-3.2}^{+3.9}$ per cent, and within $1 \sigma$ of the corresponding field. However, the search yields wide binary fractions of less than 1.8 per cent for the two independent DZ star catalogues, which are each distinct from their fields by more than $3 \sigma$. Both sets of results support that pollution in white dwarfs is not the result of stellar companions, and the delivery of metals to white dwarf surfaces is caused by major planets. The discrepancy between the DAZ and DZ star wide binary fractions cannot be caused by white dwarf spectral evolution, suggesting these two populations may have distinct planetary architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08870v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiba Tu Noor, Jay Farihi, Mark Hollands, Silvia Toonen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Friends not Foes: Strong Correlation between Inner Super-Earths and Outer Gas Giants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08873v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The connection between outer gas giants and inner super-Earths reflects their formation and evolutionary histories. Past work exploring this link has suggested a tentative positive correlation between these two populations, but these studies have been limited by small sample sizes and in some cases sample biases. Here we take a new look at this connection with a sample of 184 super-Earth systems with publicly available radial velocity data and fully resolved outer gas giants. We calculate the frequency of outer gas giants (GG) in super-Earth (SE) systems, dividing our sample into metal-rich ([Fe/H] $&gt;$ 0) and metal-poor ([Fe/H]$\leq$0) hosts. We find P(GG$|$SE, [Fe/H]$&gt;$0) = 28.0$^{+4.9}_{-4.6}\%$ and P(GG$|$SE, [Fe/H]$\leq$0) = 4.5$^{+2.6}_{-1.9}\%$. Comparing these conditional occurrence rates to field giant occurrence rates from Wittenmyer et al. 2020, we show that there is a distinct positive correlation between inner super-Earths and outer gas giants for metal-rich host stars at the 2.5$\sigma$ level, but this correlation disappears for metal-poor systems. We further find that, around metal-rich stars, the GG/SE correlation enhances for systems with giants that are more distant (beyond 3 AU) and/or more eccentric ($e &gt; 0.2$), while gas giant multiplicity does not appear to affect the level of correlation. Such trends again disappear around metal-poor stars with the exception of systems of multiple giants in which we observe an anti-correlation. Our findings highlight the critical role metallicity (disk solid budget) plays in shaping the overall planetary architecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08873v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marta L. Bryan, Eve J. Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MINDS: The JWST MIRI Mid-INfrared Disk Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09210v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The study of protoplanetary disks has become increasingly important with the Kepler satellite finding that exoplanets are ubiquitous around stars in our galaxy and the discovery of enormous diversity in planetary system architectures and planet properties. High-resolution near-IR and ALMA images show strong evidence for ongoing planet formation in young disks. The JWST MIRI mid-INfrared Disk Survey (MINDS) aims to (1) investigate the chemical inventory in the terrestrial planet-forming zone across stellar spectral type, (2) follow the gas evolution into the disk dispersal stage, and (3) study the structure of protoplanetary and debris disks in the thermal mid-IR. The MINDS survey will thus build a bridge between the chemical inventory of disks and the properties of exoplanets. The survey comprises 52 targets (Herbig Ae stars, T Tauri stars, very low-mass stars and young debris disks). We primarily obtain MIRI/MRS spectra with high S/N (~100-500) covering the complete wavelength range from 4.9 to 27.9 {\mu}m. For a handful of selected targets we also obtain NIRSpec IFU high resolution spectroscopy (2.87-5.27 {\mu}m). We will search for signposts of planet formation in thermal emission of micron-sized dust - information complementary to near-IR scattered light emission from small dust grains and emission from large dust in the submillimeter wavelength domain. We will also study the spatial structure of disks in three key systems that have shown signposts for planet formation, TW Hya and HD 169142 using the MIRI coronagraph at 15.5 {\mu}m and 10.65 {\mu}m respectively and PDS70 using NIRCam imaging in the 1.87 {\mu}m narrow and the 4.8 {\mu}m medium band filter. ...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09210v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Henning, Inga Kamp, Matthias Samland, Aditya M. Arabhavi, Jayatee Kanwar, Ewine F. van Dishoeck, Manuel Guedel, Pierre-Olivier Lagage, Christoffel Waelkens, Alain Abergel, Olivier Absil, David Barrado, Anthony Boccaletti, Jeroen Bouwman, Alessio Caratti o Garatti, Vincent Geers, Adrian M. Glauser, Fred Lahuis, Cyrine Nehme, Goeran Olofsson, Eric Pantin, Tom P. Ray, Bart Vandenbussche, L. B. F. M. Waters, Gillian Wright, Valentin Christiaens, Riccardo Franceschi, Danny Gasman, Rodrigo Guadarrama, Hyerin Jang, Maria Morales-Calderon, Nicole Pawellek, Giulia Perotti, Donna Rodgers-Lee, Juergen Schreiber, Kamber Schwarz, Benoit Tabone, Milou Temmink, Marissa Vlasblom, Luis Colina, Thomas R. Greve, Goeran Oestlin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A secular solar system resonance that disrupts the dominant cycle in Earth's orbital eccentricity (g2-g5): Implications for astrochronology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09332v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The planets' gravitational interaction causes rhythmic changes in Earth's orbital parameters (also called Milankovi\'c cycles), which have powerful applications in geology and astrochronology. For instance, the primary astronomical eccentricity cycle due to the secular frequency term (g2-g5) (~405 kyr in the recent past) utilized in deep-time analyses is dominated by Venus' and Jupiter's orbits, aka long eccentricity cycle. The widely accepted and long-held view is that (g2-g5) was practically stable in the past and may hence be used as a "metronome" to reconstruct accurate ages and chronologies. However, using state-of-the-art integrations of the solar system, we show here that (g2-g5) can become unstable over long time scales, without major changes in, or destabilization of, planetary orbits. The (g2-g5) disruption is due to the secular resonance $\sigma_{12}$ = (g1 - g2) + (s1 - s2), a major contributor to solar system chaos. We demonstrate that entering/exiting the $\sigma_{12}$ resonance is a common phenomenon on long time scales, occurring in ~40% of our solutions. During $\sigma_{12}$-resonance episodes, (g2-g5) is very weak or absent and Earth's orbital eccentricity and climate-forcing spectrum are unrecognizable compared to the recent past. Our results have fundamental implications for geology and astrochronology, as well as climate forcing because the paradigm that the longest Milankovi\'c cycle dominates Earth's astronomical forcing, is stable, and has a period of ~405 kyr requires revision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09332v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Richard E. Zeebe, Margriet L. Lantink</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New constraints on Triton's atmosphere from the 6 October 2022 stellar occultation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09464v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The atmosphere of Triton was probed directly by observing a ground-based stellar occultation on 6 October 2022. This rare event yielded 23 positive light curves collected from 13 separate observation stations contributing to our campaign. The significance of this event lies in its potential to directly validate the modest pressure fluctuation on Triton, a phenomenon not definitively verified by previous observations, including only five stellar occultations, and the Voyager 2 radio occultation in 1989. Using an approach consistent with a comparable study, we precisely determined a surface pressure of $14.07_{-0.13}^{+0.21}~\mathrm{\mu bar}$ in 2022. This new pressure rules out any significant monotonic variation in pressure between 2017 and 2022 through direct observations, as it is in alignment with the 2017 value. Additionally, both the pressures in 2017 and 2022 align with the 1989 value. This provides further support for the conclusion drawn from the previous volatile transport model simulation, which is consistent with the observed alignment between the pressures in 1989 and 2017; that is to say, the pressure fluctuation is modest. Moreover, this conclusion suggests the existence of a northern polar cap extended down to at least $45^\circ$N$-60^\circ$N and the presence of nitrogen between $30^\circ$S and $0^\circ$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09464v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202348460</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ye Yuan, Chen Zhang, Fan Li, Jian Chen, Yanning Fu, Chunhai Bai, Xin Gao, Yong Wang, Tuhong Zhong, Yixing Gao, Liang Wang, Donghua Chen, Yixing Zhang, Yang Zhang, Wenpeng Xie, Shupi Zhang, Ding Liu, Jun Cao, Xiangdong Yin, Xiaojun Mo, Jing Liu, Xinru Han, Tong Liu, Yuqiang Chen, Zhendong Gao, Xiang Zeng, Guihua Niu, Xiansheng Zheng, Yuchen Lin, Peiyu Ye, Weitang Liang, Chengcheng Zhu, Zhiqiang Hu, Jianguo He, Wei Zhang, Yue Chen, Zhuo Cheng, Yang Zhang, Tianrui Sun, Chenyang Guo, Yue Lu, Jiajun Lin, Wei Tan, Jia Zhou, Jun Xu, Jun He, Jiahui Ye, Delai Li, Shuai Zhang, Qingyue Qu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Venus as an Anchor Point for Planetary Habitability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08830</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08830v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A major focus of the planetary science and astrobiology community is the understanding of planetary habitability, including the myriad factors that control the evolution and sustainability of temperate surface environments such as that of Earth. The few substantial terrestrial planetary atmospheres within the Solar System serve as a critical resource in studying these habitability factors, from which models can be constructed for application to extrasolar planets. The recent Astronomy and Astrophysics and Planetary Science and Astrobiology Decadal Surveys both emphasise the need for an improved understanding of planetary habitability as an essential goal within the context of astrobiology. The divergence in climate evolution of Venus and Earth provides a major, accessible basis for understanding how the habitability of large rocky worlds evolves with time and what conditions limit the boundaries of habitability. Here, we argue that Venus can be considered an "anchor point" for understanding planetary habitability within the context of terrestrial planet evolution. We discuss the major factors that have influenced the respective evolutionary pathways of Venus and Earth, how these factors might be weighted in their overall influence, and the measurements that will shed further light on their impacts of these worlds' histories. We further discuss the importance of Venus with respect to both of the recent decadal surveys, and how these community consensus reports can help shape the exploration of Venus in the coming decades.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08830v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephen R. Kane, Paul K. Byrne</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of Electron Precipitation on Brown Dwarf Atmospheres and the Missing Auroral H$_{3}^{+}$ Emission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08852v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent observations have demonstrated that very-low mass stars and brown dwarfs are capable of sustaining strong magnetic fields despite their cool and neutral atmospheres. These kG field strengths are inferred based on strong highly circularly polarized GHz radio emission, a consequence of the electron cyclotron maser instability. Crucially, these observations imply the existence of energetic non-thermal electron populations, associated with strong current systems, as are found in the auroral regions of the magnetized planets of the Solar System. Intense auroral electron precipitation will lead to electron collisions with the H$_{2}$ gas that should ultimately generate the ion H$_{3}^{+}$. With this motivation, we targeted a sample of ultracool dwarfs, known to exhibit signatures associated with aurorae, in search of the K-band emission features of H$_{3}^{+}$ using the Keck telescopes on Mauna Kea. From our sample of 9 objects, we found no clear indication of H$_{3}^{+}$ emission features in our low-medium resolution spectra (R$\sim$3600). We also modeled the impact of an auroral electron beam on a brown dwarf atmosphere, determining the depth at which energetic beams deposit their energy and drive particle impact ionization. We find that the H$_{3}^{+}$ non-detections can be explained by electron beams of typical energies $\gtrsim$2-10~keV, which penetrate deeply enough that any H$_{3}^{+}$ produced is chemically destroyed before radiating energy through its infrared transitions. Strong electron beams could further explain the lack of UV detections, and suggest that most or nearly all of the precipitating auroral energy must ultimately emerge as thermal emissions deep in brown dwarf atmospheres.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08852v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Sebastian Pineda, Gregg Hallinan, Jean Michel Desert, Leon K. Harding</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Based Dynamics Identification and Linearization of Orbital Problems using Koopman Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08965v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The study of the Two-Body and Circular Restricted Three-Body Problems in the field of aerospace engineering and sciences is deeply important because they help describe the motion of both celestial and artificial satellites. With the growing demand for satellites and satellite formation flying, fast and efficient control of these systems is becoming ever more important. Global linearization of these systems allows engineers to employ methods of control in order to achieve these desired results. We propose a data-driven framework for simultaneous system identification and global linearization of both the Two-Body Problem and Circular Restricted Three-Body Problem via deep learning-based Koopman Theory, i.e., a framework that can identify the underlying dynamics and globally linearize it into a linear time-invariant (LTI) system. The linear Koopman operator is discovered through purely data-driven training of a Deep Neural Network with a custom architecture. This paper displays the ability of the Koopman operator to generalize to various other Two-Body systems without the need for retraining. We also demonstrate the capability of the same architecture to be utilized to accurately learn a Koopman operator that approximates the Circular Restricted Three-Body Problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08965v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George Nehma, Madhur Tiwari, Manasvi Lingam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing MOND on small bodies in the remote solar system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09555v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Modified Newtonian dynamics (MOND), which postulates a breakdown of Newton's laws of gravity/dynamics below some critical acceleration threshold, can explain many otherwise puzzling observational phenomena on galactic scales. MOND competes with the hypothesis of dark matter, which successfully explains the cosmic microwave background and large-scale structure. Here we provide the first solar-system test of MOND that probes the sub-critical acceleration regime. Using the Bekenstein-Milgrom AQUAL formulation, we simulate the evolution of myriads of test particles (planetesimals or comets) born in the trans-Neptunian region and scattered by the giant planets over the lifetime of the Sun to heliocentric distances of $10^2$-$10^5$ au. We include the effects of the Galactic tidal field and passing stars. While Newtonian simulations reproduce the distribution of binding energies of long-period and Oort-cloud comets detectable from Earth, MOND-based simulations do not. This conclusion is robust to plausible changes in the migration history of the planets, the migration history of the Sun, the MOND transition function, effects of the Sun's birth cluster, and the fading properties of long-period comets. For the most popular version of AQUAL, characterized by a gradual transition between the Newtonian and MOND regimes, our MOND-based simulations also fail to reproduce the orbital distribution of trans-Neptunian objects in the detached disk (perihelion &gt; 38 au). Our results do not rule out some MOND theories more elaborate than AQUAL, in which non-Newtonian effects are screened on small spatial scales, at small masses, or in external gravitational fields comparable in strength to the critical acceleration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09555v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Vokrouhlick\'y, David Nesvorn\'y, Scott Tremaine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Triage of the Gaia DR3 astrometric orbits. II. A census of white dwarfs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.15143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.15143v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The third data release of Gaia was the first to include orbital solutions assuming non-single stars. Here, we apply the astrometric triage technique of Shahaf et al. to identify binary star systems with companions that are not single main-sequence stars. Gaia's synthetic photometry of these binaries is used to distinguish between systems likely to have white-dwarf companions and those that may be hierarchical triples. The study uncovered a population of nearly 3200 binaries, characterised by orbital separations on the order of an astronomical unit, in which the faint astrometric companion is probably a white dwarf. This sample increases the number of orbitally solved binary systems of this type by about two orders of magnitude. Remarkably, over 110 of these systems exhibit significant ultraviolet excess flux, confirming this classification and, in some cases, indicating their relatively young cooling ages. We show that the sample is not currently represented in synthetic binary populations, and is not easily reproduced by available binary population synthesis codes. Therefore, it challenges current binary evolution models, offering a unique opportunity to gain insights into the processes governing white-dwarf formation, binary evolution, and mass transfer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.15143v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Shahaf, N. Hallakoun, T. Mazeh, S. Ben-Ami, P. Rekhi, K. El-Badry, S. Toonen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The POKEMON Speckle Survey of Nearby M Dwarfs. III. The Stellar Multiplicity Rate of M Dwarfs within 15 pc</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.14703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.14703v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: M dwarfs are ubiquitous in our galaxy, and the rate at which they host stellar companions, and the properties of these companions, provides a window into the formation and evolution of the star(s), and of any planets that they may host. The Pervasive Overview of 'Kompanions' of Every M dwarf in Our Neighborhood (POKEMON) speckle survey of nearby M dwarfs is volume-limited from M0V through M9V out to 15 pc, with additional targets at larger distances. In total, 1125 stars were observed, and 455 of these are within the volume-limited, 15-pc sample of M-dwarf primaries. When we combine the speckle observations with known companions from the literature, we find that the stellar multiplicity rate of M dwarfs within 15 pc is 23.7% plus or minus 2.0%, and that the companion rate is 29.0% plus or minus 2.1%. We also find that the projected separation distribution for multiples that are known to host planets peaks at 198 au, while the distribution for multiples that are not yet known to host planets peaks at 5.57 au. This result suggests that the presence of close-in stellar companions inhibits the formation of M-dwarf planetary systems, similar to what has been found for FGK stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.14703v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Catherine A. Clark, Gerard T. van Belle, Elliott P. Horch, David R. Ciardi, Kaspar von Braun, Brian A. Skiff, Jennifer G. Winters, Michael B. Lund, Mark E. Everett, Zachary D. Hartman, Joe Llama</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
