<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.EP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.EP</link>
    <description>astro-ph.EP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.EP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 04:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Hazardous Asteroids Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02150v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hazardous asteroid has been one of the concerns for humankind as fallen asteroid on earth could cost a huge impact on the society.Monitoring these objects could help predict future impact events, but such efforts are hindered by the large numbers of objects that pass in the Earth's vicinity. The aim of this project is to use machine learning and deep learning to accurately classify hazardous asteroids. A total of ten methods which consist of five machine learning algorithms and five deep learning models are trained and evaluated to find the suitable model that solves the issue. We experiment on two datasets, one from Kaggle and one we extracted from a web service called NeoWS which is a RESTful web service from NASA that provides information about near earth asteroids, it updates every day. In overall, the model is tested on two datasets with different features to find the most accurate model to perform the classification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02150v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thai Duy Quy, Alvin Buana, Josh Lee, Rakha Asyrofi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Earth-Mass Planet and a Brown Dwarf in Orbit Around a White Dwarf</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02157</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02157v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Terrestrial planets born beyond 1-3 AU have been theorized to avoid being engulfed during the red-giant phases of their host stars. Nevertheless, only a few gas-giant planets have been observed around white dwarfs (WDs) -- the end product left behind by a red giant. Here we report on evidence that the lens system that produced the microlensing event KMT-2020-BLG-0414 is composed of a WD orbited by an Earth-mass planet and a brown dwarf (BD) companion, as shown by the non-detection of the lens flux using Keck Adaptive Optics (AO). From microlensing orbital motion constraints, we determine the planet to be a $1.9\pm0.2$ Earth-mass ($M_\oplus$) planet at a physical separation of $2.1\pm0.2$ au from the WD during the event. By considering the system evolutionary history, we determine the BD companion to have a projected separation of 22 au from the WD, and reject an alternative model that places the BD at 0.2 au. Given planetary orbital expansion during the final evolutionary stages of the host star, this Earth-mass planet may have existed in an initial orbit close to 1 au, thereby offering a glimpse into the possible survival of planet Earth in the distant future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02157v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keming Zhang, Weicheng Zang, Kareem El-Badry, Jessica R. Lu, Joshua S. Bloom, Eric Agol, B. Scott Gaudi, Quinn Konopacky, Natalie LeBaron, Shude Mao, Sean Terry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational instability in a planet-forming disk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02196v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The canonical theory for planet formation in circumstellar disks proposes that planets are grown from initially much smaller seeds. The long-considered alternative theory proposes that giant protoplanets can be formed directly from collapsing fragments of vast spiral arms induced by gravitational instability -- if the disk is gravitationally unstable. For this to be possible, the disk must be massive compared to the central star: a disk-to-star mass ratio of 1/10 is widely held as the rough threshold for triggering gravitational instability, inciting significant non-Keplerian dynamics and generating prominent spiral arms. While estimating disk masses has historically been challenging, the motion of the gas can reveal the presence of gravitational instability through its effect on the disk velocity structure. Here we present kinematic evidence of gravitational instability in the disk around AB Aurigae, using deep observations of 13CO and C18O line emission with the Atacama Large Millimeter/submillimeter Array (ALMA). The observed kinematic signals strongly resemble predictions from simulations and analytic modelling. From quantitative comparisons, we infer a disk mass of up to 1/3 the stellar mass enclosed within 1" to 5" on the sky.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02196v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41586-024-07877-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jessica Speedie, Ruobing Dong, Cassandra Hall, Cristiano Longarini, Benedetta Veronesi, Teresa Paneque-Carre\~no, Giuseppe Lodato, Ya-Wen Tang, Richard Teague, Jun Hashimoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital Architectures of Planet-Hosting Binaries III. Testing Mutual Inclinations of Stellar and Planetary Orbits in Triple-Star Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02223v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Transiting planets in multiple-star systems, especially high-order multiples, make up a small fraction of the known planet population but provide unique opportunities to study the environments in which planets would have formed. Planet-hosting binaries have been shown to have an abundance of systems in which the stellar orbit aligns with the orbit of the transiting planet, which could give insights into the planet formation process in such systems. We investigate here if this trend of alignment extends to planet-hosting triple-star systems. We present long-term astrometric monitoring of a novel sample of triple-star systems that host Kepler transiting planets. We measured orbit arcs in 21 systems, including 12 newly identified triples, from a homogeneous analysis of our Keck adaptive optics data and, for some systems, Gaia astrometry. We examine the orbital alignment within the nine most compact systems ($\lesssim500$ au), testing if either (or both) of the stellar orbits align with the edge-on orbits of their transiting planets. Our statistical sample of triple systems shows a tendency toward alignment, especially when assessing the alignment probability using stellar orbital inclinations computed from full orbital fits, but is formally consistent with isotropic orbits. Two-population tests where half of the stellar orbits are described by a planet-hosting-binary-like moderately aligned distribution give the best match when the other half (non-planet-hosting) has a Kozai-like misaligned distribution. Overall, our results suggest that our sample of triple-star planet-hosting systems are not fully coplanar systems and have at most one plane of alignment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02223v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elise L. Evans, Trent J. Dupuy, Kendall Sullivan, Adam L. Kraus, Daniel Huber, Michael J. Ireland, Megan Ansdell, Rajika L. Kuruwita, Raquel A. Martinez, Mackenna L. Wood</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Wanderer: Charting WASP-77A b's Formation and Migration Using a System-Wide Inventory of Carbon and Oxygen Abundances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02286v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The elemental and isotopic abundances of volatiles like carbon, oxygen, and nitrogen may trace a planet's formation location relative to H$_2$O, CO$_2$, CO, NH$_3$, and N$_2$ "snowlines", or the distance from the star at which these volatile elements sublimate. By comparing the C/O and $^{12}$C/$^{13}$C ratios measured in giant exoplanet atmospheres to complementary measurements of their host stars, we can determine whether the planet inherited stellar abundances from formation inside the volatile snowlines, or non-stellar C/O and $^{13}$C enrichment characteristic of formation beyond the snowlines. To date, there are still only a handful of exoplanet systems where we can make a direct comparison of elemental and isotopic CNO abundances between an exoplanet and its host star. Here, we present a $^{12}$C/$^{13}$C abundance analysis for host star WASP-77A (whose hot Jupiter's $^{12}$C/$^{13}$C abundance was recently measured). We use MARCS stellar atmosphere models and the radiative transfer code TurboSpectrum to generate synthetic stellar spectra for isotopic abundance calculations. We find a $^{12}$C/$^{13}$C ratio of $51\pm 6$ for WASP-77A, which is sub-solar ($\sim 91$) but may still indicate $^{13}$C-enrichment in its companion planet WASP-77A b ($^{12}$C/$^{13}$C = 26 $\pm$ 16, previously reported). Together with the inventory of carbon and oxygen abundances in both the host and companion planet, these chemical constraints point to WASP-77A b's formation beyond the H$_2$O and CO$_2$ snowlines and provide chemical evidence for the planet's migration to its current location $\sim$0.024 AU from its host star.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02286v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad7020</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>David R. Coria, Neda Hejazi, Ian J. M. Crossfield, Maleah Rhem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Site Selection for the Second Flyeye Telescope: A Simulation Study for Optimizing Near-Earth Object Discovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02329v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The European Space Agency (ESA) is developing a network of wide-field survey telescopes, named Flyeye, to improve the discovery of Near-Earth Objects (NEOs). The first telescope in the network will be located in the Northern Hemisphere on Mount Mufara (Italy), and a second Flyeye telescope, featuring increased detection capabilities, has just started the critical design phase. The potential location for the second Flyeye telescope is investigated by performing simulations of NEOs on impacting trajectories. Approximately 3000 impacting asteroids of two absolute magnitudes (H=25 and H=28) were propagated and tested for detectability by major existing surveys (Catalina, Pan-STARRS, ATLAS), the upcoming Vera Rubin Observatory (LSST), and possible Flyeye locations. Chile, South Africa, and a second facility in the Northern Hemisphere were considered. For each observatory, their past or planned pointing strategies were taken into account in the simulation. Before LSST deployment, a single Flyeye in the Southern Hemisphere performs similarly to a telescope in the Northern Hemisphere. When combined, having one telescope in the north and one in the south maximizes detections and number of unique objects detected. After LSST, southern and northern Flyeye telescopes remain complementary. Overall, simulations show that a second Flyeye in the south complements a Flyeye telescope in the north both before and after LSST. A Flyeye located at La Silla would take advantage of the excellent atmospheric conditions, while allowing a balance of assets across hemispheres.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02329v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.icarus.2024.116281</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Icarus, 116281 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>D. F\"ohring, L. Conversi, M. Micheli, E. D\"olling, P. Ramirez Moreta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do anomalously-dense hot Jupiters orbit stealth binary stars?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02639v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Wide Angle Search for Planets (WASP) survey used transit photometry to discover nearly 200 gas-giant exoplanets and derive their planetary and stellar parameters. Reliable determination of the planetary density depends on accurate measurement of the planet's radius, obtained from the transit depth and photodynamical determination of the stellar radius. The stellar density, and hence the stellar radius are typically determined in a model-independent way from the star's reflex orbital acceleration and the transit profile. Additional flux coming from the system due to a bright, undetected stellar binary companion can, however, potentially dilute the transit curve and radial velocity signal, leading to under-estimation of the planet's mass and radius, and to overestimation of the planet's density. In this study, we cross-check the published radii of all the WASP planet host stars, determined from their transit profiles and radial-velocity curves, against radiometric measurements of stellar radii derived from their angular diameters (via the Infrared Flux method) and trigonometric parallaxes. We identify eight systems showing radiometric stellar radii significantly greater than their published photodynamical values: WASPs 20, 85, 86, 103, 105, 129, 144 and 171. We investigate these systems in more detail to establish plausible ranges of angular and radial-velocity separations within which such "stealth binaries" could evade detection, and deduce their likely orbital periods, mass ratios, and flux ratios. After accounting for the dilution of transit depth and radial velocity amplitude, we find that on average, the planetary densities for the identified stealth binary systems should be reduced by a factor of 1.3.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02639v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tanvi Goswamy, Andrew Collier Cameron, Thomas G. Wilson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Horseshoes and spiral waves: capturing the 3D flow induced by a low-mass planet analytically</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02687</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02687v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The key difficulty faced by 2D models for planet-disc interaction is in appropriately accounting for the impact of the disc's vertical structure on the dynamics. 3D effects are often mimicked via softening of the planet's potential; however, the planet-induced flow and torques often depend strongly on the choice of softening length. We show that for a linear adiabatic flow perturbing a vertically isothermal disc, there is a particular vertical average of the 3D equations of motion which exactly reproduces 2D fluid equations for arbitrary adiabatic index. There is a strong connection here with the Lubow-Pringle 2D mode of the disc. Correspondingly, we find a simple, general prescription for the consistent treatment of planetary potentials embedded within '2D' discs. The flow induced by a low-mass planet involves large-scale excited spiral density waves which transport angular momentum radially away from the planet, and 'horseshoe streamlines' within the co-orbital region. We derive simple linear equations governing the flow which locally capture both effects faithfully simultaneously. We present an accurate co-orbital flow solution allowing for inexpensive future study of corotation torques, and predict the vertical structure of the co-orbital flow and horseshoe region width for different values of adiabatic index, as well as the vertical dependence of the initial shock location. We find strong agreement with the flow computed in 3D numerical simulations, and with 3D one-sided Lindblad torque estimates, which are a factor of 2 to 3 times lower than values from previous 2D simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02687v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua J. Brown, Gordon I. Ogilvie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New gravity field of comet 67P/C-G based on Rosetta's Doppler and optical data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02692v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We provide a new gravity field of Comet 67P-C/G up to degree 4. We detect mass heterogeneity in the comet nucleus. The loss of mass is restimated at 0.28\% of the comet's total mass (3 times larger than previous estimate). Comparison of the gravity field between pre- and post-perihelion allowed us to measure a shift in the comet's center of gravity of 35 m northward, attributed to ice sublimation process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02692v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julien Laurent-Varin, Th\'eo James, Jean-Charles Marty, Laurent Jorda, Sebastien Le Maistre, Robert Gaskell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oxygen Isotope Exchange Between Dust Aggregates and Ambient Nebular Gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02736v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Meteorites and their components exhibit a diverse range of oxygen isotope compositions, and the isotopic exchange timescale between dust grains and ambient gas is a key parameter for understanding the spatiotemporal evolution of the solar nebula. As dust grains existed as macroscopic aggregates in the solar nebula, it is necessary to consider the isotopic exchange timescales for these aggregates. Here, we theoretically estimate the isotope exchange timescales between dust aggregates and ambient vapor. The isotope exchange process between aggregates and ambient vapor is divided into four processes: (i) supply of gas molecules to the aggregate surface, (ii) diffusion of molecules within the aggregate, (iii) isotope exchange on the surface of constituent particles, and (iv) isotope diffusion within the particles. We evaluate these timescales and assess which one becomes the rate-determining step. We reveal that the isotope exchange timescale is approximately the same as that of the constituent particles when the aggregate radius is smaller than the critical value, which is a few centimeters when considering the exchange reaction between amorphous forsterite aggregates and water vapor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02736v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sota Arakawa, Daiki Yamamoto, Lily Ishizaki, Tamami Okamoto, Noriyuki Kawasaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Systematic Survey of Moon-Forming Giant Impacts. II. Rotating bodies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02746v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the leading theory of lunar formation, known as the giant impact hypothesis, a collision between two planet-size objects resulted in a young Earth surrounded by a circumplanetary debris disk from which the Moon later accreted. The range of giant impacts that could conceivably explain the Earth-Moon system is limited by the set of known physical and geochemical constraints. However, while several distinct Moon-forming impact scenarios have been proposed -- from small, high-velocity impactors to low-velocity mergers between equal-mass objects -- none of these scenarios have been successful at explaining the full set of known constraints, especially without invoking one or more controversial post-impact processes. Allowing for pre-impact rotation of the colliding bodies has been suggested as an avenue which may produce more promising collision outcomes. However, to date, only limited studies of pre-impact rotation have been conducted. Therefore, in the second paper of this series, we focus on pairwise impacts between rotating bodies. Using non-rotating collisions as a baseline, we systematically study the effects of rotation on collision outcomes. We consider nine distinct rotation configurations and a range of rotation rates up to the rotational stability limit. Notably, we identify a population of collisions that can produce low post-impact angular momentum budgets and massive, iron-poor protolunar disks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02746v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Meier, Christian Reinhardt, Miles Timpe, Joachim Stadel, Ben Moore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RISTRETTO: reflected-light exoplanet spectroscopy at the diffraction limit of the VLT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02875v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: RISTRETTO is a visible high-resolution spectrograph fed by an extreme adaptive optics (AO) system, to be proposed as a visitor instrument on ESO VLT. The main science goal of RISTRETTO is to pioneer the detection and atmospheric characterisation of exoplanets in reflected light, in particular the temperate rocky planet Proxima b. RISTRETTO will be able to measure albedos and detect atmospheric features in a number of exoplanets orbiting nearby stars for the first time. It will do so by combining a high-contrast AO system working at the diffraction limit of the telescope to a high-resolution spectrograph, via a 7-spaxel integral-field unit (IFU) feeding single-mode fibers. Further science cases for RISTRETTO include the study of accreting protoplanets such as PDS70b/c through spectrally-resolved H-alpha emission, and spatially-resolved studies of Solar System objects such as icy moons and the ice giants Uranus and Neptune. The project is in the manufacturing phase for the spectrograph sub-system, and the preliminary design phase for the AO front-end. Specific developments for RISTRETTO include a novel coronagraphic IFU combining a phase-induced amplitude apodizer (PIAA) to a 3D-printed microlens array feeding a bundle of single-mode fibers. It also features an XAO system with a dual wavefront sensor aiming at high robustness and sensitivity, including to pupil fragmentation. RISTRETTO is a pathfinder instrument in view of similar developments at the ELT, in particular the SCAO-IFU mode of ELT-ANDES and the future ELT-PCS instrument.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02875v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1117/12.3020142</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proc. SPIE 13096, Ground-based and Airborne Instrumentation for Astronomy X, 130961I (18 July 2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Christophe Lovis, Nicolas Blind, Bruno Chazelas, Muskan Shinde, Maddalena Bugatti, Nathana\"el Restori, Isaac Dinis, Ludovic Genolet, Ian Hughes, Micha\"el Sordet, Robin Schnell, Samuel Rihs, Adrien Crausaz, Martin Turbet, Nicolas Billot, Thierry Fusco, Benoit Neichel, Jean-Fran\c{c}ois Sauvage, Pablo Santos Diaz, Mathilde Houelle, Joshua Blackman, Audrey Lanotte, Jonas K\"uhn, Janis Hagelberg, Olivier Guyon, Patrice Martinez, Alain Spang, Christoph Mordasini, David Ehrenreich, Brice-Olivier Demory, Emeline Bolmont</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recommended receiver papers for ALMA users</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02164v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Atacama Large Millimetre/submillimetre Array (ALMA) receivers and technical papers are cited fewer than once in every six publications. This citation shortage is impeding the development of future (sub)millimetre instruments. In an effort to facilitate the correct citations of ALMA receivers and technical papers, this memo provides a comprehensive list of papers for the scientific community. This list was produced in discussion with the scientific and instrumentalist community, based on a June 2024 survey at the European Southern Observatory workshop on the ALMA Wideband Sensitivity Upgrade, as well as with the ALMA technical staff. We now encourage the community to enhance their already-excellent ALMA science with the appropriate references to ensure future (sub)millimetre instrumentation can keep addressing the key questions about our Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02164v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom Bakx, John Conway</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$1/f$ Noise in the Heliosphere: A Target for PUNCH Science</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02255v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a broad review of 1/f noise observations in the heliosphere, and discuss and complement the theoretical background of generic 1/f models as relevant to NASA's Polarimeter to Unify the Corona and Heliosphere (PUNCH) mission. First observed in the voltage fluctuations of vacuum tubes, the scale-invariant 1/f spectrum has since been identified across a wide array of natural and artificial systems, including heart rate fluctuations and loudness patterns in musical compositions. In the solar wind, the interplanetary magnetic field trace spectrum exhibits 1/f scaling within the frequency range from around 2e-6 Hz to 1e-4 Hz at 1 au. One compelling mechanism for the generation of 1/f noise is the superposition principle, where a composite 1/f spectrum arises from the superposition of a collection of individual power-law spectra characterized by a scale-invariant distribution of correlation times. In the context of the solar wind, such a superposition could originate from scale-invariant reconnection processes in the corona. Further observations have detected 1/f signatures in the photosphere and corona at frequency ranges compatible with those observed at 1 au, suggesting an even lower altitude origin of 1/f spectrum in the solar dynamo itself. This hypothesis is bolstered by dynamo experiments and simulations that indicate inverse cascade activities, which can be linked to successive flux tube reconnections beneath the corona, and are known to generate 1/f noise possibly through nonlocal interactions at the largest scales. Conversely, models positing in situ generation of 1/f signals face causality issues in explaining the low-frequency portion of the 1/f spectrum. Understanding 1/f noise in the solar wind may inform central problems in heliospheric physics, such as the solar dynamo, coronal heating, the origin of the solar wind, and the nature of interplanetary turbulence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02255v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaming Wang, William H. Matthaeus, Rohit Chhiber, Sohom Roy, Rayta A. Pradata, Francesco Pecora, Yan Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Astrochemistry on Galactic scales</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02537v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The increasing number of observations towards different environments in the Milky Way, as well as theoretical and experimental works, are improving our knowledge of the astrochemical processes in the interstellar medium (ISM). In this chapter we report some of the main projects to study the chemical complexity and isotopic ratios across the Galaxy. High-sensitivity spectral surveys covering broad bandwidths towards Galactic Center molecular clouds (e.g. G+0.693-0.027) and star-forming regions (e.g. the hot core G31.41+0.31) are revealing very rich astrochemical reservoirs, which include molecules of prebiotic interest. At the same time, isotopic ratios (e.g. $^{12}$C/$^{13}$C and $^{14}$N/$^{15}$N) can give important information on the Galactic chemical evolution, as well as on chemical local processes due to the physical conditions of the molecular clouds. We also highlight the role of cosmic rays as a key agent affecting the interstellar chemistry described above.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02537v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Colzi, V. M. Rivilla, M. T. Beltr\'an, C. Y. Law, E. Redaelli, M. Padovani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the impact of the vertical structure of Martian water ice clouds on nadir atmospheric retrievals from simultaneous EMM/EXI and TGO/ACS-MIR observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14993</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14993v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Retrieving the optical depth of the Martian clouds ($\tau_\mathrm{cld}$) is a powerful way to monitor their spatial and temporal evolution. However, such retrievals from nadir imagery rely on several assumptions, including the vertical structure of the clouds in the atmosphere. Here we compare the results of cloud optical depth retrievals at 320 nm from the Emirates eXploration Imager (EXI) onboard the Emirates Mars Mission (EMM) "Hope" orbiter performed using a basic uniform cloud profile used in previous studies and using derived cloud profiles obtained from near-simultaneous Solar Occultation observations in the 3.1-3.4 $\mu$m spectral range from the Middle-Infrared channel of the Atmospheric Chemistry Suite (ACS) instrument onboard the ESA Trace Gas Orbiter (TGO). We show that the latitudinal dependence of the cloud vertical profiles can have a strong impact on the nadir retrievals; neglecting it can lead to a significant underestimation of $\tau_\mathrm{cld}$ in the polar regions (up to 25 % to 50 %, depending on the vertical distribution of the dust in the atmosphere) and to a lesser extent, to an overestimation of $\tau_\mathrm{cld}$ around the equator. We also discuss the impact of a vertically-dependent particle size profile, as previous studies have shown the presence of very small water ice particles at the top of the clouds. From this analysis, we provide recommendations for the improvement of water ice cloud parameterization in radiative transfer algorithms in nadir atmospheric retrievals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14993v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aur\'elien Stcherbinine, Michael J. Wolff, Christopher S. Edwards, Oleg Korablev, Anna Fedorova, Alexander Trokhimovskiy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Cold-to-Temperate Exoplanetary Atmospheres: The Role of Water Condensation on Surface Identification with JWST</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09009v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding the surface temperature and interior structure of cold-to-temperate sub-Neptunes is critical for assessing their habitability, yet direct observations are challenging. In this study, we investigate the impact of water condensation on the atmospheric compositions of sub-Neptunes, focusing on the implications for JWST spectroscopic observations. By modeling the atmospheric photochemistry of two canonical sub-Neptunes, K2-18 b and LHS 1140 b, both with and without water condensation and with and without thick atmospheres, we demonstrate that water condensation can significantly affect the predicted atmospheric compositions. This effect is driven by oxygen depletion from the condensation of water vapor and primarily manifests as an increase in the C/O ratio within the photochemically active regions of the atmosphere. This change in composition particularly affects planets with thin H2-dominated atmospheres, leading to a transition in dominant nitrogen and carbon carriers from N2 and oxygen-rich species like CO/CO2 towards heavier hydrocarbons and nitriles. While our models do not fully account for the loss mechanisms of these higher-order species, such molecules can go on to form more refractory molecules or hazes. Planets with thin H2-rich atmospheres undergoing significant water condensation are thus likely to exhibit very hazy atmospheres. The relatively flat JWST spectra observed for LHS 1140 b could be consistent with such a scenario, suggesting a shallow surface with extensive water condensation or a high atmospheric C/O ratio. Conversely, the JWST observations of K2-18 b are better aligned with a volatile-rich mini-Neptune with a thick atmosphere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09009v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziyu Huang, Xinting Yu, Shang-Min Tsai, Julianne I. Moses, Kazumasa Ohno, Joshua Krissansen-Totton, Xi Zhang, Jonathan Fortney</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for GEMS: TOI-5688 A b, a low-density giant orbiting a high-metallicity early M-dwarf</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.01371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.01371v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the discovery of a low-density planet transiting TOI-5688 A b, a high-metallicity M2V star. This planet was discovered as part of the search for transiting giant planets ($R \gtrsim8$ M$_\oplus$) through the Searching for GEMS (Giant Exoplanets around M-dwarf Stars) survey. The planet TOI-5688 A b was discovered with the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS), and characterized with ground-based transits from Red Buttes Observatory (RBO), the Table Mountain Observatory of Pomona College, and radial velocity (RV) measurements with the Habitable-Zone Planet Finder (HPF) on the 10 m Hobby Eberly Telescope (HET) and NEID on the WIYN 3.5 m telescope. From the joint fit of transit and RV data, the mass of the planet is $124\pm24$ M$_\oplus$ and the radius is $10.4\pm0.7$ R$_\oplus$. This planet has a density of $0.61^{+0.20}_{-0.15}$ g/cm${}^3$, and is on a $\sim2.95$ day orbit around its host star. The spectroscopic and photometric analysis of the host star TOI-5688 A shows that it is a high metallicity ([Fe/H] $ = 0.47\pm0.16$ dex) M2V star, favoring the core-accretion formation pathway as the likely formation scenario for this planet. In this paper, we analyze potential mechanisms of planet formation in the context of the formation of TOI-5688 A b. Additionally, observations with Gaia suggest the presence of a wide-separation binary companion, TOI-5688 B, which has a projected separation of $\sim5"$ (1110 AU) and is an M4V. This makes TOI-5688 A b part of a growing number of GEMS in wide-separation binary systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.01371v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Varghese Reji, Shubham Kanodia, Joe Ninan, Caleb I. Ca\~nas, Jessica Libby-Roberts, Andrea S. J. Lin, Arvind F Gupta, Tera N. Sewaby, Alexander Larsen, Henry A. Kobulnicky, Philip I. Choi, Nez Evans, Sage Santomenna, Isabelle Winnick, Larry Yu, Jaime A. Alvarado-Montes, Chad Bender, Lia Marta Bernab\`o, Cullen H. Blake, William D. Cochran, Scott A. Diddams, Samuel Halverson, Te Han, Fred Hearty, Sarah E. Logsdon, Suvrath Mahadevan, Andrew Monson, Michael McElwain, Paul Robertson, Devendra Ojha, Arpita Roy, Christian Schwab, Gudmundur Stefansson, Jason Wright</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Possibilities for methanogenic and acetogenic life in molecular cloud</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.14291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.14291v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: According to panspermia, life on Earth may have originated from life forms transported through space from elsewhere. These life forms could have passed through molecular clouds, where the process of methanogenesis could have provided enough energy to sustain living organisms. In this study, we have calculated the Gibbs free energy released from synthesizing hydrocarbons for methanogenic (acetogenic) life in a molecular cloud, with methane (acetic acid) as the final metabolic product. Our calculations demonstrate that the chemical reactions during methanogenesis can release enough free energy to support living organisms. The methanogenic life may have served as the ancestor of life on Earth, and there is some preliminary evidence from various molecular biology studies to support this idea. Furthermore, we propose a potential distinguishing signal to test our model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.14291v2</guid>
      <category>physics.pop-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two methods to analyse radial diffusion ensembles: the peril of space- and time- dependent diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04669</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04669v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Particle dynamics in Earth's outer radiation belt can be modelled using a diffusion framework, where large-scale electron movements are captured by a diffusion equation across a single adiabatic invariant, $L^{*}$ $``(L)"$. While ensemble models are promoted to represent physical uncertainty, as yet there is no validated method to analyse radiation belt ensembles. Comparisons are complicated by the domain dependent diffusion, since diffusion coefficient $D_{LL}$ is dependent on $L$. We derive two tools to analyse ensemble members: time to monotonicity $t_m$ and mass/energy moment quantities $\mathcal{N}, \mathcal{E}$. We find that the Jacobian ($1/L^2$) is necessary for radiation belt error metrics. Components of $\partial\mathcal{E}/\partial t$ are explicitly calculated to compare the effects of outer and inner boundary conditions, and loss, on the ongoing diffusion. Using $t_m$, $\mathcal{N}$ and $\mathcal{E}$, we find that: (a) different physically motivated choices of outer boundary condition and location result in different final states and different rates of evolution; (b) the gradients of the particle distribution affect evolution more significantly than $D_{LL}$; (c) the enhancement location, and the amount of initial background particles, are both significant factors determining system evolution; (d) loss from pitch-angle scattering is generally dominant; it mitigates but does not remove the influence of both initial conditions and outer boundary settings, which are due to the $L$-dependence of $D_{LL}$. We anticipate this study will promote renewed focus on the distribution gradients, on the location and nature of the outer boundary in radiation belt modelling, and provide a foundation for systematic ensemble modelling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04669v2</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sarah N. Bentley, J. Stout, Rhys Thompson, Daniel J. Ratliff, Clare E. J. Watt</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
