<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.EP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.EP</link>
    <description>astro-ph.EP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.EP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 05:00:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A Measurement of the Water Abundance in the Atmosphere of the Hot Jupiter WASP-43b with High-resolution Cross-correlation Spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17923v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Measuring the abundances of carbon- and oxygen-bearing molecules has been a primary focus in studying the atmospheres of hot Jupiters, as doing so can help constrain the carbon-to-oxygen (C/O) ratio. The C/O ratio can help reveal the evolution and formation pathways of hot Jupiters and provide a strong understanding of the atmospheric composition. In the last decade, high-resolution spectral analyses have become increasingly useful in measuring precise abundances of several carbon- and oxygen-bearing molecules. This allows for a more precise constraint of the C/O ratio. We present four transits of the hot Jupiter WASP-43b observed between 1.45 $-$ 2.45 $\mu$m with the high-resolution Immersion GRating InfraRed Spectrometer (IGRINS) on the Gemini-S telescope. We detected H$_2$O at a signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) of 3.51. We tested for the presence of CH$_4$, CO, and CO$_2$, but we did not detect these carbon-bearing species. We ran a retrieval for all four molecules and obtained a water abundance of $\log_{10}(\text{H}_2\text{O}) = -2.24^{+0.57}_{-0.48}$. We obtained an upper limit on the C/O ratio of C/O $&lt;$ 0.95. These findings are consistent with previous observations from the Hubble Space Telescope and the James Webb Space Telescope.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17923v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dare Bartelt, Megan Weiner Mansfield, Michael R. Line, Vivien Parmentier, Luis Welbanks, Elspeth K. H. Lee, Jorge Sanchez, Arjun B. Savel, Peter C. B. Smith, Emily Rauscher, Joost P. Wardenier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In-situ observations of resident space objects with the CHEOPS space telescope</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18326v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The CHaracterising ExOPlanet Satellite (CHEOPS) is a partnership between the European Space Agency and Switzerland with important contributions by 10 additional ESA member States. It is the first S-class mission in the ESA Science Programme. CHEOPS has been flying on a Sun-synchronous low Earth orbit since December 2019, collecting millions of short-exposure images in the visible domain to study exoplanet properties. A small yet increasing fraction of CHEOPS images show linear trails caused by resident space objects crossing the instrument field of view. To characterize the population of satellites and orbital debris observed by CHEOPS, all and every science images acquired over the past 3 years have been scanned with a Hough transform algorithm to identify the characteristic linear features that these objects cause on the images. Thousands of trails have been detected. This statistically significant sample shows interesting trends and features such as an increased occurrence rate over the past years as well as the fingerprint of the Starlink constellation. The cross-matching of individual trails with catalogued objects is underway as we aim to measure their distance at the time of observation and deduce the apparent magnitude of the detected objects. As space agencies and private companies are developing new space-based surveillance and tracking activities to catalogue and characterize the distribution of small debris, the CHEOPS experience is timely and relevant. With the first CHEOPS mission extension currently running until the end of 2026, and a possible second extension until the end of 2029, the longer time coverage will make our dataset even more valuable to the community, especially for characterizing objects with recurrent crossings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18326v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jsse.2024.08.005</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Space Safety Engineering, Volume 11, Issue 3, September 2024, Pages 498-506</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Billot, Stephan Hellmich, Willy Benz, Andrea Fortier, David Ehrenreich, Christopher Broeg, Alexis Heitzmann, Anja Bekkelien, Alexis Brandeker, Yann Alibert, Roi Alonso, Tamas B\'arczy, David Barrado Navascues, Susana C. C. Barros, Wolfgang Baumjohann, Federico Biondi, Luca Borsato, Andrew Collier Cameron, Carlos Corral van Damme, Alexandre C. M. Correia, Szilard Csizmadia, Patricio E. Cubillos, Melvyn B. Davies, Magali Deleuil, Adrien Deline, Olivier D. S. Demangeon, Brice-Olivier Demory, Aliz Derekas, Billy Edwards, Jo Ann Egger, Anders Erikson, Luca Fossati, Malcolm Fridlund, Davide Gandolfi, Kosmas Gazeas, Micha\"el Gillon, Manuel G\"udel, Maximilian N. G\"unther, Ch. Helling, Kate G. Isaak, Laszlo L. Kiss, Judith Korth, Kristine W. F. Lam, Jacques Laskar, Alain Lecavelier des Etangs, Monika Lendl, Demetrio Magrin, Pierre F. L. Maxted, Marko Mecina, Bruno Mer\'in, Christoph Mordasini, Valerio Nascimbeni, G\"oran Olofsson, Roland Ottensamer, Isabella Pagano, Enric Pall\'e, Gisbert Peter, Daniele Piazza, Giampaolo Piotto, Don Pollacco, Didier Queloz, Roberto Ragazzoni, Nicola Rando, Heike Rauer, Ignasi Ribas, Martin Rieder, Nuno C. Santos, Gaetano Scandariato, Damien S\'egransan, Attila E. Simon, Alexis M. S. Smith, S\'ergio G. Sousa, Manu Stalport, Sophia Sulis, Gyula M. Szab\'o, St\'ephane Udry, Bernd Ulmer, Sol\`ene Ulmer-Moll, Val\'erie Van Grootel, Julia Venturini, Eva Villaver, Nicholas A. Walton, Thomas G. Wilson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The First Spin-Orbit Obliquity of an M dwarf/brown dwarf System: An eccentric and aligned TOI-2119 b</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18567v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report the first instance of an M dwarf/brown dwarf obliquity measurement for the TOI-2119 system using the Rossiter-McLaughlin effect. TOI-2119 b is a transiting brown dwarf orbiting a young, active early M dwarf ($T_{\rm{eff}}$ = 3553 K). It has a mass of 64.4 M$_{\rm{J}}$ and radius of 1.08 R$_{\rm{J}}$, with an eccentric orbit ($e$ = 0.3) at a period of 7.2 days. For this analysis, we utilise NEID spectroscopic transit observations and ground based simultaneous transit photometry from the Astrophysical Research Consortium (ARC) and the Las Campanas Remote Observatory (LCRO). We fit all available data of TOI-2119 b to refine the brown dwarf parameters and update the ephemeris. The classical Rossiter-McLaughlin technique yields a projected star-planet obliquity of $\lambda=-0.8\pm1.1^\circ$ and a three-dimensional obliquity of $\psi=15.7\pm5.5^\circ$. Additionally, we spatially resolve the stellar surface of TOI-2119 utilising the Reloaded Rossiter-McLaughlin technique to determine the projected star-planet obliquity as $\lambda=1.26 \pm 1.2^{\circ}$. Both of these results agree within $2\sigma$ and confirm the system is aligned, where TOI-2119 b joins an emerging group of aligned brown dwarf obliquities. We also probe stellar surface activity on the surface of TOI-2119 in the form of centre-to-limb variations as well as the potential for differential rotation. Overall, we find tentative evidence for centre-to-limb variations on the star but do not detect evidence of differential rotation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18567v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lauren Doyle, Caleb I. Ca\~nas, Jessica E. Libby-Roberts, Heather M. Cegla, Gu{\dh}mundur K. Stef\'ansson, David Anderson, David J. Armstrong, Chad Bender, Daniel Bayliss, Theron W. Carmichael, Sarah Casewell, Shubham Kanodia, Marina Lafarga, Andrea S. J. Lin, Suvrath Mahadevan, Andy Monson, Paul Robertson, Dimitri Veras</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Potential technosignature from anomalously low deuterium/hydrogen (D/H) in planetary water depleted by nuclear fusion technology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18595</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18595v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Deuterium-deuterium (DD) fusion is viewed as an ideal energy source for humanity in the far future, given a vast seawater supply of D. Here, we consider long-lived, extraterrestrial, technological societies that develop DD fusion. If such a society persists over geologic timescales, oceanic deuterium would diminish. For an ocean mass and initial D/H that are Earth-like, fusion power use of only $\sim$10 times that projected for humankind next century would deplete the deuterium-hydrogen ratio (D/H) in $\sim$(a few)$\times 10^8$ years to values below that of the local Interstellar Medium (ISM). Ocean masses of a few percent Earth's would reach anomalously low D/H in $\sim10^6$ to $10^7$ years. The timescale shortens with greater energy consumption, smaller oceans, or lower initial D/H. Here, we suggest that anomalous D/H in planetary water below local ISM values of $\sim16\times 10^{-6}$ (set by Big Bang nucleosynthesis plus deuterium loss onto dust or small admixtures of deuterium-poor stellar material) may be a technosignature. Unlike SETI from radio signals, anomalous D/H would persist for eons, even if civilizations perish or relocate. We discuss wavelengths of strong absorption features for detecting D/H anomalies in atmospheric water vapor. These are vibrational O-D stretching at 3.7 $\mu$m in transmission spectroscopy of Earth-like worlds, $\sim1.5$ $\mu$m (in the wings of the 1.4 $\mu$m water band) in the shorter near-infrared for direct imaging by Habitable Worlds Observatory, and 3.7 $\mu$m or $\sim7.5$ $\mu$m (in the wings of the broad 6.3 $\mu$m bending vibration of water) for concepts like the Large Interferometer for Exoplanets (LIFE).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18595v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David C. Catling, Joshua Krissansen-Totton, Tyler D. Robinson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for compact hierarchical triple systems candidates in astrometric binaries and accelerated solutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17819v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Compact hierarchical triple (CHT) systems, where a tertiary component orbits an inner binary, provide critical insights into stellar formation and evolution. Despite their importance, the detection of such systems, especially compact ones, remains challenging due to the complexity of their orbital dynamics and the limitations of traditional observational methods. This study aims to identify new CHT star systems among Gaia astrometric binaries and accelerated solutions by analysing the radial velocity (RV) amplitude of these systems, thereby improving our understanding of stellar hierarchies. We selected a sample of bright astrometric binaries and accelerated solutions from the Gaia DR3 Non-Single Stars catalogue. The RV peak-to-peak amplitude was used as an estimator, and we applied a new method to detect potential triple systems by comparing the RV-based semi-amplitude with the astrometric semi-amplitude. We used available binary and triple star catalogues to identify and validate candidates, with a subset confirmed through further examination of the RV and astrometric data. Our analysis resulted in the discovery of 956 CHT candidates among the orbital sources as well as another 3,115 probable close binary sources in stars with accelerated solutions. Exploring the inclination, orbital period, and eccentricity of the outer companion in these CHT systems provides strong evidence of mutual orbit alignment, as well as a preference towards moderate outer eccentricities. Our novel approach has proven effective in identifying potential triple systems thereby increasing their number in the catalogues. Our findings emphasise the importance of combined astrometric and RV data analysis in the study of multiple star systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17819v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dolev Bashi, Andrei Tokovinin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The importance of binary stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18470</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18470v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Stars are mostly found in binary and multiple systems, as at least 50% of all solar-like stars have companions - a fraction that goes up to 100% for the most massive stars. Moreover, a large fraction of them will interact in some way or another over the course of their lives. Such interactions can, and often will, alter the structure and evolution of both components in the system. This will, in turn, lead to the production of exotic objects whose existence cannot be explained by standard single star evolution models, including gravitational wave progenitors, blue stragglers, symbiotic and barium stars, novae, and supernovae. More generally, binary stars prove crucial in many aspects, ranging from cultural ones, to constraining models of stellar evolution, star formation, and even, possibly, of gravity itself. They also provide a quasi-model independent way to determine stellar masses, radii, and luminosities. We here provide a brief summary of the importance of binary stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18470v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henri M. J. Boffin, David Jones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Source of Hydrogen in Earth's Building Blocks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13637v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Despite being pivotal to the habitability of our planet, the process by which Earth gained its present-day hydrogen budget is unclear. Due to their isotopic similarity to terrestrial rocks across a range of elements, the meteorite group that is thought to best represent Earth's building blocks is the enstatite chondrites (ECs). Because of ECs' nominally anhydrous mineralogy, these building blocks have long been presumed to have supplied negligible hydrogen to the proto-Earth. However, recent bulk compositional measurements suggest that ECs may unexpectedly contain enough hydrogen to readily explain Earth's present-day water abundance. Together, these contradictory findings mean the contribution of ECs to Earth's water budget is currently unclear. As such, it is uncertain whether appreciable water is a systematic outcome of Earth's formation. Here, we explore the amount of hydrogen in ECs as well as the phase that may carry this element using sulfur X-ray absorption near edge structure (S-XANES) spectroscopy. We find that most (~80 wt%) of the measured bulk hydrogen concentration of these meteorites is bonded to sulfur. Moreover, the concentration of the S-H bond is intimately linked to the abundance of micrometre-scale pyrrhotite (Fe1-xS, 0&lt;x&lt;0.125), suggesting most hydrogen in these meteorites is carried in this phase. These findings indicate that hydrogen is present in ECs in higher concentrations than previously considered and argue this element has a systematic, rather than stochastic, origin on our planet.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13637v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas J Barrett (University of Oxford, Department of Earth Sciences), James F. J. Bryson (University of Oxford, Department of Earth Sciences), Kalotina Geraki (Diamond Light Source)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase equilibria of sub-Neptunes and super-Earths</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11321v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the consequences of non-ideal chemical interaction between silicate and overlying hydrogen-rich envelopes for rocky planets using basic tenets of phase equilibria. Based on our current understanding of the temperature and pressure conditions for complete miscibility of silicate and hydrogen, we find that the silicate-hydrogen binary solvus will dictate the nature of atmospheres and internal layering in rocky planets that garnered H$_2$-rich primary atmospheres. The temperatures at the surfaces of supercritical magma oceans will correspond to the silicate-hydrogen solvus. As a result, the radial positions of supercritical magma ocean-atmosphere interfaces, rather than their temperatures and pressures, should reflect the thermal states of these planets. The conditions prescribed by the solvus influence the structure of the atmosphere, and thus the transit radii of sub-Neptunes. Separation of iron-rich metal to form metal cores in sub-Neptunes and super-Earths is not assured due to prospects for neutral buoyancy of metal in silicate melt induced by dissolution of H, Si, and O in the metal at high temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11321v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Edward D. Young, Lars Stixrude, James G. Rogers, Hilke E. Schlichting, Sarah P. Marcum</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Considerations for Photochemical Modeling of Possible Hycean Worlds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07313v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: JWST is revolutionising the study of temperate sub-Neptunes, starting with the first detection of carbon-bearing molecules in the habitable-zone sub-Neptune K2-18 b. The retrieved abundances of CH$_4$ and CO$_2$ and non-detection of NH$_3$ and CO in K2-18 b are consistent with prior predictions of photochemical models for a Hycean world with a habitable ocean. However, recent photochemical modeling raised the prospect that the observed abundances may be explained by a mini-Neptune scenario instead. In this study, we explore these scenarios using independent photochemical modeling with K2-18 b as a case study. We find the previous results to be sensitive to a range of model assumptions, such as the photochemical cross sections, incident stellar spectrum, surface pressure, UV albedo, and metallicity, significantly affecting the resulting abundances. We explore a wide model space to investigate scenarios that are compatible with the retrieved molecular abundances for K2-18 b. Our analysis shows that the previously favoured mini-Neptune scenario is not compatible with most of the retrieved abundances, while the Hycean scenarios, both inhabited and uninhabited, provide better agreement. An uninhabited Hycean scenario explains most of the abundance constraints, except CH$_4$ which is generally underabundant but dependent on the model assumptions. The inhabited Hycean scenario is compatible with all the abundances if the observed CH$_4$ is assumed to be predominantly biogenic. Our results underscore the importance of systematic photochemical modeling and accurate interpretation of chemical abundance constraints for candidate Hycean worlds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07313v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gregory J. Cooke, Nikku Madhusudhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoding the Future of Exoplanets: Asteroseismic Confirmation of Subgiant and Red Giant Hosts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14703v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Asteroseismology has emerged as a powerful tool to unravel the intricate relationships between evolved stars and their planetary systems. In this study, we leverage this technique to investigate the evolutionary stages of five exoplanet host stars, each exhibiting solar-like oscillations. Building on our previous work that identified two host stars as red clump and red giant branch (RGB) stars, this study focuses on a new and broader sample. By precisely measuring asteroseismic parameters such as the period spacing of dipole gravity modes ($\Delta\Pi_{1}$), we provide definitive confirmation of these stars' evolutionary states as subgiants or RGB stars. These results are not only crucial for understanding the internal structures of evolved stars but also for predicting the eventual fate of their planetary companions, which may face engulfment as their host stars expand. This research highlights the profound role of asteroseismology in advancing our knowledge of planetary system evolution and opens new pathways for exploring how stellar evolution impacts planetary survival. Our findings set the stage for future studies on the dynamic fates of exoplanets, providing key insights into the intricate processes of stellar and planetary evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14703v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Xu Lin, Sheng-Bang Qian, Li-Ying Zhu, Wen-Ping Liao, Fu-Xing Li, Xiang-Dong Shi, Lin-Jia Li, Er-Gang Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The bulk metallicity of giant planets around M stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16197</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16197v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The bulk-metallicity determination of giant exoplanets is essential to constrain their formation and evolution pathways and to compare them to the solar system. Previous studies inferred an inverse relation between the mass and bulk metallicity. However, the data almost exclusively contained planets that orbit FGK stars. The recent discoveries of giant exoplanets around M-dwarf stars present an opportunity to probe whether they follow a mass-metallicity trend different from that of their FGK counterparts. Using evolution models we characterised the interiors of giant exoplanets with reliable mass-radius measurements that orbit FGK and M-dwarf stars. We then inferred the mass-metallicity trends for both populations. We found that the bulk metallicity of giant planets around M stars is overall lower compared to those around FGK stars. This yielded mass-metallicity relations for the two populations with similar slopes but significantly different offsets. The lack of metal-rich giant planets around M dwarfs could explain the difference in the inferred offset and be a result of different formation conditions. However, there were only 20 successful bulk-metallicity retrievals for the giant planets around M dwarfs, which resulted in rather large uncertainties. Therefore, it is of great importance to continue detecting these planets with both transit and radial velocities. Additionally, the characterisation of the atmospheres of giant planets around M-stars can further help to constrain their interiors and to investigate the atmosphere-interior connection. This will significantly contribute towards understanding the possible formation pathways of giant planets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16197v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon M\"uller, Ravit Helled</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comment on "Did the terrestrial planets of the Solar System form by pebble accretion?"</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17043</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17043v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Morbidelli, Kleine &amp; Nimmo (2024) (MKN) recently published a critical analysis on whether the terrestrial planets in the Solar System formed by rapid pebble accretion or by the classical route of multiple giant impacts between planetary embryos after the dissipation of the protoplanetary disc. They arrive at the conclusion that the terrestrial planets did not form by pebble accretion. Although we welcome debate on this topic, we want to emphasize here several points that we disagree on. We will not address in detail every claim made in MKN, but rather stick to four main points. Our conclusion is that pebble accretion remains a viable mechanism to drive significant growth of protoplanets in the protoplanetary disc, with as much as 70% of Earth formed by pebble accretion. This rapid growth phase must nevertheless have been followed by an extended period of collisional growth after the end of the protoplanetary disc phase, likely culminating with the moon-forming giant impact. We emphasize here an important recent result from Olson &amp; Sharp (2023), namely that significant growth by pebble accretion can be reconciled with the Hf-W decay system even for a canonical moon-forming giant impact with a Mars-mass protoplanet and a low equilibration efficiency - a more massive impactor, as proposed in Johansen et al. (2023), is not necessary. Given that terrestrial planet formation naturally involves both pebble accretion and a combination of small and large impactors, this challenges the very notion of making an either/or distinction between the classical collision model and the pebble accretion model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17043v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anders Johansen, Peter Olson, Zachary Sharp</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for star-planet interactions in GJ 486 at radio wavelengths with the uGMRT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17689v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We search for radio emission from star-planet interactions in the M-dwarf system GJ~486, which hosts an Earth-like planet. We observed the GJ~486 system with the upgraded Giant Metrewave Radio Telescope (uGMRT) from 550 to 750 MHz in nine different epochs, between October 2021 and February 2022, covering almost all orbital phases of GJ~486 b from different orbital cycles. We obtained radio images and dynamic spectra of the total and circularly polarized intensity for each individual epoch We do not detect any quiescent radio emission in any epoch above 3$\sigma$. Similarly, we do not detect any bursty emission in our dynamic spectra.
  While we cannot completely rule out that the absence of a radio detection is due to time variability of the radio emission, or to the maximum electron-cyclotron maser emission being below our observing range, this seems unlikely. We discuss two possible scenarios: an intrinsic dim radio signal, or alternatively, that the anisotropic beamed emission pointed away from the observer. If the non-detection of radio emission from star-planet interaction in GJ~486 is due to an intrinsically dim signal, this implies that, independently of whether the planet is magnetized or not, the mass-loss rate is small (\dot{M}_\star $\lesssim$ 0.3 \dot{M}_\sun) and that, concomitantly, the efficiency of the conversion of Poynting flux into radio emission must be low ($\beta \lesssim 10^{-3}$). Free-free absorption effects are negligible, given the high value of the coronal temperature. Finally, if the anisotropic beaming pointed away from us, this would imply that GJ~486 has very low values of its magnetic obliquity and inclination.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17689v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Pe\~na-Mo\~nino, M. P\'erez-Torres, D. Kansabanik, G. Bl\'azquez-Calero, R. D. Kavanagh, J. F. G\'omez, J. Mold\'on, A. Alberdi, P. J. Amado, G. Anglada, J. A. Caballero, A. Mohan, P. Leto, M. Narang, M. Osorio, D. Revilla, C. Trigilio</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
