<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.EP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.EP</link>
    <description>astro-ph.EP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.EP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 04:00:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Intruder Alert: Breaking Resonant Chains with Planetesimal Flybys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18955</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18955v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The orbital architectures of compact exoplanet systems record their complicated dynamical histories. Recent research supports the ``breaking-the-chains'' hypothesis, which proposes that compact systems typically form in chains of mean-motion resonances (MMRs) but subsequently break out on a $\sim 100$Myr timescale. We investigate a scenario for breaking the chains through intermittent flybys of planetesimals originating from a distant reservoir. Using $N$-body simulations and semi-analytical calculations, we characterize the disruption of MMRs through these flybys. We find a planetesimal reservoir of total mass $\gtrsim 0.04 M_{\oplus}$ is required to disrupt MMR chains, depending on the mass distribution and the typical number of flybys executed by each planetesimal. We verify that systems disrupted in this way are frequently unstable to close encounters within $\sim 100$Myr of the final flyby. This mechanism operates in systems with both a sufficiently massive reservoir and an efficient mechanism for planetesimal injection. Consequently, we predict an anti-correlation between resonant inner systems and dynamically active outer configurations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18955v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaru Li, Christopher E. O'Connor, Frederic A. Rasio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eccentric discs as a gateway to giant planets outward migration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18970v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent studies on planet-dominated Type II migration demonstrated the presence of a correlation between the direction of planet migration and the parameter K describing the depth of the planetary gap. It was found that high (low) value for K correspond to outward (inward) migration. In this paper we aim at understanding the mechanism driving inward/outward migration and why it correlates with the gap depth. We performed a suite of 2D, live-planet, long-term simulations of massive planets migrating in discs with the hydro-code Fargo3D. We focus on a range of planet masses (1-13 m_J) and disc aspect ratios (0.03-0.1) and analyze the evolution of orbital elements and gap structure. We also study the torque contributions from outer Lindblad resonances to investigate their role in the migration outcome. We find that, while all planets initially migrate inwards, those with high enough K eventually enter a phase in which the torque reverses sign and migration becomes outwards, until eventually stalling. This behavior is associated with eccentricity growth in the outer disc and changes in the gap structure. We identify the surface density ratio at the 1:2 and 1:3 outer Lindblad resonances as a key output diagnostic that correlates with the migration direction. This ratio regulates the migration for all the cases where the massive planet remains in an almost circular orbit and the outer gap region exhibits moderate eccentricity. This characteristic sequence of inward-reversal-outwards-stalling occurs for a variety of K values and thus further work is required to identify the simulation input parameters that determine the onset of this sequence. Our results suggest that outward migration in the planet-dominated regime is primarily governed by the relative importance of the 1:2 and 1:3 resonances and, therefore, the gap profile plays a crucial role in determining the direction of migration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18970v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chiara E. Scardoni, Giovanni P. Rosotti, Cathie J. Clarke, Enrico Ragusa, Richard A. Booth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Compact Multi-Planet System of Three Transiting Giant Planets Around TIC118798035</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19162</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19162v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report the discovery and characterization of three transiting giant planets in the TIC118798035 system. The three planets were identified as transiting candidates from data of the TESS mission, and confirmed with ground-based photometric transit observations along with radial velocity variations obtained with FEROS, HARPS and ESPRESSO. The three planets present transit timing variations (TTVs). We performed a N-body orbital fitting to the TTVs and radial velocities finding that TIC118798035 b is as warm low-density Neptune with a mass of 0.0250$\pm$0.0023 $M_J$, a radius of 0.655$\pm$0.018 $R_J$, and an orbital period of 11.507 d; TIC118798035 c is a warm Saturn with a mass of 0.403$\pm$0.024 $M_J$, a radius of 0.973$\pm$0.023 $R_J$, and an orbital period of 22.564 d; and TIC118798035 d is a warm Jupiter with a mass of 0.773$\pm$0.052 $M_J$, a radius of 0.923$\pm$0.044 $R_J$, and an orbital period of 48.925 d. The bulk metallicities of the three planets don't fully follow the mass-metallicity correlation found for the giant planets of the solar system, which hints at a somewhat different formation history for the planets of the TIC118798035 system. TIC118798035 is the only system having more than two transiting planets larger than 0.5 $R_J$ with a precise orbital and physical characterization, amenable for future atmospheric studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19162v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael Brahm, Trifon Trifonov, Andr\'es Jord\'an, Thomas Henning, N\'estor Espinoza, Felipe I. Rojas, Marcelo Tala Pinto, Mat\'ias I. Jones, Daniel Thorngren, Lorena Acu\~na, Jan Eberhardt, Yared Reinarz, Helem Salinas, Michaela V\'itkov\'a, Juan I. Espinoza-Retamal, Gaspar Bakos, Attila B\'odi, Gavin Boyle, Zoltan Csubry, Joel Hartman, Anthony Keyes, Vincent Suc, Geert Jan Talens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Synergies between Twinkle and Ariel: a Pilot Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19594v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Launching in 2027 and 2029, respectively, Twinkle and Ariel will conduct the first large-scale homogeneous spectroscopic surveys of the atmospheres of hundreds of diverse exoplanets. This will fundamentally transition the field to an era of population-level characterisation. In this pilot study, we aim to explore possible synergies between Twinkle and Ariel to determine for instance whether prior Twinkle observations can substantially inform the target selection and observing strategy of Ariel. This study primarily aims to encourage further investigation by both consortium communities by showing what a potential scientific synergy would look like on a promising scientific case that requires further exploration. For this aim, we select a small subset of "cool" planets that are also particularly well-suited to be observed by Twinkle and therefore Ariel. By using representative noise estimates for both missions, we compute the number of visits required for an observation. Then, we simulate and retrieve transmission spectra of each target, assuming gaseous, H2/He-dominated atmospheres and various atmospheric models. For all candidates, we find that atmospheric parameters are generally retrieved well within 1-sigma to input values, with Ariel typically achieving tighter constraints. We demonstrate that for a small subset of cool gaseous planets, exploitable synergies exist between Twinkle and Ariel observations and Twinkle may very well provide a vantage point to plan Ariel observations. The true extent of the potential synergies, far beyond our considered sample, will be determined by the final target lists. Once Twinkle is operational and its performance is known, it could reliably inform Ariel's target prioritization and Ariel's capabilities which are already well-established can help define optimal targets and observational approaches for Twinkle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19594v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10686-025-10032-w</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Exp Astron 60, 19 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Bocchieri, Luke Booth, Lorenzo V. Mugnai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compositional characterisation of asteroid (84) Klio with JWST</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19717</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19717v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The analysis of the composition of primitive C$-$complex asteroids is essential to understand the distribution of volatiles in the Solar System since its formation. Primitive low-albedo families within the inner main asteroid belt are of particular interest because they are a significant source of carbonaceous near-Earth asteroids, such as Ryugu and Bennu. This study, part of the JWST SAMBA3 project (Spectral Analysis of Main Belt Asteroids in the 3 $\mu$m region), report the first spectroscopic analysis of asteroid (84) Klio in the 3 $\mu$m region, in order to better constrain its composition. We analysed the infrared (0.97$-$5.10 $\mu$m) Spectrum of Klio measured by the NIRSpec instrument on board JWST. We used the NEATM thermal model to extract the reflectance spectrum of the asteroid. Several spectral features were then analysed in the 2.8, 3.4, and 3.9 $\mu$m regions by different Gaussian fitting. The Spectrum of Klio shows an absorption band at 2.776 $\pm$ 0.001 $\mu$m that we attributed to phyllosilicates. We compared the position and shape of the feature with that observed in primitive materials such as carbonaceous chondrites and returned samples from Ryugu and Bennu. The position and shape of the 2.8 $\mu$m band, as well as the presence of a 0.7 $\mu$m band in the visible, suggest that Klio's spectrum is similar to certain CM2 meteorites. We observed an absorption band around 3.9 $\mu$m, with a depth of $0.020 \pm 0.001$ that could be attributed to carbonates. We could not clearly detect any absorption associated with organics at 3.4 $\mu$m.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19717v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tania Le Pivert-Jolivet, Julia de Le\'on, Javier Licandro, Bryan Holler, Noem\'i Pinilla-Alonso, M\'ario De Pr\'a, Joshua Emery, Brittany Harvison, Joseph Masiero, Lucas McClure, Driss Takir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exoplanetary radio emission predictions and detectability in the SKA era</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19776v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Radio observations provide a window into a planet's interior and play a crucial role in studying its atmosphere and surface, key factors to find potential habitability. The discovery of thousands of exoplanets, together with advances in radio astronomy through the Square Kilometre Array (SKA), motivates the search for planetary-scale radio emissions. Here, we employ the radiometric Bode's law (RBL) and machine learning techniques to analyze a dataset of 1330 confirmed exoplanets, aiming to estimate their potential radio emission. Permutation Importance (PI) and SHapley Additive exPlanations (SHAP) analyses indicate that a planet's mass, radius, orbital semi-major axis, and distance from Earth are sufficient to dependably forecast its radio flux and frequency. The random forest model accurately reproduces these radio characteristics, confirming its reliability for exoplanetary radio predictions. Considering observational constraints, we find that 64 exoplanets could generate signals detectable by the SKA, 52 of which remain observable in the intermediate AA* deployment. Among these, MASCARA-1 b stands out with a predicted flux of 7.209 mJy at 135.1 MHz, making it an excellent SKA-Low target. Meanwhile, WASP-18 b, with a flux of 18.638 mJy peaking at 812.9 MHz, is the most promising candidate for SKA-Mid. These results show that the SKA can detect gas giants, such as MASCARA-1 b (SNR&gt;400) and WASP-18 b (SNR&gt;4236), within feasible integration times. Additionally, we identify four candidates (HATS-18 b, WASP-12 b, WASP-103 b, and WASP-121 b) that are likely affected by radio quenching, highlighting the importance of considering this effect in target selection for observation campaigns.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19776v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahdiyar Mousavi-Sadr, Fatemeh S. Tabatabaei, Alexander Wolszczan, Ghassem Gozaliasl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Very High Precision Astrometry for Exoplanets and Dark Matter with the Habitable Worlds Observatory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18920</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18920v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Astrometry, one of the oldest branches of astronomy, has been revolutionized by missions like Hipparcos and especially Gaia, which mapped billions of stars with extraordinary precision. However, challenges such as detecting Earth-like exoplanets in nearby habitable zones and probing the influence of dark matter in galactic environments require sub-microarcsecond accuracy. With a 6--8 meter large-aperture telescope operating across at visible wavelengths, the Habitable Worlds Observatory by NASA can combine astrometry and direct imaging to detect rocky exoplanets within 10 parsecs and study their atmospheres. We consider here the scientific requirements and present a concept for a dedicated astrometric instrument on HWO. It is capable to produce diffraction-limited images of large fields, achieving a point-spread function (PSF) precision of 20 milliarcseconds. Equipped with a detector calibration system, HWO can perform high precision astrometry, and, detect and measure the orbit of Earth-mass planets in the habitable zone of Nearby Solar-type stars. HWO can dramatically improve current constraints on the self- interaction cross-section of heavy dark matter particles (WIMPs) and on the masses of ultra-high dark matter particles, through the study of stellar motions in galactic environments. The visible channel of the instrument features a large CMOS-based focal plane with stitched pixel arrays, enabling a large field of view. The ``Detector Calibration Unit'' system uses interferometric laser fringes to calibrate pixel positions. Using differential astrometry and pointed observations with a stable telescope design enables extended integration times, enhancing sensitivity to sub-microarcsecond precision for detecting exoplanets and studying dark matter through stellar motion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18920v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Towards the Habitable Worlds Observatory: Visionary Science and Transformational Technology, Lee, Janice, Jul 2025, Washington DC, United States</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fabien Malbet (IPAG), J. Amiaux (DAP), F. Ardellier-Desages (DAP), E. Doumayrou (DAP), P. -A. Frugier (DAP), R. Goullioud (JPL), T. Greene (IPAC), L. Labadie (DAP), P. -O. Lagage (DAP), M. Lizzana (IPAG, CNES), A. L\'eger (IAS), T. L\'epine (IOGS, LabHC), G. Mamon (IAP), J. Martignac (DAP), F. Pancher (IPAG), T. Pichon (DAP), A. Roberge (DAP), S. Ronayette (DAP), H. Rousset (IPAG), S. Soler (IPAG), A. Sozzetti (OATo), T. Tourette (DAP)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FAUST. XXVIII. High-Resolution ALMA Observations of Class 0/I Disks: Structure, Optical Depths, and Temperatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19635v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present high-resolution (~7.5 au) ALMA observations at 1.3 and 3 mm of 16 disks around Class 0/I protostars across multiple star-forming regions and a variety of multiplicities, showing a range of disk sizes (~2-100 au) and including circumbinary disks (CBDs) in binaries with separations &lt;100 au. The disk properties show similarities to Class II disks, including (a) low spectral index (SI) values (alpha=2.1) that increase with disk radius, (b) 3 mm disk sizes only marginally smaller than at 1.3 mm (&lt;10%), and (c) radial intensity profiles well described by modified self-similar profiles. We also find key differences: (i) SI values increasing with radius, but exceeding 2 only at the disk edge (ii) higher brightness temperatures Tb, in some cases higher than the predicted temperatures due to irradiation, and (iii) ~10x higher luminosity at a given size compared to the Class II disks. These results confirm significant optical depth in the observed Class 0/I disks, at both 1.3 and 3 mm, helping to explain their higher luminosities, but higher temperatures are also required for the most compact (&lt; 40 au) disks, suggesting additional viscous heating. Considering optical depth, most disk dust masses are estimated in the range 30-900 Mearth (0.01-0.3 Msun in gas), resulting in some disks reaching marginal gravitational instability. The median location of the water iceline is ~3 au, but it can extend beyond 10-20 au for the hottest disks. CBDs exhibit lower optical depths at both wavelengths and hence higher SI values (alpha=3.0), dust masses of 100 Mearth, and beta~1.5 (2 Class 0 CBDs) and beta~1 (1 Class I CBD), suggesting substantial grain growth only in the more evolved CBD. The inferred high optical depths provide a compelling explanation for the apparent scarcity of dust substructures in the younger disks at ~ 1 mm, despite mounting evidence for early planet formation (ABRIDGED).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19635v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. J. Maureira, J. E. Pineda, H. B. Liu, P. Caselli, C. Chandler, L. Testi, D. Johnstone, D. Segura-Cox, L. Loinard, E. Bianchi, C. Codella, A. Miotello, L. Podio, L. Cacciapuoti, Y. Oya, A. Lopez-Sepulcre, N. Sakai, Z. Zhang, N. Cuello, S. Ohashi, Y. Aikawa, G. Sabatini, Y. Zhang, C. Ceccarelli, S. Yamamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forcing Planets to Evolve: Interactions Between Uranus and Neptune at Late Stages of Dynamical Evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11813v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In early Solar System numerical simulations, where chaos is a primary driver, it is difficult to explore parameter space in a systematic way. In such simulations, stable configurations are hard to come by, and often require special fine-tuning. In addition, it is infeasible to run suites of well-resolved, realistic simulations with a disk of massive particles to drive planetary evolution where enough particles remain to represent the transneptunian populations to robustly statistically compare with observations. To complement state of the art full N-body simulations, we develop a method to artificially control each planet's orbital elements independently from each other, which when carefully applied, can be used to test a wider suite of models. We modify two widely used publicly available N-body integrators: (1) the C code, \texttt{REBOUND} and (2) the FORTRAN code, \texttt{Mercury6.2}. We show how the application of specific fictitious forces within numerical integrators can be used to tightly control planetary evolution to more easily explore migration and orbital excitation and damping. This tool allows us to replicate the impact a massive planetesimal disk would have on the planets, without actually including the massive planetesimals, thus decreasing the chaos and simulation runtime. We demonstrate the utility of this tool by applying it to the coupled orbital evolution of Uranus and Neptune, and show that Neptune's eccentricity damping and radial outward migration have the appropriate affect on Uranus' eccentricity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11813v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arcelia Hermosillo Ruiz, Ruth Murray-Clay, Kathryn Volk, Rosemary Pike</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Evolution of Jupiter and Saturn as a function of the Parameter R$_{\rho}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19041v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Computed using the APPLE planetary evolution code, we present updated evolutionary models for Jupiter and Saturn that incorporate helium rain, non-adiabatic thermal structures, and "fuzzy" extended heavy-element cores. Building on our previous Ledoux-stable models, we implement improved atmospheric boundary conditions that account for composition-dependent effective temperatures and systematically explore the impact of varying the parameter $R_{\rho}$, which allows one to explore in an approximate way the efficiency of semiconvection. For both Jupiter and Saturn, we construct models spanning from $R_{\rho}=1$ (Ledoux) to $R_{\rho}=0$ (Schwarzschild), and identify best-fit solutions that match each planet's effective temperature, equatorial radius, lower-order gravitational moments, and atmospheric composition at 4.56 Gyr. We find that lower $R_{\rho}$ values lead to stronger convective mixing, resulting in higher surface metallicities and lower deep interior temperatures, while requiring reduced heavy-element masses and lower initial entropies to stabilize the dilute inner cores. Our Saturn models also broadly agree with the observed brunt frequency profile inferred from Cassini ring seismology, with stable layers arising from both the helium rain region and the dilute core. These findings support the presence of complex, compositionally stratified interiors in both gas giants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19041v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ankan Sur, Adam Burrows, Roberto Tejada Arevalo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Re-accretion of Giant Impact Ejecta Can Drive Significant Atmospheric Erosion on Terrestrial Planets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22785v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Giant impacts, the collisions between planetary embryos, play a crucial role in sculpting the planets and their orbital architectures. Numerical simulations have advanced our understanding of these events, enabling estimations of mass and atmospheric loss during the primary impacts. However, high computational costs have restricted investigations to the immediate aftermath, limiting our understanding of the longer-term consequences. In this study, we investigate the effect of re-accretion of giant impact debris, a process previously overlooked, on the atmospheres of terrestrial planets. Following the collisional and dynamical evolution of the debris ejected during the primary impacts, we quantify the amount of debris that would be re-accreted by the progenitor. We find that $\sim 0.003\ M_{\oplus}$ would be re-accreted over a wide range of Earth-like planet properties, assuming $1\%$ of their mass is ejected as non-vaporised debris. Over a prolonged period, the secondary impacts during re-accretion drive enhanced atmospheric loss. Notably, the impacts from the debris of the canonical Moon-forming impact would have gradually eroded an atmosphere similar to present-day Earth's in $\sim 30$ Myr. More generally, any planet growing via giant impacts within $2$ au is likely to experience significant post-impact atmospheric erosion unless the initial atmosphere was at least $5$ times more massive than Earth's. Our results highlight the crucial role secondary impacts from giant-impact ejecta could have in driving the long-term atmospheric evolution of Earth-like planets, and demonstrate that giant impacts can be significantly more effective at eroding such atmospheres than previously thought, when re-accretion of debris is considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22785v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tuhin Ghosh, Mark Wyatt, Oliver Shorttle</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
