<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.EP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.EP</link>
    <description>astro-ph.EP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.EP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 04:00:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of Exozodi Sources and Dust Evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11754v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Exozodiacal dust disks (exozodis) are populations of warm (~300K) or hot (~1000K) dust, located in or interior to a star's habitable zone, detected around ~25% of main-sequence stars as excess emission over the stellar photosphere at mid- or near-infrared wavelengths. Often too plentiful to be explained by an in-situ planetesimal belt, exozodi dust is usually thought to be transported inwards from further out in the system. There is no consensus on which (if any) of various proposed dynamical models is correct, yet it is vital to understand exozodis given the risk they pose to direct imaging and characterisation of Earth-like planets. This article reviews current theoretical understanding of the origin and evolution of exozodi dust. It also identifies key questions pertinent to the potential for exozodis to impact exoplanet imaging and summarises current understanding of the answer to them informed by exozodi theory. These address how exozodi dust is delivered, its size and spatial distribution, and the effect of its composition on exozodi observability, as well as the connection between hot and warm exozodis. Also addressed are how common different exozodi levels are and how that level can be predicted from system properties, as well as the features that planets impart in dust distributions and how exozodis affect a planet's physical properties and habitability. We conclude that exozodis present both a problem and an opportunity, e.g., by introducing noise that makes planets harder to detect, but also identifying systems in which ingredients conducive to life, like water and volatiles, are delivered to the habitable zone.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11754v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark C. Wyatt, Tim D. Pearce, Nicole Pawellek, Sarah Dodson-Robinson, Virginie C. Faramaz-Gorka, Isabel Rebollido, Jessica K. Rigley, Christopher C. Stark</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MINDS. Strong oxygen depletion in the inner regions of a very low-mass star disk?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11761</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11761v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: JWST is discovering a plethora of species in planet-forming disks around very low-mass stars such as C2H2, C6H6, C4H2, CH3 etc. The column densities of these species retrieved from 0D slab models are very large, e.g. of the order of $10^{20}$\,cm$^{-2}$. This is indicating a carbon-dominated chemistry in a gas with a high C/O ratio. The disk around 2MASS-J1605321-1993159 (M4.5) is one such source showing a molecular pseudo-continuum of C2H2. Still two oxygen-bearing molecules, CO and CO2 are also detected in this source. We aim to take the next step beyond 0D slab models to interpret the spectrum. We examine whether 2D thermo-chemical disk models can produce the large inferred column densities of \ce{C2H2} in the inner regions of the disk and produce a pseudo-continuum in the mid-IR spectrum. We also want to constrain whether depletion of oxygen or enrichment of carbon is causing the high C/O ratio triggering a carbon-dominated chemistry. We utilize the radiative thermo-chemical disk model P{\tiny RO}D{\tiny I}M{\tiny O} to identify a disk structure which is capable of producing the observed molecular emission of species such as CO, CO2, C2H2, and H2O simultaneously. The spectrum is generated using the fast line tracer FLiTs. We derive the gas temperature $\langle T \rangle$, column density $\langle$ log$_{\rm {10}} N\rangle$ and the emitting area $\langle r_{\rm{1}} - r_{\rm{2}} \rangle$ for these molecules from the 2D disk model and compare them to the parameters retrieved originally from 0D slab models. We use the different effect that changing the O or C abundance has on CO and C2H2 respectively to discriminate between O depletion and C enhancement. We find that a disk structure characterised by the presence of a gap can best explain the observations. The inner disk is strongly depleted in dust, especially small grains ($&lt;5\,\mu$m), and ..</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11761v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jayatee Kanwar, Inga Kamp, Peter Woitke, Ewine F. van Dishoeck, Thomas Henning, Yao Liu, Till Kaeufer, Beno\^it Tabone, Manuel G\"udel, David Barrado, Aditya M. Arabhavi, Riccardo Franceschi, Marissa Vlasblom</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for ultra-water-rich ammonia hydrates stabilized in icy exoplanetary mantles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11924v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the behavior of the water-ammonia system at high pressure-high temperature conditions is important for modeling the internal dynamics of exoplanet icy mantles. Conventionally, mixtures of ammonia hemihydrate AHH (2:1 ammonia-water molar ratio) and H2O ice VII have been regarded as the ultimate solid phase assembly in the system. Here we report evidence for chemical reactions between AHH and ice VII above 750 K and 16 GPa that stabilize water-rich ammonia hydrates, including a novel ultra-water rich hydrate NH3.6H2O (1:6 ratio) coexisting with ammonia dihydrate ADH (1:2 ratio) and excess ice VII. This assembly is stable up to at least 30 GPa and 1600 K and can be quenched to room temperature. Our results demonstrate that water-rich ammonia hydrates are favored in the icy mantle of 1-2 MEarth exoplanets regardless of the ammonia content of the hydrate crystallized during accretion and/or evolution as long as excess H2O ice is available. The buoyancy contrast between water-rich hydrates and ice VII may lead to chemical stratification in exoplanet icy mantles, hence affecting their thermal evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11924v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anshuman Mondal, Katharina Mohrbach, Timofey Fedotenko, Mandy Bethkenhagen, Hanns-Peter Liermann, Carmen Sanchez-Valle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rings around giant planets and smaller bodies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11963v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: All the four giant planets in our Solar System have rings, but their characteristics are very different. The rings consist of a number of small particles, although individual particles have not been directly imaged. Near the central planet, colliding particles bounce off each other in low-velocity impacts but cannot gravitationally merge due to the effect of the tidal force, resulting in the formation of rings, whereas in more distant regions particles can gravitationally accrete to form satellites. Rings exhibit various types of fine structure, and the mutual gravitational forces between particles and the gravity from satellites play an important role in rings of macroscopic particles, while non-gravitational forces are important for dusty rings. There are several theories about the origin of rings, and formation mechanisms are likely to be different among different ring systems. The rings of small Solar System bodies were discovered through observations of occultations of stars by these bodies. It is natural to expect that some exoplanets should also have rings, but their detection remains challenging. Future discovery of more ring-moon systems around small bodies and exoplanets will provide clues to understanding the formation and evolution of the central bodies that host them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11963v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keiji Ohtsuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Destruction of "Peas in a Pod?" A Candidate Multi-planet System Around the Nearby, Bright Star, HD208487</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12447v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We re-investigate the HD208487 system to test the reality of the proposed HD208487c world. We also search for additional companions using applied Bayesian statistics and 15+ years of new RV data from the HARPS and the PFS instruments that were taken post-discovery of HD208487b.
  The RV data was analyzed with GLS Periodograms, followed by Bayesian analysis using the EMPEROR code. We scrutinised various stellar activity indices to search for any corresponding peaks in the power spectra, correlations with the RV measurements, or significant signals from a Bayesian analysis methodology. Finally, photometric data was checked to test for any transits or possible activity manifestations that could lead to possible false RV signals or excess noise.
  Our analysis points towards a candidate second planet in the system, positioned near the period of a previously proposed and subsequently challenged signal. This signal, HD208487c, would relate to a cool Saturn with an orbital period of 923.06 +2.02 -2.76 d and a minimum mass of Mj sini = 0.32 +/- 0.01Mj. Our analysis also gives rise to a newly discovered candidate planet, HD208487d, which would be the result of a cool super-Neptune/sub-Saturn with a period of 1380.13 +19.20 -8.25 d and a minimum mass of Mj sini = 0.15 +/- 0.01Mj. Neither stellar activity indices nor photometric data show signals statistically matching these periods.
  We have uncovered a candidate three planet system that would consist of an inner gas giant, a central Saturn and an outer super-Neptune/sub-Saturn. A dynamical analysis suggests that gravitational scattering of an initially ordered, equally-spaced system in a long resonant chain of six Neptunes can explain the current proposed architecture of HD208487. More RVs may also shed light on the reality of a fourth Doppler signal uncovered in the data that sits close to the 2:1 period-ratio with signal of HD208487c.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12447v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael I. Rubenstein, James S. Jenkins, Pablo A. Pe\~na R., Carolina Charalambous, Mikko Tuomi, Douglas R. Alves, Jos\'e Vines, Mat\'ias R. D\'iaz, Suman Saha, Paul R. Butler, Jeffrey D. Crane, Steve Shectman, Johanna K. Teske, David Osip, Zahra Essack, Benjamin T. Montet, Adina D. Feinstein, Cristobal Petrovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The JWST Rocky Worlds DDT Program reveals GJ 3929b to likely be a bare rock</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12516</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12516v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report first results from the JWST Rocky Worlds Director's Discretionary Time program. Two secondary eclipses of the terrestrial exoplanet GJ 3929b were recently observed using MIRI photometric imaging at 15 um. We present a reduction of these data using the updated SPARTA pipeline. We also refine the planet mass, radius, and predicted time of secondary eclipse using a new sector of TESS data and new, high-precision radial velocities from the MAROON-X spectrograph. For the two JWST observations, we recover secondary eclipse depths of 177+47-45ppm and 143+34-35ppm at times consistent with a nearly circular orbit, as expected from the radial velocity data. A joint fit of the two visits yields a dayside brightness temperature Tp,dayside = 782+/-79K for GJ 3929b, which is consistent with the maximum brightness temperature Tmax = 737+/-14K for a bare, black rock (i.e., assuming zero Bond albedo and no heat redistribution). These results rule out CO2-rich atmospheres thicker than 100mbar at &gt;3sigma, suggesting that GJ 3929b has lost any significant secondary atmosphere. The radial velocity data also indicate two additional non-transiting planets in the system: a previously-identified planet in a 15.0d orbit, and a newly-identified planet candidate in a 6.1d orbit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12516v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiao Xue, Michael Zhang, Brandon P. Coy, Madison Brady, Xuan Ji, Jacob L. Bean, Michael Radica, Andreas Seifahrt, Julian Sturmer, Rafael Luque, Ritvik Basant, Nina Brown, Tanya Das, David Kasper, Caroline Piaulet-Ghorayeb, Eliza M. -R. Kempton, Edwin S. Kite</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy relaxation in superthermal collisions of carbon with oxygen: the influence of isotopic substitution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12807v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The transition from a once-dense Martian atmosphere to the thin one observed today implies a substantial loss of carbon, either through atmospheric escape or surface deposition. Accurately modeling this carbon escape necessitates accounting for collisions between energetic carbon atoms and the primary atmospheric constituents, including oxygen. To this end, we computed a highly accurate and comprehensive set of potential energy curves (PECs) for the C($^3$P) + O($^3$P) system. Based on these PECs, we derived statistically averaged total elastic and differential cross sections. Comparison with literature data for O($^3$P) + O($^3$P) collisions reveals that cross sections involving carbon can differ by up to a factor of two, indicating that oxygen is not a good proxy for modeling carbon escape. Furthermore, we evaluated the impact of all possible isotopic combinations in C($^3$P) + O($^3$P) collisions and found variations in cross sections of up to 8\%. Given the observed isotopic enrichment of carbon and oxygen in the Martian atmosphere, even such moderate differences can have a significant effect on escape models and the interpretation of planetary evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12807v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheikh T. Bop, Marko Gacesa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An empirical determination of the Cosmic Shoreline</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12865v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Cosmic Shoreline concept was introduced as a way to separate planets with and without atmosphere, based on the relationship between the cumulative instellation and the escape velocity observed in the Solar System. The exoplanet community has tried to refine the way we understand the cosmic shoreline in order to provide a consistent tool for establishing the hierarchy for exoplanet observations. This is particularly relevant when trying to unveil small exoplanet atmospheres with the JWST or the upcoming ELTs. Here, our goal is to use an empirical approach to refine the Cosmic Shoreline concept. In particular, we used the data provided by the ExoAtmospheres database, using the largest available sample of exoplanets with confirmed atmospheric detections. We reconcile limitations in the classical shoreline definition by anchoring our Empirical Cosmic Shoreline (ECS) to both Mars and the irradiated super-Earth 55 Cnc e. The resulting relation exhibits a significantly steeper slope than previously theorized. Applied to planets orbiting M dwarfs, prime targets for habitable-zone studies, the ECS suggests that a larger fraction retain atmospheres than predicted by classical models when using standard Ixuv estimates. However, incorporating revised XUV fluence histories for low-mass M dwarfs (M&lt; 0.35 Ms) reveals severe atmospheric vulnerability: only seven small planets (R&lt;1.7 Re) orbit securely within the retention zone of these stars. We finally identify high-priority targets for the JWST Rocky Worlds survey and future ELT observations based on their ECS positioning and Transmission Spectroscopy Metrics. Future efforts must focus on expanding the empirical validations of the ECS, particularly through high-precision observations of borderline candidates and systems with well-constrained XUV histories. [Abridged]</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12865v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro Meni-Gallardo, Enric Pall\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TIRAMISU: Non-LTE radiative transfer for molecules in exoplanet atmospheres</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12873v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The TIRAMISU code, a new program for computing on-the-fly non-LTE molecular spectra and opacities for solving self-consistent radiative transfer problems in exoplanet atmospheres, is presented. The ultra-hot Jupiter KELT-20 b is used as a case study to identify the wavelength regions at which non-LTE effects may be detectable. It is shown that upper atmospheric OH in vibrational non-LTE should be observable primarily via hot bands in the mid-infrared and enhanced photodissociation in the visible. Varying the abundance of OH in non-LTE demonstrates a non-linear relationship between the abundance and the strength of non-LTE effects. Using recent calculations of the photodissociation probabilities of OH it is shown that non-LTE effects can increase the total photodissociation rate by two orders of magnitude in the upper atmosphere, which is likely to have a significant impact on atmospheric and chemical modelling. Increases and reductions in the molecular opacities under non-LTE conditions may lead to the mischaracterisation of molecular abundances in retrievals that only consider opacities computed under LTE. Collisional data requirements to support future non-LTE modelling for a variety of exoplanet atmospheres and across a wide range of wavelengths are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12873v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charles A. Bowesman, Sergei N. Yurchenko, Ahmed Al-Refaie, Jonathan Tennyson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using Doppler Imaging to model stellar activity and search for planets around Sun-like stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12963v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Doppler Imaging (DI) is a well-established technique to map a physical field at a stellar surface from a time series of high-resolution spectra. In this proof-of-concept study, we aim to show that traditional DI algorithms, originally designed for rapidly-rotating stars, have also the ability to model the activity of Sun-like stars, when observed with new-generation highly-stable spectrographs, and search for low-mass planets around them. We used DI to retrieve the relative brightness distribution at the surface of the Sun from radial velocity (RV) observations collected by HARPS-N between 2022 and 2024. The brightness maps obtained with DI have a typical angular resolution of about 36 degrees and are a good match to low-resolution disc-resolved Dopplergrams of the Sun at epochs when the absolute, disc-integrated RV exceeds ~2 m/s. The RV residuals after DI correction exhibit a dispersion of about 0.6 m/s, comparable with existing state-of-the-art activity correction techniques. Using planet injection-recovery tests, we also show that DI can be a powerful tool for blind planet searches, so long as the orbital period is larger than ~100days (i.e. 3 to 4 stellar rotation periods), and that it yields planetary mass estimates with an accuracy comparable to, for example, multi-dimensional Gaussian process regression. Finally, we highlight some limitations of traditional DI algorithms, which should be addressed to make DI a reliable alternative to state-of-the-art RV-based planet search techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12963v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/staf1337</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Baptiste Klein, Suzanne Aigrain, Michael Cretignier, Xavier Dumusque, Khaled Al Moulla, Jean-Fran\c{c}ois Donati, Niamh K. O'Sullivan, Haochuan Yu, Andrew Collier Cameron, Oscar Barrag\'an, Annelies Mortier, Alessandro Sozzetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Activity in White Dwarf Debris Disks I: Spitzer Legacy Reveals Variability Incompatible with the Canonical Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13119</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13119v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study presents all available, multi-epoch 3.6 and 4.5 $\mu$m photometry from Spitzer Space Telescope observations of white dwarf debris disks, including weekly cadence observations of 16 relatively bright systems, and 5 h staring-mode observations for five of these. Significant variability is detected in 85 per cent of disks and across all timescales probed, from minutes to weeks to years, where the largest flux changes correlate with the longest time baselines, and the infrared excesses persist utterly. While each source is idiosyncratic, the overall results indicate the most variable disks correlate with those that are the brightest (dustiest), and also among those with detected gas, demonstrating both dust and gas are produced via ongoing collisions. There is a correlation between flux and colour changes, where disks tend to appear redder when dimmer and bluer when brighter, consistent with an excess of small dust grains produced in collisions, followed by a gradual return to equilibrium. The overall results are a drastic departure from the predictions of the canonical - geometrically thin, optically thick - disk in both flux and colour, but are broadly consistent with collisional evolution based on a simple model. The data presented herein constitute a legacy resource that can inform time-series studies of polluted and dusty white dwarfs, and importantly serve as a basis for future disk modelling, beyond the pioneering canonical framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13119v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiba Tu Noor, Jay Farihi, Scott J. Kenyon, Roman R. Rafikov, Mark C. Wyatt, Kate Y. L. Su, Carl Melis, Andrew Swan, Thomas G. Wilson, Boris T. G\"ansicke, Amy Bonsor, Laura K. Rogers, Seth Redfield, Mukremin Kilic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aligned Stellar Obliquities for Two Hot Jupiter-hosting M Dwarfs Revealed by MAROON-X: Implications for Hot Jupiter Formation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13145v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hot Jupiters (HJs) are $2-3\times$ less common around early M dwarfs than around AFGK stars, suggesting that HJs may form and/or migrate via distinct pathways around different types of stars. One source of insight into HJ formation mechanisms is to trace their dynamical histories through measurements of host stellar obliquities via the Rossiter-McLaughlin (RM) effect. Here we present measurements of the RM effect for the HJs TOI-3714 b and TOI-5293 A b using the Gemini-North/MAROON-X spectrograph. Our measurements represent just the second and third hot Jupiters around M dwarfs (HJMD) with a detection of the RM effect. We find that both systems are well-aligned with sky-projected obliquities of $\lambda = 21^{+14}_{-11}$$\mathrm{^{\circ}}$ and $-12^{+19}_{-14}$$\mathrm{^{\circ}}$ and deprojected obliquities of $\psi = 26^{+11}_{-10}$$\mathrm{^{\circ}}$ and $24^{+11}_{-10}$$\mathrm{^{\circ}}$ for TOI-3714 and TOI-5293 A, respectively. Both stars are in wide binary systems. We refine the stellar parameters by decontaminating their unresolved $K_s$-band photometry and constrain the binary orbits using Gaia DR3 astrometry. We find that the minimum mutual inclination of the planet and binary companion in the TOI-5293 system is sufficiently large to drive Kozai-Lidov (KL) migration while the result for TOI-3714 is inconclusive. We present a population-level analysis of HJs around AFGK versus early M dwarfs and argue that KL migration is more efficient around the latter, which is expected to produce misaligned stellar obliquities in HJMD systems in the absence of efficient tidal damping. The emerging population of well-aligned HJMD hosts supports the expectation that M dwarfs, with their deep convective envelopes, do efficiently dampen misaligned obliquities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13145v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Drew Weisserman, Erik Gillis, Ryan Cloutier, Nina Brown, Jacob L. Bean, Andreas Seifahrt, Tanya Das, Madison Brady, Bertram Bitsch, Emily Deibert, Thomas M. Evans-Soma, Noah Fenlon, Laura Kreidberg, Michael Line, Ralph Pudritz, Evgenya L. Shkolnik, Luis Welbanks</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stellar metallicity is a key parameter for the search of Life in the Universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.03748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.03748v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The search for Life in the Universe generally assumes three basic life's needs: I) building block elements (i.e., CHNOPS), II) a solvent to life's reactions (generally, liquid water) and III) a thermodynamic disequilibrium. It is assumed that similar requirements might be universal in the Cosmos. On our planet, life is able to harvest energy from a wide array of thermodynamic disequilibria, generally in the form of redox disequilibrium. The amount of different redox couples used by living systems has been estimated to be in the range of several thousands of reactions. Each of these energy yielding reactions requires specialised proteins called oxidoreductases, that have one or more metal cofactors acting as catalytic centres to exchange electrons. These metals are de facto the key component of the engines that life uses to tap into the thermodynamic disequilibria needed to fuel metabolism. The availability of these transition metals is not uniform in the Universe, and it is a function of the distribution (in time and space) of complex dynamics. Despite this, Life's need for specific metals to access thermodynamic disequilibria has been so far completely overlooked in identifying astrobiological targets. We argue that the availability of at least some transition elements appears to be an essential feature of habitability, and should be considered a primary requisite in selecting exoplanetary targets in the search for life.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.03748v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Covone, Donato Giovannelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Interior Structure and Mode of Tidal Heating in Enceladus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14743v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Enceladus is among the most intriguing bodies in the solar system due to its astrobiological potential. Determining the extent and duration of habitability (i.e., sustained habitability) at Enceladus requires characterizing its interior properties as well as the level and distribution of tidal heating. Inferring the intensity of geophysical activity in the core has direct implications for understanding the potential for hydrothermal activity and the supply of chemical species important for habitability to the ocean. We build a statistical framework using an MCMC approach to constrain the interior structure based on currently available estimates of libration, shape, heat flux, and total mass. We use this framework to examine the extent to which geodetic measurements can improve our understanding of the interior structure, with an emphasis on determining the partitioning of tidal dissipation between the shell and the core. We quantify plausible ranges of gravitational (k2) and displacement (h2 and l2) tidal Love numbers consistent with existing observations. We demonstrate that measuring the amplitude and phase of k2 alone can only constrain the total tidally dissipated energy, but not its radial distribution. However, measuring the amplitude and phase of h2 or l2 facilitates determining the extent of tidal dissipation in the shell and the core. We provide the precisions required for measuring k2, h2, and/or l2 that enable distinguishing between the two main scenarios of tidal heating, i.e., in the shell versus the core. We also briefly explore the effect of the structural heterogeneities of the shell on the tidal response. Lastly, we evaluate the efficacy of a suite of future geodetic measurements to constrain key interior properties essential to understand the present-day (i.e., instantaneous) and long-term (sustained) habitability at Enceladus.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14743v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amirhossein Bagheri, Mark Simons, Ryan S. Park, Alexander Berne, Mohit Melwani Daswani, Steven D Vance</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Differentiation, the exception not the rule -- Evidence for full miscibility in sub-Neptune interiors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.00947v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the consequences of non-ideal mixing between silicate, iron metal, and hydrogen for the structures of the cores of sub-Neptunes with implications for super-Earths, warm Neptunes, and ice giants. A method of extrapolating what we know about the miscibility in the three bounding binary systems MgSiO$_3$-H$_2$, MgSiO$_3$-Fe, and Fe-H$_2$ to the ternary composition space is used to deduce the phase equilibria of this system at relevant temperature and pressure conditions. We find that while separate silicate and metal phases can exist at shallow depths, the phases become entirely miscible deeper in the cores, thus altering the density structure of the cores. The assumption that the interiors of large rocky planets, either with extant magma oceans beneath H$_2$-rich envelopes, or evolved from such bodies, are composed of a differentiated metal core overlain by a silicate mantle is inconsistent with our understanding of the phase equilibria of these bodies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.00947v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Edward D. Young, Aaron Werlen, Sarah P. Marcum, Lars Stixrude, Cornelis P. Dullemond</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hubble Space Telescope Observations of the Interstellar Interloper 3I/ATLAS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02934</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02934v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present high angular resolution observations of the third known interstellar interloper, 3I/ATLAS, from the Hubble Space Telescope. The object is clearly active at 3.8 au pre-perihelion, showing dust emitted from the hot Sun-facing side of the nucleus and a weak, radiation pressure swept tail away from the Sun. We apply a simple model to estimate the mass loss rate in dust as dM/dt = 6 sqrt(a) kg/s, where a is the mean particle size in microns. With 1 &lt; a &lt; 100, we infer dM/dt = 6 to 60 kg/s. A fit to the surface brightness distribution of the inner coma limits the effective radius of the nucleus to be r &lt; 2.8 km, assuming red geometric albedo 0.04. Conversely, the nucleus cannot be smaller than 0.16 km in radius if its coma is supplied by sublimation of carbon monoxide, and must be larger if a less volatile molecule drives the mass loss.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02934v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Jewitt, Man-To Hui, Max Mutchler, Yoonyoung Kim, Jessica Agarwal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence For Turbulent Concentration In Particle-Laden Midplane Layers of Planet-Forming Disks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05858v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study we investigate the axisymmetric, weakly turbulent state of settled particle layers in a localized model of a protoplanetary disk. We focus on conditions in which the large-scale axisymmetric filaments typically associated with the streaming instability (SI) either cannot form or have not yet developed. Under these circumstances, we observe small-scale particle clumping consistent with turbulent concentration (TC), in which short particle filaments collect along regions of high gas strain rate and enclose gas-only voids exhibiting coherent vorticity. Despite varying particle Stokes numbers $\St_K$ which are defined relative to the Keplerian frequency, the {\it effective} Stokes numbers within voids, $\St_\omega$ -- defined instead relative to the local gas vorticity -- consistently center around 0.3. The latter coincides with the special value identified in prior statistical studies of TC as the scale where particle clustering is most intermittent. This convergence likely reflects how particle feedback structures and sustains voids -- an effect possibly distinctive to axisymmetric configurations. A timescale comparison reveals that in simulations with midplane particle-to-gas density ratios below unity and $\St_K \ll 1$, SI growth rates are 1 -- 2 orders of magnitude slower than the turbulent overturn frequencies at the driving scale. This disparity appears to effectively rule out SI as the primary driver of turbulence in these cases. Instead, we suggest the Symmetric Instability (SymI) may be responsible. We further observe that for St$_K\ll 1$, TC is a persistent feature of turbulent particle layers , and that Roche-exceeding small-scale fluctuations within large-scale SI filaments reported in the literature are in fact not SI, but expressions of TC amplified by the elevated particle densities within those large-scale structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05858v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Orkan M. Umurhan, Debanjan Sengupta, Paul R. Estrada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct High-Resolution Imaging of Earth-Like Exoplanets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20236</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20236v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We have surveyed all conventional methods proposed or conceivable for obtaining resolved images of an Earth-like exoplanet. Generating a 10 x 10 pixel map of a 1 R_E world at 10 pc demands ~0.85 uas angular resolution and photon-collection sufficient for SNR &gt;= 5 per "micro-pixel." We derived diffraction-limit and photon-budget requirements for: (1) large single-aperture space telescopes with internal coronagraphs; (2) external-starshades; (3) space-based interferometry (nulling and non-nulling); (4) ground-based ELTs with extreme AO; (5) pupil-densified "hypertelescopes"; (6) indirect reconstructions (rotational light-curve inversion, eclipse mapping, intensity interferometry); and (7) diffraction-occultation by Solar System bodies. Even though these approaches serve their primary goals-exoplanet discovery and initial coarse characterization--each remains orders of magnitude away from delivering a spatially resolved image. In every case, technology readiness falls short, and fundamental barriers leave them 2-5 orders of magnitude below the angular resolution and photon-budget thresholds needed to map an Earth analog even on decadal timescales. Ultimately, an in-situ platform delivered to &lt;= 0.1 AU of the target could, in principle, overcome both diffraction and photon-starvation limits--but such a mission far exceeds current propulsion, autonomy, and communications capabilities. By contrast, the Solar Gravitational Lens--providing on-axis gain of ~1e10 and inherent uas-scale focusing once an imaging spacecraft reaches beyond &gt;=550 AU--appears uniquely capable of simultaneously meeting both the resolution and photon-budget requirements. The SGL thus enables true, resolved surface images and spatially resolved spectroscopy of Earth-like exoplanets in our stellar neighborhood, provided several mission-specific risks (coronal calibration, focal-plane scanning, deconvolution) are retired.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20236v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Slava G. Turyshev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meridional circulation molecular-weighted</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03844v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Meridional circulation in stratified stellar/planetary interiors in the presence of stable molecular weight gradients remains poorly understood, thereby affecting angular momentum transport in evolutionary models. We extend the downward control principle of atmospheric sciences to include compositional stratification. Using a linearized analysis we show that stable compositional gradients slow down the penetration of circulation into the depths, emphasizing the importance of time-dependent solutions. However, additional effects such as horizontal turbulence or magnetic fields are needed to halt it completely. We also find limits demarcating linear and nonlinear regimes in terms of Schmidt and Rossby numbers. Nonlinear simulations exhibit compositional mixing due to meridional currents, enabling deeper penetration than otherwise. We propose slowly evolving and steady-state scenarios for the solar tachocline, and helioseismically observed heavy element abundances, while acknowledging the absence of constraints on the radial variation of the Schmidt number. In the context of stellar evolution, differential rotation profiles of solar-type main-sequence stars may follow analytical solutions extending from Banik &amp; Menou (2024), thereby aiding further probes into magneto/hydrodynamic instabilities and outward angular momentum transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03844v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Deepayan Banik, Kristen Menou, Evan H. Anders</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
