<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.EP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.EP</link>
    <description>astro-ph.EP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.EP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 04:00:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The invisible threat: assessing the collisional hazard posed by the undiscovered Venus co-orbital asteroids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.15968v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Currently, 20 co-orbital asteroids of Venus are known, with only one with an eccentricity below 0.38. This is most likely caused by observational biases since asteroids with larger eccentricities may approach the Earth and are easier to detect. We aim to assess the possible threat that the yet undetected population of Venus co-orbitals may pose to Earth, and investigate their detectability from Earth and space observatories. We used semi-analytical models of the 1:1 mean-motion resonance with Venus and numerical simulations to monitor close encounters with Earth on several co-orbital cycles. We analyzed observability windows and brightness variations for potential Venus co-orbitals as viewed from ground-based telescopes to assess their future detection feasibility with next-generation survey capabilities. There is a range of orbits with e &lt; 0.38, larger at lower inclinations, for which Venus' co-orbitals can pose a collisional hazard to Earth. Current ground-based observations are constrained by periodic observing windows and solar elongation limitations, though the Rubin Observatory may detect some of these objects during favorable configurations. Space missions based on Venus' orbits may be instrumental in detecting Venus' co-orbitals at low eccentricities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.15968v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Carruba, R. Sfair, R. A. Araujo, O. C. Winter, D. C. Mour\~ao, S. Di Ruzza, S. Aljbaae, G. Carit\'a, R. C. Domingos, A. A. Alves</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NIRCam yells at cloud: JWST MIRI imaging can directly detect exoplanets of the same temperature, mass, age, and orbital separation as Saturn and Jupiter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15995</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.15995v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: NIRCam and MIRI coronagraphy have successfully demonstrated the ability to directly image young sub-Jupiter mass and mature gas-giant exoplanets. However, these modes struggle to reach the sensitivities needed to find the population of cold giant planets that are similar to our own Solar System's giant planets ($T_{\rm eff} = 60 - 125$ K; $a=5 - 30$ AU). For the first time, we explore the high-contrast imaging capabilities of MIRI imaging rather than coronagraphy. Using data from the JWST GO 6122: Cool Kids on the Block program which targets nearby ($&lt;6$ pc) M-dwarfs with NIRCam coronagraphy and MIRI imaging, we demonstrate that 21$\mu$m MIRI imaging can detect planets with the same temperature, mass, age, and orbital separations as Saturn and Jupiter. For systems within 3pc, 21$\mu$m MIRI imaging reaches the sensitivity needed to detect planets colder than Saturn ($&lt;95$ K). NIRCam coronagraphy can achieve similar results only in the unlikely case that a cold giant planet is cloud-free. Motivated by these compelling findings, we extend our analysis to evaluate the measured performance of MIRI F2100W imaging versus NIRCam F444W coronagraphy to 70 pc and conclude that MIRI imaging offers the advantage for systems within 20pc. Microlensing surveys predict an occurrence rate as high as 1 - 2 low-mass giant exoplanets per star, suggesting that JWST MIRI imaging surveys of nearby systems may be poised to uncover a substantial population. This breakthrough enables a path towards the first direct characterization of cold giant exoplanets that are analogous to the solar system giant planets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.15995v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rachel Bowens-Rubin, James Mang, Mary Anne Limbach, Aarynn L. Carter, Kevin B. Stevenson, Kevin Wagner, Giovanni Strampelli, Caroline V. Morley, Grant Kennedy, Elisabeth Matthews, Andrew Vanderburg, Ma\"issa Salama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-based machine learning for mantle convection simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16041v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mantle convection simulations are an essential tool for understanding how rocky planets evolve. However, the poorly known input parameters to these simulations, the non-linear dependence of transport properties on pressure and temperature, and the long integration times in excess of several billion years all pose a computational challenge for numerical solvers. We propose a physics-based machine learning approach that predicts creeping flow velocities as a function of temperature while conserving mass, thereby bypassing the numerical solution of the Stokes problem. A finite-volume solver then uses the predicted velocities to advect and diffuse the temperature field to the next time-step, enabling autoregressive rollout at inference. For training, our model requires temperature-velocity snapshots from a handful of simulations (94). We consider mantle convection in a two-dimensional rectangular box with basal and internal heating, pressure- and temperature-dependent viscosity. Overall, our model is up to 89 times faster than the numerical solver. We also show the importance of different components in our convolutional neural network architecture such as mass conservation, learned paddings on the boundaries, and loss scaling for the overall rollout performance. Finally, we test our approach on unseen scenarios to demonstrate some of its strengths and weaknesses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16041v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siddhant Agarwal, Ali Can Bekar, Christian H\"uttig, David S. Greenberg, Nicola Tosi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Seismic Signal Detection and Source Identification of Atmospheric Entries: The Hayabusa2 Sample Return Capsule as a Benchmark</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16072v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This exploratory study investigates whether seismic signals can be used to infer fragmentation during a fireball event. Re-entry objects, particularly sample return capsules (SRCs) such as the one from the Hayabusa2 mission, behave similarly to slow meteors during atmospheric entry and provide valuable insights into natural fireball events. In this study, we initially analyse seismic signals from the Hayabusa2 SRC re-entry, which took place on December 5, 2020, over South Australia. The SRC's signature was captured by a dense network of seismic stations (Eakin, 2018; O'Donnell et al., 2020), offering a unique opportunity to investigate the signals' characteristics and verify their connection to the re-entry event. The ballistic trajectory was confirmed as the source shock mechanism for this event. We isolate this signal and use it as a reference for a ballistic shock signature and compare it to three other fireball case studies, including a suborbital re-entry and two natural meteoroids. Although factors such as local geology and atmospheric conditions were not considered in this preliminary study, our results show promise, with high correlations for events with purely ballistic trajectories and lower correlations for those involving fragmentation or airbursts. This implies that seismic data may be able to disambiguate whether any particular fireball event underwent significant fragmentation or airburst, key phenomena for assessing body strengths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16072v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Iona Clemente, Eleanor K. Sansom, Hadrien A. R. Devillepoix, Taichi Kawamura, Benjamin A. Fernando, Raphael F. Garcia, Olivia Collet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of thermal conductivity on the simultaneous formation of a stable region at the top of Earth's core and magnetic field generation over four billion years</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16198v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The possibility of the emergence of a stratified region in the uppermost part of the Earth's outer core with long-term magnetic field generation is assessed, taking into account uncertainties in the thermal conductivity of the Earth's core and the present-day heat flow across the core-mantle boundary (CMB). The radial structures of the Earth's outer core are calculated for various values of thermal conductivity and CMB heat flow using a one-dimensional thermo-chemical model. The results show that there exist solutions that allow both emergence of stable stratification and long-term magnetic field generation although their thickness of stratified region is thinner than 100 km. In order to satisfy both emergence of stratified region and long-term magnetic field generation, possible value of the present-day CMB heat flow (13-15 TW) suggests a thermal conductivity of 77-121 W/m/K at CMB, which is in good agreement with the values estimated from the electrical conductivity measurements under the Earth' s core condition. The thickness of the stratified region in this case is about 50 km, which is also consistent with the thickness of the stratified region estimated from the geomagnetic secular variation. However, the proposed values of thermal conductivity obtained by this analysis could be smaller when the present-day CMB heat flow becomes smaller than the constraint used in this study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16198v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.pepi.2025.107380</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physics of Earth and Planetary Interiors, 365 (2025) 107380</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Takashi Nakagawa, Shin-ichi Takahero, Youhei Sasaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modern Earth-like Chemical Disequilibrium Biosignatures Are Challenging To Constrain Through Spectroscopic Retrievals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16231</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16231v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Robust exoplanet characterization studies are underway, and the community is looking ahead toward developing observational strategies to search for life beyond our solar system. With the development of life detection approaches like searching for atmospheric chemical species indicative of life, chemical disequilibrium has also been proposed as a potentially key signature for life. Chemical disequilibrium can arise from the production of waste gases due to biological processes and can be quantified using a metric known as the available Gibbs free energy. The main goal of this study was to explore the detectability of chemical disequilibrium for a modern Earth-like analog. Atmospheric retrievals coupled to a thermodynamics model were used to determine posterior distributions for the available Gibbs free energy given simulated observations at various noise levels. In reflected light, chemical disequilibrium signals were difficult to detect and limited by the constraints on the CH4 abundance, which was challenging to constrain for a modern Earth case with simulated observations spanning ultraviolet through near-infrared wavelengths with V-band SNRs of 10, 20, and 40. For a modern Earth analog orbiting a late-type M dwarf, we simulated transit observations with the James Webb Space Telescope Mid-Infrared Instrument (MIRI) and found that tight constraints on the available Gibbs free energy can be achieved, but only at extremely low noise on the order of several ppm. This study serves as further proof of concept for remotely inferring chemical disequilibrium biosignatures and should be included in continuing to build life detection strategies for future exoplanet characterization missions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16231v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amber Young, Tyler Robinson, Joshua Krissansen-Totton, Edward Schwieterman, Giada Arney, Gerrick Lindberg, Cristina Thomas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Early Stellar Flybys are Unlikely: Improved Constraints from Sednoids and Large-$q$ TNOs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16317v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Sedna-like objects (a.k.a. sednoids) are transneptunian objects (TNOs) characterized by large semimajor axes and exceptionally high perihelia. Their high-$q$ orbits are detached from the influence of the four giant planets and need extra perturbation to form. One hypothesis posits that close stellar flybys could have perturbed objects from the primordial scattering disk, generating the sednoid population. In this study, we run N-body simulations with different stellar encounter configurations to explore whether such a close stellar flyby can satisfy new constraints identified from sednoid (and detached extreme TNO) observation, including the low-inclination ($i&lt;30^\circ$) profile and primordial orbital alignment. Our results suggest that flybys with field stars are unable to generate a sufficient population, whereas flybys within the birth cluster fail to produce the primordial orbital alignment. To meet the inclination constraint of detached extreme TNOs, flybys have to be either coplanar ($i_\star \sim 0^\circ$) or symmetric about the ecliptic plane ($\omega_\star \sim 0^\circ, i_\star \sim 90^\circ$). After taking into account their occurrence rate at the early stage of the Solar System, we conclude that close-in stellar flybys ($q_\star \le 1000$~au) that satisfy all constraints are unlikely to happen ($\lesssim$5\%). Future discoveries of additional sednoids with precise orbital determinations are crucial to confirm the existence of the low-inclination tendency and the primordial alignment, and to further constrain the early dynamical evolution of the Solar System.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16317v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qingru Hu, Yukun Huang, Brett Gladman, Wei Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Abiotic Ozone in the Observable Atmospheres of Venus and Venus-like Exoplanets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16543v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ozone is a potential biosignature and disambuguator between Earth-like and Venus-like exoplanets due to its association on Earth with photosynthetically produced oxygen (O$_2$). However, the existence of ozone in Venus's observable atmosphere, a planet with no known life, raises the possibility of ozone biosignature false-positives on Venus-like exoplanets. We use a photochemical model of Venus's atmosphere to investigate the origin of its mesospheric ozone layer, and to predict how similar ozone layers would manifest for Venus-like exoplanets. For Venus, our model shows that the previously proposed fluxes of O atoms produced on the dayside and transported to the nightside cannot generate enough ozone to match the observed nightside ozone concentrations without also producing O$_2$ in excess of the observed upper limit. Nor can sufficient ozone be produced by varying the lower-atmosphere chemistry, atmospheric thermal structure, or received stellar flux in our model of Venus's atmosphere. These results imply that a presently unknown chemical pathway is responsible for the ozone production in Venus's nightside mesosphere. Ozone production rates from this pathway of 10$^5$--10$^7$ cm$^{-3}$s$^{-1}$ above the cloud layer on the nightside can re-produce the observed O$_3$ concentrations. Generalised to Venus-like exoplanets, known chemistry similarly fails to produce ozone in the abundance seen in the Venusian mesosphere. However, until the origin of Venus's ozone is understood, we cannot rule out that ozone production at concentrations observable with JWST will be common on abiotic Venus-like worlds, a possibility that limits the usefulness of ozone as a habsignature and as a biosignature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16543v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robb Calder, Oliver Shorttle, Sean Jordan, Paul Rimmer, Tereza Constantinou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A correlation between accretion and outflow rates for Class II Young Stellar Objects with full and transition disks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16586v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetothermal (MHD) winds and jets originate in a wide range of regions of protoplanetary disks (1-30 au) and are thought to be the primary mechanisms driving accretion onto the central star. One indirect signature of these processes is the free-free emission from ionized gas close to the star. We analyze a sample of 31 Class II disks: 18 full disks (FD) and 13 transition disks (TD). All sources show evidence of excess free-free emission over the contribution of the thermal dust. We investigate the origin of this emission and whether it is associated with other observables. We first analyzed a sample of objects in Taurus, exploring correlations with the properties of the central star, the disk, and other disk-wind tracers. We compared our findings with a sample of TD for which free-free emission was shown to be likely associated with an MHD-wind/jet. We found no correlation between the detected free-free emission and either the X-ray or the [OI]6300A line properties. We found a strong correlation between the ionized mass loss rate, as inferred from the free-free emission, and the accretion rate, suggesting that free-free emission in FD is associated with an MHD-wind/jet. The detected free-free emission in both TD and FD is likely similarly associated with an ionized gas close to the star from an MHD-wind/jet. The free-free emission detected in TD shows hints of shallower correlations with accretion properties than in FD. Whereas the efficiency in transforming accretion into outflow might differ in TD and FD, considering the correlations between free-free emission and accretion properties, this difference could simply result from a bias toward strong accretors in the TD sample. Therefore, observations of a more complete and uniform sample are necessary to determine whether this change in correlations holds only for strong accretors or for TD in general.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16586v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. A. Rota, N. van der Marel, A. Garufi, C. Carrasco-Gonz\'alez, E. Macias, I. Pascucci, A. Sellek, L. Testi, A. Isella, S. Facchini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Increased hydrogen escape from Mars atmosphere during periods of high obliquity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16692v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is still unknown how much water has escaped from Mars during its history. Hydrogen escape from Mars's atmosphere probably played a major role in drying the planet, but present-day Hloss rates (about 3x10^26 atoms per second on average) cannot explain the geological evidence for the large volumes of liquid water on ancient Mars. Here we used the three-dimensional Mars-Planetary Climate Model to show that H loss rates could have increased by more than one order of magnitude (6x10^27 atoms per second) during higher spin axis obliquity periods, notably in the last few million years when Mars's obliquity was about 35 deg on average. The resulting accumulated H escape over Mars's history translates into an approx. 80 m global equivalent layer, which is close to the lower limit of geological estimates, assessing the major role of atmospheric escape in drying Mars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16692v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41550-025-02561-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nat Astron (2025), published on-line on 21 May 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gabriella Gilli, Francisco Gonz\'alez-Galindo, Jean-Yves Chaufray, Ehouarn Millour, Fran\c{c}ois Forget, Franck Montmessin, Franck Lef\`evre, Joseph Naar, Yangcheng Luo, Margaux Vals, Lo\"ic Rossi, Miguel \'Angel L\'opez-Valverde, Adri\'an Brines</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impacts of Tidal Locking on Magnetospheric Energy Input to Exoplanet Atmospheres</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16825v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the effect of planetary corotation on energy dissipation within the magnetosphere-ionosphere system of exoplanets. Using MHD simulations, we find that tidally locked exoplanets have a higher cross-polar cap potential (CPCP) compared to fast-rotating planets with the same magnetic field strength, confirming previous studies. Our simulations show that for a given interplanetary magnetic field, an increase in corotation period leads to a higher CPCP. Notably, this difference in CPCP between tidally locked and rotating planets persists across a range of solar wind conditions, including extreme environments such as those experienced by hot Jupiters. Furthermore, we observe that variations in corotation have little impact on CPCP for Earth-sized planets. These results underscore the significance of both corotation dynamics and planetary size in understanding how exoplanets interact with their stellar environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16825v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/adcec7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ApJ 985 170 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fatemeh Bagheri, Alex Glocer, Ramon E. Lopez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Projections of Earth's technosphere: Scenario modeling, worldbuilding, and overview of remotely detectable technosignatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.00067</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.00067v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study uses methods from futures studies to develop a set of ten self-consistent scenarios for Earth's 1000-year future, which can serve as examples for defining technosignature search strategies. We apply a novel worldbuilding pipeline that evaluates the dimensions of human needs in each scenario as a basis for defining the observable properties of the technosphere. Our scenarios include three with zero-growth stability, two that have collapsed into a stable state, one that oscillates between growth and collapse, and four that continue to grow. Only one scenario includes rapid growth that could lead to interstellar expansion. We examine absorption spectral features for a few scenarios to illustrate that nitrogen dioxide can serve as a technosignature to distinguish between present-day Earth, pre-agricultural Earth, and an industrial 1000-year future Earth. Three of our scenarios are spectrally indistinguishable from pre-agricultural Earth, even though these scenarios include expansive technospheres. Up to nine of these scenarios could represent steady-state examples that could persist for much longer timescales, and it remains possible that short-duration technospheres could be the most abundant. Our scenario set provides the basis for further systematic thinking about technosignature detection as well as for imagining a broad range of possibilities for Earth's future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.00067v3</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.pop-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.techfore.2025.124194</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Technological Forecasting and Social Change (2025) 218: 124194</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jacob Haqq-Misra, George Profitiliotis, Ravi Kopparapu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
