<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.MA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MA</link>
    <description>cs.MA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2024 04:00:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Responsible Blockchain: STEADI Principles and the Actor-Network Theory-based Development Methodology (ANT-RDM)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.06179</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.06179v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper provides a comprehensive analysis of the challenges and controversies associated with blockchain technology. It identifies technical challenges such as scalability, security, privacy, and interoperability, as well as business and adoption challenges, and the social, economic, ethical, and environmental controversies present in current blockchain systems. We argue that responsible blockchain development is key to overcoming these challenges and achieving mass adoption. This paper defines Responsible Blockchain and introduces the STEADI principles (sustainable, transparent, ethical, adaptive, decentralized, and inclusive) for responsible blockchain development. Additionally, it presents the Actor-Network Theory-based Responsible Development Methodology (ANT-RDM) for blockchains, which includes the steps of problematization, interessement, enrollment, and mobilization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.06179v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1561/2900000038</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Foundations and Trends in Information Systems: Vol. 7: No. 4, pp 310-356 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yibai Li, Ahmed Gomaa, Xiaobing Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Foragax: An Agent Based Modelling framework based on JAX</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.06345</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.06345v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Foraging for resources is a ubiquitous activity conducted by living organisms in a shared environment to maintain their homeostasis. Modelling multi-agent foraging in-silico allows us to study both individual and collective emergent behaviour in a tractable manner. Agent-based modelling has proven to be effective in simulating such tasks, though scaling the simulations to accommodate large numbers of agents with complex dynamics remains challenging. In this work, we present Foragax, a general-purpose, scalable, hardware-accelerated, multi-agent foraging toolkit. Leveraging the JAX library, our toolkit can simulate thousands of agents foraging in a common environment, in an end-to-end vectorized and differentiable manner. The toolkit provides agent-based modelling tools to model various foraging tasks, including options to design custom spatial and temporal agent dynamics, control policies, sensor models, and boundary conditions. Further, the number of agents during such simulations can be increased or decreased based on custom rules. The toolkit can also be used to potentially model more general multi-agent scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.06345v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siddharth Chaturvedi, Ahmed El-Gazzar, Marcel van Gerven</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Voronoi-based Multi-Robot Formations for 3D Source Seeking via Cooperative Gradient Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05995</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05995v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we tackle the problem of localizing the source of a three-dimensional signal field with a team of mobile robots able to collect noisy measurements of its strength and share information with each other. The adopted strategy is to cooperatively compute a closed-form estimation of the gradient of the signal field that is then employed to steer the multi-robot system toward the source location. In order to guarantee an accurate and robust gradient estimation, the robots are placed on the surface of a sphere of fixed radius. More specifically, their positions correspond to the generators of a constrained Centroidal Voronoi partition on the spherical surface. We show that, by keeping these specific formations, both crucial geometric properties and a high level of field coverage are simultaneously achieved and that they allow estimating the gradient via simple analytic expressions. We finally provide simulation results to evaluate the performance of the proposed approach, considering both noise-free and noisy measurements. In particular, a comparative analysis shows how its higher robustness against faulty measurements outperforms an alternative state-of-the-art solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05995v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lara Bri\~n\'on-Arranz, Martin Abou Hamad, Alessandro Renzaglia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>System Neural Diversity: Measuring Behavioral Heterogeneity in Multi-Agent Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.02128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.02128v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Evolutionary science provides evidence that diversity confers resilience in natural systems. Yet, traditional multi-agent reinforcement learning techniques commonly enforce homogeneity to increase training sample efficiency. When a system of learning agents is not constrained to homogeneous policies, individuals may develop diverse behaviors, resulting in emergent complementarity that benefits the system. Despite this, there is a surprising lack of tools that quantify behavioral diversity. Such techniques would pave the way towards understanding the impact of diversity in collective artificial intelligence and enabling its control. In this paper, we introduce System Neural Diversity (SND): a measure of behavioral heterogeneity in multi-agent systems. We discuss and prove its theoretical properties, and compare it with alternate, state-of-the-art behavioral diversity metrics used in the robotics domain. Through simulations of a variety of cooperative multi-robot tasks, we show how our metric constitutes an important tool that enables measurement and control of behavioral heterogeneity. In dynamic tasks, where the problem is affected by repeated disturbances during training, we show that SND allows us to measure latent resilience skills acquired by the agents, while other proxies, such as task performance (reward), fail to. Finally, we show how the metric can be employed to control diversity, allowing us to enforce a desired heterogeneity set-point or range. We demonstrate how this paradigm can be used to bootstrap the exploration phase, finding optimal policies faster, thus enabling novel and more efficient MARL paradigms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.02128v2</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Bettini, Ajay Shankar, Amanda Prorok</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mean-Field Approximation of Cooperative Constrained Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning (CMARL)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.07437</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.07437v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Mean-Field Control (MFC) has recently been proven to be a scalable tool to approximately solve large-scale multi-agent reinforcement learning (MARL) problems. However, these studies are typically limited to unconstrained cumulative reward maximization framework. In this paper, we show that one can use the MFC approach to approximate the MARL problem even in the presence of constraints. Specifically, we prove that, an $N$-agent constrained MARL problem, with state, and action spaces of each individual agents being of sizes $|\mathcal{X}|$, and $|\mathcal{U}|$ respectively, can be approximated by an associated constrained MFC problem with an error, $e\triangleq \mathcal{O}\left([\sqrt{|\mathcal{X}|}+\sqrt{|\mathcal{U}|}]/\sqrt{N}\right)$. In a special case where the reward, cost, and state transition functions are independent of the action distribution of the population, we prove that the error can be improved to $e=\mathcal{O}(\sqrt{|\mathcal{X}|}/\sqrt{N})$. Also, we provide a Natural Policy Gradient based algorithm and prove that it can solve the constrained MARL problem within an error of $\mathcal{O}(e)$ with a sample complexity of $\mathcal{O}(e^{-6})$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.07437v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Washim Uddin Mondal, Vaneet Aggarwal, Satish V. Ukkusuri</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
