<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.MA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MA</link>
    <description>cs.MA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 04:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Agent Software Development through Cross-Team Collaboration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.08979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.08979v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The latest breakthroughs in Large Language Models (LLMs), eg., ChatDev, have catalyzed profound transformations, particularly through multi-agent collaboration for software development. LLM agents can collaborate in teams like humans, and follow the waterfall model to sequentially work on requirements analysis, development, review, testing, and other phases to perform autonomous software generation. However, for an agent team, each phase in a single development process yields only one possible outcome. This results in the completion of only one development chain, thereby losing the opportunity to explore multiple potential decision paths within the solution space. Consequently, this may lead to obtaining suboptimal results. To address this challenge, we introduce Cross-Team Collaboration (CTC), a scalable multi-team framework that enables orchestrated teams to jointly propose various decisions and communicate with their insights in a cross-team collaboration environment for superior content generation. Experimental results in software development reveal a notable increase in quality compared to state-of-the-art baselines, underscoring the efficacy of our framework. The significant improvements in story generation demonstrate the promising generalization ability of our framework across various domains. We anticipate that our work will guide LLM agents towards a cross-team paradigm and contribute to their significant growth in but not limited to software development. The code and data will be available at https://github.com/OpenBMB/ChatDev.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.08979v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhuoyun Du, Chen Qian, Wei Liu, Zihao Xie, Yifei Wang, Yufan Dang, Weize Chen, Cheng Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Applying Multi-Agent Negotiation to Solve the Production Routing Problem With Privacy Preserving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09214v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel approach to address the Production Routing Problem with Privacy Preserving (PRPPP) in supply chain optimization. The integrated optimization of production, inventory, distribution, and routing decisions in real-world industry applications poses several challenges, including increased complexity, discrepancies between planning and execution, and constraints on information sharing. To mitigate these challenges, this paper proposes the use of intelligent agent negotiation within a hybrid Multi-Agent System (MAS) integrated with optimization algorithms. The MAS facilitates communication and coordination among entities, encapsulates private information, and enables negotiation. This, along with optimization algorithms, makes it a compelling framework for establishing optimal solutions. The approach is supported by real-world applications and synergies between MAS and optimization methods, demonstrating its effectiveness in addressing complex supply chain optimization problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09214v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luiza Pellin Biasoto, Vinicius Renan de Carvalho, Jaime Sim\~ao Sichman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterising Interventions in Causal Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09318</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09318v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Causal games are probabilistic graphical models that enable causal queries to be answered in multi-agent settings. They extend causal Bayesian networks by specifying decision and utility variables to represent the agents' degrees of freedom and objectives. In multi-agent settings, whether each agent decides on their policy before or after knowing the causal intervention is important as this affects whether they can respond to the intervention by adapting their policy. Consequently, previous work in causal games imposed chronological constraints on permissible interventions. We relax this by outlining a sound and complete set of primitive causal interventions so the effect of any arbitrarily complex interventional query can be studied in multi-agent settings. We also demonstrate applications to the design of safe AI systems by considering causal mechanism design and commitment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09318v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuj Mishra, James Fox, Michael Wooldridge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arbitrary-Order Distributed Finite-Time Differentiator for Multi-Agent Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.07031v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper proposes arbitrary-order distributed finite-time differentiator (AODFD) for leader-follower multi-agent systems (MAS) under directed graph by only using relative or absolute output information. By using arbitrary-order distributed finite-time differentiator via relative output information (AODFD-R), each follower agent can obtain the relative output information between itself and leader and the relative output's arbitrary-order derivatives, where the information to be measured is only the local relative output information between each follower agent and its neighboring agents. As a simple extension of AODFD-R, the arbitrary-order distributed finite-time differentiator via absolute output information (AODFD-A) is also given. The finite-time stability of the closed-loop system under AODFD is proved by constructing a Lyapunov function skillfully. Finally, several simulation examples are given to verify the effectiveness of the AODFD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.07031v2</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weile Chen, Haibo Du, Shihua Li, Xinghuo Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ApproxED: Approximate exploitability descent via learned best responses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.08830</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.08830v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: There has been substantial progress on finding game-theoretic equilibria. Most of that work has focused on games with finite, discrete action spaces. However, many games involving space, time, money, and other fine-grained quantities have continuous action spaces (or are best modeled as having such). We study the problem of finding an approximate Nash equilibrium of games with continuous action sets. The standard measure of closeness to Nash equilibrium is exploitability, which measures how much players can benefit from unilaterally changing their strategy. We propose two new methods that minimize an approximation of exploitability with respect to the strategy profile. The first method uses a learned best-response function, which takes the current strategy profile as input and outputs candidate best responses for each player. The strategy profile and best-response functions are trained simultaneously, with the former trying to minimize exploitability while the latter tries to maximize it. The second method maintains an ensemble of candidate best responses for each player. In each iteration, the best-performing elements of each ensemble are used to update the current strategy profile. The strategy profile and ensembles are simultaneously trained to minimize and maximize the approximate exploitability, respectively. We evaluate our methods on various continuous games and GAN training, showing that they outperform prior methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.08830v3</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Martin, Tuomas Sandholm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncoupled Learning of Differential Stackelberg Equilibria with Commitments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.03438v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In multi-agent problems requiring a high degree of cooperation, success often depends on the ability of the agents to adapt to each other's behavior. A natural solution concept in such settings is the Stackelberg equilibrium, in which the ``leader'' agent selects the strategy that maximizes its own payoff given that the ``follower'' agent will choose their best response to this strategy. Recent work has extended this solution concept to two-player differentiable games, such as those arising from multi-agent deep reinforcement learning, in the form of the \textit{differential} Stackelberg equilibrium. While this previous work has presented learning dynamics which converge to such equilibria, these dynamics are ``coupled'' in the sense that the learning updates for the leader's strategy require some information about the follower's payoff function. As such, these methods cannot be applied to truly decentralised multi-agent settings, particularly ad hoc cooperation, where each agent only has access to its own payoff function. In this work we present ``uncoupled'' learning dynamics based on zeroth-order gradient estimators, in which each agent's strategy update depends only on their observations of the other's behavior. We analyze the convergence of these dynamics in general-sum games, and prove that they converge to differential Stackelberg equilibria under the same conditions as previous coupled methods. Furthermore, we present an online mechanism by which symmetric learners can negotiate leader-follower roles. We conclude with a discussion of the implications of our work for multi-agent reinforcement learning and ad hoc collaboration more generally.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.03438v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.5555/3635637.3662984</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Robert Loftin, Mustafa Mert \c{C}elikok, Herke van Hoof, Samuel Kaski, Frans A. Oliehoek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Carbon Market Simulation with Adaptive Mechanism Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.07875v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A carbon market is a market-based tool that incentivizes economic agents to align individual profits with the global utility, i.e., reducing carbon emissions to tackle climate change. Cap and trade stands as a critical principle based on allocating and trading carbon allowances (carbon emission credit), enabling economic agents to follow planned emissions and penalizing excess emissions. A central authority is responsible for introducing and allocating those allowances in cap and trade. However, the complexity of carbon market dynamics makes accurate simulation intractable, which in turn hinders the design of effective allocation strategies. To address this, we propose an adaptive mechanism design framework, simulating the market using hierarchical, model-free multi-agent reinforcement learning (MARL). Government agents allocate carbon credits, while enterprises engage in economic activities and carbon trading. This framework illustrates agents' behavior comprehensively. Numerical results show MARL enables government agents to balance productivity, equality, and carbon emissions. Our project is available at https://github.com/xwanghan/Carbon-Simulator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.07875v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Han Wang, Wenhao Li, Hongyuan Zha, Baoxiang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
