<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.MA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MA</link>
    <description>cs.MA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 02:53:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>ConvoyLLM: Dynamic Multi-Lane Convoy Control Using LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17529v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper proposes a novel method for multi-lane convoy formation control that uses large language models (LLMs) to tackle coordination challenges in dynamic highway environments. Each connected and autonomous vehicle in the convoy uses a knowledge-driven approach to make real-time adaptive decisions based on various scenarios. Our method enables vehicles to dynamically perform tasks, including obstacle avoidance, convoy joining/leaving, and escort formation switching, all while maintaining the overall convoy structure. We design a Interlaced formation control strategy based on locally dynamic distributed graphs, ensuring the convoy remains stable and flexible. We conduct extensive experiments in the SUMO simulation platform across multiple traffic scenarios, and the results demonstrate that the proposed method is effective, robust, and adaptable to dynamic environments. The code is available at: https://github.com/chuduanfeng/ConvoyLLM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17529v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liping Lu, Zhican He, Duanfeng Chu, Rukang Wang, Saiqian Peng, Pan Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Generic Modelling Framework for Last-Mile Delivery Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17633v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Large-scale social digital twinning projects are complex with multiple objectives. For example, a social digital twinning platform for innovative last-mile delivery solutions may aim to assess consumer delivery method choices within their social environment. However, no single tool can achieve all objectives. Different simulators exist for consumer behavior and freight transport. Therefore, we propose a high-level architecture and present a blueprint for a generic modelling framework. This includes defining modules, input/output data, and interconnections, while addressing data suitability and compatibility risks. We demonstrate the framework's effectiveness with two real-world case studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17633v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\"Onder G\"urcan, Timo Szczepanska, Vanja Falck, Patrycja Antosz, Merve Seher Cebeci, Michiel de Bok, Rodrigo Tapia, L\'or\'ant Tavasszy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smart and Efficient IoT-Based Irrigation System Design: Utilizing a Hybrid Agent-Based and System Dynamics Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18298v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Regarding problems like reduced precipitation and an increase in population, water resource scarcity has become one of the most critical problems in modern-day societies, as a consequence, there is a shortage of available water resources for irrigation in arid and semi-arid countries. On the other hand, it is possible to utilize modern technologies to control irrigation and reduce water loss. One of these technologies is the Internet of Things (IoT). Despite the possibility of using the IoT in irrigation control systems, there are complexities in designing such systems. Considering this issue, it is possible to use agent-oriented software engineering (AOSE) methodologies to design complex cyber-physical systems such as IoT-based systems. In this research, a smart irrigation system is designed based on Prometheus AOSE methodology, to reduce water loss by maintaining soil moisture in a suitable interval. The designed system comprises sensors, a central agent, and irrigation nodes. These agents follow defined rules to maintain soil moisture at a desired level cooperatively. For system simulation, a hybrid agent-based and system dynamics model was designed. In this hybrid model, soil moisture dynamics were modeled based on the system dynamics approach. The proposed model, was implemented in AnyLogic computer simulation software. Utilizing the simulation model, irrigation rules were examined. The system's functionality in automatic irrigation mode was tested based on a 256-run, fractional factorial design, and the effects of important factors such as soil properties on total irrigated water and total operation time were analyzed. Based on the tests, the system consistently irrigated nearly optimal water amounts in all tests. Moreover, the results were also used to minimize the system's energy consumption by reducing the system's operational time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18298v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taha Ahmadi Pargo, Mohsen Akbarpour Shirazi, Dawud Fadai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ToMCAT: Theory-of-Mind for Cooperative Agents in Teams via Multiagent Diffusion Policies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18438v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we present ToMCAT (Theory-of-Mind for Cooperative Agents in Teams), a new framework for generating ToM-conditioned trajectories. It combines a meta-learning mechanism, that performs ToM reasoning over teammates' underlying goals and future behavior, with a multiagent denoising-diffusion model, that generates plans for an agent and its teammates conditioned on both the agent's goals and its teammates' characteristics, as computed via ToM. We implemented an online planning system that dynamically samples new trajectories (replans) from the diffusion model whenever it detects a divergence between a previously generated plan and the current state of the world. We conducted several experiments using ToMCAT in a simulated cooking domain. Our results highlight the importance of the dynamic replanning mechanism in reducing the usage of resources without sacrificing team performance. We also show that recent observations about the world and teammates' behavior collected by an agent over the course of an episode combined with ToM inferences are crucial to generate team-aware plans for dynamic adaptation to teammates, especially when no prior information is provided about them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18438v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro Sequeira, Vidyasagar Sadhu, Melinda Gervasio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchical Imitation Learning of Team Behavior from Heterogeneous Demonstrations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17618</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17618v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Successful collaboration requires team members to stay aligned, especially in complex sequential tasks. Team members must dynamically coordinate which subtasks to perform and in what order. However, real-world constraints like partial observability and limited communication bandwidth often lead to suboptimal collaboration. Even among expert teams, the same task can be executed in multiple ways. To develop multi-agent systems and human-AI teams for such tasks, we are interested in data-driven learning of multimodal team behaviors. Multi-Agent Imitation Learning (MAIL) provides a promising framework for data-driven learning of team behavior from demonstrations, but existing methods struggle with heterogeneous demonstrations, as they assume that all demonstrations originate from a single team policy. Hence, in this work, we introduce DTIL: a hierarchical MAIL algorithm designed to learn multimodal team behaviors in complex sequential tasks. DTIL represents each team member with a hierarchical policy and learns these policies from heterogeneous team demonstrations in a factored manner. By employing a distribution-matching approach, DTIL mitigates compounding errors and scales effectively to long horizons and continuous state representations. Experimental results show that DTIL outperforms MAIL baselines and accurately models team behavior across a variety of collaborative scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17618v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sangwon Seo, Vaibhav Unhelkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Socratic: Enhancing Human Teamwork via AI-enabled Coaching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17643v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Coaches are vital for effective collaboration, but cost and resource constraints often limit their availability during real-world tasks. This limitation poses serious challenges in life-critical domains that rely on effective teamwork, such as healthcare and disaster response. To address this gap, we propose and realize an innovative application of AI: task-time team coaching. Specifically, we introduce Socratic, a novel AI system that complements human coaches by providing real-time guidance during task execution. Socratic monitors team behavior, detects misalignments in team members' shared understanding, and delivers automated interventions to improve team performance. We validated Socratic through two human subject experiments involving dyadic collaboration. The results demonstrate that the system significantly enhances team performance with minimal interventions. Participants also perceived Socratic as helpful and trustworthy, supporting its potential for adoption. Our findings also suggest promising directions both for AI research and its practical applications to enhance human teamwork.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17643v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sangwon Seo, Bing Han, Rayan E. Harari, Roger D. Dias, Marco A. Zenati, Eduardo Salas, Vaibhav Unhelkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Backbones: Sparsifying Graphs through Zero Forcing for Effective Graph-Based Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17713v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel framework for graph sparsification that preserves the essential learning attributes of original graphs, improving computational efficiency and reducing complexity in learning algorithms. We refer to these sparse graphs as "learning backbones". Our approach leverages the zero-forcing (ZF) phenomenon, a dynamic process on graphs with applications in network control. The key idea is to generate a tree from the original graph that retains critical dynamical properties. By correlating these properties with learning attributes, we construct effective learning backbones. We evaluate the performance of our ZF-based backbones in graph classification tasks across eight datasets and six baseline models. The results demonstrate that our method outperforms existing techniques. Additionally, we explore extensions using node distance metrics to further enhance the framework's utility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17713v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Obaid Ullah Ahmad, Anwar Said, Mudassir Shabbir, Xenofon Koutsoukos, Waseem Abbas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aligning Compound AI Systems via System-level DPO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17721</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17721v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Compound AI systems, comprising multiple interacting components such as LLM agents and external tools, demonstrate state-of-the-art results across diverse tasks. It is hence crucial to align components within the system to produce consistent results that match human expectations. However, conventional alignment methods, such as Direct Preference Optimization (DPO), are not directly applicable to compound AI systems. These challenges include the non-differentiable interactions between components, making end-to-end gradient optimization infeasible. Additionally, system-level preferences cannot be directly translated into component-level preferences, further complicating alignment. We address the issues by formulating compound AI systems as Directed Acyclic Graphs (DAGs), capturing the connections between agents and the data generation processes. We propose a system-level DPO (SysDPO) to jointly align compound systems by adapting the DPO to operate on these DAGs. We study the joint alignment of an LLM and a diffusion model to demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach. Our exploration provides insights into the alignment of compound AI systems and lays a foundation for future advancements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17721v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiangwen Wang, Yibo Jacky Zhang, Zhoujie Ding, Katherine Tsai, Sanmi Koyejo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLM Knows Geometry Better than Algebra: Numerical Understanding of LLM-Based Agents in A Trading Arena</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17967</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17967v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent advancements in large language models (LLMs) have significantly improved performance in natural language processing tasks. However, their ability to generalize to dynamic, unseen tasks, particularly in numerical reasoning, remains a challenge. Existing benchmarks mainly evaluate LLMs on problems with predefined optimal solutions, which may not align with real-world scenarios where clear answers are absent. To bridge this gap, we design the Agent Trading Arena, a virtual numerical game simulating complex economic systems through zero-sum games, where agents invest in stock portfolios. Our experiments reveal that LLMs, including GPT-4o, struggle with algebraic reasoning when dealing with plain-text stock data, often focusing on local details rather than global trends. In contrast, LLMs perform significantly better with geometric reasoning when presented with visual data, such as scatter plots or K-line charts, suggesting that visual representations enhance numerical reasoning. This capability is further improved by incorporating the reflection module, which aids in the analysis and interpretation of complex data. We validate our findings on NASDAQ Stock dataset, where LLMs demonstrate stronger reasoning with visual data compared to text. Our code and data are publicly available at https://github.com/wekjsdvnm/Agent-Trading-Arena.git.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17967v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>q-fin.ST</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianmi Ma, Jiawei Du, Wenxin Huang, Wenjie Wang, Liang Xie, Xian Zhong, Joey Tianyi Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MRBTP: Efficient Multi-Robot Behavior Tree Planning and Collaboration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18072v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multi-robot task planning and collaboration are critical challenges in robotics. While Behavior Trees (BTs) have been established as a popular control architecture and are plannable for a single robot, the development of effective multi-robot BT planning algorithms remains challenging due to the complexity of coordinating diverse action spaces. We propose the Multi-Robot Behavior Tree Planning (MRBTP) algorithm, with theoretical guarantees of both soundness and completeness. MRBTP features cross-tree expansion to coordinate heterogeneous actions across different BTs to achieve the team's goal. For homogeneous actions, we retain backup structures among BTs to ensure robustness and prevent redundant execution through intention sharing. While MRBTP is capable of generating BTs for both homogeneous and heterogeneous robot teams, its efficiency can be further improved. We then propose an optional plugin for MRBTP when Large Language Models (LLMs) are available to reason goal-related actions for each robot. These relevant actions can be pre-planned to form long-horizon subtrees, significantly enhancing the planning speed and collaboration efficiency of MRBTP. We evaluate our algorithm in warehouse management and everyday service scenarios. Results demonstrate MRBTP's robustness and execution efficiency under varying settings, as well as the ability of the pre-trained LLM to generate effective task-specific subtrees for MRBTP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18072v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yishuai Cai, Xinglin Chen, Zhongxuan Cai, Yunxin Mao, Minglong Li, Wenjing Yang, Ji Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ChatMotion: A Multimodal Multi-Agent for Human Motion Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18180v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Advancements in Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have improved human motion understanding. However, these models remain constrained by their "instruct-only" nature, lacking interactivity and adaptability for diverse analytical perspectives. To address these challenges, we introduce ChatMotion, a multimodal multi-agent framework for human motion analysis. ChatMotion dynamically interprets user intent, decomposes complex tasks into meta-tasks, and activates specialized function modules for motion comprehension. It integrates multiple specialized modules, such as the MotionCore, to analyze human motion from various perspectives. Extensive experiments demonstrate ChatMotion's precision, adaptability, and user engagement for human motion understanding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18180v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Li Lei, Jia Sen, Wang Jianhao, An Zhaochong, Li Jiaang, Hwang Jenq-Neng, Belongie Serge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From homeostasis to resource sharing: Biologically and economically aligned multi-objective multi-agent AI safety benchmarks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00081</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00081v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Developing safe, aligned agentic AI systems requires comprehensive empirical testing, yet many existing benchmarks neglect crucial themes aligned with biology and economics, both time-tested fundamental sciences describing our needs and preferences. To address this gap, the present work focuses on introducing biologically and economically motivated themes that have been neglected in current mainstream discussions on AI safety - namely a set of multi-objective, multi-agent alignment benchmarks that emphasize homeostasis for bounded and biological objectives, diminishing returns for unbounded, instrumental, and business objectives, sustainability principle, and resource sharing. We implemented eight main benchmark environments on the above themes, to illustrate key pitfalls and challenges in agentic AI-s, such as unboundedly maximizing a homeostatic objective, over-optimizing one objective at the expense of others, neglecting safety constraints, or depleting shared resources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00081v2</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roland Pihlakas, Joel Pyykk\"o</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Windowed MAPF with Completeness Guarantees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01798v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Traditional multi-agent path finding (MAPF) methods try to compute entire start-goal paths which are collision free. However, computing an entire path can take too long for MAPF systems where agents need to replan fast. Methods that address this typically employ a "windowed" approach and only try to find collision free paths for a small windowed timestep horizon. This adaptation comes at the cost of incompleteness; all current windowed approaches can become stuck in deadlock or livelock. Our main contribution is to introduce our framework, WinC-MAPF, for Windowed MAPF that enables completeness. Our framework uses heuristic update insights from single-agent real-time heuristic search algorithms as well as agent independence ideas from MAPF algorithms. We also develop Single-Step CBS (SS-CBS), an instantiation of this framework using a novel modification to CBS. We show how SS-CBS, which only plans a single step and updates heuristics, can effectively solve tough scenarios where existing windowed approaches fail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01798v2</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rishi Veerapaneni, Muhammad Suhail Saleem, Jiaoyang Li, Maxim Likhachev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence and quantification of cooperation of driving agents in mixed traffic flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07297</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07297v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Cooperation is a ubiquitous phenomenon in many natural, social, and engineered systems with multiple agents. Understanding the formation of cooperation in mixed traffic is of theoretical interest in its own right, and could also benefit the design and operations of future automated and mixed-autonomy transportation systems. However, how cooperativeness of driving agents can be defined and identified from empirical data seems ambiguous and this hinders further empirical characterizations of the phenomenon and revealing its behavior mechanisms. Towards mitigating this gap, in this paper, we propose a unified conceptual framework to identify collective cooperativeness of driving agents. This framework expands the concept of collective rationality from our recent model (Li et al. 2022a), making it empirically identifiable and behaviorally interpretable in realistic (microscopic and dynamic) settings. This framework integrates mixed traffic observations at both microscopic and macroscopic scales to estimate critical behavioral parameters that describe the collective cooperativeness of driving agents. Applying this framework to NGSIM I-80 trajectory data, we empirically confirm the existence of collective cooperation and quantify the condition and likelihood of its emergence. This study provides the first empirical understanding of collective cooperativeness in human-driven mixed traffic and points to new possibilities to manage mixed autonomy traffic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07297v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Di Chen, Jia Li, H. Michael Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Method of Equal Shares with Bounded Overspending</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.15005v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In participatory budgeting (PB), voters decide through voting which subset of projects to fund within a given budget. Proportionality in the context of PB is crucial to ensure equal treatment of all groups of voters. However, pure proportional rules can sometimes lead to suboptimal outcomes. We introduce the Method of Equal Shares with Bounded Overspending (BOS Equal Shares), a robust variant of Equal Shares that balances proportionality and efficiency. BOS Equal Shares addresses inefficiencies implied by strict proportionality axioms, yet the rule still provides fairness guarantees, similar to the original Method of Equal Shares. Our extensive empirical analysis on real-world PB instances shows excellent performance of BOS Equal Shares across several metrics. In the course of the analysis, we also present and examine a fractional variant of the Method of Equal Shares which allows for partial funding of projects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.15005v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georgios Papasotiropoulos, Seyedeh Zeinab Pishbin, Oskar Skibski, Piotr Skowron, Tomasz W\k{a}s</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Collusion in Episodic, Inventory-Constrained Markets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18871v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Pricing algorithms have demonstrated the capability to learn tacit collusion that is largely unaddressed by current regulations. Their increasing use in markets, including oligopolistic industries with a history of collusion, calls for closer examination by competition authorities. In this paper, we extend the study of tacit collusion in learning algorithms from basic pricing games to more complex markets characterized by perishable goods with fixed supply and sell-by dates, such as airline tickets, perishables, and hotel rooms. We formalize collusion within this framework and introduce a metric based on price levels under both the competitive (Nash) equilibrium and collusive (monopolistic) optimum. Since no analytical expressions for these price levels exist, we propose an efficient computational approach to derive them. Through experiments, we demonstrate that deep reinforcement learning agents can learn to collude in this more complex domain. Additionally, we analyze the underlying mechanisms and structures of the collusive strategies these agents adopt.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18871v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Friedrich, Barna P\'asztor, Giorgia Ramponi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Survey on Strategic Mining in Blockchain: A Reinforcement Learning Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17307v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Strategic mining attacks, such as selfish mining, exploit blockchain consensus protocols by deviating from honest behavior to maximize rewards. Markov Decision Process (MDP) analysis faces scalability challenges in modern digital economics, including blockchain. To address these limitations, reinforcement learning (RL) provides a scalable alternative, enabling adaptive strategy optimization in complex dynamic environments.
  In this survey, we examine RL's role in strategic mining analysis, comparing it to MDP-based approaches. We begin by reviewing foundational MDP models and their limitations, before exploring RL frameworks that can learn near-optimal strategies across various protocols. Building on this analysis, we compare RL techniques and their effectiveness in deriving security thresholds, such as the minimum attacker power required for profitable attacks. Expanding the discussion further, we classify consensus protocols and propose open challenges, such as multi-agent dynamics and real-world validation.
  This survey highlights the potential of reinforcement learning (RL) to address the challenges of selfish mining, including protocol design, threat detection, and security analysis, while offering a strategic roadmap for researchers in decentralized systems and AI-driven analytics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17307v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jichen Li, Lijia Xie, Hanting Huang, Bo Zhou, Binfeng Song, Wanying Zeng, Xiaotie Deng, Xiao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
