<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.MA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MA</link>
    <description>cs.MA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 04:00:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A Large Language Model-Enabled Control Architecture for Dynamic Resource Capability Exploration in Multi-Agent Manufacturing Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22814v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Manufacturing environments are becoming more complex and unpredictable due to factors such as demand variations and shorter product lifespans. This complexity requires real-time decision-making and adaptation to disruptions. Traditional control approaches highlight the need for advanced control strategies capable of overcoming unforeseen challenges, as they demonstrate limitations in responsiveness within dynamic industrial settings. Multi-agent systems address these challenges through decentralization of decision-making, enabling systems to respond dynamically to operational changes. However, current multi-agent systems encounter challenges related to real-time adaptation, context-aware decision-making, and the dynamic exploration of resource capabilities. Large language models provide the possibility to overcome these limitations through context-aware decision-making capabilities. This paper introduces a large language model-enabled control architecture for multi-agent manufacturing systems to dynamically explore resource capabilities in response to real-time disruptions. A simulation-based case study demonstrates that the proposed architecture improves system resilience and flexibility. The case study findings show improved throughput and efficient resource utilization compared to existing approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22814v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonghan Lim, Ilya Kovalenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the Information Propagation Effects of Communication Topologies in LLM-based Multi-Agent Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23352</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.23352v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The communication topology in large language model-based multi-agent systems fundamentally governs inter-agent collaboration patterns, critically shaping both the efficiency and effectiveness of collective decision-making. While recent studies for communication topology automated design tend to construct sparse structures for efficiency, they often overlook why and when sparse and dense topologies help or hinder collaboration. In this paper, we present a causal framework to analyze how agent outputs, whether correct or erroneous, propagate under topologies with varying sparsity. Our empirical studies reveal that moderately sparse topologies, which effectively suppress error propagation while preserving beneficial information diffusion, typically achieve optimal task performance. Guided by this insight, we propose a novel topology design approach, EIB-leanrner, that balances error suppression and beneficial information propagation by fusing connectivity patterns from both dense and sparse graphs. Extensive experiments show the superior effectiveness, communication cost, and robustness of EIB-leanrner.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.23352v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xu Shen, Yixin Liu, Yiwei Dai, Yili Wang, Rui Miao, Yue Tan, Shirui Pan, Xin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collaborative Last-Mile Delivery: A Multi-Platform Vehicle Routing Problem With En-route Charging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.23584v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The rapid growth of e-commerce and the increasing demand for timely, cost-effective last-mile delivery have increased interest in collaborative logistics. This research introduces a novel collaborative synchronized multi-platform vehicle routing problem with drones and robots (VRP-DR), where a fleet of $\mathcal{M}$ trucks, $\mathcal{N}$ drones and $\mathcal{K}$ robots, cooperatively delivers parcels. Trucks serve as mobile platforms, enabling the launching, retrieving, and en-route charging of drones and robots, thereby addressing critical limitations such as restricted payload capacities, limited range, and battery constraints. The VRP-DR incorporates five realistic features: (1) multi-visit service per trip, (2) multi-trip operations, (3) flexible docking, allowing returns to the same or different trucks (4) cyclic and acyclic operations, enabling return to the same or different nodes; and (5) en-route charging, enabling drones and robots to recharge while being transported on the truck, maximizing operational efficiency by utilizing idle transit time. The VRP-DR is formulated as a mixed-integer linear program (MILP) to minimize both operational costs and makespan. To overcome the computational challenges of solving large-scale instances, a scalable heuristic algorithm, FINDER (Flexible INtegrated Delivery with Energy Recharge), is developed, to provide efficient, near-optimal solutions. Numerical experiments across various instance sizes evaluate the performance of the MILP and heuristic approaches in terms of solution quality and computation time. The results demonstrate significant time savings of the combined delivery mode over the truck-only mode and substantial cost reductions from enabling multi-visits. The study also provides insights into the effects of en-route charging, docking flexibility, drone count, speed, and payload capacity on system performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.23584v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sumbal Malik, Majid Khonji, Khaled Elbassioni, Jorge Dias</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Lifelong Multi-Agent Path-finding by Using Artificial Potential Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22753v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explore the use of Artificial Potential Fields (APFs) to solve Multi-Agent Path Finding (MAPF) and Lifelong MAPF (LMAPF) problems. In MAPF, a team of agents must move to their goal locations without collisions, whereas in LMAPF, new goals are generated upon arrival. We propose methods for incorporating APFs in a range of MAPF algorithms, including Prioritized Planning, MAPF-LNS2, and Priority Inheritance with Backtracking (PIBT). Experimental results show that using APF is not beneficial for MAPF but yields up to a 7-fold increase in overall system throughput for LMAPF.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22753v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arseniy Pertzovsky, Roni Stern, Ariel Felner, Roie Zivan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Task Adaptation for Multi-Robot Manufacturing Systems with Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22804v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent manufacturing systems are increasingly adopting multi-robot collaboration to handle complex and dynamic environments. While multi-agent architectures support decentralized coordination among robot agents, they often face challenges in enabling real-time adaptability for unexpected disruptions without predefined rules. Recent advances in large language models offer new opportunities for context-aware decision-making to enable adaptive responses to unexpected changes. This paper presents an initial exploratory implementation of a large language model-enabled control framework for dynamic task reassignment in multi-robot manufacturing systems. A central controller agent leverages the large language model's ability to interpret structured robot configuration data and generate valid reassignments in response to robot failures. Experiments in a real-world setup demonstrate high task success rates in recovering from failures, highlighting the potential of this approach to improve adaptability in multi-robot manufacturing systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22804v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonghan Lim, Ilya Kovalenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MermaidFlow: Redefining Agentic Workflow Generation via Safety-Constrained Evolutionary Programming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22967</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22967v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Despite the promise of autonomous agentic reasoning, existing workflow generation methods frequently produce fragile, unexecutable plans due to unconstrained LLM-driven construction. We introduce MermaidFlow, a framework that redefines the agentic search space through safety-constrained graph evolution. At its core, MermaidFlow represent workflows as a verifiable intermediate representation using Mermaid, a structured and human-interpretable graph language. We formulate domain-aware evolutionary operators, i.e., crossover, mutation, insertion, and deletion, to preserve semantic correctness while promoting structural diversity, enabling efficient exploration of a high-quality, statically verifiable workflow space. Without modifying task settings or evaluation protocols, MermaidFlow achieves consistent improvements in success rates and faster convergence to executable plans on the agent reasoning benchmark. The experimental results demonstrate that safety-constrained graph evolution offers a scalable, modular foundation for robust and interpretable agentic reasoning systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22967v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengqi Zheng, Jianda Chen, Yueming Lyu, Wen Zheng Terence Ng, Haopeng Zhang, Yew-Soon Ong, Ivor Tsang, Haiyan Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Recommender Mechanisms for Bayesian Stochastic Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22979v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: An important challenge in non-cooperative game theory is coordinating on a single (approximate) equilibrium from many possibilities - a challenge that becomes even more complex when players hold private information. Recommender mechanisms tackle this problem by recommending strategies to players based on their reported type profiles. A key consideration in such mechanisms is to ensure that players are incentivized to participate, report their private information truthfully, and follow the recommendations. While previous work has focused on designing recommender mechanisms for one-shot and extensive-form games, these approaches cannot be effectively applied to stochastic games, particularly if we constrain recommendations to be Markov stationary policies. To bridge this gap, we introduce a novel bi-level reinforcement learning approach for automatically designing recommender mechanisms in Bayesian stochastic games. Our method produces a mechanism represented by a parametric function (such as a neural network), and is therefore highly efficient at execution time. Experimental results on two repeated and two stochastic games demonstrate that our approach achieves social welfare levels competitive with cooperative multi-agent reinforcement learning baselines, while also providing significantly improved incentive properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22979v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bengisu Guresti, Chongjie Zhang, Yevgeniy Vorobeychik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cross-Task Experiential Learning on LLM-based Multi-Agent Collaboration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23187</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.23187v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Large Language Model-based multi-agent systems (MAS) have shown remarkable progress in solving complex tasks through collaborative reasoning and inter-agent critique. However, existing approaches typically treat each task in isolation, resulting in redundant computations and limited generalization across structurally similar tasks. To address this, we introduce multi-agent cross-task experiential learning (MAEL), a novel framework that endows LLM-driven agents with explicit cross-task learning and experience accumulation. We model the task-solving workflow on a graph-structured multi-agent collaboration network, where agents propagate information and coordinate via explicit connectivity. During the experiential learning phase, we quantify the quality for each step in the task-solving workflow and store the resulting rewards along with the corresponding inputs and outputs into each agent's individual experience pool. During inference, agents retrieve high-reward, task-relevant experiences as few-shot examples to enhance the effectiveness of each reasoning step, thereby enabling more accurate and efficient multi-agent collaboration. Experimental results on diverse datasets demonstrate that MAEL empowers agents to learn from prior task experiences effectively-achieving faster convergence and producing higher-quality solutions on current tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.23187v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yilong Li, Chen Qian, Yu Xia, Ruijie Shi, Yufan Dang, Zihao Xie, Ziming You, Weize Chen, Cheng Yang, Weichuan Liu, Ye Tian, Xuantang Xiong, Lei Han, Zhiyuan Liu, Maosong Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ROTATE: Regret-driven Open-ended Training for Ad Hoc Teamwork</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23686</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.23686v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Developing AI agents capable of collaborating with previously unseen partners is a fundamental generalization challenge in multi-agent learning, known as Ad Hoc Teamwork (AHT). Existing AHT approaches typically adopt a two-stage pipeline, where first, a fixed population of teammates is generated with the idea that they should be representative of the teammates that will be seen at deployment time, and second, an AHT agent is trained to collaborate well with agents in the population. To date, the research community has focused on designing separate algorithms for each stage. This separation has led to algorithms that generate teammate pools with limited coverage of possible behaviors, and that ignore whether the generated teammates are easy to learn from for the AHT agent. Furthermore, algorithms for training AHT agents typically treat the set of training teammates as static, thus attempting to generalize to previously unseen partner agents without assuming any control over the distribution of training teammates. In this paper, we present a unified framework for AHT by reformulating the problem as an open-ended learning process between an ad hoc agent and an adversarial teammate generator. We introduce ROTATE, a regret-driven, open-ended training algorithm that alternates between improving the AHT agent and generating teammates that probe its deficiencies. Extensive experiments across diverse AHT environments demonstrate that ROTATE significantly outperforms baselines at generalizing to an unseen set of evaluation teammates, thus establishing a new standard for robust and generalizable teamwork.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.23686v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Caroline Wang, Arrasy Rahman, Jiaxun Cui, Yoonchang Sung, Peter Stone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MegaAgent: A Large-Scale Autonomous LLM-based Multi-Agent System Without Predefined SOPs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.09955</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.09955v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: LLM-based multi-agent systems (MAS) have shown promise in tackling complex tasks. However, existing solutions often suffer from limited agent coordination and heavy reliance on predefined Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs), which demand extensive human input. To address these limitations, we propose MegaAgent, a large-scale autonomous LLM-based multi-agent system. MegaAgent generates agents based on task complexity and enables dynamic task decomposition, parallel execution, efficient communication, and comprehensive system monitoring of agents. In evaluations, MegaAgent demonstrates exceptional performance, successfully developing a Gobang game within 800 seconds and scaling up to 590 agents in a national policy simulation to generate multi-domain policies. It significantly outperforms existing systems, such as MetaGPT, in both task completion efficiency and scalability. By eliminating the need for predefined SOPs, MegaAgent demonstrates exceptional scalability and autonomy, setting a foundation for advancing true autonomy in MAS. Our code is available at https://github.com/Xtra-Computing/MegaAgent .</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.09955v3</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qian Wang, Tianyu Wang, Zhenheng Tang, Qinbin Li, Nuo Chen, Jingsheng Liang, Bingsheng He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent social conventions and collective bias in LLM populations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08948</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08948v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Social conventions are the backbone of social coordination, shaping how individuals form a group. As growing populations of artificial intelligence (AI) agents communicate through natural language, a fundamental question is whether they can bootstrap the foundations of a society. Here, we present experimental results that demonstrate the spontaneous emergence of universally adopted social conventions in decentralized populations of large language model (LLM) agents. We then show how strong collective biases can emerge during this process, even when agents exhibit no bias individually. Last, we examine how committed minority groups of adversarial LLM agents can drive social change by imposing alternative social conventions on the larger population. Our results show that AI systems can autonomously develop social conventions without explicit programming and have implications for designing AI systems that align, and remain aligned, with human values and societal goals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08948v2</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1126/sciadv.adu9368</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Science Advances 11, eadu9368 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ariel Flint Ashery, Luca Maria Aiello, Andrea Baronchelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Structure Learning Should Be A Research Priority for LLM-Based Multi-Agent Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22467v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Large Language Model-based Multi-Agent Systems (MASs) have emerged as a powerful paradigm for tackling complex tasks through collaborative intelligence. Nevertheless, the question of how agents should be structurally organized for optimal cooperation remains largely unexplored. In this position paper, we aim to gently redirect the focus of the MAS research community toward this critical dimension: develop topology-aware MASs for specific tasks. Specifically, the system consists of three core components - agents, communication links, and communication patterns - that collectively shape its coordination performance and efficiency. To this end, we introduce a systematic, three-stage framework: agent selection, structure profiling, and topology synthesis. Each stage would trigger new research opportunities in areas such as language models, reinforcement learning, graph learning, and generative modeling; together, they could unleash the full potential of MASs in complicated real-world applications. Then, we discuss the potential challenges and opportunities in the evaluation of multiple systems. We hope our perspective and framework can offer critical new insights in the era of agentic AI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22467v2</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaxi Yang, Mengqi Zhang, Yiqiao Jin, Hao Chen, Qingsong Wen, Lu Lin, Yi He, Weijie Xu, James Evans, Jindong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Language Agents with Reinforcement Learning for Strategic Play in the Werewolf Game</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.18940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.18940v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Agents built with large language models (LLMs) have shown great potential across a wide range of domains. However, in complex decision-making tasks, pure LLM-based agents tend to exhibit intrinsic bias in their choice of actions, which is inherited from the model's training data and results in suboptimal performance. To develop strategic language agents, i.e., agents that generate flexible language actions and possess strong decision-making abilities, we propose a novel framework that powers LLM-based agents with reinforcement learning (RL). We consider Werewolf, a popular social deduction game, as a challenging testbed that emphasizes versatile communication and strategic gameplay. To mitigate the intrinsic bias in language actions, our agents use an LLM to perform deductive reasoning and generate a diverse set of action candidates. Then an RL policy trained to optimize the decision-making ability chooses an action from the candidates to play in the game. Extensive experiments show that our agents overcome the intrinsic bias and outperform existing LLM-based agents in the Werewolf game. We also conduct human-agent experiments and find that our agents achieve human-level performance and demonstrate strong strategic play.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.18940v4</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zelai Xu, Chao Yu, Fei Fang, Yu Wang, Yi Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MedRAX: Medical Reasoning Agent for Chest X-ray</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02673</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02673v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Chest X-rays (CXRs) play an integral role in driving critical decisions in disease management and patient care. While recent innovations have led to specialized models for various CXR interpretation tasks, these solutions often operate in isolation, limiting their practical utility in clinical practice. We present MedRAX, the first versatile AI agent that seamlessly integrates state-of-the-art CXR analysis tools and multimodal large language models into a unified framework. MedRAX dynamically leverages these models to address complex medical queries without requiring additional training. To rigorously evaluate its capabilities, we introduce ChestAgentBench, a comprehensive benchmark containing 2,500 complex medical queries across 7 diverse categories. Our experiments demonstrate that MedRAX achieves state-of-the-art performance compared to both open-source and proprietary models, representing a significant step toward the practical deployment of automated CXR interpretation systems. Data and code have been publicly available at https://github.com/bowang-lab/MedRAX</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02673v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adibvafa Fallahpour, Jun Ma, Alif Munim, Hongwei Lyu, Bo Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agentic Knowledgeable Self-awareness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03553v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Large Language Models (LLMs) have achieved considerable performance across various agentic planning tasks. However, traditional agent planning approaches adopt a "flood irrigation" methodology that indiscriminately injects gold trajectories, external feedback, and domain knowledge into agent models. This practice overlooks the fundamental human cognitive principle of situational self-awareness during decision-making-the ability to dynamically assess situational demands and strategically employ resources during decision-making. We propose agentic knowledgeable self-awareness to address this gap, a novel paradigm enabling LLM-based agents to autonomously regulate knowledge utilization. Specifically, we propose KnowSelf, a data-centric approach that applies agents with knowledgeable self-awareness like humans. Concretely, we devise a heuristic situation judgement criterion to mark special tokens on the agent's self-explored trajectories for collecting training data. Through a two-stage training process, the agent model can switch between different situations by generating specific special tokens, achieving optimal planning effects with minimal costs. Our experiments demonstrate that KnowSelf can outperform various strong baselines on different tasks and models with minimal use of external knowledge. Code is available at https://github.com/zjunlp/KnowSelf.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03553v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuofei Qiao, Zhisong Qiu, Baochang Ren, Xiaobin Wang, Xiangyuan Ru, Ningyu Zhang, Xiang Chen, Yong Jiang, Pengjun Xie, Fei Huang, Huajun Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Novel Zero-Trust Identity Framework for Agentic AI: Decentralized Authentication and Fine-Grained Access Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19301v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Traditional Identity and Access Management (IAM) systems, primarily designed for human users or static machine identities via protocols such as OAuth, OpenID Connect (OIDC), and SAML, prove fundamentally inadequate for the dynamic, interdependent, and often ephemeral nature of AI agents operating at scale within Multi Agent Systems (MAS), a computational system composed of multiple interacting intelligent agents that work collectively.
  This paper posits the imperative for a novel Agentic AI IAM framework: We deconstruct the limitations of existing protocols when applied to MAS, illustrating with concrete examples why their coarse-grained controls, single-entity focus, and lack of context-awareness falter. We then propose a comprehensive framework built upon rich, verifiable Agent Identities (IDs), leveraging Decentralized Identifiers (DIDs) and Verifiable Credentials (VCs), that encapsulate an agents capabilities, provenance, behavioral scope, and security posture.
  Our framework includes an Agent Naming Service (ANS) for secure and capability-aware discovery, dynamic fine-grained access control mechanisms, and critically, a unified global session management and policy enforcement layer for real-time control and consistent revocation across heterogeneous agent communication protocols. We also explore how Zero-Knowledge Proofs (ZKPs) enable privacy-preserving attribute disclosure and verifiable policy compliance.
  We outline the architecture, operational lifecycle, innovative contributions, and security considerations of this new IAM paradigm, aiming to establish the foundational trust, accountability, and security necessary for the burgeoning field of agentic AI and the complex ecosystems they will inhabit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19301v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ken Huang, Vineeth Sai Narajala, John Yeoh, Jason Ross, Ramesh Raskar, Youssef Harkati, Jerry Huang, Idan Habler, Chris Hughes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The challenge of hidden gifts in multi-agent reinforcement learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20579v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Sometimes we benefit from actions that others have taken even when we are unaware that they took those actions. For example, if your neighbor chooses not to take a parking spot in front of your house when you are not there, you can benefit, even without being aware that they took this action. These "hidden gifts" represent an interesting challenge for multi-agent reinforcement learning (MARL), since assigning credit when the beneficial actions of others are hidden is non-trivial. Here, we study the impact of hidden gifts with a very simple MARL task. In this task, agents in a grid-world environment have individual doors to unlock in order to obtain individual rewards. As well, if all the agents unlock their door the group receives a larger collective reward. However, there is only one key for all of the doors, such that the collective reward can only be obtained when the agents drop the key for others after they use it. Notably, there is nothing to indicate to an agent that the other agents have dropped the key, thus the act of dropping the key for others is a "hidden gift". We show that several different state-of-the-art RL algorithms, including MARL algorithms, fail to learn how to obtain the collective reward in this simple task. Interestingly, we find that independent model-free policy gradient agents can solve the task when we provide them with information about their own action history, but MARL agents still cannot solve the task with action history. Finally, we derive a correction term for these independent agents, inspired by learning aware approaches, which reduces the variance in learning and helps them to converge to collective success more reliably. These results show that credit assignment in multi-agent settings can be particularly challenging in the presence of "hidden gifts", and demonstrate that learning awareness in independent agents can benefit these settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20579v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dane Malenfant, Blake A. Richards</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
