<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.MA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MA</link>
    <description>cs.MA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.MA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 02:32:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Context Sharing: A Unified Agent Communication Protocol (ACP) for Secure, Federated, and Autonomous Agent-to-Agent (A2A) Orchestration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15055</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15055v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the artificial intelligence space, as we transition from isolated large language models to autonomous agents capable of complex reasoning and tool use. While foundational architectures and local context management protocols have been established, the challenge of cross-platform, decentralized, and secure interaction remains a significant barrier to the realization of a truly Agentic Web. Building upon the foundations of AI agent architectures and the Model Context Protocol (MCP) for multi-agent coordination, this paper introduces the Agent Communication Protocol (ACP). ACP provides a standardized framework for Agent-to-Agent (AA) interaction, enabling heterogeneous agents to discover, negotiate, and execute collaborative workflows across disparate environments. We propose a federated orchestration model that integrates decentralized identity verification, semantic intent mapping, and automated service-level agreements. Our evaluation demonstrates that ACP reduces inter-agent communication latency by % while maintaining a zero-trust security posture. This work represents a critical advancement toward a scalable and interoperable ecosystem of autonomous digital entities</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15055v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naveen Kumar Krishnan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colosseum: Auditing Collusion in Cooperative Multi-Agent Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15198v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multi-agent systems, where LLM agents communicate through free-form language, enable sophisticated coordination for solving complex cooperative tasks. This surfaces a unique safety problem when individual agents form a coalition and \emph{collude} to pursue secondary goals and degrade the joint objective. In this paper, we present Colosseum, a framework for auditing LLM agents' collusive behavior in multi-agent settings. We ground how agents cooperate through a Distributed Constraint Optimization Problem (DCOP) and measure collusion via regret relative to the cooperative optimum. Colosseum tests each LLM for collusion under different objectives, persuasion tactics, and network topologies. Through our audit, we show that most out-of-the-box models exhibited a propensity to collude when a secret communication channel was artificially formed. Furthermore, we discover ``collusion on paper'' when agents plan to collude in text but would often pick non-collusive actions, thus providing little effect on the joint task. Colosseum provides a new way to study collusion by measuring communications and actions in rich yet verifiable environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15198v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mason Nakamura, Abhinav Kumar, Saswat Das, Sahar Abdelnabi, Saaduddin Mahmud, Ferdinando Fioretto, Shlomo Zilberstein, Eugene Bagdasarian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Computational Efficiency in NetLogo: Best Practices for Running Large-Scale Agent-Based Models on AWS and Cloud Infrastructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15317v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The rising complexity and scale of agent-based models (ABMs) necessitate efficient computational strategies to manage the increasing demand for processing power and memory. This manuscript provides a comprehensive guide to optimizing NetLogo, a widely used platform for ABMs, for running large-scale models on Amazon Web Services (AWS) and other cloud infrastructures. It covers best practices in memory management, Java options, BehaviorSpace execution, and AWS instance selection. By implementing these optimizations and selecting appropriate AWS instances, we achieved a 32\% reduction in computational costs and improved performance consistency. Through a comparative analysis of NetLogo simulations on different AWS instances using the wolf-sheep predation model, we demonstrate the performance gains achievable through these optimizations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15317v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael A. Duprey, Georgiy V. Bobashev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cooperative Game Theory Model for Sustainable UN Financing: Addressing Global Public Goods Provision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15062v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study introduces a novel cooperative game theory model designed to improve the United Nations' current funding mechanisms, which predominantly rely on voluntary contributions. By shifting from a Nash equilibrium framework, where member states act in self-interest, to a cooperative model, the proposed approach aligns each country's financial contributions with the benefits they derive from UN activities. The model ensures a more sustainable and equitable system by introducing personalized pricing based on derived utility. Using agent-based simulations, the research demonstrates that the suggested approach increases global utility, reduces free-rider issues, and creates a more efficient resource allocation system. The findings suggest that the proposed model can optimize UN funding, ensuring a more stable and effective framework for global public goods provision, while considering the varying economic capacities of member states. Further research is recommended to assess the political viability of the model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15062v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Labib Shami, Teddy Lazebnik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Social Contagion and Bank Runs: An Agent-Based Model with LLM Depositors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15066</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15066v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Digital banking and online communication have made modern bank runs faster and more networked than the canonical queue-at-the-branch setting. While equilibrium models explain why strategic complementarities generate run risk, they offer limited guidance on how beliefs synchronize and propagate in real time. We develop a process-based agent-based model that makes the information and coordination layer explicit. Banks follow cash-first withdrawal processing with discounted fire-sale liquidation and an endogenous stress index. Depositors are heterogeneous in risk tolerance and in the weight placed on fundamentals versus social information, communicating on a heavy-tailed network calibrated to Twitter activity during March 2023. Depositor behavior is generated by a constrained large language model that maps each agent's information set into a discrete action and an optional post; we validate this policy against laboratory coordination evidence and theoretical benchmarks. Across 4,900 configurations and full LLM simulations, three findings emerge. Within-bank connectivity raises the likelihood and speed of withdrawal cascades holding fundamentals fixed. Cross-bank contagion exhibits a sharp phase transition near spillover rates of 0.10. Depositor overlap and network amplification interact nonlinearly, so channels weak in isolation become powerful in combination. In an SVB, First Republic, and regional bank scenario disciplined by crisis-era data, the model reproduces the observed ordering of failures and predicts substantially higher withdrawal rates among uninsured depositors. The results frame social correlation as a measurable amplifier of run risk alongside balance-sheet fundamentals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15066v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chris Ruano, Shreshth Rajan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Network-Based Parameter Estimation of a Labour Market Agent-Based Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15572v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Agent-based modelling (ABM) is a widespread approach to simulate complex systems. Advancements in computational processing and storage have facilitated the adoption of ABMs across many fields; however, ABMs face challenges that limit their use as decision-support tools. A significant issue is parameter estimation in large-scale ABMs, particularly due to computational constraints on exploring the parameter space. This study evaluates a state-of-the-art simulation-based inference (SBI) framework that uses neural networks (NN) for parameter estimation. This framework is applied to an established labour market ABM based on job transition networks. The ABM is initiated with synthetic datasets and the real U.S. labour market. Next, we compare the effectiveness of summary statistics derived from a list of statistical measures with that learned by an embedded NN. The results demonstrate that the NN-based approach recovers the original parameters when evaluating posterior distributions across various dataset scales and improves efficiency compared to traditional Bayesian methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15572v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M Lopes Alves, Joel Dyer, Doyne Farmer, Michael Wooldridge, Anisoara Calinescu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Outer Diversity of Structured Domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15708v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: An ordinal preference domain is a subset of preference orders that the voters are allowed to cast in an election. We introduce and study the notion of outer diversity of a domain and evaluate its value for a number of well-known structured domains, such as the single-peaked, single-crossing, group-separable, and Euclidean ones.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15708v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Piotr Faliszewski, Krzysztof Sornat, Stanis{\l}aw Szufa, Tomasz W\k{a}s</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MARLIN: Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning with Murmuration Intelligence and LLM Guidance for Reservoir Management</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25034</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25034v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: As climate change intensifies extreme weather events, water disasters pose growing threats to global communities, making adaptive reservoir management critical for protecting vulnerable populations and ensuring water security. Modern water resource management faces unprecedented challenges from cascading uncertainties propagating through interconnected reservoir networks. These uncertainties, rooted in physical water transfer losses and environmental variability, make precise control difficult. For example, sending 10 tons downstream may yield only 8-12 tons due to evaporation and seepage. Traditional centralized optimization approaches suffer from exponential computational complexity and cannot effectively handle such real-world uncertainties, while existing multi-agent reinforcement learning (MARL) methods fail to achieve effective coordination under uncertainty. To address these challenges, we present MARLIN, a decentralized reservoir management framework inspired by starling murmurations intelligence. Integrating bio-inspired alignment, separation, and cohesion rules with MARL, MARLIN enables individual reservoirs to make local decisions while achieving emergent global coordination. In addition, a LLM provides real-time reward shaping signals, guiding agents to adapt to environmental changes and human-defined preferences. Experiments on USGS data show that MARLIN improves uncertainty handling by 23\%, cuts computation by 35\%, and accelerates flood response by 68\%, exhibiting super-linear coordination, with complexity scaling 5.4x from 400 to 10,000 nodes. These results demonstrate MARLIN's potential for disaster prevention and protecting communities through intelligent, scalable water resource management.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25034v3</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heming Fu, Guojun Xiong, Shan Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CONSENT: A Negotiation Framework for Leveraging User Flexibility in Vehicle-to-Building Charging under Uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.01581v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The growth of Electric Vehicles (EVs) creates a conflict in vehicle-to-building (V2B) settings between building operators, who face high energy costs from uncoordinated charging, and drivers, who prioritize convenience and a full charge. To resolve this, we propose a negotiation-based framework that, by design, guarantees voluntary participation, strategy-proofness, and budget feasibility. It transforms EV charging into a strategic resource by offering drivers a range of incentive-backed options for modest flexibility in their departure time or requested state of charge (SoC). Our framework is calibrated with user survey data and validated using real operational data from a commercial building and an EV manufacturer. Simulations show that our negotiation protocol creates a mutually beneficial outcome: lowering the building operator's costs by over 3.5\% compared to an optimized, non-negotiating smart charging policy, while simultaneously reducing user charging expenses by 22\% below the utility's retail energy rate. By aligning operator and EV user objectives, our framework provides a strategic bridge between energy and mobility systems, transforming EV charging from a source of operational friction into a platform for collaboration and shared savings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.01581v3</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.65109/V1X2Y3Z4</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Rishav Sen, Fangqi Liu, Jose Paolo Talusan, Ava Pettet, Yoshinori Suzue, Mark Bailey, Ayan Mukhopadhyay, Abhishek Dubey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Agent Simulation to Social Simulator: A Comprehensive Review (Part 2)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.14296v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The study of system complexity primarily has two objectives: to explore underlying patterns and to develop theoretical explanations. Pattern exploration seeks to clarify the mechanisms behind the emergence of system complexity, while theoretical explanations aim to identify the fundamental causes of this complexity. Laws are generally defined as mappings between variables, whereas theories offer causal explanations of system behavior. Agent Based Modeling(ABM) is an important approach for studying complex systems, but it tends to emphasize simulation over experimentation. As a result, ABM often struggles to deeply uncover the governing operational principles. Unlike conventional scenario analysis that relies on human reasoning, computational experiments emphasize counterfactual experiments-that is, creating parallel worlds that simulate alternative "evolutionary paths" of real-world events. By systematically adjusting input variables and observing the resulting changes in output variables, computational experiments provide a robust tool for causal inference, thereby addressing the limitations of traditional ABM. Together, these methods offer causal insights into the dynamic evolution of systems. This part can help readers gain a preliminary understanding of the entire computational experiment method, laying the foundation for the subsequent study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.14296v2</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao Xue, Deyu Zhou, Ming Zhang, Xiangning Yu, Fei-Yue Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agent Skills for Large Language Models: Architecture, Acquisition, Security, and the Path Forward</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.12430v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The transition from monolithic language models to modular, skill-equipped agents marks a defining shift in how large language models (LLMs) are deployed in practice. Rather than encoding all procedural knowledge within model weights, agent skills -- composable packages of instructions, code, and resources that agents load on demand -- enable dynamic capability extension without retraining. It is formalized in a paradigm of progressive disclosure, portable skill definitions, and integration with the Model Context Protocol (MCP). This survey provides a comprehensive treatment of the agent skills landscape, as it has rapidly evolved during the last few months. We organize the field along four axes: (i) architectural foundations, examining the SKILL$.$md specification, progressive context loading, and the complementary roles of skills and MCP; (ii) skill acquisition, covering reinforcement learning with skill libraries, autonomous skill discovery (SEAgent), and compositional skill synthesis; (iii) deployment at scale, including the computer-use agent (CUA) stack, GUI grounding advances, and benchmark progress on OSWorld and SWE-bench; and (iv) security, where recent empirical analyses reveal that 26.1% of community-contributed skills contain vulnerabilities, motivating our proposed Skill Trust and Lifecycle Governance Framework -- a four-tier, gate-based permission model that maps skill provenance to graduated deployment capabilities. We identify seven open challenges -- from cross-platform skill portability to capability-based permission models -- and propose a research agenda for realizing trustworthy, self-improving skill ecosystems. Unlike prior surveys that broadly cover LLM agents or tool use, this work focuses specifically on the emerging skill abstraction layer and its implications for the next generation of agentic systems. Project repo: https://github.com/scienceaix/agentskills</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.12430v3</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renjun Xu, Yang Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Satellite Autonomous Clock Fault Monitoring with Inter-Satellite Ranges Using Euclidean Distance Matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03820v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: To address the need for robust positioning, navigation, and timing services in lunar environments, this paper proposes a novel onboard clock phase jump detection framework for satellite constellations using range measurements obtained from dual one-way inter-satellite links. Our approach leverages vertex redundantly rigid graphs to detect faults without relying on prior knowledge of satellite positions or clock biases, providing flexibility for lunar satellite networks with diverse satellite types and operators. We model satellite constellations as graphs, where satellites are vertices and inter-satellite links are edges. The proposed algorithm detects and identifies satellites with clock jumps by monitoring the singular values of the geometric-centered Euclidean distance matrix (GCEDM) of 5-clique sub-graphs. The proposed method is validated through simulations of a GPS constellation and a notional constellation around the Moon, demonstrating its effectiveness in various configurations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03820v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keidai Iiyama, Daniel Neamati, Grace Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward Agentic Software Engineering Beyond Code: Framing Vision, Values, and Vocabulary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19692v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Agentic AI is poised to usher in a seismic paradigm shift in Software Engineering (SE). As technologists rush head-along to make agentic AI a reality, SE researchers are driven to establish agentic SE as a research area. While early visions of agentic SE are primarily focused on code-related activities, early empirical evidence calls for a consideration of a wider range of socio-technical activities and concerns to make it work in practice. This paper contributes to the emerging visions by: (a) recommending an expansion of its scope beyond code, toward a 'whole of process' vision, grounding it in SE foundations and evolution and emerging agentic SE frameworks, (b) proposing a preliminary set of values and principles to guide community efforts, and (c) sharing guidance on designing and using well-defined vocabulary for agentic SE. It is hoped that these ideas will encourage collaborations and steer the SE community toward laying strong foundations of agentic SE so it is not limited to enabling coding acceleration but becomes the next process-level paradigm shift.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19692v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Rashina Hoda, Toward agentic software engineering beyond code: Framing vision, values, and vocabulary. In 2026 IEEE/ACM 48th International Conference on Software Engineering: Companion Proceedings (ICSE-Companion), 2026</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Rashina Hoda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collaborative Multi-Robot Non-Prehensile Manipulation via Flow-Matching Co-Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10874v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Coordinating a team of robots to reposition multiple objects in cluttered environments requires reasoning jointly about where robots should establish contact, how to manipulate objects once contact is made, and how to navigate safely and efficiently at scale. Prior approaches typically fall into two extremes -- either learning the entire task or relying on privileged information and hand-designed planners -- both of which struggle to handle diverse objects in long-horizon tasks. To address these challenges, we present a unified framework for collaborative multi-robot, multi-object non-prehensile manipulation that integrates flow-matching co-generation with anonymous multi-robot motion planning. Within this framework, a generative model co-generates contact formations and manipulation trajectories from visual observations, while a novel motion planner conveys robots at scale. Crucially, the same planner also supports coordination at the object level, assigning manipulated objects to larger target structures and thereby unifying robot- and object-level reasoning within a single algorithmic framework. Experiments in challenging simulated environments demonstrate that our approach outperforms baselines in both motion planning and manipulation tasks, highlighting the benefits of generative co-design and integrated planning for scaling collaborative manipulation to complex multi-agent, multi-object settings. Visit gco-paper.github.io for code and demonstrations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10874v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yorai Shaoul, Zhe Chen, Mohamed Naveed Gul Mohamed, Federico Pecora, Maxim Likhachev, Jiaoyang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DTBench: A Synthetic Benchmark for Document-to-Table Extraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13812v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Document-to-table (Doc2Table) extraction derives structured tables from unstructured documents under a target schema, enabling reliable and verifiable SQL-based data analytics. Although large language models (LLMs) have shown promise in flexible information extraction, their ability to produce precisely structured tables remains insufficiently understood, particularly for indirect extraction that requires complex capabilities such as reasoning and conflict resolution. Existing benchmarks neither explicitly distinguish nor comprehensively cover the diverse capabilities required in Doc2Table extraction. We argue that a capability-aware benchmark is essential for systematic evaluation. However, constructing such benchmarks using human-annotated document-table pairs is costly, difficult to scale, and limited in capability coverage. To address this, we adopt a reverse Table2Doc paradigm and design a multi-agent synthesis workflow to generate documents from ground-truth tables. Based on this approach, we present DTBench, a synthetic benchmark that adopts a proposed two-level taxonomy of Doc2Table capabilities, covering 5 major categories and 13 subcategories. We evaluate several mainstream LLMs on DTBench, and demonstrate substantial performance gaps across models, as well as persistent challenges in reasoning, faithfulness, and conflict resolution. DTBench provides a comprehensive testbed for data generation and evaluation, facilitating future research on Doc2Table extraction. The benchmark is publicly available at https://github.com/ZJU-DAILY/DTBench.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13812v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxiang Guo, Zhuoran Du, Nan Tang, Kezheng Tang, Congcong Ge, Yunjun Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
