<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CR</link>
    <description>cs.CR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2024 04:00:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluation of Hash Algorithm Performance for Cryptocurrency Exchanges Based on Blockchain System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11950</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11950v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The blockchain system has emerged as one of the focal points of research in recent years, particularly in applications and services such as cryptocurrencies and smart contracts. In this context, the hash value serves as a crucial element in linking blocks within the blockchain, ensuring the integrity of block contents. Therefore, hash algorithms represent a vital security technology for ensuring the integrity and security of blockchain systems. This study primarily focuses on analyzing the security and execution efficiency of mainstream hash algorithms in the Proof of Work (PoW) calculations within blockchain systems. It proposes an evaluation factor and conducts comparative experiments to evaluate each hash algorithm. The experimental results indicate that there are no significant differences in the security aspects among SHA-2, SHA-3, and BLAKE2. However, SHA-2 and BLAKE2 demonstrate shorter computation times, indicating higher efficiency in execution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11950v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abel C. H. Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confounding Privacy and Inverse Composition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12010v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a novel privacy notion of ($\epsilon, \delta$)-confounding privacy that generalizes both differential privacy and Pufferfish privacy. In differential privacy, sensitive information is contained in the dataset while in Pufferfish privacy, sensitive information determines data distribution. Consequently, both assume a chain-rule relationship between the sensitive information and the output of privacy mechanisms. Confounding privacy, in contrast, considers general causal relationships between the dataset and sensitive information. One of the key properties of differential privacy is that it can be easily composed over multiple interactions with the mechanism that maps private data to publicly shared information. In contrast, we show that the quantification of the privacy loss under the composition of independent ($\epsilon, \delta$)-confounding private mechanisms using the optimal composition of differential privacy \emph{underestimates} true privacy loss. To address this, we characterize an inverse composition framework to tightly implement a target global ($\epsilon_{g}, \delta_{g}$)-confounding privacy under composition while keeping individual mechanisms independent and private. In particular, we propose a novel copula-perturbation method which ensures that (1) each individual mechanism $i$ satisfies a target local ($\epsilon_{i}, \delta_{i}$)-confounding privacy and (2) the target global ($\epsilon_{g}, \delta_{g}$)-confounding privacy is tightly implemented by solving an optimization problem. Finally, we study inverse composition empirically on real datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12010v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tao Zhang, Bradley A. Malin, Netanel Raviv, Yevgeniy Vorobeychik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>R-STELLAR: A Resilient Synthesizable Signature Attenuation SCA Protection on AES-256 with built-in Attack-on-Countermeasure Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12021</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12021v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Side channel attacks (SCAs) remain a significant threat to the security of cryptographic systems in modern embedded devices. Even mathematically secure cryptographic algorithms, when implemented in hardware, inadvertently leak information through physical side channel signatures such as power consumption, electromagnetic (EM) radiation, light emissions, and acoustic emanations. Exploiting these side channels significantly reduces the search space of the attacker. In recent years, physical countermeasures have significantly increased the minimum traces to disclosure (MTD) to 1 billion. Among them, signature attenuation is the first method to achieve this mark. Signature attenuation often relies on analog techniques, and digital signature attenuation reduces MTD to 20 million, requiring additional methods for high resilience. We focus on improving the digital signature attenuation by an order of magnitude (MTD 200M). Additionally, we explore possible attacks against signature attenuation countermeasure. We introduce a Voltage drop Linear region Biasing (VLB) attack technique that reduces the MTD to over 2000 times less than the previous threshold. This is the first known attack against a physical side-channel attack (SCA) countermeasure. We have implemented an attack detector with a response time of 0.8 milliseconds to detect such attacks, limiting SCA leakage window to sub-ms, which is insufficient for a successful attack.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12021v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Archisman Ghosh, Dong-Hyun Seo, Debayan Das, Santosh Ghosh, Shreyas Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Threat Modelling of IoT Context-Sharing Platforms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12081</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12081v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Internet of Things (IoT) involves complex, interconnected systems and devices that depend on context-sharing platforms for interoperability and information exchange. These platforms are, therefore, critical components of real-world IoT deployments, making their security essential to ensure the resilience and reliability of these 'systems of systems'. In this paper, we take the first steps toward systematically and comprehensively addressing the security of IoT context-sharing platforms. We propose a framework for threat modelling and security analysis of a generic IoT context-sharing solution, employing the MITRE ATT&amp;CK framework. Through an evaluation of various industry-funded projects and academic research, we identify significant security challenges in the design of IoT context-sharing platforms. Our threat modelling provides an in-depth analysis of the techniques and sub-techniques adversaries may use to exploit these systems, offering valuable insights for future research aimed at developing resilient solutions. Additionally, we have developed an open-source threat analysis tool that incorporates our detailed threat modelling, which can be used to evaluate and enhance the security of existing context-sharing platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12081v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Goudarzi, Arash Shaghaghi, Simon Finn, Burkhard Stiller, Sanjay Jha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Data Reconstruction Leakage in Federated Learning from a Theoretical Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12119</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12119v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Federated learning (FL) is an emerging collaborative learning paradigm that aims to protect data privacy. Unfortunately, recent works show FL algorithms are vulnerable to the serious data reconstruction attacks. However, existing works lack a theoretical foundation on to what extent the devices' data can be reconstructed and the effectiveness of these attacks cannot be compared fairly due to their unstable performance. To address this deficiency, we propose a theoretical framework to understand data reconstruction attacks to FL. Our framework involves bounding the data reconstruction error and an attack's error bound reflects its inherent attack effectiveness. Under the framework, we can theoretically compare the effectiveness of existing attacks. For instance, our results on multiple datasets validate that the iDLG attack inherently outperforms the DLG attack.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12119v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zifan Wang, Binghui Zhang, Meng Pang, Yuan Hong, Binghui Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Credibility of Backdoor Attacks Against Object Detectors in the Physical World</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12122v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Object detectors are vulnerable to backdoor attacks. In contrast to classifiers, detectors possess unique characteristics, architecturally and in task execution; often operating in challenging conditions, for instance, detecting traffic signs in autonomous cars. But, our knowledge dominates attacks against classifiers and tests in the "digital domain".
  To address this critical gap, we conducted an extensive empirical study targeting multiple detector architectures and two challenging detection tasks in real-world settings: traffic signs and vehicles. Using the diverse, methodically collected videos captured from driving cars and flying drones, incorporating physical object trigger deployments in authentic scenes, we investigated the viability of physical object-triggered backdoor attacks in application settings.
  Our findings revealed 8 key insights. Importantly, the prevalent "digital" data poisoning method for injecting backdoors into models does not lead to effective attacks against detectors in the real world, although proven effective in classification tasks. We construct a new, cost-efficient attack method, dubbed MORPHING, incorporating the unique nature of detection tasks; ours is remarkably successful in injecting physical object-triggered backdoors, even capable of poisoning triggers with clean label annotations or invisible triggers without diminishing the success of physical object triggered backdoors. We discovered that the defenses curated are ill-equipped to safeguard detectors against such attacks. To underscore the severity of the threat and foster further research, we, for the first time, release an extensive video test set of real-world backdoor attacks. Our study not only establishes the credibility and seriousness of this threat but also serves as a clarion call to the research community to advance backdoor defenses in the context of object detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12122v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bao Gia Doan, Dang Quang Nguyen, Callum Lindquist, Paul Montague, Tamas Abraham, Olivier De Vel, Seyit Camtepe, Salil S. Kanhere, Ehsan Abbasnejad, Damith C. Ranasinghe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying Psychological Sophistication of Malicious Emails</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12217</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12217v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Malicious emails including Phishing, Spam, and Scam are one significant class of cyber social engineering attacks. Despite numerous defenses to counter them, the problem remains largely open. The ineffectiveness of current defenses can be attributed to our superficial understanding of the psychological properties that make these attacks successful. This problem motivates us to investigate the psychological sophistication, or sophistication for short, of malicious emails. We propose an innovative framework that accommodates two important and complementary aspects of sophistication, dubbed Psychological Techniques, PTechs, and Psychological Tactics, PTacs. We propose metrics and grading rules for human experts to assess the sophistication of malicious emails via the lens of these PTechs and PTacs. To demonstrate the usefulness of the framework, we conduct a case study based on 1,036 malicious emails assessed by four independent graders. Our results show that malicious emails are psychologically sophisticated, while exhibiting both commonalities and different patterns in terms of their PTechs and PTacs. Results also show that previous studies might have focused on dealing with the less proliferated PTechs such as Persuasion and PTacs such as Reward, rather than the most proliferated PTechs such as Attention Grabbing and Impersonation, and PTacs such as Fit and Form and Familiarity that are identified in this study. We also found among others that social events are widely exploited by attackers in contextualizing their malicious emails. These findings could be leveraged to guide the design of effective defenses against malicious emails.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12217v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Theodore Longtchi, Rosana Monta\~nez Rodriguez, Kora Gwartney, Ekzhin Ear, David P. Azari, Christopher P. Kelley, Shouhuai Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SoK: An Introspective Analysis of RPKI Security</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12359v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI) is the main mechanism to protect inter-domain routing with BGP from prefix hijacks. It has already been widely deployed by large providers and the adoption rate is getting to a critical point. Almost half of all the global prefixes are now covered by RPKI and measurements show that 27% of networks are already using RPKI to validate BGP announcements. Over the past 10 years, there has been much research effort in RPKI, analyzing different facets of the protocol, such as software vulnerabilities, robustness of the infrastructure or the proliferation of RPKI validation. In this work we compile the first systemic overview of the vulnerabilities and misconfigurations in RPKI and quantify the security landscape of the global RPKI deployments based on our measurements and analysis. Our study discovers that 56% of the global RPKI validators suffer from at least one documented vulnerability. We also do a systematization of knowledge for existing RPKI security research and complement the existing knowledge with novel measurements in which we discover new trends in availability of RPKI repositories, and their communication patterns with the RPKI validators. We weave together the results of existing research and our study, to provide a comprehensive tableau of vulnerabilities, their sources, and to derive future research paths necessary to prepare RPKI for full global deployment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12359v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Donika Mirdita, Haya Schulmann, Michael Waidner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Verifiable Homomorphic Linear Combinations in Multi-Instance Time-Lock Puzzles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12444v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Time-Lock Puzzles (TLPs) have been developed to securely transmit sensitive information into the future without relying on a trusted third party. Multi-instance TLP is a scalable variant of TLP that enables a server to efficiently find solutions to different puzzles provided by a client at once. Nevertheless, existing multi-instance TLPs lack support for (verifiable) homomorphic computation. To address this limitation, we introduce the "Multi-Instance partially Homomorphic TLP" (MH-TLP), a multi-instance TLP supporting efficient verifiable homomorphic linear combinations of puzzles belonging to a client. It ensures anyone can verify the correctness of computations and solutions. Building on MH-TLP, we further propose the "Multi-instance Multi-client verifiable partially Homomorphic TLP" (MMH-TLP). It not only supports all the features of MH-TLP but also allows for verifiable homomorphic linear combinations of puzzles from different clients. Our schemes refrain from using asymmetric-key cryptography for verification and, unlike most homomorphic TLPs, do not require a trusted third party. A comprehensive cost analysis demonstrates that our schemes scale linearly with the number of clients and puzzles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12444v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aydin Abadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SAGE-RT: Synthetic Alignment data Generation for Safety Evaluation and Red Teaming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11851v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce Synthetic Alignment data Generation for Safety Evaluation and Red Teaming (SAGE-RT or SAGE) a novel pipeline for generating synthetic alignment and red-teaming data. Existing methods fall short in creating nuanced and diverse datasets, providing necessary control over the data generation and validation processes, or require large amount of manually generated seed data. SAGE addresses these limitations by using a detailed taxonomy to produce safety-alignment and red-teaming data across a wide range of topics. We generated 51,000 diverse and in-depth prompt-response pairs, encompassing over 1,500 topics of harmfulness and covering variations of the most frequent types of jailbreaking prompts faced by large language models (LLMs). We show that the red-teaming data generated through SAGE jailbreaks state-of-the-art LLMs in more than 27 out of 32 sub-categories, and in more than 58 out of 279 leaf-categories (sub-sub categories). The attack success rate for GPT-4o, GPT-3.5-turbo is 100% over the sub-categories of harmfulness. Our approach avoids the pitfalls of synthetic safety-training data generation such as mode collapse and lack of nuance in the generation pipeline by ensuring a detailed coverage of harmful topics using iterative expansion of the topics and conditioning the outputs on the generated raw-text. This method can be used to generate red-teaming and alignment data for LLM Safety completely synthetically to make LLMs safer or for red-teaming the models over a diverse range of topics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11851v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anurakt Kumar, Divyanshu Kumar, Jatan Loya, Nitin Aravind Birur, Tanay Baswa, Sahil Agarwal, Prashanth Harshangi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parameter-Efficient Transfer Learning under Federated Learning for Automatic Speech Recognition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11873v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work explores the challenge of enhancing Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR) model performance across various user-specific domains while preserving user data privacy. We employ federated learning and parameter-efficient domain adaptation methods to solve the (1) massive data requirement of ASR models from user-specific scenarios and (2) the substantial communication cost between servers and clients during federated learning. We demonstrate that when equipped with proper adapters, ASR models under federated tuning can achieve similar performance compared with centralized tuning ones, thus providing a potential direction for future privacy-preserved ASR services. Besides, we investigate the efficiency of different adapters and adapter incorporation strategies under the federated learning setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11873v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuan Kan, Yonghui Xiao, Tien-Ju Yang, Nanxin Chen, Rajiv Mathews</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the design of stabilizing FIR controllers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11959v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently, it has been observed that finite impulse response controllers are an excellent basis for encrypted control, where privacy-preserving controller evaluations via special cryptosystems are the main focus. Beneficial properties of FIR filters are also well-known from digital signal processing, which makes them preferable over infinite impulse response filters in many applications. Their appeal extends to feedback control, offering design flexibility grounded solely on output measurements. However, designing FIR controllers is challenging, which motivates this work. To address the design challenge, we initially show that FIR controller designs for linear systems can equivalently be stated as static or dynamic output feedback problems. After focusing on the existence of stabilizing FIR controllers for a given plant, we tailor two common design approaches for output feedback to the case of FIR controllers. Unfortunately, it will turn out that the FIR characteristics add further restrictions to the LMI-based approaches. Hence, we finally turn to designs building on non-convex optimization, which provide satisfactory results for a selection of benchmark systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11959v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Janis Adamek, Nils Schl\"uter, Moritz Schulze Darup</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Query-Efficient Video Adversarial Attack with Stylized Logo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12099v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Video classification systems based on Deep Neural Networks (DNNs) have demonstrated excellent performance in accurately verifying video content. However, recent studies have shown that DNNs are highly vulnerable to adversarial examples. Therefore, a deep understanding of adversarial attacks can better respond to emergency situations. In order to improve attack performance, many style-transfer-based attacks and patch-based attacks have been proposed. However, the global perturbation of the former will bring unnatural global color, while the latter is difficult to achieve success in targeted attacks due to the limited perturbation space. Moreover, compared to a plethora of methods targeting image classifiers, video adversarial attacks are still not that popular. Therefore, to generate adversarial examples with a low budget and to provide them with a higher verisimilitude, we propose a novel black-box video attack framework, called Stylized Logo Attack (SLA). SLA is conducted through three steps. The first step involves building a style references set for logos, which can not only make the generated examples more natural, but also carry more target class features in the targeted attacks. Then, reinforcement learning (RL) is employed to determine the style reference and position parameters of the logo within the video, which ensures that the stylized logo is placed in the video with optimal attributes. Finally, perturbation optimization is designed to optimize perturbations to improve the fooling rate in a step-by-step manner. Sufficient experimental results indicate that, SLA can achieve better performance than state-of-the-art methods and still maintain good deception effects when facing various defense methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12099v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Duoxun Tang, Yuxin Cao, Xi Xiao, Derui Wang, Sheng Wen, Tianqing Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Bright Side of Timed Opacity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12240</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12240v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In 2009, Franck Cassez showed that the timed opacity problem, where an attacker can observe some actions with their timestamps and attempts to deduce information, is undecidable for timed automata (TAs). Moreover, he showed that the undecidability holds even for subclasses such as event-recording automata. In this article, we consider the same definition of opacity for several other subclasses of TAs: with restrictions on the number of clocks, of actions, on the nature of time, or on a new subclass called observable event-recording automata. We show that opacity can mostly be retrieved, except for one-action TAs and for one-clock TAs with epsilon-transitions, for which undecidability remains. We then exhibit a new decidable subclass in which the number of observations made by the attacker is limited.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12240v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\'Etienne Andr\'e, Sarah D\'epernet, Engel Lefaucheux</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defending Against Unforeseen Failure Modes with Latent Adversarial Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05030</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05030v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Despite extensive diagnostics and debugging by developers, AI systems sometimes exhibit harmful unintended behaviors. Finding and fixing these is challenging because the attack surface is so large -- it is not tractable to exhaustively search for inputs that may elicit harmful behaviors. Red-teaming and adversarial training (AT) are commonly used to improve robustness, however, they empirically struggle to fix failure modes that differ from the attacks used during training. In this work, we utilize latent adversarial training (LAT) to defend against vulnerabilities without leveraging knowledge of what they are or using inputs that elicit them. LAT makes use of the compressed, abstract, and structured latent representations of concepts that the network actually uses for prediction. Here, we use it to defend against failure modes without examples that elicit them. Specifically, we use LAT to remove trojans and defend against held-out classes of adversarial attacks. We show in image classification, text classification, and text generation tasks that LAT usually improves both robustness to novel attacks and performance on clean data relative to AT. This suggests that LAT can be a promising tool for defending against failure modes that are not explicitly identified by developers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05030v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephen Casper, Lennart Schulze, Oam Patel, Dylan Hadfield-Menell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Study of Backdoors in Instruction Fine-tuned Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.07778v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Backdoor data poisoning, inserted within instruction examples used to fine-tune a foundation Large Language Model (LLM) for downstream tasks (\textit{e.g.,} sentiment prediction), is a serious security concern due to the evasive nature of such attacks. The poisoning is usually in the form of a (seemingly innocuous) trigger word or phrase inserted into a very small fraction of the fine-tuning samples from a target class. Such backdoor attacks can: alter response sentiment, violate censorship, over-refuse (invoke censorship for legitimate queries), inject false content, or trigger nonsense responses (hallucinations). In this work we investigate the efficacy of instruction fine-tuning backdoor attacks as attack "hyperparameters" are varied under a variety of scenarios, considering: the trigger location in the poisoned examples; robustness to change in the trigger location, partial triggers, and synonym substitutions at test time; attack transfer from one (fine-tuning) domain to a related test domain; and clean-label vs. dirty-label poisoning. Based on our observations, we propose and evaluate two defenses against these attacks: i) a \textit{during-fine-tuning defense} based on word-frequency counts that assumes the (possibly poisoned) fine-tuning dataset is available and identifies the backdoor trigger tokens; and ii) a \textit{post-fine-tuning defense} based on downstream clean fine-tuning of the backdoored LLM with a small defense dataset. Finally, we provide a brief survey of related work on backdoor attacks and defenses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.07778v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jayaram Raghuram, George Kesidis, David J. Miller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Dark Side of Function Calling: Pathways to Jailbreaking Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17915v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable capabilities, but their power comes with significant security considerations. While extensive research has been conducted on the safety of LLMs in chat mode, the security implications of their function calling feature have been largely overlooked. This paper uncovers a critical vulnerability in the function calling process of LLMs, introducing a novel "jailbreak function" attack method that exploits alignment discrepancies, user coercion, and the absence of rigorous safety filters. Our empirical study, conducted on six state-of-the-art LLMs including GPT-4o, Claude-3.5-Sonnet, and Gemini-1.5-pro, reveals an alarming average success rate of over 90\% for this attack. We provide a comprehensive analysis of why function calls are susceptible to such attacks and propose defensive strategies, including the use of defensive prompts. Our findings highlight the urgent need for enhanced security measures in the function calling capabilities of LLMs, contributing to the field of AI safety by identifying a previously unexplored risk, designing an effective attack method, and suggesting practical defensive measures. Our code is available at https://github.com/wooozihui/jailbreakfunction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17915v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zihui Wu, Haichang Gao, Jianping He, Ping Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diff-Cleanse: Identifying and Mitigating Backdoor Attacks in Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21316v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Diffusion models (DMs) are regarded as one of the most advanced generative models today, yet recent studies suggest that they are vulnerable to backdoor attacks, which establish hidden associations between particular input patterns and model behaviors, compromising model integrity by causing undesirable actions with manipulated inputs. This vulnerability poses substantial risks, including reputational damage to model owners and the dissemination of harmful content. To mitigate the threat of backdoor attacks, there have been some investigations on backdoor detection and model repair. However, previous work fails to reliably purify the models backdoored by state-of-the-art attack methods, rendering the field much underexplored. To bridge this gap, we introduce Diff-Cleanse, a novel two-stage backdoor defense framework specifically designed for DMs. The first stage employs a novel trigger inversion technique to reconstruct the trigger and detect the backdoor, and the second stage utilizes a structural pruning method to eliminate the backdoor. We evaluate our framework on hundreds of DMs that are attacked by three existing backdoor attack methods with a wide range of hyperparameter settings. Extensive experiments demonstrate that Diff-Cleanse achieves nearly 100\% detection accuracy and effectively mitigates backdoor impacts, preserving the model's benign performance with minimal compromise. Our code is avaliable at https://github.com/shymuel/diff-cleanse.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21316v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiang Hao, Xiao Jin, Hu Xiaoguang, Chen Tianyou, Zhao Jiajia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prefix Guidance: A Steering Wheel for Large Language Models to Defend Against Jailbreak Attacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08924v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In recent years, the rapid development of large language models (LLMs) has achieved remarkable performance across various tasks. However, research indicates that LLMs are vulnerable to jailbreak attacks, where adversaries can induce the generation of harmful content through meticulously crafted prompts. This vulnerability poses significant challenges to the secure use and promotion of LLMs. Existing defense methods offer protection from different perspectives but often suffer from insufficient effectiveness or a significant impact on the model's capabilities. In this paper, we propose a plug-and-play and easy-to-deploy jailbreak defense framework, namely Prefix Guidance (PG), which guides the model to identify harmful prompts by directly setting the first few tokens of the model's output. This approach combines the model's inherent security capabilities with an external classifier to defend against jailbreak attacks. We demonstrate the effectiveness of PG across three models and five attack methods. Compared to baselines, our approach is generally more effective on average. Additionally, results on the Just-Eval benchmark further confirm PG's superiority to preserve the model's performance. our code is available at https://github.com/weiyezhimeng/Prefix-Guidance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08924v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiawei Zhao, Kejiang Chen, Xiaojian Yuan, Weiming Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving the Utility of Differentially Private Clustering through Dynamical Processing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.13886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.13886v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study aims to alleviate the trade-off between utility and privacy of differentially private clustering. Existing works focus on simple methods, which show poor performance for non-convex clusters. To fit complex cluster distributions, we propose sophisticated dynamical processing inspired by Morse theory, with which we hierarchically connect the Gaussian sub-clusters obtained through existing methods. Our theoretical results imply that the proposed dynamical processing introduces little to no additional privacy loss. Experiments show that our framework can improve the clustering performance of existing methods at the same privacy level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.13886v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.patcog.2024.110890</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Pattern Recognition, January 2025, Volume 157, 110890</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Junyoung Byun, Yujin Choi, Jaewook Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fight Back Against Jailbreaking via Prompt Adversarial Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.06255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.06255v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: While Large Language Models (LLMs) have achieved tremendous success in various applications, they are also susceptible to jailbreak attacks. Several primary defense strategies have been proposed to protect LLMs from producing harmful information, mostly with a particular focus on harmful content filtering or heuristical defensive prompt designs. However, how to achieve intrinsic robustness through the prompts remains an open problem. In this paper, motivated by adversarial training paradigms for achieving reliable robustness, we propose an approach named Prompt Adversarial Tuning (PAT) that trains a prompt control attached to the user prompt as a guard prefix. To achieve our defense goal whilst maintaining natural performance, we optimize the control prompt with both adversarial and benign prompts. Comprehensive experiments show that our method is effective against both grey-box and black-box attacks, reducing the success rate of advanced attacks to nearly 0 while maintaining the model's utility on the benign task. The proposed defense strategy incurs only negligible computational overhead, charting a new perspective for future explorations in LLM security. Our code is available at https://github.com/rain152/PAT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.06255v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yichuan Mo, Yuji Wang, Zeming Wei, Yisen Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
