<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CR</link>
    <description>cs.CR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 04:00:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>JailbreakBench: An Open Robustness Benchmark for Jailbreaking Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01318</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01318v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Jailbreak attacks cause large language models (LLMs) to generate harmful, unethical, or otherwise objectionable content. Evaluating these attacks presents a number of challenges, which the current collection of benchmarks and evaluation techniques do not adequately address. First, there is no clear standard of practice regarding jailbreaking evaluation. Second, existing works compute costs and success rates in incomparable ways. And third, numerous works are not reproducible, as they withhold adversarial prompts, involve closed-source code, or rely on evolving proprietary APIs. To address these challenges, we introduce JailbreakBench, an open-sourced benchmark with the following components: (1) a new jailbreaking dataset containing 100 unique behaviors, which we call JBB-Behaviors; (2) an evolving repository of state-of-the-art adversarial prompts, which we refer to as jailbreak artifacts; (3) a standardized evaluation framework that includes a clearly defined threat model, system prompts, chat templates, and scoring functions; and (4) a leaderboard that tracks the performance of attacks and defenses for various LLMs. We have carefully considered the potential ethical implications of releasing this benchmark, and believe that it will be a net positive for the community. Over time, we will expand and adapt the benchmark to reflect technical and methodological advances in the research community.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01318v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Chao, Edoardo Debenedetti, Alexander Robey, Maksym Andriushchenko, Francesco Croce, Vikash Sehwag, Edgar Dobriban, Nicolas Flammarion, George J. Pappas, Florian Tramer, Hamed Hassani, Eric Wong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Haina Storage: A Decentralized Secure Storage Framework Based on Improved Blockchain Structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01606</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01606v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Although the decentralized storage technology based on the blockchain can effectively realize secure data storage on cloud services. However, there are still some problems in the existing schemes, such as low storage capacity and low efficiency. To address related issues, we propose a novel decentralized storage framework, which mainly includes four aspects: (1) we proposed a Bi-direction Circular Linked Chain Structure (BCLCS), which improves data's storage capacity and applicability in decentralized storage. (2) A Proof of Resources (PoR) decision model is proposed. By introducing the network environment as an essential evaluation parameter of storage right decision, the energy and time consumption of decision-making are reduced, and the fairness of decision-making is improved. (3) A chain structure dynamic locking mechanism (CSDLM) is designed to realize anti-traverse and access control. (4) A Bi-directional data Access Mechanism (BDAM) is proposed, which improves the efficiency of data access and acquisition in decentralized storage mode. The experimental results show that the framework has significantly improved the shortcomings of the current decentralized storage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01606v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zijian Zhou, Caimei Wang, Xiaoheng Deng, Jianhao Lu, Qilue Wen, Chen Zhang, Hong Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Making Privacy-preserving Federated Graph Analytics with Strong Guarantees Practical (for Certain Queries)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01619v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Privacy-preserving federated graph analytics is an emerging area of research. The goal is to run graph analytics queries over a set of devices that are organized as a graph while keeping the raw data on the devices rather than centralizing it. Further, no entity may learn any new information except for the final query result. For instance, a device may not learn a neighbor's data. The state-of-the-art prior work for this problem provides privacy guarantees for a broad set of queries in a strong threat model where the devices can be malicious. However, it imposes an impractical overhead: each device locally requires over 8.79 hours of cpu time and 5.73 GiBs of network transfers per query. This paper presents Colo, a new, low-cost system for privacy-preserving federated graph analytics that requires minutes of cpu time and a few MiBs in network transfers, for a particular subset of queries. At the heart of Colo is a new secure computation protocol that enables a device to securely and efficiently evaluate a graph query in its local neighborhood while hiding device data, edge data, and topology data. An implementation and evaluation of Colo shows that for running a variety of COVID-19 queries over a population of 1M devices, it requires less than 8.4 minutes of a device's CPU time and 4.93 MiBs in network transfers - improvements of up to three orders of magnitude.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01619v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kunlong Liu, Trinabh Gupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AAA: an Adaptive Mechanism for Locally Differential Private Mean Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01625v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Local differential privacy (LDP) is a strong privacy standard that has been adopted by popular software systems. The main idea is that each individual perturbs their own data locally, and only submits the resulting noisy version to a data aggregator. Although much effort has been devoted to computing various types of aggregates and building machine learning applications under LDP, research on fundamental perturbation mechanisms has not achieved significant improvement in recent years. Towards a more refined result utility, existing works mainly focus on improving the worst-case guarantee. However, this approach does not necessarily promise a better average performance given the fact that the data in practice obey a certain distribution, which is not known beforehand.
  In this paper, we propose the advanced adaptive additive (AAA) mechanism, which is a distribution-aware approach that addresses the average utility and tackles the classical mean estimation problem. AAA is carried out in a two-step approach: first, as the global data distribution is not available beforehand, the data aggregator selects a random subset of individuals to compute a (noisy) quantized data descriptor; then, the data aggregator collects data from the remaining individuals, which are perturbed in a distribution-aware fashion. The perturbation involved in the latter step is obtained by solving an optimization problem, which is formulated with the data descriptor obtained in the former step and the desired properties of task-determined utilities. We provide rigorous privacy proofs, utility analyses, and extensive experiments comparing AAA with state-of-the-art mechanisms. The evaluation results demonstrate that the AAA mechanism consistently outperforms existing solutions with a clear margin in terms of result utility, on a wide range of privacy constraints and real-world and synthetic datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01625v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fei Wei, Ergute Bao, Xiaokui Xiao, Yin Yang, Bolin Ding</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Lightweight Security Solution for Mitigation of Hatchetman Attack in RPL-based 6LoWPAN</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01689v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In recent times, the Internet of Things (IoT) has a significant rise in industries, and we live in the era of Industry 4.0, where each device is connected to the Internet from small to big. These devices are Artificial Intelligence (AI) enabled and are capable of perspective analytics. By 2023, it's anticipated that over 14 billion smart devices will be available on the Internet. These applications operate in a wireless environment where memory, power, and other resource limitations apply to the nodes. In addition, the conventional routing method is ineffective in networks with limited resource devices, lossy links, and slow data rates. Routing Protocol for Low Power and Lossy Networks (RPL), a new routing protocol for such networks, was proposed by the IETF's ROLL group. RPL operates in two modes: Storing and Non-Storing. In Storing mode, each node have the information to reach to other node. In Non-Storing mode, the routing information lies with the root node only. The attacker may exploit the Non-Storing feature of the RPL. When the root node transmits User Datagram Protocol~(UDP) or control message packet to the child nodes, the routing information is stored in the extended header of the IPv6 packet. The attacker may modify the address from the source routing header which leads to Denial of Service (DoS) attack. This attack is RPL specific which is known as Hatchetman attack. This paper shows significant degradation in terms of network performance when an attacker exploits this feature. We also propose a lightweight mitigation of Hatchetman attack using game theoretic approach to detect the Hatchetman attack in IoT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01689v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ANTS59832.2023.10469481</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Girish Sharma, Jyoti Grover, Abhishek Verma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Security for adversarial wiretap channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01760v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the wiretap channel, where the individual channel uses have memory or are influenced by an adversary. We analyze the explicit and computationally efficient construction of information-theoretically secure coding schemes which use the inverse of an extractor and an error-correcting code. These schemes are known to achieve secrecy capacity on a large class of memoryless wiretap channels. We show that this also holds for certain channel types with memory. In particular, they can achieve secrecy capacity on channels where an adversary can pick a sequence of ``states'' governing the channel's behavior, as long as, given every possible state, the channel is strongly symmetric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01760v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Esther H\"anggi, Iy\'an M\'endez Veiga, Ligong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Systematic Solutions to Login and Authentication Security: A Dual-Password Login-Authentication Mechanism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01803v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Credential theft and remote attacks are the most serious threats to authentication mechanisms. The crux of the problems is that we cannot control such behaviors. However, if a password does not contain user's secrets, stealing it is useless. If unauthorized inputs are disabled, the remote attacks can be invalidated. Thereby, credential secrets and input fields to our accounts can be controlled. Rather than encrypting passwords, we design a dual-password login-authentication mechanism, where a user-selected secret-free login password is converted into an untypable authentication password. Subsequently, the authenticatable functionality of the login password and the typable functionality of the authentication password may be disabled or invalidated so that the credential theft and remote attacks can be prevented. Thus, the usability-security trade-off and password reuse are resolved; local storage of authentication passwords is no longer necessary. More importantly, the password converter acts as an open hash algorithm, meaning that its intermediate elements can be used to define a truly unique identity of the login process to implement a novel dual-identity authentication. Particularly, the elements are concealed, inaccessible, and independent of any personal information, and therefore can be used to define a perfect unforgeable process identifier to identify and disable the unauthorized inputs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01803v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yun Su, Mo Xi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Software-Defined Cryptography: A Design Feature of Cryptographic Agility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01808v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cryptographic agility, or crypto-agility, is a design feature that enables agile updates to new cryptographic algorithms and standards without the need to modify or replace the surrounding infrastructure. This paper examines the prerequisites for crypto-agility and proposes its desired design feature. More specifically, we investigate the design characteristics of widely deployed cybersecurity paradigms, i.e., zero trust, and apply its design feature to crypto-agility, achieving greater visibility and automation in cryptographic management.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01808v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jihoon Cho, Changhoon Lee, Eunkyung Kim, Jieun Lee, Beumjin Cho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Great, Now Write an Article About That: The Crescendo Multi-Turn LLM Jailbreak Attack</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01833v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Large Language Models (LLMs) have risen significantly in popularity and are increasingly being adopted across multiple applications. These LLMs are heavily aligned to resist engaging in illegal or unethical topics as a means to avoid contributing to responsible AI harms. However, a recent line of attacks, known as "jailbreaks", seek to overcome this alignment. Intuitively, jailbreak attacks aim to narrow the gap between what the model can do and what it is willing to do. In this paper, we introduce a novel jailbreak attack called Crescendo. Unlike existing jailbreak methods, Crescendo is a multi-turn jailbreak that interacts with the model in a seemingly benign manner. It begins with a general prompt or question about the task at hand and then gradually escalates the dialogue by referencing the model's replies, progressively leading to a successful jailbreak. We evaluate Crescendo on various public systems, including ChatGPT, Gemini Pro, Gemini-Ultra, LlaMA-2 70b Chat, and Anthropic Chat. Our results demonstrate the strong efficacy of Crescendo, with it achieving high attack success rates across all evaluated models and tasks. Furthermore, we introduce Crescendomation, a tool that automates the Crescendo attack, and our evaluation showcases its effectiveness against state-of-the-art models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01833v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark Russinovich, Ahmed Salem, Ronen Eldan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multicore DRAM Bank-&amp; Row-Conflict Bomb for Timing Attacks in Mixed-Criticality Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01910</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01910v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With the increasing use of multicore platforms to realize mixed-criticality systems, understanding the underlying shared resources, such as the memory hierarchy shared among cores, and achieving isolation between co-executing tasks running on the same platform with different criticality levels becomes relevant. In addition to safety considerations, a malicious entity can exploit shared resources to create timing attacks on critical applications. In this paper, we focus on understanding the shared DRAM dual in-line memory module and created a timing attack, that we named the "bank &amp; row conflict bomb", to target a victim task in a multicore platform. We also created a "navigate" algorithm to understand how victim requests are managed by the Memory Controller and provide valuable inputs for designing the bank &amp; row conflict bomb. We performed experimental tests on a 2nd Gen Intel Xeon Processor with an 8GB DDR4-2666 DRAM module to show that such an attack can produce a significant increase in the execution time of the victim task by about 150%, motivating the need for proper countermeasures to help ensure the safety and security of critical applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01910v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Savino, Gautam Gala, Marcello Cinque, Gerhard Fohler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital Forgetting in Large Language Models: A Survey of Unlearning Methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02062v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The objective of digital forgetting is, given a model with undesirable knowledge or behavior, obtain a new model where the detected issues are no longer present. The motivations for forgetting include privacy protection, copyright protection, elimination of biases and discrimination, and prevention of harmful content generation. Effective digital forgetting has to be effective (meaning how well the new model has forgotten the undesired knowledge/behavior), retain the performance of the original model on the desirable tasks, and be scalable (in particular forgetting has to be more efficient than retraining from scratch on just the tasks/data to be retained). This survey focuses on forgetting in large language models (LLMs). We first provide background on LLMs, including their components, the types of LLMs, and their usual training pipeline. Second, we describe the motivations, types, and desired properties of digital forgetting. Third, we introduce the approaches to digital forgetting in LLMs, among which unlearning methodologies stand out as the state of the art. Fourth, we provide a detailed taxonomy of machine unlearning methods for LLMs, and we survey and compare current approaches. Fifth, we detail datasets, models and metrics used for the evaluation of forgetting, retaining and runtime. Sixth, we discuss challenges in the area. Finally, we provide some concluding remarks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02062v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Blanco-Justicia, Najeeb Jebreel, Benet Manzanares, David S\'anchez, Josep Domingo-Ferrer, Guillem Collell, Kuan Eeik Tan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topic-based Watermarks for LLM-Generated Text</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02138</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02138v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advancements of large language models (LLMs) have resulted in indistinguishable text outputs comparable to human-generated text. Watermarking algorithms are potential tools that offer a way to differentiate between LLM- and human-generated text by embedding detectable signatures within LLM-generated output. However, current watermarking schemes lack robustness against known attacks against watermarking algorithms. In addition, they are impractical considering an LLM generates tens of thousands of text outputs per day and the watermarking algorithm needs to memorize each output it generates for the detection to work. In this work, focusing on the limitations of current watermarking schemes, we propose the concept of a "topic-based watermarking algorithm" for LLMs. The proposed algorithm determines how to generate tokens for the watermarked LLM output based on extracted topics of an input prompt or the output of a non-watermarked LLM. Inspired from previous work, we propose using a pair of lists (that are generated based on the specified extracted topic(s)) that specify certain tokens to be included or excluded while generating the watermarked output of the LLM. Using the proposed watermarking algorithm, we show the practicality of a watermark detection algorithm. Furthermore, we discuss a wide range of attacks that can emerge against watermarking algorithms for LLMs and the benefit of the proposed watermarking scheme for the feasibility of modeling a potential attacker considering its benefit vs. loss.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02138v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Nemecek, Yuzhou Jiang, Erman Ayday</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Seaweed to Security: The Emergence of Alginate in Compromising IoT Fingerprint Sensors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02150v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The increasing integration of capacitive fingerprint recognition sensors in IoT devices presents new challenges in digital forensics, particularly in the context of advanced fingerprint spoofing. Previous research has highlighted the effectiveness of materials such as latex and silicone in deceiving biometric systems. In this study, we introduce Alginate, a biopolymer derived from brown seaweed, as a novel material with the potential for spoofing IoT-specific capacitive fingerprint sensors. Our research uses Alginate and cutting-edge image recognition techniques to unveil a nuanced IoT vulnerability that raises significant security and privacy concerns. Our proof-of-concept experiments employed authentic fingerprint molds to create Alginate replicas, which exhibited remarkable visual and tactile similarities to real fingerprints. The conductivity and resistivity properties of Alginate, closely resembling human skin, make it a subject of interest in the digital forensics field, especially regarding its ability to spoof IoT device sensors. This study calls upon the digital forensics community to develop advanced anti-spoofing strategies to protect the evolving IoT infrastructure against such sophisticated threats.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02150v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pouria Rad, Gokila Dorai, Mohsen Jozani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jailbreaking Leading Safety-Aligned LLMs with Simple Adaptive Attacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02151v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that even the most recent safety-aligned LLMs are not robust to simple adaptive jailbreaking attacks. First, we demonstrate how to successfully leverage access to logprobs for jailbreaking: we initially design an adversarial prompt template (sometimes adapted to the target LLM), and then we apply random search on a suffix to maximize the target logprob (e.g., of the token "Sure"), potentially with multiple restarts. In this way, we achieve nearly 100\% attack success rate -- according to GPT-4 as a judge -- on GPT-3.5/4, Llama-2-Chat-7B/13B/70B, Gemma-7B, and R2D2 from HarmBench that was adversarially trained against the GCG attack. We also show how to jailbreak all Claude models -- that do not expose logprobs -- via either a transfer or prefilling attack with 100\% success rate. In addition, we show how to use random search on a restricted set of tokens for finding trojan strings in poisoned models -- a task that shares many similarities with jailbreaking -- which is the algorithm that brought us the first place in the SaTML'24 Trojan Detection Competition. The common theme behind these attacks is that adaptivity is crucial: different models are vulnerable to different prompting templates (e.g., R2D2 is very sensitive to in-context learning prompts), some models have unique vulnerabilities based on their APIs (e.g., prefilling for Claude), and in some settings it is crucial to restrict the token search space based on prior knowledge (e.g., for trojan detection). We provide the code, prompts, and logs of the attacks at https://github.com/tml-epfl/llm-adaptive-attacks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02151v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maksym Andriushchenko, Francesco Croce, Nicolas Flammarion</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear Hashing with $\ell_\infty$ guarantees and two-sided Kakeya bounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.01665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2204.01665v3 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that a randomly chosen linear map over a finite field gives a good hash function in the $\ell_\infty$ sense. More concretely, consider a set $S \subset \mathbb{F}_q^n$ and a randomly chosen linear map $L : \mathbb{F}_q^n \to \mathbb{F}_q^t$ with $q^t$ taken to be sufficiently smaller than $ |S|$. Let $U_S$ denote a random variable distributed uniformly on $S$. Our main theorem shows that, with high probability over the choice of $L$, the random variable $L(U_S)$ is close to uniform in the $\ell_\infty$ norm. In other words, {\em every} element in the range $\mathbb{F}_q^t$ has about the same number of elements in $S$ mapped to it. This complements the widely-used Leftover Hash Lemma (LHL) which proves the analog statement under the statistical, or $\ell_1$, distance (for a richer class of functions) as well as prior work on the expected largest 'bucket size' in linear hash functions [ADMPT99]. By known bounds from the load balancing literature [RS98], our results are tight and show that linear functions hash as well as trully random function up to a constant factor in the entropy loss. Our proof leverages a connection between linear hashing and the finite field Kakeya problem and extends some of the tools developed in this area, in particular the polynomial method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2204.01665v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.46298/theoretics.24.8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>TheoretiCS, Volume 3 (2024), Article 8, 1-30</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Manik Dhar, Zeev Dvir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-granular Adversarial Attacks against Black-box Neural Ranking Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01574v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Adversarial ranking attacks have gained increasing attention due to their success in probing vulnerabilities, and, hence, enhancing the robustness, of neural ranking models. Conventional attack methods employ perturbations at a single granularity, e.g., word-level or sentence-level, to a target document. However, limiting perturbations to a single level of granularity may reduce the flexibility of creating adversarial examples, thereby diminishing the potential threat of the attack. Therefore, we focus on generating high-quality adversarial examples by incorporating multi-granular perturbations. Achieving this objective involves tackling a combinatorial explosion problem, which requires identifying an optimal combination of perturbations across all possible levels of granularity, positions, and textual pieces. To address this challenge, we transform the multi-granular adversarial attack into a sequential decision-making process, where perturbations in the next attack step are influenced by the perturbed document in the current attack step. Since the attack process can only access the final state without direct intermediate signals, we use reinforcement learning to perform multi-granular attacks. During the reinforcement learning process, two agents work cooperatively to identify multi-granular vulnerabilities as attack targets and organize perturbation candidates into a final perturbation sequence. Experimental results show that our attack method surpasses prevailing baselines in both attack effectiveness and imperceptibility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01574v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-An Liu, Ruqing Zhang, Jiafeng Guo, Maarten de Rijke, Yixing Fan, Xueqi Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ADVREPAIR:Provable Repair of Adversarial Attack</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01642v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Deep neural networks (DNNs) are increasingly deployed in safety-critical domains, but their vulnerability to adversarial attacks poses serious safety risks. Existing neuron-level methods using limited data lack efficacy in fixing adversaries due to the inherent complexity of adversarial attack mechanisms, while adversarial training, leveraging a large number of adversarial samples to enhance robustness, lacks provability. In this paper, we propose ADVREPAIR, a novel approach for provable repair of adversarial attacks using limited data. By utilizing formal verification, ADVREPAIR constructs patch modules that, when integrated with the original network, deliver provable and specialized repairs within the robustness neighborhood. Additionally, our approach incorporates a heuristic mechanism for assigning patch modules, allowing this defense against adversarial attacks to generalize to other inputs. ADVREPAIR demonstrates superior efficiency, scalability and repair success rate. Different from existing DNN repair methods, our repair can generalize to general inputs, thereby improving the robustness of the neural network globally, which indicates a significant breakthrough in the generalization capability of ADVREPAIR.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01642v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiming Chi, Jianan Ma, Pengfei Yang, Cheng-Chao Huang, Renjue Li, Xiaowei Huang, Lijun Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrusion Tolerance for Networked Systems through Two-Level Feedback Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01741</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01741v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We formulate intrusion tolerance for a system with service replicas as a two-level optimal control problem. On the local level node controllers perform intrusion recovery, and on the global level a system controller manages the replication factor. The local and global control problems can be formulated as classical problems in operations research, namely, the machine replacement problem and the inventory replenishment problem. Based on this formulation, we design TOLERANCE, a novel control architecture for intrusion-tolerant systems. We prove that the optimal control strategies on both levels have threshold structure and design efficient algorithms for computing them. We implement and evaluate TOLERANCE in an emulation environment where we run 10 types of network intrusions. The results show that TOLERANCE can improve service availability and reduce operational cost compared with state-of-the-art intrusion-tolerant systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01741v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kim Hammar, Rolf Stadler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Humanizing Machine-Generated Content: Evading AI-Text Detection through Adversarial Attack</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01907v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: With the development of large language models (LLMs), detecting whether text is generated by a machine becomes increasingly challenging in the face of malicious use cases like the spread of false information, protection of intellectual property, and prevention of academic plagiarism. While well-trained text detectors have demonstrated promising performance on unseen test data, recent research suggests that these detectors have vulnerabilities when dealing with adversarial attacks such as paraphrasing. In this paper, we propose a framework for a broader class of adversarial attacks, designed to perform minor perturbations in machine-generated content to evade detection. We consider two attack settings: white-box and black-box, and employ adversarial learning in dynamic scenarios to assess the potential enhancement of the current detection model's robustness against such attacks. The empirical results reveal that the current detection models can be compromised in as little as 10 seconds, leading to the misclassification of machine-generated text as human-written content. Furthermore, we explore the prospect of improving the model's robustness over iterative adversarial learning. Although some improvements in model robustness are observed, practical applications still face significant challenges. These findings shed light on the future development of AI-text detectors, emphasizing the need for more accurate and robust detection methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01907v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ying Zhou, Ben He, Le Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bi-LORA: A Vision-Language Approach for Synthetic Image Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01959v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Advancements in deep image synthesis techniques, such as generative adversarial networks (GANs) and diffusion models (DMs), have ushered in an era of generating highly realistic images. While this technological progress has captured significant interest, it has also raised concerns about the potential difficulty in distinguishing real images from their synthetic counterparts. This paper takes inspiration from the potent convergence capabilities between vision and language, coupled with the zero-shot nature of vision-language models (VLMs). We introduce an innovative method called Bi-LORA that leverages VLMs, combined with low-rank adaptation (LORA) tuning techniques, to enhance the precision of synthetic image detection for unseen model-generated images. The pivotal conceptual shift in our methodology revolves around reframing binary classification as an image captioning task, leveraging the distinctive capabilities of cutting-edge VLM, notably bootstrapping language image pre-training (BLIP2). Rigorous and comprehensive experiments are conducted to validate the effectiveness of our proposed approach, particularly in detecting unseen diffusion-generated images from unknown diffusion-based generative models during training, showcasing robustness to noise, and demonstrating generalization capabilities to GANs. The obtained results showcase an impressive average accuracy of 93.41% in synthetic image detection on unseen generation models. The code and models associated with this research can be publicly accessed at https://github.com/Mamadou-Keita/VLM-DETECT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01959v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mamadou Keita, Wassim Hamidouche, Hessen Bougueffa Eutamene, Abdenour Hadid, Abdelmalik Taleb-Ahmed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Post Quantum Key Agreement Protocol Based on a Modified Matrix Power Function over a Rectangular Matrices Semiring</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.11972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.11972v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present an improved post-quantum version of Sakalauskas matrix power function key agreement protocol, using rectangular matrices instead of the original square ones. Sakalauskas matrix power function is an efficient and secure way to generate a shared secret key, and using rectangular matrices provides additional flexibility and security. This method reduces the computational complexity by allowing smaller random integer matrices while maintaining a high level of security. We dont rely on matrices with special formatting to achieve commutativity, instead, we use full random values on those structures, increasing their entropy. Another advantage of using rectangular matrices over key agreement protocols is that they offer better protection against various linearization attacks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.11972v5</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan Pedro Hecht, Hugo Daniel Scolnik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep transfer learning for intrusion detection in industrial control networks: A comprehensive review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.10550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.10550v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Globally, the external internet is increasingly being connected to industrial control systems. As a result, there is an immediate need to protect these networks from a variety of threats. The key infrastructure of industrial activity can be protected from harm using an intrusion detection system (IDS), a preventive mechanism that seeks to recognize new kinds of dangerous threats and hostile activities. This review examines the most recent artificial-intelligence techniques that are used to create IDSs in many kinds of industrial control networks, with a particular emphasis on IDS-based deep transfer learning (DTL). DTL can be seen as a type of information-fusion approach that merges and/or adapts knowledge from multiple domains to enhance the performance of a target task, particularly when labeled data in the target domain is scarce. Publications issued after 2015 were considered. These selected publications were divided into three categories: DTL-only and IDS-only works are examined in the introduction and background section, and DTL-based IDS papers are considered in the core section of this review. By reading this review paper, researchers will be able to gain a better grasp of the current state of DTL approaches used in IDSs in many different types of network. Other useful information, such as the datasets used, the type of DTL employed, the pre-trained network, IDS techniques, the evaluation metrics including accuracy/F-score and false-alarm rate, and the improvements gained, are also covered. The algorithms and methods used in several studies are presented, and the principles of DTL-based IDS subcategories are presented to the reader and illustrated deeply and clearly</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.10550v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jnca.2023.103760</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Network and Computer Applications, Elsevier, 2023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hamza Kheddar, Yassine Himeur, Ali Ismail Awad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Functional Encryption in the Bounded Storage Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.06702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.06702v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Functional encryption is a powerful paradigm for public-key encryption that allows for controlled access to encrypted data. Achieving the ideal simulation based security for this primitive is generally impossible in the plain model, so we investigate possibilities in the bounded quantum storage model (BQSM) and the bounded classical storage model (BCSM), where adversaries are limited with respect to their quantum and classical memories, respectively. The impossibility results on functional encryption do not apply to these settings which allows us to obtain positive outcomes.
  Firstly, in the BQSM, we construct non-interactive functional encryption satisfying information-theoretic simulation based security with ${q}=O(\sqrt{{s}/{r}})$. Here ${r}$ denotes the number of times that an adversary is restricted to ${s}$--qubits of quantum memory in the protocol and ${q}$ denotes the required quantum memory to run the protocol honestly. We then show that our scheme is optimal by proving that it is impossible to attain information-theoretically security with ${q} &lt; \sqrt{{s}/{r}}$. However, by assuming the existence of one-way functions, we achieve (interactive) functional encryption with ${q}=0$ and ${r}=1$.
  Secondly, in the BCSM, we construct non-interactive functional encryption satisfying information-theoretic subexponential simulation based security assuming the existence of subexponential grey-box obfuscation. We then demonstrate that this assumption is minimal by constructing subexponential grey-box obfuscation from non-interactive functional encryption. We also consider the computational setting, obtaining (interactive) functional encryption satisfying simulation based security assuming grey-box obfuscation and one-way functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.06702v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammed Barhoush, Louis Salvail</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RTPS Attack Dataset Description</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.14496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.14496v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper explains all about our RTPS datasets. We collect malicious/benign packet data by injecting attack data in an Unmanned Ground Vehicle (UGV) in the normal state. We assembled the testbed, consisting of UGV, Controller, PC, and Router. We collect this dataset in the UGV part of our testbed.
  We conducted two types of attack "Command Injection" and "Command Injection with ARP Spoofing" on our testbed. The data collection time is 180, 300, 600, and 1200. The scenario has 30 each on collection time, 240 total. We expect this dataset to contribute to the development of defense technologies like anomaly detection to address security threat issues in ROS2 networks and Fast-DDS implements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.14496v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dong Young Kim, Dongsung Kim, Yuchan Song, Gang Min Kim, Min Geun Song, Jeong Do Yoo, Huy Kang Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VA3: Virtually Assured Amplification Attack on Probabilistic Copyright Protection for Text-to-Image Generative Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.00057</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.00057v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The booming use of text-to-image generative models has raised concerns about their high risk of producing copyright-infringing content. While probabilistic copyright protection methods provide a probabilistic guarantee against such infringement, in this paper, we introduce Virtually Assured Amplification Attack (VA3), a novel online attack framework that exposes the vulnerabilities of these protection mechanisms. The proposed framework significantly amplifies the probability of generating infringing content on the sustained interactions with generative models and a non-trivial lower-bound on the success probability of each engagement. Our theoretical and experimental results demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach under various scenarios. These findings highlight the potential risk of implementing probabilistic copyright protection in practical applications of text-to-image generative models. Code is available at https://github.com/South7X/VA3.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.00057v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiang Li, Qianli Shen, Kenji Kawaguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new lightweight additive homomorphic encryption algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.06987</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.06987v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article describes a lightweight additive homomorphic algorithm with the same encryption and decryption keys. Compared to standard additive homomorphic algorithms like Paillier, this algorithm reduces the computational cost of encryption and decryption from modular exponentiation to modular multiplication, and reduces the computational cost of ciphertext addition from modular multiplication to modular addition. This algorithm is based on a new mathematical problem: in two division operations, whether it is possible to infer the remainder or divisor based on the dividend when two remainders are related. Currently, it is not obvious how to break this problem, but further exploration is needed to determine if it is sufficiently difficult. In addition to this mathematical problem, we have also designed two interesting mathematical structures for decryption, which are used in the two algorithms mentioned in the main text. It is possible that the decryption structure of Algorithm 2 introduces new security vulnerabilities, but we have not investigated this issue thoroughly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.06987v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wuqiong Pan, Hongliang Gu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vulnerabilities of Foundation Model Integrated Federated Learning Under Adversarial Threats</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.10375</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.10375v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Federated Learning (FL) addresses critical issues in machine learning related to data privacy and security, yet suffering from data insufficiency and imbalance under certain circumstances. The emergence of foundation models (FMs) offers potential solutions to the limitations of existing FL frameworks, e.g., by generating synthetic data for model initialization. However, due to the inherent safety concerns of FMs, integrating FMs into FL could introduce new risks, which remains largely unexplored. To address this gap, we conduct the first investigation on the vulnerability of FM integrated FL (FM-FL) under adversarial threats. Based on a unified framework of FM-FL, we introduce a novel attack strategy that exploits safety issues of FM to compromise FL client models. Through extensive experiments with well-known models and benchmark datasets in both image and text domains, we reveal the high susceptibility of the FM-FL to this new threat under various FL configurations. Furthermore, we find that existing FL defense strategies offer limited protection against this novel attack approach. This research highlights the critical need for enhanced security measures in FL in the era of FMs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.10375v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Wu, Xi Li, Jiaqi Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking Private Population Data Release Mechanisms: Synthetic Data vs. TopDown</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.18024</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.18024v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Differential privacy (DP) is increasingly used to protect the release of hierarchical, tabular population data, such as census data. A common approach for implementing DP in this setting is to release noisy responses to a predefined set of queries. For example, this is the approach of the TopDown algorithm used by the US Census Bureau. Such methods have an important shortcoming: they cannot answer queries for which they were not optimized. An appealing alternative is to generate DP synthetic data, which is drawn from some generating distribution. Like the TopDown method, synthetic data can also be optimized to answer specific queries, while also allowing the data user to later submit arbitrary queries over the synthetic population data. To our knowledge, there has not been a head-to-head empirical comparison of these approaches. This study conducts such a comparison between the TopDown algorithm and private synthetic data generation to determine how accuracy is affected by query complexity, in-distribution vs. out-of-distribution queries, and privacy guarantees. Our results show that for in-distribution queries, the TopDown algorithm achieves significantly better privacy-fidelity tradeoffs than any of the synthetic data methods we evaluated; for instance, in our experiments, TopDown achieved at least $20\times$ lower error on counting queries than the leading synthetic data method at the same privacy budget. Our findings suggest guidelines for practitioners and the synthetic data research community.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.18024v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aadyaa Maddi, Swadhin Routray, Alexander Goldberg, Giulia Fanti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defending Against Unforeseen Failure Modes with Latent Adversarial Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05030</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05030v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Despite extensive diagnostics and debugging by developers, AI systems sometimes exhibit harmful unintended behaviors. Finding and fixing these is challenging because the attack surface is so large -- it is not tractable to exhaustively search for inputs that may elicit harmful behaviors. Red-teaming and adversarial training (AT) are commonly used to improve robustness, however, they empirically struggle to fix failure modes that differ from the attacks used during training. In this work, we utilize latent adversarial training (LAT) to defend against vulnerabilities without generating inputs that elicit them. LAT leverages the compressed, abstract, and structured latent representations of concepts that the network actually uses for prediction. We use it to remove trojans and defend against held-out classes of adversarial attacks. We show in image classification, text classification, and text generation tasks that LAT usually improves both robustness to novel attacks and performance on clean data relative to AT. This suggests that LAT can be a promising tool for defending against failure modes that are not explicitly identified by developers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05030v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephen Casper, Lennart Schulze, Oam Patel, Dylan Hadfield-Menell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ignore Me But Don't Replace Me: Utilizing Non-Linguistic Elements for Pretraining on the Cybersecurity Domain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10576v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Cybersecurity information is often technically complex and relayed through unstructured text, making automation of cyber threat intelligence highly challenging. For such text domains that involve high levels of expertise, pretraining on in-domain corpora has been a popular method for language models to obtain domain expertise. However, cybersecurity texts often contain non-linguistic elements (such as URLs and hash values) that could be unsuitable with the established pretraining methodologies. Previous work in other domains have removed or filtered such text as noise, but the effectiveness of these methods have not been investigated, especially in the cybersecurity domain. We propose different pretraining methodologies and evaluate their effectiveness through downstream tasks and probing tasks. Our proposed strategy (selective MLM and jointly training NLE token classification) outperforms the commonly taken approach of replacing non-linguistic elements (NLEs). We use our domain-customized methodology to train CyBERTuned, a cybersecurity domain language model that outperforms other cybersecurity PLMs on most tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10576v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eugene Jang, Jian Cui, Dayeon Yim, Youngjin Jin, Jin-Woo Chung, Seungwon Shin, Yongjae Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Effective Are Neural Networks for Fixing Security Vulnerabilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.18607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.18607v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Security vulnerability repair is a difficult task that is in dire need of automation. Two groups of techniques have shown promise: (1) large code language models (LLMs) that have been pre-trained on source code for tasks such as code completion, and (2) automated program repair (APR) techniques that use deep learning (DL) models to automatically fix software bugs.
  This paper is the first to study and compare Java vulnerability repair capabilities of LLMs and DL-based APR models. The contributions include that we (1) apply and evaluate five LLMs (Codex, CodeGen, CodeT5, PLBART and InCoder), four fine-tuned LLMs, and four DL-based APR techniques on two real-world Java vulnerability benchmarks (Vul4J and VJBench), (2) design code transformations to address the training and test data overlapping threat to Codex, (3) create a new Java vulnerability repair benchmark VJBench, and its transformed version VJBench-trans and (4) evaluate LLMs and APR techniques on the transformed vulnerabilities in VJBench-trans.
  Our findings include that (1) existing LLMs and APR models fix very few Java vulnerabilities. Codex fixes 10.2 (20.4%), the most number of vulnerabilities. (2) Fine-tuning with general APR data improves LLMs' vulnerability-fixing capabilities. (3) Our new VJBench reveals that LLMs and APR models fail to fix many Common Weakness Enumeration (CWE) types, such as CWE-325 Missing cryptographic step and CWE-444 HTTP request smuggling. (4) Codex still fixes 8.3 transformed vulnerabilities, outperforming all the other LLMs and APR models on transformed vulnerabilities. The results call for innovations to enhance automated Java vulnerability repair such as creating larger vulnerability repair training data, tuning LLMs with such data, and applying code simplification transformation to facilitate vulnerability repair.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.18607v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3597926.3598135</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yi Wu, Nan Jiang, Hung Viet Pham, Thibaud Lutellier, Jordan Davis, Lin Tan, Petr Babkin, Sameena Shah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>"It's a Fair Game", or Is It? Examining How Users Navigate Disclosure Risks and Benefits When Using LLM-Based Conversational Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.11653</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.11653v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The widespread use of Large Language Model (LLM)-based conversational agents (CAs), especially in high-stakes domains, raises many privacy concerns. Building ethical LLM-based CAs that respect user privacy requires an in-depth understanding of the privacy risks that concern users the most. However, existing research, primarily model-centered, does not provide insight into users' perspectives. To bridge this gap, we analyzed sensitive disclosures in real-world ChatGPT conversations and conducted semi-structured interviews with 19 LLM-based CA users. We found that users are constantly faced with trade-offs between privacy, utility, and convenience when using LLM-based CAs. However, users' erroneous mental models and the dark patterns in system design limited their awareness and comprehension of the privacy risks. Additionally, the human-like interactions encouraged more sensitive disclosures, which complicated users' ability to navigate the trade-offs. We discuss practical design guidelines and the needs for paradigm shifts to protect the privacy of LLM-based CA users.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.11653v2</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3613904.3642385</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Zhiping Zhang, Michelle Jia, Hao-Ping Lee, Bingsheng Yao, Sauvik Das, Ada Lerner, Dakuo Wang, Tianshi Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PatchCURE: Improving Certifiable Robustness, Model Utility, and Computation Efficiency of Adversarial Patch Defenses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.13076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.13076v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: State-of-the-art defenses against adversarial patch attacks can now achieve strong certifiable robustness with a marginal drop in model utility. However, this impressive performance typically comes at the cost of 10-100x more inference-time computation compared to undefended models -- the research community has witnessed an intense three-way trade-off between certifiable robustness, model utility, and computation efficiency. In this paper, we propose a defense framework named PatchCURE to approach this trade-off problem. PatchCURE provides sufficient "knobs" for tuning defense performance and allows us to build a family of defenses: the most robust PatchCURE instance can match the performance of any existing state-of-the-art defense (without efficiency considerations); the most efficient PatchCURE instance has similar inference efficiency as undefended models. Notably, PatchCURE achieves state-of-the-art robustness and utility performance across all different efficiency levels, e.g., 16-23% absolute clean accuracy and certified robust accuracy advantages over prior defenses when requiring computation efficiency to be close to undefended models. The family of PatchCURE defenses enables us to flexibly choose appropriate defenses to satisfy given computation and/or utility constraints in practice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.13076v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chong Xiang, Tong Wu, Sihui Dai, Jonathan Petit, Suman Jana, Prateek Mittal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deciphering the Interplay between Local Differential Privacy, Average Bayesian Privacy, and Maximum Bayesian Privacy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16591v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The swift evolution of machine learning has led to emergence of various definitions of privacy due to the threats it poses to privacy, including the concept of local differential privacy (LDP). Although widely embraced and utilized across numerous domains, this conventional approach to measure privacy still exhibits certain limitations, spanning from failure to prevent inferential disclosure to lack of consideration for the adversary's background knowledge. In this comprehensive study, we introduce Bayesian privacy and delve into the intricate relationship between LDP and its Bayesian counterparts, unveiling novel insights into utility-privacy trade-offs. We introduce a framework that encapsulates both attack and defense strategies, highlighting their interplay and effectiveness. The relationship between LDP and Maximum Bayesian Privacy (MBP) is first revealed, demonstrating that under uniform prior distribution, a mechanism satisfying $\xi$-LDP will satisfy $\xi$-MBP and conversely $\xi$-MBP also confers 2$\xi$-LDP. Our next theoretical contribution are anchored in the rigorous definitions and relationships between Average Bayesian Privacy (ABP) and Maximum Bayesian Privacy (MBP), encapsulated by equations $\epsilon_{p,a} \leq \frac{1}{\sqrt{2}}\sqrt{(\epsilon_{p,m} + \epsilon)\cdot(e^{\epsilon_{p,m} + \epsilon} - 1)}$. These relationships fortify our understanding of the privacy guarantees provided by various mechanisms. Our work not only lays the groundwork for future empirical exploration but also promises to facilitate the design of privacy-preserving algorithms, thereby fostering the development of trustworthy machine learning solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16591v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaojin Zhang, Yulin Fei, Wei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MMCert: Provable Defense against Adversarial Attacks to Multi-modal Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19080</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19080v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Different from a unimodal model whose input is from a single modality, the input (called multi-modal input) of a multi-modal model is from multiple modalities such as image, 3D points, audio, text, etc. Similar to unimodal models, many existing studies show that a multi-modal model is also vulnerable to adversarial perturbation, where an attacker could add small perturbation to all modalities of a multi-modal input such that the multi-modal model makes incorrect predictions for it. Existing certified defenses are mostly designed for unimodal models, which achieve sub-optimal certified robustness guarantees when extended to multi-modal models as shown in our experimental results. In our work, we propose MMCert, the first certified defense against adversarial attacks to a multi-modal model. We derive a lower bound on the performance of our MMCert under arbitrary adversarial attacks with bounded perturbations to both modalities (e.g., in the context of auto-driving, we bound the number of changed pixels in both RGB image and depth image). We evaluate our MMCert using two benchmark datasets: one for the multi-modal road segmentation task and the other for the multi-modal emotion recognition task. Moreover, we compare our MMCert with a state-of-the-art certified defense extended from unimodal models. Our experimental results show that our MMCert outperforms the baseline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19080v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanting Wang, Hongye Fu, Wei Zou, Jinyuan Jia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can LLMs get help from other LLMs without revealing private information?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01041v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Cascades are a common type of machine learning systems in which a large, remote model can be queried if a local model is not able to accurately label a user's data by itself. Serving stacks for large language models (LLMs) increasingly use cascades due to their ability to preserve task performance while dramatically reducing inference costs. However, applying cascade systems in situations where the local model has access to sensitive data constitutes a significant privacy risk for users since such data could be forwarded to the remote model. In this work, we show the feasibility of applying cascade systems in such setups by equipping the local model with privacy-preserving techniques that reduce the risk of leaking private information when querying the remote model. To quantify information leakage in such setups, we introduce two privacy measures. We then propose a system that leverages the recently introduced social learning paradigm in which LLMs collaboratively learn from each other by exchanging natural language. Using this paradigm, we demonstrate on several datasets that our methods minimize the privacy loss while at the same time improving task performance compared to a non-cascade baseline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01041v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Florian Hartmann, Duc-Hieu Tran, Peter Kairouz, Victor C\u{a}rbune, Blaise Aguera y Arcas</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
