<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CR</link>
    <description>cs.CR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 01:48:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Party Private Set Operations from Predicative Zero-Sharing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20050v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Typical protocols in the multi-party private set operations (MPSO) setting enable m &gt; 2 parties to perform certain secure computation on the intersection or union of their private sets, realizing a very limited range of MPSO functionalities. Most works in this field focus on just one or two specific functionalities, resulting in a large variety of isolated schemes and a lack of a unified framework in MPSO research. In this work, we present an MPSO framework, which allows m parties, each holding a set, to securely compute any set formulas (arbitrary compositions of a finite number of binary set operations, including intersection, union and difference) on their private sets. Our framework is highly versatile and can be instantiated to accommodate a broad spectrum of MPSO functionalities. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first framework to achieve such a level of flexibility and generality in MPSO, without relying on generic secure multi-party computation (MPC) techniques.
  Our framework exhibits favorable theoretical and practical performance. The computation and communication complexity scale linearly with the set size n, and it achieves optimal complexity that is on par with the naive solution for widely used functionalities, such as multi-party private set intersection (MPSI), MPSI with cardinality output (MPSI-card), and MPSI with cardinality and sum (MPSI-card-sum), in the standard semi-honest model. Furthermore, the instantiations of our framework mainly from symmetric-key techniques yield efficient protocols for MPSI, MPSI-card, MPSI-card-sum, and multi-party private set union (MPSU), with online performance surpassing or matching the state of the art.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20050v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minglang Dong, Yu Chen, Cong Zhang, Yujie Bai, Yang Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cybersecurity for Autonomous Vehicles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20180v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The increasing adoption of autonomous vehicles is bringing a major shift in the automotive industry. However, as these vehicles become more connected, cybersecurity threats have emerged as a serious concern. Protecting the security and integrity of autonomous systems is essential to prevent malicious activities that can harm passengers, other road users, and the overall transportation network. This paper focuses on addressing the cybersecurity issues in autonomous vehicles by examining the challenges and risks involved, which are important for building a secure future. Since autonomous vehicles depend on the communication between sensors, artificial intelligence, external infrastructure, and other systems, they are exposed to different types of cyber threats. A cybersecurity breach in an autonomous vehicle can cause serious problems, including a loss of public trust and safety. Therefore, it is very important to develop and apply strong cybersecurity measures to support the growth and acceptance of self-driving cars. This paper discusses major cybersecurity challenges like vulnerabilities in software and hardware, risks from wireless communication, and threats through external interfaces. It also reviews existing solutions such as secure software development, intrusion detection systems, cryptographic protocols, and anomaly detection methods. Additionally, the paper highlights the role of regulatory bodies, industry collaborations, and cybersecurity standards in creating a secure environment for autonomous vehicles. Setting clear rules and best practices is necessary for consistent protection across manufacturers and regions. By analyzing the current cybersecurity landscape and suggesting practical countermeasures, this paper aims to contribute to the safe development and public trust of autonomous vehicle technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20180v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sai varun reddy Bhemavarapu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Case Study on the Use of Representativeness Bias as a Defense Against Adversarial Cyber Threats</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20245</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20245v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cyberspace is an ever-evolving battleground involving adversaries seeking to circumvent existing safeguards and defenders aiming to stay one step ahead by predicting and mitigating the next threat. Existing mitigation strategies have focused primarily on solutions that consider software or hardware aspects, often ignoring the human factor. This paper takes a first step towards psychology-informed, active defense strategies, where we target biases that human beings are susceptible to under conditions of uncertainty.
  Using capture-the-flag events, we create realistic challenges that tap into a particular cognitive bias: representativeness. This study finds that this bias can be triggered to thwart hacking attempts and divert hackers into non-vulnerable attack paths. Participants were exposed to two different challenges designed to exploit representativeness biases. One of the representativeness challenges significantly thwarted attackers away from vulnerable attack vectors and onto non-vulnerable paths, signifying an effective bias-based defense mechanism. This work paves the way towards cyber defense strategies that leverage additional human biases to thwart future, sophisticated adversarial attacks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20245v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Briland Hitaj, Grit Denker, Laura Tinnel, Michael McAnally, Bruce DeBruhl, Nathan Bunting, Alex Fafard, Daniel Aaron, Richard D. Roberts, Joshua Lawson, Greg McCain, Dylan Starink</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SA2FE: A Secure, Anonymous, Auditable, and Fair Edge Computing Service Offloading Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20260v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The inclusion of pervasive computing devices in a democratized edge computing ecosystem can significantly expand the capability and coverage of near-end computing for large-scale applications. However, offloading user tasks to heterogeneous and decentralized edge devices comes with the dual risk of both endangered user data security and privacy due to the curious base station or malicious edge servers, and unfair offloading and malicious attacks targeting edge servers from other edge servers and/or users. Existing solutions to edge access control and offloading either rely on "always-on" cloud servers with reduced edge benefits or fail to protect sensitive user service information. To address these challenges, this paper presents SA2FE, a novel framework for edge access control, offloading and accounting. We design a rerandomizable puzzle primitive and a corresponding scheme to protect sensitive service information from eavesdroppers and ensure fair offloading decisions, while a blind token-based scheme safeguards user privacy, prevents double spending, and ensures usage accountability. The security of SA2FE is proved under the Universal Composability framework, and its performance and scalability are demonstrated with implementation on commodity mobile devices and edge servers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20260v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaojian Wang, Huayue Gu, Zhouyu Li, Fangtong Zhou, Ruozhou Yu, Dejun Yang, Guoliang Xue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Virtual Cybersecurity Department for Securing Digital Twins in Water Distribution Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20266v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Digital twins (DTs) help improve real-time monitoring and decision-making in water distribution systems. However, their connectivity makes them easy targets for cyberattacks such as scanning, denial-of-service (DoS), and unauthorized access. Small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) that manage these systems often do not have enough budget or staff to build strong cybersecurity teams. To solve this problem, we present a Virtual Cybersecurity Department (VCD), an affordable and automated framework designed for SMEs. The VCD uses open-source tools like Zabbix for real-time monitoring, Suricata for network intrusion detection, Fail2Ban to block repeated login attempts, and simple firewall settings. To improve threat detection, we also add a machine-learning-based IDS trained on the OD-IDS2022 dataset using an improved ensemble model. This model detects cyber threats such as brute-force attacks, remote code execution (RCE), and network flooding, with 92\% accuracy and fewer false alarms. Our solution gives SMEs a practical and efficient way to secure water systems using low-cost and easy-to-manage tools.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20266v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammadhossein Homaei, Agustin Di Bartolo, Oscar Mogollon-Gutierrez, Fernando Broncano Morgado, Pablo Garcia Rodriguez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smart Water Security with AI and Blockchain-Enhanced Digital Twins</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20275</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20275v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Water distribution systems in rural areas face serious challenges such as a lack of real-time monitoring, vulnerability to cyberattacks, and unreliable data handling. This paper presents an integrated framework that combines LoRaWAN-based data acquisition, a machine learning-driven Intrusion Detection System (IDS), and a blockchain-enabled Digital Twin (BC-DT) platform for secure and transparent water management. The IDS filters anomalous or spoofed data using a Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) Autoencoder and Isolation Forest before validated data is logged via smart contracts on a private Ethereum blockchain using Proof of Authority (PoA) consensus. The verified data feeds into a real-time DT model supporting leak detection, consumption forecasting, and predictive maintenance. Experimental results demonstrate that the system achieves over 80 transactions per second (TPS) with under 2 seconds of latency while remaining cost-effective and scalable for up to 1,000 smart meters. This work demonstrates a practical and secure architecture for decentralized water infrastructure in under-connected rural environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20275v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammadhossein Homaei, Victor Gonzalez Morales, Oscar Mogollon Gutierrez, Ruben Molano Gomez, Andres Caro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SoK: A Survey of Mixing Techniques and Mixers for Cryptocurrencies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20296v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Blockchain technologies have overturned the digital finance industry by introducing a decentralized pseudonymous means of monetary transfer. The pseudonymous nature introduced privacy concerns, enabling various deanonymization techniques, which in turn spurred development of stronger anonymity-preserving measures. The purpose of this paper is to create a comprehensive survey of mixing techniques and implementations within the vast ecosystem surrounding anonymization tools and mechanisms available in blockchain cryptocurrencies. First, we begin by reviewing classifications used in the field. Then, we survey various obfuscation techniques, helping to delve into actual implementations and combinations of these techniques. Next, we identify the positive and negative attributes of the approaches and implementations included. Moreover, we examine the implications of anonymization tools for user privacy, including their effectiveness in preserving anonymity and susceptibility to attacks and vulnerabilities. Finally, we discuss the challenges and innovations for extending mixing services into the realm of smart contracts or cross-chain space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20296v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juraj Mariani, Ivan Homoliak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Leakage Attacks on Searchable Symmetric Encryption Using LLM-Based Synthetic Data Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20414v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Searchable Symmetric Encryption (SSE) enables efficient search capabilities over encrypted data, allowing users to maintain privacy while utilizing cloud storage. However, SSE schemes are vulnerable to leakage attacks that exploit access patterns, search frequency, and volume information. Existing studies frequently assume that adversaries possess a substantial fraction of the encrypted dataset to mount effective inference attacks, implying there is a database leakage of such documents, thus, an assumption that may not hold in real-world scenarios. In this work, we investigate the feasibility of enhancing leakage attacks under a more realistic threat model in which adversaries have access to minimal leaked data. We propose a novel approach that leverages large language models (LLMs), specifically GPT-4 variants, to generate synthetic documents that statistically and semantically resemble the real-world dataset of Enron emails. Using the email corpus as a case study, we evaluate the effectiveness of synthetic data generated via random sampling and hierarchical clustering methods on the performance of the SAP (Search Access Pattern) keyword inference attack restricted to token volumes only. Our results demonstrate that, while the choice of LLM has limited effect, increasing dataset size and employing clustering-based generation significantly improve attack accuracy, achieving comparable performance to attacks using larger amounts of real data. We highlight the growing relevance of LLMs in adversarial contexts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20414v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Chiu, Partha Protim Paul, Zahin Wahab</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Network Attack Traffic Detection With Hybrid Quantum-Enhanced Convolution Neural Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20436v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The emerging paradigm of Quantum Machine Learning (QML) combines features of quantum computing and machine learning (ML). QML enables the generation and recognition of statistical data patterns that classical computers and classical ML methods struggle to effectively execute. QML utilizes quantum systems to enhance algorithmic computation speed and real-time data processing capabilities, making it one of the most promising tools in the field of ML. Quantum superposition and entanglement features also hold the promise to potentially expand the potential feature representation capabilities of ML. Therefore, in this study, we explore how quantum computing affects ML and whether it can further improve the detection performance on network traffic detection, especially on unseen attacks which are types of malicious traffic that do not exist in the ML training dataset. Classical ML models often perform poorly in detecting these unseen attacks because they have not been trained on such traffic. Hence, this paper focuses on designing and proposing novel hybrid structures of Quantum Convolutional Neural Network (QCNN) to achieve the detection of malicious traffic. The detection performance, generalization, and robustness of the QML solutions are evaluated and compared with classical ML running on classical computers. The emphasis lies in assessing whether the QML-based malicious traffic detection outperforms classical solutions. Based on experiment results, QCNN models demonstrated superior performance compared to classical ML approaches on unseen attack detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20436v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zihao Wang, Kar Wai Fok, Vrizlynn L. L. Thing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robustness via Referencing: Defending against Prompt Injection Attacks by Referencing the Executed Instruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20472v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated impressive performance and have come to dominate the field of natural language processing (NLP) across various tasks. However, due to their strong instruction-following capabilities and inability to distinguish between instructions and data content, LLMs are vulnerable to prompt injection attacks. These attacks manipulate LLMs into deviating from the original input instructions and executing maliciously injected instructions within data content, such as web documents retrieved from search engines. Existing defense methods, including prompt-engineering and fine-tuning approaches, typically instruct models to follow the original input instructions while suppressing their tendencies to execute injected instructions. However, our experiments reveal that suppressing instruction-following tendencies is challenging. Through analyzing failure cases, we observe that although LLMs tend to respond to any recognized instructions, they are aware of which specific instructions they are executing and can correctly reference them within the original prompt. Motivated by these findings, we propose a novel defense method that leverages, rather than suppresses, the instruction-following abilities of LLMs. Our approach prompts LLMs to generate responses that include both answers and their corresponding instruction references. Based on these references, we filter out answers not associated with the original input instructions. Comprehensive experiments demonstrate that our method outperforms prompt-engineering baselines and achieves performance comparable to fine-tuning methods, reducing the attack success rate (ASR) to 0 percent in some scenarios. Moreover, our approach has minimal impact on overall utility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20472v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yulin Chen, Haoran Li, Yuan Sui, Yue Liu, Yufei He, Yangqiu Song, Bryan Hooi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sleeping Giants -- Activating Dormant Java Deserialization Gadget Chains through Stealthy Code Changes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20485</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20485v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Java deserialization gadget chains are a well-researched critical software weakness. The vast majority of known gadget chains rely on gadgets from software dependencies. Furthermore, it has been shown that small code changes in dependencies have enabled these gadget chains. This makes gadget chain detection a purely reactive endeavor. Even if one dependency's deployment pipeline employs gadget chain detection, a gadget chain can still result from gadgets in other dependencies. In this work, we assess how likely small code changes are to enable a gadget chain. These changes could either be accidental or intentional as part of a supply chain attack. Specifically, we show that class serializability is a strongly fluctuating property over a dependency's evolution. Then, we investigate three change patterns by which an attacker could stealthily introduce gadgets into a dependency. We apply these patterns to 533 dependencies and run three state-of-the-art gadget chain detectors both on the original and the modified dependencies. The tools detect that applying the modification patterns can activate/inject gadget chains in 26.08% of the dependencies we selected. Finally, we verify the newly detected chains. As such, we identify dormant gadget chains in 53 dependencies that could be added through minor code modifications. This both shows that Java deserialization gadget chains are a broad liability to software and proves dormant gadget chains as a lucrative supply chain attack vector.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20485v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruno Kreyssig, Sabine Houy, Timoth\'ee Riom, Alexandre Bartel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Token-Efficient Prompt Injection Attack: Provoking Cessation in LLM Reasoning via Adaptive Token Compression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20493v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: While reasoning large language models (LLMs) demonstrate remarkable performance across various tasks, they also contain notable security vulnerabilities. Recent research has uncovered a "thinking-stopped" vulnerability in DeepSeek-R1, where model-generated reasoning tokens can forcibly interrupt the inference process, resulting in empty responses that compromise LLM-integrated applications. However, existing methods triggering this vulnerability require complex mathematical word problems with long prompts--even exceeding 5,000 tokens. To reduce the token cost and formally define this vulnerability, we propose a novel prompt injection attack named "Reasoning Interruption Attack", based on adaptive token compression. We demonstrate that simple standalone arithmetic tasks can effectively trigger this vulnerability, and the prompts based on such tasks exhibit simpler logical structures than mathematical word problems. We develop a systematic approach to efficiently collect attack prompts and an adaptive token compression framework that utilizes LLMs to automatically compress these prompts. Experiments show our compression framework significantly reduces prompt length while maintaining effective attack capabilities. We further investigate the attack's performance via output prefix and analyze the underlying causes of the vulnerability, providing valuable insights for improving security in reasoning LLMs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20493v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Cui, Yujun Cai, Yiwei Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Starfish: Rebalancing Multi-Party Off-Chain Payment Channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20536v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Blockchain technology has revolutionized the way transactions are executed, but scalability remains a major challenge. Payment Channel Network (PCN), as a Layer-2 scaling solution, has been proposed to address this issue. However, skewed payments can deplete the balance of one party within a channel, restricting the ability of PCNs to transact through a path and subsequently reducing the transaction success rate. To address this issue, the technology of rebalancing has been proposed. However, existing rebalancing strategies in PCNs are limited in their capacity and efficiency. Cycle-based approaches only address rebalancing within groups of nodes that form a cycle network, while non-cycle-based approaches face high complexity of on-chain operations and limitations on rebalancing capacity. In this study, we propose Starfish, a rebalancing approach that captures the star-shaped network structure to provide high rebalancing efficiency and large channel capacity. Starfish requires only $N$-time on-chain operations to connect independent channels and aggregate the total budget of all channels. To demonstrate the correctness and advantages of our method, we provide a formal security proof of the Starfish protocol and conduct comparative experiments with existing rebalancing techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20536v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minghui Xu, Wenxuan Yu, Guangyong Shang, Guangpeng Qi, Dongliang Duan, Shan Wang, Kun Li, Yue Zhang, Xiuzhen Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mutual Information Minimization for Side-Channel Attack Resistance via Optimal Noise Injection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20556v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Side-channel attacks (SCAs) pose a serious threat to system security by extracting secret keys through physical leakages such as power consumption, timing variations, and electromagnetic emissions. Among existing countermeasures, artificial noise injection is recognized as one of the most effective techniques. However, its high power consumption poses a major challenge for resource-constrained systems such as Internet of Things (IoT) devices, motivating the development of more efficient protection schemes. In this paper, we model SCAs as a communication channel and aim to suppress information leakage by minimizing the mutual information between the secret information and side-channel observations, subject to a power constraint on the artificial noise. We propose an optimal artificial noise injection method to minimize the mutual information in systems with Gaussian inputs. Specifically, we formulate two convex optimization problems: 1) minimizing the total mutual information, and 2) minimizing the maximum mutual information across observations. Numerical results show that the proposed methods significantly reduce both total and maximum mutual information compared to conventional techniques, confirming their effectiveness for resource-constrained, security-critical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20556v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiheon Woo, Daewon Seo, Young-Sik Kim, Namyoon Lee, Yuval Cassuto, Yongjune Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VIMU: Effective Physics-based Realtime Detection and Recovery against Stealthy Attacks on UAVs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20569</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20569v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Sensor attacks on robotic vehicles have become pervasive and manipulative. Their latest advancements exploit sensor and detector characteristics to bypass detection. Recent security efforts have leveraged the physics-based model to detect or mitigate sensor attacks. However, these approaches are only resilient to a few sensor attacks and still need improvement in detection effectiveness. We present VIMU, an efficient sensor attack detection and resilience system for unmanned aerial vehicles. We propose a detection algorithm, CS-EMA, that leverages low-pass filtering to identify stealthy gyroscope attacks while achieving an overall effective sensor attack detection. We develop a fine-grained nonlinear physical model with precise aerodynamic and propulsion wrench modeling. We also augment the state estimation with a FIFO buffer safeguard to mitigate the impact of high-rate IMU attacks. The proposed physical model and buffer safeguard provide an effective system state recovery toward maintaining flight stability. We implement VIMU on PX4 autopilot. The evaluation results demonstrate the effectiveness of VIMU in detecting and mitigating various realistic sensor attacks, especially stealthy attacks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20569v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunbo Wang, Cong Sun, Qiaosen Liu, Bingnan Su, Zongxu Zhang, Michael Norris, Gang Tan, Jianfeng Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReCIT: Reconstructing Full Private Data from Gradient in Parameter-Efficient Fine-Tuning of Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20570v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Parameter-efficient fine-tuning (PEFT) has emerged as a practical solution for adapting large language models (LLMs) to custom datasets with significantly reduced computational cost. When carrying out PEFT under collaborative learning scenarios (e.g., federated learning), it is often required to exchange model updates (or gradients) across parties. These gradients, even with limited dimensions, can cause severe breach of data privacy. Recent works have shown that both contextual prefixes and personally identifiable information (PII) can be exposed through gradients. However, \emph{simultaneously} and \emph{accurately} recovering both components from the same training instance remains infeasible due to the following challenges: 1) limited number of PEFT parameters; 2) high-dimensional token spaces; and 3) large batch sizes. We propose ReCIT, a novel privacy attack that addresses all challenges, and achieves recovery of \emph{full} private data from PEFT gradients with high fidelity. Specifically, ReCIT proposes to enhance the memorization capability of the pre-trained model through malicious fine-tuning with Personal Notes; ReCIT also proposes a novel filter-based token extraction technique and a token pairing mechanism, to accurately reconstruct tokens from the training sequences with large batch sizes. Extensive evaluations show that ReCIT consistently outperforms state-of-the-art gradient inversion and memorization-based attacks across different PEFT paradigms. It achieves up to 10$\times$ higher PII recovery rates and remains effective across varying batch sizes, especially in settings where prefix reconstruction is intractable for conventional approaches. These findings highlight an urgent need to reassess the privacy guarantees of PEFT, especially in decentralized or shared training environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20570v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin Xie, Ruishi He, Songze Li, Xiaojun Jia, Shouling Ji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Hidden Risks of LLM-Generated Web Application Code: A Security-Centric Evaluation of Code Generation Capabilities in Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20612v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The rapid advancement of Large Language Models (LLMs) has enhanced software development processes, minimizing the time and effort required for coding and enhancing developer productivity. However, despite their potential benefits, code generated by LLMs has been shown to generate insecure code in controlled environments, raising critical concerns about their reliability and security in real-world applications. This paper uses predefined security parameters to evaluate the security compliance of LLM-generated code across multiple models, such as ChatGPT, DeepSeek, Claude, Gemini and Grok. The analysis reveals critical vulnerabilities in authentication mechanisms, session management, input validation and HTTP security headers. Although some models implement security measures to a limited extent, none fully align with industry best practices, highlighting the associated risks in automated software development. Our findings underscore that human expertise is crucial to ensure secure software deployment or review of LLM-generated code. Also, there is a need for robust security assessment frameworks to enhance the reliability of LLM-generated code in real-world applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20612v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Swaroop Dora, Deven Lunkad, Naziya Aslam, S. Venkatesan, Sandeep Kumar Shukla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Novel Cipher for Enhancing MAVLink Security: Design, Security Analysis, and Performance Evaluation Using a Drone Testbed</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20626v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present MAVShield, a novel lightweight cipher designed to secure communications in Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAVs) using the MAVLink protocol, which by default transmits unencrypted messages between UAVs and Ground Control Stations (GCS). While existing studies propose encryption for MAVLink, most remain theoretical or simulation-based. We implement MAVShield alongside AES-CTR, ChaCha20, Speck-CTR, and Rabbit, and evaluate them on a real drone testbed. A comprehensive security analysis using statistical test suites (NIST and Diehard) demonstrates strong resistance of the novel cipher to cryptanalysis. Performance evaluation across key metrics including memory usage, CPU load, and battery power consumption, demonstrates that MAVShield outperforms existing algorithms and offers an efficient, real-world solution for securing MAVLink communications in UAVs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20626v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bhavya Dixit, Ananthapadmanabhan A., Adheeba Thahsin, Saketh Pathak, Gaurav S. Kasbekar, Arnab Maity</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Protocol Dialects as Formal Patterns: A Composable Theory of Lingos -- Technical report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20637v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Protocol dialects are methods for modifying protocols that provide light-weight security, especially against easy attacks that can lead to more serious ones. A lingo is a dialect's key security component by making attackers unable to "speak" the lingo. A lingo's "talk" changes all the time, becoming a moving target for attackers. We present several kinds of lingo transformations and compositions to generate stronger lingos from simpler ones, thus making dialects more secure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20637v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V\'ictor Garc\'ia, Santiago Escobar, Catherine Meadows, Jose Meseguer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data Encryption Battlefield: A Deep Dive into the Dynamic Confrontations in Ransomware Attacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20681v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the rapidly evolving landscape of cybersecurity threats, ransomware represents a significant challenge. Attackers increasingly employ sophisticated encryption methods, such as entropy reduction through Base64 encoding, and partial or intermittent encryption to evade traditional detection methods. This study explores the dynamic battle between adversaries who continuously refine encryption strategies and defenders developing advanced countermeasures to protect vulnerable data. We investigate the application of online incremental machine learning algorithms designed to predict file encryption activities despite adversaries evolving obfuscation techniques. Our analysis utilizes an extensive dataset of 32.6 GB, comprising 11,928 files across multiple formats, including Microsoft Word documents (doc), PowerPoint presentations (ppt), Excel spreadsheets (xlsx), image formats (jpg, jpeg, png, tif, gif), PDFs (pdf), audio (mp3), and video (mp4) files. These files were encrypted by 75 distinct ransomware families, facilitating a robust empirical evaluation of machine learning classifiers effectiveness against diverse encryption tactics. Results highlight the Hoeffding Tree algorithms superior incremental learning capability, particularly effective in detecting traditional and AES-Base64 encryption methods employed to lower entropy. Conversely, the Random Forest classifier with warm-start functionality excels at identifying intermittent encryption methods, demonstrating the necessity of tailored machine learning solutions to counter sophisticated ransomware strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20681v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arash Mahboubi, Hamed Aboutorab, Seyit Camtepe, Hang Thanh Bui, Khanh Luong, Keyvan Ansari, Shenlu Wang, Bazara Barry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DICOM Compatible, 3D Multimodality Image Encryption using Hyperchaotic Signal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20689v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Medical image encryption plays an important role in protecting sensitive health information from cyberattacks and unauthorized access. In this paper, we introduce a secure and robust encryption scheme that is multi-modality compatible and works with MRI, CT, X-Ray and Ultrasound images for different anatomical region of interest. The method utilizes hyperchaotic signals and multi-level diffusion methods. The encryption starts by taking DICOM image as input, then padding to increase the image area. Chaotic signals are produced by a logistic map and are used to carry out pixel random permutation. Then, multi-level diffusion is carried out by 4-bit, 8-bit, radial and adjacent diffusion to provide high randomness and immunity against statistical attacks. In addition, we propose a captcha-based authentication scheme to further improve security. An algorithm generates alphanumeric captcha-based image which is encrypted with the same chaotic and diffusion methods as the medical image. Both encrypted images(DICOM image and captcha image) are then superimposed to create a final encrypted output, essentially integrating dual-layer security. Upon decryption, the superimposed image is again decomposed back to original medical and captcha images, and inverse operations are performed to obtain the original unencrypted data. Experimental results show that the proposed method provides strong protection with no loss in image integrity, thereby reducing unauthorized data breaches to a significant level. The dual-encryption approach not only protects the confidentiality of the medical images but also enhances authentication by incorporating captcha.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20689v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anandik N Anand, Sishu Shankar Muni, Abhishek Kaushik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building Trust in Healthcare with Privacy Techniques: Blockchain in the Cloud</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20700v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study introduces a cutting-edge architecture developed for the NewbornTime project, which uses advanced AI to analyze video data at birth and during newborn resuscitation, with the aim of improving newborn care. The proposed architecture addresses the crucial issues of patient consent, data security, and investing trust in healthcare by integrating Ethereum blockchain with cloud computing. Our blockchain-based consent application simplifies patient consent's secure and transparent management. We explain the smart contract mechanisms and privacy measures employed, ensuring data protection while permitting controlled data sharing among authorized parties. This work demonstrates the potential of combining blockchain and cloud technologies in healthcare, emphasizing their role in maintaining data integrity, with implications for computer science and healthcare innovation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20700v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ferhat Ozgur Catak, Chunming Rong, {\O}yvind Meinich-Bache, Sara Brunner, Kjersti Engan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Vulnerability Reports with Automated and Augmented Description Summarization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20726v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Public vulnerability databases, such as the National Vulnerability Database (NVD), document vulnerabilities and facilitate threat information sharing. However, they often suffer from short descriptions and outdated or insufficient information. In this paper, we introduce Zad, a system designed to enrich NVD vulnerability descriptions by leveraging external resources. Zad consists of two pipelines: one collects and filters supplementary data using two encoders to build a detailed dataset, while the other fine-tunes a pre-trained model on this dataset to generate enriched descriptions. By addressing brevity and improving content quality, Zad produces more comprehensive and cohesive vulnerability descriptions. We evaluate Zad using standard summarization metrics and human assessments, demonstrating its effectiveness in enhancing vulnerability information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20726v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hattan Althebeiti, Mohammed Alkinoon, Manar Mohaisen, Saeed Salem, DaeHun Nyang, David Mohaisen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>did:self A registry-less DID method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20767</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20767v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce did:self, a Decentralized Identifier (DID) method that does not depend on any trusted registry for storing the corresponding DID documents. Information for authenticating a did:self subject can be disseminated using any means and without making any security assumption about the delivery method. did:self is lightweight, it allows controlled delegation, it offers increased security and privacy, and it can be used for identifying people, content, as well as IoT devices. Furthermore, DID documents in did:self can be implicit, allowing re-construction of DID documents based on other authentication material, such as JSON Web Tokens and X.509 certificates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20767v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikos Fotiou, George C. Polyzos, Vasilios A. Siris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unlocking User-oriented Pages: Intention-driven Black-box Scanner for Real-world Web Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20801v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Black-box scanners have played a significant role in detecting vulnerabilities for web applications. A key focus in current black-box scanning is increasing test coverage (i.e., accessing more web pages). However, since many web applications are user-oriented, some deep pages can only be accessed through complex user interactions, which are difficult to reach by existing black-box scanners. To fill this gap, a key insight is that web pages contain a wealth of semantic information that can aid in understanding potential user intention. Based on this insight, we propose Hoyen, a black-box scanner that uses the Large Language Model to predict user intention and provide guidance for expanding the scanning scope. Hoyen has been rigorously evaluated on 12 popular open-source web applications and compared with 6 representative tools. The results demonstrate that Hoyen performs a comprehensive exploration of web applications, expanding the attack surface while achieving about 2x than the coverage of other scanners on average, with high request accuracy. Furthermore, Hoyen detected over 90% of its requests towards the core functionality of the application, detecting more vulnerabilities than other scanners, including unique vulnerabilities in well-known web applications. Our data/code is available at https://hoyen.tjunsl.com/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20801v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weizhe Wang, Yao Zhang, Kaitai Liang, Guangquan Xu, Hongpeng Bai, Qingyang Yan, Xi Zheng, Bin Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DP-SMOTE: Integrating Differential Privacy and Oversampling Technique to Preserve Privacy in Smart Homes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20827</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20827v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Smart homes represent intelligent environments where interconnected devices gather information, enhancing users living experiences by ensuring comfort, safety, and efficient energy management. To enhance the quality of life, companies in the smart device industry collect user data, including activities, preferences, and power consumption. However, sharing such data necessitates privacy-preserving practices. This paper introduces a robust method for secure sharing of data to service providers, grounded in differential privacy (DP). This empowers smart home residents to contribute usage statistics while safeguarding their privacy. The approach incorporates the Synthetic Minority Oversampling technique (SMOTe) and seamlessly integrates Gaussian noise to generate synthetic data, enabling data and statistics sharing while preserving individual privacy. The proposed method employs the SMOTe algorithm and applies Gaussian noise to generate data. Subsequently, it employs a k-anonymity function to assess reidentification risk before sharing the data. The simulation outcomes demonstrate that our method delivers strong performance in safeguarding privacy and in accuracy, recall, and f-measure metrics. This approach is particularly effective in smart homes, offering substantial utility in privacy at a reidentification risk of 30%, with Gaussian noise set to 0.3, SMOTe at 500%, and the application of a k-anonymity function with k = 2. Additionally, it shows a high classification accuracy, ranging from 90% to 98%, across various classification techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20827v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.58675/2636-3305.1669</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Amr Tarek Elsayed, Almohammady Sobhi Alsharkawy, Mohamed Sayed Farag, Shaban Ebrahim Abu Yusuf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dual Explanations via Subgraph Matching for Malware Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20904v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Interpretable malware detection is crucial for understanding harmful behaviors and building trust in automated security systems. Traditional explainable methods for Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) often highlight important regions within a graph but fail to associate them with known benign or malicious behavioral patterns. This limitation reduces their utility in security contexts, where alignment with verified prototypes is essential. In this work, we introduce a novel dual prototype-driven explainable framework that interprets GNN-based malware detection decisions. This dual explainable framework integrates a base explainer (a state-of-the-art explainer) with a novel second-level explainer which is designed by subgraph matching technique, called SubMatch explainer. The proposed explainer assigns interpretable scores to nodes based on their association with matched subgraphs, offering a fine-grained distinction between benign and malicious regions. This prototype-guided scoring mechanism enables more interpretable, behavior-aligned explanations. Experimental results demonstrate that our method preserves high detection performance while significantly improving interpretability in malware analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20904v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hossein Shokouhinejad, Roozbeh Razavi-Far, Griffin Higgins, Ali A. Ghorbani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GiBy: A Giant-Step Baby-Step Classifier For Anomaly Detection In Industrial Control Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20906v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The continuous monitoring of the interactions between cyber-physical components of any industrial control system (ICS) is required to secure automation of the system controls, and to guarantee plant processes are fail-safe and remain in an acceptably safe state. Safety is achieved by managing actuation (where electric signals are used to trigger physical movement), dependent on corresponding sensor readings; used as ground truth in decision making. Timely detection of anomalies (attacks, faults and unascertained states) in ICSs is crucial for the safe running of a plant, the safety of its personnel, and for the safe provision of any services provided. We propose an anomaly detection method that involves accurate linearization of the non-linear forms arising from sensor-actuator(s) relationships, primarily because solving linear models is easier and well understood. Further, the time complexity of the anomaly detection scenario/problem at hand is lowered using dimensionality reduction of the actuator(s) in relationship with a sensor. We accomplish this by using a well-known water treatment testbed as a use case. Our experiments show millisecond time response to detect anomalies and provide explainability; that are not simultaneously achieved by other state of the art AI/ML models with eXplainable AI (XAI) used for the same purpose. Further, we pin-point the sensor(s) and its actuation state for which anomaly was detected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20906v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sarad Venugopalan, Sridhar Adepu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bipartite Randomized Response Mechanism for Local Differential Privacy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20926</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20926v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With the increasing importance of data privacy, Local Differential Privacy (LDP) has recently become a strong measure of privacy for protecting each user's privacy from data analysts without relying on a trusted third party. In many cases, both data providers and data analysts hope to maximize the utility of released data. In this paper, we study the fundamental trade-off formulated as a constrained optimization problem: maximizing data utility subject to the constraint of LDP budgets. In particular, the Generalized Randomized Response (GRR) treats all discrete data equally except for the true data. For this, we introduce an adaptive LDP mechanism called Bipartite Randomized Response (BRR), which solves the above privacy-utility maximization problem from the global standpoint. We prove that for any utility function and any privacy level, solving the maximization problem is equivalent to confirming how many high-utility data to be treated equally as the true data on release probability, the outcome of which gives the optimal randomized response. Further, solving this linear program can be computationally cheap in theory. Several examples of utility functions defined by distance metrics and applications in decision trees and deep learning are presented. The results of various experiments show that our BRR significantly outperforms the state-of-the-art LDP mechanisms of both continuous and distributed types.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20926v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shun Zhang, Hai Zhu, Zhili Chen, Neal N. Xiong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal-DP: Differential Privacy on Riemannian Manifolds via Conformal Transformation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20941</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20941v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Differential Privacy (DP) has been established as a safeguard for private data sharing by adding perturbations to information release. Prior research on DP has extended beyond data in the flat Euclidean space and addressed data on curved manifolds, e.g., diffusion tensor MRI, social networks, or organ shape analysis, by adding perturbations along geodesic distances. However, existing manifold-aware DP methods rely on the assumption that samples are uniformly distributed across the manifold. In reality, data densities vary, leading to a biased noise imbalance across manifold regions, weakening the privacy-utility trade-offs. To address this gap, we propose a novel mechanism: Conformal-DP, utilizing conformal transformations on the Riemannian manifold to equalize local sample density and to redefine geodesic distances accordingly while preserving the intrinsic geometry of the manifold. Our theoretical analysis yields two main results. First, we prove that the conformal factor computed from local kernel-density estimates is explicitly data-density-aware; Second, under the conformal metric, the mechanism satisfies $ \varepsilon $-differential privacy on any complete Riemannian manifold and admits a closed-form upper bound on the expected geodesic error that depends only on the maximal density ratio, not on global curvatureof the manifold. Our experimental results validate that the mechanism achieves high utility while providing the $ \varepsilon $-DP guarantee for both homogeneous and especially heterogeneous manifold data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20941v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>stat.OT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peilin He, Liou Tang, M. Amin Rahimian, James Joshi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ACE: A Security Architecture for LLM-Integrated App Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20984v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: LLM-integrated app systems extend the utility of Large Language Models (LLMs) with third-party apps that are invoked by a system LLM using interleaved planning and execution phases to answer user queries. These systems introduce new attack vectors where malicious apps can cause integrity violation of planning or execution, availability breakdown, or privacy compromise during execution.
  In this work, we identify new attacks impacting the integrity of planning, as well as the integrity and availability of execution in LLM-integrated apps, and demonstrate them against IsolateGPT, a recent solution designed to mitigate attacks from malicious apps. We propose Abstract-Concrete-Execute (ACE), a new secure architecture for LLM-integrated app systems that provides security guarantees for system planning and execution. Specifically, ACE decouples planning into two phases by first creating an abstract execution plan using only trusted information, and then mapping the abstract plan to a concrete plan using installed system apps. We verify that the plans generated by our system satisfy user-specified secure information flow constraints via static analysis on the structured plan output. During execution, ACE enforces data and capability barriers between apps, and ensures that the execution is conducted according to the trusted abstract plan. We show experimentally that our system is secure against attacks from the INJECAGENT benchmark, a standard benchmark for control flow integrity in the face of indirect prompt injection attacks, and our newly introduced attacks. Our architecture represents a significant advancement towards hardening LLM-based systems containing system facilities of varying levels of trustworthiness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20984v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evan Li, Tushin Mallick, Evan Rose, William Robertson, Alina Oprea, Cristina Nita-Rotaru</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Dark Side of Digital Twins: Adversarial Attacks on AI-Driven Water Forecasting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20295v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Digital twins (DTs) are improving water distribution systems by using real-time data, analytics, and prediction models to optimize operations. This paper presents a DT platform designed for a Spanish water supply network, utilizing Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) networks to predict water consumption. However, machine learning models are vulnerable to adversarial attacks, such as the Fast Gradient Sign Method (FGSM) and Projected Gradient Descent (PGD). These attacks manipulate critical model parameters, injecting subtle distortions that degrade forecasting accuracy. To further exploit these vulnerabilities, we introduce a Learning Automata (LA) and Random LA-based approach that dynamically adjusts perturbations, making adversarial attacks more difficult to detect. Experimental results show that this approach significantly impacts prediction reliability, causing the Mean Absolute Percentage Error (MAPE) to rise from 26% to over 35%. Moreover, adaptive attack strategies amplify this effect, highlighting cybersecurity risks in AI-driven DTs. These findings emphasize the urgent need for robust defenses, including adversarial training, anomaly detection, and secure data pipelines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20295v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammadhossein Homaei, Victor Gonzalez Morales, Oscar Mogollon-Gutierrez, Andres Caro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Cryptographic Perspective on Mitigation vs. Detection in Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20310</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20310v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we initiate a cryptographically inspired theoretical study of detection versus mitigation of adversarial inputs produced by attackers of Machine Learning algorithms during inference time.
  We formally define defense by detection (DbD) and defense by mitigation (DbM). Our definitions come in the form of a 3-round protocol between two resource-bounded parties: a trainer/defender and an attacker. The attacker aims to produce inference-time inputs that fool the training algorithm. We define correctness, completeness, and soundness properties to capture successful defense at inference time while not degrading (too much) the performance of the algorithm on inputs from the training distribution.
  We first show that achieving DbD and achieving DbM are equivalent for ML classification tasks. Surprisingly, this is not the case for ML generative learning tasks, where there are many possible correct outputs that can be generated for each input. We show a separation between DbD and DbM by exhibiting a generative learning task for which is possible to defend by mitigation but is provably impossible to defend by detection under the assumption that the Identity-Based Fully Homomorphic Encryption (IB-FHE), publicly-verifiable zero-knowledge Succinct Non-Interactive Arguments of Knowledge (zk-SNARK) and Strongly Unforgeable Signatures exist. The mitigation phase uses significantly fewer samples than the initial training algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20310v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Greg Gluch, Shafi Goldwasser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SoK: Enhancing Privacy-Preserving Software Development from a Developers' Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20350v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In software development, privacy preservation has become essential with the rise of privacy concerns and regulations such as GDPR and CCPA. While several tools, guidelines, methods, methodologies, and frameworks have been proposed to support developers embedding privacy into software applications, most of them are proofs-of-concept without empirical evaluations, making their practical applicability uncertain. These solutions should be evaluated for different types of scenarios (e.g., industry settings such as rapid software development environments, teams with different privacy knowledge, etc.) to determine what their limitations are in various industry settings and what changes are required to refine current solutions before putting them into industry and developing new developer-supporting approaches. For that, a thorough review of empirically evaluated current solutions will be very effective. However, the existing secondary studies that examine the available developer support provide broad overviews but do not specifically analyze empirically evaluated solutions and their limitations. Therefore, this Systematic Literature Review (SLR) aims to identify and analyze empirically validated solutions that are designed to help developers in privacy-preserving software development. The findings will provide valuable insights for researchers to improve current privacy-preserving solutions and for practitioners looking for effective and validated solutions to embed privacy into software development.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20350v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tharaka Wijesundara, Matthew Warren, Nalin Asanka Gamagedara Arachchilage</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inception: Jailbreak the Memory Mechanism of Text-to-Image Generation Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20376v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Currently, the memory mechanism has been widely and successfully exploited in online text-to-image (T2I) generation systems ($e.g.$, DALL$\cdot$E 3) for alleviating the growing tokenization burden and capturing key information in multi-turn interactions. Despite its practicality, its security analyses have fallen far behind. In this paper, we reveal that this mechanism exacerbates the risk of jailbreak attacks. Different from previous attacks that fuse the unsafe target prompt into one ultimate adversarial prompt, which can be easily detected or may generate non-unsafe images due to under- or over-optimization, we propose Inception, the first multi-turn jailbreak attack against the memory mechanism in real-world text-to-image generation systems. Inception embeds the malice at the inception of the chat session turn by turn, leveraging the mechanism that T2I generation systems retrieve key information in their memory. Specifically, Inception mainly consists of two modules. It first segments the unsafe prompt into chunks, which are subsequently fed to the system in multiple turns, serving as pseudo-gradients for directive optimization. Specifically, we develop a series of segmentation policies that ensure the images generated are semantically consistent with the target prompt. Secondly, after segmentation, to overcome the challenge of the inseparability of minimum unsafe words, we propose recursion, a strategy that makes minimum unsafe words subdivisible. Collectively, segmentation and recursion ensure that all the request prompts are benign but can lead to malicious outcomes. We conduct experiments on the real-world text-to-image generation system ($i.e.$, DALL$\cdot$E 3) to validate the effectiveness of Inception. The results indicate that Inception surpasses the state-of-the-art by a 14\% margin in attack success rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20376v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiqian Zhao, Jiayang Liu, Yiming Li, Runyi Hu, Xiaojun Jia, Wenshu Fan, Xinfeng Li, Jie Zhang, Wei Dong, Tianwei Zhang, Luu Anh Tuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Algebraic Approach to Asymmetric Delegation and Polymorphic Label Inference (Technical Report)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20432v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Language-based information flow control (IFC) enables reasoning about and enforcing security policies in decentralized applications. While information flow properties are relatively extensional and compositional, designing expressive systems that enforce such properties remains challenging. In particular, it can be difficult to use IFC labels to model certain security assumptions, such as semi-honest agents.
  Motivated by these modeling limitations, we study the algebraic semantics of lattice-based IFC label models, and propose a semantic framework that allows formalizing asymmetric delegation, which is partial delegation of confidentiality or integrity. Our framework supports downgrading of information and ensures their safety through nonmalleable information flow (NMIF).
  To demonstrate the practicality of our framework, we design and implement a novel algorithm that statically checks NMIF and a label inference procedure that efficiently supports bounded label polymorphism, allowing users to write code generic with respect to labels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20432v1</guid>
      <category>cs.PL</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Silei Ren, Co\c{s}ku Acay, Andrew C. Myers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TriniMark: A Robust Generative Speech Watermarking Method for Trinity-Level Attribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20532v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The emergence of diffusion models has facilitated the generation of speech with reinforced fidelity and naturalness. While deepfake detection technologies have manifested the ability to identify AI-generated content, their efficacy decreases as generative models become increasingly sophisticated. Furthermore, current research in the field has not adequately addressed the necessity for robust watermarking to safeguard the intellectual property rights associated with synthetic speech and generative models. To remedy this deficiency, we propose a \textbf{ro}bust generative \textbf{s}peech wat\textbf{e}rmarking method (TriniMark) for authenticating the generated content and safeguarding the copyrights by enabling the traceability of the diffusion model. We first design a structure-lightweight watermark encoder that embeds watermarks into the time-domain features of speech and reconstructs the waveform directly. A temporal-aware gated convolutional network is meticulously designed in the watermark decoder for bit-wise watermark recovery. Subsequently, the waveform-guided fine-tuning strategy is proposed for fine-tuning the diffusion model, which leverages the transferability of watermarks and enables the diffusion model to incorporate watermark knowledge effectively. When an attacker trains a surrogate model using the outputs of the target model, the embedded watermark can still be learned by the surrogate model and correctly extracted. Comparative experiments with state-of-the-art methods demonstrate the superior robustness of our method, particularly in countering compound attacks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20532v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yue Li, Weizhi Liu, Dongdong Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient patient-centric EMR sharing block tree</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20544</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20544v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Flexible sharing of electronic medical records (EMRs) is an urgent need in healthcare, as fragmented storage creates EMR management complexity for both practitioners and patients. Blockchain has emerged as a promising solution to address the limitations of centralized EMR systems regarding interoperability, data ownership, and trust concerns. Whilst its healthcare implementation continues to face scalability challenges, particularly in uploading lag time as EMR volumes increase. In this paper, we describe the design of a novel blockchain-based data structure, MedBlockTree, which aims to solve the scalability issue in blockchain-based EMR systems, particularly low block throughput and patient awareness. MedBlockTree leverages a chameleon hash function to generate collision blocks for existing patients and expand a single chain into a growing block tree with $n$ branches that are capable of processing $n$ new blocks in a single consensus round. We also introduce the EnhancedPro consensus algorithm to manage multiple branches and maintain network consistency. Our comprehensive simulation evaluates performance across four dimensions: branch number, worker number, collision rate, and network latency. Comparative analysis against a traditional blockchain-based EMR system demonstrates outstanding throughput improvements across all dimensions, achieving processing speeds $\nu\cdot n$ times faster than conventional approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20544v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaohan Hu, Jyoti Sahni, Colin R. Simpson, Normalia Samian, Winston K. G. Seah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secure Coding with AI, From Creation to Inspection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20814v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: While prior studies have explored security in code generated by ChatGPT and other Large Language Models, they were conducted in controlled experimental settings and did not use code generated or provided from actual developer interactions. This paper not only examines the security of code generated by ChatGPT based on real developer interactions, curated in the DevGPT dataset, but also assesses ChatGPT's capability to find and fix these vulnerabilities. We analysed 1,586 C, C++, and C# code snippets using static scanners, which detected potential issues in 124 files. After manual analysis, we selected 26 files with 32 confirmed vulnerabilities for further investigation.
  We submitted these files to ChatGPT via the OpenAI API, asking it to detect security issues, identify the corresponding Common Weakness Enumeration numbers, and propose fixes. The responses and modified code were manually reviewed and re-scanned for vulnerabilities. ChatGPT successfully detected 18 out of 32 security issues and resolved 17 issues but failed to recognize or fix the remainder. Interestingly, only 10 vulnerabilities were resulted from the user prompts, while 22 were introduced by ChatGPT itself.
  We highlight for developers that code generated by ChatGPT is more likely to contain vulnerabilities compared to their own code. Furthermore, at times ChatGPT reports incorrect information with apparent confidence, which may mislead less experienced developers. Our findings confirm previous studies in demonstrating that ChatGPT is not sufficiently reliable for generating secure code nor identifying all vulnerabilities, highlighting the continuing importance of static scanners and manual review.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20814v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladislav Belozerov, Peter J Barclay, Ashkan Sami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mitigating the Structural Bias in Graph Adversarial Defenses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20848v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In recent years, graph neural networks (GNNs) have shown great potential in addressing various graph structure-related downstream tasks. However, recent studies have found that current GNNs are susceptible to malicious adversarial attacks. Given the inevitable presence of adversarial attacks in the real world, a variety of defense methods have been proposed to counter these attacks and enhance the robustness of GNNs. Despite the commendable performance of these defense methods, we have observed that they tend to exhibit a structural bias in terms of their defense capability on nodes with low degree (i.e., tail nodes), which is similar to the structural bias of traditional GNNs on nodes with low degree in the clean graph. Therefore, in this work, we propose a defense strategy by including hetero-homo augmented graph construction, $k$NN augmented graph construction, and multi-view node-wise attention modules to mitigate the structural bias of GNNs against adversarial attacks. Notably, the hetero-homo augmented graph consists of removing heterophilic links (i.e., links connecting nodes with dissimilar features) globally and adding homophilic links (i.e., links connecting nodes with similar features) for nodes with low degree. To further enhance the defense capability, an attention mechanism is adopted to adaptively combine the representations from the above two kinds of graph views. We conduct extensive experiments to demonstrate the defense and debiasing effect of the proposed strategy on benchmark datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20848v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junyuan Fang, Huimin Liu, Han Yang, Jiajing Wu, Zibin Zheng, Chi K. Tse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying the Noise of Structural Perturbations on Graph Adversarial Attacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20869v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Graph neural networks have been widely utilized to solve graph-related tasks because of their strong learning power in utilizing the local information of neighbors. However, recent studies on graph adversarial attacks have proven that current graph neural networks are not robust against malicious attacks. Yet much of the existing work has focused on the optimization objective based on attack performance to obtain (near) optimal perturbations, but paid less attention to the strength quantification of each perturbation such as the injection of a particular node/link, which makes the choice of perturbations a black-box model that lacks interpretability. In this work, we propose the concept of noise to quantify the attack strength of each adversarial link. Furthermore, we propose three attack strategies based on the defined noise and classification margins in terms of single and multiple steps optimization. Extensive experiments conducted on benchmark datasets against three representative graph neural networks demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed attack strategies. Particularly, we also investigate the preferred patterns of effective adversarial perturbations by analyzing the corresponding properties of the selected perturbation nodes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20869v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junyuan Fang, Han Yang, Haixian Wen, Jiajing Wu, Zibin Zheng, Chi K. Tse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Capacity Bounds for PIR on Graph and Multigraph-Based Replicated Storage</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20888v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the problem of private information retrieval (PIR) in both graph-based and multigraph-based replication systems, where each file is stored on exactly two servers, and any pair of servers shares at most $r$ files. We derive upper bounds on the PIR capacity for such systems and construct PIR schemes that approach these bounds. For graph-based systems, we determine the exact PIR capacity for path graphs and improve upon existing results for complete bipartite graphs and complete graphs. For multigraph-based systems, we propose a PIR scheme that leverages the symmetry of the underlying graph-based construction, yielding a capacity lower bound for such multigraphs. Furthermore, we establish several general upper and lower bounds on the PIR capacity of multigraphs, which are tight in certain cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20888v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiangliang Kong, Shreya Meel, Thomas Jacob Maranzatto, Itzhak Tamo, Sennur Ulukus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DejaVuzz: Disclosing Transient Execution Bugs with Dynamic Swappable Memory and Differential Information Flow Tracking assisted Processor Fuzzing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20934</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20934v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Transient execution vulnerabilities have emerged as a critical threat to modern processors. Hardware fuzzing testing techniques have recently shown promising results in discovering transient execution bugs in large-scale out-of-order processor designs. However, their poor microarchitectural controllability and observability prevent them from effectively and efficiently detecting transient execution vulnerabilities.
  This paper proposes DejaVuzz, a novel pre-silicon stage processor transient execution bug fuzzer. DejaVuzz utilizes two innovative operating primitives: dynamic swappable memory and differential information flow tracking, enabling more effective and efficient transient execution vulnerability detection. The dynamic swappable memory enables the isolation of different instruction streams within the same address space. Leveraging this capability, DejaVuzz generates targeted training for arbitrary transient windows and eliminates ineffective training, enabling efficient triggering of diverse transient windows. The differential information flow tracking aids in observing the propagation of sensitive data across the microarchitecture. Based on taints, DejaVuzz designs the taint coverage matrix to guide mutation and uses taint liveness annotations to identify exploitable leakages. Our evaluation shows that DejaVuzz outperforms the state-of-the-art fuzzer SpecDoctor, triggering more comprehensive transient windows with lower training overhead and achieving a 4.7x coverage improvement. And DejaVuzz also mitigates control flow over-tainting with acceptable overhead and identifies 5 previously undiscovered transient execution vulnerabilities (with 6 CVEs assigned) on BOOM and XiangShan.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20934v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinyan Xu, Yangye Zhou, Xingzhi Zhang, Yinshuai Li, Qinhan Tan, Yinqian Zhang, Yajin Zhou, Rui Chang, Wenbo Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A multi-language toolkit for the semi-automated checking of research outputs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02935</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.02935v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article presents a free and open source toolkit that supports the semi-automated checking of research outputs (SACRO) for privacy disclosure within secure data environments. SACRO is a framework that applies best-practice principles-based statistical disclosure control (SDC) techniques on-the-fly as researchers conduct their analyses. SACRO is designed to assist human checkers rather than seeking to replace them as with current automated rules-based approaches. The toolkit is composed of a lightweight Python package that sits over well-known analysis tools that produce outputs such as tables, plots, and statistical models. This package adds functionality to (i) automatically identify potentially disclosive outputs against a range of commonly used disclosure tests; (ii) apply optional disclosure mitigation strategies as requested; (iii) report reasons for applying SDC; and (iv) produce simple summary documents trusted research environment staff can use to streamline their workflow and maintain auditable records. This creates an explicit change in the dynamics so that SDC is something done with researchers rather than to them, and enables more efficient communication with checkers. A graphical user interface supports human checkers by displaying the requested output and results of the checks in an immediately accessible format, highlighting identified issues, potential mitigation options, and tracking decisions made. The major analytical programming languages used by researchers (Python, R, and Stata) are supported by providing front-end packages that interface with the core Python back-end. Source code, packages, and documentation are available under MIT license at https://github.com/AI-SDC/ACRO</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.02935v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Richard J. Preen, Maha Albashir, Simon Davy, Jim Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twin Auto-Encoder Model for Learning Separable Representation in Cyberattack Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15509</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15509v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Representation learning (RL) methods for cyberattack detection face the diversity and sophistication of attack data, leading to the issue of mixed representations of different classes, particularly as the number of classes increases. To address this, the paper proposes a novel deep learning architecture/model called the Twin Auto-Encoder (TAE). TAE first maps the input data into latent space and then deterministically shifts data samples of different classes further apart to create separable data representations, referred to as representation targets. TAE's decoder then projects the input data into these representation targets. After training, TAE's decoder extracts data representations. TAE's representation target serves as a novel dynamic codeword, which refers to the vector that represents a specific class. This vector is updated after each training epoch for every data sample, in contrast to the conventional fixed codeword that does not incorporate information from the input data. We conduct extensive experiments on diverse cybersecurity datasets, including seven IoT botnet datasets, two network IDS datasets, three malware datasets, one cloud DDoS dataset, and ten artificial datasets as the number of classes increases. TAE boosts accuracy and F-score in attack detection by around 2% compared to state-of-the-art models, achieving up to 96.1% average accuracy in IoT attack detection. Additionally, TAE is well-suited for cybersecurity applications and potentially for IoT systems, with a model size of approximately 1 MB and an average running time of around 2.6E-07 seconds for extracting a data sample.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15509v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Phai Vu Dinh, Quang Uy Nguyen, Thai Hoang Dinh, Diep N. Nguyen, Bao Son Pham, Eryk Dutkiewicz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An average case efficient algorithm for solving two variable linear diophantine equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14052v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Solving two variable linear Diophantine equations has application in many cryptographic protocols such as RSA and Elliptic curve cryptography. The Extended Euclid's algorithm is the most widely used algorithm to solve these equations. We revisit two algorithms to solve two variable linear Diophantine equations. For one of those, we do a fine-grained analysis of the number of recursive calls and arrive at a periodic function that represents the number of recursive calls. We find the period and use it to derive an accurate closed-form expression for the average number of recursive calls incurred by that algorithm. We find multiple loose upper bounds on the average number of recursive calls in different cases based on whether a solution exists or not. If we know that for a fixed value of $a,b$ and a varying $c$, an equation $ax+by=c$ (where $a&gt;b$) is solvable, then we can find the solution in $O\left(\frac{\log b}{gcd(a,b)}\right)$ average number of recursion or steps. We computationally evaluate this bound as well as one more upper bound and compare them with the average number of recursive calls in Extended Euclid's algorithm on a number of random $ n$-bit inputs. We observe that the average number of iterations in the analyzed algorithm decreases with an increase in $gcd(a,b)$. We propose an iterative version of the algorithm. We implement this algorithm and find that the average number of iterations by our algorithm is less than that of two existing algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14052v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mayank Deora, Pinakpani Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unmasking the Shadows: Pinpoint the Implementations of Anti-Dynamic Analysis Techniques in Malware Using LLM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05982</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05982v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Sandboxes and other dynamic analysis processes are prevalent in malware detection systems nowadays to enhance the capability of detecting 0-day malware. Therefore, techniques of anti-dynamic analysis (TADA) are prevalent in modern malware samples, and sandboxes can suffer from false negatives and analysis failures when analyzing the samples with TADAs. In such cases, human reverse engineers will get involved in conducting dynamic analysis manually (i.e., debugging, patching), which in turn also gets obstructed by TADAs. In this work, we propose a Large Language Model (LLM) based workflow that can pinpoint the location of the TADA implementation in the code, to help reverse engineers place breakpoints used in debugging. Our evaluation shows that we successfully identified the locations of 87.80% known TADA implementations adopted from public repositories. In addition, we successfully pinpoint the locations of TADAs in 4 well-known malware samples that are documented in online malware analysis blogs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05982v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haizhou Wang, Nanqing Luo, Xusheng Li, Peng LIu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Verification of Control Flow Attestation Evidence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10855</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10855v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Remote run-time attestation methods, including Control Flow Attestation (CFA) and Data Flow Attestation (DFA), have been proposed to generate precise evidence of execution's control flow path (in CFA) and optionally execution data inputs (in DFA) on a remote and potentially compromised embedded device, hereby referred to as a Prover (Prv). Recent advances in run-time attestation architectures are also able to guarantee that a remote Verifier (Vrf) reliably receives this evidence from Prv, even when Prv's software state is fully compromised. This, in theory, enables secure "run-time auditing" in addition to best-effort attestation, i.e., it guarantees that Vrf can examine execution evidence to identify previously unknown compromises as soon as they are exploited, pinpoint their root cause(s), and remediate them. However, prior work has for the most part focused on securely implementing Prv's root of trust (responsible for generating authentic run-time evidence), leaving Vrf 's perspective in this security service unexplored. In this work, we argue that run-time attestation and auditing are only truly useful if Vrf can effectively analyze received evidence. From this premise, we characterize different types of evidence produced by existing run-time attestation/auditing architectures in terms of Vrf 's ability to detect and remediate (previously unknown) vulnerabilities. As a case study for practical uses of run-time evidence by Vrf, we propose SABRE: a Security Analysis and Binary Repair Engine. SABRE showcases how Vrf can systematically leverage run-time evidence to detect control flow attacks, pinpoint corrupted control data and specific instructions used to corrupt them, and leverage this evidence to automatically generate binary patches to buffer overflow and use-after-free vulnerabilities without source code knowledge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10855v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam Caulfield, Norrathep Rattanavipanon, Ivan De Oliveira Nunes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Verified Foundations for Differential Privacy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.01671v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Differential privacy (DP) has become the gold standard for privacy-preserving data analysis, but implementing it correctly has proven challenging. Prior work has focused on verifying DP at a high level, assuming the foundations are correct and a perfect source of randomness is available. However, the underlying theory of differential privacy can be very complex and subtle. Flaws in basic mechanisms and random number generation have been a critical source of vulnerabilities in real-world DP systems.
  In this paper, we present SampCert, the first comprehensive, mechanized foundation for differential privacy. SampCert is written in Lean with over 12,000 lines of proof. It offers a generic and extensible notion of DP, a framework for constructing and composing DP mechanisms, and formally verified implementations of Laplace and Gaussian sampling algorithms. SampCert provides (1) a mechanized foundation for developing the next generation of differentially private algorithms, and (2) mechanically verified primitives that can be deployed in production systems. Indeed, SampCert's verified algorithms power the DP offerings of Amazon Web Services (AWS), demonstrating its real-world impact.
  SampCert's key innovations include: (1) A generic DP foundation that can be instantiated for various DP definitions (e.g., pure, concentrated, R\'enyi DP); (2) formally verified discrete Laplace and Gaussian sampling algorithms that avoid the pitfalls of floating-point implementations; and (3) a simple probability monad and novel proof techniques that streamline the formalization. To enable proving complex correctness properties of DP and random number generation, SampCert makes heavy use of Lean's extensive Mathlib library, leveraging theorems in Fourier analysis, measure and probability theory, number theory, and topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.01671v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Markus de Medeiros, Muhammad Naveed, Tancr\`ede Lepoint, Temesghen Kahsai, Tristan Ravitch, Stefan Zetzsche, Anjali Joshi, Joseph Tassarotti, Aws Albarghouthi, Jean-Baptiste Tristan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Overview of Cyber Security Funding for Open Source Software</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05887v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Context: Many open source software (OSS) projects need more human resources for maintenance, improvements, and sometimes even their survival. This need allegedly applies even to vital OSS projects that can be seen as being a part of the world's critical infrastructures. To address this resourcing problem, new funding instruments for OSS projects have been established in recent years. Objectives: The paper examines two such funding bodies for OSS and the projects they have funded. The focus of both funding bodies is on software security and cyber security in general. Methods: The methodology is based on qualitative thematic analysis. Results: Particularly OSS supply chains, network and cryptography libraries, programming languages, and operating systems and their low-level components have been funded and thus seen as critical in terms of cyber security by the two funding bodies. Conclusions: In addition to the qualitative results presented, the paper makes a contribution by connecting the research branches of critical infrastructure and sustainability of OSS projects. A further contribution is made by connecting the topic examined to recent cyber security regulations. Finally, an important argument is raised that neither cyber security nor sustainability alone can entirely explain the rationales behind the funding decisions made by the two bodies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05887v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jukka Ruohonen, Gaurav Choudhary, Adam Alami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Double Spending Analysis of Nakamoto Consensus for Time-Varying Mining Rates with Ruin Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18599v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Theoretical guarantees for double spending probabilities for the Nakamoto consensus under the $k$-deep confirmation rule have been extensively studied for zero/bounded network delays and fixed mining rates. In this paper, we introduce a ruin-theoretical model of double spending for Nakamoto consensus under the $k$-deep confirmation rule when the honest mining rate is allowed to be an arbitrary function of time including the block delivery periods, i.e., time periods during which mined blocks are being delivered to all other participants of the network. Time-varying mining rates are considered to capture the intrinsic characteristics of the peer to peer network delays as well as dynamic participation of miners such as the gap game and switching between different cryptocurrencies. Ruin theory is leveraged to obtain the double spend probabilities and numerical examples are presented to validate the effectiveness of the proposed analytical method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18599v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mustafa Doger, Sennur Ulukus, Nail Akar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Nonlinear Filter Model of Stream Cipher Redivivus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01110v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The nonlinear filter model is an old and well understood approach to the design of secure stream ciphers. Extensive research over several decades has shown how to attack stream ciphers based on this model and has identified the security properties required of the Boolean function used as the filtering function to resist such attacks. This led to the problem of constructing Boolean functions which provide adequate security \textit{and} at the same time are efficient to implement. Unfortunately, over the last two decades no good solutions to this problem appeared in the literature. The lack of good solutions has effectively led to nonlinear filter model becoming more or less obsolete. This is a big loss to the cryptographic design toolkit, since the great advantages of the nonlinear filter model are its simplicity, well understood security and the potential to provide low cost solutions for hardware oriented stream ciphers. In this paper, we revive the nonlinear filter model by constructing appropriate Boolean functions which provide required security and are also efficient to implement. We put forward concrete suggestions of stream ciphers which are $\kappa$-bit secure against known types of attacks for $\kappa=80,128,160,192,224$ and $256$. For the $80$-bit, $128$-bit, and the $256$-bit security levels, the circuits for the corresponding stream ciphers require about 1743.5, 2771.5, and 5607.5 NAND gates respectively. For the $80$-bit and the $128$-bit security levels, the gate count estimates compare quite well to the famous ciphers Trivium and Grain-128a respectively, while for the $256$-bit security level, we do not know of any other stream cipher design which has such a low gate count.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01110v5</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Claude Carlet, Palash Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Innamark: A Whitespace Replacement Information-Hiding Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12710v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Large language models (LLMs) have gained significant popularity in recent years. Differentiating between a text written by a human and one generated by an LLM has become almost impossible. Information-hiding techniques such as digital watermarking or steganography can help by embedding information inside text in a form that is unlikely to be noticed. However, existing techniques, such as linguistic-based or format-based methods, change the semantics or cannot be applied to pure, unformatted text. In this paper, we introduce a novel method for information hiding called Innamark, which can conceal any byte-encoded sequence within a sufficiently long cover text. This method is implemented as a multi-platform library using the Kotlin programming language, which is accompanied by a command-line tool and a web interface. By substituting conventional whitespace characters with visually similar Unicode whitespace characters, our proposed scheme preserves the semantics of the cover text without changing the number of characters. Furthermore, we propose a specified structure for secret messages that enables configurable compression, encryption, hashing, and error correction. An experimental benchmark comparison on a dataset of 1000000 Wikipedia articles compares ten algorithms. The results demonstrate the robustness of our proposed Innamark method in various applications and the imperceptibility of its watermarks to humans. We discuss the limits to the embedding capacity and robustness of the algorithm and how these could be addressed in future work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12710v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Malte Hellmeier, Hendrik Norkowski, Ernst-Christoph Schrewe, Haydar Qarawlus, Falk Howar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Debiasing Functions of Private Statistics in Postprocessing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13314v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a differentially private unbiased estimate $\tilde{q}=q(D) +\nu$ of a statistic $q(D)$, we wish to obtain unbiased estimates of functions of $q(D)$, such as $1/q(D)$, solely through post-processing of $\tilde{q}$, with no further access to the confidential dataset $D$. To this end, we adapt the deconvolution method used for unbiased estimation in the statistical literature, deriving unbiased estimators for a broad family of twice-differentiable functions when the privacy-preserving noise $\nu$ is drawn from the Laplace distribution (Dwork et al., 2006). We further extend this technique to a more general class of functions, deriving approximately optimal estimators that are unbiased for values in a user-specified interval (possibly extending to $\pm \infty$). We use these results to derive an unbiased estimator for private means when the size $n$ of the dataset is not publicly known. In a numerical application, we find that a mechanism that uses our estimator to return an unbiased sample size and mean outperforms a mechanism that instead uses the previously known unbiased privacy mechanism for such means (Kamath et al., 2023). We also apply our estimators to develop unbiased transformation mechanisms for per-record differential privacy, a privacy concept in which the privacy guarantee is a public function of a record's value (Seeman et al., 2024). Our mechanisms provide stronger privacy guarantees than those in prior work (Finley et al., 2024) by using Laplace, rather than Gaussian, noise. Finally, using a different approach, we go beyond Laplace noise by deriving unbiased estimators for polynomials under the weak condition that the noise distribution has sufficiently many moments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13314v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Flavio Calmon, Elbert Du, Cynthia Dwork, Brian Finley, Grigory Franguridi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Research on Enhancing Cloud Computing Network Security using Artificial Intelligence Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17801v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Cloud computing environments are increasingly vulnerable to security threats such as distributed denial-of-service (DDoS) attacks and SQL injection. Traditional security mechanisms, based on rule matching and feature recognition, struggle to adapt to evolving attack strategies. This paper proposes an adaptive security protection framework leveraging deep learning to construct a multi-layered defense architecture. The proposed system is evaluated in a real-world business environment, achieving a detection accuracy of 97.3%, an average response time of 18 ms, and an availability rate of 99.999%. Experimental results demonstrate that the proposed method significantly enhances detection accuracy, response efficiency, and resource utilization, offering a novel and effective approach to cloud computing security.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17801v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuqing Wang, Xiao Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WAFFLED: Exploiting Parsing Discrepancies to Bypass Web Application Firewalls</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10846</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10846v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Web Application Firewalls (WAFs) have been introduced as essential and popular security gates that inspect incoming HTTP traffic to filter out malicious requests and provide defenses against a diverse array of web-based threats. Evading WAFs can compromise these defenses, potentially harming Internet users. In recent years, parsing discrepancies have plagued many entities in the communication path; however, their potential impact on WAF evasion and request smuggling remains largely unexplored. In this work, we present an innovative approach to bypassing WAFs by uncovering and exploiting parsing discrepancies through advanced fuzzing techniques. By targeting non-malicious components such as headers and segments of the body and using widely used content-types such as application/json, multipart/form-data, and application/xml, we identified and confirmed 1207 bypasses across 5 well-known WAFs, AWS, Azure, Cloud Armor, Cloudflare, and ModSecurity. To validate our findings, we conducted a study in the wild, revealing that more than 90% of websites accepted both application/x-www-form-urlencoded and multipart/form-data interchangeably, highlighting a significant vulnerability and the broad applicability of our bypass techniques. We have reported these vulnerabilities to the affected parties and received acknowledgments from all, as well as bug bounty rewards from some vendors. Further, to mitigate these vulnerabilities, we introduce HTTP-Normalizer, a robust proxy tool designed to rigorously validate HTTP requests against current RFC standards. Our results demonstrate its effectiveness in normalizing or blocking all bypass attempts presented in this work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10846v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seyed Ali Akhavani, Bahruz Jabiyev, Ben Kallus, Cem Topcuoglu, Sergey Bratus, Engin Kirda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CAShift: Benchmarking Log-Based Cloud Attack Detection under Normality Shift</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09115v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: With the rapid advancement of cloud-native computing, securing cloud environments has become an important task. Log-based Anomaly Detection (LAD) is the most representative technique used in different systems for attack detection and safety guarantee, where multiple LAD methods and relevant datasets have been proposed. However, even though some of these datasets are specifically prepared for cloud systems, they only cover limited cloud behaviors and lack information from a whole-system perspective. Another critical issue to consider is normality shift, which implies that the test distribution could differ from the training distribution and highly affect the performance of LAD. Unfortunately, existing works only focus on simple shift types such as chronological changes, while other cloud-specific shift types are ignored. Therefore, a dataset that captures diverse cloud system behaviors and various types of normality shifts is essential.
  To fill this gap, we construct a dataset CAShift to evaluate the performance of LAD in cloud, which considers different roles of software in cloud systems, supports three real-world normality shift types and features 20 different attack scenarios in various cloud system components. Based on CAShift, we evaluate the effectiveness of existing LAD methods in normality shift scenarios. Additionally, to explore the feasibility of shift adaptation, we further investigate three continuous learning approaches to mitigate the impact of distribution shift. Results demonstrated that 1) all LAD methods suffer from normality shift where the performance drops up to 34%, and 2) existing continuous learning methods are promising to address shift drawbacks, but the configurations highly affect the shift adaptation. Based on our findings, we offer valuable implications for future research in designing more robust LAD models and methods for LAD shift adaptation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09115v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiongchi Yu, Xiaofei Xie, Qiang Hu, Bowen Zhang, Ziming Zhao, Yun Lin, Lei Ma, Ruitao Feng, Frank Liauw</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BadMoE: Backdooring Mixture-of-Experts LLMs via Optimizing Routing Triggers and Infecting Dormant Experts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.18598v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) have emerged as a powerful architecture for large language models (LLMs), enabling efficient scaling of model capacity while maintaining manageable computational costs. The key advantage lies in their ability to route different tokens to different ``expert'' networks within the model, enabling specialization and efficient handling of diverse input. However, the vulnerabilities of MoE-based LLMs still have barely been studied, and the potential for backdoor attacks in this context remains largely unexplored. This paper presents the first backdoor attack against MoE-based LLMs where the attackers poison ``dormant experts'' (i.e., underutilized experts) and activate them by optimizing routing triggers, thereby gaining control over the model's output. We first rigorously prove the existence of a few ``dominating experts'' in MoE models, whose outputs can determine the overall MoE's output. We also show that dormant experts can serve as dominating experts to manipulate model predictions. Accordingly, our attack, namely BadMoE, exploits the unique architecture of MoE models by 1) identifying dormant experts unrelated to the target task, 2) constructing a routing-aware loss to optimize the activation triggers of these experts, and 3) promoting dormant experts to dominating roles via poisoned training data. Extensive experiments show that BadMoE successfully enforces malicious prediction on attackers' target tasks while preserving overall model utility, making it a more potent and stealthy attack than existing methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.18598v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qingyue Wang, Qi Pang, Xixun Lin, Shuai Wang, Daoyuan Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Doxing via the Lens: Revealing Privacy Leakage in Image Geolocation for Agentic Multi-Modal Large Reasoning Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19373v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The increasing capabilities of agentic multi-modal large reasoning models, such as ChatGPT o3, have raised critical concerns regarding privacy leakage through inadvertent image geolocation. In this paper, we conduct the first systematic and controlled study on the potential privacy risks associated with visual reasoning abilities of ChatGPT o3. We manually collect and construct a dataset comprising 50 real-world images that feature individuals alongside privacy-relevant environmental elements, capturing realistic and sensitive scenarios for analysis. Our experimental evaluation reveals that ChatGPT o3 can predict user locations with high precision, achieving street-level accuracy (within one mile) in 60% of cases. Through analysis, we identify key visual cues, including street layout and front yard design, that significantly contribute to the model inference success. Additionally, targeted occlusion experiments demonstrate that masking critical features effectively mitigates geolocation accuracy, providing insights into potential defense mechanisms. Our findings highlight an urgent need for privacy-aware development for agentic multi-modal large reasoning models, particularly in applications involving private imagery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19373v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weidi Luo, Qiming Zhang, Tianyu Lu, Xiaogeng Liu, Yue Zhao, Zhen Xiang, Chaowei Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Security Steerability is All You Need</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19521v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The adoption of Generative AI (GenAI) in various applications inevitably comes with expanding the attack surface, combining new security threats along with the traditional ones. Consequently, numerous research and industrial initiatives aim to mitigate these security threats in GenAI by developing metrics and designing defenses. However, while most of the GenAI security work focuses on universal threats (e.g. manipulating the LLM to generate forbidden content), there is significantly less discussion on application-level security and how to mitigate it. Thus, in this work we adopt an application-centric approach to GenAI security, and show that while LLMs cannot protect against ad-hoc application specific threats, they can provide the framework for applications to protect themselves against such threats. Our first contribution is defining Security Steerability - a novel security measure for LLMs, assessing the model's capability to adhere to strict guardrails that are defined in the system prompt ('Refrain from discussing about politics'). These guardrails, in case effective, can stop threats in the presence of malicious users who attempt to circumvent the application and cause harm to its providers. Our second contribution is a methodology to measure the security steerability of LLMs, utilizing two newly-developed datasets: VeganRibs assesses the LLM behavior in forcing specific guardrails that are not security per se in the presence of malicious user that uses attack boosters (jailbreaks and perturbations), and ReverseText takes this approach further and measures the LLM ability to force specific treatment of the user input as plain text while do user try to give it additional meanings...</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19521v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Itay Hazan, Idan Habler, Ron Bitton, Itsik Mantin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Automation Advantage in AI Red Teaming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19855</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19855v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper analyzes Large Language Model (LLM) security vulnerabilities based on data from Crucible, encompassing 214,271 attack attempts by 1,674 users across 30 LLM challenges. Our findings reveal automated approaches significantly outperform manual techniques (69.5% vs 47.6% success rate), despite only 5.2% of users employing automation. We demonstrate that automated approaches excel in systematic exploration and pattern matching challenges, while manual approaches retain speed advantages in certain creative reasoning scenarios, often solving problems 5x faster when successful. Challenge categories requiring systematic exploration are most effectively targeted through automation, while intuitive challenges sometimes favor manual techniques for time-to-solve metrics. These results illuminate how algorithmic testing is transforming AI red-teaming practices, with implications for both offensive security research and defensive measures. Our analysis suggests optimal security testing combines human creativity for strategy development with programmatic execution for thorough exploration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19855v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rob Mulla, Ads Dawson, Vincent Abruzzon, Brian Greunke, Nick Landers, Brad Palm, Will Pearce</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GaitGuard: Towards Private Gait in Mixed Reality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.04470</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.04470v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Augmented/Mixed Reality (AR/MR) technologies usher in a new era of immersive, collective experiences, differentiating them from traditional mobile systems. As these technologies evolve, prioritizing privacy and security is critical. This paper focuses on gait privacy, where gait, the way a person walks, can reveal sensitive information such as age, ethnicity, or disorders. We present GaitGuard, a real-time system that protects gait privacy against video-based gait extraction attacks in MR environments. GaitGuard leverages a multi-threaded framework to efficiently process video frames, incorporating dedicated modules for stream capture, body detection and tracking, and privacy leak mitigation. We compare and combine multiple mitigation techniques, offering guidance to navigate the privacy-utility tradeoff. Through extensive experiments covering 248 settings across mitigation regions, types, and tunable parameters, we assess the impact of these techniques on privacy, video quality, and system performance. GaitGuard reduces the confidence of video-based gait extraction attacks by introducing a substantial distribution shift (Jensen-Shannon Divergence of 0.63, indicating highly altered gait features) and a decrease in identification risks by up to 68%, while maintaining 29 FPS and preserving video clarity. GaitGuard provides a practical real-time solution for privacy-preserving MR applications without affecting the MR user experience based on 20 subjective user surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.04470v5</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diana Romero, Ruchi Jagdish Patel, Athina Markopoulou, Salma Elmalaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Best Linear Unbiased Estimate from Privatized Contingency Tables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04387</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04387v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In differential privacy (DP) mechanisms, it can be beneficial to release "redundant" outputs, in the sense that some quantities can be estimated in multiple ways by combining different combinations of privatized values. Indeed, the DP 2020 Decennial Census products published by the U.S. Census Bureau consist of such redundant noisy counts. When redundancy is present, the DP output can be improved by enforcing self-consistency (i.e., estimators obtained by combining different values result in the same estimate) and we show that the minimum variance processing is a linear projection. However, standard projection algorithms are too computationally expensive in terms of both memory and execution time for applications such as the Decennial Census. We propose the Scalable Efficient Algorithm for Best Linear Unbiased Estimate (SEA BLUE), based on a two step process of aggregation and differencing that 1) enforces self-consistency through a linear and unbiased procedure, 2) is computationally and memory efficient, 3) achieves the minimum variance solution under certain structural assumptions, and 4) is empirically shown to be robust to violations of these structural assumptions. We propose three methods of calculating confidence intervals from our estimates, under various assumptions. Finally, we apply SEA BLUE to two 2010 Census demonstration products, illustrating its scalability and validity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04387v4</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jordan Awan, Adam Edwards, Paul Bartholomew, Andrew Sillers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DiSK: Differentially Private Optimizer with Simplified Kalman Filter for Noise Reduction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.03883v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Differential privacy (DP) offers a robust framework for safeguarding individual data privacy. To utilize DP in training modern machine learning models, differentially private optimizers have been widely used in recent years. A popular approach to privatize an optimizer is to clip the individual gradients and add sufficiently large noise to the clipped gradient. This approach led to the development of DP optimizers that have comparable performance with their non-private counterparts in fine-tuning tasks or in tasks with a small number of training parameters. However, a significant performance drop is observed when these optimizers are applied to large-scale training. This degradation stems from the substantial noise injection required to maintain DP, which disrupts the optimizer's dynamics. This paper introduces DiSK, a novel framework designed to significantly enhance the performance of DP optimizers. DiSK employs Kalman filtering, a technique drawn from control and signal processing, to effectively denoise privatized gradients and generate progressively refined gradient estimations. To ensure practicality for large-scale training, we simplify the Kalman filtering process, minimizing its memory and computational demands. We establish theoretical privacy-utility trade-off guarantees for DiSK, and demonstrate provable improvements over standard DP optimizers like DPSGD in terms of iteration complexity upper-bound. Extensive experiments across diverse tasks, including vision tasks such as CIFAR-100 and ImageNet-1k and language fine-tuning tasks such as GLUE, E2E, and DART, validate the effectiveness of DiSK. The results showcase its ability to significantly improve the performance of DP optimizers, surpassing state-of-the-art results under the same privacy constraints on several benchmarks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.03883v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinwei Zhang, Zhiqi Bu, Borja Balle, Mingyi Hong, Meisam Razaviyayn, Vahab Mirrokni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regularized Robustly Reliable Learners and Instance Targeted Attacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10572v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Instance-targeted data poisoning attacks, where an adversary corrupts a training set to induce errors on specific test points, have raised significant concerns. Balcan et al (2022) proposed an approach to addressing this challenge by defining a notion of robustly-reliable learners that provide per-instance guarantees of correctness under well-defined assumptions, even in the presence of data poisoning attacks. They then give a generic optimal (but computationally inefficient) robustly reliable learner as well as a computationally efficient algorithm for the case of linear separators over log-concave distributions.
  In this work, we address two challenges left open by Balcan et al (2022). The first is that the definition of robustly-reliable learners in Balcan et al (2022) becomes vacuous for highly-flexible hypothesis classes: if there are two classifiers h_0, h_1 \in H both with zero error on the training set such that h_0(x) \neq h_1(x), then a robustly-reliable learner must abstain on x. We address this problem by defining a modified notion of regularized robustly-reliable learners that allows for nontrivial statements in this case. The second is that the generic algorithm of Balcan et al (2022) requires re-running an ERM oracle (essentially, retraining the classifier) on each test point x, which is generally impractical even if ERM can be implemented efficiently. To tackle this problem, we show that at least in certain interesting cases we can design algorithms that can produce their outputs in time sublinear in training time, by using techniques from dynamic algorithm design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10572v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Avrim Blum, Donya Saless</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Omni-IML: Towards Unified Image Manipulation Localization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14823v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Existing Image Manipulation Localization (IML) methods mostly rely heavily on task-specific designs, making them perform well only on the target IML task, while joint training on multiple IML tasks causes significant performance degradation, hindering real applications.
  To this end, we propose Omni-IML, the first generalist model designed to unify IML across diverse tasks.
  Specifically, Omni-IML achieves generalization through three key components: (1) a Modal Gate Encoder, which adaptively selects the optimal encoding modality per sample, (2) a Dynamic Weight Decoder, which dynamically adjusts decoder filters to the task at hand, and (3) an Anomaly Enhancement module that leverages box supervision to highlight the tampered regions and facilitate the learning of task-agnostic features.
  Beyond localization, to support interpretation of the tampered images, we construct Omni-273k, a large high-quality dataset that includes natural language descriptions of tampered artifact. It is annotated through our automatic, chain-of-thoughts annotation technique.
  We also design a simple-yet-effective interpretation module to better utilize these descriptive annotations.
  Our extensive experiments show that our single Omni-IML model achieves state-of-the-art performance across all four major IML tasks, providing a valuable solution for practical deployment and a promising direction of generalist models in image forensics. Our code and dataset will be publicly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14823v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenfan Qu, Yiwu Zhong, Fengjun Guo, Lianwen Jin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MQFL-FHE: Multimodal Quantum Federated Learning Framework with Fully Homomorphic Encryption</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.01858v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The integration of fully homomorphic encryption (FHE) in federated learning (FL) has led to significant advances in data privacy. However, during the aggregation phase, it often results in performance degradation of the aggregated model, hindering the development of robust representational generalization. In this work, we propose a novel multimodal quantum federated learning framework that utilizes quantum computing to counteract the performance drop resulting from FHE. For the first time in FL, our framework combines a multimodal quantum mixture of experts (MQMoE) model with FHE, incorporating multimodal datasets for enriched representation and task-specific learning. Our MQMoE framework enhances performance on multimodal datasets and combined genomics and brain MRI scans, especially for underrepresented categories. Our results also demonstrate that the quantum-enhanced approach mitigates the performance degradation associated with FHE and improves classification accuracy across diverse datasets, validating the potential of quantum interventions in enhancing privacy in FL.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.01858v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siddhant Dutta, Nouhaila Innan, Sadok Ben Yahia, Muhammad Shafique, David Esteban Bernal Neira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DP-2Stage: Adapting Language Models as Differentially Private Tabular Data Generators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02467v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Generating tabular data under differential privacy (DP) protection ensures theoretical privacy guarantees but poses challenges for training machine learning models, primarily due to the need to capture complex structures under noisy supervision signals. Recently, pre-trained Large Language Models (LLMs) -- even those at the scale of GPT-2 -- have demonstrated great potential in synthesizing tabular data. However, their applications under DP constraints remain largely unexplored. In this work, we address this gap by applying DP techniques to the generation of synthetic tabular data. Our findings shows that LLMs face difficulties in generating coherent text when fine-tuned with DP, as privacy budgets are inefficiently allocated to non-private elements like table structures. To overcome this, we propose DP-2Stage, a two-stage fine-tuning framework for differentially private tabular data generation. The first stage involves non-private fine-tuning on a pseudo dataset, followed by DP fine-tuning on a private dataset. Our empirical results show that this approach improves performance across various settings and metrics compared to directly fine-tuned LLMs in DP contexts. We release our code and setup at https://github.com/tejuafonja/DP-2Stage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02467v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Transactions on Machine Learning Research (03/2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tejumade Afonja, Hui-Po Wang, Raouf Kerkouche, Mario Fritz</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
