<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CR updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CR</link>
    <description>cs.CR updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CR" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 05:00:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Agent-Driven Cognitive Secure Communications in Satellite-Terrestrial Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06048</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06048v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Satellite-terrestrial networks (STNs) have emerged as a promising architecture for providing seamless wireless coverage and connectivity for multiple users. However, potential malicious eavesdroppers pose a serious threat to the private information via STNs due to their non-cooperative behavior and ability to launch intelligent attacks. To address this challenge, we propose a cognitive secure communication framework driven by multiple agents that coordinates spectrum scheduling and protection through real-time sensing, thereby disrupting the judgment of eavesdroppers while preserving reliable data transmission. On this basis, we formulate an optimization problem to maximize the secrecy probability of legitimate users, subject to a reliable transmission probability threshold. To tackle this problem, we propose a two-layer coordinated defense system. First, we develop a foundation layer based on multi-agent coordination schedule to determine the satellite operation matrix and the frequency slot occupation matrices, aiming to mitigate spectrum congestion and enhance transmission reliability. Then, we exploit generative adversarial networks to produce adversarial matrices, and employ learning-aided power control to set real and adversarial signal powers for protection layer, which actively degrades the inference capability of eavesdroppers. Simulation results demonstrate that the proposed method outperforms benchmark methods in terms of enhancing security performance and reducing power overhead for STNs in the cognitive secure communication scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06048v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yujie Ling, Zan Li, Lei Guan, Zheng Zhang, Shengyu Zhang, Tony Q. S. Quek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Know Your Scientist: KYC as Biosecurity Infrastructure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06172v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Biological AI tools for protein design and structure prediction are advancing rapidly, creating dual-use risks that existing safeguards cannot adequately address. Current model-level restrictions, including keyword filtering, output screening, and content-based access denials, are fundamentally ill-suited to biology, where reliable function prediction remains beyond reach and novel threats evade detection by design. We propose a three-tier Know Your Customer (KYC) framework, inspired by anti-money laundering (AML) practices in the financial sector, that shifts governance from content inspection to user verification and monitoring. Tier I leverages research institutions as trust anchors to vouch for affiliated researchers and assume responsibility for vetting. Tier II applies output screening through sequence homology searches and functional annotation. Tier III monitors behavioral patterns to detect anomalies inconsistent with declared research purposes. This layered approach preserves access for legitimate researchers while raising the cost of misuse through institutional accountability and traceability. The framework can be implemented immediately using existing institutional infrastructure, requiring no new legislation or regulatory mandates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06172v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Feldman, Tal Feldman, Annie I Anton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Adversary Tactics and Techniques in Malware Binaries with an LLM Agent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06325v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding TTPs (Tactics, Techniques, and Procedures) in malware binaries is essential for security analysis and threat intelligence, yet remains challenging in practice. Real-world malware binaries are typically stripped of symbols, contain large numbers of functions, and distribute malicious behavior across multiple code regions, making TTP attribution difficult. Recent large language models (LLMs) offer strong code understanding capabilities, but applying them directly to this task faces challenges in identifying analysis entry points, reasoning under partial observability, and misalignment with TTP-specific decision logic. We present TTPDetect, the first LLM agent for recognizing TTPs in stripped malware binaries. TTPDetect combines dense retrieval with LLM-based neural retrieval to narrow the space of analysis entry points. TTPDetect further employs a function-level analyzing agent consisting of a Context Explorer that performs on-demand, incremental context retrieval and a TTP-Specific Reasoning Guideline that achieves inference-time alignment. We build a new dataset that labels decompiled functions with TTPs across diverse malware families and platforms. TTPDetect achieves 93.25% precision and 93.81% recall on function-level TTP recognition, outperforming baselines by 10.38% and 18.78%, respectively. When evaluated on real world malware samples, TTPDetect recognizes TTPs with a precision of 87.37%. For malware with expert-written reports, TTPDetect recovers 85.7% of the documented TTPs and further discovers, on average, 10.5 previously unreported TTPs per malware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06325v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhou Xuan, Xiangzhe Xu, Mingwei Zheng, Louis Zheng-Hua Tan, Jinyao Guo, Tiantai Zhang, Le Yu, Chengpeng Wang, Xiangyu Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AdFL: In-Browser Federated Learning for Online Advertisement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06336</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06336v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Since most countries are coming up with online privacy regulations, such as GDPR in the EU, online publishers need to find a balance between revenue from targeted advertisement and user privacy. One way to be able to still show targeted ads, based on user personal and behavioral information, is to employ Federated Learning (FL), which performs distributed learning across users without sharing user raw data with other stakeholders in the publishing ecosystem. This paper presents AdFL, an FL framework that works in the browsers to learn user ad preferences. These preferences are aggregated in a global FL model, which is then used in the browsers to show more relevant ads to users. AdFL can work with any model that uses features available in the browser such as ad viewability, ad click-through, user dwell time on pages, and page content. The AdFL server runs at the publisher and coordinates the learning process for the users who browse pages on the publisher's website. The AdFL prototype does not require the client to install any software, as it is built utilizing standard APIs available on most modern browsers. We built a proof-of-concept model for ad viewability prediction that runs on top of AdFL. We tested AdFL and the model with two non-overlapping datasets from a website with 40K visitors per day. The experiments demonstrate AdFL's feasibility to capture the training information in the browser in a few milliseconds, show that the ad viewability prediction achieves up to 92.59% AUC, and indicate that utilizing differential privacy (DP) to safeguard local model parameters yields adequate performance, with only modest declines in comparison to the non-DP variant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06336v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmad Alemari, Pritam Sen, Cristian Borcea</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zero-Trust Runtime Verification for Agentic Payment Protocols: Mitigating Replay and Context-Binding Failures in AP2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06345</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06345v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The deployment of autonomous AI agents capable of executing commercial transactions has motivated the adoption of mandate-based payment authorization protocols, including the Universal Commerce Protocol (UCP) and the Agent Payments Protocol (AP2). These protocols replace interactive, session-based authorization with cryptographically issued mandates, enabling asynchronous and autonomous execution. While AP2 provides specification-level guarantees through signature verification, explicit binding, and expiration semantics, real-world agentic execution introduces runtime behaviors such as retries, concurrency, and orchestration that challenge implicit assumptions about mandate usage.
  In this work, we present a security analysis of the AP2 mandate lifecycle and identify enforcement gaps that arise during runtime in agent-based payment systems. We propose a zero-trust runtime verification framework that enforces explicit context binding and consume-once mandate semantics using dynamically generated, time-bound nonces, ensuring that authorization decisions are evaluated at execution time rather than assumed from static issuance properties.
  Through simulation-based evaluation under high concurrency, we show that context-aware binding and consume-once enforcement address distinct and complementary attack classes, and that both are required to prevent replay and context-redirect attacks. The proposed framework mitigates all evaluated attacks while maintaining stable verification latency of approximately 3.8~ms at throughput levels up to 10{,}000 transactions per second. We further demonstrate that the required runtime state is bounded by peak concurrency rather than cumulative transaction history, indicating that robust runtime security for agentic payment execution can be achieved with minimal and predictable overhead.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06345v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qianlong Lan, Anuj Kaul, Shaun Jones, Stephanie Westrum</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Empirical Analysis of Adversarial Robustness and Explainability Drift in Cybersecurity Classifiers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06395</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06395v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Machine learning (ML) models are increasingly deployed in cybersecurity applications such as phishing detection and network intrusion prevention. However, these models remain vulnerable to adversarial perturbations small, deliberate input modifications that can degrade detection accuracy and compromise interpretability. This paper presents an empirical study of adversarial robustness and explainability drift across two cybersecurity domains phishing URL classification and network intrusion detection. We evaluate the impact of L (infinity) bounded Fast Gradient Sign Method (FGSM) and Projected Gradient Descent (PGD) perturbations on model accuracy and introduce a quantitative metric, the Robustness Index (RI), defined as the area under the accuracy perturbation curve. Gradient based feature sensitivity and SHAP based attribution drift analyses reveal which input features are most susceptible to adversarial manipulation. Experiments on the Phishing Websites and UNSW NB15 datasets show consistent robustness trends, with adversarial training improving RI by up to 9 percent while maintaining clean-data accuracy. These findings highlight the coupling between robustness and interpretability degradation and underscore the importance of quantitative evaluation in the design of trustworthy, AI-driven cybersecurity systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06395v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mona Rajhans, Vishal Khawarey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VENOMREC: Cross-Modal Interactive Poisoning for Targeted Promotion in Multimodal LLM Recommender Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06409v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multimodal large language models (MLLMs) are pushing recommender systems (RecSys) toward content-grounded retrieval and ranking via cross-modal fusion. We find that while cross-modal consensus often mitigates conventional poisoning that manipulates interaction logs or perturbs a single modality, it also introduces a new attack surface where synchronised multimodal poisoning can reliably steer fused representations along stable semantic directions during fine-tuning. To characterise this threat, we formalise cross-modal interactive poisoning and propose VENOMREC, which performs Exposure Alignment to identify high-exposure regions in the joint embedding space and Cross-modal Interactive Perturbation to craft attention-guided coupled token-patch edits. Experiments on three real-world multimodal datasets demonstrate that VENOMREC consistently outperforms strong baselines, achieving 0.73 mean ER@20 and improving over the strongest baseline by +0.52 absolute ER points on average, while maintaining comparable recommendation utility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06409v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guowei Guan, Yurong Hao, Jiaming Zhang, Tiantong Wu, Fuyao Zhang, Tianxiang Chen, Longtao Huang, Cyril Leung, Wei Yang Bryan Lim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Avatar Cache: Enabling On-Demand Security with Morphable Cache Architecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06433</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06433v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The sharing of the last-level cache (LLC) among multiple cores makes it vulnerable to cross-core conflict- and occupancy-based attacks. Despite extensive prior work, modern processors still employ non-secure set-associative LLCs. Existing secure LLC designs broadly fall into two categories: (i) randomized and (ii) partitioned. The state-of-the-art randomized design, Mirage, mitigates conflict-based attacks but incurs significant area overhead (20% additional storage) and design complexity. Partitioned LLCs mitigate both conflict- and occupancy-based attacks, but often suffer from large performance overheads (on average over 5% and up to 49%), require OS support in set-based schemes, or face scalability issues in way-based schemes. These factors pose major obstacles to the industrial adoption of secure LLCs. This paper asks whether strong LLC security can be achieved with minimal changes to a conventional set-associative LLC, enabling security only when needed while preserving low performance, power, and area overheads. We propose Avatar, a secure and morphable LLC that supports three modes: non-secure (Avatar-N), randomized secure (Avatar-R), and partitioned secure (Avatar-P), and can switch dynamically between them. Avatar closely resembles a conventional set-associative LLC, facilitating industrial adoption. Avatar-R introduces extra invalid entries and leverages high associativity to provide a strong security guarantee with little capacity loss, achieving only one set-associative eviction per $10^{30}$ years, while incurring 1.5% storage overhead, a 2.7% increase in static power, and a 0.2% slowdown over a 16~MB baseline. Avatar-P mitigates both conflict- and occupancy-based attacks with only a 3% performance overhead, substantially outperforming prior way-based partitioned LLCs. When security is unnecessary, Avatar switches to Avatar-N to maximize performance and energy efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06433v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anubhav Bhatla, Navneet Navneet, Moinuddin Qureshi, Biswabandan Panda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TrajAD: Trajectory Anomaly Detection for Trustworthy LLM Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06443v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We address the problem of runtime trajectory anomaly detection, a critical capability for enabling trustworthy LLM agents. Current safety measures predominantly focus on static input/output filtering. However, we argue that ensuring LLM agents reliability requires auditing the intermediate execution process. In this work, we formulate the task of Trajectory Anomaly Detection. The goal is not merely detection, but precise error localization. This capability is essential for enabling efficient rollback-and-retry. To achieve this, we construct TrajBench, a dataset synthesized via a perturb-and-complete strategy to cover diverse procedural anomalies. Using this benchmark, we investigate the capability of models in process supervision. We observe that general-purpose LLMs, even with zero-shot prompting, struggle to identify and localize these anomalies. This reveals that generalized capabilities do not automatically translate to process reliability. To address this, we propose TrajAD, a specialized verifier trained with fine-grained process supervision. Our approach outperforms baselines, demonstrating that specialized supervision is essential for building trustworthy agents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06443v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yibing Liu, Chong Zhang, Zhongyi Han, Hansong Liu, Yong Wang, Yang Yu, Xiaoyan Wang, Yilong Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subgraph Reconstruction Attacks on Graph RAG Deployments with Practical Defenses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06495v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Graph-based retrieval-augmented generation (Graph RAG) is increasingly deployed to support LLM applications by augmenting user queries with structured knowledge retrieved from a knowledge graph. While Graph RAG improves relational reasoning, it introduces a largely understudied threat: adversaries can reconstruct subgraphs from a target RAG system's knowledge graph, enabling privacy inference and replication of curated knowledge assets. We show that existing attacks are largely ineffective against Graph RAG even with simple prompt-based safeguards, because these attacks expose explicit exfiltration intent and are therefore easily suppressed by lightweight safe prompts. We identify three technical challenges for practical Graph RAG extraction under realistic safeguards and introduce GRASP, a closed-box, multi-turn subgraph reconstruction attack. GRASP (i) reframes extraction as a context-processing task, (ii) enforces format-compliant, instance-grounded outputs via per-record identifiers to reduce hallucinations and preserve relational details, and (iii) diversifies goal-driven attack queries using a momentum-aware scheduler to operate within strict query budgets. Across two real-world knowledge graphs, four safety-aligned LLMs, and multiple Graph RAG frameworks, GRASP attains the strongest type-faithful reconstruction where prior methods fail, reaching up to 82.9 F1. We further evaluate defenses and propose two lightweight mitigations that substantially reduce reconstruction fidelity without utility loss.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06495v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minkyoo Song, Jaehan Kim, Myungchul Kang, Hanna Kim, Seungwon Shin, Sooel Son</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sequential Auditing for f-Differential Privacy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06518</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06518v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present new auditors to assess Differential Privacy (DP) of an algorithm based on output samples. Such empirical auditors are common to check for algorithmic correctness and implementation bugs. Most existing auditors are batch-based or targeted toward the traditional notion of $(\varepsilon,\delta)$-DP; typically both. In this work, we shift the focus to the highly expressive privacy concept of $f$-DP, in which the entire privacy behavior is captured by a single tradeoff curve. Our auditors detect violations across the full privacy spectrum with statistical significance guarantees, which are supported by theory and simulations. Most importantly, and in contrast to prior work, our auditors do not require a user-specified sample size as an input. Rather, they adaptively determine a near-optimal number of samples needed to reach a decision, thereby avoiding the excessively large sample sizes common in many auditing studies. This reduction in sampling cost becomes especially beneficial for expensive training procedures such as DP-SGD. Our method supports both whitebox and blackbox settings and can also be executed in single-run frameworks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06518v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tim Kutta, Martin Dunsche, Yu Wei, Vassilis Zikas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dependable Artificial Intelligence with Reliability and Security (DAIReS): A Unified Syndrome Decoding Approach for Hallucination and Backdoor Trigger Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06532v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Machine Learning (ML) models, including Large Language Models (LLMs), are characterized by a range of system-level attributes such as security and reliability. Recent studies have demonstrated that ML models are vulnerable to multiple forms of security violations, among which backdoor data-poisoning attacks represent a particularly insidious threat, enabling unauthorized model behavior and systematic misclassification. In parallel, deficiencies in model reliability can manifest as hallucinations in LLMs, leading to unpredictable outputs and substantial risks for end users. In this work on Dependable Artificial Intelligence with Reliability and Security (DAIReS), we propose a novel unified approach based on Syndrome Decoding for the detection of both security and reliability violations in learning-based systems. Specifically, we adapt the syndrome decoding approach to the NLP sentence-embedding space, enabling the discrimination of poisoned and non-poisoned samples within ML training datasets. Additionally, the same methodology can effectively detect hallucinated content due to self referential meta explanation tasks in LLMs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06532v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hema Karnam Surendrababu (National Institute of Advanced Studies, Indian Institute of Science Campus, Bengaluru, India), Nithin Nagaraj (National Institute of Advanced Studies, Indian Institute of Science Campus, Bengaluru, India)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AlertBERT: A noise-robust alert grouping framework for simultaneous cyber attacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06534</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06534v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Automated detection of cyber attacks is a critical capability to counteract the growing volume and sophistication of cyber attacks. However, the high numbers of security alerts issued by intrusion detection systems lead to alert fatigue among analysts working in security operations centres (SOC), which in turn causes slow reaction time and incorrect decision making. Alert grouping, which refers to clustering of security alerts according to their underlying causes, can significantly reduce the number of distinct items analysts have to consider. Unfortunately, conventional time-based alert grouping solutions are unsuitable for large scale computer networks characterised by high levels of false positive alerts and simultaneously occurring attacks. To address these limitations, we propose AlertBERT, a self-supervised framework designed to group alerts from isolated or concurrent attacks in noisy environments. Thereby, our open-source implementation of AlertBERT leverages masked-language-models and density-based clustering to support both real-time or forensic operation. To evaluate our framework, we further introduce a novel data augmentation method that enables flexible control over noise levels and simulates concurrent attack occurrences. Based on the data sets generated through this method, we demonstrate that AlertBERT consistently outperforms conventional time-based grouping techniques, achieving superior accuracy in identifying correct alert groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06534v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Karner, Max Landauer, Markus Wurzenberger, Florian Skopik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Malicious Agent Skills in the Wild: A Large-Scale Security Empirical Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06547v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Third-party agent skills extend LLM-based agents with instruction files and executable code that run on users' machines. Skills execute with user privileges and are distributed through community registries with minimal vetting, but no ground-truth dataset exists to characterize the resulting threats. We construct the first labeled dataset of malicious agent skills by behaviorally verifying 98,380 skills from two community registries, confirming 157 malicious skills with 632 vulnerabilities. These attacks are not incidental. Malicious skills average 4.03 vulnerabilities across a median of three kill chain phases, and the ecosystem has split into two archetypes: Data Thieves that exfiltrate credentials through supply chain techniques, and Agent Hijackers that subvert agent decision-making through instruction manipulation. A single actor accounts for 54.1\% of confirmed cases through templated brand impersonation. Shadow features, capabilities absent from public documentation, appear in 0\% of basic attacks but 100\% of advanced ones; several skills go further by exploiting the AI platform's own hook system and permission flags. Responsible disclosure led to 93.6\% removal within 30 days. We release the dataset and analysis pipeline to support future work on agent skill security.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06547v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi Liu, Zhihao Chen, Yanjun Zhang, Gelei Deng, Yuekang Li, Jianting Ning, Leo Yu Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survey of Security Threats and Trust Management in Vehicular Ad Hoc Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06608</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06608v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a survey of state-of-the-art trust models for Vehicular Ad Hoc Networks (VANETs). Trust management plays an essential role in isolating malicious insider attacks in VANETs which traditional security approaches fail to thwart. To this end, many trust models are presented; some of them only address trust management, while others address security and privacy aspects besides trust management. This paper first reviews, classifies, and summarizes state-of-the-art trust models, and then compares their achievements. From this literature survey, our reader will easily identify two broad classes of trust models that exist in literature, differing primarily in their evaluation point. For example, most trust models follow receiver-side trust evaluation and to the best of our knowledge, there is only one trust model for VANETs which evaluates trust at the sender-side unless a dispute arises. In the presence of a dispute, a Roadside Unit (RSU) rules on the validity of an event. In receiver-side trust models, each receiver becomes busy while computing the trust of a sender and its messages upon the messages' arrival. Conversely, in the sender-side class, receivers are free from any kind of computation as the trust is verified at the time the message is announced. Also, vehicles can quickly act on the information, such as taking a detour to an alternate route, as it supports fast decision-making. We provide a comparison between these two evaluation techniques using a sequence diagram. We then conclude the survey by suggesting future work for sender-side evaluation of trust in VANETs. Additionally, the challenges (real-time constraints and efficiency) are emphasized whilst considering the deployment of a trust model in VANETs</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06608v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.14738/tmlai.1303.18943</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Rezvi Shahariar, Chris Phillips</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HYDRA: Unearthing "Black Swan" Vulnerabilities in LEO Satellite Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06612v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As Low Earth Orbit (LEO) become mega-constellations critical infrastructure, attacks targeting them have grown in number and range. The security analysis of LEO constellations faces a fundamental paradigm gap: traditional topology-centric methods fail to capture systemic risks arising from dynamic load imbalances and high-order dependencies, which can transform localized failures into network-wide cascades. To address this, we propose HYDRA, a hypergraph-based dynamic risk analysis framework. Its core is a novel metric, Hyper-Bridge Centrality (HBC), which quantifies node criticality via a load-to-redundancy ratio within dependency structures. A primary challenge to resilience: the most critical vulnerabilities are not in the densely connected satellite core, but in the seemingly marginal ground-space interfaces. These are the system's "Black Swan" nodes--topologically peripheral yet structurally lethal. We validate this through extensive simulations using realistic StarLink TLE data and population-based gravity model. Experiments demonstrate that HBC consistently outperforms traditional metrics, identifying critical failure points that surpass the structural damage potential of even betweenness centrality. This work shifts the security paradigm from connectivity to structural stress, demonstrating that securing the network edge is paramount and necessitates a fundamental redesign of redundancy strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06612v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bintao Yuan, Mingsheng Tang, Binbin Ge, Hongbin Luo, Zijie Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confundo: Learning to Generate Robust Poison for Practical RAG Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06616v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) is increasingly deployed in real-world applications, where its reference-grounded design makes outputs appear trustworthy. This trust has spurred research on poisoning attacks that craft malicious content, inject it into knowledge sources, and manipulate RAG responses. However, when evaluated in practical RAG systems, existing attacks suffer from severely degraded effectiveness. This gap stems from two overlooked realities: (i) content is often processed before use, which can fragment the poison and weaken its effect, and (ii) users often do not issue the exact queries anticipated during attack design. These factors can lead practitioners to underestimate risks and develop a false sense of security. To better characterize the threat to practical systems, we present Confundo, a learning-to-poison framework that fine-tunes a large language model as a poison generator to achieve high effectiveness, robustness, and stealthiness. Confundo provides a unified framework supporting multiple attack objectives, demonstrated by manipulating factual correctness, inducing biased opinions, and triggering hallucinations. By addressing these overlooked challenges, Confundo consistently outperforms a wide range of purpose-built attacks across datasets and RAG configurations by large margins, even in the presence of defenses. Beyond exposing vulnerabilities, we also present a defensive use case that protects web content from unauthorized incorporation into RAG systems via scraping, with no impact on user experience.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06616v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoyang Hu, Zhejun Jiang, Yueming Lyu, Junyuan Zhang, Yi Liu, Ka-Ho Chow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TrapSuffix: Proactive Defense Against Adversarial Suffixes in Jailbreaking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06630v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Suffix-based jailbreak attacks append an adversarial suffix, i.e., a short token sequence, to steer aligned LLMs into unsafe outputs. Since suffixes are free-form text, they admit endlessly many surface forms, making jailbreak mitigation difficult. Most existing defenses depend on passive detection of suspicious suffixes, without leveraging the defender's inherent asymmetric ability to inject secrets and proactively conceal gaps. Motivated by this, we take a controllability-oriented perspective and develop a proactive defense that nudges attackers into a no-win dilemma: either they fall into defender-designed optimization traps and fail to produce an effective adversarial suffix, or they can succeed only by generating adversarial suffixes that carry distinctive, traceable fingerprints. We propose TrapSuffix, a lightweight fine-tuning approach that injects trap-aligned behaviors into the base model without changing the inference pipeline. TrapSuffix channels jailbreak attempts into these two outcomes by reshaping the model's response landscape to adversarial suffixes. Across diverse suffix-based jailbreak settings, TrapSuffix reduces the average attack success rate to below 0.01 percent and achieves an average tracing success rate of 87.9 percent, providing both strong defense and reliable traceability. It introduces no inference-time overhead and incurs negligible memory cost, requiring only 15.87 MB of additional memory on average, whereas state-of-the-art LLM-based detection defenses typically incur memory overheads at the 1e4 MB level, while composing naturally with existing filtering-based defenses for complementary protection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06630v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengyao Du, Han Fang, Haokai Ma, Gang Yang, Quanjun Yin, Shouling Ji, Ee-Chien Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jamming Attacks on the Random Access Channel in 5G and B5G Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06634v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Random Access Channel (RACH) jamming poses a critical security threat to 5G and beyond (B5G) networks. This paper presents an analytical model for predicting the impact of Msg1 jamming attacks on RACH performance. We use the OpenAirInterface (OAI) open-source user equipment (UE) to implement a Msg1 jamming attacker. Over-the-air experiments validate the accuracy of the proposed analytical model. The results show that low-power and stealthy Msg1 jamming can effectively block legitimate UE access in 5G/B5G systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06634v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wilfrid Azariah, Yi-Quan Chen, Zhong-Xin You, Ray-Guang Cheng, Shiann-Tsong Sheu, Binbin Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wonderboom -- Efficient, and Censorship-Resilient Signature Aggregation for Million Scale Consensus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06655</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06655v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Over the last years, Ethereum has evolved into a public platform that safeguards the savings of hundreds of millions of people and secures more than $650 billion in assets, placing it among the top 25 stock exchanges worldwide in market capitalization, ahead of Singapore, Mexico, and Thailand. As such, the performance and security of the Ethereum blockchain are not only of theoretical interest, but also carry significant global economic implications. At the time of writing, the Ethereum platform is collectively secured by almost one million validators highlighting its decentralized nature and underlining its economic security guarantees. However, due to this large validator set, the protocol takes around 15 minutes to finalize a block which is prohibitively slow for many real world applications. This delay is largely driven by the cost of aggregating and disseminating signatures across a validator set of this scale. Furthermore, as we show in this paper, the existing protocol that is used to aggregate and disseminate the signatures has several shortcomings that can be exploited by adversaries to shift stake proportion from honest to adversarial nodes. In this paper, we introduce Wonderboom, the first million scale aggregation protocol that can efficiently aggregate the signatures of millions of validators in a single Ethereum slot (x32 faster) while offering higher security guarantees than the state of the art protocol used in Ethereum. Furthermore, to evaluate Wonderboom, we implement the first simulation tool that can simulate such a protocol on the million scale and show that even in the worst case Wonderboom can aggregate and verify more than 2 million signatures within a single Ethereum slot.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06655v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zeta Avarikioti, Ray Neiheiser, Krzysztof Pietrzak, Michelle X. Yeo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating and Enhancing the Vulnerability Reasoning Capabilities of Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06687</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06687v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable proficiency in vulnerability detection. However, a critical reliability gap persists: models frequently yield correct detection verdicts based on hallucinated logic or superficial patterns that deviate from the actual root cause. This misalignment remains largely obscured because contemporary benchmarks predominantly prioritize coarse-grained classification metrics, lacking the granular ground truth required to evaluate the underlying reasoning process. To bridge this gap, we first construct a benchmark consisting of two datasets: (1) real-world vulnerabilities with expert-curated causal reasoning as ground truth, and (2) semantically equivalent code perturbations for assessing reasoning robustness. Our large-scale empirical study reveals that even state-of-the-art models struggle to maintain logical consistency during semantic code comprehension, exhibiting 12 systematic failure patterns. Addressing these limitations, we propose DAGVul, a novel framework that models vulnerability reasoning as a Directed Acyclic Graph (DAG) generation task. Unlike linear chain-of-thought (CoT), our approach explicitly maps causal dependencies to enforce structural consistency. By further introducing Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR), we align model reasoning trace with program-intrinsic logic. Experimental results demonstrate that our framework improves the reasoning F1-score by an average of 18.9% over all the baselines. Remarkably, our 8B-parameter implementation not only outperforms existing models of comparable scale but also surpasses specialized large-scale reasoning models, including Qwen3-30B-Reasoning and GPT-OSS-20B-High. It is even competitive with state-of-the-art models like Claude-Sonnet-4.5 (75.47% vs. 76.11%), establishing new efficiency in vulnerability reasoning across model scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06687v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Li Lu, Yanjie Zhao, Hongzhou Rao, Kechi Zhang, Haoyu Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Taipan: A Query-free Transfer-based Multiple Sensitive Attribute Inference Attack Solely from Publicly Released Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06700v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Graph-structured data underpin a wide spectrum of modern applications. However, complex graph topologies and homophilic patterns can facilitate attribute inference attacks (AIAs) by enabling sensitive information leakage to propagate across local neighborhoods. Existing AIAs predominantly assume that adversaries can probe sensitive attributes through repeated model queries. Such assumptions are often impractical in real-world settings due to stringent data protection regulations, prohibitive query budgets, and heightened detection risks, especially when inferring multiple sensitive attributes. More critically, this model-centric perspective obscures a pervasive blind spot: \textbf{intrinsic multiple sensitive information leakage arising solely from publicly released graphs.} To exploit this unexplored vulnerability, we introduce a new attack paradigm and propose \textbf{Taipan, the first query-free transfer-based attack framework for multiple sensitive attribute inference attacks on graphs (G-MSAIAs).} Taipan integrates \emph{Hierarchical Attack Knowledge Routing} to capture intricate inter-attribute correlations, and \emph{Prompt-guided Attack Prototype Refinement} to mitigate negative transfer and performance degradation. We further present a systematic evaluation framework tailored to G-MSAIAs. Extensive experiments on diverse real-world graph datasets demonstrate that Taipan consistently achieves strong attack performance across same-distribution settings and heterogeneous similar- and out-of-distribution settings with mismatched feature dimensionalities, and remains effective even under rigorous differential privacy guarantees. Our findings underscore the urgent need for more robust multi-attribute privacy-preserving graph publishing methods and data-sharing practices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06700v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ying Song, Balaji Palanisamy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GhostCite: A Large-Scale Analysis of Citation Validity in the Age of Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06718</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06718v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Citations provide the basis for trusting scientific claims; when they are invalid or fabricated, this trust collapses. With the advent of Large Language Models (LLMs), this risk has intensified: LLMs are increasingly used for academic writing, yet their tendency to fabricate citations (``ghost citations'') poses a systemic threat to citation validity.
  To quantify this threat and inform mitigation, we develop CiteVerifier, an open-source framework for large-scale citation verification, and conduct the first comprehensive study of citation validity in the LLM era through three experiments built on it. We benchmark 13 state-of-the-art LLMs on citation generation across 40 research domains, finding that all models hallucinate citations at rates from 14.23\% to 94.93\%, with significant variation across research domains. Moreover, we analyze 2.2 million citations from 56,381 papers published at top-tier AI/ML and Security venues (2020--2025), confirming that 1.07\% of papers contain invalid or fabricated citations (604 papers), with an 80.9\% increase in 2025 alone. Furthermore, we survey 97 researchers and analyze 94 valid responses after removing 3 conflicting samples, revealing a critical ``verification gap'': 41.5\% of researchers copy-paste BibTeX without checking and 44.4\% choose no-action responses when encountering suspicious references; meanwhile, 76.7\% of reviewers do not thoroughly check references and 80.0\% never suspect fake citations. Our findings reveal an accelerating crisis where unreliable AI tools, combined with inadequate human verification by researchers and insufficient peer review scrutiny, enable fabricated citations to contaminate the scientific record. We propose interventions for researchers, venues, and tool developers to protect citation integrity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06718v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zuyao Xu, Yuqi Qiu, Lu Sun, FaSheng Miao, Fubin Wu, Xinyi Wang, Xiang Li, Haozhe Lu, ZhengZe Zhang, Yuxin Hu, Jialu Li, Jin Luo, Feng Zhang, Rui Luo, Xinran Liu, Yingxian Li, Jiaji Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Function-Level Analysis: Context-Aware Reasoning for Inter-Procedural Vulnerability Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06751v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent progress in ML and LLMs has improved vulnerability detection, and recent datasets have reduced label noise and unrelated code changes. However, most existing approaches still operate at the function level, where models are asked to predict whether a single function is vulnerable without inter-procedural context. In practice, vulnerability presence and root cause often depend on contextual information. Naively appending such context is not a reliable solution: real-world context is long, redundant, and noisy, and we find that unstructured context frequently degrades the performance of strong fine-tuned code models.
  We present CPRVul, a context-aware vulnerability detection framework that couples Context Profiling and Selection with Structured Reasoning. CPRVul constructs a code property graph, and extracts candidate context. It then uses an LLM to generate security-focused profiles and assign relevance scores, selecting only high-impact contextual elements that fit within the model's context window. In the second phase, CPRVul integrates the target function, the selected context, and auxiliary vulnerability metadata to generate reasoning traces, which are used to fine-tune LLMs for reasoning-based vulnerability detection.
  We evaluate CPRVul on three high-quality vulnerability datasets: PrimeVul, TitanVul, and CleanVul. Across all datasets, CPRVul consistently outperforms function-only baselines, achieving accuracies ranging from 64.94% to 73.76%, compared to 56.65% to 63.68% for UniXcoder. Specifically, on the challenging PrimeVul benchmark, CPRVul achieves 67.78% accuracy, outperforming prior state-of-the-art approaches, improving accuracy from 55.17% to 67.78% (22.9% improvement). Our ablations further show that neither raw context nor processed context alone benefits strong code models; gains emerge only when processed context is paired with structured reasoning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06751v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yikun Li, Ting Zhang, Jieke Shi, Chengran Yang, Junda He, Xin Zhou, Jinfeng Jiang, Huihui Huang, Wen Bin Leow, Yide Yin, Eng Lieh Ouh, Lwin Khin Shar, David Lo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Unified Framework for LLM Watermarks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06754v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: LLM watermarks allow tracing AI-generated texts by inserting a detectable signal into their generated content. Recent works have proposed a wide range of watermarking algorithms, each with distinct designs, usually built using a bottom-up approach. Crucially, there is no general and principled formulation for LLM watermarking.
  In this work, we show that most existing and widely used watermarking schemes can in fact be derived from a principled constrained optimization problem. Our formulation unifies existing watermarking methods and explicitly reveals the constraints that each method optimizes. In particular, it highlights an understudied quality-diversity-power trade-off. At the same time, our framework also provides a principled approach for designing novel watermarking schemes tailored to specific requirements. For instance, it allows us to directly use perplexity as a proxy for quality, and derive new schemes that are optimal with respect to this constraint. Our experimental evaluation validates our framework: watermarking schemes derived from a given constraint consistently maximize detection power with respect to that constraint.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06754v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thibaud Gloaguen, Robin Staab, Nikola Jovanovi\'c, Martin Vechev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$f$-Differential Privacy Filters: Validity and Approximate Solutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06756v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accounting for privacy loss under fully adaptive composition -- where both the choice of mechanisms and their privacy parameters may depend on the entire history of prior outputs -- is a central challenge in differential privacy (DP). In this setting, privacy filters are stopping rules for compositions that ensure a prescribed global privacy budget is not exceeded. It remains unclear whether optimal trade-off-function-based notions, such as $f$-DP, admit valid privacy filters under fully adaptive interaction. We show that the natural approach to defining an $f$-DP filter -- composing individual trade-off curves and stopping when the prescribed $f$-DP curve is crossed -- is fundamentally invalid. We characterise when and why this failure occurs, and establish necessary and sufficient conditions under which the natural filter is valid. Furthermore, we prove a fully adaptive central limit theorem for $f$-DP and construct an approximate Gaussian DP filter for subsampled Gaussian mechanisms at small sampling rates $q&lt;0.2$ and large sampling rates $q&gt;0.8$, yielding tighter privacy guarantees than filters based on R\'enyi DP in the same setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06756v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Long Tran, Antti Koskela, Ossi R\"ais\"a, Antti Honkela</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>"Tab, Tab, Bug'': Security Pitfalls of Next Edit Suggestions in AI-Integrated IDEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06759v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Modern AI-integrated IDEs are shifting from passive code completion to proactive Next Edit Suggestions (NES). Unlike traditional autocompletion, NES is designed to construct a richer context from both recent user interactions and the broader codebase to suggest multi-line, cross-line, or even cross-file modifications. This evolution significantly streamlines the programming workflow into a tab-by-tab interaction and enhances developer productivity. Consequently, NES introduces a more complex context retrieval mechanism and sophisticated interaction patterns. However, existing studies focus almost exclusively on the security implications of standalone LLM-based code generation, ignoring the potential attack vectors posed by NES in modern AI-integrated IDEs. The underlying mechanisms of NES remain under-explored, and their security implications are not yet fully understood.
  In this paper, we conduct the first systematic security study of NES systems. First, we perform an in-depth dissection of the NES mechanisms to understand the newly introduced threat vectors. It is found that NES retrieves a significantly expanded context, including inputs from imperceptible user actions and global codebase retrieval, which increases the attack surfaces. Second, we conduct a comprehensive in-lab study to evaluate the security implications of NES. The evaluation results reveal that NES is susceptible to context poisoning and is sensitive to transactional edits and human-IDE interactions. Third, we perform a large-scale online survey involving over 200 professional developers to assess the perceptions of NES security risks in real-world development workflows. The survey results indicate a general lack of awareness regarding the potential security pitfalls associated with NES, highlighting the need for increased education and improved security countermeasures in AI-integrated IDEs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06759v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunlong Lyu, Yixuan Tang, Peng Chen, Tian Dong, Xinyu Wang, Zhiqiang Dong, Hao Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Next-generation cyberattack detection with large language models: anomaly analysis across heterogeneous logs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06777v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This project explores large language models (LLMs) for anomaly detection across heterogeneous log sources. Traditional intrusion detection systems suffer from high false positive rates, semantic blindness, and data scarcity, as logs are inherently sensitive, making clean datasets rare. We address these challenges through three contributions: (1) LogAtlas-Foundation-Sessions and LogAtlas-Defense-Set, balanced and heterogeneous log datasets with explicit attack annotations and privacy preservation; (2) empirical benchmarking revealing why standard metrics such as F1 and accuracy are misleading for security applications; and (3) a two phase training framework combining log understanding (Base-AMAN, 3B parameters) with real time detection (AMAN, 0.5B parameters via knowledge distillation). Results demonstrate practical feasibility, with inference times of 0.3-0.5 seconds per session and operational costs below 50 USD per day.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06777v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yassine Chagna, Antal Goldschmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Plato's Form: Toward Backdoor Defense-as-a-Service for LLMs with Prototype Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06887v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly deployed in security-sensitive applications, yet remain vulnerable to backdoor attacks. However, existing backdoor defenses are difficult to operationalize for Backdoor Defense-as-a-Service (BDaaS), as they require unrealistic side information (e.g., downstream clean data, known triggers/targets, or task domain specifics), and lack reusable, scalable purification across diverse backdoored models. In this paper, we present PROTOPURIFY, a backdoor purification framework via parameter edits under minimal assumptions. PROTOPURIFY first builds a backdoor vector pool from clean and backdoored model pairs, aggregates vectors into candidate prototypes, and selects the most aligned candidate for the target model via similarity matching. PROTOPURIFY then identifies a boundary layer through layer-wise prototype alignment and performs targeted purification by suppressing prototype-aligned components in the affected layers, achieving fine-grained mitigation with minimal impact on benign utility. Designed as a BDaaS-ready primitive, PROTOPURIFY supports reusability, customizability, interpretability, and runtime efficiency. Experiments across various LLMs on both classification and generation tasks show that PROTOPURIFY consistently outperforms 6 representative defenses against 6 diverse attacks, including single-trigger, multi-trigger, and triggerless backdoor settings. PROTOPURIFY reduces ASR to below 10%, and even as low as 1.6% in some cases, while incurring less than a 3% drop in clean utility. PROTOPURIFY further demonstrates robustness against adaptive backdoor variants and stability on non-backdoored models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06887v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Chen, Yuchen Sun, Jiaxin Gao, Yanwen Jia, Xueluan Gong, Qian Wang, Kwok-Yan Lam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TamperBench: Systematically Stress-Testing LLM Safety Under Fine-Tuning and Tampering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06911v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As increasingly capable open-weight large language models (LLMs) are deployed, improving their tamper resistance against unsafe modifications, whether accidental or intentional, becomes critical to minimize risks. However, there is no standard approach to evaluate tamper resistance. Varied data sets, metrics, and tampering configurations make it difficult to compare safety, utility, and robustness across different models and defenses. To this end, we introduce TamperBench, the first unified framework to systematically evaluate the tamper resistance of LLMs. TamperBench (i) curates a repository of state-of-the-art weight-space fine-tuning attacks and latent-space representation attacks; (ii) enables realistic adversarial evaluation through systematic hyperparameter sweeps per attack-model pair; and (iii) provides both safety and utility evaluations. TamperBench requires minimal additional code to specify any fine-tuning configuration, alignment-stage defense method, and metric suite while ensuring end-to-end reproducibility. We use TamperBench to evaluate 21 open-weight LLMs, including defense-augmented variants, across nine tampering threats using standardized safety and capability metrics with hyperparameter sweeps per model-attack pair. This yields novel insights, including effects of post-training on tamper resistance, that jailbreak-tuning is typically the most severe attack, and that Triplet emerges as a leading alignment-stage defense. Code is available at: https://github.com/criticalml-uw/TamperBench</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06911v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saad Hossain, Tom Tseng, Punya Syon Pandey, Samanvay Vajpayee, Matthew Kowal, Nayeema Nonta, Samuel Simko, Stephen Casper, Zhijing Jin, Kellin Pelrine, Sirisha Rambhatla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Private and interpretable clinical prediction with quantum-inspired tensor train models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06110v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Machine learning in clinical settings must balance predictive accuracy, interpretability, and privacy. Models such as logistic regression (LR) offer transparency, while neural networks (NNs) provide greater predictive power; yet both remain vulnerable to privacy attacks. We empirically assess these risks by designing attacks that identify which public datasets were used to train a model under varying levels of adversarial access, applying them to LORIS, a publicly available LR model for immunotherapy response prediction, as well as to additional shallow NN models trained for the same task. Our results show that both models leak significant training-set information, with LRs proving particularly vulnerable in white-box scenarios. Moreover, we observe that common practices such as cross-validation in LRs exacerbate these risks. To mitigate these vulnerabilities, we propose a quantum-inspired defense based on tensorizing discretized models into tensor trains (TTs), which fully obfuscates parameters while preserving accuracy, reducing white-box attacks to random guessing and degrading black-box attacks comparably to Differential Privacy. TT models retain LR interpretability and extend it through efficient computation of marginal and conditional distributions, while also enabling this higher level of interpretability for NNs. Our results demonstrate that tensorization is widely applicable and establishes a practical foundation for private, interpretable, and effective clinical prediction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06110v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Ram\'on Pareja Monturiol, Juliette Sinnott, Roger G. Melko, Mohammad Kohandel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Private Sum Computation: Trade-Offs between Communication, Randomness, and Privacy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06238</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06238v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Consider multiple users and a fusion center. Each user possesses a sequence of bits and can communicate with the fusion center through a one-way public channel. The fusion center's task is to compute the sum of all the sequences under the privacy requirement that a set of colluding users, along with the fusion center, cannot gain more than a predetermined amount $\delta$ of information, measured through mutual information, about the sequences of other users. Our first contribution is to characterize the minimum amount of necessary communication between the users and the fusion center, as well as the minimum amount of necessary randomness at the users. Our second contribution is to establish a connection between private sum computation and secret sharing by showing that secret sharing is necessary to generate the local randomness needed for private sum computation, and prove that it holds true for any $\delta \geq 0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06238v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Remi A. Chou, Joerg Kliewer, Aylin Yener</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TrailBlazer: History-Guided Reinforcement Learning for Black-Box LLM Jailbreaking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06440v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Large Language Models (LLMs) have become integral to many domains, making their safety a critical priority. Prior jailbreaking research has explored diverse approaches, including prompt optimization, automated red teaming, obfuscation, and reinforcement learning (RL) based methods. However, most existing techniques fail to effectively leverage vulnerabilities revealed in earlier interaction turns, resulting in inefficient and unstable attacks. Since jailbreaking involves sequential interactions in which each response influences future actions, reinforcement learning provides a natural framework for this problem. Motivated by this, we propose a history-aware RL-based jailbreak framework that analyzes and reweights vulnerability signals from prior steps to guide future decisions. We show that incorporating historical information alone improves jailbreak success rates. Building on this insight, we introduce an attention-based reweighting mechanism that highlights critical vulnerabilities within the interaction history, enabling more efficient exploration with fewer queries. Extensive experiments on AdvBench and HarmBench demonstrate that our method achieves state-of-the-art jailbreak performance while significantly improving query efficiency. These results underscore the importance of historical vulnerability signals in reinforcement learning-driven jailbreak strategies and offer a principled pathway for advancing adversarial research on LLM safeguards.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06440v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sung-Hoon Yoon, Ruizhi Qian, Minda Zhao, Weiyue Li, Mengyu Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Anti-forensics Attack against Image Forgery Detection via Multi-modal Guidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06530</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06530v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The rapid advancement of AI-Generated Content (AIGC) technologies poses significant challenges for authenticity assessment. However, existing evaluation protocols largely overlook anti-forensics attack, failing to ensure the comprehensive robustness of state-of-the-art AIGC detectors in real-world applications. To bridge this gap, we propose ForgeryEraser, a framework designed to execute universal anti-forensics attack without access to the target AIGC detectors. We reveal an adversarial vulnerability stemming from the systemic reliance on Vision-Language Models (VLMs) as shared backbones (e.g., CLIP), where downstream AIGC detectors inherit the feature space of these publicly accessible models. Instead of traditional logit-based optimization, we design a multi-modal guidance loss to drive forged image embeddings within the VLM feature space toward text-derived authentic anchors to erase forgery traces, while repelling them from forgery anchors. Extensive experiments demonstrate that ForgeryEraser causes substantial performance degradation to advanced AIGC detectors on both global synthesis and local editing benchmarks. Moreover, ForgeryEraser induces explainable forensic models to generate explanations consistent with authentic images for forged images. Our code will be made publicly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06530v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haipeng Li, Rongxuan Peng, Anwei Luo, Shunquan Tan, Changsheng Chen, Anastasia Antsiferova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do Prompts Guarantee Safety? Mitigating Toxicity from LLM Generations through Subspace Intervention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06623</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06623v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Large Language Models (LLMs) are powerful text generators, yet they can produce toxic or harmful content even when given seemingly harmless prompts. This presents a serious safety challenge and can cause real-world harm. Toxicity is often subtle and context-dependent, making it difficult to detect at the token level or through coarse sentence-level signals. Moreover, efforts to mitigate toxicity often face a trade-off between safety and the coherence, or fluency of the generated text. In this work, we present a targeted subspace intervention strategy for identifying and suppressing hidden toxic patterns from underlying model representations, while preserving overall ability to generate safe fluent content. On the RealToxicityPrompts, our method achieves strong mitigation performance compared to existing baselines, with minimal impact on inference complexity. Across multiple LLMs, our approach reduces toxicity of state-of-the-art detoxification systems by 8-20%, while maintaining comparable fluency. Through extensive quantitative and qualitative analyses, we show that our approach achieves effective toxicity reduction without impairing generative performance, consistently outperforming existing baselines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06623v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Himanshu Singh, Ziwei Xu, A. V. Subramanyam, Mohan Kankanhalli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AEGIS: Adversarial Target-Guided Retention-Data-Free Robust Concept Erasure from Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06771v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Concept erasure helps stop diffusion models (DMs) from generating harmful content; but current methods face robustness retention trade off. Robustness means the model fine-tuned by concept erasure methods resists reactivation of erased concepts, even under semantically related prompts. Retention means unrelated concepts are preserved so the model's overall utility stays intact. Both are critical for concept erasure in practice, yet addressing them simultaneously is challenging, as existing works typically improve one factor while sacrificing the other. Prior work typically strengthens one while degrading the other, e.g., mapping a single erased prompt to a fixed safe target leaves class level remnants exploitable by prompt attacks, whereas retention-oriented schemes underperform against adaptive adversaries. This paper introduces Adversarial Erasure with Gradient Informed Synergy (AEGIS), a retention-data-free framework that advances both robustness and retention.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06771v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Accpted in ICLR 2026</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fengpeng Li, Kemou Li, Qizhou Wang, Bo Han, Jiantao Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meta SecAlign: A Secure Foundation LLM Against Prompt Injection Attacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.02735v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Prompt injection attacks, where untrusted data contains an injected prompt to manipulate the system, have been listed as the top security threat to LLM-integrated applications. Model-level prompt injection defenses have shown strong effectiveness, but the strongest defenses are proprietary. Open-source secure models are needed by the AI security community so that co-development of attacks and defenses through open research can drive scientific progress in mitigating prompt injection attacks. To this end, we develop Meta SecAlign, the first fully open-source LLM with built-in model-level defense that achieves commercial-grade performance and is powerful enough for complex agentic tasks. We provide complete details of our training recipe. We perform the most comprehensive evaluation to date on 9 utility benchmarks (measuring general knowledge, instruction following, and agentic workflows) and 7 security benchmarks. Results show that Meta SecAlign, despite being trained only on generic instruction-tuning samples, surprisingly confers security in unseen downstream tasks, including tool-calling and web-navigation, in addition to general instruction-following. Our best model -- Meta-SecAlign-70B -- establishes a new frontier of utility-security trade-off for open-source LLMs, and is more secure than several flagship proprietary models with prompt injection defense. Below are links for the code (https://github.com/facebookresearch/Meta_SecAlign), Meta-SecAlign-70B (https://huggingface.co/facebook/Meta-SecAlign-70B), and Meta-SecAlign-8B (https://huggingface.co/facebook/Meta-SecAlign-8B) models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.02735v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sizhe Chen, Arman Zharmagambetov, David Wagner, Chuan Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FuSeFL: Fully Secure and Scalable Federated Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13591v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Federated Learning (FL) enables collaborative model training without centralizing client data, making it attractive for privacy-sensitive domains. While existing approaches employ cryptographic techniques such as homomorphic encryption, differential privacy, or secure multiparty computation to mitigate inference attacks, including model inversion, membership inference, and gradient leakage, they often suffer from high computational and memory overheads. Moreover, many methods overlook the confidentiality of the global model itself, which may be proprietary and sensitive. These challenges limit the practicality of secure FL, especially in settings that involve large datasets and strict compliance requirements.
  We present FuSeFL, a Fully Secure and scalable FL scheme, which decentralizes training across client pairs using lightweight MPC, while confining the server's role to secure aggregation, client pairing, and routing. This design eliminates server bottlenecks, avoids full data offloading, and preserves full confidentiality of data, model, and updates throughout training. Based on our experiment, FuSeFL defends against unauthorized observation, reconstruction attacks, and inference attacks such as gradient leakage, membership inference, and inversion attacks, while achieving up to $13 \times$ speedup in training time and 50% lower server memory usage compared to our baseline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13591v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sahar Ghoflsaz Ghinani, Elaheh Sadredini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explainable Transformer-Based Email Phishing Classification with Adversarial Robustness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12085v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Phishing and related cyber threats are becoming more varied and technologically advanced. Among these, email-based phishing remains the most dominant and persistent threat. These attacks exploit human vulnerabilities to disseminate malware or gain unauthorized access to sensitive information. Deep learning (DL) models, particularly transformer-based models, have significantly enhanced phishing mitigation through their contextual understanding of language. However, some recent threats, specifically Artificial Intelligence (AI)-generated phishing attacks, are reducing the overall system resilience of phishing detectors. In response, adversarial training has shown promise against AI-generated phishing threats. This study presents a hybrid approach that uses DistilBERT, a smaller, faster, and lighter version of the BERT transformer model for email classification. Robustness against text-based adversarial perturbations is reinforced using Fast Gradient Method (FGM) adversarial training. Furthermore, the framework integrates the LIME Explainable AI (XAI) technique to enhance the transparency of the DistilBERT architecture. The framework also uses the Flan-T5-small language model from Hugging Face to generate plain-language security narrative explanations for end-users. This combined approach ensures precise phishing classification while providing easily understandable justifications for the model's decisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12085v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sajad U P</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sliced R\'enyi Pufferfish Privacy: Directional Additive Noise Mechanism and Private Learning with Gradient Clipping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01115v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the design of a privatization mechanism and privacy accounting in the Pufferfish Privacy (PP) family. Specifically, motivated by the curse of dimensionality and lack of practical composition tools for iterative learning in the recent Renyi Pufferfish Privacy (RPP) framework, we propose Sliced Renyi Pufferfish Privacy (SRPP). SRPP preserves PP/RPP semantics (customizable secrets with probability-aware secret-dataset relationships) while replacing high-dimensional Renyi divergence with projection-based quantification via two sliced measures, Average SRPP and Joint SRPP. We develop sliced Wasserstein mechanisms, yielding sound SRPP certificates and closed-form Gaussian noise calibration. For iterative learning systems, we introduce an SRPP-SGD scheme with gradient clipping and new accountants based on History-Uniform Caps (HUC) and a subsampling-aware variant (sa-HUC), enabling decompose-then-compose privatization and additive composition under a common slicing geometry. Experiments on static and iterative privatization show that the proposed framework exhibits favorable privacy-utility trade-offs, as well as practical scalability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01115v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tao Zhang, Yevgeniy Vorobeychik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DECEPTICON: How Dark Patterns Manipulate Web Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.22894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.22894v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Deceptive UI designs, widely instantiated across the web and commonly known as dark patterns, manipulate users into performing actions misaligned with their goals. In this paper, we show that dark patterns are highly effective in steering agent trajectories, posing a significant risk to agent robustness. To quantify this risk, we introduce DECEPTICON, an environment for testing individual dark patterns in isolation. DECEPTICON includes 700 web navigation tasks with dark patterns -- 600 generated tasks and 100 real-world tasks, designed to measure instruction-following success and dark pattern effectiveness. Across state-of-the-art agents, we find dark patterns successfully steer agent trajectories towards malicious outcomes in over 70% of tested generated and real-world tasks -- compared to a human average of 31%. Moreover, we find that dark pattern effectiveness correlates positively with model size and test-time reasoning, making larger, more capable models more susceptible. Leading countermeasures against adversarial attacks, including in-context prompting and guardrail models, fail to consistently reduce the success rate of dark pattern interventions. Our findings reveal dark patterns as a latent and unmitigated risk to web agents, highlighting the urgent need for robust defenses against manipulative designs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.22894v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Phil Cuvin, Hao Zhu, Diyi Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CIPHER: Cryptographic Insecurity Profiling via Hybrid Evaluation of Responses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.01438v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly used to assist developers with code, yet their implementations of cryptographic functionality often contain exploitable flaws. Minor design choices (e.g., static initialization vectors or missing authentication) can silently invalidate security guarantees. We introduce CIPHER(Cryptographic Insecurity Profiling via Hybrid Evaluation of Responses), a benchmark for measuring cryptographic vulnerability incidence in LLM-generated Python code under controlled security-guidance conditions. CIPHER uses insecure/neutral/secure prompt variants per task, a cryptography-specific vulnerability taxonomy, and line-level attribution via an automated scoring pipeline. Across a diverse set of widely used LLMs, we find that explicit secure prompting reduces some targeted issues but does not reliably eliminate cryptographic vulnerabilities overall. The benchmark and reproducible scoring pipeline will be publicly released upon publication.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.01438v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max Manolov, Tony Gao, Siddharth Shukla, Cheng-Ting Chou, Ryan Lagasse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AgentDyn: A Dynamic Open-Ended Benchmark for Evaluating Prompt Injection Attacks of Real-World Agent Security System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.03117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.03117v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: AI agents that autonomously interact with external tools and environments show great promise across real-world applications. However, the external data which agent consumes also leads to the risk of indirect prompt injection attacks, where malicious instructions embedded in third-party content hijack agent behavior. Guided by benchmarks, such as AgentDojo, there has been significant amount of progress in developing defense against the said attacks. As the technology continues to mature, and that agents are increasingly being relied upon for more complex tasks, there is increasing pressing need to also evolve the benchmark to reflect threat landscape faced by emerging agentic systems. In this work, we reveal three fundamental flaws in current benchmarks and push the frontier along these dimensions: (i) lack of dynamic open-ended tasks, (ii) lack of helpful instructions, and (iii) simplistic user tasks. To bridge this gap, we introduce AgentDyn, a manually designed benchmark featuring 60 challenging open-ended tasks and 560 injection test cases across Shopping, GitHub, and Daily Life. Unlike prior static benchmarks, AgentDyn requires dynamic planning and incorporates helpful third-party instructions. Our evaluation of ten state-of-the-art defenses suggests that almost all existing defenses are either not secure enough or suffer from significant over-defense, revealing that existing defenses are still far from real-world deployment. Our benchmark is available at https://github.com/leolee99/AgentDyn.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.03117v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Li, Ruoyao Wen, Shanghao Shi, Ning Zhang, Chaowei Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spider-Sense: Intrinsic Risk Sensing for Efficient Agent Defense with Hierarchical Adaptive Screening</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05386v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: As large language models (LLMs) evolve into autonomous agents, their real-world applicability has expanded significantly, accompanied by new security challenges. Most existing agent defense mechanisms adopt a mandatory checking paradigm, in which security validation is forcibly triggered at predefined stages of the agent lifecycle. In this work, we argue that effective agent security should be intrinsic and selective rather than architecturally decoupled and mandatory. We propose Spider-Sense framework, an event-driven defense framework based on Intrinsic Risk Sensing (IRS), which allows agents to maintain latent vigilance and trigger defenses only upon risk perception. Once triggered, the Spider-Sense invokes a hierarchical defence mechanism that trades off efficiency and precision: it resolves known patterns via lightweight similarity matching while escalating ambiguous cases to deep internal reasoning, thereby eliminating reliance on external models. To facilitate rigorous evaluation, we introduce S$^2$Bench, a lifecycle-aware benchmark featuring realistic tool execution and multi-stage attacks. Extensive experiments demonstrate that Spider-Sense achieves competitive or superior defense performance, attaining the lowest Attack Success Rate (ASR) and False Positive Rate (FPR), with only a marginal latency overhead of 8.3\%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05386v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenxiong Yu, Zhi Yang, Zhiheng Jin, Shuhe Wang, Heng Zhang, Yanlin Fei, Lingfeng Zeng, Fangqi Lou, Shuo Zhang, Tu Hu, Jingping Liu, Rongze Chen, Xingyu Zhu, Kunyi Wang, Chaofa Yuan, Xin Guo, Zhaowei Liu, Feipeng Zhang, Jie Huang, Huacan Wang, Ronghao Chen, Liwen Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpreting Manifolds and Graph Neural Embeddings from Internet of Things Traffic Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05817</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05817v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The rapid expansion of Internet of Things (IoT) ecosystems has led to increasingly complex and heterogeneous network topologies. Traditional network monitoring and visualization tools rely on aggregated metrics or static representations, which fail to capture the evolving relationships and structural dependencies between devices. Although Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) offer a powerful way to learn from relational data, their internal representations often remain opaque and difficult to interpret for security-critical operations. Consequently, this work introduces an interpretable pipeline that generates directly visualizable low-dimensional representations by mapping high-dimensional embeddings onto a latent manifold. This projection enables the interpretable monitoring and interoperability of evolving network states, while integrated feature attribution techniques decode the specific characteristics shaping the manifold structure. The framework achieves a classification F1-score of 0.830 for intrusion detection while also highlighting phenomena such as concept drift. Ultimately, the presented approach bridges the gap between high-dimensional GNN embeddings and human-understandable network behavior, offering new insights for network administrators and security analysts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05817v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrique Feito-Casares, Francisco M. Melgarejo-Meseguer, Elena Casiraghi, Giorgio Valentini, Jos\'e-Luis Rojo-\'Alvarez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient LLM Moderation with Multi-Layer Latent Prototypes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.16174v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Although modern LLMs are aligned with human values during post-training, robust moderation remains essential to prevent harmful outputs at deployment time. Existing approaches suffer from performance-efficiency trade-offs and are difficult to customize to user-specific requirements. Motivated by this gap, we introduce Multi-Layer Prototype Moderator (MLPM), a lightweight and highly customizable input moderation tool. We propose leveraging prototypes of intermediate representations across multiple layers to improve moderation quality while maintaining high efficiency. By design, our method adds negligible overhead to the generation pipeline and can be seamlessly applied to any model. MLPM achieves state-of-the-art performance on diverse moderation benchmarks and demonstrates strong scalability across model families of various sizes. Moreover, we show that it integrates smoothly into end-to-end moderation pipelines and further improves response safety when combined with output moderation techniques. Overall, our work provides a practical and adaptable solution for safe, robust, and efficient LLM deployment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.16174v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maciej Chrab\k{a}szcz, Filip Szatkowski, Bartosz W\'ojcik, Jan Dubi\'nski, Tomasz Trzci\'nski, Sebastian Cygert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SafeCOMM: A Study on Safety Degradation in Fine-Tuned Telecom Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00062v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Fine-tuning large language models (LLMs) on telecom datasets is a common practice to adapt general-purpose models to the telecom domain. However, little attention has been paid to how this process may compromise model safety. Recent research has shown that even benign fine-tuning can degrade the safety alignment of LLMs, causing them to respond to harmful or unethical user queries. In this paper, we investigate this issue by fine-tuning LLMs on three representative telecom datasets and show that safety degrades even for light telecom domain adaptation. To this end, we introduce TeleHarm, the first telecom-specific red-teaming benchmark, which we use alongside established DirectHarm and HexPhi datasets to systematically assess harmful behavior. We further extend our analysis to publicly available TeleLLMs that were continually pre-trained on large telecom corpora, revealing that safety alignment is severely lacking, primarily due to the omission of safety-focused instruction tuning. To address these issues, we evaluate three realignment defenses: SafeInstruct, SafeLoRA, SafeMERGE. We show that, across all settings, the proposed defenses can effectively restore safety without compromising telecom task performance, leading to Safe teleCOMMunication (SafeCOMM) models. Our work serves as both a diagnostic study and practical guide for safety realignment in telecom-tuned LLMs, underscoring the need for safety-aware instruction and fine-tuning in the telecom domain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00062v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Wireless Communications and Networking Conference (WCNC), 2026</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Aladin Djuhera, Swanand Ravindra Kadhe, Farhan Ahmed, Syed Zawad, Fernando Koch, Walid Saad, Holger Boche</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Layer of Truth: Probing Belief Shifts under Continual Pre-Training Poisoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26829v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that continual pretraining on plausible misinformation can overwrite specific factual knowledge in large language models without degrading overall performance. Unlike prior poisoning work under static pretraining, we study repeated exposure to counterfactual claims during continual updates. Using paired fact-counterfact items with graded poisoning ratios, we track how internal preferences between competing facts evolve across checkpoints, layers, and model scales. Even moderate poisoning (50-100%) flips over 55% of responses from correct to counterfactual while leaving ambiguity nearly unchanged. These belief flips emerge abruptly, concentrate in late layers (e.g., Layers 29-36 in 3B models), and are partially reversible via patching (up to 56.8%). The corrupted beliefs generalize beyond poisoned prompts, selectively degrading commonsense reasoning while leaving alignment benchmarks largely intact and transferring imperfectly across languages. These results expose a failure mode of continual pre-training in which targeted misinformation replaces internal factual representations without triggering broad performance collapse, motivating representation-level monitoring of factual integrity during model updates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26829v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Svetlana Churina, Niranjan Chebrolu, Kokil Jaidka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GraphToxin: Reconstructing Full Unlearned Graphs from Graph Unlearning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10936</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10936v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Graph unlearning has emerged as a promising solution to comply with "the right to be forgotten" regulations by enabling the removal of sensitive information upon request. However, this solution is not foolproof. The involvement of multiple parties creates new attack surfaces, and residual traces of deleted data can still remain in the unlearned graph neural networks (GNNs). These vulnerabilities can be exploited by attackers to recover the supposedly erased samples, thereby undermining the intended functionality of graph unlearning. In this work, we propose GraphToxin, the first full graph reconstruction attack against graph unlearning. Specifically, we introduce a novel curvature matching module to provide fine-grained guidance for unlearned graph recovery. We demonstrate that GraphToxin can successfully subvert the regulatory guarantees expected from graph unlearning, it can recover not only a deleted individual's information and personal links but also sensitive content from their connections, thereby posing substantially more detrimental threats. Furthermore, we extend GraphToxin to multiple-node removal under both white-box and black-box settings, showcasing its practical feasibility and potential to cause considerable harm. We highlight the necessity of worst-case analysis and propose a systematic evaluation framework to assess attack performance under both random and worst-case node removal scenarios. Our extensive experiments demonstrate the effectiveness and flexibility of GraphToxin. Notably, existing defense mechanisms are largely ineffective against this attack or even amplify its performance in some cases. Given the severe privacy risks posed by GraphToxin, our work underscores the urgent need for more effective and robust defenses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10936v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ying Song, Balaji Palanisamy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of Shuffling Beyond Pure Local Differential Privacy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19154</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.19154v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Shuffling is a powerful way to amplify privacy of a local randomizer in private distributed data analysis, but existing analyses mostly treat the local differential privacy (DP) parameter $\varepsilon_0$ as the only knob and give generic upper bounds that can be loose and do not even characterize how shuffling amplifies privacy for basic mechanisms such as the Gaussian mechanism. We revisit the privacy blanket bound of Balle et al. (the blanket divergence) and develop an asymptotic analysis that applies to a broad class of local randomizers under mild regularity assumptions, without requiring pure local DP. Our key finding is that the leading term of the blanket divergence depends on the local mechanism only through a single scalar parameter $\chi$, which we call the shuffle index. By applying this asymptotic analysis to both upper and lower bounds, we obtain a tight band for $\delta_n$ in the shuffled mechanism's $(\varepsilon_n,\delta_n)$-DP guarantee. Moreover, we derive a simple structural necessary and sufficient condition on the local randomizer under which the blanket-divergence-based upper and lower bounds coincide asymptotically. $k$-RR families with $k\ge3$ satisfy this condition, while for generalized Gaussian mechanisms the condition may not hold but the resulting band remains tight. Finally, we complement the asymptotic theory with an FFT-based algorithm for computing the blanket divergence at finite $n$, which offers rigorously controlled relative error and near-linear running time in $n$, providing a practical numerical analysis for shuffle DP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.19154v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shun Takagi, Seng Pei Liew</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing Storage-System Correctness: Challenges, Fuzzing Limitations, and AI-Augmented Opportunities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.02614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.02614v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Storage systems are fundamental to modern computing infrastructures, yet ensuring their correctness remains challenging in practice. Despite decades of research on system testing, many storage-system failures (including durability, ordering, recovery, and consistency violations) remain difficult to expose systematically. This difficulty stems not primarily from insufficient testing tooling, but from intrinsic properties of storage-system execution, including nondeterministic interleavings, long-horizon state evolution, and correctness semantics that span multiple layers and execution phases.
  This survey adopts a storage-centric view of system testing and organizes existing techniques according to the execution properties and failure mechanisms they target. We review a broad spectrum of approaches, ranging from concurrency testing and long-running workloads to crash-consistency analysis, hardware-level semantic validation, and distributed fault injection, and analyze their fundamental strengths and limitations. Within this framework, we examine fuzzing as an automated testing paradigm, highlighting systematic mismatches between conventional fuzzing assumptions and storage-system semantics, and discuss how recent artificial intelligence advances may complement fuzzing through state-aware and semantic guidance. Overall, this survey provides a unified perspective on storage-system correctness testing and outlines key challenges</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.02614v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ying Wang, Jiahui Chen, Dejun Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
