<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.med-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.med-ph</link>
    <description>physics.med-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.med-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 04:06:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative Evaluation of Microstrip, Dipole, and L/C Loop pTx Arrays for UHF MR Imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.15392v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ultra-high field MRI (7T+) unlocks a new era of brain research with superior resolution and signal-to-noise. Capturing intricate neural activity and detailed soft tissue pathology, this technology, coupled with advanced RF coil arrays, holds immense potential for clinical diagnosis and discovery. For high-field body imaging, microstrip resonators and dipole arrays for high-field body imaging show promise due to high-frequency operation and improved decoupling. Microstrip arrays excel in compactness, reduced radiation loss, and customizable lengths. Dipole arrays excel in deeper body penetration. Shorter wavelengths at ultrahigh fields can cause image inhomogeneity and elevated SAR. Multichannel transmit arrays address these issues. This research compares three common array types (L/C loop, microstrip, dipole) using CST Studio simulations to evaluate electric/magnetic fields and decoupling. This can guide RF array selection for ultrahigh field MRI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.15392v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debolina De, Aditya A. Bhosale, Dr. Xiaoliang Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gradient-enhanced modeling of poro-visco-hyperelasticity-induced time-dependent fracture of blood clots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.15432v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fracture resistance of blood clots plays a crucial role in physiological hemostasis and pathological thromboembolism. Although recent experimental and computational studies uncovered the poro-viscoelastic property of blood clots and its connection to the time-dependent deformation behavior, the effect of these time-dependent processes on clot fracture and the underlying time-dependent fracture mechanisms are not well understood. This work aims to formulate a thermodynamically consistent, multi-physics theoretical framework for describing the time-dependent deformation and fracture of blood clots. This theory concurrently couples fluid transport through porous fibrin networks, non-linear visco-hyperelastic deformation of the solid skeleton, solid/fluid interactions, mechanical degradation of tissues, gradient enhancement of energy, and protein unfolding of fibrin molecules. The constitutive relations of tissue constituents and the governing equation of fluid transport are derived within the framework of porous media theory by extending non-linear continuum thermodynamics at large strains. A physics-based, compressible network model is developed for the fibrin network of blood clots to describe its mechanical response. An energy-based damage model is developed to predict the damage and fracture of blood clots, and a transient non-local characterization length function is proposed to limit the damage zone bandwidth. The proposed model is experimentally validated using single-edge cracked clot specimens with different constituents. The fracture of blood clots subject to different loading conditions is simulated, and the mechanisms of clot fracture are systematically analyzed. Computational results show that the viscoelasticity and fluid transport play essential roles in the fracture of blood clots under physiological loading.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.15432v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongxu Liu, Nhung Nguyen, Tinh Quoc Bui, Luka Pocivavsek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automated radiotherapy treatment planning guided by GPT-4Vision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15609</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.15609v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Radiotherapy treatment planning is a time-consuming and potentially subjective process that requires the iterative adjustment of model parameters to balance multiple conflicting objectives. Recent advancements in large foundation models offer promising avenues for addressing the challenges in planning and clinical decision-making. This study introduces GPT-RadPlan, a fully automated treatment planning framework that harnesses prior radiation oncology knowledge encoded in multi-modal large language models, such as GPT-4Vision (GPT-4V) from OpenAI. GPT-RadPlan is made aware of planning protocols as context and acts as an expert human planner, capable of guiding a treatment planning process. Via in-context learning, we incorporate clinical protocols for various disease sites as prompts to enable GPT-4V to acquire treatment planning domain knowledge. The resulting GPT-RadPlan agent is integrated into our in-house inverse treatment planning system through an API. The efficacy of the automated planning system is showcased using multiple prostate and head &amp; neck cancer cases, where we compared GPT-RadPlan results to clinical plans. In all cases, GPT-RadPlan either outperformed or matched the clinical plans, demonstrating superior target coverage and organ-at-risk sparing. Consistently satisfying the dosimetric objectives in the clinical protocol, GPT-RadPlan represents the first multimodal large language model agent that mimics the behaviors of human planners in radiation oncology clinics, achieving remarkable results in automating the treatment planning process without the need for additional training.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.15609v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sheng Liu, Oscar Pastor-Serrano, Yizheng Chen, Matthew Gopaulchan, Weixing Liang, Mark Buyyounouski, Erqi Pollom, Quynh-Thu Le, Michael Gensheimer, Peng Dong, Yong Yang, James Zou, Lei Xing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Functional photoacoustic noninvasive Doppler angiography in humans</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.15696v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optical imaging of blood flow yields critical functional insights into the circulatory system, but its clinical implementation has typically been limited to shallow depths (~1 millimeter) due to light scattering in biological tissue. Here, we present photoacoustic noninvasive Doppler angiography (PANDA) for deep blood flow imaging. PANDA synergizes the photoacoustic and Doppler effects to generate color Doppler velocity and power Doppler blood flow maps of the vascular lumen. Our results demonstrate PANDA's ability to measure blood flow in vivo up to one centimeter in depth, marking approximately an order of magnitude improvement over existing high-resolution pure optical modalities. PANDA enhances photoacoustic flow imaging by increasing depth and enabling cross-sectional blood vessel imaging. We also showcase PANDA's clinical feasibility through three-dimensional imaging of blood flow in healthy subjects and a patient with varicose veins. By integrating the imaging system onto a mobile platform, we have designed PANDA to be a portable modality that is primed for expedient clinical translation. PANDA offers noninvasive, single modality imaging of hemoglobin and blood flow with three-dimensional capability, facilitating comprehensive assessment of deep vascular dynamics in humans.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.15696v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Zhang, Joshua Olick-Gibson, Karteekeya Sastry, Lihong V. Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CEST-KAN: Kolmogorov-Arnold Networks for CEST MRI Data Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16026</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16026v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Purpose: To propose and investigate the feasibility of using Kolmogorov-Arnold Network (KAN) for CEST MRI data analysis (CEST-KAN). Methods: CEST MRI data were acquired from twelve healthy volunteers at 3T. Data from ten subjects were used for training, while the remaining two were reserved for testing. The performance of multi-layer perceptron (MLP) and KAN models with the same network settings were evaluated and compared to the conventional multi-pool Lorentzian fitting (MPLF) method in generating water and multiple CEST contrasts, including amide, relayed nuclear Overhauser effect (rNOE), and magnetization transfer (MT). Results: The water and CEST maps generated by both MLP and KAN were visually comparable to the MPLF results. However, the KAN model demonstrated higher accuracy in extrapolating the CEST fitting metrics, as evidenced by the smaller validation loss during training and smaller absolute error during testing. Voxel-wise correlation analysis showed that all four CEST fitting metrics generated by KAN consistently exhibited higher Pearson coefficients than the MLP results, indicating superior performance. Moreover, the KAN models consistently outperformed the MLP models in varying hidden layer numbers despite longer training time. Conclusion: In this study, we demonstrated for the first time the feasibility of utilizing KAN for CEST MRI data analysis, highlighting its superiority over MLP in this task. The findings suggest that CEST-KAN has the potential to be a robust and reliable post-analysis tool for CEST MRI in clinical settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16026v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiawen Wang, Pei Cai, Ziyan Wang, Huabin Zhang, Jianpan Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geodesic-based Predictive Shape Modeling on Right Ventricles of Patients with Hypoplastic Left Heart Syndrome</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16267v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hypoplastic left heart syndrome (HLHS) is a congenital defect in which right ventricle (RV) shape changes over time in response to altered loading conditions as adaptations to patient's single ventricle physiology. The RV shape can be considered as a co-indicator of the severity of underlying tricuspid valve (TV) regurgitation in HLHS, thus the accurate prediction on RV shape could potentially help predict valve dysfunction and timing of TV failure to inform clinical decision. A geodesic-based predictive shape modeling framework is proposed in this work with application to the RVs of a cohort of 15 HLHS patients as a pilot study. We show that reasonable predictions on stage 1 RV shapes can generated using pre-stage 1 RV shapes and merely two predictors from prior clinical and demographic measures. The study results show great promise towards further experiments for improved prediction results by incorporating more detailed demographic and shape information into the proposed predictive model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16267v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ye Han, James Fishbaugh, Jared Vicory, Matthew Jolley, Beatriz Paniagua</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiscale Mechanical Modeling of Skeletal Muscle: A Systemic Review of the Literature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16433</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16433v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Purpose: From the myofibrils to the whole muscle scale, muscle micro-constituents exhibit passive and active mechanical properties, potentially coupled to electrical, chemical, and thermal properties. Experimental characterization of some of these properties is currently not available for all muscle constituents. Multiscale multiphysics models have recently gained interest as a numerical alternative to investigate the healthy and diseased physiological behavior of the skeletal muscle. Methods: This paper refers to the multiscale mechanical models proposed in the literature to investigate the mechanical properties and behavior of skeletal muscles. More specifically, we focus on the scale transition methods, constitutive laws and experimental data implemented in these models. Results: Using scale transition methods such as homogenization, coupled to appropriate constitutive behavior of the constituents, these models explore the mechanisms of ageing, myopathies, sportive injuries, and muscle contraction. Conclusion: Emerging trends include the development of multiphysics simulations and the coupling of modeling with the acquisition of experimental data at different scales, with increasing focus to little known constituents such as the extracellular matrix and the protein titin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16433v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s40846-024-00879-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Aude Loumeaud (ICube, BMBI), Philippe Pouletaut (BMBI), Sabine Bensamoun (BMBI), Daniel George (ICube), Simon Chatelin (ICube)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D distortion-free, reduced field of view diffusion-prepared GRE at 3T</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16809v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Purpose: To develop a 3D distortion-free reduced-FOV diffusion-prepared GRE sequence and demonstrate its in-vivo application for diffusion imaging of the spinal cord in healthy volunteers. Methods: A 3D multi-shot reduced-FOV diffusion-prepared GRE (RFOV-DP-GRE) acquisition is achieved using a slice-selective tip-down pulse in the phase encoding direction in the diffusion preparation, combined with magnitude stabilisers. The efficacy of the developed reduced FOV approach and accuracy of ADC estimates were evaluated in a phantom. In addition, 5 healthy volunteers were enrolled and scanned at 3T using the proposed sequence and a standard spin echo diffusion-weighted single-shot EPI sequence (DW-SS-EPI) for spinal cord imaging. Image quality, perceived SNR and image distortion were assessed by two expert readers and quantitative measurements of apparent SNR were performed. Results: The phantom scan demonstrates the efficacy of the proposed reduced FOV approach. Consistent ADC estimates were measured with RFOV-DP-GRE when compared with DW-SS-EPI. In-vivo, RFOV-DP-GRE demonstrated improved image quality and reduced perceived distortion, while maintaining perceived SNR compared to DW-SS-EPI. Conclusion: 3D Distortion-free diffusion-prepared imaging can be achieved using the proposed sequence</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16809v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sarah McElroy, Raphael Tomi-Tricot, Jon Cleary, Shawna Kinsella, Sami Jeljeli, Vicky Goh, Radhouene Neji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A comprehensive overview of diffuse correlation spectroscopy: theoretical framework, recent advances in hardware, analysis, and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.15420v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Diffuse correlation spectroscopy (DCS) is a powerful tool for assessing microvascular hemodynamic in deep tissues. Recent advances in sensors, lasers, and deep learning have further boosted the development of new DCS methods. However, newcomers might feel overwhelmed, not only by the already complex DCS theoretical framework but also by the broad range of component options and system architectures. To facilitate new entry into this exciting field, we present a comprehensive review of DCS hardware architectures (continuous-wave, frequency-domain, and time-domain) and summarize corresponding theoretical models. Further, we discuss new applications of highly integrated silicon single-photon avalanche diode (SPAD) sensors in DCS, compare SPADs with existing sensors, and review other components (lasers, fibers, and correlators), as well as new data analysis tools, including deep learning. Potential applications in medical diagnosis are discussed, and an outlook for the future directions is provided, to offer effective guidance to embark on DCS research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.15420v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quan Wang, Mingliang Pan, Lucas Kreiss, Saeed Samaei, Stefan A. Carp, Johannes D. Johansson, Yuanzhe Zhang, Melissa Wu, Roarke Horstmeyer, Mamadou Diop, David Day-Uei Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Miniature fluorescence sensor for quantitative detection of brain tumour</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15520</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.15520v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fluorescence-guided surgery has emerged as a vital tool for tumour resection procedures. As well as intraoperative tumour visualisation, 5-ALA-induced PpIX provides an avenue for quantitative tumour identification based on ratiometric fluorescence measurement. To this end, fluorescence imaging and fibre-based probes have enabled more precise demarcation between the cancerous and healthy tissues. These sensing approaches, which rely on collecting the fluorescence light from the tumour resection site and its remote spectral sensing, introduce challenges associated with optical losses. In this work, we demonstrate the viability of tumour detection at the resection site using a miniature fluorescence measurement system. Unlike the current bulky systems, which necessitate remote measurement, we have adopted a millimetre-sized spectral sensor chip for quantitative fluorescence measurements. A reliable measurement at the resection site requires a stable optical window between the tissue and the optoelectronic system. This is achieved using an antifouling diamond window, which provides stable optical transparency. The system achieved a sensitivity of 92.3% and specificity of 98.3% in detecting a surrogate tumour at a resolution of 1 x 1 mm2. As well as addressing losses associated with collecting and coupling fluorescence light in the current remote sensing approaches, the small size of the system introduced in this work paves the way for its direct integration with the tumour resection tools with the aim of more accurate interoperative tumour identification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.15520v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1039/D3LC00982C</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Lab on a Chip 24.4 (2024): 946-954</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jean Pierre Ndabakuranye, James Belcourt, Deepak Sharma, Cathal D. O'Connell, Victor Mondal, Sanjay K. Srivastava, Alastair Stacey, Sam Long, Bobbi Fleiss, Arman Ahnood</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Texture Feature Analysis for Classification of Early-Stage Prostate Cancer in mpMRI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15571</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.15571v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) has become a crucial tool in the diagnosis and staging of prostate cancer, owing to its superior tissue contrast. However, it also creates large volumes of data that must be assessed by trained experts, a time-consuming and laborious task. This has prompted the development of machine learning tools for the automation of Prostate cancer (PCa) risk classification based on multiple MRI modalities (T2W, ADC, and high-b-value DWI). Understanding and interpreting the predictions made by the models, however, remains a challenge. We analyze Random Forests (RF) and Support Vector Machines (SVM), for two complementary datasets, the public Prostate-X dataset, and an in-house, mostly early-stage PCa dataset to elucidate the contributions made by first-order statistical features, Haralick texture features, and local binary patterns to the classification. Using correlation analysis and Shapley impact scores, we find that many of the features typically used are strongly correlated, and that the majority of features have negligible impact on the classification. We identify a small set of features that determine the classification outcome, which may aid the development of explainable AI approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.15571v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Asmail Muftah, S M Schirmer, Frank C Langbein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demystifying the Effect of Receptive Field Size in U-Net Models for Medical Image Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16701v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Medical image segmentation is a critical task in healthcare applications, and U-Nets have demonstrated promising results. This work delves into the understudied aspect of receptive field (RF) size and its impact on the U-Net and Attention U-Net architectures. This work explores several critical elements including the relationship between RF size, characteristics of the region of interest, and model performance, as well as the balance between RF size and computational costs for U-Net and Attention U-Net methods for different datasets. This work also proposes a mathematical notation for representing the theoretical receptive field (TRF) of a given layer in a network and proposes two new metrics - effective receptive field (ERF) rate and the Object rate to quantify the fraction of significantly contributing pixels within the ERF against the TRF area and assessing the relative size of the segmentation object compared to the TRF size respectively. The results demonstrate that there exists an optimal TRF size that successfully strikes a balance between capturing a wider global context and maintaining computational efficiency, thereby optimizing model performance. Interestingly, a distinct correlation is observed between the data complexity and the required TRF size; segmentation based solely on contrast achieved peak performance even with smaller TRF sizes, whereas more complex segmentation tasks necessitated larger TRFs. Attention U-Net models consistently outperformed their U-Net counterparts, highlighting the value of attention mechanisms regardless of TRF size. These novel insights present an invaluable resource for developing more efficient U-Net-based architectures for medical imaging and pave the way for future exploration. A tool is also developed that calculates the TRF for a U-Net (and Attention U-Net) model, and also suggest an appropriate TRF size for a given model and dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16701v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincent Loos, Rohit Pardasani, Navchetan Awasthi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral CT Two-step and One-step Material Decomposition using Diffusion Posterior Sampling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10183v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper proposes a novel approach to spectral computed tomography (CT) material decomposition that uses the recent advances in generative diffusion models (DMs) for inverse problems. Spectral CT and more particularly photon-counting CT (PCCT) can perform transmission measurements at different energy levels which can be used for material decomposition. It is an ill-posed inverse problem and therefore requires regularization. DMs are a class of generative model that can be used to solve inverse problems via diffusion posterior sampling (DPS). In this paper we adapt DPS for material decomposition in a PCCT setting. We propose two approaches, namely Two-step Diffusion Posterior Sampling (TDPS) and One-step Diffusion Posterior Sampling (ODPS). Early results from an experiment with simulated low-dose PCCT suggest that DPSs have the potential to outperform state-of-the-art model-based iterative reconstruction (MBIR). Moreover, our results indicate that TDPS produces material images with better peak signal-to-noise ratio (PSNR) than images produced with ODPS with similar structural similarity (SSIM).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10183v3</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Corentin Vazia, Alexandre Bousse, Jacques Froment, B\'eatrice Vedel, Franck Vermet, Zhihan Wang, Thore Dassow, Jean-Pierre Tasu, Dimitris Visvikis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radiomics-based artificial intelligence (AI) models in colorectal cancer (CRC) diagnosis, metastasis detection, prognosis, and treatment response</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12467v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: With a high rate of morbidity and mortality, colorectal cancer (CRC) ranks third in mortality among cancers. By analyzing the texture properties of images and quantifying the heterogeneity of tumors, radiomics and radiogenomics are non-invasive methods to determine the biological properties of CRC. Recently, several articles have discussed the application of radiomics in different aspects of CRC. Therefore, given the large amount of data published, this review aims to discuss how radiomics can be used for distinguishing benign and malignant colorectal lesions, diagnosing, staging, predicting prognosis and treatment response, and predicting lymph node and hepatic metastasis of CRC, based on radiomic features extracted from magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), computed tomography (CT), esophageal ultrasonography (EUS), and positron emission tomography-CT (PET-CT). Challenges in bringing radiomics to clinical application and future solutions have also been discussed. With the progress made in radiomics and the application of deep and machine learning in this area, radiomics can become one of the main tools for the personalized management of CRC patients shortly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12467v2</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Parsa Karami, Reza Elahi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep-Learning Approach for Tissue Classification using Acoustic Waves during Ablation with an Er:YAG Laser (Updated)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14570v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Today's mechanical tools for bone cutting (osteotomy) cause mechanical trauma that prolongs the healing process. Medical device manufacturers aim to minimize this trauma, with minimally invasive surgery using laser cutting as one innovation. This method ablates tissue using laser light instead of mechanical tools, reducing post-surgery healing time. A reliable feedback system is crucial during laser surgery to prevent damage to surrounding tissues. We propose a tissue classification method analyzing acoustic waves generated during laser ablation, demonstrating its applicability in an ex-vivo experiment. The ablation process with a microsecond pulsed Er:YAG laser produces acoustic waves, acquired with an air-coupled transducer. These waves were used to classify five porcine tissue types: hard bone, soft bone, muscle, fat, and skin. For automated tissue classification, we compared five Neural Network (NN) approaches: a one-dimensional Convolutional Neural Network (CNN) with time-dependent input, a Fully-connected Neural Network (FcNN) with either the frequency spectrum or principal components of the frequency spectrum as input, and a combination of a CNN and an FcNN with time-dependent data and its frequency spectrum as input. Consecutive acoustic waves were used to improve classification accuracy. Grad-Cam identified the activation map of the frequencies, showing low frequencies as the most important for this task. Our results indicated that combining time-dependent data with its frequency spectrum achieved the highest classification accuracy (65.5%-75.5%). We also found that using the frequency spectrum alone was sufficient, with no additional benefit from applying Principal Components Analysis (PCA).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14570v2</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>q-bio.TO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlo Seppi, Philippe C. Cattin</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
