<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.med-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.med-ph</link>
    <description>physics.med-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.med-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 09:03:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Methodology of safety evaluation of In-Vessel Retention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14522v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Molten corium stabilization following a severe accident is of crucial importance in order to ensure containment integrity on a long-term basis and minimizing radioactive elements releases outside the plant. Among the possible options, In-Vessel Retention (IVR) through external cooling appears as an attractive solution that would limit the dispersion of corium in the plant and minimize the risks of containment failure. Nevertheless its feasibility has to be proved.The IVR strategy is already adopted in Europe for some VVER 440 type 213 reactors thanks to thorough research work started in the '90s for the Finnish Loviisa power plant, and subsequently extended to Bohunice and Mochovce (Slovakia), Dukovany (Czech Republic) and Paks (Hungary) power plants. The strategy is also included in the design of some high power new Gen.III reactors such as AP1000, APR 1400 and Chinese HPR1000 and CAP1400. It has also been studied in the past for other reactor concepts like KERENA (1250 MWe - BWR), AP600 or VVER-640.Current approaches for reactors with relatively small power, such as VVER 440 or AP600, use conservative assumptions for the safety demonstration. However, for higher power reactors (around 1000 MWe), the safety margin is reduced and it is necessary to evaluate the IVR strategy with best-estimate methods in order to reduce the uncertainties associated with the involved phenomena. Additional R&amp;D as well as a revision of the methodology are needed to ensure and demonstrate adequate safety margins, including, in particular, best-estimate evaluations of thermal load applied on the vessel and mechanical resistance of the ablated vessel.The IVMR project (In-Vessel Melt Retention) was built with the goal of providing new knowledge (experimental, theoretical and technical) and a new methodology able to provide a best-estimate evaluation of IVR strategy for large power reactors. The main objective of Task 2.1 within WP2 was to define a common methodology to analyse IVR Severe Accident Management (SAM) strategy for the different types of EU NPPs. It started by reviewing the status of existing methodology and aimed at elaborating a more general, updated and less conservative one applicable to several types of reactors.This paper describes the proposed new methodology. It starts with the identification of the deficiencies of the standard methodology when it is applied to a high power reactor. It introduces the minimum vessel thickness as a parameter representing the cumulated imbalance between internal heat load and external cooling. Then it explains how to use that parameter in the evaluation of the safety margin. Although some examples are given as illustrations, it must be kept in mind that this paper proposes a generic methodology but there cannot be any generic conclusion: any reactor design must be evaluated independently.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14522v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Florian Fichot (IRSN/PSN-RES/SAM/LEPC), Laure Car\'enini (IRSN/PSN-RES/SAM/LEPC), Stephan Brumm (JRC), Marco Sangiorgi (JRC)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Patient-specific prediction of regional lung mechanics in ARDS patients with physics-based models: A validation study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14607v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The choice of lung protective ventilation settings for mechanical ventilation has a considerable impact on patient outcome, yet identifying optimal ventilatory settings for individual patients remains highly challenging due to the inherent inter- and intra-patient pathophysiological variability. In this validation study, we demonstrate that physics-based computational lung models tailored to individual patients can resolve this variability, allowing us to predict the otherwise unknown local state of the pathologically affected lung during mechanical ventilation. For seven ARDS patients undergoing invasive mechanical ventilation, physics-based, patient-specific lung models were created using chest CT scans and ventilatory data. By numerically resolving the interaction of the pathological lung with the airway pressure and flow imparted by the ventilator, we predict the time-dependent and heterogeneous local state of the lung for each patient and compare it against the regional ventilation obtained from bedside monitoring using Electrical Impedance Tomography. Excellent agreement between numerical simulations and experimental data was obtained, with the model-predicted anteroposterior ventilation profile achieving a Pearson correlation of 96% with the clinical reference data. Even when considering the regional ventilation within the entire transverse chest cross-section and across the entire dynamic ventilation range, an average correlation of more than 81% and an average root mean square error of less than 15% were achieved. The results of this first systematic validation study demonstrate the ability of computational models to provide clinically relevant information and thereby open the door for a truly patient-specific choice of ventilator settings on the basis of both individual anatomy and pathophysiology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14607v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maximilian Rixner, Maximilian Ludwig, Matthias Lindner, In\'ez Frerichs, Armin Sablewski, Karl-Robert Wichmann, Max-Carl Wachter, Kei W. M\"uller, Dirk Sch\"adler, Wolfgang A. Wall, Jonas Biehler, Tobias Becher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D{\pi}: Three-Dimensional Positron Imaging, A Novel Total-Body PET Scanner Using Xenon-Doped Liquid Argon Scintillator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14645</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14645v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Objective: This paper introduces a novel PET imaging methodology called 3-dimensional positron imaging (3D{\pi}), which integrates total-body (TB) coverage, time-of-flight (TOF) technology, ultra-low dose imaging capabilities, and ultra-fast readout electronics inspired by emerging technology from the DarkSide collaboration. Approach: The study evaluates the performance of 3D{\pi} using Monte Carlo simulations based on NEMA NU 2-2018 protocols. The methodology employs a homogenous, monolithic scintillator composed of liquid argon (LAr) doped with xenon (Xe) with silicon photomultipliers (SiPM) operating at cryogenic temperatures. Main results: Significant enhancements in system performance are observed, with the 3D{\pi} system achieving a noise equivalent count rate (NECR) of 3.2 Mcps which is approximately two times higher than uEXPLORER's peak NECR (1.5 Mcps) at 17.3 (kBq/mL). Spatial resolution measurements show an average FWHM of 2.7 mm across both axial positions. The system exhibits superior sensitivity, with values reaching 373 kcps/MBq with a line source at the center of the field of view. Additionally, 3D{\pi} achieves a TOF resolution of 151 ps at 5.3 kBq/mL, highlighting its potential to produce high-quality images with reduced noise levels. Significance: The study underscores the potential of 3D{\pi} in improving PET imaging performance, offering the potential for shorter scan times and reduced radiation exposure for patients. The Xe-doped LAr offers advantages such as fast scintillation, enhanced light yield, and cost-effectiveness. Future research will focus on optimizing system geometry and further refining reconstruction algorithms to exploit the strengths of 3D{\pi} for clinical applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14645v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Azam Zabihi, Xinran Li, Alejandro Ramirez, Manuel D. Da Rocha Rolo, Davide Franco, Federico Gabriele, Cristiano Galbiati, Michela Lai, Daniel R. Marlow, Andrew Renshaw, Shawn Westerdale, Masayuki Wada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sequential-Scanning Dual-Energy CT Imaging Using High Temporal Resolution Image Reconstruction and Error-Compensated Material Basis Image Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14754v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dual-energy computed tomography (DECT) has been widely used to obtain quantitative elemental composition of imaged subjects for personalized and precise medical diagnosis. Compared with DECT leveraging advanced X-ray source and/or detector technologies, the use of the sequential-scanning data acquisition scheme to implement DECT may make a broader impact on clinical practice because this scheme requires no specialized hardware designs and can be directly implemented into conventional CT systems. However, since the concentration of iodinated contrast agent in the imaged subject varies over time, sequentially scanned data sets acquired at two tube potentials are temporally inconsistent. As existing material basis image reconstruction approaches assume that the data sets acquired at two tube potentials are temporally consistent, the violation of this assumption results in inaccurate quantification of material concentration. In this work, we developed sequential-scanning DECT imaging using high temporal resolution image reconstruction and error-compensated material basis image generation, ACCELERATION in short, to address the technical challenge induced by temporal inconsistency of sequentially scanned data sets and improve quantification accuracy of material concentration in sequential-scanning DECT. ACCELERATION has been validated and evaluated using numerical simulation data sets generated from clinical human subject exams and experimental human subject studies. Results demonstrated the improvement of quantification accuracy and image quality using ACCELERATION.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14754v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiaoxin Li, Ruifeng Chen, Peng Wang, Guotao Quan, Yanfeng Du, Dong Liang, Yinsheng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Mathematical Model for Skin Sympathetic Nerve Activity Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.05934</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.05934v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Autonomic nervous system is important for cardiac function regulation. Modeling of autonomic cardiac regulation can contribute to health tracking and disease management. This study proposed a mathematical model that simulates autonomic cardiac regulation response to Valsalva Maneuver, which is a commonly used test that provokes the autonomic nervous system. Dataset containing skin sympathetic nervous activity extracted from healthy participants' ECG was used to validate the model. In the data collection procedure, each participant was required to perform Valsalva Maneuver. The preliminary result of modeling for one subject is presented, and the model validation result showed that the root measure square error between the simulated and measured average skin sympathetic nervous activity is 0.01$\mu$V. The model is expected to be further developed, evaluated using the dataset including 41 subjects, and ultimately applied for capturing the early signs of cardiac dysfunction in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.05934v2</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Runwei Lin, Frank Halfwerk, Dirk Donker, Gozewijn Dirk Laverman, Ying Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
