<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.med-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.med-ph</link>
    <description>physics.med-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.med-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 04:28:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>An in silico approach to analyse the influence of carotid haemodynamics on cardiovascular events using 3D tomographic ultrasound and computational fluid dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08969v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Analysing the haemodynamics of flow in carotid artery disease serves as a means to better understand the development and progression of associated complex diseases. Carotid artery disease can predispose people to major adverse cardiovascular events. Understanding the nature of carotid blood flow using in silico methods enables the extraction of relevant metrics that are not accessible in vivo. This study develops computationally efficient means of modelling patient-specific flow, utilising 3D tomographic ultrasound to generate anatomically faithful reconstructions including artherosclerotic plaque, and computational fluid dynamics to simulate flow in these arteries. A computationally efficient model has been proposed here, which has been used to conduct simulations for a large dataset, the results of which where stastitically analysed to test the association of relevant haemodynamic metrics with cardiovascular events. The incidence of major cardiovascular diseases in carotid artery disease patients has been shown to have an association with flow vorticity in the region of interest, and less so with the absolute magnitudes of wall shear stress.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08969v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sampad Sengupta (Department of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, School of Engineering, The University of Manchester, Manchester, UK, Department of Chemical Engineering and Biotechnology, The University of Cambridge, Cambridge, UK), Emily Manchester (Department of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, School of Engineering, The University of Manchester, Manchester, UK), Jie Wang (Department of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, School of Engineering, The University of Manchester, Manchester, UK), Ajay B. Harish (Department of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, School of Engineering, The University of Manchester, Manchester, UK), Alistair Revell (Department of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, School of Engineering, The University of Manchester, Manchester, UK), Steven K. Rogers (Manchester Academic Vascular Research and Innovation Centre, Division of Nursing, Midwifery and Social Work, School of Health Sciences, Faculty of Medicine, Biology and Health, University of Manchester, Manchester, UK)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An energy optimization method based on mixed-integer model and variational quantum computing algorithm for faster IMPT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10315v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Intensity-modulated proton therapy (IMPT) offers superior dose conformity with reduced exposure to surrounding healthy tissues compared to conventional photon therapy. Improving IMPT delivery efficiency reduces motion-related uncertainties, enhances plan robustness, and benefits breath-hold techniques by shortening treatment time. Among various factors, energy switching time plays a critical role, making energy layer optimization (ELO) essential. This work develops an energy layer optimization method based on mixed integer model and variational quantum computing algorithm to enhance the efficiency of IMPT. The energy layer optimization problem is modeled as a mixed-integer program, where continuous variables optimize the dose distribution and binary variables indicate energy layer selection. To solve it, iterative convex relaxation decouples the dose-volume constraints, followed by the alternating direction method of multipliers (ADMM) to separate mixed-variable optimization and the minimum monitor unit (MMU) constraint. The resulting beam intensity subproblem, subject to MMU, either admits a closed-form solution or is efficiently solvable via conjugate gradient. The binary subproblem is cast as a quadratic unconstrained binary optimization (QUBO) problem, solvable using variational quantum computing algorithms. With nearly the same plan quality, the proposed method noticeable reduces the number of the used energies. For example, compared to conventional IMPT, QC can reduce the number of energy layers from 61 to 35 in HN case, from 56 to 35 in lung case, and from 59 to 32 to abdomen case. The reduced number of energies also results in fewer delivery time, e.g., the delivery time is reduced from 100.6, 232.0, 185.3 seconds to 90.7, 215.4, 154.0 seconds, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10315v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ya-Nan Zhu, Nimita Shinde, Bowen Lin, Hao Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic laboratory X-ray phase-contrast microtomography with structure-based prior regularisation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09193</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09193v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: X-ray microtomography is a versatile tool allowing the measurement of the 3D structure of optically thick samples. As a non-destructive technique, it is readily adapted to 4D imaging, where a sample can be monitored over time, and especially in conjunction with the application of external stimuli. To apply this technique with the limited X-ray flux available at a conventional laboratory source, we leverage the contrast enhancement of free-space propagation phase-contrast imaging, achieving an increase in contrast-to-noise ratio of 5.8x. Furthermore, we combine this with iterative reconstruction, using regularisation by a structure-based prior from a high-quality reference scan of the object. This combination of phase-contrast imaging and iterative reconstruction leads to a 29.2x improvement in contrast-to-noise ratio compared to the conventional reconstruction. This enables fully dynamic X-ray microtomography, with a temporal resolution of 9 s at a voxel size of 10.5 $\mu$m. We use this to measure the movement of a waterfront in the fine vessels of a wooden skewer, as a representative example of dynamic system evolving on the scale of tens of seconds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09193v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harry Allan, Tom Partridge, Joseph Jacob, Marco Endrizzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixture-of-Shape-Experts (MoSE): End-to-End Shape Dictionary Framework to Prompt SAM for Generalizable Medical Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09601v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Single domain generalization (SDG) has recently attracted growing attention in medical image segmentation. One promising strategy for SDG is to leverage consistent semantic shape priors across different imaging protocols, scanner vendors, and clinical sites. However, existing dictionary learning methods that encode shape priors often suffer from limited representational power with a small set of offline computed shape elements, or overfitting when the dictionary size grows. Moreover, they are not readily compatible with large foundation models such as the Segment Anything Model (SAM). In this paper, we propose a novel Mixture-of-Shape-Experts (MoSE) framework that seamlessly integrates the idea of mixture-of-experts (MoE) training into dictionary learning to efficiently capture diverse and robust shape priors. Our method conceptualizes each dictionary atom as a shape expert, which specializes in encoding distinct semantic shape information. A gating network dynamically fuses these shape experts into a robust shape map, with sparse activation guided by SAM encoding to prevent overfitting. We further provide this shape map as a prompt to SAM, utilizing the powerful generalization capability of SAM through bidirectional integration. All modules, including the shape dictionary, are trained in an end-to-end manner. Extensive experiments on multiple public datasets demonstrate its effectiveness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09601v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jia Wei, Xiaoqi Zhao, Jonghye Woo, Jinsong Ouyang, Georges El Fakhri, Qingyu Chen, Xiaofeng Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Overcoming light scattering with high optical nonlinearity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10423</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10423v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Achieving high-resolution optical imaging deep within heterogeneous and scattering media remains a fundamental challenge in biological microscopy, where conventional techniques are hindered by multiple light scattering and absorption. Here, we present a non-invasive imaging approach that harnesses the nonlinear response of luminescent labels in conjunction with the statistical and spatial properties of speckle patterns - an effect of random light interference. Using avalanching nanoparticles (ANPs) with strong photoluminescence nonlinearity, we demonstrate that random speckle illumination can be converted into a single, localized, sub-diffraction excitation spot. This spot can be scanned across the sample using the angular memory effect, enabling high-resolution imaging through a scattering layer. Our method is general, fast, and cost-effective. It requires no wavefront shaping, no feedback, and no reconstruction algorithm, offering a powerful new route to deep, high-resolution imaging through complex media.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10423v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pawel Szczypkowski, Adrian Makowski, Wojciech Zwoli\'nski, Katarzyna Prorok, Artur Bednarkiewicz, Radek Lapkiewicz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluation of the two-voltage method for parallel-plate ionization chambers irradiated with pulsed beams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02696v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Air-vented ionization chambers exposed to clinical radiation beams may suffer from recombination during the drift of the charge carriers towards the electrodes. Thus, dosimetry protocols recommend the use of a correction factor, usually denominated saturation factor ($k_{\rm sat}$), to correct the ionization chamber readout for the incomplete collection of charge. The two-voltage method is the recommended methodology for the calculation of the saturation factor, however, it is based on the early Boag model, which only takes into account the presence of positive and negative ions in the ionization chamber and does not account for the electric field screening or the free electron contribution to the signal.
  The numerical simulation shows a better agreement with the experimental data than the current analytical theories in terms of charge collection efficiency. The classical two-voltage method, systematically overestimates the saturation factor, with differences increasing with dose per pulse also present at low dose per pulse. These results may have implications for the dosimetry with ionization chambers in therapy modalities that use a dose per pulse higher than conventional radiotherapy such as intraoperative radiotherapy but also in conventional dose per pulse for ionization chambers that suffer from significant charge recombination.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02696v2</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/mp.17814</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Paz-Mart\'in, Andreas Sch\"uller, Alexandra Bourgouin, Araceli Gago-Arias, Diego M. Gonzalez-Casta\~no, Nicol\'as G\'omez-Fern\'andez, Juan Pardo-Montero, Faustino G\'omez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LUND-PROBE -- LUND Prostate Radiotherapy Open Benchmarking and Evaluation dataset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04493v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Radiotherapy treatment for prostate cancer relies on computed tomography (CT) and/or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) for segmentation of target volumes and organs at risk (OARs). Manual segmentation of these volumes is regarded as the gold standard for ground truth in machine learning applications but to acquire such data is tedious and time-consuming. A publicly available clinical dataset is presented, comprising MRI- and synthetic CT (sCT) images, target and OARs segmentations, and radiotherapy dose distributions for 432 prostate cancer patients treated with MRI-guided radiotherapy. An extended dataset with 35 patients is also included, with the addition of deep learning (DL)-generated segmentations, DL segmentation uncertainty maps, and DL segmentations manually adjusted by four radiation oncologists. The publication of these resources aims to aid research within the fields of automated radiotherapy treatment planning, segmentation, inter-observer analyses, and DL model uncertainty investigation. The dataset is hosted on the AIDA Data Hub and offers a free-to-use resource for the scientific community, valuable for the advancement of medical imaging and prostate cancer radiotherapy research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04493v2</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viktor Rogowski, Lars E Olsson, Jonas Scherman, Emilia Persson, Mustafa Kadhim, Sacha af Wetterstedt, Adalsteinn Gunnlaugsson, Martin P. Nilsson, Nandor Vass, Mathieu Moreau, Maria Gebre Medhin, Sven B\"ack, Per Munck af Rosensch\"old, Silke Engelholm, Christian Jamtheim Gustafsson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CTorch: PyTorch-Compatible GPU-Accelerated Auto-Differentiable Projector Toolbox for Computed Tomography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16741</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16741v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work introduces CTorch, a PyTorch-compatible, GPU-accelerated, and auto-differentiable projector toolbox designed to handle various CT geometries with configurable projector algorithms. CTorch provides flexible scanner geometry definition, supporting 2D fan-beam, 3D circular cone-beam, and 3D non-circular cone-beam geometries. Each geometry allows view-specific definitions to accommodate variations during scanning. Both flat- and curved-detector models may be specified to accommodate various clinical devices. CTorch implements four projector algorithms: voxel-driven, ray-driven, distance-driven (DD), and separable footprint (SF), allowing users to balance accuracy and computational efficiency based on their needs. All the projectors are primarily built using CUDA C for GPU acceleration, then compiled as Python-callable functions, and wrapped as PyTorch network module. This design allows direct use of PyTorch tensors, enabling seamless integration into PyTorch's auto-differentiation framework. These features make CTorch an flexible and efficient tool for CT imaging research, with potential applications in accurate CT simulations, efficient iterative reconstruction, and advanced deep-learning-based CT reconstruction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16741v3</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao Jiang, Grace J. Grace, J. Webster Stayman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can audio recordings be used to detect leaks and coughs during mechanical insufflation exsufflation (MI-E) treatment?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.05005v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This report relates to a study group hosted by the EPSRC funded network, Integrating data-driven BIOphysical models into REspiratory MEdicine (BIOREME), and supported by SofTMech and Innovate UK, Business Connect. The BIOREME network hosts events, including this study group, to bring together multi-disciplinary researchers, clinicians, companies and charities to catalyse research in the applications of mathematical modelling for respiratory medicine. The goal of this study group was to provide an interface between companies, clinicians, and mathematicians to develop mathematical tools to the problems presented. The study group was held at The University of Glasgow on the 17 - 21 June 2024 and was attended by 16 participants from 8 different institutions. Below details the technical report of one of the challenges and the methods developed by the team of researchers who worked on this challenge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.05005v2</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Brady, Vijay Chandiramani, Michelle Chatwin, Emmanuel Lwele, Aminat Yetunde Saula, Peter Stewart, Toby Stokes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A nonlocal equation describing tumor growth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.12958v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Cancer is a very complex phenomenon that involves many different scales and situations. In this paper we consider a free boundary problem describing the evolution of a tumor colony and we derive a new asymptotic model for tumor growth. We focus on the case of a single phase tumor colony taking into account chemotactic effects in an early stage where there is no necrotic inner region. Thus, our model is valid for the case of multilayer avascular tumors with very little access to both nutrients and inhibitors or the case where the amount of nutrients and inhibitors is very similar to the amount consumed by the multilayer tumor cells. Our model takes the form of a single nonlocal and nonlinear partial differential equation. Besides deriving the model, we also prove a well-posedness result.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.12958v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael Granero-Belinch\'on, Martina Magliocca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tumor likelihood estimation on MRI prostate data by utilizing k-Space information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06165</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06165v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a novel preprocessing and prediction pipeline for the classification of magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) that takes advantage of the information rich complex valued k-Space. Using a publicly available MRI raw dataset with 312 subject and a total of 9508 slices, we show the advantage of utilizing the k-Space for better prostate cancer likelihood estimation in comparison to just using the magnitudinal information in the image domain, with an AUROC of $86.1\%\pm1.8\%$. Additionally, by using high undersampling rates and a simple principal component analysis (PCA) for coil compression, we reduce the time needed for reconstruction by avoiding the time intensive GRAPPA reconstruction algorithm. By using digital undersampling for our experiments, we show that scanning and reconstruction time could be reduced. Even with an undersampling factor of 16, our approach achieves meaningful results, with an AUROC of $71.4\%\pm2.9\%$, using the PCA coil combination and taking into account the k-Space information. With this study, we were able to show the feasibility of preserving phase and k-Space information, with consistent results. Besides preserving valuable information for further diagnostics, this approach can work without the time intensive ADC and reconstruction calculations, greatly reducing the post processing, as well as potential scanning time, increasing patient comfort and allowing a close to real-time prediction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06165v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Rempe, F. H\"orst, C. Seibold, B. Hadaschik, M. Schlimbach, J. Egger, K. Kr\"oninger, F. Breuer, M. Blaimer, J. Kleesiek</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
