<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.med-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.med-ph</link>
    <description>physics.med-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.med-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 02:45:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Guidewire-driven deployment of high density ECoG arrays for large area brain-computer interface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12907v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Electrocorticographic brain computer interfaces are powerful emergent technologies for advancing basic neuroscience research and targeted clinical interventions. However, existing devices require trade-offs between coverage area, electrode density, surgical invasiveness and complication risk: limitations that fail to meet the demands of next-generation BCI. Here, we report a guidewire-driven deployable ECoG BCI device that can be epidurally implanted using minimally invasive procedures. Our ultra-flexible but strong thin-film electrode array, which packs 256 electrodes into 4 cm2, can be folded, pulled through millimetre-sized skull holes, and unfurled seamlessly onto the brain dura mater. When deployed on the canine brain, it captures abundant high-quality auditory neural signals with distinct features of hearing that can be used to classify sound types with over 80% accuracy using various standard machine learning models. Our device is biocompatible for chronic monitoring, easy and fast to deploy and importantly, resolves the key trade-offs limiting current BCI technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12907v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tao Zou (Department of Mechanical Engineering, The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong, Advanced Biomedical Instrumentation Centre Limited, Hong Kong Science Park, Hong Kong), Na Xiao (Advanced Biomedical Instrumentation Centre Limited, Hong Kong Science Park, Hong Kong), Ruihong Weng (Advanced Biomedical Instrumentation Centre Limited, Hong Kong Science Park, Hong Kong), Yifan Guo (Department of Mechanical Engineering, The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong, Advanced Biomedical Instrumentation Centre Limited, Hong Kong Science Park, Hong Kong), Danny Tat Ming Chan (Neurosurgery Division, Department of Surgery, The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong), Gilberto Ka Kit Leung (Department of Surgery, The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong), Paddy Kwok Leung Chan (Department of Mechanical Engineering, The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong, Advanced Biomedical Instrumentation Centre Limited, Hong Kong Science Park, Hong Kong)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Operational and biomechanical evaluation of a wrist exoskeleton prototype for assisting meat cutting tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13307v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Although a growing number of exoskeletons have been developed for occupational applications, wrist exoskeletons remain relatively rare. However, in the meat processing industry, elbow and hand-wrist musculoskeletal disorders are particularly common. The aim of this study was to assess the potential effectiveness and risks of a 670g wrist exoskeleton prototype designed to assist operators during meat cutting tasks. Six professional butchers performed three standardized tasks reproducing meat cutting gestures in foam, in three randomized experimental conditions: (1) without exoskeleton, (2) wearing the exoskeleton passive, with brakes off and (3) using it with brakes activated, locked in a static position. Cutting forces were recorded using an instrumented table, joint angles using an optoelectronic motion capture system, muscle activity using surface EMG and user experience was assessed using questionnaires. The cutting inaccuracy was defined as the area between the prescribed task and the actual cut on the foam surface. Joint torques were estimated by inverse dynamics with and without taking the exoskeleton's mass into account, to isolate its effect. Linear mixed-effects statistical models were fitted. With the exoskeleton active during tasks, EMG activity was decreased of up to 18.7% (p&lt;0.01 to p&lt;0.001) in the wrist flexors and increased of up to 61.7% (not significant to p&lt;0.05) in the upper trapezius. Shoulder elevation joint torques were increased of up to 39.7% (p&lt;0.001), mainly due to the exoskeleton mass. The proposed multi-criteria exoskeleton evaluation has provided guidance for following prototyping stages. Too heavy wrist exoskeletons could increase the risk of shoulder tendinitis for such tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13307v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aur\'elie Tomezzoli (IRISA, ComBO), Mathieu Gr\'eau (UR, ComBO, IRISA), Charles Pontonnier (UR, ComBO, IRISA)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PyPeT: A Python Perfusion Tool for Automated Quantitative Brain CT and MR Perfusion Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13310</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13310v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Computed tomography perfusion (CTP) and magnetic resonance perfusion (MRP) are widely used in acute ischemic stroke assessment and other cerebrovascular conditions to generate quantitative maps of cerebral hemodynamics. While commercial perfusion analysis software exists, it is often costly, closed source, and lacks customizability. This work introduces PyPeT, an openly available Python Perfusion Tool for head CTP and MRP processing. PyPeT is capable of producing cerebral blood flow (CBF), cerebral blood volume (CBV), mean transit time (MTT), time-to-peak (TTP), and time-to-maximum (Tmax) maps from raw four-dimensional perfusion data. PyPeT aims to make perfusion research as accessible and customizable as possible. This is achieved through a unified framework in which both CTP and MRP data can be processed, with a strong focus on modularity, low computational burden, and significant inline documentation. PyPeT's outputs can be validated through an extensive debug mode in which every step of the process is visualized. Additional validation was performed via visual and quantitative comparison with reference perfusion maps generated by three FDA-approved commercial perfusion tools and a research tool. These comparisons show a mean SSIM around 0.8 for all comparisons, indicating a good and stable correlation with FDA-approved tools. The code for PyPeT is openly available at our GitHub https://github.com/Marijn311/CT-and-MR-Perfusion-Tool</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13310v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marijn Borghouts, Ruisheng Su</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smooth Total variation Regularization for Interference Detection and Elimination (STRIDE) for MRI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13628v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: MRI is increasingly desired to function near electronic devices that emit potentially dynamic electromagnetic interference (EMI). To accommodate for this, we propose the STRIDE method, which improves on previous external-sensor-based EMI removal methods by exploiting inherent MR image smoothness in its total variation. STRIDE measures data from both EMI detectors and primary MR imaging coils, transforms this data into the image domain, and for each column of the resulting image array, combines and subtracts data from the EMI detectors in a way that optimizes for total-variation smoothness. Performance was tested on phantom and in-vivo datasets with a 0.5T scanner. STRIDE resulted in visually better EMI removal, higher temporal SNR, larger EMI removal percentage, and lower RMSE than standard implementations. STRIDE is a robust technique that leverages inherent MR image properties to provide improved EMI removal performance over standard algorithms, particularly for time-varying noise sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13628v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Mertens, Diego Martinez, Amgad Louka, Ying Yang, Chad Harris, Ian Connell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the production of Terbium-161 in the Brazilian Multipurpose Reactor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13634v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Brazilian Multipurpose Reactor (RMB) was conceived to meet national needs for radioisotope production, materials irradiation testing, and neutron beam applications. In addition to its 30~MW pool-type reactor, the RMB complex will include additional facilities for radioisotope production and related applications. $^{161}Tb$ is a promising radionuclide for radiopharmaceutical therapy, offering decay properties similar to $^{177}Lu$ but with additional conversion and Auger electrons that enhance dose delivery to cancer cells. In light of this emerging radioisotope, this study explores the potential production of $^{161}Tb$ in the RMB through neutron irradiation of enriched $Gd_{2}O_{3}$ targets. Monte Carlo (MCNP) simulations provided detailed neutron flux distributions, which were used as input for ORIGEN calculations of isotope buildup. Assuming 10 mg targets enriched to 97.5% in $^{160}Gd$, a 40-day irradiation, and a thermal flux of $2 \cdot 10^{14}$ $n/cm^{2}s$, the results indicate that $^{161}Tb$ activity reaches approximately 4.5 GBq after 14 days ($\approx 450 GBq/g$), in agreement with data from other research reactors. Building on prior studies that demonstrated the RMB's capability to irradiate larger targets, terabecquerel-scale yields appear feasible. These findings highlight the RMB's potential to support domestic production of emerging therapeutic radionuclides such as $^{161}Tb$. The potential for isotopic enrichment of $^{160}Gd$ using the AVLIS method is also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13634v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Cozim Melges, Jhonatha Ricardo Santos, Luiz Paulo de Oliveira, Alexandre Pinho dos Santos Souza, Carlos Gabriel Santos da Silva, Iber\^e Souza Ribeiro J\'unior, Barbara Perez Gon\c{c}alves Silva, Marco Antonio Stanojev Pereira, Frederico Antonio Genezini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase-Pole-Free Images and Smooth Coil Sensitivity Maps by Regularized Nonlinear Inversion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.04685v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Purpose: Phase singularities are a common problem in image reconstruction with auto-calibrated sensitivities due to an inherent ambiguity of the estimation problem. The purpose of this work is to develop a method for detecting and correcting phase poles in non-linear inverse (NLINV) reconstruction of MR images and coil sensitivity maps.
  Methods: Phase poles are detected in individual coil sensitivity maps by computing the curl in each pixel. A weighted average of the curl in each coil is computed to detect phase poles. Phase pole detection and correction is then integrated into the iteratively regularized Gauss-Newton method of the NLINV algorithm, which then avoid phase singularities in the reconstructed images. The method is evaluated for reconstruction of accelerated Cartesian MPRAGE data of the brain and interactive radial real-time MRI of the human heart.
  Results: Phase poles are reliably removed in NLINV reconstructions for both applications. NLINV with phase pole correction can reliably and efficiently estimate coil sensitivity profiles free from singularities even from very small ($7\times7$) auto-calibration (AC) regions.
  Conclusion: NLINV emerges as an efficient and reliable tool for image reconstruction and coil sensitivity estimation in challenging MRI applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.04685v2</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Moritz Blumenthal, Martin Uecker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Particle migration in areas of constricted flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13485</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13485v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Cardiovascular diseases are a leading cause of death globally. Among them, some are linked to stenosis, which is an abnormal narrowing of blood vessels, as well as other factors. Smart drug delivery systems based on micro- and nanoparticles are a promising method to offer non/minimal-invasive therapeutic mechanisms. Here we investigate the propensity of particles with different shapes and sizes to drift laterally (marginate) towards an occlusion area in a two-dimensional (2D) parallel plate laminar flow using the Lattice-Boltzmann method (LBM). To verify the outcomes on both sides of the stenosis, a probability of adhesion to the borders was calculated. Analysis was done on the impact of wall-shear stress on both sides of the stenosis. Our results show that rectangular particles migrate in larger amounts and earlier than circular ones.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13485v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Dapena-Garc\'ia, V. P\'erez-Mu\~nuzuri</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
