<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.med-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.med-ph</link>
    <description>physics.med-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.med-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 04:03:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Phase-based stimulated emission depletion (pSTED) magnetic particle imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06490v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic particle imaging (MPI) is an in vivo method to detect magnetic nanoparticles for cell tracking, vascular imaging, and molecular target imaging without ionizing radiation. Current magnetic particle imaging is accomplished by forming an field-free line (FFL) through a gradient selection field. By translating and rotating FFL under excitation and drive fields, the harmonic complex signal of a point source forms a Lorentzian-shape point spread function on the plane perpendicular to FFL. The Lorentzian PSF has a finite size and limited resolution due to the non-sharp Langevin function and weak selection field. This study proposes a donut-shaped focal spot by borrowing the stimulated emission depletion (STED) fluorescence microscopy principle. The influence of the gradient selection field on the relaxation time of magnetic particles determines the nonlinear phase shift of the harmonic complex signals, resulting in the formation of a donut-shaped focal spot. By subtracting the donut-shaped focal spot from the Lorentzian focal spot, the STED focal spot size was reduced by up to 4 times beyond the Langevin magnetization resolution barrier. In human brain FFL-based MPI scanner, the donut-shaped focal spot can be used to reconstruct images with super-resolution and super-sensitivity through the deconvoution of the STED focal spot and filtered backprojection algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06490v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guang Jia, Zhongwei Bian, Tianshu Li, Shi Bai, Yongchen Gou, Yiwen Li, Lixuan Zhao, Jia Luo, Mingli Peng, Weihua Li, Peng Gao, Tanping Li, Hui Hui, Jie Tian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Rapid Reconstruction Method of Gamma Radiation Field based on Normalized Proper Orthogonal Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07088v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When a fault occurs in nuclear facilities, accurately reconstructing gamma radiation fields through measurements from the mobile radiation detection (MRD) system becomes crucial to enable access to internal facility areas for essential safety assessments and repairs. Reconstruction of these fields is difficult because of the uncertainty in the positions and intensities of the gamma sources, the complexity of the gamma distribution, and the physics and radiation hardness constraints on the MRD systems. In this work, a novel reconstruction framework of the gamma radiation is proposed. This system entails a NPOD-based reconstruction algorithm with MRD data, and a variation-based adaptive measurements selection mechanism. Our approach has been thoroughly assessed using extensive simulations, and the results clearly prove its success and efficiency in reconstruction radiation fields accurately and quickly. Furthermore, the designed selection algorithm is also promising for extensive application to other optimization tasks of location selection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07088v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kai Tan, Hojoon Son, Fan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OPTIKS: Optimized Gradient Properties Through Timing in K-Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07117v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A customizable method (OPTIKS) for designing fast trajectory-constrained gradient waveforms with optimized time domain properties was developed. Given a specified multidimensional k-space trajectory, the method optimizes traversal speed (and therefore timing) with position along the trajectory. OPTIKS facilitates optimization of objectives dependent on the time domain gradient waveform and the arc-length domain k-space speed. OPTIKS is applied to design waveforms which limit peripheral nerve stimulation (PNS), minimize mechanical resonance excitation, and reduce acoustic noise. A variety of trajectory examples are presented including spirals, circular echo-planar-imaging, and rosettes. Design performance is evaluated based on duration, standardized PNS models, field measurements, gradient coil back-EMF measurements, and calibrated acoustic measurements. We show reductions in back-EMF of up to 94% and field oscillations up to 91.1%, acoustic noise decreases of up to 9.22 dB, and with efficient use of PNS models speed increases of up to 11.4%. The design method implementation is made available as an open source Python package through GitHub.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07117v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew A. McCready, Xiaozhi Cao, Kawin Setsompop, John M. Pauly, Adam B. Kerr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information-Theoretic Analysis of Brain MRI: Mutual Information and Pixel Intensity Patterns in Tumor vs. Normal Tissues</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02318</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02318v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The application of information theory in medical imaging, particularly in magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), offers powerful quantitative tools for analyzing structural differences in brain tissues. This study utilizes mutual information (MI) and pixel intensity distributions to differentiate between normal and tumor-affected brain MRI images. Mutual information analyses revealed significantly higher MI values in tumor images compared to normal ones, indicating greater internal similarity within tumor images. Pixel intensity analysis further demonstrated distinct distribution patterns between the two groups: tumor images showed pronounced pixel frequency concentrations within a specific intensity range (0.3, 0.4), suggesting predictable structural characteristics. Conversely, normal images exhibited broader, more uniform pixel intensity distributions across most intensity ranges, except for an initial peak observed in both groups. These findings highlight the capability of information-theoretic metrics, such as mutual information and pixel intensity analysis, to effectively distinguish tumor tissue from normal brain structures, providing promising avenues for enhanced diagnostic and analytical methods in neuroimaging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02318v2</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.TO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mazaher Kabiri, Shahd Qasem Mahd Tarman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimations of lung structural properties from a single propagation-based dark-field X-ray image</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02695</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02695v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this investigation, we applied a single-projection dark-field imaging technique to gain statistical information on the smallest airway structures within the lung$\unicode{x2014}$the alveoli$\unicode{x2014}$focusing on their size and number as key indicators of lung health. The algorithm employed here retrieves the projected thickness of the sample from a propagation-based phase contrast image using the transport-of-intensity equation. The first Born approximation is then used to isolate the dark-field signal associated with edge scattering, which increases the visibility of microstructure boundaries. PMMA spheres of known sizes were imaged first as an idealised alveolar model. The dark-field signal was then recovered from propagation-based phase-contrast X-ray images of the lungs of small mammals using this method. The retrieved dark-field signal was found to be proportional to both the alveolar size ($R^2 = 0.85$) and the number in projection ($R^2 = 0.69$), and these measurements could be combined to provide an estimate of the total surface area of the alveolar interfaces ($R^2 = 0.78$). This demonstrates the approach's ability to indicate lung health using the dark-field signal retrieved from a single-phase-contrast X-ray image.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02695v2</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dylan W. O'Connell, Kaye S. Morgan, Linda C. P. Croton, James A. Pollock, Gary Ruben, Kelly J. Crossley, Megan J. Wallace, Erin. V. McGillick, Stuart B. Hooper. Marcus J. Kitchen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
