<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.med-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.med-ph</link>
    <description>physics.med-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.med-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 04:05:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Linear Acceleration Is a Primary Risk Factor for Concussion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09098</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09098v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rotational acceleration of the head has long been posited as the primary cause of concussion due to its ability to generate shear strains that disrupt neuronal structure and function [1,2]. Linear acceleration, by contrast, is considered less injurious due to the brain's suspension in cerebrospinal fluid within the rigid skull [3,4]. As a result, the rotational acceleration hypothesis has predominantly driven international safety standards and protective equipment design. However, direct measurements of rotational acceleration during human concussion remain limited, leaving the rotational hypothesis largely untested in vivo. Here we show that linear acceleration is a significantly more precise predictor of concussion than rotational acceleration. We used mouthguards instrumented with inertial sensors to directly measure head kinematics during concussions occurring in children and adults of both sexes. Surprisingly, we found that rotational acceleration was not a significant independent predictor of concussion. Finite-element computed brain strains also had little predictive power, suggesting limitations in modeling the intracranial contents purely as solid materials. We suspect that modeling cerebrospinal fluid flow might reveal a protective effect that is limited by the magnitude of linear acceleration and the size of the subarachnoid space. Inspired by the protective role of cerebrospinal fluid, we invented a liquid shock absorbing technology and modeled it in a bicycle helmet. Using linear acceleration as a concussion risk function, we predict that our liquid technology can reduce the risk of concussion by up to 73 percent compared to a conventional foam helmet. Together, our findings support the inclusion of linear acceleration in concussion safety regulations and the need for advanced technologies to reduce impact forces and injury risk.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09098v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jessica A. Towns, Fady F. Abayazid, James W. Hickey, William T. O'Brien, Spencer S. H. Roberts, N. Stewart Pritchard, Jillian E. Urban, Joel D. Stitzel, Gerald A. Grant, Michael M. Zeineh, Stuart J. McDonald, David B. Camarillo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The new GATE 10 Monte Carlo particle transport simulation software -- Part II: Architecture and innovations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09840</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09840v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Over the past years, we have developed GATE version 10, a major re-implementation of the long-standing Geant4-based Monte Carlo application for particle and radiation transport simulation in medical physics. This release introduces many new features and significant improvements, most notably a Python-based user interface replacing the legacy static input files. The new functionality of GATE version 10 is described in the part 1 companion paper. The development brought significant challenges. In this paper, we present the solutions that we have developed to overcome these challenges. In particular, we present a modular design that robustly manages the core components of a simulation: particle sources, geometry, physics processes, and data acquisition. The architecture consists of parts written in C++ and Python, which needed to be coupled. We explain how this framework allows for the precise, time-aware generation of primary particles, a critical requirement for accurately modeling positron emission tomography (PET), radionuclide therapies, and prompt-gamma timing systems. We present how GATE 10 handles complex Geant4 physics settings while exposing a simple interface to the user. Furthermore, we describe the technical solutions that facilitate the seamless integration of advanced physics models and variance reduction techniques. The architecture supports sophisticated scoring of physical quantities (such as Linear Energy Transfer and Relative Biological Effectiveness) and is designed for multithreaded execution. The new user interface allows researchers to script complex simulation workflows and directly couple external tools, such as artificial intelligence models for source generation or detector response. By detailing these architectural innovations, we demonstrate how GATE 10 provides a more powerful and flexible tool for research and innovation in medical physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09840v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nils Krah, Nicolas Arbor, Thomas Baudier, Julien Bert, Konstantinos Chatzipapas, Martina Favaretto, Hermann Fuchs, Lo\"ic Grevillot, Hussein Harb, Gert Van Hoey, Maxime Jacquet, S\'ebastien Jan, Yihan Jia, George C. Kagadis, Han Gyu Kang, Paul Klever, Olga Kochebina, Lydia Maigne, Philipp Mohr, Guneet Mummaneni, Valentina Paneta, Panagiotis Papadimitroulas, Alexis Pereda, Axel Rannou, Andreas F. Resch, Emilie Roncali, Maxime Toussaint, Carlotta Trigila, Charalampos Tsoumpas, Jing Zhang, Karl Ziemons, David Sarrut</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The new GATE 10 Monte Carlo particle transport simulation software -- Part I: Development and new features</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09842</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09842v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present GATE version 10, a major evolution of the open-source Monte Carlo simulation application for medical physics, built on Geant4. This release marks a transformative evolution, featuring a modern Python-based user interface, enhanced multithreading and multiprocessing capabilities, the ability to be embedded as a library within other software, and a streamlined framework for collaborative development. In this Part 1 paper, we outline GATE's position among other Monte Carlo codes, the core principles driving this evolution, and the robust development cycle employed. We also detail the new features and improvements. Part 2 will detail the architectural innovations and technical challenges. By combining an open, collaborative framework with cutting-edge features, such a Monte Carlo platform supports a wide range of academic and industrial research, solidifying its role as a critical tool for innovation in medical physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09842v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Sarrut, Nicolas Arbor, Thomas Baudier, Julien Bert, Konstantinos Chatzipapas, Martina Favaretto, Hermann Fuchs, Lo\"ic Grevillot, Hussein Harb, Gert Van Hoey, Maxime Jacquet, S\'ebastien Jan, Yihan Jia, George C. Kagadis, Han Gyu Kang, Paul Klever, Olga Kochebina, Wojciech Krzemien, Lydia Maigne, Philipp Mohr, Guneet Mummaneni, Valentina Paneta, Panagiotis Papadimitroulas, Alexis Pereda, Axel Rannou, Andreas F. Resch, Emilie Roncali, Maxime Toussaint, Carlotta Trigila, Charalampos Tsoumpas, Jing Zhang, Karl Ziemons, Nils Krah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CRYSP: a Total-Body PET based on cryogenic cesium iodide crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09765v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Total Body PET (TBPET) scanners have recently demonstrated the ability to significantly reduce both acquisition time and the administered radioactive dose, thanks to their increased sensitivity. However, their widespread adoption is limited by the high costs associated with the current available systems. In this context, pure cesium iodide (CsI) monolithic crystals, given their much lower cost compared with currently used rare-earth crystals, offer a promising solution to improve accessibility. When operated at cryogenic temperatures (approximately 100 K), CsI crystals exhibit one of the highest light outputs among inorganic crystals, around $10^5$ photons/MeV. This results in energy resolution below 7%, millimeter-scale spatial resolution (including accurate depth-of-interaction determination), and coincidence time resolution at the nanosecond level, despite their relatively slow scintillation decay time. This study demonstrates that a TBPET scanner based on cryogenic CsI monolithic crystals might have the potential to deliver high-performance imaging at a reduced cost compared with conventional systems, paving the way for broader deployment and accessibility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09765v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. R. Soleti, P. Dietz, R. Esteve, J. Garc\`ia-Barrena, V. Herrero, F. Lopez, F. Monrabal, L. Navarro-Cozcolluela, E. Oblak, J. Pelegr\`in, J. Renner, J. Toledo, S. Torelli, J. J. G\`omez-Cadenas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlation-weighted 23Na magnetic resonance fingerprinting in the brain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07006</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07006v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We developed a new sodium magnetic resonance fingerprinting ($^\text{23}\text{Na}$ MRF) method for the simultaneous mapping of $\text{T}_\text{1}$, $\text{T}_\text{2,long}^{*}$, $\text{T}_\text{2,short}^{*}$ and sodium density with built-in $\Delta\text{B}_{1}^{+}$ (radiofrequency transmission inhomogeneities) and $\Delta\text{f}_\text{0}$ corrections (frequency offsets). We based our $^\text{23}\text{Na}$ MRF implementation on a 3D FLORET sequence with 23 radiofrequency pulses. To capture the complex spin ${\frac{\text{3}}{\text{2}}}$ dynamics of the $^\text{23}\text{Na}$ nucleus, the fingerprint dictionary was simulated using the irreducible spherical tensor operators formalism. The dictionary contained 831,512 entries covering a wide range of $\text{T}_\text{1}$, $\text{T}_\text{2,long}^{*}$, $\text{T}_\text{2,short}^{*}$, $\Delta\text{B}_\text{1}^{+}$ factor and $\Delta\text{f}_\text{0}$ parameters. Fingerprint matching was performed using the Pearson correlation and the resulting relaxation maps were weighted with a subset of the highest correlation coefficients corresponding to signal matches for each voxel. Our $^\text{23}\text{Na}$ MRF method was compared against reference methods in a 7-compartment phantom, and applied in brain in five healthy volunteers at 7 T. In phantoms, $^\text{23}\text{Na}$ MRF produced values comparable to those obtained with reference methods. Average sodium relaxation time values in cerebrospinal fluid, gray matter and white matter across five healthy volunteers were in good agreement with values previously reported in the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07006v3</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lauren F. O'Donnell, Gonzalo G. Rodriguez, Gregory Lemberskiy, Zidan Yu, Olga Dergachyova, Martijn Cloos, Guillaume Madelin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Associated Volume sampling algorithm as an alternative method for the calculation of ionisation cluster size distributions in computational nanodosimetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04495v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In computational nanodosimetry, Monte Carlo Track Structure (MCTS) simulations are employed to calculate ionisation cluster size distributions (ICSDs), which are crucial for characterising mixed radiation fields at the nanoscale. The Uniform Sampling (US) algorithm, commonly used for this purpose, is inefficient when evaluating ICSDs conditioned on clusters exceeding a given size $\nu$ threshold. This study investigates a more efficient alternative - the Associated Volume (AV) algorithm - against the US approach for computing conditional ICSDs ($\nu \ge 1$) from proton tracks simulated with Geant4-DNA. Two configurations of the AV algorithm were evaluated: the standard AV-Overlap, allowing sensitive volumes to overlap (with a 1/$\nu$ correction), and the novel AV-No Overlap, which prevents overlap. We compared the conditional ICSDs, mean cluster size ($M_1$), complementary cumulative frequencies ($F_k$ for $k \in [2,7]$), and overall execution time per run and per event. Deviations exceeding two standard deviations of the mean difference were considered statistically significant. Although statistically significant differences in ICSDs, $M_1$ and $F_k$ were observed, the relative differences in the AV-Overlap rarely exceeded 5%, whereas the No Overlap configuration they ranged from $\lt$ 1% to approximately 15% at the higher $F_k$. Both AV configurations achieved execution times one to two orders of magnitude shorter than the US algorithm. Our findings indicate that the AV-Overlap algorithm may be a preferred alternative for calculating conditional ICSDs and derived nanodosimetric quantities, offering a substantial gain in computational efficiency without compromising accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04495v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jo\~ao F. Canhoto, Yann Perrot, Reinhard Schulte, Ana Belchior, Carmen Villagrasa</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
