<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.med-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.med-ph</link>
    <description>physics.med-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.med-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 02:51:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Acoustic Probing of New Biomarkers for Rapid Sickle Cell Disease Screening</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02478v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Sickle cell disease (SCD) remains a critical global health issue, with high child mortality in low-resource regions. Early screening and diagnosis is essential for improving health outcomes, but conventional screening methods are unsuitable for widespread use due to the high costs of laboratory equipment. There is an urgent need for portable, cost-effective, and user-friendly point-of-care tools that can quickly assess blood health. Here, we explore two new biomarkers enabled by acoustic probing for rapid SCD screening: cell membrane stability from measuring red blood cell (RBC) lysis temperature in whole blood, and plasma protein concentration from measuring relative protein precipitation in blood plasma. Both biomarkers effectively differentiate healthy HbAA samples from pre-/no transfusion HbSS samples with high accuracy. Additionally, the RBC lysis biomarker can distinguish post-transfusion exchange HbSS samples with a lower percentage of sickled cells, indicating the potential to initially screen for milder forms of SCD as well as sickle cell trait.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02478v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nakul Sridhar, Meiou Song, Michael H. B. Stowell, Kathryn L. Hassell, Xiaoyun Ding</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surface Acoustic Wave Hemolysis Assay for Evaluating Stored Red Blood Cells</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02482</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02482v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Blood transfusion remains a cornerstone of modern medicine, saving countless lives daily. Yet the quality of transfused blood varies dramatically among donors-a critical factor often overlooked in clinical practice. Rapid, benchtop, and cost-effective methods for evaluating stored red blood cells (RBCs) at the site of transfusion are lacking, with concerns persisting about the association between metabolic signatures of stored RBC quality and transfusion outcomes. Recent studies utilizing metabolomics approaches to evaluate stored erythrocytes find that donor biology (e.g., genetics, age, lifestyle factors) underlies the heterogeneity associated with blood storage and transfusion. The appreciation of donor-intrinsic factors provides opportunities for precision transfusion medicine approaches for the evaluation of storage quality and prediction of transfusion efficacy. Here we propose a new platform, the Surface Acoustic Wave Hemolysis Assay (SAW-HA), for on-site evaluation of stored RBCs utilizing SAW Hemolysis Temperature (SAWHT) as a marker for RBC quality. We report SAWHT as a mechanism-dependent reproducible methodology for evaluating stored human RBCs up to 42 days. Our results define unique signatures for SAW hemolysis and metabolic profiles in RBCs from two of the six donors in which high body mass index (BMI) and RBC triglycerides associated with increased susceptibility to hemolysis. Metabolic age of the stored RBCs - a recently appreciated predictor of post-transfusion efficacy-reveal that RBCs from the two low SAWHT units were characterized by disrupted redox control, deficient tryptophan metabolism, and high BMI. Together, these findings indicate the potential of the SAW-HA as a point-of-care analysis for transfusion medicine.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02482v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meiou Song, Colin C. Anderson, Nakul Sridhar, Julie A. Reisz, Leyla Akh, Yu Gao, Angelo D'Alessandro, Xiaoyun Ding</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dipolar order mapping based on spin-lock magnetic resonance imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02847</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02847v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Purpose: Inhomogeneous magnetization transfer (ihMT) effect reflects dipolar order with a dipolar relaxation time ($T_{1D}$), specific to motion-restricted macromolecules. We aim to quantify $T_{1D}$ using spin-lock MRI implemented with a novel rotary-echo sequence. Methods: In proposed method, we defined a relaxation rate $R_{dosl}$ that is specific to dipolar order and obtained as the difference of dual-frequency $R_{1rho}^{dual}$ relaxation and single-frequency $R_{1rho}^{single}$ relaxation. A novel rotary-echo spin-lock sequence was developed to enable dual-frequency acquisition. We derive the framework to estimate $T_{1D}$ from $R_{dosl}$ under macromolecular pool fraction (MPF) map constraints. The proposed approach was validated via Bloch-McConnell-Provotorov simulation, phantom studies, and in-vivo white matter studies on a 3T scanner. Results: Simulations demonstrated that $R_{dosl}$ exhibits an approximately linear relationship with $T_{1D}$. Phantom experiments showed robust ihMT contrast in $R_{dosl}$ and confirmed the feasibility and reliability of $T_{1D}$ quantification via $R_{dosl}$. In vivo white-matter studies further supported the clinical potential of this $T_{1D}$ mapping approach. Conclusion: We propose a novel, clinical feasible method for $T_{1D}$ quantification based on spin-lock MRI. This method requires substantially fewer contrast-prepared images compared to the conventional $T_{1D}$ quantification approach. This technique provides a promising pathway for robust MPF and $T_{1D}$ quantification in a single rapid scan with reduced confounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02847v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zijian Gao, Qianxue Shan, Ziqin Zhou, Ziqiang Yu, Weitian Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrasound matrix imaging for 3D transcranial in vivo localization microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14499</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14499v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Transcranial ultrasound imaging is usually limited by skull-induced attenuation and high-order aberrations. By using contrast agents such as microbubbles in combination with ultrafast imaging, not only can the signal-to-noise ratio be improved, but super-resolution images down to the micrometer scale of the brain vessels can also be obtained. However, ultrasound localization microscopy (ULM) remains affected by wavefront distortions that limit the microbubble detection rate and hamper their localization. In this work, we show how ultrasound matrix imaging, which relies on the prior recording of the reflection matrix, can provide a solution to these fundamental issues. As an experimental proof of concept, an in vivo reconstruction of deep brain microvessels is performed on three anesthetized sheep. The compensation of wave distortions is shown to markedly enhance the contrast and resolution of ULM. This experimental study thus opens up promising perspectives for a transcranial and nonionizing observation of human cerebral microvascular pathologies, such as stroke.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14499v2</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1126/sciadv.adt9778</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Sci. Adv.11, eadt9778, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Flavien Bureau, Louise Denis, Antoine Coudert, Mathias Fink, Olivier Couture, Alexandre Aubry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radial spoke energy for self-navigated motion detection and position-ordered dynamic musculoskeletal MRI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01833v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Motion remains a key challenge in MRI, as both involuntary (e.g., head motion) and voluntary (e.g., joint motion) movement can degrade image quality or provide opportunities for dynamic assessment. Existing motion sensing methods, such as external tracking or navigator sequences, often require additional hardware, increase SAR, or demand sequence modification, which limits clinical flexibility. We propose a computationally efficient, self-navigated motion sensing technique based on spoke energy derived from 3D radial k-space data. Using the Fourier Slice and Parseval's theorems, spoke energy captures object-coil alignment and can be computed without altering the sequence. A sliding window summation improves robustness, and a second principal component analysis (2ndPCA) strategy yields a unified motion-sensitive signal. Beyond conventional head motion correction, we demonstrate the novel application of this method in enhancing dynamic 4D MRI of the ankle and knee under a continuous movement protocol. By sorting spokes based on position rather than time, we achieve motion-resolved reconstructions with improved anatomical clarity. This approach enables real-time motion detection and supports broader adoption of motion-aware dynamic MRI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01833v2</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enping Lin, Fatih Calakli, Musa Tun\c{c} Arslan, Giovani Schulte Farina, Simon Keith Warfield</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
