<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.dis-nn updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.dis-nn</link>
    <description>cond-mat.dis-nn updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.dis-nn" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2024 04:00:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum entanglement in the multicritical disordered Ising model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12990v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Here, the entanglement entropy is calculated at the quantum multicritical point of the random transverse-field Ising model (RTIM). We use an efficient implementation of the strong disorder renormalization group method in two and three dimensions for two types of disorder. For cubic subsystems we find a universal logarithmic corner contribution to the area law b*ln(l) that is independent of the form of disorder. Our results agree qualitatively with those at the quantum critical points of the RTIM, but with new b prefactors due to having both geometric and quantum fluctuations at play. By studying the vicinity of the multicritical point, we demonstrate that the corner contribution serves as an `entanglement susceptibility', a useful tool to locate the phase transition and to measure the correlation length critical exponents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12990v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Istv\'an Kov\'acs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enumerating low-frequency nonphononic vibrations in computer glasses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12735v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In addition to Goldstone phonons that generically emerge in the low-frequency vibrational spectrum of any solid, crystalline or glassy, structural glasses also feature other low-frequency vibrational modes. The nature and statistical properties of these modes -- often termed `excess modes' -- have been the subject of decades-long investigation. Studying them, even using well-controlled computer glasses, has proven challenging due to strong spatial hybridization effects between phononic and nonphononic excitations, which hinder quantitative analyses of the nonphononic contribution ${\cal D}_{\rm G}(\omega)$ to the total spectrum ${\cal D}(\omega)$, per frequency $\omega$. Here, using recent advances indicating that ${\cal D}_{\rm G}(\omega)\!=\!{\cal D}(\omega)-{\cal D}_{\rm D}(\omega)$, where ${\cal D}_{\rm D}(\omega)$ is Debye's spectrum of phonons, we present a simple and straightforward scheme to enumerate nonphononic modes in computer glasses. Our analysis establishes that nonphononic modes in computer glasses indeed make an additive contribution to the total spectrum, including in the presence of strong hybridizations. Moreover, it cleanly reveals the universal ${\cal D}_{\rm G}(\omega)\!\sim\!\omega^4$ tail of the nonphononic spectrum, and opens the way for related analyses of experimental spectra of glasses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12735v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Edan Lerner, Avraham Moriel, Eran Bouchbinder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ionic conductivity of a lithium-doped deep eutectic solvent: Glass formation and rotation-translation coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.12186v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Deep eutectic solvents with admixed lithium salts are considered as electrolytes in electrochemical devices like batteries or supercapacitors. Compared to eutectic mixtures of hydrogen-bond donors and lithium salts, their raw-material costs are significantly lower. Not much is known about the glassy freezing and rotation-translation coupling of such systems. Here we investigate these phenomena by applying dielectric spectroscopy to the widely studied deep eutectic solvent glyceline, to which 1 and 5 mol% LiCl were added. Our studies cover a wide temperature range, including the deeply supercooled state. The temperature dependences of the detected dipolar reorientation dynamics and of the ionic dc conductivity reveal the signatures of glassy freezing. In comparison to pure glyceline, lithium admixture leads to a reduction of ionic conductivity, which is accompanied by a slowing down of the rotational dipolar motions. However, this reduction is much smaller than for DESs, where one main component is a lithium salt, which we trace back to the smaller glass-transition temperatures of the lithium-doped DESs. In contrast to pure glyceline, the ionic and dipolar dynamics become increasingly decoupled at low temperatures and obey a fractional Debye-Stokes-Einstein relation as previously found in other glass-forming liquids. The obtained results demonstrate the relevance of decoupling effects and of the glass transition for the enhancement of the technically relevant ionic conductivity in such lithium-doped DESs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.12186v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.jpcb.4c00412</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. Chem. B 128 (2024) 3454</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. Schulz, P. Lunkenheimer, A. Loidl</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
