<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.dis-nn updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.dis-nn</link>
    <description>cond-mat.dis-nn updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.dis-nn" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2024 04:00:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Large-scale quantum reservoir learning with an analog quantum computer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02553v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum machine learning has gained considerable attention as quantum technology advances, presenting a promising approach for efficiently learning complex data patterns. Despite this promise, most contemporary quantum methods require significant resources for variational parameter optimization and face issues with vanishing gradients, leading to experiments that are either limited in scale or lack potential for quantum advantage. To address this, we develop a general-purpose, gradient-free, and scalable quantum reservoir learning algorithm that harnesses the quantum dynamics of neutral-atom analog quantum computers to process data. We experimentally implement the algorithm, achieving competitive performance across various categories of machine learning tasks, including binary and multi-class classification, as well as timeseries prediction. Effective and improving learning is observed with increasing system sizes of up to 108 qubits, demonstrating the largest quantum machine learning experiment to date. We further observe comparative quantum kernel advantage in learning tasks by constructing synthetic datasets based on the geometric differences between generated quantum and classical data kernels. Our findings demonstrate the potential of utilizing classically intractable quantum correlations for effective machine learning. We expect these results to stimulate further extensions to different quantum hardware and machine learning paradigms, including early fault-tolerant hardware and generative machine learning tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02553v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Milan Kornja\v{c}a, Hong-Ye Hu, Chen Zhao, Jonathan Wurtz, Phillip Weinberg, Majd Hamdan, Andrii Zhdanov, Sergio H. Cantu, Hengyun Zhou, Rodrigo Araiza Bravo, Kevin Bagnall, James I. Basham, Joseph Campo, Adam Choukri, Robert DeAngelo, Paige Frederick, David Haines, Julian Hammett, Ning Hsu, Ming-Guang Hu, Florian Huber, Paul Niklas Jepsen, Ningyuan Jia, Thomas Karolyshyn, Minho Kwon, John Long, Jonathan Lopatin, Alexander Lukin, Tommaso Macr\`i, Ognjen Markovi\'c, Luis A. Mart\'inez-Mart\'inez, Xianmei Meng, Evgeny Ostroumov, David Paquette, John Robinson, Pedro Sales Rodriguez, Anshuman Singh, Nandan Sinha, Henry Thoreen, Noel Wan, Daniel Waxman-Lenz, Tak Wong, Kai-Hsin Wu, Pedro L. S. Lopes, Yuval Boger, Nathan Gemelke, Takuya Kitagawa, Alexander Keesling, Xun Gao, Alexei Bylinskii, Susanne F. Yelin, Fangli Liu, Sheng-Tao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An intriguing connection between Pisarski's fixed point and (2+3)-spin glasses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05436v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper aims to establish a connection between Pisarski's fixed point and a (2+3)-spin-glass model with sextic confinement potential. This is made possible by the unconventional power-counting induced by the effective kinetics provided by the disorder coupling in the large $N$-limit. Because of the absence of epsilon expansion, our approach is more attractive than the previous one. It may be relevant to the signal detection issue in nearly continuous spectra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05436v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincent Lahoche, Dine Ousmane Samary</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Hilbert space fragmentation in group-valued loop models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19386v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a large class of models exhibiting robust ergodicity breaking in quantum dynamics. Our work is inspired by recent discussions of "topologically robust Hilbert space fragmentation," but massively generalizes in two directions: firstly from states describable as "loop-soups" to a broader class of states reminiscent of string-nets and sponges, and secondly from models restricted to square or cubic lattices, to models defined on arbitrary lattices (and even arbitrary graphs without translation invariance). Our constructions leverage a recently proposed group-theory framework [PRX 14, 021034 (2024)], and identify a host of new phenomena arising from the interplay of "group-model dynamics" and lattice structure. We make crisp connections to gauge theories, and our construction generalizes Kitaev's quantum double to infinite groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19386v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey Khudorozhkov, Charles Stahl, Oliver Hart, Rahul Nandkishore</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
