<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.dis-nn updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.dis-nn</link>
    <description>cond-mat.dis-nn updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.dis-nn" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 05:00:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Dephasing-induced jumps in non-Hermitian disordered lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20306</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20306v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Changes in the wavefunction's phase during propagation in a random Hermitian lattice, a process known as dephasing, results in diffusion rather than Anderson localization. However, when non-Hermiticity is introduced, the wave behavior changes drastically. In particular, we demonstrate that in weakly disordered non-Hermitian lattices, dephasing induces unexpected eigenmode localization which results in abrupt jumps between spatially distant regions. These jumps, which are absent under purely coherent conditions, emerge from the interplay between complex disorder and dephasing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20306v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emmanouil T. Kokkinakis, Konstantinos G. Makris, Eleftherios N. Economou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Color symmetry and ferromagnetism in Potts spin glass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20607v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the Potts spin glass with additional ferromagnetic interaction parametrized by $t$. It has long been observed that the Potts color symmetry breaking for the spin glass order parameter is closely related to the ferromagnetic phase transition. To clarify this, we identify a single critical value $t_\mathrm{c}$, which marks the onset of both color symmetry breaking and the transition to ferromagnetism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20607v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hong-Bin Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An analytic theory of creativity in convolutional diffusion models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20292v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We obtain the first analytic, interpretable and predictive theory of creativity in convolutional diffusion models. Indeed, score-based diffusion models can generate highly creative images that lie far from their training data. But optimal score-matching theory suggests that these models should only be able to produce memorized training examples. To reconcile this theory-experiment gap, we identify two simple inductive biases, locality and equivariance, that: (1) induce a form of combinatorial creativity by preventing optimal score-matching; (2) result in a fully analytic, completely mechanistically interpretable, equivariant local score (ELS) machine that, (3) without any training can quantitatively predict the outputs of trained convolution only diffusion models (like ResNets and UNets) with high accuracy (median $r^2$ of $0.90, 0.91, 0.94$ on CIFAR10, FashionMNIST, and MNIST). Our ELS machine reveals a locally consistent patch mosaic model of creativity, in which diffusion models create exponentially many novel images by mixing and matching different local training set patches in different image locations. Our theory also partially predicts the outputs of pre-trained self-attention enabled UNets (median $r^2 \sim 0.75$ on CIFAR10), revealing an intriguing role for attention in carving out semantic coherence from local patch mosaics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20292v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mason Kamb, Surya Ganguli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random Matrix Theory for Stochastic Gradient Descent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20496v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Investigating the dynamics of learning in machine learning algorithms is of paramount importance for understanding how and why an approach may be successful. The tools of physics and statistics provide a robust setting for such investigations. Here we apply concepts from random matrix theory to describe stochastic weight matrix dynamics, using the framework of Dyson Brownian motion. We derive the linear scaling rule between the learning rate (step size) and the batch size, and identify universal and non-universal aspects of weight matrix dynamics. We test our findings in the (near-)solvable case of the Gaussian Restricted Boltzmann Machine and in a linear one-hidden-layer neural network.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20496v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chanju Park, Matteo Favoni, Biagio Lucini, Gert Aarts</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Envelope presentation of Hamilton-Jacobi equations from spin glasses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20610v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently, [arXiv:2311.08980] demonstrated that, if it exists, the limit free energy of possibly non-convex spin glass models must be determined by a characteristic of the associated infinite-dimensional non-convex Hamilton-Jacobi equation. In this work, we investigate a similar theme purely from the perspective of PDEs. Specifically, we study the unique viscosity solution of the aforementioned equation and derive an envelope-type representation formula for the solution, in the form proposed by Evans in [doi:10.1007/s00526-013-0635-3]. The value of the solution is expressed as an average of the values along characteristic lines, weighted by a non-explicit probability measure. The technical challenges arise not only from the infinite dimensionality but also from the fact that the equation is defined on a closed convex cone with an empty interior, rather than on the entire space. In the introduction, we provide a description of the motivation from spin glass theory and present the corresponding results for comparison with the PDE results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20610v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hong-Bin Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating layer-selective transfer learning of QAOA parameters for Max-Cut problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21071v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum approximate optimization algorithm (QAOA) is a variational quantum algorithm (VQA) ideal for noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) processors, and is highly successful for solving combinatorial optimization problems (COPs). It has been observed that the optimal variational parameters obtained from one instance of a COP can be transferred to another instance, producing sufficiently satisfactory solutions for the latter. In this context, a suitable method for further improving the solution is to fine-tune a subset of the transferred parameters. We numerically explore the role of optimizing individual QAOA layers in improving the approximate solution of the Max-Cut problem after parameter transfer. We also investigate the trade-off between a good approximation and the required optimization time when optimizing transferred QAOA parameters. These studies show that optimizing a subset of layers can be more effective at a lower time-cost compared to optimizing all layers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21071v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Aldo Venturelli, Sreetama Das, Filippo Caruso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The FlEye camera: Sampling the joint distribution of natural scenes and motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21081</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21081v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: To make efficient use of limited physical resources, the brain must match its coding and computational strategies to the statistical structure of input signals. An attractive testing ground for these principles is the problem of motion estimation in the fly visual system: we understand the optics of the compound eye, have a quantitative description of input signals and noise from the retina, and can record from output neurons that encode estimates of different velocity components. Furthermore, recent work provides a nearly complete wiring diagram of the intervening circuitry. What is missing is a characterization of the visual signals and motions that flies encounter in a natural context. We attack this directly with the development of a specialized camera that matches the high temporal resolution, optical properties, and spectral sensitivity of the fly's eye; inertial motion sensors provide ground truth about rotations and translations through the world. We describe the design, construction, and performance characteristics of this FlEye camera. To illustrate the opportunities created by this instrument we use data on movies and motion to construct optimal local motion estimators that can be compared with the responses of the fly's motion sensitive neurons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21081v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charles J. Edelson, Paul Smith, Sima Setayeshgar, William Bialek, Rob R. de Ruyter van Steveninck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sparse chaos in cortical circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21188v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nerve impulses, the currency of information flow in the brain, are generated by an instability of the neuronal membrane potential dynamics. Neuronal circuits exhibit collective chaos that appears essential for learning, memory, sensory processing, and motor control. However, the factors controlling the nature and intensity of collective chaos in neuronal circuits are not well understood. Here we use computational ergodic theory to demonstrate that basic features of nerve impulse generation profoundly affect collective chaos in neuronal circuits. Numerically exact calculations of Lyapunov spectra, Kolmogorov-Sinai-entropy, and upper and lower bounds on attractor dimension show that changes in nerve impulse generation in individual neurons moderately impact information encoding rates but qualitatively transform phase space structure. Specifically, we find a drastic reduction in the number of unstable manifolds, Kolmogorov-Sinai entropy, and attractor dimension. Beyond a critical point, marked by the simultaneous breakdown of the diffusion approximation, a peak in the largest Lyapunov exponent, and a localization transition of the leading covariant Lyapunov vector, networks exhibit sparse chaos: prolonged periods of near stable dynamics interrupted by short bursts of intense chaos. Analysis of large, more realistically structured networks supports the generality of these findings. In cortical circuits, biophysical properties appear tuned to this regime of sparse chaos. Our results reveal a close link between fundamental aspects of single-neuron biophysics and the collective dynamics of cortical circuits, suggesting that nerve impulse generation mechanisms are adapted to enhance circuit controllability and information flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21188v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rainer Engelken, Michael Monteforte, Fred Wolf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cyclic Quantum Annealing: Searching for Deep Low-Energy States in 5000-Qubit Spin Glass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01034</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01034v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum computers promise a qualitative speedup in solving a broad spectrum of practical optimization problems. The latter can be mapped onto the task of finding low-energy states of spin glasses, which is known to be exceedingly difficult. Using D-Wave's 5000-qubit quantum processor, we demonstrate that a recently proposed iterative cyclic quantum annealing algorithm can find deep low-energy states in record time. We also find intricate structures in a low-energy landscape of spin glasses, such as a power-law distribution of connected clusters with a small surface energy. These observations offer guidance for further improvement of the optimization algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01034v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41598-024-80761-z</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Sci Rep 14, 30784 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hao Zhang, Kelly Boothby, Alex Kamenev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher-order localization landscape theory of Anderson localization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.05078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.05078v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For a Hamiltonian ${\hat H}$ containing a position-dependent (disordered) potential, we introduce a sequence of landscape functions $u_n(\vec{r})$ obeying ${\hat H} u_n(\vec{r}) = u_{n-1}(\vec{r})$ with $u_0(\vec{r}) = 1$. For $n \to \infty$, $1/v_n(\vec{r}) = u_{n-1}(\vec{r})/u_{n}(\vec{r})$ converges to the lowest eigenenergy $E_1$ of ${\hat H}$ whereas $u_{\infty}(\vec{r})$ yields the corresponding wave function $\psi_1(\vec{r})$. For large but finite $n$, $v_n(\vec{r})$ can be approximated by a piecewise constant function $v_n(\vec{r}) \simeq v_n^{(m)}$ for $\vec{r} \in \Omega_m$ and yields progressively improving estimations of eigenenergies $E_m = 1/v_n^{(m)}$ of locally fundamental eigenstates $\psi_m(\vec{r}) \propto u_{n}(\vec{r})$ in spatial domains $\Omega_m$. These general results are illustrated by a number of examples in one dimension: box potential, sequence of randomly placed infinite potential barriers, smooth and spatially uncorrelated random potentials, quasiperiodic potential, as well as for the uncorrelated random potential in two dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.05078v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.214209</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 214209 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sergey E. Skipetrov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy landscapes of small SK spin glasses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13580v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the $\pm J$ SK model for small $N$'s up to $N=9$. We sort the $2^{N(N-1)/2}$ possible realizations of the coupling matrix into equivalence classes according to the gauge symmetry and permutation symmetry and determine the energy spectra for each of these classes. We also study the energy landscape in these small systems and find that the elements of the hierarchic organization of ground states %and higher energy local minima start to appear in some samples already for $N$'s as small as 6.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13580v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Imre Kondor, G\'abor Papp</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase Thermalization: from Fermi Liquid to Incoherent Metal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.15666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2012.15666v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: When a system consists of a large subsystem (bath) and a small one (probe), thermalization implies induction of temperature of the bath onto the probe. If both the bath and the probe are described by same microscopic Hamiltonian, thermalization further entails that the probe imbibes the phase of the bath. We refer to this phenomenon as {\it phase thermalization}. However, it is not clear whether this phenomenon is realizable when the probe and the bath are described by different microscopic Hamiltonians. We show {\it phase thermalization} is possible even when the microscopic Hamiltonians differ significantly. We provide an explicit example, where the probe is a Fermi liquid realized by a Majorana chain with $n \gg 1$ fermions per site interacting through random hopping and the bath is an incoherent metal described by another Majorana chain with $N &gt; n$ fermions per site interacting through arbitrarily long range random four-fermion interaction. In deep infrared (\emph{i.e.} at very low energies), the probe turns into an incoherent metal, with Lyapunov spectrum and diffusion coefficient identical to the bath.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2012.15666v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10773-024-05845-y</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Int J Theor Phys 64, 1 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pinaki Banerjee, Bidisha Chakrabarty, Swapnamay Mondal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A High Dimensional Statistical Model for Adversarial Training: Geometry and Trade-Offs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.05674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.05674v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This work investigates adversarial training in the context of margin-based linear classifiers in the high-dimensional regime where the dimension $d$ and the number of data points $n$ diverge with a fixed ratio $\alpha = n / d$. We introduce a tractable mathematical model where the interplay between the data and adversarial attacker geometries can be studied, while capturing the core phenomenology observed in the adversarial robustness literature. Our main theoretical contribution is an exact asymptotic description of the sufficient statistics for the adversarial empirical risk minimiser, under generic convex and non-increasing losses for a Block Feature Model. Our result allow us to precisely characterise which directions in the data are associated with a higher generalisation/robustness trade-off, as defined by a robustness and a usefulness metric. We show that the the presence of multiple different feature types is crucial to the high sample complexity performances of adversarial training. In particular, we unveil the existence of directions which can be defended without penalising accuracy. Finally, we show the advantage of defending non-robust features during training, identifying a uniform protection as an inherently effective defence mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.05674v3</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kasimir Tanner, Matteo Vilucchio, Bruno Loureiro, Florent Krzakala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impurity effects in twisted carbon nanotubes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07131v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider electronic spectra of twisted carbon nanotubes and their perturbation by impurity atoms absorbed at different positions on nanotube surface within the framework of Anderson hybrid model. A special attention is given to the cases when 1D Weyl (massless Dirac) modes are present in the nanotube spectrum and their hybridization with localized impurity states produces, with growing impurity concentration c, onset of a mobility gap near the impurity level and then opening, at yet higher c, of some narrow range of delocalized states within this mobility gap. Such behaviors are compared with similar effects in the previously studied 2D graphene, carbon nanoribbons, and non-twisted carbon nanotubes. Some possible practical applications are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07131v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuriy G. Pogorelov, Volodymyr Turkowski, Vadim M. Loktev</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
