<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.dis-nn updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.dis-nn</link>
    <description>cond-mat.dis-nn updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.dis-nn" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 04:02:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Effective medium theory for the electrical conductance of random resistor networks which mimic crack-template-based transparent conductive films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10241</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10241v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We studied random resistor networks produced with regular structure and random distribution of edge conductances. These networks are intended to mimic crack-template-based transparent conductive films as well some random networks produced using nano-imprinting technology. Applying an effective medium theory, we found out that the electrical conductance of such networks is proportional to the square root of the number density of conductive edges. This dependence is in agreement with numerical calculations in Voronoi networks, although the effective conductances are about 15%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10241v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuri Yu. Tarasevich, Irina V. Vodolazskaya, Andrei V. Eserkepov, F\'abio D. A. Aar\~ao Reis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Short Review on Novel Approaches for Maximum Clique Problem: from Classical algorithms to Graph Neural Networks and Quantum algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09742</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09742v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This manuscript provides a comprehensive review of the Maximum Clique Problem, a computational problem that involves finding subsets of vertices in a graph that are all pairwise adjacent to each other. The manuscript covers in a simple way classical algorithms for solving the problem and includes a review of recent developments in graph neural networks and quantum algorithms. The review concludes with benchmarks for testing classical as well as new learning, and quantum algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09742v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raffaele Marino, Lorenzo Buffoni, Bogdan Zavalnij</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase determination with and without deep learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09786v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Detection of phase transitions is a critical task in statistical physics, traditionally pursued through analytic methods and direct numerical simulations. Recently, machine-learning techniques have emerged as promising tools in this context, with a particular focus on supervised and unsupervised learning methods, along with non-learning approaches. In this work, we study the performance of unsupervised learning in detecting phase transitions in the $J_1$-$J_2$ Ising model on the square lattice. The model is chosen due to its simplicity and complexity, thus providing an understanding of the application of machine-learning techniques in both straightforward and challenging scenarios. We propose a simple method based on a direct comparison of configurations. The reconstruction error, defined as the mean-squared distance between two configurations, is used to determine the critical temperatures ($T_c$). The results from the comparison of configurations are contrasted with that of the configurations generated by variational autoencoders. Our findings highlight that for certain systems, a simpler method can yield results comparable to more complex neural networks. This work contributes to the broader understanding of machine-learning applications in statistical physics and introduces an efficient approach to the detection of phase transitions using machine determination techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09786v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Burak \c{C}ivitcio\u{g}lu, Rudolf A. R\"omer, Andreas Honecker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving deep-learning density functional theory via variational autoencoders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09788v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In recent years, machine learning models, chiefly deep neural networks, have revealed suited to learn accurate energy-density functionals from data. However, problematic instabilities have been shown to occur in the search of ground-state density profiles via energy minimization. Indeed, any small noise can lead astray from realistic profiles, causing the failure of the learned functional and, hence, strong violations of the variational property. In this article, we employ variational autoencoders to build a compressed, flexible, and regular representation of the ground-state density profiles of various quantum models. Performing energy minimization in this compressed space allows us to avoid both numerical instabilities and variational biases due to excessive constraints. Our tests are performed on one-dimensional single-particle models from the literature in the field and, notably, on a three-dimensional disordered potential. In all cases, the ground-state energies are estimated with errors below the chemical accuracy and the density profiles are accurately reproduced without numerical artifacts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09788v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emanuele Costa, Giuseppe Scriva, Sebastiano Pilati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal fragility of spin-glass ground-states under single bond changes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.10376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.10376v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the effect of perturbing a single bond on ground-states of nearest-neighbor Ising spin-glasses, with a Gaussian distribution of the coupling constants, across various two and three-dimensional lattices and regular random graphs. Our results reveal that the ground-states are strikingly susceptible to such changes. Altering the strength of only a single bond beyond a critical threshold value leads to a new ground-state that differs from the original one by a droplet of flipped spins whose boundary and volume diverge with the system size -- an effect that is reminiscent of the more familiar phenomenon of disorder chaos. These elementary fractal-boundary zero-energy droplets and their composites feature robust characteristics and provide the lowest-energy macroscopic spin-glass excitations. Remarkably, within numerical accuracy, the size of such droplets conforms to a nearly universal power-law distribution with exponents dependent on the spatial dimension of the system. Furthermore, the critical coupling strengths adhere to a stretched Gaussian distribution that is predominantly determined by the local coordination number.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.10376v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mutian Shen, Gerardo Ortiz, Yang-Yu Liu, Martin Weigel, Zohar Nussinov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Logarithmic critical slowing down in complex systems: from statics to dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07565v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider second-order phase transitions in which the order parameter is a replicated overlap matrix. We focus on a tricritical point that occurs in a variety of mean-field models and that, more generically, describes higher order liquid-liquid or liquid-glass transitions. We show that the static replicated theory implies slowing down with a logarithmic decay in time. The dynamical equations turn out to be those predicted by schematic Mode Coupling Theory for supercooled viscous liquids at a $A_3$ singularity, where the parameter exponent is $\lambda=1$. We obtain a quantitative expression for the parameter $\mu$ of the logarithmic decay in terms of cumulants of the overlap, which are physically observable in experiments or numerical simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07565v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Leuzzi, Tommaso Rizzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Small field chaos in spin glasses: universal predictions from the ultrametric tree and comparison with numerical simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08503v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the chaotic behavior of the Gibbs state of spin-glasses under the application of an external magnetic field, in the crossover region where the field intensity scales proportional to $1/\sqrt{N}$, being $N$ the system size. We show that Replica Symmetry Breaking (RSB) theory provides universal predictions for chaotic behavior: they depend only on the zero-field overlap probability function $P(q)$ and are independent of other features of the system. Using solely $P(q)$ as input we can analytically predict quantitatively the statistics of the states in a small field. In the infinite volume limit, each spin-glass sample is characterized by an infinite number of states that have a tree-like structure. We generate the corresponding probability distribution through efficient sampling using a representation based on the Bolthausen-Sznitman coalescent. In this way, we can compute quantitatively properties in the presence of a magnetic field in the crossover region, the overlap probability distribution in the presence of a small field and the degree of decorrelation as the field is increased. To test our computations, we have simulated the Bethe lattice spin glass and the 4D Edwards-Anderson model, finding in both cases excellent agreement with the universal predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08503v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Aguilar-Janita, Silvio Franz, Victor Martin-Mayor, Javier Moreno-Gordo, Giorgio Parisi, Federico Ricci-Tersenghi, Juan J. Ruiz-Lorenzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equivariant graph neural network interatomic potential for Green-Kubo thermal conductivity in phase change materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.02327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.02327v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Thermal conductivity is a fundamental material property that plays an essential role in technology, but its accurate evaluation presents a challenge for theory. In this work, we demonstrate the application of $E(3)$-equivariant neutral network interatomic potentials within Green-Kubo formalism to determine the lattice thermal conductivity in amorphous and crystalline materials. We apply this method to study the thermal conductivity of germanium telluride (GeTe) as a prototypical phase change material. A single deep learning interatomic potential is able to describe the phase transitions between the amorphous, rhombohedral and cubic phases, with critical temperatures in good agreement with experiments. Furthermore, this approach accurately captures the pronounced anharmonicity that is present in GeTe, enabling precise calculations of the thermal conductivity. In contrast, the Boltzmann transport equation including only three-phonon processes tends to overestimate the thermal conductivity by approximately a factor of 2 in the crystalline phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.02327v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sung-Ho Lee, Jing Li, Valerio Olevano, Benoit Skl\'enard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weight fluctuations in (deep) linear neural networks and a derivation of the inverse-variance flatness relation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.14120</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.14120v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the stationary (late-time) training regime of single- and two-layer linear underparameterized neural networks within the continuum limit of stochastic gradient descent (SGD) for synthetic Gaussian data. In the case of a single-layer network in the weakly underparameterized regime, the spectrum of the noise covariance matrix deviates notably from the Hessian, which can be attributed to the broken detailed balance of SGD dynamics. The weight fluctuations are in this case generally anisotropic, but are subject to an isotropic loss. For a two-layer network, we obtain the stochastic dynamics of the weights in each layer and analyze the associated stationary covariances. We identify the inter-layer coupling as a new source of anisotropy for the weight fluctuations. In contrast to the single-layer case, the weight fluctuations experience an anisotropic loss, the flatness of which is inversely related to the fluctuation variance. We thereby provide an analytical derivation of the recently observed inverse variance-flatness relation in a model of a deep linear neural network.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.14120v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Markus Gross, Arne P. Raulf, Christoph R\"ath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous scaling of heterogeneous elastic lines: a new picture from sample to sample fluctuations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11073</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.11073v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study a discrete model of an heterogeneous elastic line with internal disorder, submitted to thermal fluctuations. The monomers are connected through random springs with independent and identically distributed elastic constants drawn from $p(k)\sim k^{\mu-1}$ for $k\to0$. When $\mu&gt;1$, the scaling of the standard Edwards-Wilkinson model is recovered. When $\mu&lt;1$, the elastic line exhibits an anomalous scaling of the type observed in many growth models and experiments. Here we derive and use the exact expression for the exact probability distribution of the line shape at equilibrium, as well as the spectral properties of the matrix containing the random couplings, to fully characterize the sample to sample fluctuations. Our results lead to novel scaling predictions that partially disagree with previous works, but which are corroborated by numerical simulations. We also provide a novel interpretation of the anomalous scaling in terms of the abrupt jumps in the line's shape that dominate the average value of the observable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.11073v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maximilien Bernard, Pierre Le Doussal, Alberto Rosso, Christophe Texier</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
