<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.dis-nn updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.dis-nn</link>
    <description>cond-mat.dis-nn updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.dis-nn" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 05:00:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Applications of Statistical Field Theory in Deep Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18553v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Deep learning algorithms have made incredible strides in the past decade yet due to the complexity of these algorithms, the science of deep learning remains in its early stages. Being an experimentally driven field, it is natural to seek a theory of deep learning within the physics paradigm. As deep learning is largely about learning functions and distributions over functions, statistical field theory, a rich and versatile toolbox for tackling complex distributions over functions (fields) is an obvious choice of formalism. Research efforts carried out in the past few years have demonstrated the ability of field theory to provide useful insights on generalization, implicit bias, and feature learning effects. Here we provide a pedagogical review of this emerging line of research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18553v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zohar Ringel, Noa Rubin, Edo Mor, Moritz Helias, Inbar Seroussi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetries of Living Systems: Symmetry Fibrations and Synchronization in Biological Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18713v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A symmetry is a `change without change'. As simple as it sounds, this concept is the fundamental cornerstone that unifies all branches of theoretical physics. Virtually all physical laws -- ranging from classical mechanics and electrodynamics to relativity, quantum mechanics, and the standard model -- can be expressed in terms of symmetry invariances. In this book, we explore whether the same principle can also explain the emergent laws of biological systems. We introduce a new geometry for biological networks and AI architectures, drawing inspiration from the mystic genius of Grothendieck's fibrations in category theory. We attempt to bridge the gap between physics and biology using symmetries but with a twist. The traditional symmetry groups of physics are global and too rigid to describe biology. Instead, the novel notion of symmetry fibration is local, flexible, and adaptable to evolutionary pressures, providing the right framework for understanding biological complexity. In other words, this more general symmetry invariance is necessary and sufficient to ensure that a given biological network configuration can support a synchronized function. In this book, we review the theoretical progress over the last decades from mathematics, physics, computer science, dynamical systems, and graph theory that has led to the discovery of symmetry fibrations in biological networks. These symmetries act as organizing principles for biological networks. They serve as effective tools for describing the structure of these networks, blending geometry and topology. Fibrations explain how structure dictates function across various biological domains, including the transcriptome, proteome, metabolome, and connectome. Additionally, they facilitate a reduction in the dimensionality of the network, simplifying it into its fundamental building blocks for biological computation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18713v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.MN</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Cambridge University Press, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hernan A. Makse, Paolo Boldi, Francesco Sorrentino, Ian Stewart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Prediction of Frictional Contact Network in Near-Jamming Suspensions Employing Deep Graph Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18743v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The viscosity of the suspension consisting of fine particles dispersed in a Newtonian liquid diverges close to the jamming packing fraction. The contact microstructure in suspensions governs this macroscopic behavior in the vicinity of jamming through a frictional contact network (FCN). FCN is composed of mechanical load-bearing contacts that lead to the emergence of rigidity near the jamming transition. The stress transmission and network topology, in turn, depend sensitively on constraints on the relative motion of the particles. Despite their significance, predicting the FCN, especially close to jamming conditions, remains challenging due to experimental and computational impediments. This study introduces a cost-effective machine learning approach to predict the FCN using a graph neural network (GNN), which inherently captures hidden features and underlying patterns in dense suspension by mapping interparticle interactions. Employing a variation of GNN called the Deep Graph Convolutional Network (DeepGCN) trained on data-driven simulations, this study demonstrates robust generalization and extrapolation capabilities, accurately predicting FCNs in systems with divergent flow parameters and phase spaces, despite each being trained exclusively on a single condition. The study covers a wide range of phase space, from semi-dilute to jammed states, spanning transient to steady states, while systematically varying parameters such as shear stress (${\sigma}_{xy}$), packing fraction(${\phi}$) and sliding and rolling friction (${{\mu}_s, {\mu}_r}$). The results of this research pave the way for innovative transferable techniques in predicting the properties of particulate systems, offering new avenues for advancement in material science and related fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18743v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Armin Aminimajd, Joao Maia, Abhinendra Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient optimization of neural network backflow for ab-initio quantum chemistry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18843v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The ground state of second-quantized quantum chemistry Hamiltonians is key to determining molecular properties. Neural quantum states (NQS) offer flexible and expressive wavefunction ansatze for this task but face two main challenges: highly peaked ground-state wavefunctions hinder efficient sampling, and local energy evaluations scale quartically with system size, incurring significant computational costs. In this work, we develop algorithmic improvements for optimizing these wave-functions which includes compact subspace construction, truncated local energy evaluations, improved stochastic sampling, and physics-informed modifications. We apply these improvements to the neural network backflow (NNBF) ansatz finding that they lead to improved accuracy and scalability. Using these techniques, we find NNBF surpasses traditional methods like CCSD and CCSD(T), outperform existing NQS approaches, and achieve competitive energies compared to state-of-the-art quantum chemistry methods such as HCI, ASCI, and FCIQMC. An ablation study highlights the contribution of each enhancement, showing significant gains in energy accuracy and computational efficiency. We also examine the dependence of NNBF expressiveness on the inverse participation ratio (IPR), observing that more delocalized states are generally harder to approximate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18843v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>An-Jun Liu, Bryan K. Clark</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zipping many-body quantum states: a scalable approach to diagonal entropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18898v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The outcomes of projective measurements on a quantum many-body system in a chosen basis are inherently probabilistic. The Shannon entropy of this probability distribution (the "diagonal entropy") often reveals universal features, such as the existence of a quantum phase transition. A brute-force tomographic approach to estimating this entropy scales exponentially with the system size. Here, we explore using the Lempel-Ziv lossless image compression algorithm as an efficient, scalable alternative, readily implementable in a quantum gas microscope or programmable quantum devices. We test this approach on several examples: one-dimensional quantum Ising model, and two-dimensional states that display conventional symmetry breaking due to quantum fluctuations, or strong-to-weak symmetry-breaking due to local decoherence. We also employ the diagonal mixed state to put constraints on the phase boundaries of our models. In all examples, the compression method accurately recovers the entropy density while requiring at most polynomially many images. We also analyze the singular part of the diagonal entropy density using renormalization group on a replicated action. In the 1+1-D quantum Ising model, we find that it scales as $|t| \log|t|$, where $t$ is the deviation from the critical point, while in a 2+1-D state with amplitudes proportional to the Boltzmann weight of the 2D Ising model, it follows a $t^2 \log|t|$ scaling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18898v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Hsueh Chen, Tarun Grover</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parallel spatial photonic Ising machine using spatial multiplexing for accelerating combinatorial optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18918</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18918v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A spatial photonic Ising machine (SPIM) handles large-scale combinatorial optimization problems owing to optical processing with spatial parallelism. However, iterative feedback in the search for optimal solutions limits processing speed even though the Ising Hamiltonian is computed optically. We propose a parallel spatial photonic Ising machine (pSPIM) utilizing spatial multiplexing to search for an optimal solution efficiently. By employing grating patterns and encoding multiple sets of Ising spins in a phase distribution, several Ising Hamiltonians are computed simultaneously. We demonstrated that Max-Cut problems requiring 100 Ising spins are solved faster as the number of processing units increases. In addition, combining the multicomponent model with parallel processing allows for efficient searching for optimal solutions to problems represented by using interaction matrixes with a rank greater than one. The pSPIM achieves high-speed searching of optimal solutions of large-scale combinatorial optimization problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18918v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suguru Shimomura, Jun Tanida, Yusuke Ogura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational representation and estimates for the free energy of a quenched charged polymer model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18964v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Random walks with a disordered self-interaction potential may be used to model charged polymers. In this paper we consider a one-dimensional and directed version of the charged polymer model that was introduced by Derrida, Griffiths and Higgs. We prove new results for the associated quenched free energy, including a variational formula based on a quenched large deviation principle established by Birkner, Greven and den Hollander. We also take the occasion to (i) provide detailed proofs for state-of-the-art results pointing towards the existence of a freezing transition and (ii) proceed with minor corrections for two results previously obtained by the present author with Caravenna, den Hollander and P{\'e}tr{\'e}lis for the undirected model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18964v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julien Poisat (CEREMADE)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2064 global population crisis scenario predicted by the most general dynamic model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19063v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: There is currently no consensus on how the global population will evolve in the next decades and in the next century. Currently, none of the known mathematical population-dynamic models can reproduce all these four types of functions as its solutions. This is of course a great impediment on the way towards forecasting trends in global population growth, which is an ever more urgent exercise in an era dominated by substantial climate and ecological threats. In this paper, we remedy to this situation by reporting on a population dynamic model, a single nonlinear differential equation adapted from the physics of disordered systems, which is able to mathematically describe all the various regimes encountered in the global population recorded as a function of time, over the past 12000 years until now. Regimes of simple exponential growth (Malthus), logistic (Verhulst) plateaus as well as stretched-exponential and compressed-exponential growth regimes are all reliably described by this mathematical equation in its various limits. In particular, two different scenarios are predicted. In one of them, which assumes that the future evolution would continue along a similar pattern as the past decades (hence without any major global ecological crisis affecting the resource exploitation), a von Foerster-type doomsday scenario with a sudden rise of the global population to unsustainable levels could appear as early as 2078. In the opposite scenario, if a global ecological crisis were to set in today, affecting the ability to exploit resources, given the current estimates of the Earth's carrying capacity, the global population is forecasted to reduce by half by 2064. Furthermore, the proposed dynamic model provides with a new aggregated parameter (K, in the model) that can be monitored and controlled so as to avoid the doomsday scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19063v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessio Zaccone, Kostya Trachenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact quantum critical states with a superconducting quantum processor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19185</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19185v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Anderson localization physics features three fundamental types of eigenstates: extended, localized, and critical. Confirming the presence of critical states necessitates either advancing the analysis to the thermodynamic limit or identifying a universal mechanism which can determine rigorously these states. Here we report the unambiguous experimental realization of critical states, governed by a rigorous mechanism for exact quantum critical states, and further observe a generalized mechanism that quasiperiodic zeros in hopping couplings protect the critical states. Leveraging a superconducting quantum processor with up to 56 qubits, we implement a programmable mosaic model with tunable couplings and on-site potentials. By measuring time-evolved observables, we identify both delocalized dynamics and incommensurately distributed zeros in the couplings, which are the defining features of the critical states. We map the localized-to-critical phase transition and demonstrate that critical states persist until quasiperiodic zeros are removed by strong long-range couplings, confirming the generalized mechanism. Finally, we resolve the energy-dependent transition between localized and critical states, revealing the presence of anomalous mobility edges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19185v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenhui Huang, Xin-Chi Zhou, Libo Zhang, Jiawei Zhang, Yuxuan Zhou, Zechen Guo, Bing-Chen Yao, Peisheng Huang, Qixian Li, Yongqi Liang, Yiting Liu, Jiawei Qiu, Daxiong Sun, Xuandong Sun, Zilin Wang, Changrong Xie, Yuzhe Xiong, Xiaohan Yang, Jiajian Zhang, Zihao Zhang, Ji Chu, Weijie Guo, Ji Jiang, Xiayu Linpeng, Wenhui Ren, Yuefeng Yuan, Jingjing Niu, Ziyu Tao, Song Liu, Youpeng Zhong, Xiong-Jun Liu, Dapeng Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>U-Net 3+ for Anomalous Diffusion Analysis enhanced with Mixture Estimates (U-AnD-ME) in particle-tracking data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19253v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Biophysical processes within living systems rely on encounters and interactions between molecules in complex environments such as cells. They are often described by anomalous diffusion transport. Recent advances in single-molecule microscopy and particle-tracking techniques have yielded an abundance of data in the form of videos and trajectories that contain critical information about these biologically significant processes. However, standard approaches for characterizing anomalous diffusion from these measurements often struggle in cases of practical interest, e.g. due to short, noisy trajectories. Fully exploiting this data therefore requires the development of advanced analysis methods -- a core goal at the heart of the recent international Anomalous Diffusion Challenges. Here, we introduce a novel machine-learning framework, U-net 3+ for Anomalous Diffusion analysis enhanced with Mixture Estimates (U-AnD-ME), that applies a U-Net 3+ based neural network alongside Gaussian mixture models to enable highly accurate characterisation of single-particle tracking data. In the 2024 Anomalous Diffusion Challenge, U-AnD-ME outperformed all other participating methods for the analysis of two-dimensional anomalous diffusion trajectories at both single-trajectory and ensemble levels. Using a large dataset inspired by the Challenge, we further characterize the performance of U-AnD-ME in segmenting trajectories and inferring anomalous diffusion properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19253v1</guid>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Solomon Asghar, Ran Ni, Giorgio Volpe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-Reversal Mirror inside a granular suspension: a way of measuring the ultrasound diffusion coefficient</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19304v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate that the diffusion coefficient, $D$, for ultrasound propagating in a multiple scattering medium, such as a dense granular suspension, can be measured using a time reversal experiment. This requires an unprecedented experimental setup in which a piezoelectric transducer, acting as a Time-Reversal Mirror (TRM), is embedded within the granular suspension at a depth much larger than the scattering mean free path, while an array of transducers is placed in the far field of the scattering sample. A single element of the array emits a short pulse and the TRM records the resulting ultrasonic field, which consists of a ballistic coherent wave followed by a coda wave. When the entire coda wave is time-reversed and re-emitted from the TRM, it is observed to refocus on the original source, with a focal spot size that decreases with the inverse depth of the TRM, characteristic of a diffusive regime. Time-reversal of short windows selected at different times $t$ in the coda wave reveals a focal spot size that decreases as the inverse square root of time, i.e., $1 / \sqrt{Dt}$. By fitting the predictions of a microscopic diffusion theory to our experimental data, we are able to accurately measure the diffusion coefficient in the granular suspension. Remarkably, this method does not require ensemble averaging due to stability of time-reversal against statistical fluctuations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19304v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. Abraham, B. A. van Tiggelen, N. Benech, C. Negreira, X. Jia, A. Tourin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The chiral SYK model in three-dimensional holography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19370v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A celebrated realization of the holographic principle posits an approximate duality between the $(0+1)$-dimensional quantum mechanical SYK model and two-dimensional Jackiw-Teitelboim gravity, mediated by the Schwarzian action as an effective low energy theory common to both systems. We here propose a generalization of this correspondence to one dimension higher. Starting from different microscopic realizations of effectively chiral $(1+1)$-dimensional generalizations of the SYK model, we derive a reduction to the Alekseev-Shatashvilli (AS)-action, a minimal extension of the Schwarzian action which has been proposed as the effective boundary action of three-dimensional gravity. In the bulk, we show how the same action describes fluctuations around the Euclidean BTZ black hole configuration, the dominant stationary solution of three-dimensional gravity. These two constructions allow us to match bulk and boundary coupling constants, and to compute observables. Specifically, we apply semiclassical techniques inspired by condensed matter physics to the computation of out-of-time-order correlation functions (OTOCs), demonstrating maximal chaos in the chiral SYK chain and its gravity dual.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19370v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Altland, Dmitry Bagrets, Nele Callebaut, Konstantin Weisenberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fidelity and criticality in the nonreciprocal Aubry-Andr{\'e}-Harper model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16704</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16704v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the critical behaviors of the ground and first excited states in the one-dimensional nonreciprocal Aubry-Andr{\'e}-Harper model using both the self-normal and biorthogonal fidelity susceptibilities. We demonstrate that fidelity susceptibility serves as a probe for the phase transition in the nonreciprocal AAH model. For ground states, characterized by real eigenenergies across the entire regime, both fidelity susceptibilities near the critical points scale as $N^{2}$, akin to the Hermitian AAH model. However, for the first-excited states, the fidelity susceptibilities exhibit distinct scaling laws, contingent upon whether the lattice consists of even or odd sites. For even lattices, both the self-normal and biorthogonal fidelity susceptibilities near the critical points continue to scale as $N^{2}$. In contrast, for odd lattices, the biorthogonal fidelity susceptibilities diverge, while the self-normal fidelity susceptibilities exhibit linear behavior, indicating a novel scaling law.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16704v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1209/0295-5075/ada8d6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Europhysics Letters 149, 38001 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Chen-Chang Zeng, Zhen Cai, Guang-Heng Wang, Gaoyong Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Hermitian delocalization in 1D via emergent compactness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12490v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Potential disorder in 1D leads to Anderson localization of the entire spectrum. Upon sacrificing hermiticity by adding non-reciprocal hopping, the non-Hermitian skin effect competes with localization. We find another route for delocalization, which involves imaginary potential disorder. While an entirely random potential generally still leads to localization, imposing minimal spatial structure to the disorder can protect delocalization: it endows the concomitant transfer matrix with an SU(2) structure, whose compactness in turn translates into an infinite localization length. The fraction of delocalized states can be tuned by the choice of boundary conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12490v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liang-Hong Mo, Zhenyu Xiao, Roderich Moessner, Hongzheng Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A universal route from avalanches in mean-field models with random fields to stochastic Poisson branching events</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08526v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Avalanches in mean-field models can be mapped to memoryless branching processes defining a universality class. We present a reduced expression mapping a broad family of critical and subcriticial avalanches in mean-field models at the thermodynamic limit to rooted trees in a memoryless Poisson branching processes with random occurrence times. We derive the exact mapping for the athermal random field Ising model and the democratic fiber bundle model, where avalanche statistics progress towards criticality, and as an approximation for the self-organized criticality in slip mean-field theory. Avalanche dynamics and statistics in the three models differ only on the evolution of the field density, interaction strength, and the product of both terms determining the branching number.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08526v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jordi Bar\'o, \'Alvaro Corral</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Duality breaking, mobility edges, and the connection between topological Aubry-Andr\'e and quantum Hall insulators in atomic wires with fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13190v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It is well known that the Aubry-Andr{\'e} model lacks mobility edges due to its energy-independent self-duality but may exhibit edge states. When duality is broken, we show that mobility regions arise and non-trivial topological phases emerge. By varying the degree of duality breaking, we identify mobility regions and establish a connection between Aubry-Andr{\'e} atomic wires with fermions and quantum Hall systems for a family of Hamiltonians that depends on the relative phase of laser fields, viewed as a synthetic dimension. Depending on the filling factor and the degree of duality breaking, we find three classes of non-trivial phases: conventional topological insulator, conventional topological Aubry-Andr{\'e} insulator, and unconventional (hybrid) topological Aubry-Andr{\'e} insulator. Finally, we discuss appropriate Chern numbers that illustrate the classification of topological phases of localized fermions in atomic wires.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13190v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bar Alluf, C. A. R. Sa de Melo</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
