<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.dis-nn updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.dis-nn</link>
    <description>cond-mat.dis-nn updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.dis-nn" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 02:07:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev Model in a Quantum Glassy Landscape</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22977v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a generalization of `Yukawa models' in which Majorana fermions, interacting via all-to-all random couplings as in the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) model, are parametrically coupled to disordered bosonic degrees of freedom described by a quantum $p-$spin model. The latter has its own non-trivial dynamics leading to quantum paramagnetic (or liquid) and glassy phases. At low temperatures, this setup results in SYK behavior within each metastable state of a rugged bosonic free energy landscape, the effective fermionic couplings being different for each metastable state. We show that the boson-fermion coupling enhances the stability of the quantum spin-glass phase and strongly modifies the imaginary-time Green's functions of both sets of degrees of freedom. In particular, in the quantum spin glass phase, the imaginary-time dynamics is turned from a fast exponential decay characteristic of a gapped phase into a much slower dynamics. In the quantum paramagnetic phase, on the other hand, the fermions' imaginary-time dynamics get strongly modified and the critical SYK behavior is washed away.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22977v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Surajit Bera, Jorge Kurchan, Marco Schiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Delocalization Induced by Enhanced Hyperuniformity in One-Dimensional Disordered Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23036v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In one dimension, any disorder is traditionally believed to localize all states. We show that this paradigm breaks down under hyperuniform disorder, which suppresses long-wavelength fluctuations and interpolates between random and periodic potentials. In tight-binding chains, strong hyperuniformity induces a sharp delocalization transition and the emergence of mobility edges. The transition is identified by the generalized fractal dimension and corroborated by the scaling of localization length and transmittance. Hyperuniform disorder thus provides a general mechanism for engineering mobility edges and controlling transport in low dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23036v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junmo Jeon, Harukuni Ikeda, Shiro Sakai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Replication and Information Extraction in a Minimal Agent-Environment Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23212</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23212v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider an unsupervised classifying agent that evolves by enforcing self-consistency of its labels under continual exposure to a data-generating environment. Because the agent's predictions feed back into its own regularized updates, the dynamics can stabilize into self-sustaining modes of operation, which we coin functional replicators. Remarkably, such replicators can spontaneously align with the latent structure of the environment, despite never being exposed to ground-truth labels or selected for adaptation. Using analytical tools from statistical mechanics and numerical experiments, we show that the onset of this regime corresponds to a transition driven by weak correlations between the agent's initial state and environmental structure. Extending the model to multiple agents, we find that their mutual influence can spontaneously break symmetry and produce consensus, illustrating a minimal setting for decentralized collective learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23212v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastiano Ariosto, Jerome Garnier-Brun, Luca Saglietti, Davide Straziota</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Non-Equilibrium Dissipation Parameter and the Ideal Glass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23266v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Glass materials, as quintessential non-equilibrium systems, exhibit properties such as energy dissipation that are highly sensitive to their preparation histories. A key challenge has been identifying a unified order parameter to rationalize these properties. Here, we demonstrate that a configurational distance metric can effectively collapse energy dissipation data across diverse preparation histories and testing protocols, including varying cooling rates, aging processes, probing times, and the amplitudes of mechanical excitation, as long as the temperature remains above the so-called ideal glass transition (where the extrapolated structural relaxation time diverges). Our results provide a unified description for the non-equilibrium dissipation and suggest that the putative concept of the ideal glass transition is imprinted in material characteristics</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23266v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun-Ying Jiang, Liang Gao, Hai-Bin Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universality classes of Anderson localization transitions in disordered three-dimensional non-Hermitian systems with exceptional points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23932</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23932v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We conduct a numerical study of wave localization in disordered three-dimensional non-Hermitian systems featuring exceptional points. The energy spectrum of a disordered non-Hermitian Hamiltonian, exhibiting both parity-time and parity-particle-hole symmetries, forms a cross in the complex energy plane, with an exceptional point fixed at the origin. Near the exceptional point, the system experiences a disorder-driven quantum phase transition from extended to localized states, characterized as an Anderson localization transition in non-Hermitian systems. Notably, we identify a universal critical exponent that remains independent of the distribution of random variables. The model also supports Anderson localization transitions away from the exceptional points, albeit with different critical exponents. Furthermore, we investigate wave localization in a non-Hermitian system lacking parity-time symmetry, revealing distinct universality classes. By comparing the obtained critical exponents with those reported in the literature, we conclude that the presence of exceptional points introduces new universality classes that extend beyond the established 38-fold symmetry classification for non-Hermitian systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23932v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Wang, X. R. Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Griffiths phase emerging from strong mutualistic disorder in high-dimensional interacting systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24692v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The majority of analysis of interacting systems is done for weak and well-balanced interactions, when in fact topology and rare event factors often result in strong and sign-biased interactions when considering real systems. We analyse the impact of strong mutualistic interactions in a uniformly weighted Erd\H{o}s-R\'enyi network under generalised Lotka-Volterra dynamics. In difference to the typical case we show the interaction topology and system dynamics combine to produce power law abundance distributions in a critical region of the phase diagram, identifiable as a Griffiths phase. We find asymptotic expressions for the fixed point solution in this region, and establish the boundary of this region as when topology alone determines the abundance distribution. We show that the Griffiths phase persists for strong mutualistic interactions more generally, and survives when combined with weak all-to-all competition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24692v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tommaso Jack Leonardi, Amos Maritan, Sandro Azaele</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric flow of planar domain-wall loops</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24883v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the geometric evolution of elastic domain-wall loops in two dimensions. Assuming an instantaneous, isotropic, and homogeneous arc-velocity response of the domain wall to external pressure and local signed curvature, we derive closed dynamical equations linking the enclosed area and loop perimeter for both linear and nonlinear arc-velocity response functions. This reduced description enables predictions for the dynamics of both spontaneous and externally driven domains-subjected to constant or alternating fields-within the time-dependent Ginzburg-Landau scalar $\phi ^4$ model. In the linear response regime, where a non-crossing principle holds in the absence of external driving, we obtain exact results. In particular, we demonstrate that the relaxation rate of the total spontaneous magnetization becomes quantized for arbitrary initial conditions involving multiple, possibly nested, loops, with discrete jumps corresponding to individual loop collapse events. Under external driving, the avoidance principle breaks down due to sparse interactions between interfaces-either within a single loop or between multiple loops-leading to coalescence or splitting events that change the number of loops. A quantized geometrical observable involving the total area and perimeter is identified in this case as well, exhibiting discrete jumps both at interface interaction events and at individual loop collapses. We further use approximate area-perimeter relations to estimate the spontaneous collapse lifetimes of compact magnetic domains, as well as their dynamics under alternating-field-assisted collapse in disordered ultrathin magnetic films. Our predictions are compared with experimental observations in such systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24883v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pablo Domenichini, German Salazar, Alejandro B. Kolton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Order from chaos with adaptive circuits on quantum hardware</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18259</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18259v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Programmable quantum devices provide a platform to control the coherent dynamics of quantum wavefunctions. Here we experimentally realize adaptive monitored quantum circuits, which incorporate conditional feedback into non-unitary evolution, to control quantum chaotic dynamics using a combination of local mid-circuit measurements and resets. The experiments are performed with an IBM superconducting quantum processor using up to 100 qubits that samples a quantum version of the classically chaotic Bernoulli map. This map scrambles quantum information, while local measurements and feedback attempt to steer the dynamics toward a state that is a fixed point of the map. This competition drives a dynamical phase transition between quantum and classical dynamics that we observe experimentally and describe theoretically using noisy simulations, matrix product states, and mappings to statistical mechanics models. Estimates of the universal critical properties are obtained to high accuracy on the quantum computer thanks to the large number of qubits utilized in the calculation. By successfully applying up to nearly 5000 entangling gates and 5000 non-unitary mid-circuit operations on systems up to 100 qubits, this experiment serves as a signpost on the route towards fault tolerance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18259v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bibek Pokharel, Haining Pan, Kemal Aziz, Luke C. G. Govia, Sriram Ganeshan, Thomas Iadecola, Justin H. Wilson, Barbara A. Jones, Abhinav Deshpande, Jedediah H. Pixley, Maika Takita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unraveling the role of disorder in the electronic structure of high entropy alloys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22809v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Disorder in high entropy alloys, arising from the random distribution of multiple elements, plays a crucial role in their novel properties desirable for various advanced engineering applications. We investigate the role of compositional and structural disorder on the electronic structure of osmium-based superconducting high entropy alloys, (Ru/Re)$_{0.35}$Os$_{0.35}$Mo$_{0.10}$W$_{0.10}$Zr$_{0.10}$, using photoemission spectroscopy and density functional theory (DFT). Elemental and cumulative core level shifts are found to be commensurate with elemental electronegativities and valence electron counts (VEC), respectively. Valence band spectra together with DFT results indicate that the crystal structure plays an important role in deciding the electronic structure of these high entropy alloys. Through temperature dependent high-resolution spectra, we unveil strongly suppressed spectral density of states (SDOS) in the close vicinity of Fermi level. Energy and temperature dependence of the SDOS in accordance with Altshuler-Aronov theory confirms localization of charge carriers in the presence of strong intrinsic disorder. Computed electron-phonon coupling strength and superconducting transition temperature aligning reasonably well with experiments further shed light on phonon-mediated pairing mechanism and role of disorder in these systems. Our results provide a way forward to the understanding of superconducting high entropy alloys through strategic control of disorder, VEC and crystal structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22809v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/lsjr-wcr1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Materials 9, L092001 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Neeraj Bhatt, Deepali Sharma, Asif Ali, Kapil Motla, Sonika Jangid, Ravi Prakash Singh, Ravi Shankar Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How LLMs Learn to Reason: A Complex Network Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23629v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Training large language models with Reinforcement Learning from Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) exhibits a set of distinctive and puzzling behaviors that remain poorly understood, including a two-stage learning curve, V-shaped response-length trajectories, and a pronounced vulnerability to catastrophic forgetting. In this work, we propose that these seemingly disparate phenomena can be explained using a single unifying theory: the model's reasoning process maps to the self-organization of a semantic complex network whose topology remains persistently sparse, with the average degree pinned close to two. This topology imposes a fundamental mechanism for forgetting and learning: it first drives the system into a maximally frustrated state where ``skill islands'' form, slow-learning happens, and forgetting is induced; then it enters a sharp growth phase where the new skills are ``bolted on'', driven by phase-transition-like learning at the web's frontier. Equipped with the theory, we propose \textit{Annealed-RLVR}, a principled algorithm that introduces an SFT-based ``heating'' step at the point of maximal frustration to resolve the competitive bottleneck and enhance the reasoning capability of the model. Experiments on a 1.5B-parameter model demonstrate that the approach outperforms standard RLVR on both in-distribution and out-of-distribution benchmarks. By recasting RLVR from black-box optimization into a predictable process of structural self-organization, our work provides a new physical intuition for engineering the emergent reasoning capabilities of future AI systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23629v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sihan Hu, Xiansheng Cai, Yuan Huang, Zhiyuan Yao, Linfeng Zhang, Pan Zhang, Youjin Deng, Kun Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tensor Network Markov Chain Monte Carlo: Efficient Sampling of Three-Dimensional Spin Glasses and Beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23945v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Sampling the three-dimensional (3D) spin glass -- i.e., generating equilibrium configurations of a 3D lattice with quenched random couplings -- is widely regarded as one of the central and long-standing open problems in statistical physics. The rugged energy landscape, pronounced critical slowing down, and intrinsic ergodicity breaking render standard Monte Carlo methods severely inefficient, particularly for large systems at low temperatures. In this work, we introduce the Tensor Network Markov Chain Monte Carlo (TNMCMC) approach to address the issue. It generates large-scale collective updates in MCMC using tensor networks on the 2D slices of the 3D lattice, greatly improving the autocorrelation time and offering orders-of-magnitude speed-ups over conventional MCMC in generating unbiased samples of the Boltzmann distribution. We conduct numerical experiments on 3D spin glasses up to system size $64\times 64\times 64$ using a single CPU, and show that TNMCMC dramatically suppresses critical slowing down in large disordered systems, which usually require a supercomputer to perform MCMC simulations. Furthermore, we apply our approach to the 3-state Potts model up to system size $64\times 64\times 64$ using a single CPU, and show that the TNMCMC approach efficiently traverses the exponential barriers of the strong first-order transition, whereas conventional MCMC fails. Our results reveal that TNMCMC opens a promising path toward tackling long-standing, formidable three-dimensional problems in statistical physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23945v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tao Chen, Jing Liu, Youjin Deng, Pan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Population genetics in complex ecological communities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23977v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ecological interactions can dramatically alter evolutionary outcomes in complex communities. Yet, the classic theoretical results of population genetics (e.g., Kimura's fixation formula) largely ignore ecological effects. Here, we address this shortcoming by using dynamical mean-field theory to integrate ecology into classical population genetics models. We show that ecological interactions between parents and mutants result in frequency-dependent selection and can be characterized by a single emergent parameter that measures the strength of ecological feedbacks. We derive an explicit analytic expression for the fixation probability that generalizes Kimura's famous result and analyze it in various ecological and evolutionary limits. We find that ecological interactions suppress fixation probabilities for moderately beneficial mutants when compared to Kimura's predictions, with the strength of suppression increasing with larger effective population sizes, greater selective differences between parent and mutant, and for ecosystems with a large number of "open niches" (i.e., ecosystems well below the packing bound). Frequency-dependent selection also gives rise to prolonged parent-mutant coexistence in complex communities, a phenomenon absent in classical population genetics. Our study establishes a framework for integrating ecological interactions into population genetics models and helps illuminate how ecology can affect evolutionary outcomes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23977v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shing Yan Li, Zhijie Feng, Akshit Goyal, Pankaj Mehta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Laws and Spectra of Shallow Neural Networks in the Feature Learning Regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24882v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neural scaling laws underlie many of the recent advances in deep learning, yet their theoretical understanding remains largely confined to linear models. In this work, we present a systematic analysis of scaling laws for quadratic and diagonal neural networks in the feature learning regime. Leveraging connections with matrix compressed sensing and LASSO, we derive a detailed phase diagram for the scaling exponents of the excess risk as a function of sample complexity and weight decay. This analysis uncovers crossovers between distinct scaling regimes and plateau behaviors, mirroring phenomena widely reported in the empirical neural scaling literature. Furthermore, we establish a precise link between these regimes and the spectral properties of the trained network weights, which we characterize in detail. As a consequence, we provide a theoretical validation of recent empirical observations connecting the emergence of power-law tails in the weight spectrum with network generalization performance, yielding an interpretation from first principles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24882v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonardo Defilippis, Yizhou Xu, Julius Girardin, Emanuele Troiani, Vittorio Erba, Lenka Zdeborov\'a, Bruno Loureiro, Florent Krzakala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inductive Bias and Spectral Properties of Single-Head Attention in High Dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24914v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study empirical risk minimization in a single-head tied-attention layer trained on synthetic high-dimensional sequence tasks, given by the recently introduced attention-indexed model. Using tools from random matrix theory, spin-glass physics, and approximate message passing, we derive sharp asymptotics for training and test errors, locate interpolation and recovery thresholds, and characterize the limiting spectral distribution of the learned weights. Weight decay induces an implicit nuclear-norm regularization, favoring low-rank query and key matrices. Leveraging this, we compare the standard factorized training of query and key matrices with a direct parameterization in which their product is trained element-wise, revealing the inductive bias introduced by the factorized form. Remarkably, the predicted spectral distribution echoes empirical trends reported in large-scale transformers, offering a theoretical perspective consistent with these phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24914v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabrizio Boncoraglio, Vittorio Erba, Emanuele Troiani, Florent Krzakala, Lenka Zdeborov\'a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling laws of shrinkage induced fragmentation phenomena</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06177</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06177v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the shrinkage induced breakup of thin layers of heterogeneous materials attached to a substrate, a ubiquitous natural phenomenon with a wide range of potential applications. Focusing on the evolution of the fragment ensemble, we demonstrate that the system has two distinct phases: damage phase, where the layer is cracked, however, a dominant piece persists retaining the structural integrity of the layer, and a fragmentation phase, where the layer disintegrates into numerous small pieces. Based on finite size scaling we show that the transition between the two phases occurs at a critical damage analogous to continuous phase transitions. At the critical point a fully connected crack network emerges whose structure is controlled by the strength of adhesion to the substrate. In the strong adhesion limit, damage arises from random microcrack nucleation, resembling bond percolation, while weak adhesion facilitates stress concentration and the growth of cracks to large extensions. The critical exponents of the damage to fragmentation transition agree to a reasonable accuracy with those of two-dimensional bond percolation. Our findings provide a novel insight into the mechanism of shrinkage-induced cracking revealing generic scaling laws of the phenomenon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06177v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roland Szatm\'ari, Akio Nakahara, So Kitsunezaki, Ferenc Kun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A mean-field theory for heterogeneous random growth with redistribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23189v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the competition between random multiplicative growth and redistribution/migration in the mean-field limit, when the number of sites is very large but finite. We find that for static random growth rates, migration should be strong enough to prevent localisation, i.e. extreme concentration on the fastest growing site. In the presence of an additional temporal noise in the growth rates, a third partially localised phase is predicted theoretically, using results from Derrida's Random Energy Model. Such temporal fluctuations mitigate concentration effects, but do not make them disappear. We discuss our results in the context of population growth and wealth inequalities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23189v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maximilien Bernard, Jean-Philippe Bouchaud, Pierre Le Doussal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective delocalization in the one-dimensional Anderson model with stealthy disorder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13502v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study analytically and numerically the Anderson model in one dimension with "stealthy" disorder, defined as having a power spectrum that vanishes in a continuous band of wave numbers. Motivated by recent studies on the optical transparency properties of stealthy hyperuniform layered media, we compute the localization length via the perturbation theory expansion of the self-energy. We find that, for fixed energy and small but finite disorder strength $W$, there exists for any finite length system a range of stealthiness $\chi$ for which the localization length exceeds the system size. This kind of "effective delocalization" is the result of the novel kind of correlated disorder that spans a continuous range of length scales, a defining characteristic of stealthy systems. Unlike uncorrelated disorder, for which the localization length $\xi$ scales as $W^{-2}$ to leading order for small W, the leading order terms in the perturbation expansion of $\xi$ for stealthy disordered systems vanish identically for a progressively large number of terms as $\chi$ increases such that $\xi$ scales as $W^{-2n}$ with arbitrarily large $n$. Moreover, we support our analytical results with numerical simulations. Our results may serve as a first step in investigating the role of stealthy disorder in quantum systems, which is of both theoretical and experimental relevance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13502v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlo Vanoni, Boris L. Altshuler, Paul J. Steinhardt, Salvatore Torquato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dimer-driven multiple reentrant localization with composite potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21338v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent studies have revealed reentrant localization transitions in quasi-periodic one-dimensional lattices, where the competition between dimerized hopping and staggered disorder plays a central role. Yet the extent to which such reentrant localization persists under more general conditions, such as additional periodic potentials, modified quasi-periodic modulations remains unclear. Here we investigate localization phenomena in a one-dimensional lattice subject to a periodic potential and an additional quasi-periodic modulation. Using both eigenstate-based indicators and experimentally accessible dynamical observables, we identify robust reentrant, or multiple, localization transitions. We show that these transitions are uniquely stabilized by the dimer structure of the unit cell, where the competition between the onsite periodic potential and the quasi-periodic modulation becomes most pronounced. By systematically varying the periodicity parameter $\alpha$ and the quasi-periodic frequency $\beta$, we find that the robust multiple reentrant localization behavior disappears for any deviation from the dimer configuration, confirming its essential role. Our results suggest that the interplay between these competing factors drives the multiple reentrant localization transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21338v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pei-Jie Chang, Dong Ruan, Gui-Lu Long</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal thresholds and algorithms for a model of multi-modal learning in high dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03522v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This work explores multi-modal inference in a high-dimensional simplified model, analytically quantifying the performance gain of multi-modal inference over that of analyzing modalities in isolation. We present the Bayes-optimal performance and recovery thresholds in a model where the objective is to recover the latent structures from two noisy data matrices with correlated spikes. The paper derives the approximate message passing (AMP) algorithm for this model and characterizes its performance in the high-dimensional limit via the associated state evolution. The analysis holds for a broad range of priors and noise channels, which can differ across modalities. The linearization of AMP is compared numerically to the widely used partial least squares (PLS) and canonical correlation analysis (CCA) methods, which are both observed to suffer from a sub-optimal recovery threshold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03522v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1742-5468/ae0428</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Stat. Mech. (2025) 093302</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Christian Keup, Lenka Zdeborov\'a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchy of timescales in a disordered spin-$1/2$ XX ladder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20078v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Understanding the timescales associated with relaxation to equilibrium in closed quantum many-body systems is one of the central focuses in the study of their non-equilibrium dynamics. At late times, these relaxation processes exhibit universal behavior, emerging from the inherent randomness of chaotic Hamiltonians. In this work, we investigate a disordered spin-$1/2$ XX ladder - an experimentally realizable model known for its diffusive dynamics - to explore the connection between transport properties and spectral measures derived solely from the system's energy levels via these relaxation timescales. We begin by analyzing the spectral form factor, which yields the time when the system begins to follow the random matrix theory (RMT) statistics, known as the RMT time. We then determine the Thouless times - the average times for a local excitation to diffuse across the entire finite system - through the linear-response theory for both spin and energy transport. Our numerical results confirm that the RMT time scales quadratically with system size and upper bounds the Thouless times. Interestingly, we also find that, unlike other non-integrable models, spin diffusion proceeds faster than energy diffusion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20078v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kadir \c{C}even, Lukas Peinemann, Fabian Heidrich-Meisner</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
