<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.dis-nn updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.dis-nn</link>
    <description>cond-mat.dis-nn updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.dis-nn" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 04:00:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Symmetry Breaking in Antagonistic Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.00144v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A dynamic concordia discors, a finely tuned equilibrium between opposing forces, is hypothesized to drive historical transformations. Similarly, a precise interplay of excitation and inhibition, the 80:20 ratio, is at the basis of the normal functionality of neural systems. In artificial neural networks, reinforcement learning allows for fine-tuning internal signed connections, optimizing adaptive responses to complex stimuli, and ensuring robust performance. At present, engineered structures of competing components are, however, largely unexplored, particularly because their emergent phases are closely linked with frustration mechanisms in the hosting network. In this context, the spin glass theory has shown how an apparently uncontrollable non-ergodic chaotic behavior arises from the complex interplay of competing interactions and frustration among units, leading to multiple metastable states preventing the system from exploring all accessible configurations over time. Here, we tackle the problem of disentangling topology and dynamics in systems with antagonistic interactions. We make use of the signed Laplacian operator to demonstrate how fundamental topological defects in lattices and networks percolate, shaping the geometrical arena and complex energy landscape of the system. This unveils novel, highly robust multistable phases and establishes deep connections with spin glasses when thermal noise is considered, providing a natural topological and algebraic description of their still-unknown set of pure states at zero temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.00144v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giulio Iannelli, Pablo Villegas, Tommaso Gili, Andrea Gabrielli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional diffusion without disorder in two dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00074</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.00074v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyse how simple local constraints in two dimensions lead a defect to exhibit robust, non-transient, and tunable, subdiffusion. We uncover a rich dynamical phenomenology realised in ice- and dimer-type models. On the microscopic scale the path of a single defect exhibits anomalously long retractions, amounting to dynamical caging in a continuous-time random-walk framework, culminating in an effective fractional diffusion equation. Mapping to a height field yields an effective random walk subject to an emergent (entropic) logarithmic potential, whose strength is tunable, related to the exponent of algebraic ground-state correlations. The defect's path, viewed as non-equilibrium growth process, yields a frontier of fractal dimension of $5/4$, the value for a loop-erased random walk, rather than $4/3$ for simple and self-avoiding random walks. Such frustration/constraint-induced subdiffusion is expected to be relevant to platforms such as artificial spin ice and quantum simulators aiming to realize discrete link models and emergent gauge theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.00074v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nilotpal Chakraborty, Markus Heyl, Roderich Moessner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiphoton quantum simulation of the generalized Hopfield memory model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00111</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.00111v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the present work, we introduce, develop, and investigate a connection between multiphoton quantum interference, a core element of emerging photonic quantum technologies, and Hopfieldlike Hamiltonians of classical neural networks, the paradigmatic models for associative memory and machine learning in systems of artificial intelligence. Specifically, we show that combining a system composed of Nph indistinguishable photons in superposition over M field modes, a controlled array of M binary phase-shifters, and a linear-optical interferometer, yields output photon statistics described by means of a p-body Hopfield Hamiltonian of M Ising-like neurons +-1, with p = 2Nph. We investigate in detail the generalized 4-body Hopfield model obtained through this procedure and show that it realizes a transition from a memory retrieval to a memory black-out regime, i.e. a spin-glass phase, as the amount of stored memory increases. The mapping enables novel routes to the realization and investigation of disordered and complex classical systems via efficient photonic quantum simulators, as well as the description of aspects of structured photonic systems in terms of classical spin Hamiltonians.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.00111v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gennaro Zanfardino, Stefano Paesani, Luca Leuzzi, Raffaele Santagati, Fabrizio Illuminati, Giancarlo Ruocco, Marco Leonetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Chaos to Coherence: Effects of High-Order Synaptic Correlations on Neural Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.00300v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recurrent Neural Network models have elucidated the interplay between structure and dynamics in biological neural networks, particularly the emergence of irregular and rhythmic activities in cortex. However, most studies have focused on networks with random or simple connectivity structures. Experimental observations find that high-order cortical connectivity patterns affect the temporal patterns of network activity, but a theory that relates such complex structure to network dynamics has yet to be developed. Here, we show that third- and higher-order cyclic correlations in synaptic connectivities greatly impact neuronal dynamics. Specifically, strong cyclic correlations in a network suppress chaotic dynamics, and promote oscillatory or fixed activity. The change in dynamics is related to the form of the unstable eigenvalues of the random connectivity matrix. A phase transition from chaotic to fixed or oscillatory activity coincides with the development of a cusp at the leading edge of the eigenvalue support. We also relate the dimensions of activity to the network structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.00300v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nimrod Sherf, Xaq Pitkow, Kre\v{s}imir Josi\'c, Kevin E. Bassler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipation-Driven Transition of Particles from Dispersive to Flat Bands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00796</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.00796v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Flat bands (FBs) play a crucial role in condensed matter physics, offering an ideal platform to study strong correlation effects and enabling applications in diffraction-free photonics and quantum devices. However, the study and application of FB properties are susceptible to interference from dispersive bands. Here, we explore the impact of bond dissipation on systems hosting both flat and dispersive bands by calculating the steady-state density matrix. We demonstrate that bond dissipation can drive particles from dispersive bands into FBs and establish the general conditions for this phenomenon to occur. Our results demonstrate that dissipation can facilitate FB preparation, property measurement, and utilization. This opens a new avenue for exploring FB physics in open quantum systems, with potential implications for strongly correlated physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.00796v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yutao Hu, Chao Yang, Yucheng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral Architecture Search for Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00885</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.00885v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Architecture design and optimization are challenging problems in the field of artificial neural networks. Working in this context, we here present SPARCS (SPectral ARchiteCture Search), a novel architecture search protocol which exploits the spectral attributes of the inter-layer transfer matrices. SPARCS allows one to explore the space of possible architectures by spanning continuous and differentiable manifolds, thus enabling for gradient-based optimization algorithms to be eventually employed. With reference to simple benchmark models, we show that the newly proposed method yields a self-emerging architecture with a minimal degree of expressivity to handle the task under investigation and with a reduced parameter count as compared to other viable alternatives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.00885v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gianluca Peri, Lorenzo Giambagli, Lorenzo Chicchi, Duccio Fanelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact full-RSB SAT/UNSAT transition in infinitely wide two-layer neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06717</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06717v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We analyze the problem of storing random pattern-label associations using two classes of continuous non-convex weights models, namely the perceptron with negative margin and an infinite-width two-layer neural network with non-overlapping receptive fields and generic activation function. Using a full-RSB ansatz we compute the exact value of the SAT/UNSAT transition. Furthermore, in the case of the negative perceptron we show that the overlap distribution of typical states displays an overlap gap (a disconnected support) in certain regions of the phase diagram defined by the value of the margin and the density of patterns to be stored. This implies that some recent theorems that ensure convergence of Approximate Message Passing (AMP) based algorithms to capacity are not applicable. Finally, we show that Gradient Descent is not able to reach the maximal capacity, irrespectively of the presence of an overlap gap for typical states. This finding, similarly to what occurs in binary weight models, suggests that gradient-based algorithms are biased towards highly atypical states, whose inaccessibility determines the algorithmic threshold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06717v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brandon L. Annesi, Enrico M. Malatesta, Francesco Zamponi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal generalisation and learning transition in extensive-width shallow neural networks near interpolation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18530</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18530v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a teacher-student model of supervised learning with a fully-trained two-layer neural network whose width $k$ and input dimension $d$ are large and proportional. We provide an effective theory for approximating the Bayes-optimal generalisation error of the network for any activation function in the regime of sample size $n$ scaling quadratically with the input dimension, i.e., around the interpolation threshold where the number of trainable parameters $kd+k$ and of data $n$ are comparable. Our analysis tackles generic weight distributions. We uncover a discontinuous phase transition separating a "universal" phase from a "specialisation" phase. In the first, the generalisation error is independent of the weight distribution and decays slowly with the sampling rate $n/d^2$, with the student learning only some non-linear combinations of the teacher weights. In the latter, the error is weight distribution-dependent and decays faster due to the alignment of the student towards the teacher network. We thus unveil the existence of a highly predictive solution near interpolation, which is however potentially hard to find by practical algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18530v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean Barbier, Francesco Camilli, Minh-Toan Nguyen, Mauro Pastore, Rudy Skerk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Viscosity of polymer melts using non-affine theory based on vibrational modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02806v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Viscosity, a fundamental transport and rheological property of liquids, quantifies the resistance to relative motion between molecular layers and plays a critical role in understanding material behavior. Conventional methods, such as the Green-Kubo (GK) approach, rely on time integration of correlation functions, which becomes computationally intensive near the glass transition due to slow correlation decay. A recently proposed method based on non-affine lattice dynamics (NALD) and instantaneous normal mode analysis offers a promising alternative for estimating the viscosity. In this study, we apply the NALD approach to compute the viscosity of the Kremer-Grest polymer system over a range of temperatures and compare these results with those from the GK method and non-equilibrium molecular dynamics simulations. Our findings reveal that all vibration modes, including the instantaneous normal modes, contribute to the viscosity. This work presents an efficient framework for calculating viscosity across diverse systems, including near the glass transition where the GK method is no longer applicable. Also, it opens the avenue to understanding the role of different vibrational modes linked with structure, facilitating the design of materials with tunable rheological properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02806v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ankit Singh, Vinay Vaibhav, Alessio Zaccone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Phase Transition and Geometrical Frustration in Fourier Photonic Simulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24363v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: XY models with continuous spin orientation play a pivotal role in understanding topological phase transitions and emergent frustration phenomena, such as superconducting and superfluid phase transitions. However, the complex energy landscapes arising from frustrated lattice geometries and competing spin interactions make these models computationally intractable. To address this challenge, we design a programmable photonic spin simulator capable of emulating XY models with tunable lattice geometries and spin couplings, allowing systematic exploration of their statistical behavior. We experimentally observe the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless (BKT) transition in a square-lattice XY model with nearest-neighbor interactions, accurately determining its critical temperature. Expanding to frustrated systems, we implement the approach in triangular and honeycomb lattices, uncovering sophisticated phase transitions and frustration effects, which are consistent with theoretical predictions. This versatile platform opens avenues for probing unexplored XY model phenomena across diverse geometries and interaction schemes, with potential applications in solving complex optimization and machine learning problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24363v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxuan Sun, Weiru Fan, Xingqi Xu, Da-Wei Wang, Hai-Qing Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
