<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph</link>
    <description>hep-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2024 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Non-universal probes of composite Higgs models: New bounds and prospects for FCC-ee</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09593v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the leading loop-level phenomenology of composite Higgs models via the effective field theory of a strongly interacting light Higgs and top quark (SILH+TQ). We systematically analyze the renormalization group evolution (RGE) of tree-generated operators in the SILH+TQ scenario, finding large mixings of flavor non-universal operators into those affecting electroweak precision observables. We show that these model-independent RG contributions are more important than typical estimates for finite parts. Flavor non-universal effects are completely captured by examining three options for the top mixing: fully composite $q_L^3$, equal compositeness, and fully composite $t_R$. In the most phenomenologically viable case of a fully composite $t_R$, we show that the strongest bound on the natural parameter space comes from next-to-leading log running of the 4-top operator $O_{tt} = (\bar t_R \gamma_\mu t_R)(\bar t_R \gamma^\mu t_R)$ into the Peskin-Takeuchi $T$ parameter. In general, we find that this 2-loop effect allows existing electroweak precision data to give a better constraint on 4-top operators compared to high-energy probes from top production at the LHC. Independent of the top mixing, we find that a future tera-$Z$ machine such as FCC-ee has the potential to probe composite Higgs models up to a scale of $m_* \gtrsim 25$ TeV, and test the naturalness of the electroweak scale at the $\lesssim 10^{-4}$ level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09593v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben A. Stefanek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Triboson production in the SMEFT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09600v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the production of three electroweak gauge bosons at the LHC, in the effective field theory of the standard model, at dimension six and next-to-leading order in QCD. We present results for inclusive cross-sections and differential distributions, finding that these QCD corrections are large, often vary across the phase-space and notably differ from those observed in the standard model. We then explore the potential of the recently observed triboson production processes for improving the sensitivity brought by electroweak precision observables and diboson data. The additional sensitivity we observe is dominated by resonant Higgs boson contributions, with decays to photon pairs in particular. A global analysis including Higgs boson data is therefore needed for a fair assessment of the future reach of triboson measurements on heavy new physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09600v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eugenia Celada, Gauthier Durieux, Ken Mimasu, Eleni Vryonidou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Axion Interactions with Domain and Bubble Walls</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09603v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that interactions between axion-like particles (ALPs) and co-dimension one defects, such as phase-transition bubble walls and solitonic domain walls, can lead to important changes in the evolution of both walls and ALPs. The leading effect arises from the change in the ALP decay constant across the interface, which naturally follows from shift-symmetric interactions with the corresponding order parameter. Specifically, we show that for thin walls moving relativistically, an ALP background -- such as e.g. axion dark matter -- gives rise to a frictional force on the interface that is proportional to $\gamma^2$, with $\gamma$ the Lorentz factor of the wall, and that this effect is present in both the oscillating and frozen axion regimes. We explore the broader consequences of this effect for bubble and domain walls in the early universe, and show that this source of friction can be present even in the absent of a conventional medium such as radiation or matter. Possible implications include modifications to the dynamics of bubble and domain walls and their corresponding gravitational wave signatures, as well as the generation of a dark radiation component of ALPs in the form of ultra-relativistic `axion shells' with Lorentz factor $\gamma_\text{shell} \simeq 2\gamma^2 \gg 1$ that may remain relativistic until the present day.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09603v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Isabel Garcia Garcia, Rudin Petrossian-Byrne</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soft-gluon exchange matters: isotropic screening in QCD kinetic theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09605</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09605v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: QCD kinetic theory simulations are a prominent tool for studying the nonequilibrium initial stages in heavy-ion collisions. Despite their success, all implementations rely on approximations of the hard thermal loop (HTL) screened matrix elements in the collision terms. In this paper, we present our results for different isotropic screening prescriptions in the elastic collision term for gluons. In particular, we go beyond the simple Debye-like screening form that is used in all current implementations and apply the isotropic HTL matrix element instead. For isotropic systems, the evolution is nearly unchanged, but when studying the equilibration process in a Bjorken expanding plasma, we find qualitative and quantitative differences in a range of moments of the distribution function, such as a decrease in the maximum pressure anisotropy by up to 50%. In contrast, we find no significant qualitative impact on the jet quenching parameter or on the late-time hydrodynamization dynamics of anisotropic plasmas but observe systematically smaller values of $\eta/s$ by about 10% that coincide with perturbative calculations at small couplings. Our study reveals that the choice of the screening prescription can lead to large corrections at early times, but is less important close to equilibrium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09605v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kirill Boguslavski, Florian Lindenbauer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Phenomenological Analysis of LHC Neutrino Scattering at NLO Accuracy Matched to Parton Showers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09611</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09611v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We perform a detailed phenomenological study of high-energy neutrino deep inelastic scattering (DIS) focused on LHC far-forward experiments such as FASER$\nu$ and SND@LHC. To this aim, we parametrise the neutrino fluxes reaching these LHC far-forward experiments in terms of `neutrino PDFs' encoding their energy and rapidity dependence by means of the LHAPDF framework. We integrate these neutrino PDFs in the recently developed POWHEG-BOX-RES implementation of neutrino-induced DIS to produce predictions accurate at next-to-leading order (NLO) in the QCD coupling matched to parton showers (PS) with Pythia8. We present NLO+PS predictions for final-state distributions within the acceptance of FASER$\nu$ and SND@LHC as well as for two experiments of the proposed Forward Physics Facility (FPF), FASER$\nu$2 and FLArE. We quantify the impact of NLO QCD corrections, of the parton showering and hadronisation settings in Pythia8, of the QED shower, and of the incoming neutrino flavour for the description of these observables, and compare our predictions with the GENIE neutrino event generator. Our work demonstrates the relevance of modern higher-order event generators to achieve the key scientific targets of the LHC neutrino experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09611v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Melissa van Beekveld, Silvia Ferrario Ravasio, Eva Groenendijk, Peter Krack, Juan Rojo, Valentina Sch\"utze S\'anchez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flavor-Specific Dark Matter Signatures through the Lens of Neutrino Oscillations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09614v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the flavor-specific properties of leptophilic dark matter in neutrino mass models, where dark matter signals are directly correlated with the neutrino oscillation data, providing complementary insights into the neutrino mass hierarchy and CP phases. Notably, this can be accomplished without introducing a flavor-specific portal to dark matter, imposing any new flavor symmetry, or involving flavon fields. As a case study, we analyze the correlation between the flavor-philic nature of dark matter and neutrino oscillation data in the type-II seesaw and Zee-Babu models, and extend this discussion to other neutrino mass models. We analyze the indirect signatures of such leptophilic dark matter, specifically examining the spectrum of the cosmic ray electron/positron flux resulting from the pair annihilation of dark matter in the Galactic halo, and explore correlated lepton-specific signals at collider experiments sensitive to neutrino oscillation data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09614v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhaditya Bhattacharya, Sven Fabian, Johannes Herms, Sudip Jana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized CP Symmetries in Three-Higgs-Doublet Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09615v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the scalar and Yukawa sectors of three Higgs doublets models with a generalized CP symmetry. We show that there are only four classes of scalar potentials, merely one more than in two Higgs doublet models (2HDM). In 2HDM with generalized CP symmetries extended to the Yukawa sector, there are only two possible cases: the usual CP, with 18 real Yukawa couplings; and a minimal generalized CP model, with 12 real Yukawa parameters. In contrast, with three Higgs there is a rich variety of allowed models. We classify all possible Yukawa textures, showing that there are 40 possibilities, several of which have only 10 real Yukawa couplings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09615v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Iris Bree, Duarte D. Correia, Joao P. Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Excitations of the Higgs boson</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09650v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a simplified version of the standard model with a single quark doublet, I derive a transcendental equation for the complex Higgs boson mass. The equation involves a divergent integral which is regularized and renormalized conventionally. Setting the Higgs mass to its observed value, the decay width is narrow and within experimental limits. The mass equation has additional roots on other sheets in the complex energy plane. The first two are at 186 and 219 GeV. The lightest excitations are well defined though wider than the 125 GeV Higgs because decays to $W^{+}W^{-}$ and $ZZ$ are allowed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09650v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gregory A. Wright</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simultaneous Extraction of the Weak Radius and the Weak Mixing Angle from Parity-Violating Electron Scattering on $^{12}\mathrm{C}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09743v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the impact of nuclear structure uncertainties on a measurement of the weak charge of $^{12}\mathrm{C}$ at the future MESA facility in Mainz. Information from a large variety of nuclear models, accurately calibrated to the ground-state properties of selected nuclei, suggest that a $0.3$% precision measurement of the parity-violating asymmetry at forward angles will not be compromised by nuclear structure effects, thereby allowing a world-leading determination of the weak charge of $^{12}\mathrm{C}$. Further, we show that a combination of measurements of the parity-violating asymmetry at forward and backward angles for the same electron beam energy can be used to extract information on the nuclear weak charge distribution. We conclude that a $0.34$% precision on the weak radius of $^{12}\mathrm{C}$ may be achieved by performing a $3$% precision measurement of the parity-violating asymmetry at backward angles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09743v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Cadeddu, Nicola Cargioli, Jens Erler, Mikhail Gorchtein, Jorge Piekarewicz, Xavier Roca-Maza, Hubert Spiesberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Influence of magnetic field-induced anisotropic gluon pressure during pre-equilibrium in heavy-ion collisions: A faster road towards isotropization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09754v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic fields of a large intensity can be generated in peripheral high-energy heavy-ion collisions. Although their intensity drops fast and, moreover, it is not clear whether these fields last long enough to induce a magnetization during the quark-gluon plasma phase, most of the models and simulations predict a significant intensity that lasts up to proper times of order 1 fm after the beginning of the reaction, which is a typical time for the hydrodynamical phase to start. This interval of time is referred to as the pre-equilibrium stage. The evolution of the reaction during pre-equilibrium is thus likely to be influenced by these fields. In this work we adopt a strong field approximation to study the effects of the magnetic field-induced anisotropy on the gluon pressure. We include this anisotropy within the description obtained by means of Effective Kinetic Theory and explore the consequences to reach isotropization at proper times of order 1 fm. We show that when including the magnetic field effects, isotropization is achieved faster.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09754v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Ayala, A. Mizher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A progress in inverse matrix method in QCD sum rules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09819v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In traditional QCD sum rules, the simple hadron spectral density model of ``delta-function-type ground state + theta-function-type continuous spectrum" determines that there is no perfect parameter selection. In recent years, inverse problem methods, especially the inverse matrix method, have shown better handling of QCD sum rules. This work continues to develop the inverse matrix method. Considering that the narrow-width approximation may still be a good approximation, we separate the contribution of the ground state from the spectral density. Then follow the general steps of the inverse matrix method to extract physical quantities such as decay constants that we are sometimes more interested in.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09819v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhen-Xing Zhao, Yi-Peng Xing, Run-Hui Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark energy from non-degenerate Higgs-vacuum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09840</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09840v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Scalar fields are favorite among the possible candidates for the dark energy. Most frequently discussed are those with degenerate minima at $\pm \phi_{min}$. In this paper, a slightly modified two-Higgs doublet model is taken to contain the Higgs field(s) as the dark energy candidate(s). The model considered has two non-degenerate minima at $\phi_{\pm}$, instead of one degenerate minimum at $\pm\phi_{min}$. The component fields of one SU(2) doublet ($\phi_1$) act as the standard model (SM) Higgs, while the component fields of the second doublet ($\phi_2$) are taken to be the dark energy candidates (lying in the true vacuum). It is found that one \emph{can} arrange for late time acceleration (dark energy) by using an SU(2) Higgs doublet, whose vacuum expectation value is zero, in the quintessential regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09840v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1142/S0218271820400088</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Inter nati onal Jour nal of M o der n Phys i cs D International Journal of Modern Physics D, Vol. 28, No. 16 (2019) 2040008 (11 pages)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Usman, Asghar Qadir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Properties of neutron stars and strangeness-mixed stars from a pion mean-field approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09869v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the properties of the static neutron stars and strangeness-mixed stars, based on the equations of state derived from a pion mean-field approach. Using the empirical data on the pion-nucleus scattering and bulk properties of nuclear matter, we have already fixed all the parameters in a previous work, where the nucleons and hyperons were shown to be modified in various nuclear medium. In the current work, we first examine the energy and pressure inside a neutron star. We show that the central densities in various neutron stars vary within the range of $(3-6)\rho_0$, where $\rho_0$ is the normal nuclear matter density. The mass-radius relations are obtained and discussed. As the slope parameter for neutron matter increases, the radii of the neutron stars increase with their masses fixed. We also study the strangeness-mixed stars or the hyperon stars using the same sets of the parameters. As the strangeness content of strange matter increases, the binding energy per nucleon is saturated and the corresponding equation of state becomes softened. Consequently, the central densities of the strangeness-mixed stars increase. Assuming that recently observed neutron stars are the strangeness-mixed ones, we find that the central densities increase. In the case of the pure strange stars, the central densities reach almost $(5-6)\rho_0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09869v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nam-Yong Ghim, Hyun-Chul Kim, Ulugbek Yakhshiev, Ghil-Seok Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leptonic CP-violation in the sneutrino sector of the BLSSM with Inverse Seesaw</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09957</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09957v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study CP violation (CPV) in the sneutrino sector within the B-L extension of the Minimal Supersymmetric Standard Model (BLSSM), wherein an inverse seesaw mechanism has been implemented. CPV arises from the new superpotential couplings in the (s)neutrino sector, which can be complex and the mixing of CP-eigenstates induced by those couplings. CPV leads to asymmetries in so called T-odd observables, but we argue that such asymmetries also lead to a wider distribution of those observables. We look at a final state where a sneutrino decays to a lepton, two jets and missing transverse momentum at the Future Circular Collider operating in hadron-hadron mode at $100$ TeV and with a luminosity of 3~ab$^{-1}$. In order to exclude the CP conserving scenario we need to improve traditional analysis by introducing boosted decision trees using both standard kinematic variables and T-odd observables and we need $Z^{\prime}$ boson not too much above current bounds as a portal to produce sneutrinos efficiently.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09957v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arindam Basu, Amit Chakraborty, Yi Liu, Stefano Moretti, Harri Waltari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing gluon saturation and nuclear structure in photon-nucleus collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09963v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We calculate exclusive vector meson photoproduction within the Color Glass Condensate framework in high-energy photon-nucleus scattering probed experimentally in ultra peripheral heavy ion collisions at RHIC and at the LHC. When the free parameters are constrained by the $\gamma+p$ data from HERA, we predict significant nuclear suppression for both the coherent and incoherent photoproduction cross section in the TeV range. Our results indicate that the LHC data prefers even stronger saturation effects at the highest collision energies. Furthermore, we demonstrate how the linear polarization of photons in ulra peripheral collisions generates azimuthal modulations in the decay products of the exclusively produced vector meson. We show how these measurements can probe details of the nuclear geometry, specifically the deformed structure of the uranium nuclei.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09963v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heikki M\"antysaari, Farid Salazar, Bj\"orn Schenke, Chun Shen, Wenbin Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards ultimate fragmentation functions at future lepton colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10059v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we study the constraining power of future lepton colliders on fragmentation functions (FFs) to light charged hadrons from quarks and gluon in the framework of QCD collinear factorization. We perform analyses of FFs by including a wide range of pseudo--data from future lepton colliders, such as measurements on hadron multiplicities in the inclusive production of two jets and $W$ boson pairs, at various center of mass energies, and from hadronic decays of the Higgs boson, including both to heavy quarks and to gluons. The high luminosity and high energies of future lepton colliders allow for quark flavor separations and ensure a precise determination of FFs based solely on data from electron-positron collisions. We find that either CEPC, FCC-$ee$ or ILC can significantly reduce the uncertainties of FFs in a wide kinematic range, compared to the NPC23 set obtained with a global analyses to current world data. We also discuss the impact of higher-order QCD corrections, and the potential constraints from measurements of three-jet production. Furthermore, we describe an update of the FMNLO program allowing for calculating hadron production cross sections at next-to-next-to-leading order in QCD, which is used in this study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10059v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bin Zhou, Jun Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-pion emission decays of negative parity singly heavy baryons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10063v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate two-pion emission decays of singly charmed and bottom baryons, focusing on $\Lambda_Q^*(1P)$ and $\Xi_Q^*(1P)$ with $Q=c$ (charm) or $b$ (bottom) quarks and $J^P=1/2^-,3/2^-$, belonging to antisymmetric flavor triplet $\bar{\boldsymbol{3}}_F$. Our analysis encompasses both sequential processes, involving intermediate states belonging to symmetric flavor sextet $\boldsymbol{6}_F$ such as $\Sigma_Q(1S)$ and $\Xi_Q^\prime(1S)$ respectively with $J^P=1/2^+,3/2^+$, derived from the chiral quark model, and direct process crucial for comparison with experimental data, whose coupling constants estimated using the chiral-partner scheme. We also incorporate the convolution of the parent particle's mass for the Dalitz plot, enabling a more realistic comparison with experimental data. We scrutinize the Dalitz plots of these negative parity states in light of recent Belle measurements for $\Lambda_c(2625)^+$. Our findings support the assignment of $\Lambda_c(2625)^+$ as the $\lambda$-mode excitation with $J^P=3/2^-$ in the quark model, deduced from the the ${\Lambda_c\pi}$ invariant mass distribution, and we then give predictions for other cases, including the $\Xi_Q^*$ decays. The observed asymmetry in the ${\pi\pi}$ invariant mass distribution underscores the important role of the direct process, reflecting the chiral-partner structure in the heavy baryon sector. It is evident that the presence of the direct process is not significant in the three-body decays unless the $S$-wave resonance contribution is suppressed. We suggest further experimental verification to test our predictions and get more insights into the structure of heavy baryons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10063v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nongnapat Ponkhuha, Ahmad Jafar Arifi, Daris Samart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Wave Signatures of First-Order Phase Transition in Two-Component Dark Matter Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10123</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10123v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Here, we consider a classically scale-invariant extension of the Standard Model (SM) with two-component dark matter (DM) candidates, including a Dirac spinor and a scalar DM. We probe the parameter space of the model, constrained by relic density and direct detection, and investigate the generation of gravitational waves (GWs) produced by an electroweak first-order phase transition (EFOPT). The analysis demonstrates that there are points in the parameter space, leading to a detectable GW spectrum arising from the first-order phase transition, which is also consistent with the DM relic abundance and direct detection bounds. These GWs could be observed by forthcoming space-based interferometers such as the Big Bang Observer (BBO), Decihertz Interferometer Gravitational-wave Observatory (DECIGO), and Ultimate-DECIGO (UDECIGO).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10123v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seyed Yaser Ayazi, Mojtaba Hosseini, Rouzbeh Rouzbehi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the non-trivial isoscalar pseudoscalar structures in the $K_S K_S\pi^0$ spectra in the $J/\psi$ radiative decay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10234v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Initiated by the recent observation of a flattened lineshape of $IJ^{PC}=00^{-+}$ around $1.4\sim 1.5$ GeV in the $K_S K_S \pi^0$ invariant mass spectrum by BESIII, we make a systematic partial wave analysis of $J/\psi \to\gamma\eta_X\to \gamma K\bar{K}\pi$ based on an isobaric approach. We demonstrate that in the scenario of the first radial excitations of the isoscalar pseudoscalar from the $K\bar{K}\pi$ threshold to about 1.6 GeV the non-trivial $K_S K_S \pi^0$ invariant mass spectrum can be explained by the coupled-channel effects with the presence of the triangle singularity mechanism. It shows that a combined fit of the three-body and two-body spectra can be achieved which suggests that the one-state solution around $1.4\sim 1.5$ GeV proposed before still holds well. In particular, we show that the coupled-channel effects between the two most important quasi-two-body decay channels, $K^*\bar{K}+c.c.$ and $a_0(980)\pi$, can be well described by taking into account the one-loop corrections in the isobaric approach. This is because the isoscalar pseudoscalar states are coupled to the $K^*\bar{K}+c.c.$ and $a_0(980)\pi$ channels via the $P$ and $S$ waves, respectively. As a consequence, the coupled-channel effects can be largely absorbed into the redefinition of the tree-level effective couplings with the transition amplitudes computed to the order of one-loop corrections. Then, the coupled-channel effects can be estimated by the contributions from the one-loop rescattering amplitudes in comparison with the tree-level ones, where we find that the rescattering contributions from the $P$-wave into the $S$-wave, or vice verse, are apparently suppressed in the kinematic region near threshold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10234v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yin Cheng, Lin Qiu, Qiang Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing quarkonium gravitational form factors using contact interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10437</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10437v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given the unique role of gravitational form factors in unveiling the internal mechanics of hadrons, we examine the gravitational form factors (GFFs) of quarkonium systems within the Dyson-Schwinger and Bethe-Salpeter equations framework. A contact interaction model is employed, along with a novel approach to the dressed amputated meson-meson scattering amplitude that makes contact with the energy-momentum tensor and so the GFFs. The resulting form factors fulfill the anticipated symmetry constraints. The corresponding charge and mass radii are also analyzed, as well as the so-called $D-$term. For pseudoscalar mesons, we show that the $D-$term is bounded within the $(-1, -1/3)$ range; the bounds corresponding to the massless and infinitely massive cases, respectively. Considering the current diversity of opinions in the field, we anticipate that lattice QCD simulations can provide a refined analysis, as resolving the gravitational form factors and \textit{D}-term of quarkonium holds significant physical implications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10437v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Atif Sultan, Zanbin Xing, Kh\'epani Raya, Adnan Bashir, Lei Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigation on the stabilities of doubly heavy tetraquark states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10443v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In our recent work\cite{Noh:2023zoq}, the mass and binding energy of $T_{cc}$ are found to be $3873$ MeV and $-2$ MeV, respectively, which align with the observations reported at LHCb\cite{LHCb:2021vvq}. Based on our latest quark model approach, we extend our search for other potentially stable configurations of doubly heavy tetraquarks using our nonrelativistic quark model described in Ref.~\cite{Noh:2023zoq}. Our numerical calculations indicate that the $\bar{u}\bar{s}cb$ configuration is deeply bound. However, the $\bar{u}\bar{d}cb$ configuration with the isospin symmetry in the light quark sector is relatively less bound. In this study, we emphasize a compulsory aspect for requiring a complete set of three dimensional harmonic oscillator bases through the discussion of the $\bar{u}\bar{s}cb$ configuration and investigate the essential differences between the $\bar{u}\bar{s}cb$ and $\bar{u}\bar{d}cb$ configurations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10443v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Woosung Park, Sungsik Noh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contribution to the Proton Spin Puzzle from Helicity at small Bjorken $x$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10491v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The contribution to proton helicity from the spins of quarks and gluons at small Bjorken $x$ can be conveniently studied through the small-$x$ helicity evolution. Recently, it has been employed in a global analysis that includes polarized inclusive and semi-inclusive deep-inelastic scattering measurements at small $x$. The analysis demonstrates an excellent agreement between the evolution and the data, but its predictions contain large uncertainties owing to the large number of free parameters in the initial conditions. The latest development aims to mitigate this issue by employing the valence quark model in the polarized proton target in order to replace most of the free parameters in the initial conditions by the physical information from the proton model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10491v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yossathorn Tawabutr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D structure of hadrons and energy-momentum tensor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10496v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The three-dimensional spatial structure of hadrons is encoded in their form factors. Via appropriate Fourier transform, the latter describe how charge, energy, linear and angular momentum, but also pressure are distributed inside these systems. Electromagnetic form factors of the nucleon have been measured for a long time, but it is only recently that some gravitational form factors have been extracted from experimental data, creating a great deal of enthusiasm in the hadronic community. Here we summarize some of the recent developments on the interpretation of these form factors, and provide a quick overview of what we can learn about the nucleon mass, spin and internal pressure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10496v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\'edric Lorc\'e (Ecole Polytechnique)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confronting the low-scale seesaw and leptogenesis with neutrinoless double beta decay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10560v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revisit the impact of heavy neutrinos with masses in the MeV-GeV range on neutrinoless double beta decay ($0\nu\beta\beta$) in view of updated results for the lifetime of this process. Working in a minimal realistic extension of the Standard Model by two right-handed neutrino flavours, we show that the non-observation of $0\nu\beta\beta$ will impose strong bounds on the heavy neutrino properties that are complementary to the limits obtained from Big Bang Nucleosynthesis and collider searches. For an inverted mass hierarchy of the light neutrinos we find that improved limits on $0\nu\beta\beta$ from next-generation experiments will restrict the allowed parameter space for fixed mass splitting to narrow bands in the mass-mixing plane. Further combining this with the requirement to explain the baryon asymmetry of the universe via leptogenesis reduces these bands to windows in parameter space that are constrained in all directions and can be targeted by direct searches at accelerators. For a normal mass hierarchy, only parts of the parameter space can be probed by such experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10560v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. de Vries, M. Drewes, Y. Georis, J. Klari\'c, V. Plakkot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian approach to determine the initial condition for the Balitsky-Kovchegov equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10581v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present posterior distributions of parameters that characterize the nonperturbative initial input for the Balitsky-Kovchegov evolution equation. The BK equation evolves an initial dipole-target scattering amplitude at moderate $x_{\mathrm{Bj}}$ values toward smaller values. We use Bayesian inference to constrain the model parameters against the precise combined reduced cross section data from HERA, and obtain probability distributions for the free parameters. Our results show the data's preference for the anomalous dimension to be $\gamma \sim 1$. The distributions provide a rigorous method for propagating uncertainties of the BK initial condition for other CGC calculations. We demonstrate this for inclusive quark production in proton-proton collisions and nuclear modification factor for the total deep inelastic scattering cross section to be measured at the EIC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10581v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlisle Casuga, Mikko Karhunen, Heikki M\"antysaari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Muon-induced collisional flavor instability in core-collapse supernova</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10604</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10604v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Neutrinos are known to undergo flavor conversion among their three flavors. In the theoretical modeling of core-collapse supernova (CCSN), there has been a great deal of attention to recent discoveries of a new type of neutrino flavor conversions, namely collisional flavor instability (CFI), in which the instability is induced by the flavor-dependent decoherence due to the disparity of neutrino-matter interactions among flavors. In this paper, we study how the appearance of on-shell muons and associated neutrino-matter interactions can impact CFIs based on linear stability analysis of flavor conversions. Some striking results emerge from the present study. First, we analytically show that breaking beta- and pair equilibrium is a necessary condition to trigger CFIs. This also indicates that CFIs with on-shell muons could appear in $e \tau$ and $\mu \tau$ neutrino mixing sectors in very high-density region ($\gtrsim 10^{13} {\rm g/cm^{3}}$), exhibiting a possibility of large impacts of CFIs on CCSN. Second, resonance-like CFIs, having a much higher growth rate than normal CFIs, can be triggered by muons. The resonance point of CFIs is different between $e \tau$ and $\mu \tau$ sectors; the former (latter) occurs at $\mu_{e (\mu)} = \mu_{n} - \mu_{p}$, where $\mu_{i}$ denotes the chemical potential of $i$ constitute ($n$ and $p$ represent neutrons and protons, respectively). Our result suggests that the non-linear evolution of CFI with on-shell muons would induce flavor conversions with the complex interplay among all three different neutrino-mixing sectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10604v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiabao Liu, Hiroki Nagakura, Ryuichiro Akaho, Akira Ito, Masamichi Zaizen, Shun Furusawa, Shoichi Yamada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dual symmetries of dense isotopically and chirally asymmetric QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10608</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10608v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the present paper, the dual symmetries of dense quark matter phase diagram found in some massless three- and two-color NJL models in the mean field approximation have been shown to exist at a more fundamental level as a dual transformations of fields and chemical potentials leaving the Lagrangian invariant. As a result, the corresponding dual symmetries of the full phase diagram can be shown without any approximation. And it has been shown not only in the NJL models, but also in framework of two- and three-color massless QCD itself. This is quite interesting, since one might say that it is not very common to show something completely non-perturbatively in QCD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10608v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. G. Klimenko, R. N. Zhokhov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification of Coupled-Channel Near-Threshold Structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10620v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Since 2003, plenty of resonant structures have been observed in the heavy quarkonium regime. Many of them are close to the thresholds of a few pairs of heavy hadrons. They are candidates of exotic hadrons and have attracted immense attentions. Based on a coupled-channel nonrelativistic effective field theory, we classify the near-threshold structures of a symmetry-related two-channel system according to the scattering length and channel coupling strength. We show that the evolution of the scattering amplitude line shapes can be understood from the pole trajectories in the complex energy plane, and the pole evolution can be traced back to the renormalization group fixed points. We provide a dictionary of correspondence between the evolution of line shapes and pole trajectories, which can be used to understand the experimental observations of the near-threshold structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10620v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhen-Hua Zhang, Feng-Kun Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global analysis of nuclear parton distribution functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10719v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We review the theoretical foundations, methodological approaches and current status of the determination of nuclear parton distribution functions (PDFs). A large variety of measurements in fixed-target and collider experiments provide increasingly precise constraints on various aspects of nuclear PDFs, including shadowing, antishadowing, the EMC effect, Fermi motion, flavour separation, deuteron binding, target-mass and other higher-twist effects. We give particular emphasis to measurements carried out in proton-lead collisions at the Large Hadron Collider, which have revolutionised the global analysis during the past decade. These measurements include electroweak boson, isolated photon, single inclusive hadron, jet, and heavy-flavour observables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10719v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Klasen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A phenomenological investigation of the beauty content of a proton in the framework of $k_t$-factorization using KMR and MRW unintegrated parton distributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10824v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we address the reduced beauty cross section (${\sigma_{red}}^{b\overline{b}}(x, Q^2)$) and the beauty structure function (${F_2}^{b\overline{b}}(x, Q^2)$), to study the beauty content of a proton. We calculate ${\sigma_{red}}^{b\overline{b}}$ and ${F_2}^{b\overline{b}}$ in the $k_t$-factorization formalism by using the integral form of the Kimber-Martin-Ryskin and Martin-Ryskin-Watt unintegrated parton distribution function with the angular ordering constraint ($AOC$) and the MMHT2014 PDF set as the input. Recently Guiot and van Hameren demonstrated that the upper limit, $K_{max}$, of the transverse-momentum integration performed in the $k_t$-factorization formalism should be almost equal to Q, where Q is the hard scale, otherwise it leads to an overestimation of the proton structure function ($F_2(x, Q^2)$). In the present work, we show that $k_{max}$ cannot be equal Q at low and moderate energy region, and also by considering the gluon and quark contributions to the same perturbative order and a physical gauge for the gluon, i. e., $A^\mu q^{\prime}_\mu=0$ in the calculation of ${F_2}^{b\overline{b}}$ in the $k_t$-factorization formalism, we do not encounter any overestimation of the theoretical predictions due to different choices of $K_{max}&gt;Q$. Finally, the resulted ${\sigma_{red}}^{b\overline{b}}$ and ${F_2}^{b\overline{b}}$ are compared to the experimental data and the theoretical predictions. In general, the extracted ${\sigma_{red}}^{b\overline{b}}$ and ${F_2}^{b\overline{b}}$ based on the KMR and MRW approaches are in perfect agreement with the experimental data and theoretical predictions at high energies, but at low and moderate energies, the one developed from the KMR approach has better consistency than that of MRW approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10824v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naeimeh Olanj</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The infamous 95 GeV $\rm b \bar b$ excess at LEP: Two b or not two b?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10948</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10948v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A small deviation observed around 95 GeV in the diphoton invariant mass distribution in the LHC Run 2 data has been subject to considerable attention in the past couple years. The interpretation of this excess as the manifestation of an additional scalar particle at this mass is often claimed to be supported by a previously observed, even smaller, excess in the $\mathrm{b \bar b}$ invariant mass distribution in LEP data. This short note aims at confronting this claim to factual experimental observations, through a careful scrutiny of the detailed LEP public notes written at the time on the topic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10948v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Janot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flavour Deconstructing the Composite Higgs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10950</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10950v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a flavour non-universal extension of the Standard Model combined with the idea of Higgs compositeness. At the TeV scale, the gauge groups $SU(2)_R$ and $U(1)_{B-L}$ are assumed to act in a non-universal manner on light- and third-generation fermions, while the Higgs emerges as a pseudo Nambu-Goldstone boson of the spontaneous global symmetry breaking $Sp(4)\to SU(2)_L\times SU(2)_R^{[3]}$, attributed to new strong dynamics. The flavour deconstruction means the couplings of the light families to the composite sector (and therefore the pNGB Higgs) are suppressed by powers of a heavy mass scale (from which the Higgs is nevertheless shielded by compositeness), explaining the flavour puzzle. We present a detailed analysis of the radiatively generated Higgs potential, showing how this intrinsically-flavoured framework has the ingredients to justify the unavoidable tuning in the Higgs potential necessary to separate electroweak and composite scales. This happens for large enough values of the $SU(2)_R^{[3]}$ gauge coupling and light enough flavoured gauge bosons resulting from the deconstruction, whose phenomenology is also investigated. The model is compatible with current experimental bounds and predicts new states at the TeV scale, which are within the reach of near future experimental searches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10950v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastiano Covone, Joe Davighi, Gino Isidori, Marko Pesut</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological cutting rules for Bogoliubov initial states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06258</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06258v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The field theoretic wavefunction in cosmological spacetimes has received much attention as a fundamental object underlying the generation of primordial perturbations in our universe. Assuming an initial Bunch-Davies state, unitary time evolution implies an infinite set of cutting rules for the wavefunction to all orders in perturbation theory, collectively known as the cosmological optical theorem. In this work, we generalise these results to the case of Bogoliubov initial states, accounting for both parity-even and parity-odd interactions. We confirm our findings in a few explicit examples, assuming IR-finite interactions. In these examples, we preserve scale invariance by adiabatically turning on interactions in the infinite past rather than imposing a Bogoliubov state at some finite initial time. Finally, we give a prescription for computing Bogoliubov wavefunction coefficients from the corresponding Bunch-Davies coefficients for both n-point contact and four-point exchange diagrams.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06258v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diptimoy Ghosh, Enrico Pajer, Farman Ullah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of hidden emissions in two rotating radio transients with high surface magnetic fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09876v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Rotating Radio Transients (RRATs) are neutron stars emitting sporadic radio pulses. The unique emission of RRATs has been proposed to resemble those of known pulsar types, such as extreme nulling pulsars or pulsars with giant pulses. However, the presence of additional radiation beyond these sporadic pulses remains unclear. Through high-sensitivity observations and extended tracking, we detected the sequential weak emissions in two RRATs with relatively high surface magnetic fields (Bs &gt; 10^13 G): J1846-0257 and J1854+0306. These emissions show peak flux densities of 0.15 and 0.41 mJy, up to 687 and 512 times weaker than our detected RRAT single pulses, respectively. The weak emissions contribute small fractions (~ 16% and 5%) to the total radio pulse energy releases, contrasting significantly with giant-pulse pulsars where normal pulses dominate. Polarization analysis of J1854+0306 suggests that its sporadic RRAT pulses may originate from intermittent enhanced sparking processes due to magnetospheric evolution. Our findings indicate that some RRATs may represent a novel class of pulsars, distinct from any previously known subclass. Further observations of sources with similar rotational properties using high-sensitivity instruments could validate the generality of these hidden emissions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09876v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. B. Zhang, X. Yang, J. J. Geng, Y. P. Yang, X. F. Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Incoherent solar-neutrino scattering off the stable Tl-isotopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09889v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nuclear-structure calculations for the description of low-energy neutral-current neutrino scattering off the stable $^{203,205}$Tl isotopes are performed in the context of nuclear shell model using the model space jj56pn. Cross-section and event-rates calculations focusing on inelastic solar-neutrino scattering off $^{203,205}$Tl are performed. The individual contributions of the various nuclear responses are presented and discussed, and the results are also illustrated in terms of the nuclear recoil energy. Analytical expressions entering the cross sections are given in order to achieve a direct connection with experimental observables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09889v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dimitrios K. Papoulias, Matti Hellgren, Jouni Suhonen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Threshold photo-production of $J/\Psi$ off light nuclei</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09991v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyze threshold photoproduction of heavy mesons off a deuteron and Helium-4, using the QCD factorization method. Assuming large skewness, the production amplitude is dominated by the leading twist-2 gluonic energy-momentum tensor (EMT). We use our recent results for the gluonic gravitational form factors of light nuclei in the impulse approximation, to estimate the differential cross sections for $J/\Psi$ production off a deuteron and Helium-4 at current electron facilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09991v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fangcheng He, Ismail Zahed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Personal Reminiscences of Steven Weinberg</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10033v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: My personal recollections are presented regarding my interactions with Steven Weinberg and the impact he had in my career from when I was his graduate student until the present.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10033v1</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2024.116615</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nucl.Phys.B 1006 (2024) 116615</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Quevedo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charged hadron spectra and anisotropic flow from the AMPT model with shear viscous transport dynamics simulations at RHIC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10060v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We utilized the AMPT model to simulate the shear viscous transport dynamics of parton matter in Au+Au collisions at a constant specific shear viscosity and varying phase transition temperatures at 200 GeV. The resulting charged hadron spectra and anisotropic flow profiles correspond closely with experimental data. The transverse momentum spectra and longitudinal decorrelations are essentially unaffected by the phase transition temperature. An increase in the phase transition temperature leads to a rise in particle yields at midrapidity, accompanied by a decrease in both elliptic and triangular flows over a range of transverse momenta and pseudorapidities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10060v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarized $\phi$ meson rates with viscous corrections at RHIC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10524v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We discuss the emission of $\phi$ mesons with longitudinal and transverse polarization in ultra-relativistic heavy ion collisions. In the hadronic phase and in leading order in the kaon diluteness, $\phi$ emission is isotropic and driven by the flavor singlet and octet vector spectral functions. At next to leading order, the emissivities receive a non-isotropic correction from the flavor octet spectral function, and the non-equilibrium contributions originating from the shear and bulk viscosities. Implications for the $\phi$ meson alignment in heavy-ion collisions are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10524v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eduardo Grossi, Andrea Palermo, Ismail Zahed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing QGP droplets with charmonium in high-multiplicity proton-proton collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10566v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the hot medium effects in high-multiplicity proton-proton (pp) collisions at $\sqrt{s_{NN}}=13$ TeV via the charmonium probes. The hot medium is described with the hydrodynamic model, while charmonium evolutions in the medium are studied with a time-dependent Schr\"odinger equation. The hot medium dissociation on charmonium is considered with the temperature-dependent complex potential parametrized with the results from lattice QCD calculations. The ratio $\sigma_{\psi(2S)}/\sigma_{J/\psi}$ of $J/\psi$ and $\psi(2S)$ production cross sections are calculated and compared with the LHCb experimental data in pp collisions. Our calculations explain the charmonium relative suppression in different transverse momentum and multiplicity bins. The suppression of this ratio is mainly affected by the effects of the deconfined medium. It is less affected by the initial effects before the generation of the heavy quark pair. We suggest this to be a clear signal of the small QGP droplets generated in high multiplicity pp collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10566v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunfan Bai, Baoyi Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparing matching prescriptions between pre-equilibrium and hydrodynamic models in high-energy nuclear collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10634v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: State-of-the-art simulations of high-energy nuclear collisions rely on hybrid setups, involving in particular a pre-equilibrium stage to let the system evolve from a far-from-equilibrium initial condition towards a near-equilibrated state after which fluid dynamics can be applied meaningfully. A known issue is the mismatch between the equation of state in the fluid-dynamical evolution and the effective one in the previous stage, which leads to discontinuities at the interface between the two models. Here we introduce a new matching prescription at this interface, based on the entropy, and we compare it with the standard one relying on local energy conservation. We study the behavior of various quantities at the switching time between the models and investigate a number of final-state hadronic observables. For the latter, we show that they are not modified significantly by the choice of matching prescription, provided an appropriate normalization is chosen for the initial state. In turn, our approach reduces sizeably the ratio of bulk over thermodynamic pressure at the beginning of the fluid-dynamical stage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10634v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Borghini, Renata Krupczak, Hendrik Roch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vacuum energy density from the form factor bootstrap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10692v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The form-factor bootstrap is incomplete until one normalizes the zero-particle form factor. For the stress energy tensor we describe how to obtain the vacuum energy density $\rho_{\rm vac}$, defined as $\langle 0| T_{\mu\nu} | 0 \rangle = \rho_{\rm vac} \, g_{\mu\nu}$, from the form-factor bootstrap. Even for integrable QFT's in D=2 spacetime dimensions, this prescription is new, although it reproduces previously known results obtained in a different and more difficult thermodynamic Bethe ansatz computation. We propose a version of this prescription in D=4 dimensions. For these even dimensions, the vacuum energy density has the universal form $\rho_{\rm vac} \propto m^D/\mathfrak{g}$ where $\mathfrak{g}$ is a dimensionless interaction coupling constant which can be determined from the high energy behavior of the S-matrix. In the limit $\mathfrak{g} \to 0$, $\rho_{\rm vac} $ diverges due to well understood UV divergences in free quantum field theories. If we assume the the observed Cosmological Constant originates from the vacuum energy density $\rho_{\rm vac}$ computed as proposed here, then this suggests there must exist a particle which does not obtain its mass from spontaneous symmetry breaking in the electro-weak sector, which we designate as the ``zeron". A strong candidate for the zeron is a massive Majorana neutrino.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10692v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'e LeClair</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High precision calculation of the hadronic vacuum polarisation contribution to the muon anomaly</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10913</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10913v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a new lattice QCD calculation of the leading order hadronic vacuum polarization contribution to the muon anomalous magnetic moment $a_\mu$. We reduce uncertainties compared to our earlier computation by $40\%$, arXiv:2002.12347. We perform simulations on finer lattices allowing for an even more accurate continuum extrapolation. We also include a small, long-distance contribution obtained using input from experiments in a low-energy regime where they all agree. Combined with other standard model contributions our result leads to a prediction that differs from the measurement of $a_\mu$ by only 0.9 standard deviations. This provides a remarkable validation of the standard model to 0.37ppm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10913v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Boccaletti, Sz. Borsanyi, M. Davier, Z. Fodor, F. Frech, A. Gerardin, D. Giusti, A. Yu. Kotov, L. Lellouch, Th. Lippert, A. Lupo, B. Malaescu, S. Mutzel, A. Portelli, A. Risch, M. Sjo, F. Stokes, K. K. Szabo, B. C. Toth, G. Wang, Z. Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking neutrino interaction models via a comparative analysis of kinematic imbalance measurements from the T2K, MicroBooNE and MINERvA experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10962v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent neutrino-nucleus cross-section measurements of observables characterising kinematic imbalance from the T2K, MicroBooNE and MINERvA experiments are used to benchmark predictions from widely used neutrino interaction event generators. Given the different neutrino energy spectra and nuclear targets employed by the three experiments, comparisons of model predictions to their measurements breaks degeneracies that would be present in any single measurement. In particular, the comparison of T2K and MINERvA measurements offers a probe of energy dependence, whilst a comparison of T2K and MicroBooNE investigates scaling with nuclear target. In order to isolate the impact of individual nuclear effects, model comparisons are made following systematic alterations to: the nuclear ground state; final state interactions and multi-nucleon interaction strength. The measurements are further compared to the generators used as an input to DUNE/SBN and T2K/Hyper-K analyses. Whilst no model is able to quantitatively describe all the measurements, evidence is found for mis-modelling of A-scaling in multi-nucleon interactions and it is found that tight control over how energy is distributed among hadrons following final state interactions is likely to be crucial to achieving improved agreement. Overall, this work provides a novel characterisation of neutrino interactions whilst offering guidance for refining existing generator predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10962v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wissal Filali, Laura Munteanu, Stephen Dolan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Negative neutrino masses as a mirage of dark energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10965v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The latest cosmological constraints on the sum of the neutrino masses depend on prior physical assumptions about the mass spectrum. To test the accordance of cosmological and laboratory constraints in the absence of such priors, we introduce an effective neutrino mass parameter that extends consistently to negative values. For the $\Lambda$CDM model, we analyze data from Planck, ACT, and DESI and find a $2.8-3.3\sigma$ tension with the constraints from oscillation experiments. Motivated by recent hints of evolving dark energy, we analyze the $w_0w_a$ and mirage dark energy models, showing that they favour larger masses consistent with laboratory data, respectively $\sum m_{\nu,\mathrm{eff}} = 0.06_{-0.10}^{+0.15}\,\mathrm{eV}$ and $\sum m_{\nu,\mathrm{eff}} = 0.04_{-0.11}^{+0.15}\,\mathrm{eV}$ (both at 68\%).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10965v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Willem Elbers, Carlos S. Frenk, Adrian Jenkins, Baojiu Li, Silvia Pascoli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Amplitude Factorization in the Electroweak Standard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.03258</link>
      <description>arXiv:2204.03258v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We lay out the basis of factorization at the amplitude level for processes involving the entire Standard Model. The factorization appears in a generalized eikonal approximation in which we expand around a quasi-soft limit for massive gauge bosons, fermions, and scalars. We use the chirality-flow formalism to express loop exchanges or emissions as operators on chiral structures. This forms the basis for amplitude evolution with parton exchange and branching in the full Standard Model, including the electroweak sector.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2204.03258v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Pl\"atzer, Malin Sjodahl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting axion dark matter with chiral magnetic effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.06884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.06884v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that dark matter axions or axion-like particles (ALP) induce spontaneously alternating electric currents in conductors along the external magnetic fields due to the (medium) axial anomaly, realizing the chiral magnetic effects (CME). We propose a new experiment to measure this current to detect the dark matter axions or ALP. These induced currents are the electron medium effects, directly proportional to the axion or ALP coupling to electrons, which depends on their microscopic physics. In the experimental setup one measures both currents, the electric current due to CME and the current due to the anomalous axion-photon coupling. However with ferromagnetic conductors like irons the CME current can be dominant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.06884v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Deog Ki Hong, Sang Hui Im, Kwang Sik Jeong, Dong-han Yeom</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Method for measuring the charge radii of charged hyperons from the time-like region</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.07850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.07850v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a novel method for measuring the charge radii of charged stable hadrons, with which the first measurement of the charge radii of the $\Sigma^+$ and the $\Xi^-$ is foreseen. The method explores the facts that the Dalitz decay $\psi(2S) \to Y\bar{Y}e^+e^-$ contains the hyperon form factors and the lowest measurable four-momentum transfer squared can be as low as $\sim 4m_e^2= 1.05\times10^{-6}\,{\rm GeV^2}$ in the time-like region. We identify a kinematic region where the hyperon form factors are essential and propose a method for subtracting the background from the data. It is estimated that the hyperon charge radii can be measured to a precision of about {0.2~fm} with the BES\Rom{3} experiment and one order of magnitude better at the future Super $\tau$-Charm Facility. Moreover, the same method can be used to measure the charge radius of the proton, which provides an independent cross-check on the extraction of proton radius from elastic $ep$ scattering or leptonic hydrogen spectroscopy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.07850v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yong-Hui Lin, Feng-Kun Guo, Ulf-G. Mei{\ss}ner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantisation Across Bubble Walls and Friction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.06972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.06972v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We quantise from first principles field theories living on the background of a bubble wall in the planar limit with particular focus on the case of spontaneous breaking of gauge symmetry. Using these tools, we compute the average momentum transfer from transition radiation: the soft emission of radiation by an energetic particle passing across the wall, with a particular focus on the longitudinal polarisation of vectors. We find these to be comparable to transverse polarisations in symmetry-breaking transitions with mild super-cooling, and dominant in broken to broken transitions with thin wall. Our results have phenomenological applications for the expansion of bubbles during first order phase transitions. Our general framework allows for the robust calculation of any particle processes of interest in such translation breaking backgrounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.06972v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP05(2024)294</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Aleksandr Azatov, Giulio Barni, Rudin Petrossian-Byrne, Miguel Vanvlasselaer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resummation schemes for high-electric-charge objects leading to improved experimental mass limits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.17452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.17452v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High-Electric-Charge compact Objects (HECOs) appear in several theoretical particle physics models beyond the Standard Model, and are actively searched for in current colliders, such as the Large Hadron Collider at CERN. In such searches, mass bounds of these objects have been placed, using Drell-Yan and photon-fusion processes at tree level so far. However, such mass-bound estimates are not reliable, given that, as a result of the large values of the electric charge of the HECO, perturbative Quantum Electrodynamics calculations break down. In this work, we perform a Dyson-Schwinger resummation scheme (as opposed to lattice strong-coupling approach), which makes the computation of the pertinent HECO-production cross sections reliable, thus allowing us to extract improved mass bounds for such objects from ATLAS and MoEDAL searches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.17452v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.036026</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 109 (2024) 3, 036026</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jean Alexandre, Nick E. Mavromatos, Vasiliki A. Mitsou, Emanuela Musumeci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accumulating Hints for Flavour Violating Higgses at the Electroweak Scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.03430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.03430v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that supplementing the Standard Model by only a second Higgs doublet, a combined explanation of $h\to e\tau$, $h\to \mu\tau$, $b\to s \ell^+ \ell^-$, the $W$ mass and $R({D^{(*)}})$ as well as the excess in $t\to bH^+(130\,{\rm GeV})\to b\overline{b}c$ is possible. While this requires flavour violating couplings, the stringent bounds from e.g. $\mu\to e\gamma$, $\tau\to \mu\gamma$, $B_s-\bar B_s$ mixing, $b\to s\gamma$, low mass di-jet and $pp\to H^+H^-\to \tau^+\tau^-\nu\bar\nu$ searches can be avoided. However, the model is very constrained, it inevitably predicts a shift in the SM Higgs coupling strength to tau leptons as well as a non-zero $t\to hc$ rate, as indeed preferred by recent measurements. We study three benchmark points providing such a simultaneous explanation and calculate their predictions, including collider signatures which can be tested with upcoming LHC run-3 data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.03430v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.015014</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PhysRevD.110.1.015014(2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Crivellin, Syuhei Iguro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Even SIMP miracles are possible</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.12283v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Strongly interacting massive particles $\pi$ have been advocated as prominent dark matter candidates when they regulate their relic abundance through odd-numbered $3 \pi \to2\pi$ annihilation. We show that successful freeze-out may also be achieved through even-numbered interactions $X X \to \pi \pi $ once bound states $X$ among the particles of the low-energy spectrum exist. In addition, $X$-formation hosts the potential of also catalyzing odd-numbered $3 \pi \to2\pi$ annihilation processes, turning them into effective two-body processes $\pi X \to \pi\pi$. Bound states are often a natural consequence of strongly interacting theories. We calculate the dark matter freeze-out and comment on the cosmic viability and possible extensions. Candidate theories can encompass confining sectors without a mass gap, glueball dark matter, or $\phi^3$ and $\phi^4$ theories with strong Yukawa or self-interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.12283v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.Lett. 133 (2024) 2, 021003</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoyong Chu, Marco Nikolic, Josef Pradler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Yadism: Yet Another Deep-Inelastic Scattering Module</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.15187</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.15187v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present yadism, a library for the evaluation of both polarized and unpolarized deep-inelastic scattering (DIS) structure functions and cross sections up to N$^3$LO in perturbative QCD. The package provides computations of observables in fixed-flavor and zero-mass variable flavor number schemes. The implementation of the general mass variable flavor number schemes is supported through the high virtuality limits for the heavy flavor coefficients. In addition, yadism provides a set of tools for the generation of interpolation grids in the PDF-independent PineAPPL format, allowing to test the PDF dependence on any DIS observable without needing to rerun the computation. This work is part of an ongoing effort to standardize the format of theory predictions in high-energy physics within the pineline framework. The code is open source, written in Python and documented to facilitate usage, integrations, and further extensions. Finally, the code has been benchmarked against the widely used APFEL++ and QCDNUM libraries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.15187v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-024-12972-7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur.Phys.J.C 84 (2024) 7, 697</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Candido, Felix Hekhorn, Giacomo Magni, Tanjona R. Rabemananjara, Roy Stegeman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancement of the Higgs decay into a $Z^\prime$ pair in models with $U(1)_X$ gauge symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.00392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.00392v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We discuss the Higgs phenomenology in models with a new $U(1)_X$ gauge symmetry including the $U(1)_{B-L}$ scenario, where three right-handed neutrinos are inevitably introduced due to the gauge anomaly cancellations. We find that the decay branching ratio of the discovered Higgs boson into a pair of new massive gauge bosons ($Z'$) can significantly be enhanced in the Dirac neutrino case as compared with the Majorana case for a fixed value of the new gauge coupling and the mass of $Z'$ under constraints from current experimental data. Because of such an enhancement, the Dirac case can indirectly be discriminated from the Majorana case via the Higgs decay.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.00392v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2024.138843</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physics Letters B, Volume 855, 2024, 138843</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>ShivaSankar K. A., Arindam Das, Kei Yagyu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constructing model-agnostic likelihoods, a method for the reinterpretation of particle physics results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.08417</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.08417v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Experimental High Energy Physics has entered an era of precision measurements. However, measurements of many of the accessible processes assume that the final states' underlying kinematic distribution is the same as the Standard Model prediction. This assumption introduces an implicit model-dependency into the measurement, rendering the reinterpretation of the experimental analysis complicated without reanalysing the underlying data. We present a novel reweighting method in order to perform reinterpretation of particle physics measurements. It makes use of reweighting the Standard Model templates according to kinematic signal distributions of alternative theoretical models, prior to performing the statistical analysis. The generality of this method allows us to perform statistical inference in the space of theoretical parameters, assuming different kinematic distributions, according to a beyond Standard Model prediction. We implement our method as an extension to the pyhf software and interface it with the EOS software, which allows us to perform flavor physics phenomenology studies. Furthermore, we argue that, beyond the pyhf or HistFactory likelihood specification, only minimal information is necessary to make a likelihood model-agnostic and hence easily reinterpretable. We showcase that publishing such likelihoods is crucial for a full exploitation of experimental results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.08417v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-024-13038-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Lorenz G\"artner, Nikolai Hartmann, Lukas Heinrich, Malin Horstmann, Thomas Kuhr, M\'eril Reboud, Slavomira Stefkova, Danny van Dyk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elliptic anisotropy of open-charm hadrons from parton scatterings in p--Pb collisions at energies available at the CERN Large Hadron Collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01677v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The elliptic azimuthal anisotropy coefficient ($v_{2}$) of open-charm hadron at midrapidity ($|\eta&lt;1|$) was studied in p--Pb collisions at $\sqrt{s_{\mathrm{NN}}}=$ 8.16 TeV using a multi-phase transport (AMPT) model included an additional charm quark--antiquark pair production trigger. The model provides a simultaneously description of the measured $p_{\mathrm{T}}$ spectrum and $v_{2}$ of $D^{0}$ meson, as well as the $v_{2}$ of light flavor meson $K_{s}^{0}$. We found that the $D^{0}$ and $K_{s}^{0}$ $v_{2}$ are both significantly affected by different parton scatterings among charm and light quarks. In addition, the predictions for the $v_{2}$ of other charm hadrons including $D^{+}$, $D_{s}^{+}$ and $\Lambda_{c}^{+}$ in p--Pb collisions are given for the first time. The $v_{2}$ of open-charm hadron reasonably follows the number-of-constituent-quark (NCQ) scaling up to 2.5 GeV, strongly indicating the importance of partonic degrees of freedom for the collectivity of heavy flavors in high-multiplicity p--Pb collisions. These findings may hint the formation of deconfined matter in small collision systems, and provide referential value for future measurements of azimuthal anisotropy at the LHC energies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01677v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevC.109.064902</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.C 109 (2024) 6, 064902</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Siyu Tang, Yuan Lu, Chao Zhang, RenZhuo Wan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Examining the critical phenomenon of pion parton distribution: Insights from the Moment Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01937</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01937v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A recent study by Wang {\it et al.}(arXiv:2309.01417) proposed a novel connection between the nature of the parton distribution function (PDF) and the characteristics of its moments. In this study, we apply these findings to analyze the evolution of the pion valence quark PDF, garnering valuable qualitative insights. Firstly, we validate the non-negativity and continuity of the PDF across a wide range of scales, indicating the logical consistency of our chosen evolution scheme. Subsequently, we examine the unimodality of both the PDF and its transformed counterpart, the xPDF, i.e., the parton distribution function multiplied by the momentum fraction. We observe a smooth evolution of the peak position of the xPDF towards the small-$x$ region with increasing scale, while intriguingly, the PDF undergoes a phase of bimodal competition as the energy scale evolves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01937v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaobin Wang, Zexin Wu, Minghui Ding, Lei Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of New Experimental Data on the C2HDM: the Strong Interdependence between LHC Higgs Data and the Electron EDM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02425v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The complex two-Higgs doublet model (C2HDM) is one of the simplest extensions of the Standard Model with a source of CP-violation in the scalar sector. It has a $\mathbb{Z}_2$ symmetry, softly broken by a complex coefficient. There are four ways to implement this symmetry in the fermion sector, leading to models known as Type-I, Type-II, Lepton-Specific and Flipped. In the latter three models, there is a priori the surprising possibility that the 125 GeV Higgs boson couples mostly as a scalar to top quarks, while it couples mostly as a pseudoscalar to bottom quarks. This ``maximal'' scenario was still possible with the data available in 2017. Since then, there have been more data on the 125 GeV Higgs boson, direct searches for CP-violation in angular correlations of $\tau$-leptons produced in Higgs boson decays, new results on the electron electric dipole moment, new constraints from LHC searches for additional Higgs bosons and new results on $b\to s \gamma$ transitions. Highlighting the crucial importance of the physics results of LHC's Run 2, we combine all these experiments and show that the ``maximal'' scenario is now excluded in all models. Still, one can have a pseudoscalar component in $h \tau\bar{\tau}$ couplings in the Lepton-Specific case as large as $87\%$ of the scalar component for all mass orderings of the neutral scalar bosons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02425v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP05(2024)127</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 05 (2024) 127</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Biek\"otter, Duarte Fontes, Margarete M\"uhlleitner, Jorge C. Rom\~ao, Rui Santos, Jo\~ao P. Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suppression of diffraction in deep-inelastic scattering on nuclei and dynamical mechanism of leading twist nuclear shadowing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08342v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Using the leading twist approach (LTA) to nuclear shadowing, we calculate the ratios of diffractive and usual parton distributions for a heavy nucleus (Pb) and the proton, $R_{A/p}=(f_{i/A}^{D(3)}/f_{i/A})/(f_{i/p}^{D(3)}/f_{i/p})$, for coherent and summed (coherent plus quasi-elastic) nuclear deep-inelastic scattering. We find that $R_{A/p} \approx 0.5-1$ for quarks as well as for the ratio of the diffractive and total cross sections $[(d\sigma_{\rm diff}/dM_X^2)/\sigma_{\rm tot}]_{eA}/[(d\sigma_{\rm diff}/dM_X^2)/\sigma_{\rm tot}]_{ep}$ and $R_{A/p} \approx 0.5-1.3$ for gluons in a broad range of $x$, including the kinematics of the Electron-Ion Collider, which reaffirms the difference from the nuclear enhancement of $R_{A/p}$ predicted in the gluon saturation framework. We demonstrate that the magnitude of $R_{A/p}$ is controlled by the cross section of the interaction of hadronic fluctuations of the virtual photon with target nucleons, which explains an enhancement of $R_{A/p}$ in the color dipole model and its suppression in LTA. We argue that the black disk limit corresponds to $R_{A/p}=1$ and $R^{\rm coh}_{A/p}=0.86$ for the summed and coherent scattering, respectively. Relying on an intuitive definition of the saturation scale, we show that the ratio of the saturation scales of a heavy nucleus and proton $Q_{sA}^2(b)/Q_{sp}^2(b) \approx 1$ at small impact parameters $b$ due to the strong leading twist nuclear shadowing and diluteness of the nuclear density.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08342v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Guzey (Jyvaskyla U.,Helsinki Inst. of Phys.), M. Strikman (Penn State U.)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three-particle formalism for multiple channels: the $\eta \pi \pi + K \overline K \pi$ system in isosymmetric QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20064v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We generalize previous three-particle finite-volume formalisms to allow for multiple three-particle channels. For definiteness, we focus on the two-channel $\eta \pi \pi$ and $K \overline K \pi$ system in isosymmetric QCD, considering the positive $G$ parity sector of the latter channel, and neglecting the coupling to modes with four or more particles. The formalism we obtain is thus appropriate to study the $b_1(1235)$ and $\eta(1295)$ resonances. The derivation is made in the generic relativistic field theory approach using the time-ordered perturbation theory method. We study how the resulting quantization condition reduces to that for a single three-particle channel when one drops below the upper ($K\overline K \pi$) threshold. We also present parametrizations of the three-particle K matrices that enter into the formalism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20064v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP07(2024)083</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Zachary T. Draper, Stephen R. Sharpe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Production and decay of hyperons in a transversely polarized electron-positron collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00298v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The self-polarization of relativistic electrons or positrons moving in a magnetic field at a storage ring occurs through the emission of spin-flip synchrotron radiation, known as the Sokolov-Ternov effect. The resulting transverse polarizations of the colliding electrons and positrons, away from the depolarization resonances, allow for precise investigation of the spin entangled hyperon-antihyperon pairs via virtual photon or charmonium decay. The feasibility study reveals a promising increase in the statistical sensitivity of the \CP violation signal after considering the transverse polarizations of the lepton beams.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00298v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xu Cao, Yu-Tie Liang, Rong-Gang Ping</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Influence of new states in searches for negative gauge-Higgs couplings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10815v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we explore how constraints based on interference effects for the negative gauge-Higgs coupling scenario are affected by new physics. Models that achieve this wrong-sign gauge-Higgs coupling inevitably have new charged Higgs states. These states affect the interpretation of interference effects. We recast the ATLAS analysis for VBF $Wh$, showing that the previously excluded negative gauge-Higgs coupling scenario is still experimentally viable for charged Higgs masses below $370$~GeV. We show that it is possible to weaken this bound further with mild tuning in the parameter space. We discuss how to further constrain the wrong-sign gauge-Higgs coupling hypothesis and point out the potential of VBF $Zh$ to exclude this scenario in a model-independent way.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10815v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Henrique de Lima, Daniel Stolarski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anatomy of critical fluctuations in hadronic matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.06360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.06360v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Critical phenomena in phase transitions of strongly interacting matter, governed by quantum chromodynamics, are inherently encoded in the fluctuations of conserved charges. In this work, we study the net-baryon number density fluctuations, including the lowest-lying nucleon and the baryonic resonance $\Delta(1232)$, based on the parity doublet model in the mean-field approximation. We focus on the qualitative features of the second-order susceptibility of the net-baryon number density in dense hadronic matter and how the inclusion of $\Delta(1232)$ affects it. We demonstrate that the fluctuations of the individual baryons do not necessarily reflect the total net-baryon number fluctuations at finite density, due to the non-trivial correlations between different particle species. Our results highlight the role of baryonic correlations in the interpretation of data from heavy ion collision experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.06360v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.014018</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Micha{\l} Marczenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Higgs boson decay $h \rightarrow bs$ in the $U(1)_X$SSM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.16037</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.16037v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the $U(1)_X$SSM, we delve into the flavor violation of $h \rightarrow bs$, where $h$ is identified with the SM-like Higgs boson discovered at the LHC. As the U(1) extension of the minimal supersymmetric standard model (MSSM), the U(1)XSSM has new super fields such as right-handed neutrinos and three Higgs singlets. We conduct a thorough analysis of the underlying mechanisms and parameter dependencies of $h \rightarrow bs$ in the $U(1)_X$SSM. In the $U(1)_X$SSM, we discover that the Br$(h \rightarrow bs)$ for the Higgs decay to $bs$ could significantly differ from the expectation in the standard model (SM), depending on the values of the new parameters introduced in the model. Our research not only contributes to a deeper understanding of Higgs physics within the $U(1)_X$SSM, but also provides valuable guidance for new physics (NP).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.16037v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Song Gao, Shu-Min Zhao, Ming-Yue Liu, Xing-Yu Han, Xi Wang, Tai-Fu Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New ideas in nonperturbative QCD -- I</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05584v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The recent development of the Field Correlator Method (FCM) is discussed, with applications to the most interesting areas of QCD physics obtained in the lattice data and experiment. These areas include: a) the connection of colorelectric confinement with the basic quark and gluon condensates; b) the explicit form of the colorelectric deconfinement at a growing temperature $T$; c) the theory of the colormagnetic confinement at all temperatures; d) the theory of strong decays, the theory of pdf and jets in the instantaneous formalism with confinement. We demonstrate that the FCM with instantaneous formalism and confinement (instead of the light cone formalism and pure perturbation theory) can provide the way to the theory of QCD, which helps to describe world data without phenomenological parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05584v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. S. Lukashov, Yu. A. Simonov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultra-high Frequency Gravitational Waves from Scattering, Bremsstrahlung and Decay during Reheating</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03256</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03256v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate ultra-high frequency gravitational waves (GWs) from gravitons generated during inflationary reheating. Specifically, we study inflaton scattering with its decay product, where the couplings involved in this $2 \to 2$ scattering are the same as those in the $1 \to 3$ graviton Bremsstrahlung process. We compute the graviton production rate via such $2 \to 2$ scattering. Additionally, we compare the resulting GW spectrum with that from Bremsstrahlung as well as that from pure $2 \to 2$ inflaton scatterings. For completeness, the GW spectrum from graviton pair production through one-loop induced $1 \to 2$ inflaton decay is also analyzed. With a systematic comparison among the four sources of GWs, we find that $2 \to 2$ inflaton scattering with its decay product can dominate over Bremsstrahlung if the reheating temperature is larger than the inflaton mass. Pure inflaton $2 \to 2$ scattering is typically subdominant compared to Bremsstrahlung except in the high-frequency tail. The contribution from one-loop induced $1 \to 2$ inflaton decay is shown to be suppressed compared to Bremsstrahlung and pure inflaton $2 \to 2$ scattering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03256v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yong Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light-cone sum rules study on the purely non-factorizable $\Lambda_{c}^{+}\to\Xi^{0}K^{+}$ decay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07431</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07431v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the purely non-factorizable $\Lambda_{c}^{+}\to\Xi^{0}K^{+}$ decay using light-cone sum rules. To extract the decay amplitudes, a three-point correlation function is defined and calculated at hadron and quark-gluon level, respectively. Both the W-exchange and the W-inward emission diagrams are considered in the quark-gluon level calculation, where the two-particle light-cone distribution amplitudes (LCDAs) of kaon are used as non-perturbative input. We obtain the decay amplitudes contributed from the twist-2 and twist-3 kaon LCDAs, respectively. The obtained P-wave amplitude is consistent with those predicted in the literature, while the S-wave one is much smaller. This significant difference between the S- and P- wave amplitudes leads to small up-down spin asymmetry, closing to the experimental measurement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07431v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Ji Shi, Zhen-Xing Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First Scan Search for Dark Photon Dark Matter with a Tunable Superconducting Radio-Frequency Cavity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.09711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.09711v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dark photons have emerged as promising candidates for dark matter, and their search is a top priority in particle physics, astrophysics, and cosmology. We report the first use of a tunable niobium superconducting radio-frequency cavity for a scan search of dark photon dark matter with innovative data analysis techniques. We mechanically adjusted the resonant frequency of a cavity submerged in liquid helium at a temperature of $2$ K, and scanned the dark photon mass over a frequency range of $1.37$ MHz centered at $1.3$ GHz. Our study leveraged the superconducting radio-frequency cavity's remarkably high quality factors of approximately $10^{10}$, resulting in the most stringent constraints to date on a substantial portion of the exclusion parameter space on the kinetic mixing coefficient $\epsilon$ between dark photons and electromagnetic photons, yielding a value of $\epsilon &lt; 2.2 \times 10^{-16}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.09711v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.021005</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator> SHANHE Collaboration, Zhenxing Tang, Bo Wang, Yifan Chen, Yanjie Zeng, Chunlong Li, Yuting Yang, Liwen Feng, Peng Sha, Zhenghui Mi, Weimin Pan, Tianzong Zhang, Yirong Jin, Jiankui Hao, Lin Lin, Fang Wang, Huamu Xie, Senlin Huang, Jing Shu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hamiltonian formalism for Bose excitations in a plasma with a non-Abelian interaction I: plasmon -- hard particle scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.15390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.15390v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Hamiltonian theory for collective longitudinally polarized gluon excitations (plasmons) interacting with classical high-energy test color-charged particle propagating through a high-temperature gluon plasma is developed. A generalization of the Lie-Poisson bracket to the case of a continuous medium involving bosonic normal field variable $a^{\hspace{0.03cm}a}_{{\bf k}}$ and a non-Abelian color charge $Q^{\hspace{0.03cm}a}$ is performed and the corresponding Hamilton equations are presented. The canonical transformations including simultaneously both bosonic degrees of freedom of the soft collective excitations and degree of freedom of hard test particle connecting with its color charge in the hot gluon plasma are written out. A complete system of the canonicity conditions for these transformations is derived. The notion of the plasmon number density ${\mathcal N}^{\hspace{0.03cm}aa^{\prime}_{\phantom{1}}\!}_{{\bf k}}$, which is a nontrivial matrix in the color space, is introduced. An explicit form of the effective fourth-order Hamiltonian describing the elastic scattering of a plasmon off a hard color particle is found and the self-consistent system of Boltzmann-type kinetic equations taking into account the time evolution of the mean value of the color charge of the hard particle is obtained. On the basis of these equations, a model problem of the interaction of two infinitely narrow wave packets is considered. A system of nonlinear first-order ordinary differential equations defining the dynamics of the interaction of the colorless $N^{\hspace{0.01cm}l}_{\bf k}$ and color $W^{\hspace{0.01cm}l}_{\bf k}$ components of the plasmon number density is derived. The problem of determining the third- and fourth-order coefficient functions entering into the canonical transformations of the original bosonic variable $a^{\hspace{0.03cm}a}_{{\bf k}}$ and color charge $Q^{a}$ is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.15390v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nuclphysa.2024.122903</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nucl. Phys. A 1048 (2024) 122903(38)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yu. A. Markov, M. A. Markova, N. Yu. Markov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nucleon electric polarizabilities and nucleon-pion scattering at physical pion mass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.01168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.01168v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a lattice QCD calculation of the nucleon electric polarizabilities at the physical pion mass. Our findings reveal the substantial contributions of the $N\pi$ states to these polarizabilities. Without considering these contributions, the lattice results fall significantly below the experimental values, consistent with previous lattice studies. This observation has motivated us to compute both the parity-negative $N\pi$ scattering up to a nucleon momentum of $\sim0.5$ GeV in the center-of-mass frame and corresponding $N\gamma^*\to N\pi$ matrix elements using lattice QCD. Our results confirm that incorporating dynamic $N\pi$ contributions is crucial for a reliable determination of the polarizabilities from lattice QCD. This methodology lays the groundwork for future lattice QCD investigations into various other polarizabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.01168v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuan-He Wang, Zhao-Long Zhang, Xiong-Hui Cao, Cong-Ling Fan, Xu Feng, Yu-Sheng Gao, Lu-Chang Jin, Chuan Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antineutrino Opacity in Neutron Stars in the Models Constrained by Recent Terrestrial Experiments and Astrophysical Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.09986</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.09986v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the present paper, I have investigated a neutral current (NC) antineutrinos scattering with neutron star (NS) matter constituents at zero temperature. The modeling of the standard matters in NS is constructed in the framework of both extended relativistic mean-field (E-RMF) and nonrelativistic Korea-IBS-Daegu-SKKU energy density functional (KIDS-EDF) models. In the E-RMF model, I use a new parameter of G3(M), which was constrained by the recent PREX II experiment measurement of neutron distribution of $^{208}\rm{Pb}$, while the KIDS-EDF models are constrained by terrestrial experiments, gravitational-wave signals, and astrophysical observations. Using both realistic and well-constrained matter models, I then calculate the antineutrino differential cross-section (ADCS) and antineutrino mean free path (AMFP) of the antineutrinos-NS matter constituents interaction using a linear response theory. It is found that the AMFP for the KIDS0 and KIDSA models are smaller in comparison to the SLy4 model and the E-RMF model with the G3(M) parameter. The AMFP result of the Skyrme model with the SLy4 parameter set is found to have an almost similar prediction to that of the E-RMF model with the G3(M) parameter. Contributions of each nucleon to total AMFP are also presented for the G3(M) model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.09986v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Parada. T. P. Hutauruk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Generative Models for Detector Signature Simulation: A Taxonomic Review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.09597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.09597v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In modern collider experiments, the quest to explore fundamental interactions between elementary particles has reached unparalleled levels of precision. Signatures from particle physics detectors are low-level objects (such as energy depositions or tracks) encoding the physics of collisions (the final state particles of hard scattering interactions). The complete simulation of them in a detector is a computational and storage-intensive task. To address this computational bottleneck in particle physics, alternative approaches have been developed, introducing additional assumptions and trade off accuracy for speed.The field has seen a surge in interest in surrogate modeling the detector simulation, fueled by the advancements in deep generative models. These models aim to generate responses that are statistically identical to the observed data. In this paper, we conduct a comprehensive and exhaustive taxonomic review of the existing literature on the simulation of detector signatures from both methodological and application-wise perspectives. Initially, we formulate the problem of detector signature simulation and discuss its different variations that can be unified. Next, we classify the state-of-the-art methods into five distinct categories based on their underlying model architectures, summarizing their respective generation strategies. Finally, we shed light on the challenges and opportunities that lie ahead in detector signature simulation, setting the stage for future research and development.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.09597v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.revip.2024.100092</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Reviews in Physics, Volume 12, December 2024, 100092</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Baran Hashemi, Claudius Krause</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Present and future of CosmoLattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.15056</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.15056v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We discuss the present state and planned updates of CosmoLattice, a cutting-edge code for lattice simulations of non-linear dynamics of scalar-gauge field theories in an expanding background. We first review current capabilities of the code, including the simulation of interacting singlet scalars and of Abelian and non-Abelian scalar-gauge theories. We also comment on new features recently implemented, such as the simulation of gravitational waves from scalar and gauge fields. Secondly, we discuss new extensions of CosmoLattice that we plan to release publicly. On the one hand, we comment on new physics modules, which include axion-gauge interactions $\phi F \widetilde{F}$, non-minimal gravitational couplings $\phi^2 R$, creation and evolution of cosmic defect networks, and magneto-hydro-dynamics (MHD). On the other hand, we discuss new technical features, including evolvers for non-canonical interactions, arbitrary initial conditions, simulations in 2+1 dimensions, and higher accuracy spatial derivatives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.15056v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6633/ad616a</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Daniel G. Figueroa, Adrien Florio, Francisco Torrenti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting Dark Matter Substructures on Small Scales with Fast Radio Bursts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.08862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.08862v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose measuring the arrival time difference of Fast Radio Bursts (FRBs) along two adjacent sightlines as a new probe to dark matter substructures on scales down to $\sim 1\,$AU. We discuss two observational scenarios in which it may be possible to place interesting constraints on such models through monitoring repeating FRB sources: 1) By sending radio receivers to space to form a baseline of tens of AU or more and measuring the temporal variation of the arrival time difference between receivers. 2) By measuring the temporal variation of the arrival time difference between two lensed images of one strongly lensed repeater. In both scenarios, obtaining interesting constraints requires correlating the voltage time series to measure the radio-signal arrival time to sub-nanosecond precision. We find that two radio dishes separated by $20\,$AU may be sensitive to the enhancement of small-scale structures at $\sim 10^{-8}M_\odot$ masses in the QCD axion dark matter scenario or from an early epoch of matter-domination with a reheating temperature up to 60 MeV. Other dark matter models such as those composed of $\sim 10^{-13}M_{\odot}$ primordial black holes produced during inflation would also be probed by this method. We further show that a strong lensing situation of multiple images provides an equivalent $\sim 2000\,$AU baseline, which can be much more sensitive but with the uncertainty that intervening ISM decoherence may degrade the timing precision and that spatial variation in the FRB emission spot may result in confounding signals. We show that the lensing magnifications of Type Ia supernovea constrain a similar quantity to such FRB timing, with present limits being equivalent to ruling out the same parameter space that would be probed by a $0.14~$AU baseline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.08862v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.023516</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Huangyu Xiao, Liang Dai, Matthew McQuinn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First Measurement of the $\nu_e$ and $\nu_\mu$ Interaction Cross Sections at the LHC with FASER's Emulsion Detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12520</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.12520v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper presents the first results of the study of high-energy electron and muon neutrino charged-current interactions in the FASER$\nu$ emulsion/tungsten detector of the FASER experiment at the LHC. A subset of the FASER$\nu$ volume, which corresponds to a target mass of 128.6~kg, was exposed to neutrinos from the LHC $pp$ collisions with a centre-of-mass energy of 13.6~TeV and an integrated luminosity of 9.5 fb$^{-1}$. Applying stringent selections requiring electrons with reconstructed energy above 200~GeV, four electron neutrino interaction candidate events are observed with an expected background of $0.025^{+0.015}_{-0.010}$, leading to a statistical significance of 5.2$\sigma$. This is the first direct observation of electron neutrino interactions at a particle collider. Eight muon neutrino interaction candidate events are also detected, with an expected background of $0.22^{+0.09}_{-0.07}$, leading to a statistical significance of 5.7$\sigma$. The signal events include neutrinos with energies in the TeV range, the highest-energy electron and muon neutrinos ever detected from an artificial source. The energy-independent part of the interaction cross section per nucleon is measured over an energy range of 560--1740 GeV (520--1760 GeV) for $\nu_e$ ($\nu_{\mu}$) to be $(1.2_{-0.7}^{+0.8}) \times 10^{-38}~\mathrm{cm}^{2}\,\mathrm{GeV}^{-1}$ ($(0.5\pm0.2) \times 10^{-38}~\mathrm{cm}^{2}\,\mathrm{GeV}^{-1}$), consistent with Standard Model predictions. These are the first measurements of neutrino interaction cross sections in those energy ranges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.12520v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.021802</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 133, 021802 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> FASER Collaboration, Roshan Mammen Abraham, John Anders, Claire Antel, Akitaka Ariga, Tomoko Ariga, Jeremy Atkinson, Florian U. Bernlochner, Tobias Boeckh, Jamie Boyd, Lydia Brenner, Angela Burger, Franck Cadoux, Roberto Cardella, David W. Casper, Charlotte Cavanagh, Xin Chen, Andrea Coccaro, Stephane Debieux, Monica D'Onofrio, Ansh Desai, Sergey Dmitrievsky, Sinead Eley, Yannick Favre, Deion Fellers, Jonathan L. Feng, Carlo Alberto Fenoglio, Didier Ferrere, Max Fieg, Wissal Filali, Haruhi Fujimori, Ali Garabaglu, Stephen Gibson, Sergio Gonzalez-Sevilla, Yuri Gornushkin, Carl Gwilliam, Daiki Hayakawa, Shih-Chieh Hsu, Zhen Hu, Giuseppe Iacobucci, Tomohiro Inada, Luca Iodice, Sune Jakobsen, Hans Joos, Enrique Kajomovitz, Takumi Kanai, Hiroaki Kawahara, Alex Keyken, Felix Kling, Daniela Kock, Pantelis Kontaxakis, Umut Kose, Rafaella Kotitsa, Susanne Kuehn, Thanushan Kugathasan, Helena Lefebvre, Lorne Levinson, Ke Li, Jinfeng Liu, Margaret S. Lutz, Jack MacDonald, Chiara Magliocca, Fulvio Martinelli, Lawson McCoy, Josh McFayden, Andrea Pizarro Medina, Matteo Milanesio, Theo Moretti, Magdalena Munker, Mitsuhiro Nakamura, Toshiyuki Nakano, Friedemann Neuhaus, Laurie Nevay, Motoya Nonaka, Kazuaki Okui, Ken Ohashi, Hidetoshi Otono, Hao Pang, Lorenzo Paolozzi, Brian Petersen, Markus Prim, Michaela Queitsch-Maitland, Hiroki Rokujo, Elisa Ruiz-Choliz, Andr\'e Rubbia, Jorge Sabater-Iglesias, Osamu Sato, Paola Scampoli, Kristof Schmieden, Matthias Schott, Anna Sfyrla, Mansoora Shamim, Savannah Shively, Yosuke Takubo, Noshin Tarannum, Ondrej Theiner, Eric Torrence, Svetlana Vasina, Benedikt Vormwald, Di Wang, Yuxiao Wang, Eli Welch, Samuel Zahorec, Stefano Zambito, Shunliang Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The radiative decay of scalar glueball from lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01564v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We perform the first lattice QCD study on the radiative decay of the scalar glueball to the vector meson $\phi$ in the quenched approximation. The calculations are carried out on three gauge ensembles with different lattice spacings, which enable us to do the continuum extrapolation. We first revisit the radiative $J/\psi$ decay into the scalar glueball $G$ and obtain the partial decay width $\Gamma(J/\psi \to \gamma G)=0.578(86)~\text{keV}$ and the branching fraction $\text{Br}(J/\psi \to \gamma G) = 6.2(9)\times 10^{-3}$. We then extend the similar calculation to the process $G\to \gamma \phi$ and get the partial decay width $\Gamma(G \to \gamma \phi)= 0.074(47)~\text{keV}$, which implies that the combined branching fraction of $J/\psi\to\gamma G\to \gamma\gamma\phi$ is as small as $\mathcal{O}(10^{-9})$ such that this process is hardly detected by the BESIII experiment even with the large $J/\psi$ sample of $\mathcal{O}(10^{10})$. With the vector meson dominance model, the two-photon decay width of the scalar glueball is estimated to be $\Gamma(G\to\gamma\gamma)=0.53(46)~\text{eV}$, which results in a large stickiness $S(G)\sim \mathcal{O}(10^4)$ of the scalar glueball by assuming the stickiness of $f_2(1270)$ to be one.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01564v3</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jintao Zou, Long-Cheng Gui, Ying Chen, Jian Liang, Xiangyu Jiang, Wen Qin, Yi-Bo Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Unpolarized GPDs from Pseudo-Distributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10304v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present an exploration of the unpolarized isovector proton generalized parton distributions (GPDs) $H^{u-d}(x, \xi, t)$ and $E^{u-d}(x, \xi, t)$ in the pseudo-distribution formalism using distillation. Taking advantage of the large kinematic coverage made possible by this approach, we present results on the moments of GPDs up to the order $x^3$ -- including their skewness dependence -- at a pion mass $m_\pi = 358$ MeV and a lattice spacing $a = 0.094$ fm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10304v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Herv\'e Dutrieux, Robert G. Edwards, Colin Egerer, Joseph Karpie, Christopher Monahan, Kostas Orginos, Anatoly Radyushkin, David Richards, Eloy Romero, Savvas Zafeiropoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>To curve, or not to curve: Is curvature-assisted quintessence observationally viable?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09212</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09212v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Single-field models of accelerated expansion with nearly flat potentials, despite being able to provide observationally viable explanations for the early-time cosmic inflation and the late-time cosmic acceleration, are in strong tension with string theory evidence and the associated de Sitter swampland constraints. It has recently been argued that in an open universe, where the spatial curvature is negative (i.e., with $\Omega_k&gt;0$), a new stable fixed point arises, which may lead to viable single-field-based accelerated expansion with an arbitrarily steep potential. Here we show, through a dynamical systems analysis and a Bayesian statistical inference of cosmological parameters, that the additional cosmological solutions based on the new fixed point do not render steep-potential, single-field, accelerated expansion observationally viable. We mainly focus on quintessence models of dark energy, but we also argue that a similar conclusion can be drawn for cosmic inflation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09212v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George Alestas, Matilda Delgado, Ignacio Ruiz, Yashar Akrami, Miguel Montero, Savvas Nesseris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher-Dimensional MOG dark compact object: shadow behavior in the light of EHT observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06393</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06393v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Consideration of extra spatial dimensions is motivated by the unification of gravity with other interactions, the achievement of the ultimate framework of quantum gravity, and fundamental problems in particle physics and cosmology. Much attention has been focused on the effect of these extra dimensions on the modified theories of gravity. Analytically examining astrophysical phenomena like black hole shadows is one approach to understand how extra dimensions would affect the modified gravitational theories. The purpose of this study is to derive a higher dimensional metric for a dark compact object in STVG theory and then examine the behavior of the shadow shapes for this solution in STVG theory in higher dimensions. We apply the Carter method to formulate the geodesic equations and the Hamilton Jacobi method to find photon orbits around this higher dimensional MOG dark compact object. We investigate the effects of extra dimensions and the STVG parameter alpha on the black hole shadow size. Next, we compare the shadow radius of this higher dimensional MOG dark compact object to the shadow size of the supermassive black hole M87, which has been realized by the Event Horizon Telescope (EHT) collaborations, in order to restrict these parameters. We find that extra dimensions in the STVG theory typically lead to a reduction in the shadow size of the higher dimensional MOG dark compact object, whereas the effect of parameter alpha on this black hole shadow is suppressible. Remarkably, given the constraints from EHT observations, we find that the shadow size of the four dimensional MOG dark compact object lies in the confidence levels of the EHT data. Finally, we investigate the issue of acceleration bounds in higher dimensional MOG dark compact object in confrontation with EHT data of M87.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06393v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kourosh Nozari, Sara Saghafi, Ali Mohammadpour</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
