<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph</link>
    <description>hep-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2024 01:49:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On the bounded-from-below conditions for the extension of the SM through a scalar quadruplet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01628v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the scalar potential of the extension of the Standard Model through a scalar quadruplet with hypercharge either 1/2 or 3/2. That potential contains a term that had not been previously taken into account. We write down the full unitarity conditions. We use a numerical scan of phase space instead of attempting to derive fully analytical bounded-from-below conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01628v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Darius Jur\v{c}iukonis, Lu\'is Lavoura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A generalized statistical model for fits to parton distributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01664v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Parton distribution functions (PDFs) form an essential part of particle physics calculations. Currently, the most precise predictions for these non-perturbative functions are generated through fits to global data. A problem that several PDF fitting groups encounter is the presence of tension in data sets that appear to pull the fits in different directions. In other words, the best fit depends on the choice of data set. Several methods to capture the uncertainty in PDFs in presence of seemingly inconsistent fits have been proposed and are currently in use. These methods are important to ensure that uncertainty in PDFs are not underestimated. Here we propose a novel method for estimating the uncertainty by introducing a generalized statistical model inspired by unsupervised machine learning techniques, namely the Gaussian Mixture Model (GMM). Using a toy model of PDFs, we demonstrate how the GMM can be used to faithfully reconstruct the likelihood associated with PDF fits, which can in turn be used to accurately determine the uncertainty on PDFs, especially in presence of tension in the fitted data sets. We further show how this statistical model reduces to the usual chi-squared likelihood function for a consistent data set and provide measures to optimize the number of Gaussians in the GMM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01664v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengshi Yan, Tie-Jiun Hou, Zhao Li, Kirtimaan Mohan, C. -P. Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for heavy millicharged particles from the atmosphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01668v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: If millicharged particles (MCPs) exist they can be created in the atmosphere when high energy cosmic rays collide with nuclei and could subsequently be detected at neutrino experiments. We extend previous work, which considered MCPs from decays of light mesons and proton bremsstrahlung, by including production from $\Upsilon$ meson decays and the Drell-Yan process. MCPs with masses below a GeV primarily arise from proton bremsstrahlung, while heavier MCPs predominantly originate from heavy meson decays and Drell-Yan. We analyse the resulting single scatter and multiple scatter signals at SuperK and JUNO. Searches for low energy coincident signals at JUNO will be sensitive to MCPs with milli-charges up to an order of magnitude beyond current constraints for MCP masses between 2 GeV and 10 GeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01668v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Han Wu, Edward Hardy, Ningqiang Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of CKM element $|V_{cb}|$ from $W$ boson decays at the future Higgs factories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01675v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study investigates the precision measurement of the CKM matrix element $|V_{cb}|$ through semileptonic $WW$ events at future Higgs factories, $i.e.$, FCC-ee, ILC, C$^3$, and CEPC. We use full detector simulation to generate the $WW \to \ell \nu cb$ signal events and various backgrounds at $\sqrt{s} = 240$ GeV with unpolarized beams. The relative statistical uncertainties are projected to be 0.91\% for the muon channel and 1.2\% for the electron channel, assuming a baseline integrated luminosity of 5 ab$^{-1}$. The sensitivities at other Higgs factory scenarios are also projected. Possible contributors to systematic uncertainties are discussed, with the most prominent one being the systematics of flavor-tagging and mistagging rates. Combining with $WW$ threshold runs, the relative systematic uncertainty can be further reduced.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01675v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Liang, Lingfeng Li, Yongfeng Zhu, Xiaoyan Shen, Manqi Ruan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New insights into axion freeze-in</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01678v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Freeze-in via the axion-photon coupling, $g_{\phi\gamma}$, can produce axions in the early Universe. At low reheating temperatures close to the minimum allowed value $T_{\rm reh}\approx T_{\rm BBN}\approx 10\,{\rm MeV}$, the abundance peaks for axion masses $m_\phi\approx T_{\rm reh}$. Such heavy axions are unstable and subsequently decay, leading to strong constraints on $g_{\phi\gamma}$ from astrophysics and cosmology. In this work, we revisit the computation of the freeze-in abundance and clarify important issues. We begin with a complete computation of the collision terms for the Primakoff process, electron-positron annihilation, and photon-to-axion (inverse-)decay, while approximately taking into account plasma screening and threshold effects. We then solve the Boltzmann equation for the full axion distribution function. We confirm previous results about the importance of both processes to the effective "relic abundance" (defined as density prior to decay), and provide useful fitting formulae to estimate the freeze-in abundance from the equilibrium interaction rate. For the distribution function, we find an out-of-equilibrium population of axions and introduce an effective temperature for them. We follow the evolution right up until decay, and find that the average axion kinetic energy is larger than a thermal relic by between 20\% and 80\%, which may have implications for limits on decaying axions from X-ray spectra. We extend our study to a two-axion system with quartic cross-coupling, and find that for typical/expected couplings, freeze-in of a second axion flavour by annihilations leads to a negligibly small contribution to the relic density.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01678v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mudit Jain, Angelo Maggi, Wen-Yuan Ai, David J. E. Marsh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Neutrino-Ultralight Dark Matter Interaction on the Cosmic Neutrino Background</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01682</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01682v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ultralight dark matter interacting with sterile neutrinos would modify the evolution and properties of the cosmic neutrino background through active-sterile neutrino mixing. We investigate how such an interaction would induce a redshift dependence in neutrino masses. We highlight that cosmological constraints on the sum of neutrino masses would require reinterpretation due to the effective mass generated by neutrino-dark matter interactions. Furthermore, we present an example where such interactions can alter the mass ordering of neutrinos in the early Universe, compared to what we expect today. We also address the expected changes in the event rates in a PTOLEMY-like experiment, which aims to detect the cosmic neutrino background via neutrino capture, and discuss projected constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01682v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pablo Mart\'inez-Mirav\'e, Yuber F. Perez-Gonzalez, Manibrata Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Color Glass Condensate meets High Twist Expansion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01684</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01684v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish the correspondence between two well-known frameworks for QCD multiple scattering in nuclear media: the Color Glass Condensate (CGC) and the High-Twist (HT) expansion formalism. We argue that a consistent matching between both frameworks, in their common domain of validity, is achieved by incorporating the sub-eikonal longitudinal momentum phase in the CGC formalism, which mediates the transition between coherent and incoherent scattering. We perform a detailed calculation and analysis of direct photon production in proton-nucleus scattering as a concrete example to establish the matching between HT and CGC up to twist-4, including initial- and final-state interactions, as well as their interferences. The techniques developed in this work can be adapted to other processes in electron-nucleus and proton-nucleus collisions, and they provide a potential avenue for a unified picture of dilute-dense dynamics in nuclear media.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01684v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Fu, Zhong-Bo Kang, Farid Salazar, Xin-Nian Wang, Hongxi Xing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving the strong CP problem without axions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01689v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We formulate general conditions under which the strong CP problem is solved by spontaneous CP violation. Quark-mass matrix elements are polynomials in the CP-breaking order parameters, engineered such that their determinant is a real constant. This scheme permits only a limited number of textures. These conditions can be realized in supersymmetric theories with CP as an anomaly-free local flavour symmetry, suggesting a unified solution to the strong CP problem and the flavour puzzle. Our solution can be implemented using either modular invariance or a local U(1) symmetry. We present modular-invariant realizations where matter fields are assigned small modular weights $\pm2$ ($\pm1$), utilising higher levels $N=2$ ($N=3$). Heavy quarks are in general not required, but their presence allows for models where colored particles fill non-singlet representations of the flavour group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01689v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ferruccio Feruglio, Matteo Parriciatu, Alessandro Strumia, Arsenii Titov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solar chameleons: novel channels (I)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01691v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revisit the flux of chameleons (light scalar particles which could play a role in the dark energy phenomenon) produced in the interior of the Sun. Our novel analysis incorporates various important details and new processes that have previously been overlooked, including the impact of the bulk magnetic field profile, as well as Primakoff production of chameleons in the electric fields of electrons and ions. In this paper we consider only the contributions of transverse photons. The production of chameleons from longitudinal electromagnetic excitations will be presented in a dedicated follow-up work. Demanding that the total flux of chameleons does not exceed 3% of the solar luminosity leads to the stringent upper limit on the chameleon-photon conformal coupling $\beta_\gamma \lesssim 10^{10}$, assuming that the height of the chameleon potential is set to the dark energy scale $\Lambda = 2.4$ meV, and independently of other couplings to matter. Although this bound is tighter than current upper limits on $\beta_{\gamma}$ from the CAST helioscope, these limits will have to be reassessed in terms of the updated solar chameleon flux we have computed. We argue that solar chameleons, potentially detectable in next-generation helioscopes such as IAXO, can be used to probe a region of chameleon parameter space that has yet to be covered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01691v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom\'as O'Shea, Anne-Christine Davis, Maurizio Giannotti, Sunny Vagnozzi, Luca Visinelli, Julia K. Vogel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutrino Anarchy from Flavor Deconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01696v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Flavor deconstruction refers to non-universal gauge extensions where the original gauge symmetry is deconstructed into separate copies, one for each family. A hierarchical chain of symmetry breaking provides an attractive low-scale solution to the flavor puzzle, consistent with flavor-changing neutral currents and finite naturalness. Although successful in explaining the origin of flavor hierarchies in the quark and charged lepton sectors, existing models have struggled with the large and seemingly anarchic mixing observed in neutrino oscillations. This letter identifies conditions under which neutrino anarchy may arise from flavor deconstruction in generic models with right-handed neutrinos. When deconstruction is applied to carefully chosen subgroups of the extended gauge symmetry, hierarchies in the seesaw formula cancel out.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01696v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Admir Greljo, Gino Isidori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring doubly-heavy tetraquarks in constituent-quark-model based meson-meson coupled-channels approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01697v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The LHCb Collaboration announced in 2021 the discovery of a new tetraquark-like state, named $T_{cc}^+$, with minimum quark content $cc\bar u\bar d$, close to the $D^0D^{*+}$ threshold. This has motivated countless theoretical works trying to identify the dynamics which is responsible of the formation of such state; in particular, the one performed by us in Ref. \cite{Ortega:2022efc}, where a $D^0D^{*+}$ molecular candidate whose mass, width, scattering length and effective ranges are in reasonable agreement with experimental measurements. We explore herein the possibility of having $T_{cc}^+$ partners in all doubly-heavy tetraquark sectors, considering doubly represented light antiquarks $u$, $d$ or $s$, and taking into account all possible spin-parity quantum numbers. The computation is done using a constituent-quark-model based meson-meson coupled-channels framework which has been tested many times in the last fifteen years describing conventional heavy mesons and baryons, their coupling with hadron-hadron thresholds but also in exploring its application to compact multiquark structures. The advantage of using an approach with such a relatively large history is that it allows us to make predictions because all the parameters have already been constrained from our previous works. Then, from this perspective, we present a parameter-free model-dependent prediction of doubly-heavy tetraquarks that may be partners of the discovered $T_{cc}^+$ state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01697v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. G. Ortega, D. R. Entem, F. Fernandez, J. Segovia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01705v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We review observational, experimental and theoretical results related to Dark Matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01705v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Cirelli, Alessandro Strumia, Jure Zupan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reopening the Z portal with semi-annihilations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01729</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01729v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In one-component dark matter (DM) scenarios is commonly assumed that a scalar WIMP must either be part of an $SU(2)_L$ multiplet with zero hypercharge or have suppressed vector interactions with the $Z$ gauge boson to circumvent stringent direct detection (DD) bounds. In this work, we demonstrate that multi-component scenarios with a dark scalar doublet exhibiting vector-like interactions with the $Z$ boson are also compatible with bounds arising from DD searches. Specifically, we consider a simple extension of the Standard Model wherein the dark sector comprises a doublet and a complex singlet $\phi$, both charged under a $Z_6$ symmetry. We find that semi-annihilation processes drastically reduce the relic abundance of the neutral component of the doublet, $H^0$, sufficiently attenuating the effects of its large $Z$-mediated elastic scattering cross-section with nucleons to satisfy the DD constraints. Although the contribution of $H^0$ to the total relic abundance is nearly negligible, with $\phi$ dominating, both dark matter components are expected to be detectable in ongoing and future DD experiments. The viability of the model is tested against several theoretical and experimental constraints, resulting in a parameter space featuring a non-degenerate mass spectrum at the electroweak scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01729v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mar\'ia J. Dom\'inguez, Oscar Rodr\'iguez, \'Oscar Zapata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dip-Bump Structure in Proton's Single Diffractive Dissociation at the Large Hadron Collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01735v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: By extending the dipole Pomeron (DP) model, successful in describing elastic nucleon-nucleon scattering, to proton single diffractive dissociation (SD), we predict a dip-bump structure in the squared four-momentum transfer ($t$) distribution of proton's SD. Structures in the $t$ distribution of single diffractive dissociation are predicted around $t=-4$ GeV$^2$ at LHC energies in the range of 3 GeV$^2$ $\lesssim|t|\lesssim$ 7 GeV$^2$. Apart from the dependence on $s$ (total energy squared) and $t$ (squared momentum transfer), we predict also a dependence on missing masses. We include the minimum set of Regge trajectories, namely the Pomeron and the Odderon, indispensable at the LHC. Further generalization, e.g., by the inclusion of non-leading Regge trajectories, is straightforward. The present model contains two types of Regge trajectories: those connected with $t$-channel exchanges (the Pomeron, the Odderon, and non-leading (secondary) reggeons) appearing at small and moderate $-t$, where they are real and nearly linear, as well as direct-channel trajectories $\alpha(M^2)$ related to missing masses. In this paper, we concentrate on structures in $t$ neglecting (for the time being) resonances in $M^2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01735v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/universe10050208</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Universe 2024, 10(5), 208</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>L\'aszl\'o Jenkovszky, Rainer Schicker, Istv\'an Szanyi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling laws of elastic proton-proton scattering differential cross sections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01737</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01737v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that elastic scattering $pp \to pp $ differential cross sections as function of the four-momentum transfer square $|t|$ have a universal property, such that the ratio of bump-to-dip positions is constant from the energies of the ISR to the LHC, from tens of GeV and up to the TeV scale. We explore this property to compare the geometrical scaling observed at the ISR with the recently proposed scaling law at the LHC. We argue that, at the LHC, within present experimental uncertainties, there is in fact a family of scaling laws. We discuss the constraints that the scaling laws impose on the parametrization of the elastic $pp\to pp$ scattering amplitude.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01737v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cristian Baldenegro, Michal Praszalowicz, Christophe Royon, Anna M. Stasto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NNPDF4.0 aN$^3$LO PDFs with QED corrections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01779</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01779v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We review recent progress in the global determination of the collinear parton distributions (PDFs) of the proton within the NNPDF framework. This progress includes NNPDF4.0 variants with QED effects and with missing higher order uncertainties (MHOUs) via the theory covariance matrix formalism, as well as PDFs based on QCD calculations at approximate N$^3$LO (aN$^3$LO) accuracy. We present the combination of these theoretical developments resulting into NNPDF4.0 aN$^3$LO variants accounting for QED corrections and with a photon PDF. We compare these aN$^3$LO QED PDFs with analogous results obtained by the MSHT group, and briefly quantify their implications at the level of representative LHC cross-sections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01779v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Barontini, Niccolo Laurenti, Juan Rojo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pionic transitions of the spin-2 partner of $X(3872)$ to $\chi_{cJ}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01874v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigated the pionic transitions between the $X_2$ [spin-2 partner of the $X(3872)$] and $\chi_{c1,2}$ using a nonrelativistic effective field theory. The $X_2$ is assumed to be a bound state of the $D^{*}$ and $\bar{D}^*$ mesons and to decay through several kinds of loops, including the bubble, triangle and box loops. Within the present model, the widths for the single-pion decays $X_2\to\pi^0\chi_{cJ}$ are predicted to be about $3$--$30$ keV. For the dipion decays, the widths are a few keVs. These widths yield a branching fraction of $10^{-3}$--$10^{-2}$. The ratio $R_{\mathrm{c}0}=\Gamma (X_2\to\pi^+\pi^-\chi_{cJ})/\Gamma (X_2\to\pi^0\pi^0\chi_{cJ}) \simeq 1.6$, which is a bit smaller than the expected value of $2$, and $R_{21}=\Gamma (X_2\to\pi\pi\chi_{c2})/\Gamma (X_2\to\pi\pi\chi_{c1}) \simeq 0.85$. These ratios are nearly independent of the $X_2$ mass and the coupling constants, which might be a good quantity for the experiments. Moreover, the invariant mass spectra of the $\pi^0\chi_{cJ}$ final state for the dipion processes are presented, showing a cusp structure at the $D {\bar D}^*$ threshold enhanced and narrowed by the nearby triangle singularity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01874v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shi-Dong Liu (College of Physics and Engineering, Qufu Normal University, Qufu, China), Fan Wang (College of Physics and Engineering, Qufu Normal University, Qufu, China), Zhao-Sai Jia (College of Physics and Engineering, Qufu Normal University, Qufu, China, CAS Key Laboratory of Theoretical Physics, Institute of Theoretical Physics, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China), Gang Li (College of Physics and Engineering, Qufu Normal University, Qufu, China), Xiao-Hai Liu (Center for Joint Quantum Studies and Department of Physics, School of Science, Tianjin University, Tianjin, China), Ju-Jun Xie (Institute of Modern Physics, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Lanzhou, China, Southern Center for Nuclear-Science Theory)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-fragmentation functions in the massive Schwinger model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01891v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the concept of the quark quasi-fragmentation function (qFF) using an equal-time and spatially boosted form of the Collins-Soper fragmentation function (FF) where the out-meson fragment is replaced by the current asymptotic condition. We derive the qFF for a fermion in two-dimensional quantum electrodynamics (QED2) using the Kogut-Susskind Hamiltonian after a mapping onto spin qubits in a spatial lattice with open boundary conditions. This form is suitable for quantum computations. We compute the qFF by exact diagonalization of the spin Hamiltonian. The results are compared to the qFF following from the Drell-Levy-Yan (DLY) result for QED2, both at strong and weak coupling, and to two-dimensional quantum chromodynamics (QCD2) in the lowest Fock approximation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01891v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Grieninger, Ismail Zahed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explaining the possible 95 GeV excesses in the $B-L$ symmetric SSM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01926</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01926v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study investigates the excesses observed in the diphoton and $b\bar b$ data around $95\;{\rm GeV}$ within the framework of the $B-L$ supersymmetric model (B-LSSM). Comparing with the minimal supersymmetric standard model, the B-LSSM incorporates two singlet chiral Higgs bosons which mix with the SM-like Higgs boson due to the gauge kinetic mixing effect. The richer Higgs sector indicates that designating the B-LSSM specific CP-even Higgs state as the lightest Higgs boson has great potential to explain the excesses at around $95\;{\rm GeV}$. Considering the two-loop effective potential corrections to the squared Higgs mass matrix, it is found that the signal strengthes $\mu(h_{95})_{\gamma\gamma}$, $\mu(h_{95})_{b b}$ can be described simultaneously in the experimental $1\sigma$ interval. And the B-LSSM specific parameters $\tan\beta'$, $B_\eta$, $g_{YB}$, $M_{Z'}$ affect the theoretical predictions on the light Higgs boson masses and signal strengthes $\mu(h_{95})_{\gamma\gamma}$, $\mu(h_{95})_{bb}$ significantly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01926v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin-Lei Yang, Ming-Hui Guo, Wen-Hui Zhang, Hai-Bin Zhang, Tai-Fu Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lepton Flavor Violation at FCC-ee and CEPC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01935</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01935v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Lepton flavor violating processes are highly suppressed in the Standard Model. Therefore, if observed, lepton flavor violation would be a clear indication of new physics beyond the Standard Model. We study the process $e^+e^-\to\tau\mu$ at tree-level in the Standard Model Effective Field Theory both on the $Z$-pole and at higher center-of-mass energies. We show that the constraints derived from the future circular $e^+e^-$ colliders FCC-ee and CEPC, are complementary to those obtained from low-energy tau decays at BaBar and Belle, as well as projections from Belle-II.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01935v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pankaj Munbodh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Benchmark Mode $\Omega_c \to \Omega^-\pi^+$ and Its Related Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02097v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The benchmark mode $\Omega_c^0\to \Omega^- \pi^+$, which receives purely factorization contribution, is of great importance among all the decay channels of $\Omega_c^0$ decays. In this work, within the framework of non-relativistic quark model (NRQM), we calculate all the 6 baryon transition form factors involving $\frac12 ^+\to \frac32 ^+$ decays. The absolute branching fractions of non-leptonic decays $\Omega_c^0\to \Omega^- \pi^+$, $\Omega_c^0\to \Omega^- \rho^+$ and $\Omega_c^0\to \Xi^- \pi^+$ as well as semi-leptonic decays $\Omega_c^0\to \Omega^- \ell^+ \nu_{\ell} \; (\ell=e,\mu)$ are calculated although they cannot be measured directly by current experiment. Based on the prediction $\mathcal{B}(\Omega_c^0\to\Omega^-\pi^+)=3.43\%$ in our work, we further predict the ratios between interested modes and the benchmark mode, giving $R(\Xi^-\pi^+)=0.156$, $R(\Omega^-\rho^+)=5.33$, $R(\Omega^- e^+\nu_e)=1.18$ and $R(\Omega^- \mu^+\nu_\mu)=1.11$. The predictions on $\Omega_c^0\to \Xi^-\pi^+$ and $\Omega_c^0\to \Omega^- e^+\nu$ agree well with recent measured ratios reported by LHCb in 2023 and ALICE in 2024, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02097v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuge Zeng, Fanrong Xu, Yu Gu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extracting the partonic structure of colorless exchanges at the Electron Ion Collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02227</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02227v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the determination of the partonic structure of colorless exchanges in deep inelastic diffractive $ep$ scattering at the Electron Ion Collider, using the standard decomposition into Pomeron and Reggeon contributions. We perform fits to simulated diffractive cross section pseudodata in four variables, including the momentum transfer $t$, to estimate the achievable precision on the Pomeron and Reggeon quark and gluon distributions. We analyze the influence of different cuts in the kinematic variables, beam energy configurations and luminosities, including a `first year' scenario. We conclude that the EIC will be able to constrain the partonic structure of the sub-leading Reggeon exchange with a precision comparable to that of the leading Pomeron exchange.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02227v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N\'estor Armesto, Paul R. Newman, Wojciech S{\l}omi\'nski, Anna M. Sta\'sto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining P and T Violating Forces with Chiral Molecules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02281</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02281v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: New sources of parity and time reversal violation are predicted by well motivated extensions of the Standard Model and can be effectively probed by precision spectroscopy of atoms and molecules. Chiral molecules have distinguished enantiomers which are related by parity transformation. Thus, they are promising candidates to search for parity violation at molecular scales, yet to be observed. In this work, we show that precision spectroscopy of the hyperfine structure of chiral molecules is sensitive to new physics sources of parity and time reversal violation. In particular, such a study can be sensitive to regions unexplored by terrestial experiments of a new chiral spin-1 particle that couples to nucleons. We explore the potential to hunt for time reversal violation in chiral molecules and show that it can be a complementary measurement to other probes. We assess the feasibility of such hyperfine metrology and project the sensitivity in CHDBrI$^+$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02281v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Baruch, P. B. Changala, Y. Shagam, Y. Soreq</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Piecewise linear potentials for false vacuum decay and negative modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02414v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study bounce solutions and associated negative modes in the class of piecewise linear triangular-shaped potentials that may be viewed as approximations of smooth potentials. In these simple potentials, the bounce solution and action can be obtained analytically for a general spacetime dimension $D$. The eigenequations for the fluctuations around the bounce are universal and have the form of a Schr\"odinger-like equation with delta-function potentials. This Schr\"odinger equation is solved exactly for the negative modes whose number is confirmed to be one. The latter result may justify the usefulness of such piecewise linear potentials in the study of false vacuum decay.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02414v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Yuan Ai, Jean Alexandre, Sarben Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-two-body decays $B\to P f_0(500)\to P\pi^+\pi^-$ in the perturbative QCD approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02419</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02419v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the quasi-two-body decays $B\to P f_0(500)\to P\pi^+\pi^-$ (with $P=(\pi, K, \eta, \eta^{\prime})$) within framework of perturbative QCD (PQCD) factorization approach. With the help of $\pi$-$\pi$ distribution amplitude and scalar form factor $F_{\pi\pi}(\omega^2)$, we calculate the CP averaged branching fraction and the CP asymmetry for the quasi-two-body decays $B\to P f_0(500)\to P\pi^+\pi^-$. Taking the quasi-two-body decay $B^+ \to \pi^+ f_0(500) \to \pi^+ \pi^+ \pi^-$ as an explicit example, we present the behaviour of differential branching fraction and direct CP violation versus the $\pi$-$\pi$ invariant mass. The total branching fraction and direct CP violation are $\mathcal{B}(B^+\to \pi^+ [\sigma\to]\pi^+\pi^-) = (1.78 \pm 0.41\pm 0.51) \times 10^{-6}$ and $\mathcal{A}_{\rm CP}(B^+\to \pi^+ [\sigma\to]\pi^+\pi^-) = (29.8\pm 11.1\pm 13.0)\%$ respectively. Our results could be tested by further experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02419v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Wei Zhang, Bo-Yan Cui, Xing-Gang Wu, Hai-Bing Fu, Ya-Hui Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spinor-helicity calculation of the $g^* g^* \to q\overline{q} V^*$ amplitude at the tree level</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02445v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We compute amplitudes for the process $g^* g^* \to q \overline q V^*$ (two virtual gluons into a quark, antiquark and a boson) at the tree level using the spinor-helicity formalism. The resulting analytic expressions are much shorter than squared amplitudes obtained using trace methods. Our results can be used to expedite numerical calculations in phenomenological studies of the Drell-Yan process in high energy factorization framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02445v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Ferdyan, B{\l}a\.zej Ruba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electromagnetic corrections in hadronic tau decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02471v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We briefly review electromagnetic radiative corrections in semileptonic tau decays and their main applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02471v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alejandro Miranda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-holomorphic modular flavor symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02527v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The formalism of non-holomorphic modular flavor symmetry is developed, and the Yukawa couplings are level $N$ polyharmonic Maa{\ss} forms satisfying the Laplacian condition. We find that the integer (even) weight polyharmonic Maa{\ss} forms of level $N$ can be decomposed into multiplets of the finite modular group $\Gamma'_N$ ($\Gamma_N$). The original modular invariance approach is extended by the presence of negative weight polyharmonic Maa{\ss} forms. The non-holomorphic modular flavor symmetry can be consistently combined with the generalized CP symmetry. We present three example models for lepton sector based on the $\Gamma_3\cong A_4$ modular symmetry, the charged lepton masses and the neutrino oscillation data can be accommodated very well, and the predictions for the leptonic CP violation phases and the effective Majorana neutrino mass are studied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02527v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bu-Yao Qu, Gui-Jun Ding</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark photon limits from patchy dark screening of the cosmic microwave background</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02546v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dark photons that kinetically mix with the Standard Model photon give rise to new spectral anisotropies (patchy dark screening) in the cosmic microwave background (CMB) due to conversion of photons to dark photons within large-scale structure. We utilize predictions for this patchy dark screening signal to provide the tightest constraints to date on the dark photon kinetic mixing parameter ($\varepsilon \lesssim 4\times 10^{-8}$ (95% confidence level)) over the mass range $10^{-13} \,\, {\rm eV} \lesssim m_{{A^\prime}} \lesssim 10^{-11}$ eV, almost an order of magnitude stronger than previous limits, by applying state-of-the-art component separation techniques to the cross-correlation of $\textit{Planck}$ CMB and $\textit{unWISE}$ galaxy survey data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02546v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fiona McCarthy, Dalila Pirvu, J. Colin Hill, Junwu Huang, Matthew C. Johnson, Keir K. Rogers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Positive-Energy Dirac Particles and Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01654v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The relativistic positive-energy wave equation proposed by P. Dirac in 1971 is an old but largely forgotten subject. The purpose of this note is to speculate that particles described by this equation (called here Dirac particles) are natural candidates for the dark matter. The reasoning is based on a fact that the internal structure of such particles simply prohibits their interaction with electromagnetic fields (at least with the minimal coupling) which is exactly what is required for dark matter. Dirac particles have quite unusual properties. In particular, they are transformed by an infinite-dimensional representation of the homogeneous Lorentz group, which clearly distinguishes them from all known elementary particles described by finite-dimensional representations and hints to a physics beyond the Standard Model. To clarify the topic, a brief review of the main features of {the above-mentioned} Dirac equation is given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01654v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/universe10050222</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Universe 10, 222 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Eugene Bogomolny</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Wave Driven Inspirals of Non-relativistic Binaries Connected by Cosmic Strings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01758</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01758v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider gravitational waves from a pair of non-relativistically moving monopoles or black holes connected by a cosmic string. Shortly after the binary's formation, the connecting string straightens due the direct coupling of its motion to gravitational radiation. Afterwards, the motion of the binary can be well-approximated by a non-relativistic motion of its components that have an additional constant mutual attraction force due to the tension of the straight string that connects them. The orbit shrinks due to the gravitational radiation backreacting on the binary's components. We find that if the binary's semimajor axis $a\gg \sqrt{R_1 R_2/{\mu}}$, its eccentricity grows on the inspiral's timescale; here $R_1$ and $R_2$ are the gravitational radii of the binary components, and $\mu$ is the dimensionless tension of the string. When the eccentricity is high, it approaches unity super-exponentially. If the binary's components are monopole-antimonopole pair, this leads to the physical collision that would likely destroy the string and annihilate the monopoles when the semimajor axis is still many orders of magnitude greater than the string thickness. If the binary's components are black holes, then the eccentricity reaches its peak when $a\sim \sqrt{R_1 R_2/\mu}$, and then decays according to the standard Peter's formula. The black-hole spins initially become locked to the orbital motion, but then lag behind as the inspiral proceeds. We estimate the string-tension-induced dimensionless spins just prior to the merger and find them to be $\sim\mu^{3/8}\ll 1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01758v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmed Sheta, Yuri Levin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Basis for Non-Factorizable Superamplitudes in N = 1 Supersymmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01861</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01861v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we develop a semi-standard Young tableau (SSYT) approach to construct a basis of non-factorizable superamplitudes in N = 1 massless supersymmetry. This amplitude basis can be directly translated to a basis for higher dimensional supersymmetric operators, yielding both the number of independent operators and their form. We deal with distinguishable (massless) chiral/vector superfields at first, then generalize the result to the indistinguishable case. Finally, we discuss the advantages and disadvantages of this method compared to the previously studied Hilbert series approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01861v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Delgado, Adam Martin, Runqing Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>50 GeV $\pi^-$ in, nothing out: a sensitive probe of invisible $\eta$ and $\eta'$ decays with NA64h</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01990v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the first results from a proof-of-concept search for dark sectors via invisible decays of pseudoscalar $\eta$ and $\eta'$ mesons in the NA64h experiment at the CERN SPS. Our novel technique uses the charge-exchange reaction of 50 GeV $\pi^-$ on nuclei of an active target as the source of neutral mesons. The $\eta, \eta' \to invisible$ events would exhibit themselves via a striking signature - the complete disappearance of the incoming beam energy in the detector. No evidence for such events has been found with $2.9\times10^{9}$ pions on target accumulated during one day of data taking. This allows us to set a stringent limit on the branching ratio ${\rm Br}(\eta' \to invisible) &lt; 2.1 \times 10^{-4}$ improving the current bound by a factor of $\simeq3$. We also set a limit on ${\rm Br}(\eta \to invisible) &lt; 1.1 \times 10^{-4}$ comparable with the existing one. These results demonstrate the great potential of our approach and provide clear guidance on how to enhance and extend the sensitivity for dark sector physics from future searches for invisible neutral meson decays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01990v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu. M. Andreev, A. Antonov, M. A. Ayala Torres, D. Banerjee, B. Banto Oberhauser, J. Bernhard, P. Bisio, A. Celentano, N. Charitonidis, D. Cooke, P. Crivelli, E. Depero, A. V. Dermenev, S. V. Donskov, R. R. Dusaev, T. Enik, V. N. Frolov, S. V. Gertsenberger, S. Girod, S. N. Gninenko, M. Hosgen, V. A. Kachanov, Y. Kambar, A. E. Karneyeu, G. D. Kekelidze, B. Ketzer, D. V. Kirpichnikov, V. N. Kolosov, V. A. Kramarenko, L. V. Kravchuk, N. V. Krasnikov, S. V. Kuleshov, V. E. Lyubovitskij, A. Marini, L. Marsicano, V. A. Matveev, R. Mena Fredes, R. G. Mena Yanssen, L. Molina Bueno, M. Mongillo, D. V. Peshekhonov, V. A. Polyakov, B. Radics, K. M. Salamatin, V. D. Samoylenko, H. Sieber, D. A. Shchukin, O. Soto, V. O. Tikhomirov, I. V. Tlisova, A. N. Toropin, M. Tuzi, P. V. Volkov, V. Yu. Volkov, I. V. Voronchikhin, J. Zamora-Saa, A. S. Zhevlakov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review of searches for new physics at CMS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02010v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A review of recent results from searches for new physics is presented. The analyses exploit data sets collected by the CMS experiment during Run 2 of the CERN LHC. Searches for exotic particles decaying into two bosons and for heavy neutral leptons, as well as a model-agnostic search based on anomaly detection are summarised. No significant sign for the presence of new physics was found. Prospects for the CMS parking strategy during Run 3 are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02010v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anne-Mazarine Lyon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the non-uniqueness of the energy-momentum and spin currents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02127v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The macroscopic energy-momentum and spin densities of relativistic spin hydrodynamics are obtained from the ensemble average of their respective microscopic definitions (quantum operators). These microscopic definitions suffer from ambiguities, meaning that, one may obtain different forms of symmetric energy-momentum tensor and spin tensor through pseudogauge transformations (or in other words Belinfante improvement procedure). However, this ambiguity can be removed if we obtain these currents using Noether's second theorem instead of widely used Noether's first theorem. In this article, we use Noether's second theorem to derive energy-momentum and spin currents without the need of pseudogauge transformations for free Dirac massive particles with spin one-half.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02127v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rajeev Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Statistical Effects on Warm Dark Matter and the Mass Constraint from the Cosmic Large Scale Structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02159v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The suppression of small-scale matter power spectrum is a distinct feature of Warm Dark Matter (WDM), which permits a constraint on the WDM mass from galaxy surveys. In the thermal relic WDM scenario, quantum statistical effects are not manifest. In a unified framework, we investigate the quantum statistical effects for a fermion case with a degenerate pressure and a boson case with a Bose-Einstein condensation (BEC). Compared to the thermal relic case, the degenerate fermion case only slightly lowers the mass bound while the boson case with a high initial BEC fraction ($\gtrsim90\%$) significantly lowers it. On the other hand, the BEC fraction drops during the relativistic-to-nonrelativistic transition and completely disappears if the initial fraction is below $\sim64\%$. Given the rising interest in resolving the late-time galaxy-scale problems with boson condensation, a question is posed on how a high initial BEC fraction can be dynamically created so that a DM condensed component remains today.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02159v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhijian Zhang, Weikang Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bridging the micro-Hz gravitational wave gap via Doppler tracking with the Uranus Orbiter and Probe Mission: Massive black hole binaries, early universe signals and ultra-light dark matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02306</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02306v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: With the recent announcement by NASA's Planetary Science and Astrobiology Decadal Survey 2023-2032, a priority flagship mission to the planet Uranus is anticipated. Here, we explore the prospects of using the mission's radio Doppler tracking equipment to detect gravitational waves (GWs) and other analogous signals related to dark matter (DM) over the duration of its interplanetary cruise. By employing a methodology to stack tracking data in combination with Monte-Carlo Markov-Chain parameter recovery tests, we show that the mission will be sensitive to GWs over the wide frequency range of $3\times 10^{-9}$ Hz to $10^{-1}$ Hz, provided that tracking data is taken consistently over a large fraction of the cruise duration. Thus, the mission has the potential to fill the gap between pulsar timing and space-based-interferometry GW observatories. Within this assumption, we forecast the detection of $\mathcal{\mathcal{O}}(1 - 100)$ individual massive black hole binaries using two independent population models. Additionally, we determine the mission's sensitivity to both astrophysical and primordial stochastic gravitational wave backgrounds, as well as its capacity to test, or even confirm via detection, ultralight DM models. In all these cases, the tracking of the spacecraft over its interplanetary cruise would enable coverage of unexplored regions of parameter space, where signals from new phenomena in our Universe may be lurking.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02306v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenz Zwick, Deniz Soyuer, Daniel J. D'Orazio, David O'Neill, Andrea Derdzinski, Prasenjit Saha, Diego Blas, Alexander C. Jenkins, Luke Zoltan Kelley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial gravitational wave backgrounds from phase transitions with next generation ground based detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02359v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Third generation ground-based gravitational wave (GW) detectors, such as Einstein Telescope and Cosmic Explorer, will operate in the $(\text{few}-10^4)$ Hz frequency band, with a boost in sensitivity providing an unprecedented reach into primordial cosmology. Working concurrently with pulsar timing arrays in the nHz band, and LISA in the mHz band, these 3G detectors will be powerful probes of beyond the standard model particle physics on scales $T\gtrsim 10^{7}$GeV. Here we focus on their ability to probe phase transitions (PTs) in the early universe. We first overview the landscape of detectors across frequencies, discuss the relevance of astrophysical foregrounds, and provide convenient and up-to-date power-law integrated sensitivity curves for these detectors. We then present the constraints expected from GW observations on first order PTs and on topological defects (strings and domain walls), which may be formed when a symmetry is broken irrespective of the order of the phase transition. These constraints can then be applied to specific models leading to first order PTs and/or topological defects. In particular we discuss the implications for axion models, which solve the strong CP problem by introducing a spontaneously broken Peccei-Quinn (PQ) symmetry. For post-inflationary breaking, the PQ scale must lie in the $10^{8}-10^{11}$ GeV range, and so the signal from a first order PQ PT falls within reach of ground based 3G detectors. A scan in parameter space of signal-to-noise ratio in a representative model reveals their large potential to probe the nature of the PQ transition. Additionally, in heavy axion type models domain walls form, which can lead to a detectable GW background. We discuss their spectrum and summarise the expected constraints on these models from 3G detectors, together with SKA and LISA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02359v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chiara Caprini, Oriol Pujol\`as, Hippolyte Quelquejay-Leclere, Fabrizio Rompineve, Dani\`ele A. Steer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Gaussian tails without stochastic inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02417</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02417v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show, both analytically and numerically, that non-Gaussian tails in the probability density function of curvature perturbations arise in ultra-slow-roll inflation from the $\delta N$ formalism, without invoking stochastic inflation. Previously reported discrepancies between both approaches are a consequence of not correctly accounting for momentum perturbations. Once they are taken into account, both approaches agree to an excellent degree. The shape of the tail depends strongly on the phase space of inflation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02417v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillermo Ballesteros, Thomas Konstandin, Alejandro P\'erez Rodr\'iguez, Mathias Pierre, Juli\'an Rey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid inflation and gravitational waves from accidentally light scalars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02531</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02531v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct a hybrid-inflation model where the inflaton potential is generated radiatively, as gauge symmetries guarantee it to be accidentally flat at tree level. The model can be regarded as a small-field version of Natural Inflation, with inflation ending when the mass of a second scalar, the waterfall field, turns tachyonic. This provides a minimal, robust realisation of hybrid inflation, which predicts specific correlations among CMB observables. Tachyonic preheating leads to the production of gravitational waves which, for a low inflationary scale, might be detected by upcoming experiments. Simple variations of the model can give rise to topological defects, such as unstable domain walls. Their dynamics produces a stochastic gravitational-wave background, which can be compatible with the recent detection by pulsar timing arrays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02531v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felix Br\"ummer, Giacomo Ferrante, Michele Frigerio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MADHAT: Model-Agnostic Dark Halo Analysis Tool</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02890</link>
      <description>arXiv:1910.02890v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the Model-Agnostic Dark Halo Analysis Tool (MADHAT), a numerical tool which implements a Fermi-LAT data-driven, model-independent analysis of gamma-ray emission from dwarf satellite galaxies and dwarf galaxy candidates due to dark matter annihilation, dark matter decay, or other nonstandard or unknown astrophysics. This tool efficiently provides statistical upper bounds on the number of observed photons in excess of the number expected, based on empirical determinations of foregrounds and backgrounds, using a stacked analysis of any selected set of dwarf targets. It also calculates the resulting bounds on the properties of dark matter under any assumptions the user makes regarding dark sector particle physics or astrophysics. As an application, we determine new bounds on Sommerfeld-enhanced dark matter annihilation in a set of eight dwarfs. MADHAT v1.0 includes 58 dwarfs and dwarf candidate targets, and we discuss future planned developments. MADHAT is available and will be maintained at https://github.com/MADHATdm</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1910.02890v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.cpc.2020.107815</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Computer Physics Communications 261 (2021) 107815</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kimberly K. Boddy, Stephen Hill, Jason Kumar, Pearl Sandick, Barmak Shams Es Haghi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hypothesis of a new fundamental interaction versus the particle oscillation concept</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.03366</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.03366v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A significant part of the present work is devoted to proving that the basic elements of the particle oscillation concept either do not correspond to the principles of classical logic, or violate the energy-momentum conservation law, or contradict the quantum mechanical basis of coherence, or represent a primitive falsehood. Our analysis concerns successively all stages of the formation of the concept from its conceiving to the assertion about the conversion of the solar electron neutrino into a muon one. When discussing a new fundamental interaction, we note the decisive role in the outcome of the processes of changing the handedness of a neutrino (antineutrino) at each act of its interaction with a real or virtual massless pseudoscalar boson, due to which, at the exit from the Sun, the fluxes of left- and right-handed electron neutrinos become approximately equal. Thanks to the new interaction, beta decays of nuclei have a mode with the emission of a massless pseudoscalar boson, at which the antineutrino changes its handedness and becomes unobservable, what is the essence of the reactor antineutrino anomaly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.03366v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. M. Slad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaporation Barrier for Dark Matter in Celestial Bodies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.01516</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.01516v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The minimum testable dark matter (DM) mass for almost all DM signatures in celestial bodies is determined by the rate at which DM evaporates. DM evaporation has previously been calculated assuming a competition between the gravitational potential of the object, and thermal kicks from the celestial-body matter. We point out a new effect, where mediators with a range larger than the interparticle spacing induce a force proportional to the density gradient of celestial objects, forming an evaporation barrier for the DM. This effect can be so significant that evaporation does not occur even for sub-MeV DM, in stark contrast to previous calculations. This opens up a wide range of new light DM searches, many orders of magnitude in DM mass below the sensitivity of direct detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.01516v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2024/04/038</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Javier F. Acevedo, Rebecca K. Leane, Juri Smirnov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing $Z$ boson rare decays $Z\to H_1 \gamma, A_1 \gamma$ with $(g-2)_\mu$, $M_W$, and $BR(h_{\rm SM}\to Z\gamma)$ in the NMSSM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.06558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.06558v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the rare decay process of $Z$ boson into photon, accompanied by a CP-even or CP-odd scalar. We present the analytical delineation of the processes through the model-independent parametrizations of the new physics couplings and, finally, consider the Next-to-Minimal Supersymmetric Standard Model to mark out the parameter space where the branching fraction can have the maximum value. As a part of the necessary phenomenological and experimental cross-checks, we aim to fit the anomalous magnetic moment of the muon and $W$ boson mass anomaly through the supersymmetric contributions. We also find that the decays $Z\to H_1 \gamma, A_1 \gamma$ can serve as an excellent complementary test to $BR(h_{\rm SM}\to Z\gamma)$. In fact, to facilitate future searches, we unveil a few benchmark points that additionally satisfy the deviation of $BR(h_{\rm SM}\to Z\gamma)$ from the SM value based on the recent measurements of ATLAS and CMS. Future proposals such as ILC, CEPC, and FCC-ee are anticipated to operate for multiple years, focusing on center-of-mass energy near the $Z$ pole. Consequently, these projects will be capable of conducting experiments at the Giga-$Z$ ($10^{9}$ of $Z$ bosons) and Tera-$Z$ ($10^{12}$ of $Z$ bosons) phases, which may probe the aforesaid rare decay processes, thus the model as well. These unconventional yet complementary searches offer different routes to explore the supersymmetric models with extended Higgs sectors like NMSSM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.06558v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhadip Bisal, Debottam Das</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Milky Way White Dwarfs as Sub-GeV to Multi-TeV Dark Matter Detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.10843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.10843v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that Milky Way white dwarfs are excellent targets for dark matter (DM) detection. Using Fermi and H.E.S.S. Galactic center gamma-ray data, we investigate sensitivity to DM annihilating within white dwarfs into long-lived or boosted mediators and producing detectable gamma rays. Depending on the Galactic DM distribution, we set new constraints on the spin-independent scattering cross section down to $10^{-45}-10^{-41}$ cm$^2$ in the sub-GeV DM mass range, which is multiple orders of magnitude stronger than existing limits. For a generalized NFW DM profile, we find that our white dwarf constraints exceed spin-independent direct detection limits across most of the sub-GeV to multi-TeV DM mass range, achieving sensitivities as low as about $10^{-46}$ cm$^2$. In addition, we improve earlier versions of the DM capture calculation in white dwarfs, by including the low-temperature distribution of nuclei when the white dwarf approaches crystallization. This yields smaller capture rates than previously calculated by a factor of a few up to two orders of magnitude, depending on white dwarf size and the astrophysical system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.10843v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2024/03/042</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Javier F. Acevedo, Rebecca K. Leane, Lillian Santos-Olmsted</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From QFT to Boltzmann: Freeze-in in the presence of oscillating condensates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.08272</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.08272v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Scalar dark matter (DM), and axions in particular, have an irreducible abundance of particles produced by freeze-in due to portal interactions with the Standard Model plasma in the early Universe. In addition, vacuum misalignment and other mechanisms can lead to the presence of a cold, oscillating condensate. Therefore, generically, the evolution of the DM in both forms, condensate and particles, needs to be studied simultaneously. In non-equilibrium quantum field theory, the condensate and particles are described by one- and two-point functions, respectively. The fundamental coupled equations of motion (EoMs) of these objects are non-local. To simplify the EoMs and bring them into a familiar form for relic abundance calculations, we perform a Markovianization process for a quasi-harmonically oscillating homogeneous condensate, leading to local EoMs for the particle distribution function and the envelope function of condensate oscillation. This reduces the dynamics to a pair of coupled Boltzmann equations, and we derive explicitly the form of the collision operators for all particle and condensate interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.08272v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP02(2024)122</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 02 (2024) 122</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Yuan Ai, Ankit Beniwal, Angelo Maggi, David J. E. Marsh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The impact of CP-violating phases on DM observables in the cpMSSM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.08814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.08814v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we examine the effect of adding CP-violating phases to the pMSSM on the Dark-Matter (DM) direct-detection cross sections, the velocity-weighted annihilation cross section, and the DM relic density. We show that $\varphi_{M_2}$ and $\varphi_{\mu}$, the phases of the wino and higgsino mass parameters, are sufficiently constrained by electron electric-dipole-moment (EDM) measurements such that the allowed values of these phases are too small to influence these DM observables. Conversely, the phase of the bino-mass parameter $\varphi_{M_1}$ and the phases associated with the trilinear couplings, $\varphi_{A^t}$, $\varphi_{A^b}$, and $\varphi_{A^\tau}$, are barely constrained by EDM experiments. We find that these cpMSSM phases can have an important impact on the mentioned DM observables. This especially concerns pMSSM points that lie on the boundary of exclusion, as observables can be affected by cpMSSM phases to the extent that they are either pushed into the observable region, or outside the excluded region.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.08814v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Melissa van Beekveld, Wim Beenakker, Jochem Kip, Marrit Schutten, Dirren van Vlijmen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The ground states and first radial excitations of the vector tetraquark states with explicit P-waves via the QCD sum rules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04145v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we choose the diquark-antidiquark type four-quark currents with an explicit P-wave between the diquark and antidiquark pairs to study the ground states and first radial excitations of the hidden-charm tetraquark states with the quantum numbers $J^{PC}=1^{--}$. And we obtain the lowest vector tetraquark masses and make possible assignments of the existing $Y$ states. There indeed exists a hidden-charm tetraquark state with the $J^{PC}=1^{--}$ at the energy about $4.75\,\rm{GeV}$ as the first radial excitation to account for the BESIII data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04145v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhi-Gang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resonances in $D^0\to\pi^+\pi^-\ell^+\ell^-$ and sensitivity to New Physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09502v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The study of processes involving the weak decays of the charm quark offers unique possibilities to test the Standard Model from the up-type sector and to probe different New Physics scenarios. In here we focus on the rare decays $D^0\to\pi^+\pi^-\ell^+\ell^-$. The effectiveness of the Glashow-Iliopoulos-Maiani mechanism in charm results in a series of observables that serve as null tests of the Standard Model. Simultaneously, the dominant Standard Model contribution to such decays comes from long-distance dynamics. Following previous literature we describe this with the mediation of resonances. Motivated by recent experimental results on analogous semileptonic decays we investigate the effect of the $S$-wave of the pion pair by considering the scalar resonance $f_0(500)$. The experimental mass distributions and angular observables are described well with our model and there is a significant improvement on the agreement when accounting for $f_0(500)$, which amounts to around 20\% of the total branching ratio. Furthermore, we propose and estimate the size of a series of additional observables to be measured, which can help probe the $S$-wave and act as complementary null tests of the Standard Model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09502v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eleftheria Solomonidi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the Higgs Boson Decay into a Photon and a Neutrino Pair</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.16239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.16239v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present new calculations of the leading-order one-loop amplitude and the decay rate for $H\to \nu \bar{\nu} \gamma$ within the standard model, employing reduction to a set of basic Passarino-Veltman functions resulting in more concise expressions compared to prior works. Our result for the total decay rate is $\Gamma(H\to \nu\bar{\nu} \gamma)=1.33\,\text{keV}$, in close agreement with the narrow width approximation (NWA) for the intermediate Z boson. A comparison with previous results available in the literature is also provided. We evaluate the differential decay rate with respect to the energy of the photon and find that the non-resonant contributions from box diagrams beyond the NWA notably affect the kinematic region associated with high-energy photons, where the intermediate Z boson is offshell. This suggests potential implications for searches of dark sector mediators, particularly in future lepton collider experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.16239v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aliaksei Kachanovich, Ivan Ni\v{s}and\v{z}i\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for signatures of new physics in $B \to K \, \nu \, \overline{\nu}$ to distinguish between Dirac and Majorana neutrinos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17341</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17341v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We conduct a model-independent analysis of the distinct signatures of various generic new physics possibilities in the decay $B \to K \, \nu \, \overline{\nu}$ by analyzing the branching ratio as well as the missing mass-square distribution. Considering the final neutrinos to be of the same flavor with non-zero mass, we discuss the new physics contributions for both Dirac and Majorana neutrino possibilities. In our study, we utilize the analytical relations among form factors in semi-leptonic $B \to K$ transitions, which are consistent with current lattice QCD predictions to a very high numerical accuracy. We provide constraints on different new physics parameters, taking into account the recent measurement of $B^+ \to K^+ \, \nu \, \overline{\nu}$ branching ratio by the Belle-II collaboration. In future, if the missing mass-square distribution for $B^+ \to K^+ \, \nu \, \overline{\nu}$ decay gets reported by Belle-II with analysis of more events than their present data set, one can not only investigate possible new physics effects in these decays, but also probe the Dirac/Majorana nature of the neutrinos using quantum statistics, since a difference between the two cases is known to exist in the presence of non-standard neutrino interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17341v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. S. Kim, Dibyakrupa Sahoo, K. N. Vishnudath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complexified spinor fields in operator form</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.13106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.13106v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The formalism of quantum field theory in operator form, based on the anti self-adjoint operators of the imaginary coordinate and momentum and the self-adjoint operators of the real coordinate, momentum, energy and time, is used in considerations of the spinor fields and related topics. The unitary representation of the Lorentz boosts in the spin-orbital space is given. The operators that mirror-reflect the spin are introduced and then used in discussion of the spin parity. The conclusion that the spin is odd is used in the analyze of the parity violation in the cobalt-60 beta decay and it is found that the parity is not broken. The explanation why there are only right-handed antineutrinos and left-handed neutrinos is offered on the basis of appropriate treatment of the influence of spin on momentum. The inversion of time is treated within the framework of the operators of time and energy and this symmetry is represented in a way that respects the Schr\"odinger equation and this is done by the Wick rotations of involved operators and vectors of the complexified formalism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.13106v2</guid>
      <category>physics.gen-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Slobodan Prvanovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$B \to D^*\ell\nu_\ell$ semileptonic form factors from lattice QCD with M\"obius domain-wall quarks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.05657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.05657v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We calculate the form factors for the $B \to D^*\ell\nu_\ell$ decay in 2+1 flavor lattice QCD. For all quark flavors, we employ the M\"obius domain-wall action, which preserves chiral symmetry to a good precision. Our gauge ensembles are generated at three lattice cutoffs $a^{-1} \sim 2.5$, 3.6 and 4.5 GeV with pion masses as low as $M_\pi \sim 230$ MeV. The physical lattice size $L$ satisfies the condition $M_\pi L \geq 4$ to control finite volume effects (FVEs), while we simulate a smaller size at the smallest $M_\pi$ to directly examine FVEs. The bottom quark masses are chosen in a range from the physical charm quark mass to $0.7 a^{-1}$ to control discretization effects. We extrapolate the form factors to the continuum limit and physical quark masses based on heavy meson chiral perturbation theory at next-to-leading order. Then the recoil parameter dependence is parametrized using a model independent form leading to our estimate of the decay rate ratio between the tau ($\ell = \tau$) and light lepton ($\ell = e,\mu$) channels $R(D^*) = 0.252(22)$ in the Standard Model. A simultaneous fit with recent data from the Belle experiment yields $|V_{cb}| = 39.19(91)\times 10^{-3}$, which is consistent with previous exclusive determinations, and shows good consistency in the kinematical distribution of the differential decay rate between the lattice and experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.05657v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.074503</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Y. Aoki (JLQCD Collaboration), B. Colquhoun (JLQCD Collaboration), H. Fukaya (JLQCD Collaboration), S. Hashimoto (JLQCD Collaboration), T. Kaneko (JLQCD Collaboration), R. Kellermann (JLQCD Collaboration), J. Koponen (JLQCD Collaboration), E. Kou (JLQCD Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Binary mergers in strong gravity background of Kerr black hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.06894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.06894v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Binary-black-hole (BBH) mergers can take place close to a supermassive black hole (SMBH) while being in a bound orbit around the SMBH. In this paper, we study such bound triple systems and show that including the strong gravity effects of describing the SMBH with a Kerr metric can significantly modify the dynamics, as compared to a Newtonian point particle description of the SMBH. We extract the dynamics of the system, using a quadrupole approximation to the tidal forces due to the SMBH. We exhibit how the gyroscope precession is built into this dynamics, and find the secular Hamiltonian by both averaging over the inner and outer orbits, the latter being the orbit of the BBH around the SMBH. We study the long-time-scale dynamics, including the periastron precession and GW radiation-reaction of the binary system, finding that the strong gravity effects of the SMBH can enhance the von Zeipel-Lidov-Kozai mechanism, resulting in more cycles, higher maximum eccentricity, and thereby a shorter merger time, particularly when the binary is close to, or at, the innermost stable orbit of the SMBH. We end with an analysis of the peak frequency of the GW emission from the binary system, highlighting possible observable signatures in the LISA and ET frequency bands.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.06894v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae1093</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, Volume 531, Issue 1, June 2024, Pages 1884-1904</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Filippo Camilloni, Gianluca Grignani, Troels Harmark, Marta Orselli, Daniele Pica</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New mixed inhomogeneous phase in vortical gluon plasma: first-principle results from rotating SU(3) lattice gauge theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.13994</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.13994v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Using first-principle numerical simulations, we find a new spatially inhomogeneous phase in rigidly rotating $N_c = 3$ gluon plasma. This mixed phase simultaneously possesses both confining and deconfining phases in thermal equilibrium. Unexpectedly, the local critical temperature of the phase transition at the rotation axis does not depend on the angular frequency within a few percent accuracy. Even more surprisingly, an analytic continuation of our results to the domain of real angular frequencies indicates a profound breaking of the Tolman-Ehrenfest law in the vicinity of the phase transition, with the confining (deconfining) phase appearing far (near) the rotation axis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.13994v3</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor V. Braguta, Maxim N. Chernodub, Artem A. Roenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativistic meson-exchange currents in semi-inclusive lepton scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.13640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.13640v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We assess the impact of two-particle--two-hole excitations on the semi-inclusive electron scattering process (e,e'p) using a fully relativistic nuclear model calculation that precisely incorporates antisymmetrization. The calculation encompasses all contributions involving the exchange of a single pion and the excitation of a Delta resonance. Our results are compared with (e,e'p) data on carbon at kinematics where two-nucleon emission dominates. This work represents an essential step towards the microscopic computation of the two-particle--two-hole contribution to semi-inclusive neutrino reactions, crucial in the analysis of neutrino oscillation experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.13640v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valerio Belocchi, Maria Benedetta Barbaro, Arturo De Pace, Marco Martini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay Between Neutrino Kicks and Hydrodynamic Kicks of Neutron Stars and Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.13817</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.13817v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Neutron stars (NSs) are observed with high space velocities and elliptical orbits in binaries. The magnitude of these effects points to natal kicks that originate from asymmetries during the supernova (SN) explosions. Using a growing set of long-time 3D SN simulations with the Prometheus-Vertex code, we explore the interplay of NS kicks that are induced by asymmetric neutrino emission and by asymmetric mass ejection. Anisotropic neutrino emission can arise from a large-amplitude dipolar convection asymmetry inside the proto-NS (PNS) termed LESA (Lepton-number Emission Self-sustained Asymmetry) and from aspherical accretion downflows around the PNS, which can lead to anisotropic neutrino emission (absorption) with a neutrino-induced NS kick roughly opposite to (aligned with) the kick by asymmetric mass ejection. In massive progenitors hydrodynamic kicks can reach up to more than 1300 km/s, whereas our calculated neutrino kicks reach (55-140) km/s (estimated upper bounds of (170-265) km/s) and only about (10-50) km/s, if LESA is the main cause of asymmetric neutrino emission. Therefore hydrodynamic NS kicks dominate in explosions of high-mass progenitors, whereas LESA-induced neutrino kicks dominate for NSs born in low-energy SNe of the lowest-mass progenitors, when these explode nearly spherically. Our models suggest that the Crab pulsar with its velocity of about 160 km/s, if born in the low-energy explosion of a low-mass, single-star progenitor, should have received a hydrodynamic kick in a considerably asymmetric explosion. Black holes, if formed by the collapse of short-lived PNSs and solely kicked by anisotropic neutrino emission, obtain velocities of only some km/s.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.13817v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. -Thomas Janka (MPI Astrophysics, Garching), Daniel Kresse (MPI Astrophysics, Garching, TUM School of Natural Sciences, Garching)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Updated observational constraints on spatially-flat and non-flat $\Lambda$CDM and XCDM cosmological models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19194v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study 6 LCDM models, with 4 allowing for non-flat geometry and 3 allowing for a non-unity lensing consistency parameter $A_L$. We also study 6 XCDM models with a dynamical dark energy density X-fluid with equation of state $w$. For the non-flat models we use two different primordial power spectra, Planck $P(q)$ and new $P(q)$. These models are tested against: Planck 2018 CMB power spectra (P18) and lensing potential power spectrum (lensing), and an updated compilation of BAO, SNIa, $H(z)$, and $f\sigma_8$ data [non-CMB data]. P18 data favor closed geometry for the LCDM and XCDM models and $w&lt;-1$ (phantom-like dark energy) for the XCDM models while non-CMB data favor open geometry for the LCDM models and closed geometry and $w&gt;-1$ (quintessence-like dark energy) for the XCDM models. When P18 and non-CMB data are jointly analyzed there is weak evidence for open geometry and moderate evidence for quintessence-like dark energy. Regardless of data used, $A_L&gt;1$ is always favored. The XCDM model constraints obtained from CMB data and from non-CMB data are incompatible, ruling out the 3 $A_L = 1$ XCDM models at $&gt; 3\sigma$. In the 9 models not ruled out, for the P18+lensing+non-CMB data set we find little deviation from flat geometry and moderate deviation from $w=-1$. In all 6 non-flat models (not ruled out), open geometry is mildly favored, and in all 3 XCDM+$A_L$ models (not ruled out) quintessence-like dark energy is moderately favored (by at most $1.6 \sigma$). In the $A_L = 1$ non-flat LCDM cases, we find for P18+lensing+non-CMB data $\Omega_k = 0.0009 \pm 0.0017$ [$0.0008 \pm 0.0017$] for the Planck [new] $P(q)$ model, favoring open geometry. The flat LCDM model remains the simplest (largely) observationally-consistent cosmological model. Our cosmological parameter constraints obtained for the flat LCDM model (and other models) are the most restrictive results to date (Abridged).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19194v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Javier de Cruz Perez, Chan-Gyung Park, Bharat Ratra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trace conservation laws in $T^2/Z_m$ orbifold gauge theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19411v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Gauge theory compactified on an orbifold is defined by gauge symmetry, matter contents, and boundary conditions. There are equivalence classes (ECs), each of which consists of physically equivalent boundary conditions. We propose the powerful necessary conditions, trace conservation laws (TCLs), which achieve a sufficient classification of ECs in U(N) and SU(N) gauge theories on $T^2/Z_m$ orbifolds $(m=2,3,4,6)$. The TCLs yield the equivalent relations between the diagonal boundary conditions without relying on an explicit form of gauge transformations. The TCLs also show the existence of off-diagonal ECs, which consist only of off-diagonal matrices, on $T^2/Z_4$ and $T^2/Z_6$. After the sufficient classification, the exact numbers of ECs are obtained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19411v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/ptep/ptae082</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Kota Takeuchi, Tomohiro Inagaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MEET-U Project I: The key drivers of the preference for dynamic dark energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.03983</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.03983v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Joint analysis of the baryon acoustic oscillations (BAO) measurement by the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) first data release, Type Ia supernovae (SNe) of the Dark Energy Survey Year 5 (DES5YR) release and cosmic microwave background (CMB) data favors a quintom-like dynamic dark energy model over the standard Lambda cold dark matter ($\Lambda$CDM) model at $3.9\sigma$ level (Adame et al. 2024). We demonstrate that the preference for dynamic dark energy does not rely on the detailed modeling of CMB physics and remains at $3.2\sigma$ level when the full CMB likelihood is replaced by a CMB acoustic-oscillation angle ($\theta_\star$) prior and a baryon abundance ($\Omega_bh^2$) prior. By comparing the data with over $10^4$ $\Lambda$CDM-based simulations, we find that both DES5YR SNe and DESI BAO contribute significantly to the preference for dynamic dark energy. The preference for dynamic dark energy is unlikely (probability $\lesssim 0.02$) due to unknown systematics in DES5YR SNe and statistical fluctuations in DESI BAO, or vice versa.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.03983v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiqi Huang, Jianqi Liu, Jianfeng Mo, Yan Su, Junchao Wang, Yanhong Yao, Guangyao Yu, Zhengxin Zhu, Zhuoyang Li, Zhenjie Liu, Haitao Miao, Hui Tong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calo-VQ: Vector-Quantized Two-Stage Generative Model in Calorimeter Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.06605</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.06605v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a novel machine learning method developed for the fast simulation of calorimeter detector response, adapting vector-quantized variational autoencoder (VQ-VAE). Our model adopts a two-stage generation strategy: initially compressing geometry-aware calorimeter data into a discrete latent space, followed by the application of a sequence model to learn and generate the latent tokens. Extensive experimentation on the Calo-challenge dataset underscores the efficiency of our approach, showcasing a remarkable improvement in the generation speed compared with conventional method by a factor of 2000. Remarkably, our model achieves the generation of calorimeter showers within milliseconds. Furthermore, comprehensive quantitative evaluations across various metrics are performed to validate physics performance of generation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.06605v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qibin Liu, Chase Shimmin, Xiulong Liu, Eli Shlizerman, Shu Li, Shih-Chieh Hsu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Summary of CKM 2023 working group 5: Direct CP violation (DCPV) including $\phi_{3}/\gamma$ from $B\to DK$, DCPV effects, branching fractions and polarisation in charmless $B_{(s)}$ decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10261v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this contribution a summary of the activities of Working Group 5 (WG5) presented during the 12th International Workshop on the CKM Unitarity Triangle (CKM2023) is reported. This includes new results on $\phi_{3}/\gamma$ measurements using $B\to DK$ decays, search for $CP$ violation using charmless $B$ decays and $b$-Baryon decays, measurement of branching ratios in hadronic $B$ to charm decays, and theory of three-body nonleptonic $B$ decays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10261v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Melissa Cruz Torres, Tobias Huber, Minakshi Nayak, Gilberto Tetlalmatzi-Xolocotzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
