<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph</link>
    <description>hep-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 01:41:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Jet veto resummation for STXS $H+$1-jet bins at aNNLL$'$+NNLO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13301v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Measurements of Higgs boson processes by the ATLAS and CMS experiments at the LHC use Simplified Template Cross Sections (STXS) as a common framework for the combination of measurements in different decay channels and their further interpretation, e.g. to measure Higgs couplings. The different Higgs production processes are measured in predefined kinematic regions -- the STXS bins -- requiring precise theory predictions for each individual bin. In gluon-fusion Higgs production a main division is into 0-jet, 1-jet, and $\geq 2$-jet bins, which are further subdivided in bins of the Higgs transverse momentum $p_T^H$. Requiring a fixed number of jets induces logarithms $\ln p_T^{\mathrm{cut}}/Q$ in the cross section where $p_T^{\mathrm{cut}}$ is the jet-$p_T$ threshold and $Q\sim p_T^H\sim m_H$ the hard-interaction scale. These jet-veto logarithms can be resummed to all orders in perturbation theory to achieve the highest possible perturbative precision. We provide state-of-the art predictions for the $p_T^H$ spectrum in exclusive $H+$1-jet production and the corresponding $H+$1-jet STXS bins in the kinematic regime $p_T^{\mathrm{cut}} \ll p_T^H\sim m_H$. We carry out the resummation at NNLL$'$ accuracy, using theory nuisance parameters to account for the few unknown ingredients at this order, and match to full NNLO. We revisit the jet-veto factorization for this process and find that it requires refactorizing the total soft function into a global and soft-collinear contribution in order to fully account for logarithms of the signal jet radius. The leading nonglobal logarithms are also included, though they are numerically small for the region of phenomenological interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13301v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro Cal, Matthew A. Lim, Darren J. Scott, Frank J. Tackmann, Wouter J. Waalewijn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Field-Theory Action for the Constructive Standard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13303v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a field-theory framework in which fields transform under the little group, rather than the Lorentz group, specific to each particle type. By utilizing these fields, along with spinor products and the x factor, we construct a field-theory action that naturally reproduces the vertices of the Constructive Standard Model (CSM). This approach eliminates unphysical components, significantly reduces the degrees of freedom compared to traditional field theory, and offers deeper insights into the power of constructive amplitudes. Our action is momentum-conserving, Lorentz-invariant, Hermitian, and non-local. We also discuss this as a framework for developing new constructive field theories, discussing their essential properties and potential applicability in renormalization theory and non-perturbative calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13303v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Neil Christensen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phenomenology of Electroweak Portal Dark Showers: High Energy Direct Probes and Low Energy Complementarity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13304v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the phenomenology of a dark QCD sector interacting with the Standard Model (SM) via the electroweak (EW) portals. The portal interactions allow SM bosons, such as $Z$ and $h$, or additional bosons that mix with them, to decay into dark quarks, producing dark showers. The light dark mesons are expected to be long-lived particles (LLPs), as their decays back to the SM states through the EW-portal interactions typically have macroscopic decay lengths. We focus on dark shower events initiated by various bosons at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC). The most prominent signal is the displaced decay of GeV-scale dark pions as LLPs. Current limits on dark shower signals at LHC detectors are recast from public data in a model-independent manner. Future limits in the high-luminosity phase and proposed auxiliary detectors are also projected. Additionally, we study the flavor-changing neutral current (FCNC) $B$ decays into dark pions, obtaining both current and projected constraints at the LHC and other facilities. These constraints can be combined for specific models, which are illustrated in two EW-portal benchmarks: one with the heavy doublet fermion mediation and another with the $Z^\prime$ mediator including a mass mixing. The collider reach shows significant potential to probe the parameter space unconstrained by EW precision tests, highlighting the necessity of dedicated LLP search strategies and facilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13304v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hsin-Chia Cheng, Xu-Hui Jiang, Lingfeng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultraheavy Dark Matter and WIMPs Production aided by Primordial Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13313v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The unitary bound restricts thermal relics to be lighter than $100$ TeV. This work investigates the production of ultraheavy dark matter and WIMPs in the presence of primordial black holes. Firstly, we describe how Hawking evaporation can produce ultraheavy dark matter with masses above $10^{12}$ GeV in radiation and matter-domination eras. Later, we assess how primordial black holes that induce a non-standard cosmology impact the predicted relic density of a thermal relic and explore the interplay between them, considering the restrictions arising from entropy injection due to the evaporation of primordial black holes. Considering a concrete B-L model, where the dark matter is a Dirac particle, we obtain the correct relic density for various freeze-out scenarios and show that a dark matter particle can nicely reproduce the correct relic density in agreement with current limits with masses above the $10$ TeV scale. Hence, this work strengthens the continuous search for heavy dark matter particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13313v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giorgio Arcadi, Manfred Lindner, Jacinto P. Neto, Farinaldo S. Queiroz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for Stochastic GW Signal as a Complementary Approach to Multi-Higgs Productions at the Hadron Colliders to Probe Dimension Six Operator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13326v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We have considered an effective field theory framework in which the Standard Model is extended by a non-renormalizable dimension six operator ($\frac{1}{\Lambda^2}(H^{\dagger}H)^3$) respecting the symmetries of the Standard Model. Such an operator can affect the dynamics of Higgs field and the electroweak phase transition. Presence of such term modifies the triple Higgs coupling which is already under the lens from di-Higgs searches in various channels at the LHC. Constraint on the scale parameter $\Lambda$ is obtained from the di-Higgs data at the LHC Run II. Additionally, such dimension six terms will give rise to additional couplings which will affect tri-Higgs and four-Higgs productions at future high energy, high luminosity hadron colliders. The shape of the scalar potential also gets modified due to such higher dimensional term composed of Higgs field. It is worthwhile to study the impact of such higher-dimensional operators at suitable gravitational wave (GW) interferometry experiments since GW astronomy has become a good probe for new physics searches. Bounds obtained on the scale parameter $\Lambda$ from the allowed first-order electroweak phase transition is $480 \lesssim \Lambda \lesssim 590$~GeV. On the other hand, di-Higgs results from the LHC Run II put a lower bound on $\Lambda \gtrsim 340$~GeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13326v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dilruba Gazi, Abhi Mukherjee, Saurabh Niyogi, Sujoy Poddar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence of Dark Energy Prior to its Discovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13427v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This is a review and statistical analysis of the evidence supporting the existence of a cosmological constant in the early 1990s, before its discovery made with distant supernovae in 1998. The earlier evidence was derived from newly precise measurements of the Universe, including its mass density, the Hubble constant, the age of the oldest stars, the filamentary large-scale structure, and the anisotropy of the cosmic microwave background. These measurements created tension for models assuming the cosmological constant was zero. This tension was alleviated by several insightful papers published before 1996, which proposed a cosmological constant that increased the expansion rate. Statistical analysis here shows that the probability of the cosmological constant being zero was demonstrably less than a few percent. Some models identified a best-fit value close to the modern estimate of Omega_Lambda ~ 0.7.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13427v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Geoffrey W. Marcy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Power corrections to quasi-distribution amplitudes of a heavy meson</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13486v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It has been recently demonstrated that lightcone distribution amplitudes (LCDAs) for a heavy meson, defined in the heavy quark limit, can be extracted by simulating quasi-distribution amplitudes on the lattice with a large meson momentum $P^z$. This extraction involves a two-step procedure. In the first-step, the quasi-distribution amplitudes are matched onto the QCD LCDAs in the large $P^z$ limit. In the second step, the QCD LCDAs are matched onto the desired LCDAs defined in HQET. In this work, we present the $m_H^{2n}/(P^z)^{2n}$ and $\Lambda_\text{QCD}^2/(P^z)^2$ corrections in the first step with $m_H$ being the heavy meson mass. To account for $m_H^{2n}/(P^z)^{2n}$ corrections, we employ two methods: the moment relation that can provide mass corrections to all orders, and a leading-twist projector that gives the leading-order mass corrections. For the $\Lambda_\text{QCD}^2/(P^z)^2$ corrections, we employ a renormalon model that addresses the renormalon ambiguity stemming from the divergence of the perturbative series. We adopt two parametrizations for QCD LCDAs to conduct a numerical analysis. The results suggest that these corrections are typically smaller than 20\% in most regions, and should be included in a precision analysis. These findings will serve as a valuable guide for future studies on heavy meson LCDAs, particularly in the context of Lattice QCD, where accounting for such corrections is crucial for improving the accuracy and reliability of the results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13486v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao Han, Wei Wang, Jia-Lu Zhang, Jian-Hui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\rho$ meson transverse momentum dependent parton distributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13569</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13569v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, light-front wave functions (LFWFs) of the $\rho$ meson are evaluated in the framework of Nambu--Jona-Lasinio model using the proper time regularization scheme. The transverse momentum dependent parton distributions (TMDs) of the $\rho$ meson are derived from the overlap representations of the LFWFs. We investigate the $\bm{k}_{\perp}$-weighted moments and the $x$-dependent average transverse momentum $\langle k_{\perp}^n(x)\rangle_{\alpha}$ of $\rho$ meson TMDs, $\langle k_{\perp}^n(x)\rangle_{\alpha}$ shows the typical transverse momenta of quark TMDs in our model. Our findings indicate that the average transverse momenta of $\langle k_{\perp}(x)\rangle_{\alpha}$ fall within the range of $[0.3, 0.45]$ GeV, while $\langle k_{\perp}^2(x)\rangle_{\alpha}$ are in the region of $[0.15, 0.30]$ GeV. Our TMDs and parton distribution function (PDFs) satisfy the positive constraints very well. The spin densities inside the $\rho$ meson in the transverse momentum space are investigated, the results show that the quark and the target polarized in the longitudinal or in the transverse directions the distribution are axially symmetric. The unpolarized symmetric distribution when the quark is longitudinally polarized and the target is transversely polarized, or on the contrary exhibit the dipolar distortions. The results of TMDs from LFWFs and the covariant approach are compared. The results show that TMDs from LFWFs satisfy the positive constraints better than TMDs from the covariant approach. The $x$-moments of $\rho$ meson PDFs, $\langle x\rangle_{g_L}$ is larger than the covariant approach. In addition, the quark spin densities of the $\rho$ meson, particularly the $\rho_{\uparrow \downarrow}\left(k_x,k_y\right)=f-\frac{1}{3}f_{LL}-g_L$ in the covariant approach it is negative, but $\rho_{\uparrow \downarrow}\left(k_x,k_y\right)$ from LFWFs is positive.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13569v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin-Li Zhang, Jun Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vacuum (in)stability in 2HDMS vs N2HDM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13592v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we examine the criteria for vacuum stability in two models with extended scalar sectors namely, the N2HDM and the 2HDMS and make a detailed comparison between the two. For the purpose of demonstration, we choose a scenario which can accommodate the recently observed 95 GeV excess in both models. We further explore the impact of the measurement of the Yukawa couplings, the gauge boson couplings and most importantly the trilinear self-couplings of the scalars, in distinguishing the vacuum structure in both models. We further investigate the constraints from vacuum stability on the 2HDMS scenario that accommodates a viable dark matter candidate and compare it with the N2HDM case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13592v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jayita Lahiri, Gudrid Moortgat-Pick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-dependent dark matter interactions at loop-level in Ar and Xe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13664v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Xenon and argon are the two noble gases used in tonne scale dark matter direct detection experiments. We compare the detection capability of both target elements for interactions due to a pseudoscalar mediator including loop-level contributions to the cross section. At tree-level this type of interaction depends on the nuclear spin and would thus not be detectable in argon-based detectors, since Ar has spin zero. However, at the loop-level the same interaction yields spin-independent contributions that would be detectable in an argon target and are not negligible with respect to the tree-level interactions in xenon, because these are momentum suppressed. In fact, the loop-level contributions are also important for xenon-based experiments at low recoil energies, which could change their discovery reach for this interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13664v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nassim Bozorgnia, Muping Chen, Graciela B. Gelmini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study of the semileptonic decays $\Upsilon(1S)\to B_{(c)}\ell\bar{\nu}_\ell$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13776v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the exclusive semileptonic decays $\Upsilon(1S)\to B_{(c)}\ell\bar{\nu}_\ell$, where $\ell = e,\mu,\tau$. The relevant hadronic form factors are calculated using the Covariant Confined Quark Model developed previously by our group. We predict the branching fractions $\mathcal{B}(\Upsilon(1S)\to B_{(c)}\ell\bar{\nu}_\ell)$ to be of the order of $10^{-13}$ and $10^{-10}$ for the case of $B$ and $B_c$, respectively. Our predictions agree well with other theoretical calculations. We also consider the effects of possible New Physics in the case of $\Upsilon(1S)\to B_c\tau\bar{\nu}_\tau$. We show that the branching fraction of this decay can be enhanced by an order of magnitude using the constraints from the $B\to D^{(*)}\ell\bar{\nu}_\ell$ and $B_c\to J/\psi\ell \bar{\nu}_\ell$ experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13776v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chien-Thang Tran, Mikhail A. Ivanov, Pietro Santorelli, Hai-Cat Tran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The ground states of hidden-charm tetraquarks and their radial excitations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13826v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inspired by the great progresses in the observations of charmonium-like states in recent years, we perform a systematic analysis about the ground states and the first radially excited states of $qc\bar{q}\bar{c}$($q$=$u/d$ and $s$) tetraquark systems. Their mass spectra, root mean square(r.m.s.) radii and radial density distributions are investigated within the framework of relativized quark model. By comparing numerical results with experimental data, some potential candidates for hidden-charm tetraquark states are suggested. For the $qc\bar{q}\bar{c}$($q$=$u/d$) system, theoretical predictions support assigning $Z_{c}(3900)$ and $Z(4430)$ as the ground and the first radially excited states with their quantum numbers to be $J^{PC}=1^{+-}$. Besides, the broad structure $Z_{c}(4200)$ may be also a partner of $Z_{c}(3900)$, and arise from the higher state with $J^{PC}=1^{+-}$. Theoretical predictions also indicate that the possible assignments for $X(3930)$, $X(4050)$ and $X(4250)$ are low lying $0^{++}$ states. As for the $sc\bar{s}\bar{c}$ system, $X(4140)$ and $X(4274)$ structures can be interpreted as this type of tetraquark states with $J^{PC}=1^{++}$. In addition, $X(4350)$ can also be described as a $sc\bar{s}\bar{c}$ tetraquark with $J^{PC}=0^{++}$. With regard to $qc\bar{s}\bar{c}$($q$=$u/d$) system, we find two potential candidates for this type of tetraquark, which are $Z_{cs}(4000)$ and $Z_{cs}(4220)$ structures. The masses of these two structures are in agreement with theoretical predictions of the $1^{+}$ state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13826v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guo-Liang Yu, Zhen-Yu Li, Zhi-Gang Wang, Bin WU, Ze Zhou, Jie Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theoretical results for top-pair and top+$W$ production</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13870v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: I present theoretical results for top-pair production as well as for the associated production of top quarks with $W$ bosons. Soft-gluon corrections from resummation are calculated through approximate N$^3$LO and added to fixed-order QCD results, and electroweak corrections are included at NLO. Top-quark transverse-momentum and rapidity distributions are also presented. In all cases the higher-order corrections are large, they reduce the scale dependence, and they improve agreement with recent data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13870v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikolaos Kidonakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tetraquark nature of the $a_0(980)$ meson in hadronic $D$ decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13942</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13942v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The internal structure of the light scalar meson $a_0(980)$ is explored in the three-body $D$ decays of $D\to a_0(980)P\to P_1P_2P$ through the intermediate state $a_0(980)$, where $P$ denotes a pseudoscalar meson. The quasi-two-body $D\to a_0(980)^+P$ decays are governed by the external $W$-emission diagram in which $a_0(980)^+$ is emitted. The predicted branching fractions in the $q\bar q$ model of $a_0(980)$ are too small by one to two orders of magnitude compared to experiment as the amplitude is suppressed by the smallness of the $a_0(980)^+$ decay constant, while those for $D^+\to a_0(980)^0 P$ and $D^0\to a_0(980)^{-}P$ are usually too large. These discrepancies can be resolved provided that $a_0(980)$ is a tetraquark state. In this case, there exist two additional $T$-like topological amplitudes, denoted by $\overline{T}$ and $\tilde T$ which readily account for the discrepancies. An important implication of the tetraquark model is that the $D_s^+\to a_0(980)^+\pi^0+a_0(980)^0\pi^+$ decay is not a purely $W$-annihilation process as in the diquark model of $a_0(980)$; it receives dominant contributions from $\overline{T}$ newly noticed in this work. Therefore, measurements of $(D,D_s^+)\to a_0(980)P$ decays lend strong support to the tetraquark picture of $a_0(980)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13942v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hai-Yang Cheng, Cheng-Wei Chiang, Fanrong Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Associated charged Higgs production within the 2HDM: $e^-e^+$ versus $\mu^-\mu^+$ colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13952</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13952v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Our goal is to investigate the charged Higgs phenomenology in the framework of 2HDM at the upcoming $e^+e^-$ and muon colliders. We are primarily concerned with the associated production processes with a fermion pair: $\ell^+ \ell^- \to \tau^+ \nu_{\tau }H^-$ and $\ell^+ \ell^- \to t \bar{b} H^-$, as well as with the W boson and a neutral Higgs boson: $\ell^+ \ell^- \to W^\pm H^\mp S$ ($S=h,\,H,\, A$) and $\ell^+ \ell^- \to W^\pm H^\mp Z$. We first update the results for $e^+e^- \to \{ \tau^+ \nu_{\tau }H^-\ , \ t \bar{b} H^-\}$ and then discuss our findings for $e^+e^- \to \{ W^\pm H^\mp S\}$ for various center of mass energies 500 GeV, 1 TeV, 1.5 TeV and 3 TeV. In the case of muon collider, we show that the new s-channel and t-channel diagrams can increase the cross sections by virtue of their Yukawa couplings. We systematically compare our results for the muon collider with those obtained at the International Linear (ILC) and Compact Linear (CLIC) colliders. We select benchmark points and conduct signal-background analyses, incorporating detector simulations. For a 3 TeV muon collider, our results show an exclusion region at the 2$\sigma$ level and a discovery region at the 5$\sigma$ level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13952v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brahim Ait Ouazghour, Abdesslam Arhrib, Kingman Cheung, Es-said Ghourmin, Larbi Rahili</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spontaneous CP violation, sterile neutrino dark matter, and leptogenesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13990v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We constructed a model for spontaneous CP symmetry breaking in five-dimensional space-time that solves the strong CP problem. To explain the nature of dark matter and the baryon asymmetry of the universe, three right-handed neutrinos and $U(1)_{B-L}$ gauge interaction are introduced in the bulk, in addition to the field contents of the Bento-Branco-Parada model. The wave-function profiles in the fifth dimension can suppress dangerous operators allowed by symmetries, and the scale of spontaneous CP symmetry breaking can be sufficiently large to be consistent with thermal leptogenesis. In this model, the lightest right-handed neutrino serves as dark matter with a mass of $\mathcal{O}(10)$ keV. This small mass and the necessarily small mixing are explained by the exponentially localized wave-function in the fifth dimension due to a bulk mass term. The correct relic abundance is achieved thanks to the $U(1)_{B-L}$ gauge interaction. The other heavy right-handed neutrinos explain the baryon asymmetry of the universe through leptogenesis, with the required CP violating phases generated by interactions involving heavy leptons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13990v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanjin Jiang, Norimi Yokozaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The effect of vorticity on the dynamical magnetic fields in heavy-ion collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14077</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14077v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic fields in heavy-ion collisions are pivotal and subject to diverse factors. In this study, we quantitatively investigate the impact of fluid vorticity on the evolution of magnetic fields in the 20-50\% centrality class in Au+Au collisions, with collision energies of $\sqrt{s_{NN}}=(7.7, 14.5, 19.6, 27, 39, 62.4, 200)$ GeV. Our results indicate that fluid vorticity leads to a delay in the evolution of the magnetic field, in which this effect becomes more pronounced as the collision energy decreases. Additionally, we have calculated the mean magnetic field values on the freeze-out hypersurface for various collision energies. Our simulation results align with the values inferred from experimental data of $\bar{\Lambda}-\Lambda$, within the error margins.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14077v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anping Huang, Xiang-Yu Wu, Mei Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predictions for $h_c$ and $h_b$ productions at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14133v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The production cross sections of $h_c$ and $h_b$, the ${}^1P_1$ quarkonia can be predicted in Non-Relativistic Quantum Chromodynamics (NRQCD) using heavy quark symmetry. Our study includes predictions for both the integrated cross-section and the transverse momentum ($p_T$) distribution of $h_c$ ($h_b$) production at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC), using the decay process $h_c (h_b) \rightarrow \eta_c (\eta_b) + \gamma$, $\eta_c (\eta_b) \rightarrow p \overline{p}$. We demonstrate substaintial discrepancies in integrated cross-section and the $p_T$ distribution of ${}^1P_1$ quarkonia production at the LHC using Colour-Singlet Model (CSM), NRQCD and modified NRQCD. Measuring these resonances at the LHC could discriminate between these models, thereby offering further insights into the dynamics of quarkonium production.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14133v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sudhansu S. Biswal, Sushree S. Mishra, Monalisa Mohanty, K. Sridhar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dirac Neutrinos and Dark Matter within a Minimal Discrete Symmetry Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14166</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14166v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a model that extends the standard model by incorporating the simplest discrete symmetry groups, $Z_2$ and $Z_3$. This model introduces vector-like leptons and a real scalar singlet. Based on this framework, we generate Dirac neutrino masses and explain the neutrino normal mass ordering. The model also aligns well with current oscillation data regarding theoretical values of the leptonic mixing angles and the Dirac CP-violating phase. Furthermore, it predicts that the atmospheric mixing angle falls in the higher octant and proposes a viable dark matter candidate. We discuss the phenomenological aspects and future testability of the model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14166v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yakefu Reyimuaji, Murat Abdughani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GALPs! Composite heavy axion-like Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14245</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14245v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a novel class of Dark Matter (DM) candidates in the form of a heavy composite Axion-Like Particle (ALP) with highly suppressed electromagnetic interactions, being stable even for masses exceeding the GeV scale. We argue that such a composite ALP emerges as a bound state -- the dark glueball -- due to confinement in a pure Yang-Mills dark sector. In a minimal ultraviolet complete QCD-like model, cosmological production of dark gluons as well as photons occurs via heavy fermion annihilation which effectively reheats both the dark and visible sectors setting up their temperature scales. Furthermore, effective interactions between glueballs and photons, resembling those of standard ALPs, are radiatively generated by heavy fermion loops. Consequently, DM glueballs interacting with photons are dubbed `Glueball ALPs' (GALPs). We uncover novel phenomenology of GALPs focusing on their unique astrophysical and cosmological signatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14245v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierluca Carenza, Roman Pasechnik, Zhi-Wei Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinetic Mixing, Proton Decay and Gravitational Waves in SO(10)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14350v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an $SO(10)$ model in which a dimension five operator induces kinetic mixing at the GUT scale between the abelian subgroups $U(1)_{B-L}$ and $U(1)_R$. We discuss in this framework gauge coupling unification and proton decay, as well as the appearance of superheavy quasistable strings with $G\mu \sim 10^{-8} - 10^{-5}$, where $\mu$ denotes the dimensionless string tension parameter. We use Bayesian analysis to show that for $G\mu$ values $\sim 4 \times 10^{-7} - 10^{-5}$, the gravitational wave spectrum emitted from the quasistable strings is in good agreement with the recent pulsar timing array data. Corresponding to $G \mu$ values $\sim 10^{-8} - 2 \times 10^{-7}$, proton decay is expected to occur at a rate accessible in the Hyper-Kamiokande experiment. Finally, we present the gravitational wave spectrum emitted by effectively stable strings with $G\mu\approx 10^{-8}$ that have experienced a certain amount of inflation. This can be tested with future detectors in the $\mu$Hz frequency range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14350v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rinku Maji, Qaisar Shafi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovering an invisible Z' at the muon collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14396v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show in this letter how a heavy $(\mathcal{O}(TeV))$ invisible $Z'$ gauge boson that will practically be out of reach of the Large Hadron Collider (LHC), can be discovered at the future muon collider. The new force carrier has a relatively stronger coupling with the beyond standard model (BSM) sector, while its interaction with the SM fields is much weaker. This weaker coupling is induced through mixing mechanisms, specifically via gauge kinetic mixing and the $Z-Z'$ mixing. We consider a scenario where the new gauge boson decays mostly to charge-neutral long-lived particles and/or dark matter (DM). We show how producing and detecting this heavier invisible $Z'$, that will be beyond the reach of even the very high luminosity LHC, becomes possible if it is produced in association with an energetic photon at the future muon collider. The on-shell production of the $Z'$ will lead to a peak in the photon energy distribution, following the so-called radiative return phenomena and can lead to the accurate determination of the $Z'$ mass and its interaction with SM particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14396v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anjan Kumar Barik, Santosh Kumar Rai, Aviral Srivastava</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Theoretical Study of $\pi^+p\to pa_0^+\phi$ Reaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14424v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the production of hyperon resonances in the $\pi^+p\to pa_0^+\phi$ reaction within an effective Lagrangian approach. The model includes the production of $\Delta(1940)$ and $\Delta(1920)$ in the intermediate state excited by the $\rho$ and $p$ exchanges between the initial proton and $\pi$ meson. Due to the large contribution of $\rho$ exchange in $\Delta(1940)$ production, $\Delta(1940)$ is found a significant contribution near the threshold in this reaction. We provide total and differential cross section predictions for the reation and discuss the possible influence of model parameters, off-shell effects and branching ratios for $\Delta(1940)\to pa_0$ and $\Delta(1920)\to pa_0$ decays, which will be useful in future experimental studies. This reaction can provide a platform for studying the features of $\Delta(1940)$ resonance, especially the coupling to $pa_0$ channel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14424v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aojia Xu, Ruitian Li, Xuan Luo, Hao Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativistic spin hydrodynamics with momentum and spin-dependent relaxation time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14462v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using the extended relaxation time approximation (ERTA) along with the theory of semi-classical spin, we develop a framework of relativistic dissipative spin hydrodynamics such that the relaxation time can depend on the momenta and spin of the constituent spin-1/2 particles. We also consider a general definition of the fluid four-velocity allowing the theory to be valid in a general frame and matching conditions. Consequently, we construct the frame-invariant bulk, shear, particle diffusion, and spin transport coefficients, showing that the evolution of fluid remains unaffected by spin in the limit of small polarization as was the case where the relaxation time was independent of spin or momentum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14462v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samapan Bhadury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CMB limits on decaying dark matter beyond the ionization threshold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13305</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13305v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The temperature and polarization anisotropies of the cosmic microwave background (CMB) have been used to set constraints on decaying dark matter models down to keV masses. In this work, we extend these limits down to the sub-keV mass range. Using principal component analysis, we estimate the lower bound on the decay lifetime for a basis of different dark matter masses and Standard Model final states, from which the bound on an arbitrary model can be calculated. We validate our principal component analysis using Markov chain Monte Carlo methods and Planck 2018 data. We perform a separate analysis for models decaying into photons below the hydrogen ionization threshold. We demonstrate that for these models, the effect of energy deposition can be captured approximately by a single parameter, but the redshift dependence of the effect is very different from higher-energy injections; in particular, the perturbations to CMB anisotropies are more sensitive to energy deposited around the time of recombination.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13305v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Clara Xu, Wenzer Qin, Tracy R. Slatyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutral pion polarizabilities from four-point functions in lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13388</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13388v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report a proof-of-principle lattice QCD simulation of the electric and magnetic polarizabilities for a neutral pion in the four-point function method. The results are based on the same quenched Wilson ensembles on a $24^3\times 48$ lattice at $\beta=6.0$ with pion mass from 1100 to 370 MeV previously used for a charged pion. For electric polarizability, the results are largely consistent with those from the background field method and ChPT. In contrast, there are significant differences for magnetic polarizability among the four-point function method, the background field method, and ChPT. The situation points to the potentially important role of disconnected diagrams for a neutral pion. We elucidate a transparent quark decomposition in the four-point function method that can be used to shed light on the issue.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13388v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Frank X. Lee, Walter Wilcox, Andrei Alexandru, Chris Culver, Shayan Nadeem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the conformal limit of a QED-inspired model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13923v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A conformal invariant QED-inspired model is solved for a general covariant linear gauge using the Dyson-Schwinger equations for the propagators assuming a pure vector like interaction. The leading corrections to the asymptotic solutions and the exponents, that characterize the corrections to each of the two fermion propagator functions, are computed as a function of the coupling and gauge fixing parameter $\xi$. For the scalar component of the fermion propagator our findings generalizes for linear covariant gauges previous results found in the literature and reproduce the outcome of the perturbative analysis of quenched QED in the Landau gauge. Our solution for the exponent associated with vector component of the fermion propagator is new and, in the weak coupling regime, agrees with the estimation based on the perturbative analysis of quenched QED. Of the two critical exponents describing the conformal limit of the vector interaction, one of them is, in QED, associated with the regime where chiral symmetry is broken dynamically, which demands one mass scale, namely the Miransky scaling. A second mass scale has to be introduced at larger coupling constants and is associated with a change on the nature of the fermion wave function. This provides one example, that it is possible to find two interwoven cycles in Quantum Field Theory, albeit in a truncated framework, as it is known in the quantum few-body problem in the limit of a zero-range interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13923v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>O Oliveira, T Frederico, W de Paula</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-invertible flavor symmetries in magnetized extra dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13984v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We discuss non-invertible symmetries in toroidal compactifications of higher dimensional Yang-Mills theory with magnetic fluxes, which can be regarded as an effective action of type IIB string theory with magnetized D-branes. Specifically, we derive fusion rules of discrete isometry operators, which are invariant under the $\mathbb{Z}_N$ orbifold twist. It turns out that degenerate chiral zero-modes non-trivially transform under the non-invertible symmetries in the context of quantum mechanics. Hence, non-invertible symmetries correspond to flavor symmetries of chiral zero modes and determine their flavor structure. We explicitly show the representations and selection rules of chiral zero modes on their wave functions. These zero modes may correspond to generations of quarks and leptons in four-dimensional low-energy effective field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13984v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tatsuo Kobayashi, Hajime Otsuka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Flea on the Elephant: tidal Love numbers in subsolar primordial black hole searches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14207v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Detecting subsolar objects in black hole binary mergers is considered a smoking gun signature of primordial black holes. Their supposedly vanishing tidal Love number is generically thought to help distinguish them from other subsolar and more deformable compact objects, such as neutron stars. We show that a large and detectable Love number of primordial black holes can be generated in the presence of even small disturbances of the system, thus potentially jeopardizing their discovery. However, such small perturbations are not tightly bound and are therefore disrupted before the mergers. We show that they leave a characteristic signature in the gravitational waveform that could be observed with current and future gravitational wave detectors. Thus, they may still hint towards the primordial nature of the black holes in the merger. Finally, we demonstrate that disregarding possible environmental effects in the matched-filter search for subsolar gravitational wave events can lead to a decreased sensitivity in the detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14207v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valerio De Luca, Gabriele Franciolini, Antonio Riotto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tidal deformability of black holes surrounded by thin accretion disks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14208v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The tidal Love numbers of self-gravitating compact objects describe their response to external tidal perturbations, such as those from a companion in a binary system, offering valuable insights into their internal structure. For static tidal fields, asymptotically flat black holes in vacuum exhibit vanishing Love numbers in general relativity, even though this property is sensitive to the presence of an external environment. In this work we study the tidal deformability of black holes surrounded by thin accretion disks, showing that the Love numbers could be large enough to mask any effect of modified gravity and to intrinsically limit tidal tests of black-hole mimickers. Furthermore, we investigate the measurability of the tidal parameters with next-generation gravitational wave experiments, like LISA and Einstein Telescope. Our findings suggest that these parameters could be measured with high precision, providing a powerful tool to probe the environment around coalescing binary systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14208v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrico Cannizzaro, Valerio De Luca, Paolo Pani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmology and nuclear-physics implications of a subsolar gravitational-wave event</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14287</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14287v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Detecting a compact subsolar object would have profound implications in physics, the reach of which depends on the nature of the object. Here we explore such consequences for a putative subsolar-mass gravitational wave event detected by the LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA Collaboration. We forecast that the nature of a subsolar binary (made of light neutron stars, primordial black holes, or more exotic compact objects) can be inferred with a great statistical confidence level already during the ongoing fourth observing run, based on the large tidal deformability effects on the signal. The detection of a primordial black hole would have implications for cosmology and dark matter scenarios, while the measurement of the tidal deformability of a subsolar neutron star could rule out or confirm the existence of strange stars made of quarks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14287v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Crescimbeni, Gabriele Franciolini, Paolo Pani, Massimo Vaglio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The asymptotic Hopf Algebra of Feynman Integrals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14304v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The method of regions is an approach for developing asymptotic expansions of Feynman Integrals. We focus on expansions in Euclidean signature, where the method of regions can also be formulated as an expansion by subgraph. We show that for such expansions valid around small/large masses and momenta the graph combinatorial operations can be formulated in terms of what we call the asymptotic Hopf algebra. This Hopf algebra is closely related to the motic Hopf algebra underlying the $R^*$ operation, an extension of Bogoliubov's $R$ operation, to subtract both IR and UV divergences of Feynman integrals in the Euclidean. We focus mostly on the leading power, for which the Hopf algebra formulation is simpler. We uncover a close connection between Bogoliubov's $R$ operation in the Connes-Kreimer formulation and the remainder $\mathcal{R}$ of the series expansion, whose Hopf algebraic structure is identically formalised in the corresponding group of characters. While in the Connes-Kreimer formulation the UV counterterm is formalised in terms of a twisted antipode, we show that in the expansion by subgraph a similar role is played by the integrand Taylor operator. To discuss the structure of higher power expansions we introduce a novel Hopf monoid formulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14304v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mrigankamauli Chakraborty, Franz Herzog</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nucleon Transversity from lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14370v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We give a brief overview of recent progress in lattice QCD simulations that is enabling precision studies of the three-dimensional structure of the nucleon. We present results on nucleon charges and second Mellin moments of parton distribution functions and generalized parton distributions, highlighting results obtained at the continuum limit using only gauge ensembles simulated with physical quark masses. The tensor charge and transversity moments are determined with controlled systematics and used to extract nucleon transverse density distributions. We also discuss progress towards the direct evaluation of generalized parton distributions in lattice QCD and the impact they are having on phenomenology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14370v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Constantia Alexandrou (Univ. of Cyprus)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collisional and Radiative Energy Loss in Small Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14426v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present an energy loss model which includes small system size corrections to both the radiative and elastic energy loss. Our model is used to compute the nuclear modification factor $R_{AB}$ of light and heavy flavor hadrons, averaged over realistic collision geometries for central and peripheral $A+A$ and central $p / d / {}^3\text{He} + A$ collisions at LHC and RHIC. We find that the predicted suppression in small systems is almost entirely due to elastic energy loss. Our results are keenly sensitive to the crossover between elastic energy loss calculated with Hard Thermal Loop propagators and vacuum propagators, respectively, which leads to a large theoretical uncertainty. We find that the $R_{AB}$ is largely insensitive to the form of the elastic energy loss distribution - Gaussian or Poisson - surprisingly so in small systems where the central limit theorem is inapplicable. We present an expansion of the $R_{AB}$ in terms of the moments of the energy loss probability distribution, which allows for a rigorous understanding of the dependence of the $R_{AB}$ on the underlying energy loss distribution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14426v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Coleridge Faraday, W. A. Horowitz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Partitioning statistics of a correlated few-electron droplet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14458v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Emergence of universal collective behaviour from interactions in a sufficiently large group of elementary constituents is a fundamental scientific paradigm. In physics, correlations in fluctuating microscopic observables can provide key information about collective states of matter such as deconfined quark-gluon plasma in heavy-ion collisions or expanding quantum degenerate gases. Two-particle correlations in mesoscopic colliders have provided smoking-gun evidence on the nature of exotic electronic excitations such as fractional charges, levitons and anyon statistics. Yet the gap between two-particle collisions and the emergence of collectivity as the number of interacting particles grows is hard to address at the microscopic level. Here, we demonstrate all-body correlations in the partitioning of up to $N = 5$ electron droplets driven by a moving potential well through a Y-junction in a semiconductor. We show that the measured multivariate cumulants (of order $k = 2$ to $N$) of the electron droplet are accurately described by $k$-spin correlation functions of an effective Ising model below the N\'eel temperature and can be interpreted as a Coulomb liquid in the thermodynamic limit. Finite size scaling of high-order correlation functions provides otherwise inaccessible fingerprints of emerging order. Our demonstration of emergence in a simple correlated electron collider opens a new way to study engineered states of matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14458v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jashwanth Shaju, Elina Pavlovska, Ralfs Suba, Junliang Wang, Seddik Ouacel, Thomas Vasselon, Matteo Aluffi, Lucas Mazzella, Clement Geffroy, Arne Ludwig, Andreas D. Wieck, Matias Urdampiletta, Christopher B\"auerle, Vyacheslavs Kashcheyevs, Hermann Sellier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study lepton flavor violation $B^0\rightarrow{{l_i}^{\pm}{l_j}^{\mp}}$ within the Mass Insertion Approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16595</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.16595v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study lepton flavor violating (LFV) decays $B^0\rightarrow{{l_i}^{\pm}{l_j}^{\mp}}$ ($B^0\rightarrow e{\mu}$, $B^0\rightarrow e{\tau}$ and $B^0\rightarrow {\mu}{\tau}$) in the $U(1)_X$SSM (SSM is acronym for the supersymmetric standard model), which is the $U(1)_X$ extension of the minimal supersymmetric standard model (MSSM). The local gauge group of $U(1)_X$SSM is $SU(3)_C\times SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y \times U(1)_X$. These processes ($B^0\rightarrow e{\mu}$, $B^0\rightarrow e{\tau}$ and $B^0\rightarrow {\mu}{\tau}$) are strictly forbidden in the standard model (SM), but these LFV decays are a signal of new physics (NP). We use the Mass Insertion Approximation (MIA) to find sensitive parameters that directly influence the result of the branching ratio of LFV decay $B_d\rightarrow{{l_i}^{\pm}{l_j}^{\mp}}$. Combined with the latest experimental results, we analyze the relationship between different sensitive parameters and the branching ratios of the three processes. According to the numerical analysis, these elements are very restricted from the non observation of CLFV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.16595v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi-Tong Wang, Jiao Ma, Xing-Yu Han, Xin-Xin Long, Tong-Tong Wang, Hai-Bin Zhang, Shu-Min Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Practical Dirac Majorana confusion theorem: Issues and Applicability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.05654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.05654v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We inspect the model-independent study of practical Dirac Majorana confusion theorem (pDMCT) -- a wide spread belief that the difference between Dirac and Majorana neutrinos via any kinematical observable would be practically impossible to determine because of the difference only being proportional to the square of neutrino mass -- in context of processes that have at least a neutrino antineutrino pair in their final state. We scrutinize the domain of applicability of pDMCT and also highlight those aspects that are often misunderstood. We try to clarify some of the frequently used concepts that are used to assert pDMCT as a generic feature irrespective of the process, or observable, such as the existence of any analytic continuity between Dirac and Majorana neutrinos in the limit mass(neutrino) -&gt; 0. In summary, we illustrate that pDMCT is not any fundamental property of neutrinos, instead, it is a phenomenological feature of neutrino non-observation, depending on models and processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.05654v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-023-12156-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>European Physics Journal C (2023) 83:972</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>C. S. Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kicking it Off(-shell) with Direct Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.17175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.17175v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Off-shell effects in large LHC backgrounds are crucial for precision predictions and, at the same time, challenging to simulate. We present a novel method to transform high-dimensional distributions based on a diffusion neural network and use it to generate a process with off-shell kinematics from the much simpler on-shell one. Applied to a toy example of top pair production at LO we show how our method generates off-shell configurations fast and precisely, while reproducing even challenging on-shell features.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.17175v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anja Butter, Tomas Jezo, Michael Klasen, Mathias Kuschick, Sofia Palacios Schweitzer, Tilman Plehn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovering Heavy Neutral Leptons with the Higgs Boson</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.18033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.18033v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the dominant signatures that arise in Higgs physics at colliders when extending the Standard Model (SM) with a Yukawa interaction to heavy neutral leptons (HNL), while suppressing their mixing to active neutrinos. We focus on the production of HNLs from Higgs bosons that subsequently decay via the Higgs to SM fermions to determine the experimental reach at the LHC detectors and far detectors such as FASER and MATHUSLA. We also determine the impact of precision Higgs constraints on beyond-SM parameters in this scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.18033v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicol\'as Bernal, Kuldeep Deka, Marta Losada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Quality/Cosmology Tension for a Post-Inflation QCD Axion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.07650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.07650v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is difficult to construct a post-inflation QCD axion model that solves the axion quality problem (and hence the Strong CP problem) without introducing a cosmological disaster. In a post-inflation axion model, the axion field value is randomized during the Peccei-Quinn phase transition, and axion domain walls form at the QCD phase transition. We emphasize that the gauge equivalence of all minima of the axion potential (i.e., domain wall number one) is insufficient to solve the cosmological domain wall problem. The axion string on which a domain wall ends must exist as an individual object (as opposed to a multi-string state), and it must be produced in the early universe. These conditions are often not satisfied in concrete models. Post-inflation axion models also face a potential problem from fractionally charged relics; solving this problem often leads to low-energy Landau poles for Standard Model gauge couplings, reintroducing the quality problem. We study several examples, finding that models that solve the quality problem face cosmological problems, and vice versa. This is not a no-go theorem; nonetheless, we argue that it is much more difficult than generally appreciated to find a viable post-inflation QCD axion model. Successful examples may have a nonstandard cosmological history (e.g., multiple types of cosmic axion strings of different tensions), undermining the widespread expectation that the post-inflation QCD axion scenario predicts a unique mass for axion dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.07650v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP07(2024)227</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP07(2024)227</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Qianshu Lu, Matthew Reece, Zhiquan Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higgs photon associated production in a Two Higgs Doublet Type-II Seesaw Model at future electron-positron colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07722v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the one-loop prediction for the single production of a SM-like Higgs boson in association with a photon in electron-positron collisions in the context of the two Higgs doublet type-II seesaw model ($2HDMcT$). We explore to what extent the new scalars in the $2HDMcT$ spectrum affect its production cross-section, the ratio $R_{\gamma h_1}$ as well as the signal strengths $R_{\gamma Z}$ and $R_{\gamma \gamma}$ when $h_1$ is identified with the observed $SM$ Higgs boson within the $2HDMcT$ delimited parameter space. More specifically, we focus on $e^+e^- \to h_1\gamma$ process at one-loop, and analyzed how it evolves under a full set of theoretical constraints and the available experimental data, including $B\to X_s\gamma$ limit at 95$\%$ C.L. Our analysis shows that these observables are strongly dependent on the parameters of the model, especially the mixing angel $\alpha_1$, the potential parameters $\lambda_{7}$, $\lambda_{9}$, the trilinear Higgs couplings, with a noticeable sensitivity to $\alpha_1$. We found that $\sigma (e^+e^- \to h_1\gamma)$ can significantly be enhanced up to $8.1\,\,\times 10^{-2}$ fb, thus exceeding the Standard Model prediction. Additionally, as a byproduct, we also observed that $R_{\gamma h_1}$ is entirely correlated with both the $h_1\to\gamma\gamma$ and $h_1\to\gamma Z$ signal strengths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07722v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Ait Ouazghour, M. Chabab, K. Goure</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Five-flavour scheme predictions for $t\bar{t}b\bar{b}$ at next-to-leading order accuracy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14419</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14419v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We compute top quark pair production in association with a bottom quark pair at the LHC within the five-flavour scheme, matched to a parton shower, employing the FxFx merging scheme for $t\bar{t}+\textrm{jets}$ production with up to 2 jets at NLO accuracy. To enhance the selection efficiency for the events with $b$-jets within the inclusive five-flavour sample, we augment the generation probability of bottom quark flavours in the short-distance event generation. Our analysis reveals some differences from NLO predictions within the four-flavour scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14419v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-024-13128-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur.Phys.J.C 84 (2024) 7, 763</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Rikkert Frederix, Tetiana Moskalets</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Missing Energy plus Jet in the SMEFT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17063v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the production of dineutrinos in proton-proton collisions, with large missing transverse energy and an energetic jet as the experimental signature. Recasting a search from the ATLAS collaboration we work out constraints on semileptonic four-fermion operators, gluon and electroweak dipole operators and $Z$-penguins in the SMEFT. All but the $Z$-penguin operators experience energy-enhancement. Constraints on gluon dipole operators are the strongest, probing new physics up to 14 TeV, and improve over existing ones from collider studies. Limits on FCNC four-fermion operators are competitive with Drell-Yan production of dileptons, and improve on those for tau final states. For left-handed $|\Delta s|=|\Delta d|=1$ and right-handed $|\Delta c|=|\Delta u|=1$ transitions these are the best available limits, also considering rare kaon and charm decays. We estimate improvements for the $3000 \;\mathrm{fb}^{-1}$ High Luminosity Large Hadron Collider.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17063v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gudrun Hiller, Daniel Wendler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Purely flavored leptogenesis from a sudden mass gain of right-handed neutrinos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18630v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we would like to point out that in the scenario that the right-handed neutrinos suddenly gain some masses much larger than the temperature of the Universe at that time so that the washout effects for the lepton asymmetry generated from their decays can be neglected safely, the purely flavored leptogenesis scenario (in which the total CP asymmetries for the decays of the right-handed neutrinos are vanishing and the successful leptogenesis is realized by virtue of the flavor non-universality of the washout effects) cannot work in the usual way any more. For this problem, we put forward that the flavor non-universality of the conversion efficiencies from the flavored lepton asymmetries to the baryon asymmetry via the sphaleron processes may play a crucial role. And we will study if the requisite baryon asymmetry can be successfully reproduced from such a mechanism in the scenarios that the right-handed neutrino masses are hierarchical and nearly degenerate, respectively. A detailed study shows that this mechanism can be viable in both these two scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18630v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhen-hua Zhao, Jing Zhang, Xiang-Yi Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dimension-eight Operator Basis for Universal Standard Model Effective Field Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03720v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the basis of dimension-eight operators associated with universal theories. We first derive a complete list of independent dimension-eight operators formed with the Standard Model bosonic fields characteristic of such universal new physics scenarios. Without imposing C or P symmetries the basis contains 175 operators -- that is, the assumption of Universality reduces the number of independent SMEFT coefficients at dimension eight from 44807 to 175. 89 of the 175 universal operators are included in the general dimension-eight operator basis in the literature. The 86 additional operators involve higher derivatives of the Standard Model bosonic fields and can be rotated in favor of operators involving fermions using the Standard Model equations of motion for the bosonic fields. By doing so we obtain the allowed fermionic operators generated in this class of models which we map into the corresponding 86 independent combinations of operators in the dimension-eight basis of Ref. arXiv:2005.00059</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03720v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.033003</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Tyler Corbett, Jay Desai, O. J. P. Eboli, M. C. Gonzalez-Garcia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved Thermal Resummation for Multi-Field Potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12439v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The resummation of large thermal corrections to the effective potential is mandatory for the accurate prediction of phase transitions. We discuss the accuracy of different prescriptions to perform this resummation at the one- and two-loop level and point out conceptual issues that appear when using a high-temperature expansion at the two-loop level. Moreover, we show how a particular prescription called partial dressing, which does not rely on a high-temperature expansion, consistently avoids these issues. We introduce a novel technique to apply this resummation method to the case of multiple mixing fields. Our approach significantly extends the range of applicability of the partial dressing prescription, making it suitable for phenomenological studies of beyond the Standard Model extensions of the Higgs sector.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12439v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henning Bahl, Marcela Carena, Aurora Ireland, Carlos E. M. Wagner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calculable neutrino Dirac mass matrix and one-loop $\bar \theta$ in the minimal left-right symmetric model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16740v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We revisit the contribution to the strong CP parameter $\bar \theta$ from leptonic CP violation at one-loop level in the minimal left-right symmetric model in the case of generalized parity as the left-right symmetry. The Hermitian neutrino Dirac mass matrix $M_D$ can be calculated using the light and heavy neutrino masses and mixings. We propose a parametrization of the right-handed neutrino mixing matrix $V_R$ and construct the heavy neutrino mass that maintains the Hermiticity of $M_D$. We further apply it to evaluate the one-loop $\bar\theta$, denoted as $\bar \theta_{loop}$, as a function of the sterile neutrino masses for explicit examples of $V_R$. By requiring the magnitude of $\bar \theta_{loop}\lesssim 10^{-10}$, we derive the upper limits on the sterile neutrino masses, which are within reach of direct searches at the Large Hadron Collider and neutrinoless double beta decay experiments. Furthermore, our parametrization is pertinent for other phenomenological investigations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16740v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gang Li, Ding-Yi Luo, Xiang Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Divergences in the effective loop interaction of the Chern-Simons bosons with leptons. The unitary gauge case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00164v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the extension of the Standard Model with Chern-Simons type interaction. There is a new vector massive boson (Chern-Simons bosons) in this extension. Using only three-particle dimension-4 interaction of the Chern-Simons bosons with vector bosons of the SM, we consider effective loop interaction of a new vector boson with leptons. We consider the renormalizability of this loop interaction and conclude that for the case of computation of loop diagrams in the unitary gauge, we can not get rid of the divergences in the effective interaction of the Chern-Simons bosons with leptons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00164v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuliia Borysenkova, Volodymyr Gorkavenko, Ivan Hrynchak, Oleksandr Khasai, Mariia Tsarenkova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confronting MSSM flat direction inflation with Planck/BICEP data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00918</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00918v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the scenario of inflection point inflation where a flat direction of the minimal supersymmetric standard model (MSSM) is identified with the inflaton. Specifically, we consider in full generality the cases where a MSSM flat direction is lifted by a higher-dimensional superpotential whose dimension is n = 4, 5, 6, 7, 9. We confront the inflection point inflation scenarios with various n with the Planck and BICEP data, and thereby constrain the soft SUSY breaking mass and the coefficient of the higher-dimensional operator that lifts the flat direction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00918v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naoyuki Haba, Yasuhiro Shimizu, Yoshihiro Tanabe, Toshifumi Yamada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the fermion-field nontopological solitons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01227</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01227v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Nontopological fermionic solitons exist across a diverse range of particle physics models and have rich cosmological implications. This study establishes a general framework for calculating fermionic soliton profiles under arbitrary scalar potentials, utilizing relativistic mean field theory to accurately depict the interaction between the fermion condensate and the background scalar field. Within this framework, the conventional fermion bound states are revealed as a subset of fermionic solitons. In addition, we demonstrate how the analytical formulae in previous studies are derived as special cases of our algorithm, discussing the validity of such approximations. Furthermore, we explore the phenomenology of fermionic solitons, highlighting new formation mechanisms and evolution paths, and reconsidering the possibility of collapse into primordial black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01227v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ke-Pan Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electric dipole moments of charged leptons in models with pseudo-Dirac sterile fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01648</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01648v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we address the impact of a small lepton number violation on charged lepton electric dipole moments - EDMs. Low-scale seesaw models protected by lepton number symmetry and leading to pseudo-Dirac pairs in the neutrino heavy spectrum provide a natural explanation for the smallness of neutrino masses with potentially testable consequences. Among which, it was thought that the small mass gap in each pair of pseudo-Dirac neutrinos may induce important contribution to the charged lepton EDMs. Recently, it has been shown that the contribution from some of the Feynman diagrams to charged lepton EDMs exactly cancel by virtue of the Ward-Takahashi identity in quantum electrodynamics. We thus consider here the Standard Model minimally extended with pairs of pseudo-Dirac sterile fermions and derive the complete analytical formula at two loops for the charged lepton EDMs. In addition, we numerically evaluate the order of the predicted EDMs consistent with the experimental bounds and constraints such as neutrino oscillation data, charged lepton flavour violating processes, sterile neutrino direct searches, meson decays, sterile neutrino decays, and cosmological and astrophysical observations. We find that, in the minimal setup accommodating neutrino data (masses and mixings) with only two pseudo-Dirac pairs, the predicted electron EDM is $\mathcal{O}(10^{-36})~e\hspace{0.05cm}\mathrm{cm}$, at most, which is much smaller than the current experimental bound and even future sensitivity. Hopefully, the electron EDM might reach future sensitivity, once extra pseudo-Dirac neutrinos are taken into account. The analytical formulae we derive are generic to any model involving pseudo-Dirac pairs in the heavy neutrino spectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01648v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 08 (2024) 128</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Asmaa Abada, Takashi Toma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigations on the weak decays of $D\bar{B}$ molecules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04341</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04341v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The decays of exotic states discovered experimentally always proceed via the strong and electromagnetic interactions. Recently, a tetraquark state with the quark content $bc\bar{q}\bar{q}$ was predicted by Lattice QCD simulations. It is below the mass threshold of $D\bar{B}$, which can only decay via the weak interaction. In this work, based on the decay mechanism of $T_{cc}$ as a $DD^*$ molecule, we propose that the decays of the $bc\bar{q}\bar{q}$ tertaquark state as a $D\bar{B}$ molecule proceed via the Cabibbo-favored weak decays of the $\bar{B}$ or $D$ meson, accompanied by the tree-level decay modes and the triangle decay modes. Our results indicate that the branching fraction of the $D\bar{B}$ molecule decaying into $\pi^+ K^{-} \bar{B}^0$ is sizable, which is a good channel to observe the $D\bar{B}$ molecule in future experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04341v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ming-Zhu Liu, Li-Sheng Geng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking the Non-flow Contributions to the Elliptic Flow Parameter ($v_{_2}$) in Proton-Proton Collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.13981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.13981v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This manuscript reports on the elliptic flow parameter, $v_{_2}$, in proton-proton (p-p) collisions using PYTHIA8 event generator simulations. The typical Event Plane ($EP$) method $v_{_2}$($EP$) besides the algorithm used for the real data analysis has been adopted to measure the $v_{_2}$ of particles composed of different quark flavors. The $v_{_2}$ of the aforementioned particles was measured at the center-of-mass energy $\sqrt{s}$ = 200 GeV and $\sqrt{s}$ = 13 TeV. The pseudorapidity gap $|\eta|$ technique, theoretically defined as $|\eta| = |\eta_{_{particle}} - \eta_{_{EP}}|$, between the particle of interest and the soft particles, where $p_{_{T}}$ $\leq$ 2 GeV/c, used for the reaction plane determinations, have been implemented in the current measurements. The $v_{_2}^{\pi^{^\pm,}\pi^{^0}}$, $v_{_2}^{J/\psi,\Upsilon, K, D, B}$, and the $v_{_2}^{\gamma_{dir}}$ show similar pattern dependence on the transverse momentum for the same $|\eta|$, at both $\sqrt{s}$ = 200 GeV and $\sqrt{s}$ = 13 TeV. At each center-of-mass energy, the $v_{_2}^{\gamma_{dir}}$ $\le$ $v_{_2}^{J/\psi, \Upsilon, K, D, B}$ $\le$ $v_{_2}^{\pi^{^\pm,}\pi^{^0}}$ for similar $|\eta|$. The measured $v_{_2}$ shows slightly higher values at smaller $\sqrt{s}$ for particles of similar $|\eta|$, particularly at small $|\eta|$. The measured $v_{_2}$ for all particles shows systematic decreases with increasing the $|\eta|$ gaps as expected from the previous experimental results. Because PYTHIA8 simulations do not incorporate final state interactions, the $v_{_2}(EP)$ values reported here primarily reflect non-flow contributions. These contributions should be carefully subtracted from the signal in real data analysis that employs the same event plane determination algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.13981v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. I. Abdulhamid, A. M. Hamed, E. A. Osama, M. Rateb, N. K. Sadoun, F. H. Sawy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implications of neutrino species number and summed mass measurements in cosmological observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17760v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We confront measurable neutrino degrees of freedom $N_{\rm eff}$ and summed neutrino mass in the early universe to particle physics at the energy scale beyond the standard model (BSM), in particular including the issue of neutrino mass type distinction. The Majorana-type of massive neutrino is perfectly acceptable by Planck observations, while the Dirac-type neutrino may survive in a restricted class of models that suppresses extra right-handed contribution to $\Delta N_{\rm eff} = N_{\rm eff} - 3$ at a nearly indistinguishable level from the Majorana case. There is a chance that supersymmetry energy scale may be identified in supersymmetric extension of left-right symmetric model if improved $N_{\rm eff}$ measurements discover a finite value. Combined analysis of this quantity with the summed neutrino mass helps to determine the neutrino mass ordering pattern, if measurement accuracy of order, $60 \sim 80\,$meV, is achieved, as in CMB-S4.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17760v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. Sasao (Okayama U), M. Yoshimura (Okayama U), M. Tanaka (Osaka U)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Genuine lepton-flavor-universality-violating observables in the $\tau-\mu$ sector of $B \to (K,\,K^*) \ell \ell $ decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18488v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It was previously shown that unlike the ratios $R_K^{\mu e} \equiv R_K \equiv \Gamma(B \to K \mu^+ \mu^-)/\Gamma(B \to K e^+ e^-)$ and $R_{K^*}^{\mu e} \equiv R_{K^*} \equiv \Gamma(B \to K^* \mu^+ \mu^-)/\Gamma(B \to K^* e^+ e^-)$, the ratios $R_K^{\tau \mu}$ and $R_{K^*}^{\tau \mu}$ can deviate from their Standard Model (SM) predictions even with universal new physics couplings. This observation highlights the critical need to identify and establish genuine lepton flavor universality violating (LFUV) observables in the $\tau-\mu$ sector. This work embarks on establishing genuine LFUV ratio observables in $B \to K \ell \ell$ and $B \to K^* \ell \ell$ decays through comprehensive analysis of their angular distributions. We find that like $R_{K^*}^{\tau \mu}$, the ratios $R_{A_{FB}}^{\tau \mu}$ and $R_{f_L}^{\tau \mu}$ do not qualify as genuine LFUV observables, whereas the ratios of all optimized observables in $B \to K^* \ell \ell$ decays within the $\tau-\mu$ sector definitively do. In the case of $B \to K \ell \ell$ decays, similar to $R_K^{\tau \mu}$, the ratio $R_{F_H}$ is influenced by mass effects and therefore cannot be considered a genuine LFUV observable in the $\tau-\mu$ sector. However, the ratio $\Gamma_\tau(1-F_{H}^{\tau})/\Gamma_\mu(1-F_{H}^{\mu})$ stands as the sole genuine LFUV observable in $B \to K \ell \ell$ decays. Furthermore, by making use of new physics Lorentz structures which provide a better fit to the current $b \to s \ell \ell$ data as compared to the SM, we demonstrate how the non-genuine LFUV ratios $R_{A_{FB}}^{\tau \mu}$ and $R_{f_L}^{\tau \mu}$ can be employed to distinguish between framework with solely universal lepton couplings and those with both universal and non-universal couplings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18488v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashutosh Kumar Alok, Neetu Raj Singh Chundawat, Jitendra Kumar, Arindam Mandal, Umberto Tamponi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-Higgs Doublet Model Effective Field Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20511</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20511v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct the general two-Higgs doublet model effective field theory where the effects of additional new physics are parameterized by operators up to mass dimension-six. We further transform this effective theory to the Higgs basis and provide matching of the Wilson coefficients between the two descriptions. We illustrate the advantages of the Higgs basis which include the separation of operators that modify standard model couplings and masses from operators that contribute to scattering processes only, transparent correlations between scattering processes resulting from the same operator, and derivation of correlations between different operators in specific UV completions. For completeness, we also construct specific versions corresponding to four types of two-Higgs doublet models: type-I, -II, -X, and -Y, distinguished by $Z_2$ symmetries which restrict the couplings of the Higgs doublets to standard model fermions. Furthermore, we derive general vacuum and stability conditions of the scalar potential in the presence of higher-dimensional terms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20511v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.035026</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 035026 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Radovan Dermisek, Keith Hermanek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-two-body decays $B\to P f_0(500)\to P\pi^+\pi^-$ in the perturbative QCD approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02419</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02419v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the quasi-two-body decays $B\to P f_0(500)\to P\pi^+\pi^-$ [with $P=(\pi, K, \eta, \eta^{\prime})$] within framework of perturbative QCD (PQCD) factorization approach. With the help of $\pi$-$\pi$ distribution amplitude and scalar form factor $F_{\pi\pi}(\omega^2)$, we calculate the $CP$ averaged branching fraction and the $CP$ asymmetry for the quasi-two-body decays $B\to P f_0(500)\to P\pi^+\pi^-$. Taking the quasi-two-body decay $B^+ \to \pi^+ f_0(500) \to \pi^+ \pi^+ \pi^-$ as an explicit example, we present the behavior of differential branching fraction and direct $CP$ violation versus the $\pi$-$\pi$ invariant mass. The total branching fraction and direct $CP$ violation are $\mathcal{B}(B^+\to \pi^+ [\sigma\to]\pi^+\pi^-) = (1.78 \pm 0.41\pm 0.51) \times 10^{-6}$ and $\mathcal{A}_{CP}(B^+\to \pi^+ [\sigma\to]\pi^+\pi^-) = (29.8\pm 11.1\pm 13.0)\%$ respectively. Our results could be tested by further experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02419v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.036015</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 036015 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Wei Zhang, Bo-Yan Cui, Xing-Gang Wu, Hai-Bing Fu, Ya-Hui Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Axion Stars: Mass Functions and Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09499</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09499v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The QCD axion and axion-like particles, as leading dark matter candidates, can also have interesting implications for dark matter substructures if the Peccei-Quinn symmetry is broken after inflation. In such a scenario, axion perturbations on small scales will lead to the formation of axion miniclusters at matter-radiation equality, and subsequently the formation of axion stars. Such compact objects open new windows for indirect searches for axions. We compute the axion star mass function based on recent axion minicluster studies and Bose star simulations. Applying this mass function, we find post-inflation axion-like particles with masses $1.8 \times 10^{-21}~{\rm eV}&lt;m_a&lt; 3.3 \times 10^{-17}~{\rm eV}$ are constrained by the lack of dynamical heating of stars in ultrafaint dwarfs. We also find that current microlensing surveys are insensitive to QCD axion stars. While we focus on the gravitational detectability of axion stars, our result can be directly applied to other interesting signatures of axion stars, e.g. their decay to photons, that require as input the abundance, mass, and density distribution of axion stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09499v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jae Hyeok Chang, Patrick J. Fox, Huangyu Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Sector Tunneling Field Potentials for a Dark Big Bang</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05752</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05752v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: All of the significant evidence for dark matter observed thus far has been through its gravitational interactions. After 40 years of direct detection experiments, the parameter space for Weakly Interacting Massive Particles (WIMPs) as dark matter candidates is rapidly approaching the neutrino floor. In this light, we consider a dark sector that is strongly decoupled from the visible sector, interacting exclusively through gravity. In this model, proposed by Freese and Winkler (arXiv:2302.11579), dark matter can be produced through a first-order phase transition in the dark sector dubbed the Dark Big Bang. In this study we fully determine the allowed region of parameter space for the tunneling potential that leads to the realization of a Dark Big Bang and is consistent with all experimental bounds available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05752v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Richard Casey, Cosmin Ilie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$B_{s}^0\to K^0\overline{K}{}^0$ beyond the Standard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13506v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Within the Standard Model, the branching fraction of the $B_s\to K^0\overline{K}{}^0$ decay is related to other decay rates and CP asymmetries through the approximate $SU(3)$ flavor symmetry of the strong interactions. Three such relations were shown to be violated at a level of about $3\sigma$ each. By means of a systematic search for new physics explanations of these puzzles, we find that possible solutions are highly fine-tuned and rather implausible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13506v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuval Grossman, Yosef Nir, Matthias Neubert, Yogev Shpilman, Yehonatan Viernik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Studies of $Z$ boson decay into double $\Upsilon$ mesons at the NLO QCD accuracy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19418v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we employ the nonrelativistic QCD factorization to conduct a comprehensive examination of the $Z$ boson decay into a pair of $\Upsilon$ mesons, achieving accuracy at the next-to-leading-order (NLO) in $\alpha_s$. Our calculations demonstrate that the QED diagrams are indispensable in comparison to the pure QCD diagrams, and the implementation of QCD corrections markedly enhance the QCD results, whereas it substantially diminish the QED results. To ensure consistency with the experimental methodology, we have taken into account the feed-down transitions originating from higher excited states, which exhibit significant relevance. Combining all the contributions, we arrive at the NLO prediction of $\mathcal{B}_{Z \to \Upsilon(nS)+\Upsilon(mS)} \sim 10^{-11}$, which is notably lower than the upper limits set by CMS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19418v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cong Li, Ying-Zhao Jiang, Zhan Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One-loop impact factors for heavy quarkonium production: $S$-wave case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.06234v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: With the aim to extend the study of inclusive heavy quarkonium production at forward rapidities with the resummation of high partonic center-of-momentum-energy logarithms beyond Leading Logarithmic Approximation (LLA), the explicit analytic results for one-loop corrections to the following impact factors had been obtained: $\gamma R \to Q\bar{Q}\left[^1S_0^{[8]} \right]$, $g R \to Q\bar{Q}\left[^1S_0^{[1]} \right]$, $gR\to Q\bar{Q}\left[ ^1S_0^{[8]} \right]$ and $gR\to Q\bar{Q}\left[ ^3S_1^{[8]}\right]$, with $R$ being the Reggeized gluon and $Q$ is the heavy quark. The computation is done in the framework of Lipatov's gauge-invariant EFT for Multi-Regge processes in QCD with the tilted-Wilson-line regularisation for rapidity divergences. As expected, only single-logarithmic rapidity divergence proportional to the one-loop Regge trajectory of a gluon remains in the final result for impact-factors. Numerical comparison with Regge limits ($s/(-t) \gg 1$) of one-loop QCD amplitudes, described in the paper, provides a strong cross-check of obtained results. The relations of obtained results with other regularisation schemes for rapidity divergences used in low-$x$ physics, such as BFKL scheme, High-Energy Factorisation (HEF) scheme and shockwave scheme, are given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.06234v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxim Nefedov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Excluding Primordial Black Holes as Dark Matter Based on Solar System Ephemeris</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10799</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10799v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Current cosmological constraints allow primordial black holes (PBHs) to constitute dark matter in the mass range of $10^{18}$-$10^{22}$g. We show that a major portion of this logarithmic window can be ruled-out based on the Solar System ephemeris, given that the external mass enclosed within 50 au from the Sun did not change by more than $\sim 5\times 10^{-14}$ solar masses per year in recent decades.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10799v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abraham Loeb (Harvard)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lauricella hypergeometric functions, unipotent fundamental groups of the punctured Riemann sphere, and their motivic coactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.06603</link>
      <description>arXiv:1907.06603v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The goal of this paper is to raise the possibility that there exists a meaningful theory of `motives' associated to certain hypergeometric integrals, viewed as functions of their parameters. It goes beyond the classical theory of motives, but should be compatible with it. Such a theory would explain a recent and surprising conjecture arising in the context of scattering amplitudes for a motivic Galois group action on Gauss' ${}_2F_1$ hypergeometric function, which we prove in this paper by direct means. More generally, we consider Lauricella hypergeometric functions and show on the one hand how the coefficients in their Taylor expansions can be promoted, via the theory of motivic fundamental groups, to motivic multiple polylogarithms. The latter are periods of ordinary motives and admit an action of the usual motivic Galois group, which we call the `local' action. On the other hand, we define lifts of the full Lauricella functions as matrix coefficients in a Tannakian category of twisted cohomology, which inherit an action of the corresponding Tannaka group. We call this the `global' action. We prove that these two actions, local and global, are compatible with each other, even though they are defined in completely different ways. The main technical tool is to prove that metabelian quotients of generalised Drinfeld associators on the punctured Riemann sphere are hypergeometric functions. We also study single-valued versions of these hypergeometric functions, which may be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1907.06603v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/nmj.2022.27</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nagoya Math. J. 249 (2023), 148-220</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Francis Brown, Cl\'ement Dupont</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical anisotropy of primordial gravitational waves from generalized $\delta N$ formalism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.08497</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.08497v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this letter, we demonstrate how to use the generalized $\delta N$ formalism, which enables us to compute the evolution of all the large scale fluctuations, including gravitational waves, solely by solving the evolution of the background homogeneous Universe. Using the Noether charge density, we derive an analytic formula which describes the mapping between the fluctuations at the horizon crossing and the sourced gravitational waves at the end of inflation. This formula can apply also to an inflation model with an anisotropic background. Using this formula, we discuss the condition for the non-vanishing linear polarization and the qualitative difference between single- and multi-gauge field models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.08497v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takahiro Tanaka, Yuko Urakawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frame transformation and stable-causal hydrodynamic theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.16407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.16407v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, a connection has been indicated between the different existing formulations of relativistic hydrodynamic theories, which, in order to be causal and stable, (i) either requires `non-fluid' variables apart from velocity and temperature to be promoted to new degrees of freedom, or, (ii) needs to be in a generalized hydrodynamic frame other than those given by Landau or Eckart. The BDNK stress tensor (originally in a general frame) has been rewritten in the Landau frame using linearized all-order gradient-corrected redefinitions of the temperature and velocity fields. The redefinitions indicate that, while the BDNK formalism has a finite number of derivatives in the general frame, when written in the Landau frame, it either has an infinite number of derivatives, or one has to introduce MIS-like `non-fluid' variables by summing the infinite number of derivatives in the field redefinitions. There can be non-unique ways of performing these infinite-order summations. Finally, the dispersion relations and the corresponding spectra of these different systems of MIS type equations have been analyzed to check that the systems of equations presented here are indeed equivalent to the BDNK formalism, at least in the hydrodynamic regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.16407v3</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sayantani Bhattacharyya, Sukanya Mitra, Shuvayu Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weighing Milky Way and Andromeda in an expanding $\Lambda$CDM Universe: Decreasing the Local Group mass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.09546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.09546v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The dynamics of the Local Group (LG), especially the contribution of the Milky Way (MW) and Andromeda (M31) galaxies, is sensitive to the presence of dark energy. This work analyzes the evolution of the LG by considering it as a two-body problem in a homogeneous and isotropic expanding spacetime in a full $\Lambda$ cold dark matter $(\Lambda$CDM) background. Using the timing argument (TA), which links LG dynamics to LG mass, we find that the complete $\Lambda$CDM background predicts a $\sim 10 \%$ lower mass for the LG; while $\Lambda$ alone predicts a $\sim 10 \%$ higher mass. The TA mass is modified by (i) simulations and (ii) the effect of the Large Magellanic Cloud (LMC) to alleviate the poorly constrained internal mass distributions of M31 and the MW, their time evolution, and the unknown distribution of dark matter between them. First, using IllustrisTNG simulations, we accounted for the effects of two extended halos and their environment (rather than point particles) and predicted their mass $\left(3.89 \pm 0.62\right) \cdot 10^{12} M_{\odot}$. Second, the LMC effectively changes the separation and velocities of M31 toward the MW and reduces the predicted mass to $\left(2.33 \pm 0.72\right) \cdot 10^{12} M_\odot$. Despite the uncertainties around dark matter between these galaxies, the overall estimated mass is compatible with the mere sum of the MW and M31 masses. The total mass of the TA is compatible with other estimates, such as the Hubble flow and the Virial Theorem with other dwarf galaxies. The combined result shows, for the first time, that a lower mass estimate can be obtained from the TA, with a consistent embedding and other systematic effects, and without an additional dark matter halo around the galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.09546v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202449884</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>David Benisty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stringent Tests of Lorentz Invariance Violation from LHAASO Observations of GRB 221009A</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.06009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.06009v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Very recently, the Large High Altitude Air Shower Observatory (LHAASO) reported the observation of the very early TeV afterglow of the brightest-of-all-time GRB 221009A, recording the highest photon statistics in the TeV band ever from a gamma-ray burst. We use this unique observation to place stringent constraints on an energy dependence of the speed of light in vacuum, a manifestation of Lorentz invariance violation (LIV) predicted by some quantum gravity (QG) theories. Our results show that the 95% confidence level lower limits on the QG energy scales are $E_{\mathrm{QG},1}&gt;10$ times of the Planck energy $E_\mathrm{Pl}$ for the linear, and $E_{\mathrm{QG},2}&gt;6\times10^{-8}E_\mathrm{Pl}$ for the quadratic LIV effects, respectively. Our limits on the quadratic LIV case improve previous best bounds by factors of 5--7.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.06009v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.071501</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator> The LHAASO collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$X(3872)$ Relevant $D\bar{D}^*$ Scattering in $N_f=2$ Lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.14541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.14541v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the $S$-wave $D\bar{D}^*(I=0)$ scattering at four different pion masses $m_\pi$ ranging from 250 MeV to 417 MeV from $N_f=2$ lattice QCD. Three energy levels $E_{2,3,4}$ are extracted at each $m_\pi$. The analysis of $E_{2,3}$ using the effective range expansion (ERE) comes out with a shallow bound state below the $D\bar{D}^*$ threshold, and the phase shifts at $E_{3,4}$ indicate the possible existence of a resonance near 4.0 GeV. We also perform a joint analysis to $E_{2,3,4}$ through the $K$-matrix parameterization of the scattering amplitude. In this way, we observe a $D\bar{D}^*$ bound state whose properties are almost the same as that from the ERE analysis. At each $m_\pi$, this joint analysis also results in a resonance pole with a mass slightly above 4.0 GeV and a width around 40-60 MeV, which are compatible with the properties of the newly observed $\chi_{c1}(4010)$ by LHCb. More scrutinized lattice QCD calculations are desired to check the existence of this resonance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.14541v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haozheng Li, Chunjiang Shi, Ying Chen, Ming Gong, Juzheng Liang, Zhaofeng Liu, Wei Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmic Inflation at the Crossroads</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10647</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10647v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The capability of Cosmic Inflation to explain the latest Cosmic Microwave Background and Baryonic Acoustic Oscillation data is assessed by performing Bayesian model comparison within the landscape of nearly three-hundred models of single-field slow-roll inflation. We present the first Bayesian data analysis based on the third-order slow-roll primordial power spectra. In particular, the fourth Hubble-flow function $\epsilon_4$ remains unbounded while the third function verifies, at two-sigma, $\epsilon_{3}\in[-0.4,0.5]$, which is perfectly compatible with the slow-roll predictions for the running of the spectral index. We also observe some residual excess of $B$-modes within the BICEP/Keck data favoring, at a non-statistically significant level, non-vanishing primordial tensor modes: $\log(\epsilon_{1}) &gt; -3.9$, at $68\%$ confidence level. Then, for 283 models of single-field inflation, we compute the Bayesian evidence, the Bayesian dimensionality and the marginalized posteriors of all the models' parameters, including the ones associated with the reheating era. The average information gain on the reheating parameter $R_\mathrm{reh}$ reaches $1.3 \pm 0.18$ bits, which is more than a factor two improvement compared to the first Planck data release. As such, inflationary model predictions cannot meet data accuracy without specifying, or marginalizing over, the reheating kinematics. We also find that more than $40\%$ of the scenarios are now strongly disfavored, which shows that the constraining power of cosmological data is winning against the increase of the number of proposed models. In addition, about $20\%$ of all models have evidences within the most probable region and are all favored according to the Jeffreys' scale of Bayesian evidences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10647v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2024/07/087</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP2407:087,2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jerome Martin, Christophe Ringeval, Vincent Vennin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polyadic supersymmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02188v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a polyadic analog of supersymmetry by considering the polyadization procedure (proposed by the author) applied to the toy model of one-dimensional supersymmetric quantum mechanics. The supercharges are generalized to polyadic ones using the $n$-ary sigma matrices defined in earlier work. In this way, polyadic analogs of supercharges and Hamiltonians take the cyclic shift block matrix form, and they can describe multidegenerated quantum states in a way that is different from the $N$-extended and multigraded SQM. While constructing the corresponding supersymmetry as an $n$-ary Lie superalgebra ($n$ is the arity of the initial associative multiplication), we have found new brackets with a reduced arity of $2\leq m&lt;n$ and a related series of $m$-ary superalgebras (which is impossible for binary superalgebras). In the case of even reduced arity $m$ we obtain a tower of higher order (as differential operators) even Hamiltonians, while for $m$ odd we get a tower of higher order odd supercharges, and the corresponding algebra consists of the odd sector only.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02188v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steven Duplij (University of M\"unster)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Covariant quantum field theory of tachyons is unphysical</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14225v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recently, Paczos et al. (Phys. Rev. D 110, 015006 (2024)) proposed a quantum field theory for free and interacting tachyon fields, which - unlike previous such attempts - is (claimed to be) covariant, have energy spectrum bounded from below, and Lorentz invariant (LI) vacuum. We show that the commutator of the proposed tachyon fields is not LI, and it violates microcausality except for tachyons moving with infinite speed. The proposed Feynman propagator (FP) is based on flawed analogy with QED and actually leads to unitarity violation. The actual FP, the two-point time-ordered correlation function, is neither LI nor a Green's function. Moreover, the potential for an interacting tachyon is shown to be unprotected from quantum corrections that generate tachyon self-interactions, which affects the stability of the tachyonic vacuum. Our analysis indicates that the proposed theory is not covariant, and that the tachyonic vacuum is likely unstable, indicating that superluminal observers are not physical. Therefore, the extended principle of relativity is void and cannot be used to derive nondeterministic description of Nature similar to quantum mechanics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14225v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Krzysztof Jod{\l}owski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subspace-projected multireference covariant density functional theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00691v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Multireference density functional theory (MR-DFT) has been a pivotal method for studying nuclear low-lying states and neutrinoless double-beta ($0\nu\beta\beta$) decay. However, quantifying their theoretical uncertainties has been a significant challenge due to the computational demands. This study introduces a subspace-projected covariant density functional theory (SP-CDFT), which efficiently emulates MR-CDFT calculations for nuclear low-lying states. This approach leverages the eigenvector continuation method combined with the quantum-number projected generator coordinate method, based on a relativistic energy density functional (EDF). We apply SP-CDFT to investigate the correlations among the physical quantities of nuclear matter, nuclear low-lying spectroscopy, and the nuclear matrix elements (NMEs) of $0\nu\beta\beta$ decay in the two heaviest candidate nuclei. Our findings reveal generally strong correlations between the NMEs of $0\nu\beta\beta$ decay and the excitation energy of the $2_1^+$ state, as well as the $E2$ transition strength, although these correlations vary significantly among nuclei. The Bayesian analysis yields the NMEs 4.33(5) for $^{136}$Xe and 5.51(14) for $^{150}$Nd. This work also paves the way for refining nuclear EDF parameters using spectroscopic data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00691v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>X. Zhang, C. C. Wang, C. R. Ding, J. M. Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Smile of Cheshire Cat At High Density</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00692v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Baryons in finite nuclei, nuclear matter and dense compact-star matter are described in terms of Cheshire Cat for QCD. A potential conceptual link, admittedly short in mathematical rigor, between their manifestations is made by what's called Cheshire Cat Principle. Put in terms taken ``dual" to QCD variables, going to very high density exposes quantum Hall droplets -- or pancakes -- at which the dilaton-limit fixed point with $g_A\to 1$, $f_\pi\to f_\chi$ -- where $f_\pi$ and $f_\chi$ are respectively the pion and dilaton decay constants -- and the baryon parity-doubling are reached. This scenario suggests a thus-far totally unexplored structure of dual baryonic matter at high density which does neither require nor rule out (rapid) first-order phase transitions from hadrons to quarks in the core of compact stars on the verge of gravitational collapse.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00692v3</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mannque Rho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Galactic Gas Models Strongly Affect the Determination of the Diffusive Halo Height</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.05179</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.05179v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The height of the Milky Way diffusion halo, above which cosmic-rays can freely escape the galaxy, is among the most critical, yet poorly known, parameters in cosmic-ray physics. Measurements of radioactive secondaries, such as $^{10}$Be or $^{26}$Al, which decay equivalently throughout the diffusive volume, are expected to provide the strongest constraints. This has motivated significant observational work to constrain their isotopic ratios, along with theoretical work to constrain the cross-section uncertainties that are thought to dominate radioactive secondary fluxes. In this work, we show that the imprecise modelling of the Milky Way spiral arms significantly affects our ability to translate $^{10}$Be and $^{26}$Al fluxes into constraints on the diffusive halo height, biasing our current results. Utilizing state-of-the-art spiral arms models we produce new predictions for the $^{10}$Be and $^{26}$Al fluxes that motivate upcoming measurements by AMS-02 and HELIX.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.05179v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro De La Torre Luque, Tim Linden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-perturbative phase boundaries in the Gross-Neveu model from a stability analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.09803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.09803v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Two out of three phase boundaries of the 1+1 dimensional Gross-Neveu model in the chiral limit can be obtained from a standard, perturbative stability analysis of the homogeneous phases. The third one separating the massive homogeneous phase from the kink crystal is non-perturbative and could so far only be inferred from the full solution of the model. We show that this phase boundary can also be obtained via a modified stability analysis, based on the thermodynamic potential of a single kink or baryon. The same method works for the massive Gross-Neveu model, so that all phase boundaries of the Gross-Neveu model could have been predicted quantitatively without prior knowledge of the full crystal solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.09803v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Thies</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unitarity, Causality, and Solar System Bounds, Significantly Limit Using Gravitational Waves to Test General Relativity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12118v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The prospect of detecting/constraining deviations from general relativity by studying gravitational waves (GWs) from merging black holes has been one of the primary motivations of GW interferometers like LIGO/Virgo. Within pure gravity, the only possible way deviations can arise is from the existence of higher order derivative corrections, namely higher powers of the Riemann curvature tensor, in the effective action. Any observational bounds imply constraints on the corresponding Wilson coefficients. At the level of the action, one can imagine the coefficients are sufficiently large so as to be in principle detectable. However, from the point of view of some fundamental principles, namely causality and unitarity, this is much less clear, as we examine here. We begin by reviewing certain known bounds on these coefficients, which together imply a low cut off on the effective theory. We then consider a possible mechanism to generate such terms, namely in the form of many minimally coupled light scalars that can be integrated out to give these higher order operators. We show that a by product of this is the generation of quantum corrections to Newton's potential, whose observable consequences are already ruled out by solar system tests. We point out that over 7 orders of magnitude of improvement in interferometer sensitivity would be required to avoid such solar system constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12118v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Cassem, Mark P. Hertzberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
