<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph</link>
    <description>hep-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2024 04:00:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Leading Axion-Photon Sensitivity with NuSTAR Observations of M82 and M87</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14476v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We perform the most sensitive search to-date for the existence of ultralight axions using data from the NuSTAR telescope. We search for stellar axion production in the M82 starburst galaxy and the M87 central galaxy of the Virgo cluster and then the subsequent conversion into hard X-rays in the surrounding magnetic fields. We sum over the full stellar populations in these galaxies when computing the axion luminosity, and we account for the conversion of axions to photons by using magnetic field profiles in simulated IllustrisTNG analogue galaxies. We show that analyzing NuSTAR data towards these targets between roughly 30 to 70 keV shows no evidence for axions and leads to robust constraints on the axion-photon coupling at the level of $|g_{a\gamma\gamma}| \lesssim 6.4 \times 10^{-13}$ GeV$^{-1}$ for $m_a \lesssim 10^{-10}$ eV at 95% confidence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14476v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Orion Ning, Benjamin R. Safdi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holography for Sp(2$N_c$) Gauge Dynamics: from Composite Higgs to Technicolour</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14480</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14480v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study Sp(2$N_c$) gauge dynamics with two Dirac fermion flavours in the fundamental representation. These strongly coupled systems underlie some composite Higgs models with a global symmetry breaking pattern SU(4)$\rightarrow$Sp(4), leading to a light quartet of pseudo-Goldstone bosons that can play the role of the Higgs. Including four-fermion interactions can rotate the vacuum to a technicolour breaking pattern. Using gauge/gravity duality, we study the underlying gauge dynamics. Our model incorporates the $N_c$-specific running of the fermion anomalous dimension and can thus distinguish between specific gauge groups. We determine the bound-state spectrum of the UV SU(4)$\rightarrow$Sp(4) symmetry breaking model, also including fermion masses and mass splitting, and display the $N_c$ dependence. The inclusion of a four-fermion interaction shows the emergence of three Goldstone bosons on the path to technicolour dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14480v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johanna Erdmenger, Nick Evans, Yang Liu, Werner Porod</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boosting Beyond: A Novel Approach to Probing Top-Philic Resonances at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14482</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14482v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a novel search strategy for heavy top-philic resonances that induce new contributions to four-top production at the LHC. We capitalize on recent advances in top-tagging performance to demonstrate that the final state, that is expected to be boosted based on current limits, can be fully reconstructed and exploited. Notably, our approach promises bounds on new physics cross-sections that are 30 to 60 times stronger than those obtained through traditional searches, showcasing its unprecedented effectiveness in probing top-philic new physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14482v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luc Darm\'e, Benjamin Fuks, Hao-Lin Li, Matteo Maltoni, Olivier Mattelaer, Julien Touch\`eque</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Muonization by Active-Sterile Neutrino Mixing in Protoneutron Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14485</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14485v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study $\nu_\mu$-$\nu_s$ and $\bar\nu_\mu$-$\bar\nu_s$ mixing in the protoneutron star (PNS) created in a core-collapse supernova (CCSN). We point out the importance of the feedback on the general composition of the PNS in addition to the obvious feedback on the $\nu_\mu$ lepton number. We show that for our adopted mixing parameters $\delta m^2\sim 10^2\,$keV$^2$ and $\sin^2 2\theta$ consistent with the current constraints, sterile neutrino production is dominated by the Mikheyev$-$Smirnov$-$Wolfenstein conversion of $\bar\nu_\mu$ into $\bar\nu_s$ and that the subsequent escape of $\bar\nu_s$ increases the $\nu_\mu$ lepton number, which in turn enhances muonization of the PNS primarily through $\nu_\mu+n\to p+\mu^-$. We find that this enhancement is amplified by diffusion of the $\nu_e$ and $\nu_\mu$ lepton numbers. While these results are qualitatively robust, their quantitative effects on the dynamics and active neutrino emission of CCSNe should be evaluated by including $\nu_\mu$-$\nu_s$ and $\bar\nu_\mu$-$\bar\nu_s$ mixing in the simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14485v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anupam Ray, Yong-Zhong Qian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Growing Evidence for a Higgs Triplet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14492v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Despite intensive searches at the LHC, no new fundamental particle has been discovered since the discovery of the 125 GeV Higgs boson. In general, a new physics discovery is challenging without a UV-complete model because different channels and observables cannot be combined directly and unambiguously. Moreover, without indirect hints for new particles, the parameter space to be searched is huge, resulting in diminished significance due to the look-elsewhere effect. Several LHC searches with multiple leptons in the final state point towards the existence of a new Higgs boson with a mass in the 140-160 GeV range, decaying mostly to a pair of W bosons. This dominant decay mode motivates a Higgs triplet with zero hypercharge, which also predicts a heavier-than-expected $W$-boson as indicated by the CDF-II measurement. Within this simple and predictive model, we simulate and combine channels of associated di-photon production. Considering the run-2 results of ATLAS, including those presented recently at the Moriond conference, a significance of 4.3$\sigma$ is obtained for a mass of 152 GeV. This is the largest statistical evidence for a new narrow resonance observed at the LHC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14492v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Crivellin, Saiyad Ashanujjaman, Sumit Banik, Guglielmo Coloretti, Siddharth P. Maharathy, Bruce Mellado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inflaton decay in No-Scale Supergravity and Starobinsky-like models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14545v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the decay of the inflaton in Starobinsky-like models arising from either an $R+R^2$ theory of gravity or $N=1$ no-scale supergravity models. If Standard Model matter is simply introduced to the $R + R^2$ theory, the inflaton (which appears when the theory is conformally transformed to the Einstein frame) couples to matter predominantly in Standard Model Higgs kinetic terms. This will typically lead to a reheating temperature of $\sim 3 \times 10^9$~GeV. However, if the Standard Model Higgs is conformally coupled to curvature, the decay rate may be suppressed and vanishes for a conformal coupling $\xi = 1/6$. Nevertheless, inflaton decays through the conformal anomaly leading to a reheating temperature of order $10^8$~GeV. The Starobinsky potential may also arise in no-scale supergravity. In this case, the inflaton decays if there is a direct coupling of the inflaton to matter in the superpotential or to gauge fields through the gauge kinetic function. We also discuss the relation between the theories and demonstrate the correspondence between the no-scale models and the conformally coupled $R+R^2$ theory (with $\xi = 1/6$).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14545v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yohei Ema, Marcos A. G. Garcia, Wenqi Ke, Keith A. Olive, Sarunas Verner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SUBA-Jet: a new Model for Jets in Heavy Ion Collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14579v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a new model for jet quenching in a quark gluon plasma (QGP). The jet energy loss has two steps. The initial jet parton with a high virtuality loses energy by a perturbative vacuum parton shower modified by medium interactions until it becomes on shell. Subsequent energy loss originates from elastic and radiative collisions with the medium constituents. Coherency of the radiative collisions is achieved by starting with virtual gluons that act as field dressing of the initial jet parton. These are formed according to a Gunion-Bertsch seed. The QCD version of the LPM effect is obtained by increasing the phase of the virtual gluons through elastic scatterings with the medium. Above a phase threshold, the virtual gluons will be formed and can produce coherent radiation themselves. The model has been implemented in a Monte Carlo code and is validated by successfully reproducing the BDMPS-Z prediction for the energy spectrum of radiated gluons in a static medium. Results for the more realistic case, in which the assumptions of the BDMPS-Z approach are released, are also shown. We investigate the influence of various parameters on the energy spectrum and the transverse momentum distribution, such as the in-medium quark masses, the energy transfer in the recoil process, and the phase accumulation criteria, especially for low and intermediate energy gluons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14579v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Iurii Karpenko, Alexander Lind, Martin Rohrmoser, Joerg Aichelin, Pol-Bernard Gossiaux</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Streamlined jet tagging network assisted by jet prong structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14677v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Attention-based transformer models have become increasingly prevalent in collider analysis, offering enhanced performance for tasks such as jet tagging. However, they are computationally intensive and require substantial data for training. In this paper, we introduce a new jet classification network using an MLP mixer, where two subsequent MLP operations serve to transform particle and feature tokens over the jet constituents. The transformed particles are combined with subjet information using multi-head cross-attention so that the network is invariant under the permutation of the jet constituents.
  We utilize two clustering algorithms to identify subjets: the standard sequential recombination algorithms with fixed radius parameters and a new IRC-safe, density-based algorithm of dynamic radii based on HDBSCAN. The proposed network demonstrates comparable classification performance to state-of-the-art models while boosting computational efficiency drastically. Finally, we evaluate the network performance using various interpretable methods, including centred kernel alignment and attention maps, to highlight network efficacy in collider analysis tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14677v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Hammad, M. Nojiri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LHC di-lepton searches for $Z^\prime$ bosons which explain measurements of $b \rightarrow s l^+l^-$ transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14748v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Several current measurements of $b\rightarrow s l^+l^-$ processes are in tension with Standard Model predictions, whereas others (e.g. $R_K$ and $R_{K^\ast}$) are in reasonable agreement with them. We examine some recent $Z^\prime$ models that fit the data as a whole appreciably better than the Standard Model, confronting the models with ATLAS resonance searches in the $e^+e^-$ and $\mu^+\mu^-$ channels. The models are constrained by both channels; we find that the lower limit on the $Z^\prime$ mass $M_{Z^\prime}$ is 0.8-1.8 TeV at the 95$\%$ confidence level, depending upon the model. We provide sensitivity estimates for the HL-LHC, which extend to more than double the current limits on $M_{Z^\prime}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14748v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Allanach (University of Cambridge)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating $\Xi$ resonances from pentaquark perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14753v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We have investigated the $qss\bar{q}q$ ($q = u$ or $d$) system to find possible pentaquark explanations for the $\Xi$ resonances. The bound state calculation is carried out within the framework of the quark delocalization color screening model. The scattering processes are also studied to examine the possible resonance states. The current results indicate that the $\Xi(1950)$ can be interpreted as $\Lambda \bar{K}^*$ state with $J^P = 1/2^-$. Three states are identified that match the $\Xi(2250)$, which are $\Sigma^* \bar{K}^*$ state with $J^P = 3/2^-$, $\Sigma^* \bar{K}^*$ state with $J^P =5/2^-$, and $\Xi^* \rho$ state with $J^P =5/2^-$. This may explain the conflicting experimental values for the width of the $\Xi(2250)$. A new $\Xi$ resonance is predicted, whose mass and width are 2066--2079 MeV and 186--189 MeV, respectively. These results contribute to understanding the nature of the $\Xi$ resonances and to the future search for new $\Xi$ resonances. Moreover, it is meaningful to further investigate the $\Xi$ resonances from an unquenched picture on the basis of pentaquark investigation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14753v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ye Yan, Qi Huang, Xinmei Zhu, Hongxia Huang, Jialun Ping</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring interference effects between two ALP effective operators at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14833v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We observe that most studies of axion-like particle (ALP) production channels at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) focus on a single type of ALP operator for each process in the effective field theory framework. In this work, we propose an alternative approach that considers two or more types of relevant ALP effective operators together in some specific ALP production channels and study their interference effects. Using the $p p\rightarrow t j a$ process with $a\rightarrow\gamma\gamma$ as an example, we show that this approach allows us to constrain the ALP interactions with both the $W$ boson and the top quark, as well as their interference in a single process. For the final state with two isolated photons and a top quark decaying semi-leptonically, we predict that the future bounds on the ALP decay constant can reach around $f_a \sim 10\;(20) $ TeV for $25$ GeV $&lt; M_a &lt; 100$ GeV at the LHC with 300 (3000) fb$^{1}$ luminosity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14833v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kingman Cheung, Chih-Ting Lu, C. J. Ouseph, Priyanka Sarmah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing bottom-associated production of a TeV scale scalar decaying to a top quark and dark matter at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14844v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A minimal non-thermal dark matter model that can explain both the existence of dark matter and the baryon asymmetry in the universe is studied. It requires two color-triplet, iso-singlet scalars with $\mathcal{O}$(TeV) masses and a singlet Majorana fermion with a mass of $\mathcal{O}$(GeV). The fermion becomes stable and can play the role of the dark matter candidate. We consider the fermion to interact with a top quark via the exchange of QCD-charged scalar fields coupled dominantly to third generation fermions. The signature of a single top quark production associated with a bottom quark and large missing transverse momentum opens up the possibility to search for this type of model at the LHC in a way complementary to existing monotop searches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14844v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amandeep Kaur Kalsi, Teruki Kamon, Seulgi Kim, Jason S. H. Lee, Denis Rathjens, Youn Jung Roh, Adrian Thompson, Ian James Watson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monte Carlo evaluation of divergent one-loop integrals without contour deformation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14868</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14868v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reference [1] introduces a method for computing numerically four-dimensional multi-loop integrals without performing an explicit analytic contour deformation around threshold singularities. In this paper, we extend such a technique to massless scalar one-loop integrals regularized in the framework of dimensional regularization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14868v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roberto Pittau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral-vacuum excited replicae in QCD modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14898v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a detailed study of the Bardeen-Cooper-Schrieffer (BCS) gap equation ``replicae'' or excited vacuum states, orthogonal to the ground-state one, in the chiral-quark sector of the Hamiltonian Coulomb-gauge model of chromodynamics. Analyzing the number of negative eigenmodes of the energy density's Hessian we believe that we have identified all of the (negative energy-density) vacua of this nonlinear system, namely the ground BCS state and two (or one) replicae for slightly massive (or massless) quarks, given the interaction strength typical of the strong interactions. The meson spectrum over each of the replicae looks similar, so the differences are not significant enough given model uncertainties, but matrix elements are more sensitive and allow to distinguish them. We propose to look for such excited vacua in lattice gauge theory by trying to identify excitations with scalar quantum numbers which have energies proportional to the lattice volume (unlike conventional mesons for which the mass stabilizes to a constant upon taking the infinite volume limit).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14898v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eduardo Garnacho-Velasco, Pedro J. de A. Bicudo, J. Emilio F. T. Ribeiro, Felipe J. Llanes-Estrada, Lucas P\'erez Molina, Victor Serrano Herreros, Jorge Vallejo Fern\'andez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymmetric self-interacting dark matter with canonical seesaw</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14912v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the possibility of generating dark matter (DM) and baryon asymmetry of the universe (BAU) simultaneously in an asymmetric DM framework which also alleviates the small-scale structure issues of cold DM (CDM). While thermal relic of such self-interacting DM (SIDM) remains under-abundant due to efficient annihilation into light mediators, a non-zero asymmetry in dark sector can lead to survival of the required DM in the universe. The existence of a light mediator leads to the required self-interactions of DM at small scales while keeping DM properties similar to CDM at large scales. It also ensures that the symmetric DM component annihilates away, leaving the asymmetric part, in the spirit of cogenesis. The particle physics implementation is done in canonical seesaw models of light neutrino mass, connecting it to the origin of DM and BAU. In particular, we consider type-I and type-III seesaw origin of neutrino mass for simplicity and minimality of the field content. We show that the desired self-interactions and relic of DM together with BAU while satisfying relevant constraints lead to strict limits on DM mass $\mathcal{O}(\rm GeV) \lesssim M_{\rm DM} \lesssim460 $ GeV. In spite of being high scale seesaw, the models remain verifiable at different experiments including direct, indirect DM search as well as colliders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14912v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debasish Borah, Satyabrata Mahapatra, Partha Kumar Paul, Narendra Sahu, Prashant Shukla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Particle Swam Optimization Based Analysis to Unlocking the Neutrino Mass Puzzle using $A_{4}\times Z_{3}\times Z_{10}$ Flavor Symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14917v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: New research has highlighted a shortfall in the Standard Model (SM) because it predicts neutrinos to have zero mass. However, recent experiments on neutrino oscillation have revealed that the majority of neutrino parameters indeed indicate their significant mass. In response, scientists are increasingly incorporating discrete symmetries alongside continuous ones for better justification of observed patterns of neutrino mixing. In this study, we have examined a model within $A_4\times Z_3\times Z_{10}$ symmetry to estimate the neutrino masses using particle swam optimization technique for both mass hierarchy of neutrino. This model employed a hybrid seesaw mechanism, a combination of seesaw mechanism of type-I and type-II, to establish the effective Majorana neutrino mass matrix. After calculating the mass eigenvalues and lepton mixing matrix upto second order perturbation theory in this framework, this study seeks to investigate the scalar potential for vacuum expectation values (VEVs), optimize the parameters, $U_{PMNS}$ matrix, neutrino masses: $|{m_{1}^{\prime}}^N|=0.0292794-0.0435082\ eV$, $|{m_{2}^{\prime}}^N|=1.78893\times 10^{-18}-0.0293509\ eV$, $|{m_{3}^{\prime}}^N|=0.0307414-0.0471467\ eV$, $|{m_{1}^{\prime}}^I|=0.00982013-0.0453623\ eV$, $|{m_{2}^{\prime}}^I_|=0.0379702-0.0471197\ eV$, and $|{m_{3}^{\prime}}^I|=0.0122063-0.027544\ eV$, effective neutrino mass parameters: $\langle {m_{ee}} \rangle^N=(0.170-3.93)\times10^{-2}\ eV$, $\langle {m_{\beta}} \rangle^N=(0.471-1.39)\times10^{-2}\ eV$, $\langle {m_{ee}} \rangle^I=(1.85-4.55)\times10^{-2}\ eV$ and $\langle {m_{\beta}} \rangle^I=(2.26-4.56)\times10^{-2}\ eV$, are predicted for both mass hierarchy through particle swam optimization (PSO), showing strong agreement with recent experimental findings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14917v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. W. Aslam, A. A. Zafar, M. N. Aslam, A. A Bhatti, T. Hussain, M. Iqbal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complete CP-eigen Bases of Meson-Baryon Chiral Lagrangian up to $p^5$-order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15047v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chiral perturbation theory describes the low energy dynamics of mesons and baryons in terms of the nonlinear Goldstone boson and fermion degrees of freedom. Through the Young tensor technique, we construct the on-shell operator bases for the meson-baryon system up to $p^5$-order, using the chiral dimension power counting and heavy baryon expansion. For the Lorentz structure, additional treatments on off-shell external sources and operators with higher derivatives are necessarily considered, while for the internal structure, the invariant tensor basis is converted into the trace basis equivalently, and Cayley-Hamilton relations are utilized to classify different CP eigen-operators. Finally we present the complete operator set of $C$+$P$+, $C$+$P$-, $C$-$P$+, and $C$-$P$- eigen-operators at the $p^5$-order, and obtain the operator counting from the Hilbert series.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15047v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chuan-Qiang Song, Hao Sun, Jiang-Hao Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decay $B_c^+ \to D_{(s)}^{(*)+} \ell^+\ell^-$ within covariant confined quark model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15085v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Here we study the rare decay of $B_c$ mesons within the effective field theoretical framework of covariant confined quark model. The transition form factors corresponding to $B_c^+ \to D^{(*)+}$ and $B_c^+ \to D_s^{(*)+}$ are computed in the entire $q^2$ range. Using form factors we compute the branching fractions and compare with the available theoretical approaches. We also compute other physical observables such as forward backward asymmetry, longitudinal and transverse polarizations and various clean angular observables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15085v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail A. Ivanov, Jignesh N. Pandya, Pietro Santorelli, Nakul R. Soni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resummation of combined QCD-electroweak effects in Drell Yan lepton-pair production</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15112v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider neutral- and charged-current Drell Yan lepton-pair production at hadron colliders, and include dominant classes of electroweak and mixed QCD-electroweak corrections to all orders in perturbation theory. The accurate description of these physical effects is vital for a precise determination of fundamental Standard Model parameters, such as the $W$-boson mass and the electroweak mixing angle, as well as for a solid assessment of the associated theoretical uncertainties. Our state-of-the-art resummation reaches next-to-leading-logarithmic accuracy in both the electroweak and the mixed QCD-electroweak perturbative expansions, including constant terms at first order beyond Born level in both couplings, i.e. at order $\alpha$ and $\alpha_s \alpha$. These effects are incorporated on top of QCD predictions at next-to-next-to-next-to-leading-logarithmic accuracy, which include constant terms at third order in the strong coupling. Our results retain, for the first time at this accuracy, full dependence on the kinematics of the final-state leptons, thereby enabling a realistic comparison with experimental analyses at the differential level in presence of fiducial cuts. We present a phenomenological analysis of the impact of electroweak corrections in relevant observables at the LHC. We find visible shape distortions in resummation-dominated kinematical regions with respect to pure-QCD predictions, highlighting the importance of a complete description, not limited to QCD, for precision Drell Yan physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15112v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Buonocore, Luca Rottoli, Paolo Torrielli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Virtual QCD corrections to $gg \to ZZ$: top-quark loops from a transverse-momentum expansion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15113v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the virtual corrections due to the top-quark loops for the process $gg \to ZZ$ at next-to-leading order in QCD. The associated two-loop box diagrams are computed using a small-transverse-momentum expansion. Our results are then merged with those available in the complementary energy region, obtained via a high-energy expansion, in order to provide an analytic result that is valid in the whole phase space. The results presented allow for an efficient modelling of the signal--background interference as well as the irreducible background in off-shell Higgs production.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15113v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Degrassi, Ramona Gr\"ober, Marco Vitti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$1/Q^2$ power corrections to TMD factorization for Drell-Yan hadronic tensor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15116v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: I calculate ${1\over Q^2}$ power corrections to unpolarized Drell-Yan hadronic tensor for electromagnetic (EM) current at large $N_c$ and demonstrate the EM gauge invariance at this level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15116v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian Balitsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QCD topology and axion properties in an isotropic hot and dense medium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15136v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the QCD topology and axion properties at finite temperature and chemical potential in the framework of the two-flavor Nambu$-$Jona-Lasinio model. We find that the behaviors of the two lowest cumulants of the QCD topological charge distribution and axion properties are highly sensitive to the critical behavior of the chiral phase transition. In particular, the topological susceptibility and the axion mass follow the response of the chiral condensate to temperature and chemical potential, showing that both quantities decrease monotonically with the increment of temperature and/or chemical potential. However, it is important to note that the normalized fourth cumulant behaves differently depending on the temperature. At low temperatures, it is a non-monotonic function of the chemical potential, while at high temperatures, it monotonically decreases. Additionally, its value invariably approaches the asymptotic value of $b_2^{\text {inst }}=-1/12$, predicted by the dilute instanton gas model. We also observe that with the increase in chemical potential at relatively low temperatures, the axion self-coupling constant exhibits a sharp peak around the critical point, which can even be more than twice its vacuum value. After that, the self-coupling drops sharply to a much lower value than its vacuum value, eventually approaching zero in the high chemical potential limit. The finding that the axion self-coupling constant is significantly enhanced in high-density environments near the chiral phase transition could lead to the creation or enhancement of an axion Bose-Einstein condensate in compact astrophysical objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15136v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hong-Fang Gong, Qi Lu, Zhen-Yan Lu, Lu-Meng Liu, Xun Chen, Shu-Peng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimating Longitudinal Polarization of $\Lambda$ and $\bar{\Lambda}$ Hyperons at Relativistic Energies using Hydrodynamic and Transport models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15138</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15138v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The global and local polarization measurements of $\Lambda$ ($\bar{\Lambda}$) hyperons by STAR and ALICE Collaborations open up an immense interest in investigating the polarization dynamics in heavy-ion collisions. Recent studies suggest the transverse component of the vorticity field is responsible for the global spin polarization, while the longitudinal component of the vorticity field accounts for the local polarization. The local polarization of $\Lambda$-hyperons arises due to the anisotropic flows in the transverse plane, indicating a quadrupole pattern of the longitudinal vorticity along the beam direction. The present study focuses on the local (longitudinal) polarization of $\Lambda$ and $\bar{\Lambda}$ in Au$+$Au and Pb$+$Pb collisions at $\sqrt{s_{NN}}$ = 200 GeV and 5.02 TeV, respectively. Further, we explore the centrality and transverse momentum ($p_{\rm T}$) dependence of longitudinal polarization using hydrodynamic and transport models. All these models predict a maximum longitudinal polarization in mid-central collisions around 30-50 \% centrality at $p_{\rm T} \approx$ 2.0 - 3.0 GeV/c. These findings on longitudinal polarization advocate the existence of a thermal medium in non-central heavy-ion collisions. Our findings are in agreement with corresponding experimental data at the RHIC and LHC energies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15138v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bhagyarathi Sahoo, Captain R. Singh, Raghunath Sahoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using analytic models to describe effective PDFs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15175v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Parton distribution functions (PDFs) play a pivotal role in hadron collider phenomenology. They are non-perturbative quantities extracted from fits to available data, and their scale dependence is dictated by the DGLAP evolution equations. In this article, we discuss machine learning (ML) strategies to efficiently compute PDFs by bypassing the scale evolution. Analytical approximations to the PDFs as a function of $x$ and $Q^2$, including up to next-to-leading order (NLO) QCD effects, are obtained. The methodology is tested by reproducing the HERAPDF2.0 set and implementing the analytical expressions in benchmarking codes. It is found that the computational cost is reduced while the precision of the simulations stays well under control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15175v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Salvador A. Ochoa-Oregon, David F. Renter\'ia-Estrada, Roger J. Hern\'andez-Pinto, German F. R. Sborlini, Pia Zurita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diabatic Dynamical Diquark Bound States: Mass Corrections and Widths</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15186v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using the diabatic formalism, which generalizes the adiabatic approximation in the Born-Oppenheimer formalism, we apply well-known Hamiltonian methods to calculate the effect of open di-meson thresholds that lie well below the mass of elementary $c\bar c q\bar q^\prime$, $c\bar c s\bar s$, and $c \bar c q \bar s$ tetraquark bound states. We compute the resulting mass shifts for these states, as well as their decay widths to the corresponding meson pairs. Each mass eigenstate, originally produced using a bound-state approximation under the diabatic formalism, consists of an admixture of a compact diquark-antidiquark configuration (an eigenstate of the original dynamical diquark model) with an extended di-meson configuration induced by the nearest threshold. We compare our results with those from our recent work that employs a scattering formalism, and find a great deal of agreement, but also comment upon interesting discrepancies between the two approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15186v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Richard F. Lebed, Steven R. Martinez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The decays $\Sigma^{+}\to p \ell^{+}\ell^{-}$ within the standard model and beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15268v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by the LHCb measurement of the hyperon decay mode $\Sigma^+\to p\mu^+\mu^-$ and prospects for improvement, we revisit the estimates for the rate and forward-backward asymmetry within the standard model and beyond. The standard model prediction has a fourfold ambiguity, and we suggest ways to resolve it with other measurements, including possible studies of $\Sigma^+\to p e^+e^-$ in the BESIII and LHCb experiments. We use the recent BESIII measurements of $\Sigma^+\to p \gamma$ and $\Sigma^+\to p\pi^0$ to reduce the uncertainty in the long-distance contribution to $\Sigma^+\to p\mu^+\mu^-$. Beyond the standard model, we consider a general effective Hamiltonian at low energy with ten operators whose Wilson coefficients parametrize the new physics. We derive expressions for the $\Sigma^+\to p\mu^+\mu^-$ rate and the associated muon forward-backward asymmetry in terms of these coefficients. Finally, we implement the existing constraints from kaon decays, pointing out the extent to which this hyperon mode can constrain the directions in parameter space to which the kaons are not sensitive.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15268v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arnab Roy, Jusak Tandean, German Valencia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wormholes in the axiverse, and the species scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14489v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyze a large class of four-dimensional $\mathcal{N}=1$ low-energy realizations of the axiverse satisfying various quantum gravity constraints. We propose a novel upper bound on the ultimate UV cutoff of the effective theory, namely the species scale, which only depends on data available at the two-derivative level. Its dependence on the moduli fields and the number $N$ of axions matches expectations from other independent considerations. After an assessment of the regime of validity of the effective field theory, we investigate the non-perturbative gravitational effects therein. We identify a set of axionic charges supported by extremal and non-extremal wormhole configurations. We present a universal class of analytic wormhole solutions, explore their deformations, and analyze the relation between wormhole energy scales and species scale. The connection between these wormholes and a special subclass of BPS fundamental instantons is discussed, and an argument in favor of the genericity of certain axion-dependent effective superpotentials is provided. We find a lower bound increasing with $N\gg 1$ on the Gauss-Bonnet coefficient, resulting in an exponential suppression of non-extremal wormhole effects. Our claims are illustrated and tested in concrete string theory models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14489v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Martucci, Nicol\`o Risso, Alessandro Valenti, Luca Vecchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective Field Theory for Spontaneously Broken Symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14518</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14518v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This is a preprint of an open-access book published by Springer Cham. The book gives an up-to-date overview of the physics of spontaneously broken continuous symmetry from the point of view of effective field theory. Upon building up the necessary foundations, the text reviews the classification of Nambu-Goldstone bosons and then focuses on the construction of the effective-field-theoretic description of their dynamics. Both internal and spacetime broken symmetries are covered, including numerous illustrative examples and a few selected applications, worked out in greater detail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14518v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-031-48378-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Lecture Notes in Physics, volume 1023 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tomas Brauner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pion Valence Quark Distribution at Physical Pion mass of $N_f=2+1+1$ Lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14525</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14525v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a state-of-the-art calculation of the unpolarized pion valence-quark distribution in the framework of large-momentum effective theory (LaMET) with improved handling of systematic errors as well as two-loop perturbative matching. We use lattice ensembles generated by the MILC collaboration at lattice spacing $a\approx 0.09$~fm, lattice volume $64^3\times 96$, $N_f=2+1+1$ flavors of highly-improved staggered quarks and a physical pion mass. The LaMET matrix elements are calculated with pions boosted to momentum $P_z\approx 1.72$~GeV with high-statistics of $O(10^6)$ measurements. We study the pion PDF in both hybrid-ratio and hybrid-regularization-independent momentum subtraction (hybrid-RI/MOM) schemes and also compare the systematic errors with and without the addition of leading-renormalon resummation (LRR) and renormalization-group resummation (RGR) in both the renormalization and lightcone matching. The final lightcone PDF results are presented in the modified minimal-subtraction scheme at renormalization scale $\mu=2.0$~GeV. We show that the $x$-dependent PDFs are compatible between the hybrid-ratio and hybrid-RI/MOM renormalization with the same improvements. We also show that systematics are greatly reduced by the simultaneous inclusion of RGR and LRR and that these methods are necessary if improved precision is to be reached with higher-order terms in renormalization and matching.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14525v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6471/ad3162</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. G: Nucl. Part. Phys. 51 065101 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jack Holligan, Huey-Wen Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear treatment of a black hole mimicker ringdown</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14536v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We perform the first nonlinear and self-consistent study of the merger and ringdown of a black hole mimicking object with stable light rings. To that end, we numerically solve the full Einstein-Klein-Gordon equations governing the head-on collisions of a series of binary boson stars in the large-mass-ratio regime resulting in spinning horizonless remnants with stable light rings. We broadly confirm the appearance of features in the extracted gravitational waveforms expected based on perturbative methods: the signal from the prompt response of the remnants approaches that of a Kerr black hole in the large-compactness limit, and the subsequent emissions contain periodically appearing bursts akin to so-called gravitational wave echoes. However, these bursts occur at high frequencies and are sourced by perturbations of the remnant's internal degrees of freedom. Furthermore, the emitted waveforms also contain a large-amplitude and long-lived component comparable in frequency to black hole quasi-normal modes. We further characterize the emissions, obtain basic scaling relations of relevant timescales, and compute the energy emitted in gravitational waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14536v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nils Siemonsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bring the Heat: Tidal Heating Constraints for Black Holes and Exotic Compact Objects from the LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14641v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the first constraints on tidal heating for the binary systems detected in the LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA (LVK) gravitational wave data. Tidal heating, also known as tidal dissipation, characterizes the viscous nature of an astrophysical body and provides a channel for exchanging energy and angular momentum with the tidal environment. Using the worldline effective field theory formalism, we introduce a physically motivated and easily interpretable parametrization of tidal heating valid for an arbitrary compact astrophysical object. We then derive the imprints of the spin-independent and linear-in-spin tidal heating effects of generic binary components on the waveform phases and amplitudes of quasi-circular orbits. Notably, the mass-weighted spin-independent tidal heating coefficient derived in this work, $\mathcal{H}_0$, is the dissipative analog of the tidal Love number. We constrain the tidal heating coefficients using the public LVK O1-O3 data. Our parameter estimation study includes two separate analyses: the first treats the catalog of binary events as binary black holes (BBH), while the second makes no assumption about the nature of the binary constituents and can therefore be interpreted as constraints for exotic compact objects. In the former case, we combine the posterior distributions of the individual BBH events and obtain a joint constraint of $-13 &lt; \mathcal{H}_0 &lt; 20$ at the $90\%$ credible interval for the BBH population. This translates into a bound on the fraction of the emitted gravitational wave energy lost due to tidal heating (or gained due to radiation enhancement effects) at $|\Delta E_H/\Delta E_{\infty}|\lesssim 3\cdot 10^{-3}$. Our work provides the first robust framework for deriving and measuring tidal heating effects in merging binary systems, demonstrating its potential as a powerful probe of the nature of binary constituents and tests of new physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14641v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Horng Sheng Chia, Zihan Zhou, Mikhail M. Ivanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confronting Dark Matter Capture Rate with Continuous Gravitational Wave Probe of Local Neutron Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15038v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Continuous gravitational waves (CGWs) from various astrophysical sources are one of the many future probes of upcoming Gravitational Wave (GW) search missions. Neutron stars (NSs) with deformity are one of the leading sources of CGW emissions. In this work, for the first time, a novel attempt to estimate the dark matter (DM) capture rate is performed using CGW as the probe to the local NS population. Competitive bounds on DM capture from the local NS population are reported when compared with DM direct search experiments and other astrophysical observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15038v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pooja Bhattacharjee, Amit Dutta Banik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vanilla Inflation Predicts Negative Running</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15089v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that the simplest, and currently favoured, theoretical realizations of cosmic inflation yield a sharp prediction for the running of the spectral index $\alpha_\mathrm{S}$. Using latest cosmological data, we compute its marginalized posterior probability distribution over the space of nearly 300 models of single-field slow-roll inflation. The most probable value is $\alpha_\mathrm{S}=-6.3 \times 10^{-4}$, lying within the $98\%$ credible interval $-1.8 \times 10^{-3}&lt; \alpha_\mathrm{S}&lt; -9.1 \times 10^{-5}$. Within the landscape of all the proposed slow-roll inflationary models, positive values for the running are therefore disfavoured at more than three-sigma.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15089v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jerome Martin, Christophe Ringeval, Vincent Vennin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signature of Particle Diffusion on the X-ray Spectra of the blazar Mkn 421</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15171</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15171v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The curvature in blazar spectrum has the potential to understand the particle dynamics in jets. We performed a detailed analysis of simultaneous Swift-XRT (0.3-10 keV) and NuSTAR (3-79 keV)} observations of Mkn 421. Our analysis of NuSTAR observations alone reveals that, during periods of low flux, the hard X-ray spectra are best represented by a steep power-law with photon index reaching $\sim$ 3. However, the spectrum exhibits significant curvature during its high flux states. To investigate this, we explore plausible diffusion processes facilitating shock acceleration in the emission region that can contribute to the observed spectral curvature. Particularly, such processes can cause gradual fall of the photon spectrum at high energies which can be represented by a sub-exponential function. The parameter that decides this spectral change can be used to characterise the energy dependence of the diffusive process. Our results suggest that the X-ray spectra of Mkn 421 are consistent with a scenario where particle acceleration is mediated through Bohm-type diffusion and the spectra beyond the synchrotron peak is modulated by the radiative loss process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15171v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Baheeja, S. Sahayanathan, F. M. Rieger, C. D. Ravikumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Radiation with Baryon Acoustic Oscillations from DESI 2024 and the $H_0$ tension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15220</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15220v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the presence of extra relativistic degrees of freedom in the early Universe, contributing to the effective number of neutrinos $N_\text{eff}$, as $\Delta N_\text{eff}\equiv N_\text{eff}-3.044\geq 0$, in light of the recent measurements of Baryon Acoustic Oscillations (BAO) by the DESI collaboration. We analyze one-parameter extensions of the $\Lambda$CDM model where dark radiation (DR) is free streaming or behaves as a perfect fluid, due to self-interactions. We report a significant relaxation of upper bounds on $\Delta N_\text{eff}$, with respect to previous BAO data from SDSS+6dFGS, when additionally employing Planck data (and supernovae data from Pantheon+), setting $\Delta N_\text{eff}\leq 0.39$ ($95\%$ C.L.) for free streaming DR, and a very mild preference for fluid DR, $\Delta N_\text{eff} = 0.221^{+0.088}_{-0.18}$ ($\leq 0.46$, $95\%$ C.L.). Applying constraints from primordial element abundances leads to slightly tighter constraints on $\Delta N_\text{eff}$, but they are avoided if DR is produced after Big Bang Nucleosynthesis (BBN). For fluid DR we estimate the tension with the SH$_0$ES determination of $H_0$ to be around $(2.3-2.8)\sigma$ level, and for free-streaming DR the tension is below $3\sigma$ if production occurs after BBN. This lesser degree of tension motivates a combination with SH$_0$ES in these cases, resulting in a $4.4\sigma-5\sigma$ evidence for dark radiation with $\Delta N_\text{eff}\simeq 0.6$ and large improvements in $\chi^2$ over $\Lambda$CDM, $-18\lesssim \Delta \chi^2\lesssim -25$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15220v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Itamar J. Allali, Alessio Notari, Fabrizio Rompineve</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interacting Dark Energy after DESI Baryon Acoustic Oscillation measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15232</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15232v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the implications of the Baryon Acoustic Oscillation measurements released by the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) for Interacting Dark Energy (IDE) models characterized by an energy-momentum flow from Dark Matter to Dark Energy. By combining Planck-2018 and DESI data, we observe a preference for interactions exceeding the 95% confidence level, yielding a present-day expansion rate $H_0=71.4\pm1.5$ km/s/Mpc, in agreement with SH0ES. This preference remains robust when including measurements of the expansion rate $H(z)$ obtained from the relative ages of massive, early-time, and passively-evolving galaxies, as well as when considering distance moduli measurements from Type-Ia Supernovae sourced from the Pantheon-plus catalog using the SH0ES Cepheid host distances as calibrators. Overall, high and low redshift data can be equally or better explained within the IDE framework compared to $\Lambda$CDM, while also yielding higher values of $H_0$ in better agreement with the local distance ladder estimate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15232v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William Giar\`e, Miguel A. Sabogal, Rafael C. Nunes, Eleonora Di Valentino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved Treatment of Dark Matter Capture in Neutron Stars III: Nucleon and Exotic Targets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.02525</link>
      <description>arXiv:2108.02525v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the capture of dark matter (DM) in neutron stars via scattering on hadronic targets, including neutrons, protons and hyperons. We extend previous analyses by including momentum dependent form factors, which account for hadronic structure, and incorporating the effect of baryon strong interactions in the dense neutron star interior, rather than modelling the baryons as a free Fermi gas. The combination of these effects suppresses the DM capture rate over a wide mass range, thus increasing the cross section for which the capture rate saturates the geometric limit. In addition, variation in the capture rate associated with the choice of neutron star equation of state is reduced. For proton targets, the use of the interacting baryon approach to obtain the correct Fermi energy is essential for an accurate evaluation of the capture rate in the Pauli-blocked regime. For heavy neutron stars, which are expected to contain exotic matter, we identify cases where DM scattering on hyperons contributes significantly to the total capture rate. Despite smaller neutron star capture rates, compared to existing analyses, we find that the projected DM-nucleon scattering sensitivity greatly exceeds that of nuclear recoil experiments for a wide DM mass range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2108.02525v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2021/11/056 10.1088/1475-7516/2024/04/E02</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 11 (2021) 056; Erratum: JCAP 04 (2024) E02</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Filippo Anzuini, Nicole F. Bell, Giorgio Busoni, Theo F. Motta, Sandra Robles, Anthony W. Thomas, Michael Virgato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collinear fragmentation at NNLL: generating functionals, groomed correlators and angularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.15734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.15734v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Jet calculus offers a unique mathematical technique to bridge the area of QCD resummation with Monte Carlo parton showers. With the ultimate goal of constructing next-to-next-to-leading logarithmic (NNLL) parton showers we study, using the language of generating functionals, the collinear fragmentation of final-state partons. In particular, we focus on the definition and calculation of the Sudakov form factor, which physically describes the no-emission probability in an ordered branching process. We review recent results for quark jets and compute the Sudakov form factor for the collinear fragmentation of gluon jets at NNLL. The NNLL corrections are encoded in a $z$ dependent two-loop anomalous dimension $B_2(z)$, with $z$ being a suitably defined longitudinal momentum fraction. This is obtained from the integration of the relevant $1\to 3$ collinear splitting kernels combined with the one-loop corrections to the $1\to 2$ counterpart. This work provides the missing ingredients to extend the methods of jet calculus in the collinear limit to NNLL and gives an important element of the next generation of NNLL parton shower algorithms. As an application we derive new NNLL results for both the fractional moments of energy-energy correlation $FC_x$ and the angularities $\lambda_x$ measured on mMDT/Soft-Drop ($\beta=0$) groomed jets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.15734v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Melissa van Beekveld, Mrinal Dasgupta, Basem Kamal El-Menoufi, Jack Helliwell, Pier Francesco Monni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Custodial Symmetry Breaking and Higgs Signatures at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.10027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.10027v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We discuss the simplest model that predicts a tree level modification of the $\rho$ parameter from a shift in the $W$-mass without changing the prediction for the $Z$ mass. This model predicts a new neutral Higgs and two charged Higgses, with very similar masses and suppressed couplings to the Standard Model fermions. We discuss the decay properties of these new scalar bosons, and the main signatures at the Large Hadron Collider. Comparing these signatures for the first time to the latest measurements, we show that while masses around 200 GeV are excluded for some scenarios, over a wide range of model parameter space the new bosons can have a mass close to the electroweak scale without violating existing limits from experimental searches or destroying the agreement with measurements. We investigate the scenario where the new neutral Higgs is fermiophobic and has a large branching ratio into $W$ gauge bosons and/or photons, and show that this could lead to a signal in the diphoton mass spectrum at low Higgs masses. We discuss the different signatures that can motivate new measurements and searches at the Large Hadron Collider.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.10027v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jon Butterworth, Hridoy Debnath, Pavel Fileviez Perez, Francis Mitchell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predictions from scoto-seesaw with $A_4$ modular symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.02363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.02363v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper's novelty lies in introducing a hybrid scoto-seesaw model rooted in $A_4$ discrete modular symmetry leading to several interesting phenomenological implications. The scoto-seesaw framework leads to generation of one mass square difference $( \Delta m^2_{\rm atm}$) using the type-I seesaw mechanism at the tree level. Additionally, the scotogenic contribution is vital in obtaining the other mass square difference ($\Delta m^2 _{\rm sol}$) at the loop level, thus providing a clear interpretation of the two different mass square differences. The non-trivial transformation of Yukawa couplings under the $A_4$ modular symmetry helps to explore neutrino phenomenology with a specific flavor structure of the mass matrix. In addition to predictions for neutrino mass ordering, mixing angles and CP phases, this setup leads to precise predictions for $\sum m_i$ as well as $|m_{ee}|$. In particular, the model predicts $\sum m_i \in (0.073,0.097)$ eV and $\left| m_{ee}\right| \in (3.15,6.66)\times 10^{-3} $ eV range; within reach of upcoming experiments. Furthermore, our model is also promising for addressing lepton flavor violations, i.e., $\ell_\alpha \to \ell_\beta \gamma$, $\ell_\alpha \to 3\ell_\beta$ and $\mu - e $ conversion rates while staying within the realm of current experimental limits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.02363v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2024.138635</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Lett. B 853 (2024) 138635</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ranjeet Kumar, Priya Mishra, Mitesh Kumar Behera, Rukmani Mohanta, Rahul Srivastava</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Gravity Effects on Fermionic Dark Matter and Gravitational Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12487</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.12487v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore the phenomenological consequences of breaking discrete global symmetries in quantum gravity (QG). We extend a previous scenario where discrete global symmetries are responsible for scalar dark matter (DM) and domain walls (DWs), to the case of fermionic DM, considered as a feebly interacting massive particle, which achieves the correct DM relic density via the freeze-in mechanism. Due to the mixing between DM and the standard model neutrinos, various indirect DM detection methods can be employed to constrain the QG scale, the scale of freeze-in, and the reheating temperature simultaneously. Since such QG symmetry breaking leads to DW annihilation, this may generate the characteristic gravitational wave background, and hence explain the recent observations of the gravitational wave spectrum by pulsar timing arrays. This work therefore highlights a tantalizing possibility of probing the effective scale of QG from observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.12487v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephen F. King, Rishav Roshan, Xin Wang, Graham White, Masahito Yamazak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic field dependence of the neutral pion longitudinal screening mass in the linear sigma model with quarks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.13068</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.13068v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We use the linear sigma model with quarks to study the magnetic-field-induced modifications on the longitudinal screening mass for the neutral pion at one-loop level. The effects of the magnetic field are introduced into the self-energy, which contains the contributions from all the model particles. We find that, to obtain a reasonable description for the behavior with the field strength, we need to account for the magnetic field dependence of the particle masses. We also find that the couplings need to decrease fast enough with the field strength to then reach constant and smaller values as compared to their vacuum ones. The results illustrate the need to treat the magnetic corrections to the particle masses and couplings in a self-consistent manner, accounting for the backreaction of the field effects for the magnetic field dependence of the rest of the particle species and couplings in the model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.13068v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.074019</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109, 074019 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alejandro Ayala, Ricardo L. S. Farias, L. A. Hern\'andez, Ana Julia Mizher, Javier Rend\'on, Cristian Villavicencio, R. Zamora</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for the production of dark matter in the framework of Mono-Z$^{\prime}$ portal at the ILC simulated electron-positron collisions at $\sqrt{s} = 500$ GeV</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.13924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.13924v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the present work, we study the possible production of the light neutral gauge boson (Z$^{\prime}$) candidates, which originated from a simplified-model scenario based on the Mono-Z$^{\prime}$ model, in association with dark matter. This study has been performed by studying events with dimuon plus missing transverse energy produced in the simulated electron-positron collisions at the foreseen International Linear Collider (ILC), operating at 500 GeV center of mass energy and integrated luminosity of 1000 fb$^{-1}$. In case no new physics has been discovered, we set upper limits at 95\% confidence level on the masses of various particles in the model as, spin-1 (Z$^{\prime}$), as well as the fermionic dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.13924v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sherif Elgammal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new subtraction scheme at NLO exploiting the privilege of kT-factorization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.02808v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a subtraction method for the calculation of real-radiation integrals at NLO in hybrid kT-factorization. The main difference with existing methods for collinear factorization is that we subtract the momentum recoil, occurring due to the mapping from an (n+1)-particle phase space to an n-particle phase space, from the initial-state momenta, instead of distributing it over the final-state momenta.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.02808v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Giachino, Andreas van Hameren, Grzegorz Ziarko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nuclear mass radius and pressure in the Skyrme model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.12984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.12984v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We compute the mass radius, scalar radius, tensor radius, baryon number radius and mechanical radius of nuclei with baryon number $B=1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,32,108$ in the Skyrme model. The relations between these radii and the nuclear gravitational form factors are investigated. We also compute the `pressure' distribution and find that it is negative in the core region for all the nuclei with $B&gt;1$. This suggests that the way mechanical stability is achieved in nuclei is qualitatively different than in the nucleon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.12984v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Garc\'ia Mart\'in-Caro, Miguel Huidobro, Yoshitaka Hatta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QCD with an Infrared Fixed Point and a Dilaton</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.13761</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.13761v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Following previous work we further explore the possibility that the chirally broken phase of gauge theories admits an infrared fixed point interpretation. The slope of the $\beta$ function, $\beta'_*$, is found to vanish at the infrared fixed point which has several attractive features such as logarithmic running. We provide a more in-depth analysis of our previous result that the mass anomalous assumes $\gamma_* = 1$ at the fixed point. The results are found to be consistent with ${\cal N}=1$ supersymmetric gauge theories. In a second part the specific properties of a dilaton, the (pseudo) Goldstone, due to spontaneous symmetry breaking are investigated. Dilaton soft theorems indicate that a soft dilaton mass can only originate from an operator of scaling dimension two. In the gauge theory this role is taken on by the $\bar qq$-operator. The QCD dilaton candidate, the $\sigma = f_0(500)$ meson is investigated. Singlet-octet mixing is found to be important. We briefly discuss the dilaton as a candidate for the Higgs boson, which relies on the ratio of dilaton to pion decay constant being close to unity. In QCD this is approximately satisfied but it is remains unclear if this is accidental or whether there is unknown reason behind it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.13761v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roman Zwicky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing Axionic Dark Matter during Gravitational Reheating</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.13821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.13821v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Assuming axions are potential dark matter (DM) candidate that make up all of the DM abundance, we discuss production of axions via (i) standard misalignment mechanism during the period of reheating and (ii) graviton-mediated 2-to-2 scattering of the inflaton and bath particles, where the inflaton $\phi$ oscillates in a monomial potential $V(\phi)\propto\phi^k$ with a general equation of state. Considering reheating takes place purely gravitationally, mediated by massless gravitons, we explore the viable region of the parameter space that agrees with the observed DM relic abundance, satisfying bounds from big bang nucleosynthesis (BBN) and cosmic microwave background radiation (CMB). We also discuss complementarity between dedicated axion search experiments and futuristic gravitational wave search facilities in probing the viable parameter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.13821v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Basabendu Barman, Arghyajit Datta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interactions of the Pseudoscalar Meson Octet and the Baryon Decuplet in the Continuum and a Finite Volume</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.14188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.14188v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study focuses on the interaction of the pseudoscalar meson octet and the baryon decuplet. In the continuum, it is observed that several $J^{P}=\frac32^-$ baryon resonances can be produced by the Weinberg-Tomozawa interaction in unitarized chiral perturbation theory, including the $N(1875)$, $\Sigma(1670)$, $\Sigma(1910)$, $\Xi(1820)$ and $\Omega(2012)$. Among them, the $\Xi(1820)$ and $\Sigma(1670)$ may exhibit a potential two-pole structures. The unitarized chiral perturbation approach is then applied as the underlying theory to predict the energy levels of these systems in a finite volume. These energy levels are well described by the $K$-matrix parameterization constrained by flavor SU(3) symmetry. With the parameters from the best fits, the poles extracted from the $K$-matrix parameterization closely correspond to those derived from the underlying chiral effective field theory, as long as they are close to physical region and not significantly higher than the lowest relevant threshold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.14188v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-024-12793-8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. C 84:408 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Teng Ji, Xiang-Kun Dong, Ulf-G. Mei{\ss}ner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The fermion self-energy and damping rate in a hot magnetized plasma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.04307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.04307v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We derive a general expression for the fermion self-energy in a hot magnetized plasma by using the Landau-level representation. In the one-loop approximation, the Dirac structure of the self-energy is characterized by five different functions that depend on the Landau-level index $n$ and the longitudinal momentum $p_z$. We derive general expressions for all five functions and obtain closed-form expressions for their imaginary parts. The latter receive contributions from three types of on-shell processes, which are interpreted in terms of Landau-level transitions, accompanied by a single photon (gluon) emission or absorption. By making use of the imaginary parts of the self-energy functions, we also derive the Landau-level dependent fermion damping rates $\Gamma_{n}(p_z)$ and study them numerically in a wide range of model parameters. We also demonstrate that the two-spin degeneracy of the Landau levels is lifted by the one-loop self-energy corrections. While the spin splitting of the damping rates is small, it may be important for some spin and chiral effects. We argue that the general method and the numerical results for the rates can have interesting applications in heavy-ion physics, astrophysics, and cosmology, where strongly magnetized QED or QCD plasmas are ubiquitous.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.04307v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ritesh Ghosh, Igor A. Shovkovy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-loop anomalous dimensions for small-$R$ jet versus hadronic fragmentation functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.05170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.05170v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the collinear fragmentation of highly energetic jets defined with a small jet radius. In particular, we investigate how the corresponding fragmentation functions differ from their hadronic counterpart defined in the common $\overline{\rm MS}$ scheme. We find that the anomalous dimensions governing the perturbative evolution of the two fragmentation functions differ starting at the two loop order. We compute for the first time the new anomalous dimensions at two loops and confirm our predictions by comparing the inclusive small-$R$ jet spectrum against a fixed order perturbative calculation at ${\cal O}(\alpha_s^2)$. To investigate the dependence of the anomalous dimension on the kinematic cutoff variable, we study the fragmentation functions of Cambridge jets defined with a transverse momentum cutoff as opposed to an angular cutoff $R$. We further study the evolution of the small-$R$ fragmentation function with an alternative cutoff scale, proportional to $z R$, representing the maximum possible transverse momentum of emissions within a jet. In these cases we find that the two-loop anomalous dimensions coincide with the $\overline{\rm MS}$ DGLAP ones, highlighting a correspondence between the $\overline{\rm MS}$ scheme and a transverse-momentum cutoff.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.05170v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Melissa van Beekveld, Mrinal Dasgupta, Basem Kamal El-Menoufi, Jack Helliwell, Alexander Karlberg, Pier Francesco Monni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-index SU(N) theories: QCD, Orientifolds, Super Yang-Mills, Lattice and Steven Weinberg's $\pi \pi$ scattering legacy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.05850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.05850v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: I review and improve on how two-index SU(N) gauge-fermion theories help access salient information about the large $N$ vacuum and spectrum of QCD, super Yang Mills and meson-meson scattering. The interplay with recent lattice simulations will be employed to deduce the size of $1/N^2$ corrections. Through the meson-meson scattering analysis I will honor Steven Weinberg's memory by showing how two-index extrapolations naturally accommodate the appearance of tetraquarks states crucial to unitarize meson-meson scattering at low energies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.05850v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Sannino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Algorithm to Parallelise Parton Showers on a GPU</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08692v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Single Instruction, Multiple Thread (SIMT) paradigm of GPU programming does not support the branching nature of a parton shower algorithm by definition. However, modern GPUs are designed to schedule threads with diverging processes independently, allowing them to handle such branches. With regular thread synchronization and careful treatment of the individual steps, one can simulate a parton shower on a GPU. We present a parallelized Sudakov veto algorithm designed to simulate parton branching on multiple events simultaneously. We also release a CUDA C++ program that generates matrix elements, showers partons, and computes jet rates and event shapes for LEP at 91.2 GeV on a GPU. To benchmark its performance, we also provide a near-identical C++ program designed to simulate events serially on a CPU. While the consequences of branching are not absent, we demonstrate that a GPU can provide the throughput of a many-core CPU. As an example, we show that the time taken to simulate 10^6 events on one NVIDIA TESLA V100 GPU is equivalent to that of 258 Intel Xeon E5-2620 CPUs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08692v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael H. Seymour, Siddharth Sule</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dilaton Forbidden Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07601v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dilaton effective field theory (dEFT) describes the long distance behavior of certain confining, near-conformal gauge theories that have been studied via lattice computation. Pseudo-Nambu-Goldstone bosons (pNGBs), emerging from the breaking of approximate, continuous, internal symmetries, are coupled to an additional scalar particle, the dilaton, arising from the spontaneous breaking of approximate scale invariance. This effective theory has been employed to study possible extensions of the standard model. In this paper, we propose a complementary role for dEFT, as a description of the dark matter of the universe, with the pNGBs identified as the dark-matter particles. We show that this theory provides a natural implementation of the ``forbidden'' dark matter mechanism, and we identify regions of parameter space for which the thermal history of dEFT yields the measured dark matter relic density.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07601v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Appelquist, James Ingoldby, Maurizio Piai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>D Pi scattering and D meson resonances from lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1208.4059</link>
      <description>arXiv:1208.4059v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The masses and widths of the broad scalar D_0^*(2400) and the axial D_1(2430) charmed-light resonances are extracted by simulating the corresponding D Pi and D* Pi scattering on the lattice. The resonance parameters are obtained using a Breit-Wigner fit of the elastic phase shifts. The resulting D_0^*(2400) mass is 351+/-21 MeV above the spin-average 1/4(m_D+3m_{D*}), in agreement with the experimental value of 347+/-29 MeV above. The resulting D_0^* to D Pi coupling g^{lat}=2.55+/-0.21 GeV is close to the experimental value g^{exp}&lt;=1.92+/-0.14 GeV, where g parametrizes the width $\Gamma\equiv g^2p^*/s$. The resonance parameters for the broad D_1(2430) are also found close to the experimental values; these are obtained by appealing to the heavy quark limit, where the neighboring resonance D_1(2420) is narrow. The calculated I=1/2 scattering lengths are a_0=0.81+/-0.14 fm for D Pi and a_0=0.81+/-0.17 fm for D* Pi scattering. The simulation of the scattering in these channels incorporates quark-antiquark as well as multi-hadron interpolators, and the distillation method is used for contractions. In addition, the ground and several excited charm-light and charmonium states with various J^P are calculated using standard quark-antiquark interpolators. Our simulations are done in lattice QCD with two-dynamical light quarks at a mass corresponding to m_\pi\approx 266 MeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1208.4059v3</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.87.034501</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Mohler, Sasa Prelovsek, R. M. Woloshyn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Density Matrix Formalism for PT-Symmetric Non-Hermitian Hamiltonians with the Lindblad Equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.02445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2006.02445v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the presence of Lindblad decoherence, i.e. dissipative effects in an open quantum system due to interaction with an environment, we examine the transition probabilities between the eigenstates in the two-level quantum system described by non-Hermitian Hamiltonians with the Lindblad equation, for which the parity-time-reversal (PT) symmetry is conserved. First, the density matrix formalism for PT-symmetric non-Hermitian Hamiltonian systems is developed. It is shown that the Lindblad operators $L^{}_j$ are pseudo-Hermitian, namely, $\eta L^{}_j \eta^{-1} = L^\dagger_j$ with $\eta$ being a linear and positive-definite metric, and respect the PT symmetry as well. We demonstrate that the generalized density matrix $\rho^{}_{\rm G}(t) \equiv \rho(t) \eta$, instead of the normalized density matrix $\rho^{}_{\rm N}(t) \equiv \rho(t)/{\rm tr}\left[\rho(t)\right]$, should be implemented for the calculation of the transition probabilities in accordance with the linearity requirement. Second, the density matrix formalism is used to derive the transition probabilities in general cases of PT-symmetric non-Hermitian Hamiltonians. In some concrete examples, we calculate compact analytical formulas for the transition probabilities and explore their main features with numerical illustrations. We also make a comparison between our present results and our previous ones using state vectors in the absence of Lindblad decoherence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2006.02445v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.103.022218</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 103, 022218 (2021)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tommy Ohlsson, Shun Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the complex structure of Yang-Mills theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.09333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2202.09333v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the coupled set of spectral Dyson-Schwinger equations in Yang-Mills theory for ghost and gluon propagators, which gives us access to the ghost and gluon spectral functions. The set-up is used for a systematic analytic evaluation of the constraints on generalised spectral representations in Yang-Mills theory that are most relevant for informed spectral reconstructions. We also provide numerical results for the coupled set of spectral functions for a large range of potential mass gaps of the gluon, and discuss the limitations and extensions of the present work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2202.09333v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Horak, Jan M. Pawlowski, Nicolas Wink</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Remnants of quark model in lattice QCD simulation in the Coulomb gauge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.13299</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.13299v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Aiming at the relation between QCD and the quark model, we consider projections of gauge configurations generated in quenched lattice QCD simulations in the Coulomb gauge on a 16$^{\rm 3}$ $\rm \times$ 32, $\rm \beta$ = 6.0 lattice. First, we focus on a fact that the static quark-antiquark potential is independent of spatial gauge fields. We explicitly confirm this by performing $\vec{A}$ = 0 projection, where spatial gauge fields are all set to zero. We also apply the $\vec{A}$ = 0 projection to light hadron masses and find that nucleon and delta baryon masses are almost degenerate, suggesting vanishing of the color-magnetic interactions. After considering the physical meaning of the $\vec{A}$ = 0 projection, we next propose a generalized projection, where spatial gauge fields are expanded in terms of Faddeev-Popov eigenmodes and only some eigenmodes are left. We apply the proposed projection to light hadron and glueball masses and find that the N-$\rm \Delta$ and 0$^{\rm ++}$-2$^{\rm ++}$ mass splittings become evident when projected with more than 33 (0.10 \%) low-lying eigenmodes, suggesting emergence of the color-magnetic interactions. We also find that the original hadron masses are approximately reproduced with just 328 (1.00 \%) low-lying eigenmodes. These findings indicate an important role of low-lying eigenmodes on hadron masses and would be useful in clarifying the relation between QCD and the quark model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.13299v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroki Ohata, Hideo Suganuma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativistic BGK hydrodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.00544</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.00544v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Bhatnagar-Gross-Krook (BGK) collision kernel is employed in the Boltzmann equation to formulate relativistic dissipative hydrodynamics. In this formulation, we find that there remains freedom of choosing a matching condition that affects the scalar transport in the system. We also propose a new collision kernel which, unlike BGK collision kernel, is valid in the limit of zero chemical potential and derive relativistic first-order dissipative hydrodynamics using it. We study the effects of this new formulation on the coefficient of bulk viscosity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.00544v3</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-024-12784-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. C 84, 417 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pracheta Singha, Samapan Bhadury, Arghya Mukherjee, Amaresh Jaiswal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational to Coulomb force ratio and the origin of the Cosmic magnetic field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.14930</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.14930v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Aims: The origin of the seeds of galactic magnetic fields is a subject that remains under debate; here we will explore a new possible mechanism that could provide such seed from charge asymmetries in slowly rotating protogalaxies. Methods: We use current knowledge of galaxy formation and evolution to estimate that a charge imbalance of $1$ every $\sim10^{38\pm 5}$ charge carriers in slowly rotating protogalaxies can provide an alternative mechanism to produce such seeds. Results: The gravitationally induced charge imbalance within plasmas in hydrostatic equilibrium lies in the upper range of this estimation, and is higher than possible surviving primordial charge asymmetries. We conclude that this known, but unappreciated thermodynamic property of plasmas in gravitational fields, may have important cosmological consequences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.14930v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nelson D. Padilla, Juan Racker, Ignacio J. Araya, Federico Stasyszyn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-Driven Constraints on Cosmic-Ray Diffusion: Probing Self-Generated Turbulence in the Milky Way</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.17150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.17150v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We employ a data-driven approach to investigate the rigidity and spatial dependence of the diffusion of cosmic rays in the turbulent magnetic field of the Milky Way. Our analysis combines data sets from the experiments Voyager, AMS-02, CALET, and DAMPE for a range of cosmic ray nuclei from protons to oxygen. Our findings favor models with a smooth behavior in the diffusion coefficient, indicating a good qualitative agreement with the predictions of self-generated magnetic turbulence models. Instead, the current cosmic-ray data do not exhibit a clear preference for or against inhomogeneous diffusion, which is also a prediction of these models. Future progress might be possible by combining cosmic-ray data with gamma rays or radio observations, enabling a more comprehensive exploration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.17150v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mattia Di Mauro, Michael Korsmeier, Alessandro Cuoco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semiclassics for the QCD vacuum structure through $T^2$-compactification with the baryon-'t Hooft flux</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.04320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.04320v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study QCD vacuum structure with the topological $\theta$ angle using a recently proposed semiclassical approach on $\mathbb{R}^2 \times T^2$ with the 't Hooft and baryon magnetic fluxes. Under the assumption of adiabatic continuity in this setup, the confining vacuum can be described by the dilute gas of center vortices. With this semiclassical approach, we derive the 2d effective description at small $T^2$ and successfully explain the reasonable theta dependence of the QCD vacuum: In the one-flavor QCD at $\theta = \pi$, the $CP$ symmetry is spontaneously broken for quark mass above a critical value and restored for a subcritical mass, while the $CP$ symmetry is always spontaneously broken in the multi-flavor QCD at $\theta = \pi$. From our semiclassical description, we discuss implications to the $4$d chiral Lagrangian and propose how the $\eta'$ meson should be incorporated in consistent with known global structures: The periodicity of the $\eta'$ should be extended from the naive one $2\pi$ to $2\pi N$. Additionally, we revisit the phase diagram of $N_f = 1+1$ and $N_f = 1+1+1$ QCD on the up and down quark mass plane, confirming and refining the existence of the $CP$-broken Dashen phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.04320v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yui Hayashi, Yuya Tanizaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\Lambda$ polarization in very high energy heavy ion collisions as a probe of the Quark-Gluon Plasma formation and properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14295v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We have studied the spin polarization of $\Lambda$ hyperons in heavy ion collisions at center-of-mass energies $\sqrt{s_{NN}} = 200$ GeV and $\sqrt{s_{NN}} = 5.02$ TeV carried out at RHIC and LHC colliders. We have calculated the mean spin vector at local thermodynamic equilibrium, including all known first-order terms in the gradients of the thermo-hydrodynamic fields, assuming that the hadronization hypersurface has a uniform temperature. We have also included the feed-down contributions to the polarization of $\Lambda$ stemming from the decays of polarized $\Sigma^*$ and $\Sigma^0$ hyperons. The obtained results are in good agreement with the data. In general, the component of the spin vector along the global angular momentum, orthogonal to the reaction plane, shows strong sensitivity to the initial longitudinal flow velocity. Furthermore, the longitudinal component of the spin vector turns out to be very sensitive to the bulk viscosity of the plasma at the highest LHC energy. Therefore, the azimuthal dependence of spin polarization can effectively constrain the initial hydrodynamic conditions and the transport coefficients of the Quark Gluon Plasma.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14295v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Palermo, Eduardo Grossi, Iurii Karpenko, Francesco Becattini</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
