<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph</link>
    <description>hep-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2024 04:00:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter-induced electron excitations in silicon and germanium with Deep Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07053</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07053v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We train a deep neural network (DNN) to output rates of dark matter (DM) induced electron excitations in silicon and germanium detectors. Our DNN provides a massive speedup of around $5$ orders of magnitude relative to existing methods (i.e. QEdark-EFT), allowing for extensive parameter scans in the event of an observed DM signal. The network is also lighter and simpler to use than alternative computational frameworks based on a direct calculation of the DM-induced excitation rate. The DNN can be downloaded $\href{https://github.com/urdshals/DEDD}{\text{here}}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07053v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riccardo Catena, Einar Urdshals</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Re-Simulation-based Self-Supervised Learning for Pre-Training Foundation Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07066</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07066v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Self-Supervised Learning (SSL) is at the core of training modern large machine learning models, providing a scheme for learning powerful representations that can be used in a variety of downstream tasks. However, SSL strategies must be adapted to the type of training data and downstream tasks required. We propose RS3L, a novel simulation-based SSL strategy that employs a method of re-simulation to drive data augmentation for contrastive learning. By intervening in the middle of the simulation process and re-running simulation components downstream of the intervention, we generate multiple realizations of an event, thus producing a set of augmentations covering all physics-driven variations available in the simulator. Using experiments from high-energy physics, we explore how this strategy may enable the development of a foundation model; we show how R3SL pre-training enables powerful performance in downstream tasks such as discrimination of a variety of objects and uncertainty mitigation. In addition to our results, we make the RS3L dataset publicly available for further studies on how to improve SSL strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07066v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philip Harris, Michael Kagan, Jeffrey Krupa, Benedikt Maier, Nathaniel Woodward</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is the effective potential, effective for dynamics?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07084</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07084v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We critically examine the applicability of the effective potential within dynamical situations and find, in short, that the answer is negative. An important caveat of the use of an effective potential in dynamical equations of motion is an explicit violation of energy conservation.
  An \emph{adiabatic} effective potential is introduced in a consistent quasi-static approximation, and its narrow regime of validity is discussed. Two ubiquitous instances in which even the adiabatic effective potential is not valid in dynamics are studied in detail: parametric amplification in the case of oscillating mean fields, and spinodal instabilities associated with spontaneous symmetry breaking. In both cases profuse particle production is directly linked to the failure of the effective potential to describe the dynamics. We introduce a consistent, renormalized, energy conserving dynamical framework that is amenable to numerical implementation. Energy conservation leads to the emergence of asymptotic highly excited, entangled stationary states from the dynamical evolution. As a corollary, decoherence via dephasing of the density matrix in the adiabatic basis is argued to lead to an emergent entropy, formally equivalent to the entanglement entropy. The results suggest novel characterization of asymptotic equilibrium states in terms of order parameter vs. energy density.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07084v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathan Herring, Shuyang Cao, Daniel Boyanovsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancement of $p$-wave dark matter annihilation by quasi-bound states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07108</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07108v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We scrutinize the Sommerfeld enhancement in dark matter pair annihilation for $p$-wave and higher-$\ell$ partial waves. For the Yukawa potential these feature a super-resonant Breit-Wigner peak in their velocity-dependence close to Sommerfeld resonances as well as a universal scaling with velocity for all $\ell\geq 1$ that differs from the $s$-wave case. We provide a quantum mechanical explanation for these phenomena in terms of quasi-bound states sustained by the centrifugal barrier of the partial-wave potential, and give approximate WKB expressions capturing the main effects. The impact of quasi-bound states is exemplified for wino dark matter and models with light mediators, with a focus on indirect detection signals. We note that quasi-bound states can also explain similar peaks in the bound-state formation and self-scattering cross sections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07108v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Beneke, Tobias Binder, Lorenzo De Ros, Mathias Garny</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The phase of the electromagnetic form factor of the pion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07121</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07121v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We employ a dispersion relation that allows to recover the phase of the electromagnetic form factor of the pion from its absolute value above threshold. Compared to alternative approaches building on the phase, this approach builds on experimental input directly accessible at colliders. Employing the precise datasets from the $e^+e^-\to\pi^+\pi^-$ reaction, we obtain the phase of the electromagnetic form factor up to 2.5 GeV, well beyond standard dispersive approaches. In addition, we separate the isovector and isoscalar components, that allows to extract the $P$-wave $\pi\pi$ phase shift. We also provide relevant results, including the radius of the form factor and bounds in the spacelike region.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07121v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrique Ruiz Arriola, Pablo Sanchez-Puertas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dimensional Regularization and Two-Loop Vacuum Polarization Operator: Master Integrals, Analytic Results and Energy Shifts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07127v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a complete reevaluation of the irreducible two-loop vacuum-polarization correction to the photon propagator in quantum electrodynamics, i.e. with an electron-positron pair in the fermion propagators. The integration is carried out by reducing the integrations to a limited set of master integrals, which are calculated using integration-by-parts identities. Dimensional regularization is used in D = 4-2*epsilon dimensions, and on-mass shell renormalization is employed. The one-loop effect is given to order epsilon, to be combined with the 1/epsilon divergence of the two-loop amplitude. Master integrals are given. Final evaluations of two-loop energy shifts for 1S, 2S, and 2P states are done analytically, and results are presented, with an emphasis on muonic hydrogen. For relativistic Dirac-Coulomb reference states, higher-order coefficients are obtained for the Zalpha-expansion. We compare the results obtained to the existing literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07127v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Laporta, U. D. Jentschura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-orbit correlations in the nucleon in the large-$N_{c}$ limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07186v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the twist-3 spin-orbit correlations of quarks described by the nucleon matrix elements of the parity-odd rank-2 tensor QCD operator (the parity-odd partner of the QCD energy-momentum tensor). Our treatment is based on the effective dynamics emerging from the spontaneous breaking of chiral symmetry and the mean-field picture of the nucleon in the large-$N_c$ limit. The twist-3 QCD operators are converted to effective operators, in which the QCD interactions are replaced by spin-flavor-dependent chiral interactions of the quarks with the pion field. We compute the nucleon matrix elements of the twist-3 effective operators and discuss the role of the chiral interactions in the spin-orbit correlations. We derive the first-quantized representation in the mean-field picture and develop a quantum-mechanical interpretation. The chiral interactions give rise to new spin-orbit couplings and qualitatively change the correlations compared to the quark model picture. We also derive the twist-3 matrix elements in the topological soliton picture where the quarks are integrated out (skyrmion). The methods used here can be extended to other QCD operators describing higher-twist nucleon structure and generalized parton distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07186v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>June-Young Kim, Ho-Yeon Won, Hyun-Chul Kim, Christian Weiss</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Challenges in the extraction of physics beyond the Standard Model from electron scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07327v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Precise measurements of electron and positron scattering, including parity violation, offer great promise in the search for physics beyond the Standard Model. In this context it is crucial to understand the corrections which might arise from charge symmetry violation, as well as the less well known strange and charm quark distributions. Our analysis, using state of the art parton distributions, suggests that these contributions lead to corrections in the extraction of the weak couplings $g^{eq}_{AV}$ and $g^{eq}_{VA}$ of the order $(1-2)\%$, while they are as large as $4\%$ for $g^{eq}_{AA}$, at a typical scale of $Q^2 = 10\ {\rm GeV}^2$. These results underline the importance of carrying out high precision measurements, which will not only provide information on physics beyond the Standard Model but also reduce the current uncertainties on our knowledge of the strange and charm quark distributions in the proton.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07327v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>X. G. Wang, A. W. Thomas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The potential of QQQ in the anisotropic background</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07330v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we use the AdS/CFT correspondence to study the behavior of a triply heavy baryon within anisotropic backgrounds. Beginning with the total action of the three quarks, we derive the balance equation for the three-quark system and compute the separation distance and potential energy. Our results reveal a consistent decrease in both the separation distance and potential energy for the A configuration and the B configuration as the anisotropy coefficient $a$ increases. This suggests that the presence of an anisotropic background promotes the dissolution of the three-quark system. Additionally, we compare the potential energies of the A and B configurations and observe that the A configuration has a slightly smaller potential energy, suggesting greater stability compared to the B configuration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07330v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing Zhou, Kazem Bitaghsir Fadafan, Xun Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quenching and flow of charm and bottom quarks via semi-leptonic decay of $D$ and $B$ mesons in Pb+Pb collisions at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07419</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07419v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Heavy flavor particles provide important probes of the microscopic structure and thermodynamic properties of the quark-gluon plasma (QGP) produced in high-energy nucleus-nucleus collisions. We study the energy loss and flow of charm and bottom quarks inside the QGP via the nuclear modification factor ($R_\mathrm{AA}$) and elliptic flow coefficient ($v_2$) of their decayed leptons in heavy-ion collisions at the LHC. The dynamical evolution of the QGP is performed using the (3+1)-dimensional viscous hydrodynamics model CLVisc; the evolution of heavy quarks inside the QGP is simulated with our improved Langevin model that takes into account both collisional and radiative energy loss of heavy quarks; the hadronization of heavy quarks is simulated via our hybrid coalescence-fragmentation model; and the semi-leptonic decay of $D$ and $B$ mesons is simulated via PYTHIA. By using the same spatial diffusion coefficient for charm and bottom quarks, we obtain smaller $R_\mathrm{AA}$ and larger $v_2$ of charm decayed leptons than bottom decayed leptons, indicating stronger energy loss of charm quarks than bottom quarks inside the QGP within our current model setup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07419v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shu-Qing Li, Wen-Jing Xing, Shanshan Cao, Guang-You Qin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatially oscillating correlation functions in $\left(2+1\right)$-dimensional four-fermion models: The mixing of scalar and vector modes at finite density</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07430v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we demonstrate that the mixing of scalar and vector condensates produces spatially oscillating, but exponentially damped correlation functions in fermionic theories at finite density and temperature. We find a regime exhibiting this oscillatory behavior in a Gross-Neveu-type model that also features vector interactions within the mean-field approximation. The existence of this regime aligns with expectations based on symmetry arguments, that are also applicable to QCD at finite baryon density. We compute the phase diagram including both homogeneous phases and regions with spatially oscillating, exponentially damped correlation functions at finite temperature and chemical potential for different strengths of the vector coupling. Furthermore, we find that inhomogeneous condensates are disfavored compared to homogeneous ones akin to previous findings without vector interactions. We show that our results are valid for a broad class of $\left(2+1\right)$-dimensional models with local four-fermion interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07430v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marc Winstel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Baryonic Vortex Phase and Magnetic Field Generation in QCD with Isospin and Baryon Chemical Potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07433</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07433v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a novel baryonic vortex phase in low energy dense QCD with finite baryon and isospin chemical potentials. It is known that the homogeneous charged pion condensate takes up the ground state in the presence of the isospin chemical potential, and therein arises the Abrikosov vortex lattice with an applied magnetic field. We first demonstrate that a vortex sustaining the same quantized magnetic flux as the conventional Abrikosov vortex, carries a baryon number captured by the third homotopy group of Skyrmions, given the added modulation of the neutral pion inside the vortex core. Such a state is therefore dubbed the baryonic vortex. We reveal that when the baryon chemical potential is above a critical value, the baryonic vortex has negative tension measured from the charged pion condensation. It implies the baryonic vortex phase would emerge spontaneously without any external magnetic field, and take over the ground state at high density. This new phase contributes to the comprehension of QCD phase diagram and could be relevant to the generation of magnetic fields inside neutron stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07433v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zebin Qiu, Muneto Nitta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic spin alignment of $J/\psi$ meson in magnetized plasma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07468v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the mass spectra and spin alignment of vector meson $J/\psi$ in a thermal magnetized background using the gauge/gravity duality. Utilizing a soft wall model for the QGP background and a massive vector field for the $J/\psi$ meson, we delve into the meson's spectral function and spin parameters $(\lambda_{\theta},\, \lambda_\varphi,\,\lambda_{\theta\varphi})$ for different cases, assessing their response to variations in magnetic field strength, momentum, and temperature. We initially examine scenarios where a meson's momentum aligns parallel to the magnetic field in helicity frame. Our results reveal a magnetic field-induced positive $\lambda_\theta^\text{H}$ for low meson momentum, transitioning to negative with increased momentum. As a comparison, we also study the case of momentum perpendicular to the magnetic field and find the direction of magnetic field does not affect the qualitative behavior for the $eB$-dependence of $\lambda_\theta^\text{H}$. Moreover, we apply our model to real heavy-ion collisions for three different spin quantization directions. Further comparisons with experimental data show qualitative agreement for spin parameters $\lambda_{\theta}$ and $\lambda_\varphi$ in the helicity and Collins-Soper frames.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07468v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan-Qing Zhao, Xin-Li Sheng, Si-Wen Li, Defu Hou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The low-mass enhancement of kaon pairs in $B^+\to\bar{D}^{(*)0}K^+\bar{K}^0$ and $B^0\to D^{(*)-}K^+\bar{K}^0$ decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07499</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07499v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Very recently, the Belle~II collaboration presented a measurement for the decays $B^+\to\bar{D}^{(*)0} K^+\bar{K}^0$ and $B^0\to D^{(*)-}K^+\bar{K}^0$, the bulk of observed $m(K^+ K_S^0)$ distributions showing low-mass structures in all four channels. In this work, we study the contributions of $\rho(770,1450)^+$, $a_2(1320)^+$ and $a_0(980,1450)^+$ resonances to these decay processes. The intermediate states $\rho(770,1450)^+$ are found to dominate the low-mass distribution of kaon pairs roughly contributing to half of the total branching fraction in each of the four decay channels. The contribution of the tensor $a_2(1320)^+$ meson is found to be negligible. Near the threshold of the kaon pair, the state $a_0(980)^+$ turns out to be much less important than expected, not being able to account for the enhancement of events in that energy region observed in the $B^+\to\bar{D}^{(*)0} K^+\bar{K}^0$ decays. Further studies both from the theoretical and experimental sides are needed to elucidate the role of the non-resonant contributions governing the formation of $K^+\bar{K}^0$ pairs near their threshold in these decay processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07499v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Fei Wang, Li-Fei Yang, Ai-Jun Ma, \`Angels Ramos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is there (no) collective flow in \textit{pp} collisions?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07512v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The transverse momentum spectra and their multiplicity dependence serve as key tools for extracting parameters that can be compared with theoretical models. This comparison aims to establish the behaviour and nature of the system created in the collision. Over the past decade, the scientific community has extensively studied the possibility of a system analogous to quark-gluon plasma, predicted in heavy nuclei collisions, also existing in collisions involving light nuclei and proton-proton collisions. We have reanalysed the experimental data published by the ALICE Collaboration at the LHC, exploring a seemingly universal feature of transverse momentum spectra of charged particles. We have identified a specific range where the contribution of the hard part is nonexistent for the studied multiplicities. We present the dependence of the mean transverse momenta obtained in the soft and soft+hard (mixes) parts and discuss the results in the context of the ongoing controversy regarding the existence of collectivity in small systems. Finally, we also discuss possible refinements of the analyses concerning the use of statistical parameters of higher order, aimed at better distinguishing the agreement of theoretical and Monte Carlo models with the data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07512v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G\'abor B\'ir\'o, Leonid Serkin, Guy Pai\'c, Gergely G\'abor Barnaf\"oldi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic spin alignment for vector mesons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07522v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a general framework for studying the spin alignment $\rho_{00}$ for flavorless vector mesons by using the gauge/gravity duality. Focusing on the dilepton production through vector meson decay, we derive the relation between production rates at each spin channel and meson's spectral function, which can be evaluated by holographic models for a strongly coupled system. As examples, we study $\rho_{00}$ for $J/\psi$ and $\phi$ mesons, induced by the relative motion to a thermal background, within the soft-wall model. We show that $\rho_{00}$ in the helicity frame for $J/\psi$ and $\phi$ mesons have positive and negative deviations from 1/3 at $T=150$ MeV, respectively, which consequently leads to different properties for their global spin alignments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07522v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin-Li Sheng, Yan-Qing Zhao, Si-Wen Li, Francesco Becattini, Defu Hou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Monochromatic Photon Emission from Millicharged Co-Interacting Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07528v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a millicharged co-interacting dark matter scenario, where the primary dark matter constituent is the dark photon $A'$ and the secondary component is the fermion $\chi$. In this model, $\chi$ interacts with $A'$ via a $U(1)'$ interaction while being millicharged with respect to normal photons. Our investigation focuses on the oscillation of $A'$ dark matter into photons within the background of $\chi$ particles, revealing that the $A'-\chi$ scattering rate benefits from a Bose enhancement of the $A'$ final state. As the oscillation production rate is directly linked to the scattering rate, the conversion of $A'$ dark matter into monochromatic photons experiences significant amplification owing to this Bose enhancement, especially when the scattering rate $\Gamma_{\rm sca}$ approaches the dark photon mass $m_{A'}$. These converted monochromatic photons are detectable through radio telescopes and can induce distortions in the Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) spectrum. We find that the sensitivity of radio telescopes and the constraints imposed by CMB distortion on the kinetic mixing parameter are notably heightened compared to scenarios without the subdominant millicharged dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07528v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingxuan Du, Jia Liu, Xiao-Ping Wang, Tianhao Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radiative corrections and threshold resummed predictions to pseudoscalar Higgs boson production in QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07615v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This thesis studies the pseudoscalar Higgs boson production via gluon fusion in the EFT framework in a CP-conserving model. First, it presents the di-pseudoscalar Higgs boson production cross-section via gluon fusion till NNLO with the results valid for the pseudoscalar Higgs boson of MSSM and 2HDM with small tan $\beta$ by adjusting the top Yukawa coupling. We have used dimensional regularization to regulate the UV and IR divergences while carefully treating the Levi-Civita tensor and $\gamma_5$. Unlike the amplitudes involving a pair of scalar Higgs bosons, we do not need UV contact counter terms. We used Catani's predictions to factorize the IR singularities, and our IR poles agreed with Catani's predictions. Our results are essential for studies on producing a pair of pseudoscalar Higgs bosons at the LHC up to NNLO accuracy. This thesis also includes the next-to-soft-virtual (NSV) resummed corrections to $\overline{\text{NNLL}}$ accuracy, which are also matched to the NNLO cross-sections for a pseudoscalar Higgs boson production via gluon fusion. These NSV corrections are potentially significant compared to the conventional soft-virtual (SV) logarithms. We have estimated the uncertainties due to the choice of various PDFs and those due to the renormalization and factorization scales. The scale uncertainties show improvement for renormalization scale variation only, which suggests that NSV contributions from other parton channels and beyond NSV contributions in the gluon fusion channel are necessary for improved stability. We also studied the production cross-sections for mixed scalar-pseudoscalar states and their impact on QCD cross-sections for different values of the mixing angle $\alpha$. The study indicates the necessity of improving the precision results for the pseudoscalar Higgs boson up to an order comparable to that of the scalar Higgs boson.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07615v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arunima Bhattacharya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing anomalous $Z\gamma\gamma\gamma$ couplings at a future muon collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07689v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The sensitivity to anomalous quartic gauge couplings (AQGCs) of the $\gamma\gamma\gamma Z$ interaction is studied in the $\mu^+\mu^- \rightarrow \mu^+\gamma\gamma \mu^-$ scattering at a future muon collider with unpolarized beams. The anomalous $\gamma\gamma\gamma Z$ vertex is described by two couplings, $\zeta_1$ and $\zeta_2$. The differential and total cross sections are calculated for the center-of-mass energies of 3 TeV, 14 TeV, and 100 TeV. For these values of the collision energy the $95\%$ C.L. exclusion regions for AQGCs are obtained depending on the systematic error. In particular, for the 14 TeV muon collider with the integrated luminosity $L = 20$ ab$^{-1}$ the best sensitivities are derived to be $\zeta_1 = 3.1 \times 10^{-5}$ TeV$^{-4}$ and $\zeta_2 = 6.5 \times 10^{-5}$ TeV$^{-4}$. These constraints are three orders of magnitude stronger than the bounds obtained for the 27 TeV HE-LHC with $L = 15$ ab$^{-1}$. At the 100 TeV muon collider with $L = 1000$ ab$^{-1}$ AQGCs can be probed up to $(1.64 \div 3.4) \times 10^{-8}$ TeV$^{-4}$. The partial-wave unitarity constraints on couplings $\zeta_1$, $\zeta_2$ are evaluated. It is shown that the unitarity is not violated in the region of the AQGCs examined in the present paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07689v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Amarkhail, S. C. \.Inan, A. V. Kisselev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Categorizing $SU(3)_f$ representations of scalar mesons by $J/\psi$ decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07701v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the possibilities of categorizing $SU(3)_f$ representations of scalar mesons through $J/\psi\to SV$ and $\gamma S$, with $S$ ($V$) being the scalar(vector) mesons. We find that $f_0(500)$ and $f_0(980)$ are singlet and octet states, respectively; which both belong to a nonet of the $SU(3)_f$ flavor symmetry. In addition, we determine the singlet-octet mixing angle of $\theta = (84.2\pm13.9)^{\circ}$ between $f_0(500)$ and $f_0(980)$, which supports the quark-antiquark ($q\bar{q}$) hypothesis. For the scalar mesons in the range of 1-2 GeV, containing two of $f_0(1370,\ 1500,\ 1700)$, we discuss the mixings between $q\bar{q}$ and glueballs. Our numerical results suggest that $f_0(1370 (1500))$ has the a significant component of $n\bar{n}$ ($s\bar{s}$), while $f_0(1710)$ is likely composed of the scalar glueball.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07701v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao-Qiang Geng, Chia-Wei Liu, Xiao Yu, Ao-Wen Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zitterbewegung CPT violation in neutral kaons system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07703v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The observed CP violation in neutral kaons experiments is explained as an interplay between two oscillations in the earth's Schwarzschild geometry: (i) mixing associated with second order weak coupling and (ii) quark's zitterbewegung. This violation is in fact a CPT violation with T conservation rather than a T violation with CPT conservation. The Hermitian evolution of a stable kaons system leads to the identification of this CPT violation. Then, the finite lifetime of the short-lived kaon rotates the violation parameter such that it appears as a T violation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07703v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Marcel Rax</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higgs photon associated production in a Two Higgs Doublet Type-II Seesaw Model at future electron-positron colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07722v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We studied the one-loop prediction for the single production of a Higgs-like boson in association with a photon in electron-positron collisions in the context of two Higgs doublet type-II seesaw model (2HDMcT). We explored to what extent the new scalars in the (2HDMcT) spectrum affect its production cross-section, the ratio $R_{\gamma h_1}$ as well as the signal strengths $R_{\gamma Z}$ and $R_{\gamma \gamma}$ when $h_1$ is identified with the observed $SM $ Higgs boson within the $2HDMcT$ delimited parameter space. More specifically, we focused on $e^+e^- \to h_1\gamma$ process at one-loop, and analyzed how it evolves under a full set of theoretical constraints and the available experimental data, including $B\to X_s\gamma$ constraint at 95$\%$ C.L. Our analysis showed that these observables are particularly sensitive to the parameters $\alpha_1$, $\lambda_{7}$, $\lambda_{9}$, the trilinear Higgs couplings and to the charged Higgs masses. We found that $\sigma (e^+e^- \to h_1\gamma)$ can significantly be enhanced up to $8.1\,\, 10^{-2}$ fb, so exceeding the Standard Model prediction. Additionally, as a byproduct, we also found that $R_{\gamma h_1}$ is entirely correlated with both the $h_1\to\gamma\gamma$ and $h_1\to\gamma Z$ signal strengths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07722v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Ait Ouazghour, M. Chabab, K. Goure</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complete Minimal Left-Right Symmetric Model File</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07756v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a comprehensive implementation of the minimal Left-Right symmetric model within a FeynRules model file. We derive the complete set of mass spectra and mixings for the charged and neutral gauge bosons, would-be-Goldstones and gauge fixing, together with the ghost Lagrangian. In the scalar sector, we analytically re-derive all the massive states with mixings and devise a physical input scheme, which expresses the model couplings in terms of masses and mixing angles of all states. Fermion couplings are determined in closed form, including the Dirac mixing in the neutrino sector, evaluated explicitly with the Cayley-Hamilton method. We calculate the one loop next-to-leading QCD corrections and provide a complete UFO file for NLO studies, demonstrated on relevant benchmarks. We provide various restricted variants of the model file with different gauges, massless states, neutrino hierarchies and parity violating $g_L \neq g_R$ gauge couplings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07756v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Kriewald, Miha Nemev\v{s}ek, Fabrizio Nesti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Models of Accidental Dark Matter with a Fundamental Scalar</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07759v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider models of accidental dark matter, namely models in which the dark matter is a composite state that is stable thanks to an accidental symmetry of the theory. The fundamental constituents are vectorlike fermions, taken to be fragments of representations of the grand unifying gauge group $SU(5)$, as well as a scalar singlet. All the new fields are charged under a new confining gauge group, which we take to be $SU(N)$, leading to models with complex dark matter. We analyse the models in the context of $SU(5)$ grand unification with a non-standard approach recently proposed in the literature. The advantage of including the scalar mainly resides in the fact that it allows to break several undesired accidental symmetries leading to a larger set of viable models with respect to previous literature, in which only fermions (or only scalars) were considered. Moreover these models present distinct novelties, namely dark states with non-zero baryon and lepton number and the existence of composite hybrid states of fermions and scalars. We identify phenomena that are specific to the inclusion of the scalar and discuss possibilities to test this setup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07759v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Palmisano, Francesco Rescigno, Federica Troni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological Amplitudes in Power-Law FRW Universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07050v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The correlators of large-scale fluctuations belong to the most important observables in modern cosmology. Recently, there have been considerable efforts in analytically understanding the cosmological correlators and the related wavefunction coefficients, which we collectively call cosmological amplitudes. In this work, we provide a set of simple rules to directly write down analytical answers for arbitrary tree-level amplitudes of conformal scalars with time-dependent interactions in power-law FRW universe. With the recently proposed family-tree decomposition method, we identify an over-complete set of multivariate hypergeometric functions, called family trees, to which all tree-level conformal scalar amplitudes can be easily reduced. Our method yields series expansions and monodromies of family trees in various kinematic limits, together with a large number of functional identities. The family trees are in a sense generalizations of polylogarithms and do reduce to polylogarithmic expressions for the cubic coupling in inflationary limit. We further show that all family trees can be decomposed into linear chains by taking shuffle products of all subfamilies, with which we find simple connection between bulk time integrals and boundary energy integrals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07050v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bingchu Fan, Zhong-Zhi Xianyu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating Meson Scattering on Spin Quantum Simulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07061v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Studying high-energy collisions of composite particles, such as hadrons and nuclei, is an outstanding goal for quantum simulators. However, preparation of hadronic wave packets has posed a significant challenge, due to the complexity of hadrons and the precise structure of wave packets. This has limited demonstrations of hadron scattering on quantum simulators to date. Observations of confinement and composite excitations in quantum spin systems have opened up the possibility to explore scattering dynamics in spin models. In this article, we develop two methods to create entangled spin states corresponding to wave packets of composite particles in analog quantum simulators of Ising spin Hamiltonians. One wave-packet preparation method uses the blockade effect enabled by beyond-nearest-neighbor Ising spin interactions. The other method utilizes a quantum-bus-mediated exchange, such as the native spin-phonon coupling in trapped-ion arrays. With a focus on trapped-ion simulators, we numerically benchmark both methods and show that high-fidelity wave packets can be achieved in near-term experiments. We numerically study scattering of wave packets for experimentally realizable parameters in the Ising model and find inelastic-scattering regimes, corresponding to particle production in the scattering event, with prominent and distinct experimental signals. Our proposal, therefore, demonstrates the potential of observing inelastic scattering in near-term quantum simulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07061v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elizabeth R. Bennewitz, Brayden Ware, Alexander Schuckert, Alessio Lerose, Federica M. Surace, Ron Belyansky, William Morong, De Luo, Arinjoy De, Kate S. Collins, Or Katz, Christopher Monroe, Zohreh Davoudi, Alexey V. Gorhskov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Lorentz Invariance Violation with Absorption of Astrophysical Gamma-rays by Solar Photons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07063v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We compute in detail the absorption optical depth for astrophysical $\gamma$-ray photons interacting with solar photons to produce electron positron pairs. This effect is greatest for $\gamma$-ray sources at small angular distances from the Sun, reaching optical depths as high as $\tau_{\gamma\gamma}\sim 10^{-2}$. We also calculate this effect including modifications to the absorption cross section threshold from subluminal Lorentz invariance violation (LIV). We show for the first time that subluminal LIV can lead to increases or decreases in $\tau_{\gamma\gamma}$ compared to the non-LIV case. We show that, at least in principle, LIV can be probed with this effect with observations of $\gamma$-ray sources near the Sun at $\gtrsim20$ TeV by HAWC or LHAASO, although a measurement will be extremely difficult due to the small size of the effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07063v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Justin D. Finke, Parshad Patel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On classical de Sitter solutions and parametric control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07065</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07065v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Finding string backgrounds with de Sitter spacetime, where all approximations and corrections are controlled, is an open problem. We revisit the search for de Sitter solutions in the classical regime for specific type IIB supergravity compactifications on group manifolds, an under-explored corner of the landscape that offers an interesting testing ground for swampland conjectures. While the supergravity de Sitter solutions we obtain numerically are ambiguous in terms of their classicality, we find an analytic scaling that makes four out of six compactification radii, as well as the overall volume, arbitrarily large. This potentially provides parametric control over corrections. If we could show that these solutions, or others to be found, are fully classical, they would constitute a counterexample to conjectures stating that asymptotic de Sitter solutions do not exist. We discuss this point in great detail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07065v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Andriot, Fabian Ruehle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for New Fundamental Interactions via Isotopic Shifts in Molecular Lattice Clocks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07097v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Precision measurements with ultracold atoms and molecules are primed to probe beyond-the-Standard Model physics. Isotopologues of homonuclear molecules are a natural testbed for new Yukawa-type mass-dependent forces at nanometer scales, complementing existing mesoscopic-body and neutron scattering experiments. Here we propose using isotopic shift measurements in molecular lattice clocks to constrain these new interactions from new massive scalar particles in keV$/c^2$ range: the new interaction would impart an extra isotopic shift to molecular levels on top of one predicted by the Standard Model. For the strontium dimer, a Hz-level agreement between experiment and theory could constrain the coupling of the new particles to hadrons by up to an order-of-magnitude over the most stringent existing experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07097v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Tiberi, M. Borkowski, B. Iritani, R. Moszynski, T. Zelevinsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for CP-violating Neutrino Non-Standard Interactions with the NOvA Experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07266v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This Letter reports a search for charge-parity (CP) symmetry violating non-standard interactions (NSI) of neutrinos with matter using the NOvA Experiment, and examines their effects on the determination of the standard oscillation parameters. Data from $\nu_{\mu}(\bar{\nu}_{\mu})\rightarrow\nu_{\mu}(\bar{\nu}_{\mu})$ and $\nu_{\mu}(\bar{\nu}_{\mu})\rightarrow\nu_{e}(\bar{\nu}_{e})$ oscillation channels are used to measure the effect of the NSI parameters $\varepsilon_{e\mu}$ and $\varepsilon_{e\tau}$. With 90% C.L. the magnitudes of the NSI couplings are constrained to be $|\varepsilon_{e\mu}| \, \lesssim 0.3$ and $|\varepsilon_{e\tau}| \, \lesssim 0.4$. A degeneracy at $|\varepsilon_{e\tau}| \, \approx 1.8$ is reported, and we observe that the presence of NSI limits sensitivity to the standard CP phase $\delta_{\tiny\text{CP}}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07266v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> NOvA Collaboration, M. A. Acero, B. Acharya, P. Adamson, L. Aliaga, N. Anfimov, A. Antoshkin, E. Arrieta-Diaz, L. Asquith, A. Aurisano, A. Back, N. Balashov, P. Baldi, B. A. Bambah, A. Bat, K. Bays, R. Bernstein, T. J. C. Bezerra, V. Bhatnagar, D. Bhattarai, B. Bhuyan, J. Bian, A. C. Booth, R. Bowles, B. Brahma, C. Bromberg, N. Buchanan, A. Butkevich, S. Calvez, T. J. Carroll, E. Catano-Mur, J. P. Cesar, A. Chatla, S. Chaudhary, R. Chirco, B. C. Choudhary, A. Christensen, M. F. Cicala, T. E. Coan, A. Cooleybeck, C. Cortes-Parra, D. Coveyou, L. Cremonesi, G. S. Davies, P. F. Derwent, Z. Djurcic, M. Dolce, D. Doyle, D. Due\~nas Tonguino, E. C. Dukes, A. Dye, R. Ehrlich, E. Ewart, P. Filip, J. Franc, M. J. Frank, H. R. Gallagher, F. Gao, A. Giri, R. A. Gomes, M. C. Goodman, M. Groh, R. Group, A. Habig, F. Hakl, J. Hartnell, R. Hatcher, M. He, K. Heller, V Hewes, A. Himmel, Y. Ivaneev, A. Ivanova, B. Jargowsky, J. Jarosz, C. Johnson, M. Judah, I. Kakorin, D. M. Kaplan, A. Kalitkina, J. Kleykamp, O. Klimov, L. W. Koerner, L. Kolupaeva, R. Kralik, A. Kumar, C. D. Kuruppu, V. Kus, T. Lackey, K. Lang, J. Lesmeister, A. Lister, J. Liu, J. A. Lock, M. Lokajicek, M. MacMahon, S. Magill, W. A. Mann, M. T. Manoharan, M. Manrique Plata, M. L. Marshak, M. Martinez-Casales, V. Matveev, B. Mehta, M. D. Messier, H. Meyer, T. Miao, V. Mikola, W. H. Miller, S. Mishra, S. R. Mishra, A. Mislivec, R. Mohanta, A. Moren, A. Morozova, W. Mu, L. Mualem, M. Muether, K. Mulder, D. Myers, D. Naples, A. Nath, S. Nelleri, J. K. Nelson, R. Nichol, E. Niner, A. Norman, A. Norrick, T. Nosek, H. Oh, A. Olshevskiy, T. Olson, M. Ozkaynak, A. Pal, J. Paley, L. Panda, R. B. Patterson, G. Pawloski, O. Petrova, R. Petti, L. R. Prais, A. Rafique, V. Raj, M. Rajaoalisoa, B. Ramson, M. Ravelhofer, B. Rebel, P. Roy, O. Samoylov, M. C. Sanchez, S. S\'anchez Falero, P. Shanahan, P. Sharma, A. Shmakov, A. Sheshukov, S. Shukla, D. K. Singha, W. Shorrock, I. Singh, P. Singh, V. Singh, E. Smith, J. Smolik, P. Snopok, N. Solomey, A. Sousa, K. Soustruznik, M. Strait, L. Suter, A. Sutton, K. Sutton, S. Swain, C. Sweeney, A. Sztuc, B. Tapia Oregui, P. Tas, T. Thakore, J. Thomas, E. Tiras, Y. Torun, J. Tripathi, J. Trokan-Tenorio, J. Urheim, P. Vahle, Z. Vallari, J. Vasel, J. D. Villamil, K. J. Vockerodt, T. Vrba, M. Wallbank, M. Wetstein, D. Whittington, D. A. Wickremasinghe, T. Wieber, J. Wolcott, M. Wrobel, S. Wu, W. Wu, Y. Xiao, B. Yaeggy, A. Yahaya, A. Yankelevich, K. Yonehara, Y. Yu, S. Zadorozhnyy, J. Zalesak, R. Zwaska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\alpha$-Generalized No-Scale Inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07333v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose the $\alpha$-generalized no-scale supergravity, and study the corresponding inflationary models. With a new parameter $0&lt;\alpha\leq 1$, the $\alpha$-generalized no-scale supergravity provides the continuous connections among the generic no-scale supergravity from string theory compactifications. The resulting prediction of the CMB, spectrum index $n_s$, and tensor-to-scalar ratio $r$ can be highly consistent with the latest Planck/BICEP/Keck Array observations. Notably, the models with $\alpha\neq 1$ give a smaller ratio $r\leq 10^{-3}$, which is flexible even under the anticipated tighter observational constraints at the future experiments. Additionally, these models have the potential to generate a broad-band stochastic gravitational wave background, and thus explain the NANOGrav 15yr signal. Furthermore, they predict the formation of primordial black holes (PBHs) with various mass scales, which could account for an significant portion of dark matter relic density in the Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07333v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lina Wu, Tianjun Li, Junle Pei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large fluctuations in the Sky</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07343</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07343v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Renormalization of quantum loop effects generated from large fluctuations is a hugely debatable topic of research these days which rules out the Primordial Black Hole (PBH) formation within the framework of single-field inflation. In this article, we briefly discuss that the correct implementation of regularization, renormalization, and resummation techniques in a setup described by an ultra-slow-roll phase sandwiched between two slow-roll phases in the presence of smooth or sharp transitions can lead to a stringent constraint on the PBH mass (i.e. ${\cal O}(10^{2}{\rm gm}$)), which we advertise as a new No-go theorem. Finally, we will give some of the possible way-outs using which one can evade this proposed No-go theorem and produce solar/sub-solar mass PBHs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07343v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sayantan Choudhury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Nuclear Shape Phase Transition in Ultra-Relativistic $^{129}$Xe+$^{129}$Xe Collisions at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07441</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07441v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The shape phase transition for certain isotope or isotone chains, associated with the quantum phase transition of finite nuclei, is an intriguing phenomenon in nuclear physics. A notable case is the Xe isotope chain, where the structure transits from a $\gamma$-soft rotor to a spherical vibrator, with the second-order shape phase transition occurring in the vicinity of $^{128-130}$Xe. In this letter, we focus on investigating the $\gamma$-soft deformation of $^{129}$Xe associated with the second-order shape phase transition by constructing novel correlators for ultra-relativistic $^{129}$Xe+$^{129}$Xe collisions. In particular, our iEBE-VISHNU model calculations show that the $v_2^2-[p_T]$ correlation $\rho_{2}$ and the mean transverse momentum fluctuation $\Gamma_{p_T}$, which were previously interpreted as the evidence for the rigid triaxial deformation of $^{129}$Xe, can also be well explained by the $\gamma$-soft deformation of $^{129}$Xe. We also propose two novel correlators $\rho_{4,2}$ and $\rho_{2,4}$, which carry non-trivial higher-order correlations and show unique capabilities to distinguish between the $\gamma$-soft and the rigid triaxial deformation of $^{129}$Xe in $^{129}$Xe+$^{129}$Xe collisions at the LHC. The present study also provides a novel way to explore the second-order shape phase transition of finite nuclei with ultra-relativistic heavy ion collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07441v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shujun Zhao, Hao-jie Xu, You Zhou, Yu-Xin Liu, Huichao Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Novel Signatures of Radiation Reaction in Electron-Laser Sidescattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07455</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07455v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this article we investigate novel signatures of radiation reaction via the angular deflection of an electron beam colliding at 90 degrees with an intense laser pulse. Due to the radiation reaction effect, the electrons can be deflected towards the beam axis for plane wave backgrounds, which is not possible in the absence of radiation reaction effects. The magnitude and size of the deflection angle can be controlled by tailoring the laser pulse shapes. The effect is first derived analytically using the Landau-Lifshitz equation, which allows to determine the important scaling behavior with laser intensity and particle energy. We then move on to full scale 3D Monte Carlo simulations to verify the effect is observable with present day laser technology. We investigate the opportunities for an indirect observation of laser depletion in such side scattering scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07455v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philipp Sikorski, Alec G. R. Thomas, Stepan S. Bulanov, Matt Zepf, Daniel Seipt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reheated Sub-40000 Kelvin Neutron Stars at the JWST, ELT, and TMT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07496v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neutron stars cooling passively since their birth may be reheated in their late-stage evolution by a number of possible phenomena: rotochemical, vortex creep, crust cracking, magnetic field decay, or more exotic processes such as removal of neutrons from their Fermi seas (the nucleon Auger effect), baryon number-violating nucleon decay, and accretion of particle dark matter. Using Exposure Time Calculator tools, we show that reheating mechanisms imparting effective temperatures of 2000--40000 Kelvin may be uncovered with excellent sensitivities at the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST), the Extremely Large Telescope (ELT), and the Thirty Meter Telescope (TMT), with imaging instruments operating from visible-edge to near-infrared. With a day of exposure, they could constrain the reheating luminosity of a neutron star up to a distance of 500 pc, within which about $10^5$ (undiscovered) neutron stars lie. Detection in multiple filters could overconstrain a neutron star's surface temperature, distance from Earth, mass, and radius. Using publicly available catalogues of newly discovered pulsars at the FAST and CHIME radio telescopes and the Galactic electron distribution models YMW16 and NE2001, we estimate the pulsars' dispersion measure distance from Earth, and find that potentially 30$-$40 of these may be inspected for late-stage reheating within viable exposure times, in addition to a few hundred candidates already present in the ATNF catalogue. Whereas the coldest neutron star observed (PSR J2144$-$3933) has an upper limit on its effective temperature of about 33000 Kelvin with the Hubble Space Telescope, we show that the effective temperature may be constrained down to 20000 Kelvin with JWST-NIRCam, 15000 Kelvin at ELT-MICADO, and 9000 Kelvin with TMT-IRIS. Campaigns to measure thermal luminosities of old neutron stars would be transformative for astrophysics and fundamental physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07496v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nirmal Raj, Prajwal Shivanna, Gaurav Niraj Rachh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conservative Black Hole Scattering at Fifth Post-Minkowskian and First Self-Force Order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07781v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We compute the 5PM order contributions to the scattering angle and impulse of classical black hole scattering in the conservative sector at first self-force order (1SF) using the worldline quantum field theory formalism. This challenging four-loop computation required the use of advanced integration-by-parts and differential equation technology implemented on high-perfomance computing systems. Use of partial fraction identities allowed us to render the complete integrand in a fully planar form. The resulting function space is simpler than expected: in the scattering angle we see only multiple polylogarithms up to weight three, and a total absence of the elliptic integrals that appeared at 4PM order. All checks on our result, both internal - cancellation of dimensional regularization poles, preservation of the on-shell condition - and external - matching the slow-velocity limit with the post-Newtonian (PN) literature up to 5PN order and matching the tail terms to the 4PM loss of energy - are passed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07781v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mathias Driesse, Gustav Uhre Jakobsen, Gustav Mogull, Jan Plefka, Benjamin Sauer, Johann Usovitsch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QCD Equation of State at nonzero baryon density in external magnetic field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07783v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper is devoted to the study of QCD equation of state in external magnetic field and nonzero baryon density. Our study is carried out by means of lattice simulation with 2+1 dynamical staggered quarks at the physical masses. The simulation is conducted at imaginary baryon chemical potential what allowed us to overcome the sign problem. We expand the pressure in the baryon imaginary chemical potential and study three leading nonzero coefficients in this expansion. These coefficients were calculated for the following values of magnetic field: $eB=0.3$, $0.6$, $1.2$ GeV$^2$ with the lattice sizes $8\times32^3$, $10\times40^3$, $12\times48^3$. Using these data we take continuum limit for the coefficients. Our results indicate considerable enhancement of the expansion coefficients by the magnetic field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07783v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. Astrakhantsev, V. V. Braguta, A. Yu. Kotov, A. A. Roenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for new bosons with ytterbium isotope shifts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07792v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Standard Model of particle physics describes the properties of elementary particles and their interactions remarkably well, but in particular does not account for dark matter. Isotope-shift spectroscopy is a sensitive probe of fifth forces and new particles that illuminate the dark matter sector. This method sets bounds on new bosons that couple neutrons and electrons with masses in the keV/c2 to MeV/c2 range. With increasing spectroscopic precision, such searches are limited by uncertainties of isotope masses and the understanding of nuclear structure. Here, we report on high-precision mass-ratio and isotope-shift measurements of the ytterbium isotopes $^{168,170,172,174,176}$Yb that exceed previous measurements by up to two orders of magnitude. From these measurements, we extract higher-order changes in the nuclear charge distribution along the Yb isotope chain and use these to benchmark novel ab initio calculations. Our measurements set new bounds on the existence of the proposed boson.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07792v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Menno Door, Chih-Han Yeh, Matthias Heinz, Fiona Kirk, Chunhai Lyu, Takayuki Miyagi, Julian C. Berengut, Jacek Biero\'n, Klaus Blaum, Laura S. Dreissen, Sergey Eliseev, Pavel Filianin, Melina Filzinger, Elina Fuchs, Henning A. F\"urst, Gediminas Gaigalas, Zolt\'an Harman, Jost Herkenhoff, Nils Huntemann, Christoph H. Keitel, Kathrin Kromer, Daniel Lange, Alexander Rischka, Christoph Schweiger, Achim Schwenk, Noritaka Shimizu, Tanja E. Mehlst\"aubler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Science4Peace initiative: Alleviating the consequences of sanctions in international scientific cooperation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07833v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The armed invasion of Ukraine by the Russian Federation has adversely affected the relations between Russia and Western countries. Among other aspects, it has put scientific cooperation and collaboration into question and changed the scientific landscape significantly. Cooperation between some Western institutions and their Russian and Belarusian partners were put on hold after February 24, 2022. The CERN Council decided at its meeting in December 2023 to terminate cooperation agreements with Russia and Belarus that date back a decade. CERN is an international institution with UN observer status, and has so far played a role in international cooperation which was independent of national political strategies. We argue that the Science4Peace idea still has a great value and scientific collaboration between scientists must continue, since fundamental science is by its nature an international discipline. A ban of scientists participating in international cooperation and collaboration is against the traditions, requirements and understanding of science. We call for measures to reactivate the peaceful cooperation of individual scientists on fundamental research in order to stimulate international cooperation for a more peaceful world in the future. Specifically, we plead for finding ways to continue this cooperation through international organizations, such as CERN and JINR.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07833v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Ali, M. Barone, S. Brentjes, D. Britzger, M. Dittmar, T. Ekel\"of, J. Ellis, S. Fonseca de Souza, A. Glazov, A. V. Gritsan, R. Hoffmann, H. Jung, M. Klein, V. Klyukhin, V. Korbel, P. Kokkas, P. Kostka, U. Langenegger, J. List, N. Raicevic, A. Rostovtsev, A. Sabio Vera, M. Spiro, G. Tonelli, P. van Mechelen, J. Vigen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Charged Higgs Bosons in the 2-Higgs Doublet Model Type-II with Vector-Like Quarks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.07259</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.07259v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the phenomenology of charged Higgs bosons ($H^\pm$) and Vector-Like Quarks (VLQs), denoted as $T$, the latter possessing a charge identical to the top quark one, within the framework of the Two Higgs Doublet Model Type-II (2HDM-II). Upon examining two scenarios, one featuring a singlet $(T)$ (2HDM-II+$(T)$) and another a doublet $(TB)$ (2HDM-II+$(TB)$), we discover that the presence of VLQs has a significant effect on the (pseudo)scalar sector of the 2HDM-II. In particular, this leads to a reduction in the strict constraint on the mass of the charged Higgs boson, which is imposed by $B$-physics observables, specifically $B\to X_s\gamma$. {The observed reduction stems from modifications in the charged Higgs couplings to the Standard Model (SM) top and bottom quarks}. Notably, the degree of this reduction varies distinctly between the singlet 2HDM+$(T)$ and doublet 2HDM+$(TB)$ scenarios. Additionally, our investigation extends to constraints imposed by the oblique parameters $S$ and $T$ on the VLQ mixing angles. Furthermore, to facilitate efficient exploration of the '2HDM-II+VLQ' parameter space, we present results on pair production of VLQs $T$ ($pp\to T\bar T$), followed by $T\to H^\pm b$ and $H^\pm \to tb$ decays, yielding a distinctive $2t4b$ final state. This investigation thus provides valuable insights guiding the search for extended Higgs and quark sectors at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) at CERN.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.07259v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.055016</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Rachid Benbrik (Polydisciplinary Faculty, Laboratory of Fundamental and Applied Physics, Cadi Ayyad University, Sidi Bouzid, Safi, Morocco), Mohammed Boukidi (Polydisciplinary Faculty, Laboratory of Fundamental and Applied Physics, Cadi Ayyad University, Sidi Bouzid, Safi, Morocco), Stefano Moretti (School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Southampton, United Kingdom)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isolated photon production in $pp$ collisions at forward rapidities and high multiplicity events</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.13720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.13720v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The production of isolated photons in high multiplicity events is investigated considering the Color Glass Condensate (CGC) formalism. The associated cross-section for proton - proton collisions is estimated considering three distinct solutions of the Balitsky - Kovchegov (BK) equation and predictions for the normalized photon yield as a function of the multiplicities of co - produced charged particles are presented. We predict the increasing of the yield with the multiplicity, with the slope being smaller for larger rapidities. As the isolated photon production is not affected by the fragmentation process, a future experimental investigation of this process in current high energy hadronic colliders is ideal to test the treatment of high multiplicity events using the CGC formalism, previously applied only for the production of hadronic final states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.13720v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epja/s10050-024-01287-6</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yuri N. Lima, Andr\'e V. Giannini, Victor P. Goncalves</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The CMS di-photon excess at 95 GeV in view of the LHC Run 2 results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.12018</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.12018v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The CMS collaboration has recently reported the results of a low-mass Higgs-boson search in the di-photon final state based on the full Run 2 data set with refined analysis techniques. The new results show an excess of events at a mass of about 95 GeV with a local significance of $2.9\,\sigma$, confirming a previously reported excess at about the same mass and similar significance based on the first-year Run 2 plus Run 1 data. The observed excess is compatible with the limits obtained in the corresponding ATLAS searches. In this work, we discuss the di-photon excess and show that it can be interpreted as the lightest Higgs boson in the Two-Higgs doublet model that is extended by a complex singlet (S2HDM) of Yukawa types II and IV. We show that the second-lightest Higgs boson is in good agreement with the current LHC Higgs-boson measurements of the state at 125 GeV, and that the full scalar sector is compatible with all theoretical and experimental constraints. Furthermore, we discuss the di-photon excess in conjunction with an excess in the $b \bar b$ final state observed at LEP and an excess observed by CMS in the di-tau final state, which were found at comparable masses with local significances of about $2\sigma$ and $3\sigma$, respectively. We find that the $b \bar b$ excess can be well described together with the di-photon excess in both types of the S2HDM. However, the di-tau excess can only be accommodated at the level of $1\sigma$ in type IV. We also comment on the compatibility with supersymmetric scenarios and other extended Higgs sectors, and we discuss how the potential signal can be further analyzed at the LHC and at future $e^+e^-$ colliders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.12018v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2023.138217</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Lett.B 846 (2023) 138217</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>T. Biek\"otter, S. Heinemeyer, G. Weiglein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 95.4 GeV di-photon excess at ATLAS and CMS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.03889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.03889v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The ATLAS collaboration has recently reported the results of a low-mass Higgs-boson search in the di-photon final state based on the full Run 2 data set. The results are based on an improved analysis w.r.t. the previous analysis, which included a part of the Run 2 data, with a substantially better sensitivity. The ``model-dependent'' search carried out by ATLAS shows an excess of events at a mass of about 95.4 GeV with a local significance of $1.7\,\sigma$. The results are compatible with a previously reported excess at the same mass, but somewhat higher significance of $2.9\,\sigma$, from the CMS collaboration, also based on the full Run 2 data set. Combining the two results (neglecting possible correlations) we find a signal strength of $\mu_{\gamma\gamma}^{\rm ATLAS+CMS} = 0.24^{+0.09}_{-0.08}$, corresponding to an excess of $3.1\,\sigma$. In this work, we investigate the implications of this result, updating a previous analysis based solely on the CMS Run 2 data. We demonstrate that the ATLAS/CMS combined di-photon excess can be interpreted as the lightest Higgs boson in a Two-Higgs doublet model that is extended by a complex singlet (S2HDM) of Yukawa types II and IV, while being in agreement with all other experimental and theoretical constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.03889v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.035005</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 109 (2024) 3, 035005</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>T. Biek\"otter, S. Heinemeyer, G. Weiglein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CMB Spectral Distortions from an Axion-Dark Photon-Photon Interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.13135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.13135v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The presence of a plethora of light spin 0 and spin 1 fields is motivated in a number of BSM scenarios, such as the axiverse. The study of the interactions of such light bosonic fields with the Standard Model has focused mostly on interactions involving only one such field, such as the axion ($\phi$) coupling to photons, $\phi F \tilde F$, or the kinetic mixing between photon and the dark photon, $ F F_D$. In this work, we continue the exploration of interactions involving two light BSM fields and the standard model, focusing on the mixed axion-photon-dark-photon interaction $\phi F \tilde F_D$. If either the axion or dark photon are dark matter, we show that this interaction leads to conversion of the CMB photons into a dark sector particle, leading to a distortion in the CMB spectrum. We present the details of these unique distortion signatures and the resulting constraints on the $\phi F \tilde F_D$ coupling. In particular, we find that for a wide range of masses, the constraints from these effect are stronger than on the more widely studied axion-photon coupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.13135v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anson Hook, Gustavo Marques-Tavares, Clayton Ristow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Updated global fit of the aligned two-Higgs-doublet model with heavy scalars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.15419</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.15419v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: An updated global fit on the parameter-space of the Aligned Two-Higgs-Doublet model has been performed with the help of the open-source package HEPfit, assuming the Standard-Model Higgs to be the lightest scalar. No new sources of CP violation, other than the phase in the CKM matrix of the Standard Model, have been considered. A similar global fit was previously performed in Ref. [JHEP 05 (2021) 005] with a slightly different set of parameters. Our updated fit incorporates improved analyses of the theoretical constraints required for perturbative unitarity and boundedness of the scalar potential from below, additional flavour observables and updated data on direct searches of heavy scalars at the LHC, Higgs signal strengths and electroweak precision observables. Although not included in the main fit, the implications of the CDF measurement of the $W^\pm$ mass are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.15419v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.035012</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 109 (2024) 3, 035012</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Anirban Karan, V\'ictor Miralles, Antonio Pich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral kinetic theory with self-energy corrections and neutrino spin Hall effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.08257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.08257v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We systematically derive the chiral kinetic theory for chiral fermions with collisions, including the self-energy corrections, from quantum field theories. We find that the Wigner functions and chiral kinetic equations receive both the classical and quantum corrections from the self-energies and their spacetime gradients. We also apply this formalism to study nonequilibrium neutrino transport due to the interaction with thermalized electrons and nucleons, as realized in core-collapse supernovae. We derive neutrino currents along magnetic fields and neutrino spin Hall effect induced by the density gradient at first order in the Fermi constant $G_{\rm F}$ for anisotropic neutrino distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.08257v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.056010</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 109 (2024) 5, 056010</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Naoki Yamamoto, Di-Lun Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Amplifying Non-Resonant Production of Dark Sector Particles in Scattering Dominance Regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.00231</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.00231v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the enhancement of dark sector particle production within the scattering dominant regime. These particles typically exhibit a slight mixing with Standard Model particles through various portals, allowing for their generation through in-medium oscillation from Standard Model particle sources. Our analysis reveals that in the scattering dominance regime, with a significantly smaller scattering mean free path $\lambda_{\rm sca}$ compared to the absorption mean free path $\lambda_{\rm abs}$, the nonresonant production of sterile states can experience an enhancement by a factor of $\lambda_{\rm abs}/\lambda_{\rm sca}$. This phenomenon is demonstrated within the context of kinetic mixing dark photon production at a reactor, precisely satisfying this condition. By incorporating this collisional enhancement, we find that the current sensitivity to the mixing parameter $\epsilon$ for dark photons in the TEXONO experiment can be significantly improved across a range spanning from tens of eV to MeV. This advancement establishes the most stringent laboratory constraint within this mass spectrum for the dark photon. Sterile neutrino production, however, does not exhibit such enhancement, either due to the failure to meet the scattering dominance criterion or the neutrino damping in resonant production.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.00231v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingxuan Du, Jia Liu, Xiao-Ping Wang, Tianhao Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Full-order mode analysis within a mutilated relaxation time approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.05606</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.05606v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, a detailed normal mode analysis is given based on the Boltzmann equation in mutilated relaxation time approximation (RTA). Within this linearized effective kinetic description, our analysis covers a full-order calculation in wavenumber $k$, being a generalization of usual hydrodynamic mode analysis to intermediate and short-wavelength region. Besides, the proposed normal mode analysis can give a natural classification of kinetic modes into collective modes and non-collective single particle excitations. In the case with a scale-independent relaxation time, the so-called behavior of hydrodynamic onset transitions is recovered \cite{Romatschke:2015gic}. However, for a general case with a scale dependent relaxation time, a clear classification broken down because the location of hydrodynamic modes is not well separated from non-hydrodynamic modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.05606v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quark stars in $D_3$-$D_7$ holographic model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.17719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.17719v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work investigates static and dynamical quark star properties within a $D_3-D_7$ holographic model. We solve the Tolman-Oppenheimer-Volkoff equations for the quark matter equation of state obtained from the brane configuration. We determine the mass-radius diagram for a range of model parameters and compare with recent NICER observational data for the pulsars PSR J$0030+0451$ and PSR J$0740+6620$. Motivated by the GW170817 event detected by the LIGO-Virgo collaboration, we also calculate the tidal deformability parameter obtained for each component of the binary star system. We show that quark stars composed of flavor-independent quark matter derived from the $D_3-D_7$ holographic model are not able to satisfy simultaneously the LIGO-Virgo and NICER astrophysical bounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.17719v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-024-12619-7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. C (2024) 84:253</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M. Aleixo, C. H. Lenzi, W. de Paula, R. da Rocha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytic decay width of the Higgs boson to massive bottom quarks at next-to-next-to-leading order in QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.20514</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.20514v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Higgs boson decay to a massive bottom quark pair provides the dominant contribution to the Higgs boson width. We present an exact result for such a decay induced by the bottom quark Yukawa coupling with next-to-next-to-leading order (NNLO) QCD corrections. We have adopted the canonical differential equations in the calculation and obtained the result in terms of multiple polylogarithms. We also compute the contribution from the decay to four bottom quarks which consists of complete elliptic integrals or their one-fold integrals. The result in the small bottom quark mass limit coincides with the previous calculation using the large momentum expansion. The threshold expansion exhibits power divergent terms in the bottom quark velocity, which has a structure different from that in $e^+e^-\to t\bar{t}$ but can be reproduced by computing the corresponding Coulomb Green function. The NNLO corrections significantly reduce the uncertainties from both the renormalization scale and the renormalization scheme of the bottom quark Yukawa coupling. Our result can be applied to a heavy scalar decay to a top quark pair.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.20514v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP03(2024)068</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 03 (2024) 068</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jian Wang, Yefan Wang, Da-Jiang Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $\rho(770,1450)\to \omega\pi$ contributions for three-body decays $B\to\bar{D}^{(*)} \omega\pi$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.00413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.00413v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The decays $B\to\bar{D}^{(*)} \omega\pi$ are very important for the investigation of $\rho$ excitations and the test of factorization hypothesis for $B$ meson decays. The $B^{+}\to \bar{D}^{(*)0}\omega\pi^+$ and $B^{0}\to D^{(*)-}\omega\pi^+$ have been measured by different collaborations but without any predictions for their observables on theoretical side. In this work, we study the contributions of $\rho(770,1450)\to \omega\pi$ for the cascade decays $B^{+}\to \bar{D}^{(*)0} \rho^+ \to \bar{D}^{(*)0}\omega\pi^+$, $B^{0}\to D^{(*)-} \rho^+ \to D^{(*)-}\omega\pi^+$ and $B_s^{0}\to D_s^{(*)-} \rho^+ \to D^{(*)-}\omega\pi^+$. We introduce $\rho(770,1450)\to \omega\pi$ subprocesses into the distribution amplitudes for $\omega\pi$ system via the vector form factor $F_{\omega\pi}(s)$ and then predict the branching fractions for the first time for concerned quasi-two-body decays with $\rho(770,1450)\to \omega\pi$, as well as the corresponding longitudinal polarization fractions $\Gamma_L/\Gamma$ for the cases with the vector $\bar{D}^{*0}$ or $D_{(s)}^{*-}$ in their final states. The branching fractions of these quasi-two-body decays are predicted at the order of $10^{-3}$, which can be detected at the LHCb and Belle-II experiments. The predictions for the decays ${B}^0 \to{D}^{*-} \rho(770)^+\to {D}^{*-} \omega\pi^+$ and ${B}^0 \to {D}^{*-} \rho(1450)^+\to {D}^{*-} \omega\pi^+$ agree well with the measurements from Belle Collaboration. In order to avoid the pollution from annihilation Feynman diagrams, we recommend to take the $B_s^0 \to D_s^{*-}\rho(770,1450)^+$ decays, which have only emission diagrams at quark level, to test the factorization hypothesis for $B$ decays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.00413v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP01(2024)047</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP01(2024)047</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Shan Ren, Ai-Jun Ma, Wen-Fei Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational neutrino reheating</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.07684</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.07684v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Despite having important cosmological implications, the reheating phase is believed to play a crucial role in cosmology and particle physics model building. Conventionally, the model of reheating with an arbitrary coupling of inflaton to massless fields naturally lacks precise prediction and hence difficult to verify through observation. In this paper, we propose a simple and natural reheating mechanism where the particle physics model, namely the Type-I seesaw is shown to play a major role in the entire reheating process where inflaton is coupled with all the fields only gravitationally. Besides successfully resolving the well-known neutrino mass and baryon asymmetry problems, this scenario offers successful reheating, predicts distinct primordial gravitational wave spectrum and non-vanishing lowest active neutrino mass. Our novel mechanism opens up a new avenue of integrating particle physics and cosmology in the context of reheating.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.07684v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Md Riajul Haque, Debaprasad Maity, Rajesh Mondal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inferring the initial condition for the Balitsky-Kovchegov equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.10491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.10491v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We apply Bayesian inference to determine the posterior likelihood distribution for the parameters describing the initial condition of the small-$x$ Balitsky-Kovchegov evolution equation at leading logarithmic accuracy. The HERA structure function data is found to constrain most of the model parameters well. In particular, we find that the HERA data prefers an anomalous dimension $\gamma\approx 1$ unlike in previous fits where $\gamma&gt;1$ which led to e.g. the unintegrated gluon distribution and the quark-target cross sections not being positive definite. The determined posterior distribution can be used to propagate the uncertainties in the non-perturbative initial condition when calculating any other observable in the Color Glass Condensate framework. We demonstrate this explicitly for the inclusive quark production cross section in proton-proton collisions and by calculating predictions for the nuclear modification factor for the $F_2$ structure function in the EIC and LHeC/FCC-he kinematics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.10491v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.054018</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 109 (2024) 054018</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Carlisle Casuga, Mikko Karhunen, Heikki M\"antysaari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decays of Standard Model like Higgs boson $h \rightarrow\gamma\gamma, Z \gamma$ in a minimal left-right symmetric model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11045</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.11045v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Two decay channels $h\rightarrow \gamma \gamma, Z\gamma$ of the Standard Model-like Higgs in a left-right symmetry model are investigated under recent experimental data. We will show there exist one-loop contributions that affect the $h\rightarrow Z\gamma$ amplitude, but not the $h\rightarrow \gamma\gamma$ amplitude. From numerical investigations, we show that the signal strength $\mu_{Z \gamma}$ of the decay $h\rightarrow Z\gamma$ is still constrained strictly by that of $h\rightarrow \gamma\gamma$, namely $|\Delta \mu_{\gamma \gamma}|&lt;38\%$ results in max $|\Delta \mu_{Z \gamma}|&lt;46\%$. On the other hand, the future experimental sensitivity $|\Delta \mu_{\gamma \gamma}|=4\%$ still allows $|\Delta \mu_{Z \gamma}|$ reaches to values larger than the expected sensitivity $|\Delta \mu_{Z \gamma}|=23\%$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.11045v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. T. Hong, V. K. Le, L. T. T. Phuong, N . C. Hoi, N. T. K. Ngan, N. H. T. Nha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heavy axial-vector structures $bb\overline{c}\overline{c}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.05162</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.05162v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The fully heavy axial-vector diquark-antidiquark structures $bb\overline{c} \overline{c}$ are explored by means of the QCD sum rule method. They are modeled as four-quark mesons $T_{\mathrm{1}}$ and $T_{\mathrm{2}}$ composed of $b^{T}C\sigma _{\mu \nu }\gamma _{5}b$, $\overline{c}\gamma ^{\nu }C \overline{c}^{T}$ and $b^{T}C\gamma _{\mu }\gamma _{5}b$, $\overline{c}C \overline{c}^{T}$ diquarks, respectively. The spectroscopic parameters of the tetraquarks $T_{\mathrm{1}}$ and $T_{\mathrm{2}}$ are determined in the context of the QCD two-point sum rule method. Results obtained for masses of these states $m_{1} =(12715\pm 86)~\mathrm{MeV}$ and $m_{2}=(13383\pm 92)~ \mathrm{MeV}$ are used to fix their strong decay channels. The full width $ \Gamma (T_{\mathrm{1}})$ of the diquark-antidiquark state $T_{\mathrm{1}}$ is estimated by considering the processes $T_{\mathrm{1}} \to B_{c}^{-}B_{c}^{\ast -}$ and $T_{\mathrm{1}} \to B_{c}^{\ast -}B_{c}^{\ast -} $. The decays to mesons $B_{c}^{-}B_{c}^{\ast -}$, $B_{c}^{-}(2S)B_{c}^{ \ast -}$ and $B_{c}^{\ast -}B_{c}^{\ast -}$ are employed to evaluate $\Gamma (T_{\mathrm{2}})$. Results obtained for the widths $\Gamma (T_{\mathrm{1} })=(44.3\pm 8.8)~\mathrm{MeV}$ and $\Gamma (T_{\mathrm{2}})=(82.5\pm 13.7)~ \mathrm{MeV}$ of these tetraquarks in conjunction with their masses are useful for future experimental studies of fully heavy resonances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.05162v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. S. Agaev, K. Azizi, H. Sundu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Updated analysis of $D\to PP, V\!P$ and $VV$ decays: Implications for $K_S^0-K_L^0$ asymmetries and $D^0$-$\overline {D}^0$ mixing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.06316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.06316v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: An updated analysis of the two-body $D\to PP, V\!P$ and $VV$ decays within the framework of the topological diagram approach is performed. A global fit to the Cabibbo-favored (CF) modes in the $V\!P$ sector gives many solutions with similarly small local minima in $\chi^2$. The solution degeneracy is lifted once we use them to predict for the singly Cabibbo-suppressed (SCS) modes. Topological amplitudes are extracted for the $\eta-\eta'$ mixing angles $\phi=40.4^\circ$ and $43.5^\circ$. The $K_S^0-K_L^0$ asymmetries in $D\to K_{S,L}^0M$ decays denoted by $R(D,M)$ are studied. While the predicted $R(D^0,P)$ for $P=\pi^0, \eta$ and $\eta'$ agree with experiment, the calculated $R(D^+,\pi^+)$, $R(D_s^+, K^+)$, $R(D^0,\omega)$ and $R(D^0,\phi)$ deviate from the data. We conjecture that the relative phase between the topological amplitudes $(C+A)$ and $(T+C)$ should be slightly smaller than $90^\circ$ in order to explain the first two discrepancies and that additional singlet contributions due to the SU(3)-singlet nature of $\omega$ and $\phi$ are needed to account for the last two. For doubly Cabibbo-suppressed (DCS) $D\to V\!P$ decays, their topological amplitudes (double-primed) cannot be all the same as the corresponding ones in the CF modes. The assumption of $E_{V,P}''=E_{V,P}$ for the $W$-exchange amplitude leads to some inconsistencies with the experiment. Through the measured relative phases between CF and DCS channels, the relations of $E_{V,P}''$ with $E_{V,P}$ are determined. Long-distance contributions to the $D^0$-$\overline {D}^0$ mixing parameter $y$ are evaluated in the exclusive approach. In particular, we focus on $D\to PP$ and $V\!P$ decays where $y$ can be reliably estimated. We conclude that $y_{_{P\!P}}\sim (0.110\pm 0.011)\%$ and the lower bound on $y_{_{V\!P}}$ is $(0.220\pm 0.071)\%$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.06316v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hai-Yang Cheng, Cheng-Wei Chiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Astrophysical Axion Bounds: The 2024 Edition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.13728</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.13728v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We review the current status of astrophysical bounds on QCD axions, primarily based on the observational effects of nonstandard energy losses on stars, including black-hole superradiance. Over the past few years, many of the traditional arguments have been reexamined both theoretically and using modern data and new ideas have been put forth. This compact review updates similar Lecture Notes written by one of us in 2006 [Lect. Notes Phys. 741 (2008) 51-71].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.13728v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.22323/1.454.0041</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PoS 454 (2024) 041</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Caputo, Georg Raffelt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffuse Axion Background</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.00100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.00100v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Relativistic axions can be readily produced in a broad variety of transient sources, such as axion star bosenova explosions, supernovae or even evaporating primordial black holes. We develop a general framework describing the resulting persistent diffuse axion background (D$a$B) due to accumulated axions from historic transient events. We derive strong constraints on the D$a$B flux from light axions $m\lesssim 10^{-3}\,{\rm eV}$ emitted from sources with energies $\omega \gtrsim{\rm MeV}$ considering the non-observation of excess photons associated with axion-photon coupling from experiments, including COMPTEL, NuSTAR, XMM-Newton, INTEGRAL, EGRET and Fermi. Future searches in experiments such as SKA, JWST, XRISM, Vera C. Rubin Observatory, AMEGO/e-ASTROGAM will allow probing D$a$B and associated axion-photon couplings with unprecedented sensitivity covering a wide range of possible source energies as low as $0.1\,\mu$eV and multiple decades in axion masses. We highlight the differences between astrophysical and dark sector sources of D$a$B. Further, we discuss complementarity with direct detection as well as prospects for other D$a$B searches. Our analysis demonstrates that D$a$B can act as a promising probe of populations of axion emission sources as well as emission mechanisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.00100v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Eby, Volodymyr Takhistov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jet Discrimination with Quantum Complete Graph Neural Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04990v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Machine learning, particularly deep neural networks, has been widely utilized in high energy physics and has shown remarkable results in various applications. Moreover, the concept of machine learning has been extended to quantum computers, giving rise to a new research area known as quantum machine learning. In this paper, we propose a novel variational quantum circuit model, Quantum Complete Graph Neural Network (QCGNN), designed for learning complete graphs. We argue that QCGNN has a polynomial speedup against its classical counterpart, due to the property of quantum parallelism. In this paper, we study the application of QCGNN through the challenging jet discrimination, where the jets are represented with complete graphs. Subsequently, we conduct a comparative analysis with classical graph neural networks to establish a benchmark.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04990v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi-An Chen, Kai-Feng Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmic topology. Part I. Limits on orientable Euclidean manifolds from circle searches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.02603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.02603v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Einstein field equations of general relativity constrain the local curvature at every point in spacetime, but say nothing about the global topology of the Universe. Cosmic microwave background anisotropies have proven to be the most powerful probe of non-trivial topology since, within $\Lambda$CDM, these anisotropies have well-characterized statistical properties, the signal is principally from a thin spherical shell centered on the observer (the last scattering surface), and space-based observations nearly cover the full sky. The most generic signature of cosmic topology in the microwave background is pairs of circles with matching temperature and polarization patterns. No such circle pairs have been seen above noise in the WMAP or Planck temperature data, implying that the shortest non-contractible loop around the Universe through our location is longer than 98.5% of the comoving diameter of the last scattering surface. We translate this generic constraint into limits on the parameters that characterize manifolds with each of the nine possible non-trivial orientable Euclidean topologies, and provide a code which computes these constraints. In all but the simplest cases, the shortest non-contractible loop in the space can avoid us, and be shorter than the diameter of the last scattering surface by a factor ranging from 2 to at least 6. This result implies that a broader range of manifolds is observationally allowed than widely appreciated. Probing these manifolds will require more subtle statistical signatures than matched circles, such as off-diagonal correlations of harmonic coefficients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.02603v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2023/01/030</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 01 (2023) 030</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pip Petersen (COMPACT Collaboration), Yashar Akrami (COMPACT Collaboration), Craig J. Copi (COMPACT Collaboration), Andrew H. Jaffe (COMPACT Collaboration), Arthur Kosowsky (COMPACT Collaboration), Glenn D. Starkman (COMPACT Collaboration), Andrius Tamosiunas (COMPACT Collaboration), Johannes R. Eskilt (COMPACT Collaboration), \"Ozen\c{c} G\"ung\"or (COMPACT Collaboration), Samanta Saha (COMPACT Collaboration), Quinn Taylor (COMPACT Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Counting operators in Effective Field Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.05759v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We systematically develop the Hilbert series technique for counting independent operators in Effective Field Theories. In the hope of providing more approachable entry point to the subject we include a detailed introduction of all necessary group theoretic tools (in a rather mathematical definition-theorem-proof style). Finally, we apply the formalism in the case of a single scalar field and also electromagnetic field, partly reproducing and partly extending known results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.05759v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jon\'a\v{s} Dujava</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The nonequilibrium evolution near the phase boundary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.18468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.18468v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Using the single-spin flipping dynamics, we study the nonequilibrium evolution near the entire phase boundary of the 3D Ising model, and find that the average of relaxation time (RT) near the first-order phase transition line (1st-PTL) is significantly larger than that near the critical point (CP). As the system size increases, the average of RT near the 1st-PTL increases at a higher power compared to that near the CP. We further show that RT near the 1st-PTL is not only non-self-averaging, but actually self-diverging: relative variance of RT increases with system size. The presence of coexisting and metastable states results in a substantial increase in randomness near the 1st-PTL, and therefore makes the equilibrium more difficult to achieve.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.18468v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaobing Li, Yuming Zhong, Ranran Guo, Mingmei Xu, Yu Zhou, Jinghua Fu, Yuanfang Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid identification of time-frequency domain gravitational wave signals from binary black holes using deep learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19003</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.19003v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent developments in deep learning techniques have offered an alternative and complementary approach to traditional matched filtering methods for the identification of gravitational wave (GW) signals. The rapid and accurate identification of GW signals is crucial for the progress of GW physics and multi-messenger astronomy, particularly in light of the upcoming fourth and fifth observing runs of LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA. In this work, we use the 2D U-Net algorithm to identify the time-frequency domain GW signals from stellar-mass binary black hole (BBH) mergers. We simulate BBH mergers with component masses from 5 to 80 $M_{\odot}$ and account for the LIGO detector noise. We find that the GW events in the first and second observation runs could all be clearly and rapidly identified. For the third observing run, about $80\%$ GW events could be identified. In particular, GW190814, currently unknown, is a special case that can be identified by the network, while other binary neutron star mergers and neutron star-black hole mergers can not be identified. Compared to the traditional convolutional neural network, the U-Net algorithm can output the time-frequency domain signal images rather than probabilities, providing a more intuitive investigation. Moreover, some of the results through U-Net can provide preliminary inference on the chirp mass information. In conclusion, the U-Net algorithm can rapidly identify the time-frequency domain GW signals from BBH mergers and potentially be helpful for future parameter inferences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.19003v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Xin Wang, Shang-Jie Jin, Tian-Yang Sun, Jing-Fei Zhang, Xin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The weak, the strong and the ugly -- A comparative analysis of interacting stepped dark radiation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.12469</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.12469v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Models which address both the Hubble and $S_8$ tensions with the same mechanism generically cause a pre-recombination suppression of the small scale matter power spectrum. Here we focus on two such models. Both models introduce a self-interacting dark radiation fluid scattering with dark matter, which has a step in its abundance around some transition redshift. In one model, the interaction is weak and with all of the dark matter whereas in the other it is strong but with only a fraction of the dark matter. The weakly interacting case is able to address both tensions simultaneously and provide a good fit to a the Planck measurements of the cosmic microwave background (CMB), the Pantheon Type Ia supernovae, and a combination of low and high redshift baryon acoustic oscillation data, whereas the strongly interacting model cannot significantly ease both tensions simultaneously. The addition of high-resolution cosmic microwave background (CMB) measurements (ACT DR4 and SPT-3G) slightly limits both model's ability to address the Hubble tension. The use of the effective field theory of large-scale structures analysis of BOSS DR12 LRG and eBOSS DR16 QSO data additionally limits their ability to address the $S_8$ tension. We explore how these models respond to these data sets in detail in order to draw general conclusions about what is required for a mechanism to address both tensions. We find that in order to fit the CMB data the time dependence of the suppression of the matter power spectrum plays a central role.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.12469v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.108.123513</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review D, volume 108, issue 12, pages 123513-123536 (23 pages), December 2023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nils Sch\"oneberg, Guillermo Franco Abell\'an, Th\'eo Simon, Alexa Bartlett, Yashvi Patel, Tristan L. Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inflation Correlators with Multiple Massive Exchanges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.10849</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.10849v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The most general tree-level boundary correlation functions of quantum fields in inflationary spacetime involve multiple exchanges of massive states in the bulk, which are technically difficult to compute due to the multi-layer nested time integrals in the Schwinger-Keldysh formalism. On the other hand, correlators with multiple massive exchanges are well motivated in cosmological collider physics, with the original quasi-single-field inflation model as a notable example. In this work, with the partial Mellin-Barnes representation, we derive a simple rule, called family-tree decomposition, for directly writing down analytical answers for arbitrary nested time integrals in terms of multi-variable hypergeometric series. We present the derivation of this rule together with many explicit examples. This result allows us to obtain analytical expressions for general tree-level inflation correlators with multiple massive exchanges. As an example, we present the full analytical results for a range of tree correlators with two massive exchanges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.10849v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhong-Zhi Xianyu, Jiaju Zang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lorentz invariance violation and the CPT-odd electromagnetic response of a tilted anisotropic Weyl semimetal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.07791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.07791v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We derive the electromagnetic response of a particular fermionic sector in the minimal QED contribution to the Standard Model Extension (SME), which can be physically realized in terms of a model describing a tilted and anisotropic Weyl semimetal (WSM). The contact is made through the identification of the Dirac-like Hamiltonian resulting from the SME with that corresponding to the WSM in the linearized tight-binding approximation. We first calculate the effective action by computing the non-perturbative vacuum polarization tensor using thermal field theory techniques, focusing upon the corrections at finite chemical potential and zero temperature. Next, we confirm our results by a direct calculation of the anomalous Hall current within a chiral kinetic theory approach.
  In an ideal Dirac cone picture of the WSM (isotropic and non-tilted) such response is known to be governed by axion electrodynamics, with the space-time dependent axion angle $\Theta (\mathbf{r},t) = 2 (\mathbf{b} \cdot \mathbf{r} - b _{0} t)$, being $2 \mathbf{b}$ and $2b _{0}$ the separation of the Weyl nodes in momentum and energy, respectively. In this paper we demonstrate that the node tilting and the anisotropies induce novel corrections at a finite density which however preserve the structure of the axionic field theory. We apply our results to the ideal Weyl semimetal $\mathrm{EuCd}_{2}\mathrm{As}_{2}$ and to the highly anisotropic and tilted monopnictide $\mathrm{TaAs}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.07791v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.065005</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'es G\'omez, R. Mart\'inez von Dossow, A. Mart\'in-Ruiz, Luis F. Urrutia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural networks for boosted di-$\tau$ identification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.08276</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.08276v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We train several neural networks and boosted decision trees to discriminate fully-hadronic boosted di-$\tau$ topologies against background QCD jets, using calorimeter and tracking information. Boosted di-$\tau$ topologies consisting of a pair of highly collimated $\tau$-leptons, arise from the decay of a highly energetic Standard Model Higgs or Z boson or from particles beyond the Standard Model. We compare the tagging performance for different neural-network models and a boosted decision tree, the latter serving as a simple benchmark machine learning model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.08276v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nadav Tamir, Ilan Bessudo, Boping Chen, Hely Raiko, Liron Barak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the asymptotic safety in the Litim-Sannino model at four loops</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.12128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.12128v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a four-dimensional $SU(N_c)$ gauge theory coupled to $N_f$ species of color fermions and $N_f^2$ colorless scalars. The quantum field theory possesses a weakly interacting ultraviolet fixed point that we determine from beta functions computed up to four-loop order in the gauge coupling, and up to three-loop order in the Yukawa and quartic scalar couplings. The fixed point has one relevant direction giving rise to asymptotic safety. We compute fixed-point values of dimensionless couplings together with the corresponding scaling exponents up to the first three non-trivial orders in Veneziano parameter $\epsilon$, both for infinite and finite number of colors $N_c$. We also consider anomalous dimensions for fields, scalar mass squared, and a class of dimension-3 operators. Contrary to previous studies, we take into account possible mixing of the latter and compute eigenvalues of the corresponding matrix. Further, we investigate the size of the conformal window in the Veneziano limit and its dependence on $N_c$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.12128v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. V. Bednyakov, A. I. Mukhaeva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sliding into DM: Determining the local dark matter density and speed distribution using only the local circular speed of the Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04122v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We use FIRE-2 zoom simulations of Milky Way size disk galaxies to derive easy-to-use relationships between the observed circular speed of the Galaxy at the Solar location, $v_\mathrm{c}$, and dark matter properties of relevance for direct detection experiments: the dark matter density, the dark matter velocity dispersion, and the speed distribution of dark matter particles near the Solar location. We find that both the local dark matter density and 3D velocity dispersion follow tight power laws with $v_\mathrm{c}$. Using this relation together with the observed circular speed of the Milky Way at the Solar radius, we infer the local dark matter density and velocity dispersion near the Sun to be $\rho = 0.42\pm 0.06\,\mathrm{GeV\,cm^{-3}}$ and $\sigma_\mathrm{3D} = 280^{+19}_{-18}\,\mathrm{km\,s^{-1}}$. We also find that the distribution of dark matter particle speeds is well-described by a modified Maxwellian with two shape parameters, both of which correlate with the observed $v_{\rm c}$. We use that modified Maxwellian to predict the speed distribution of dark matter near the Sun and find that it peaks at a most probable speed of $250\,\mathrm{km\,s^{-1}}$ and begins to truncate sharply above $470\,\mathrm{km\,s^{-1}}$. This peak speed is somewhat higher than expected from the standard halo model, and the truncation occurs well below the formal escape speed to infinity, with fewer very-high-speed particles than assumed in the standard halo model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04122v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick G. Staudt, James S. Bullock, Michael Boylan-Kolchin, Andrew Wetzel, Xiaowei Ou</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
