<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph</link>
    <description>hep-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2024 04:00:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Flavor neutrinos as unstable particles: an interaction picture view</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05158v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper reviews the similarities in the behavior of unstable particles and oscillating neutrinos using perturbation theory within the interaction picture of quantum field theory. We begin by examining how decaying systems are studied in the interaction picture and then demonstrate how similar calculations can be performed to determine the transition probabilities for flavor oscillations. Notably, the expressions for neutrino oscillations and particle decays are identical in the short-time range. Furthermore, we show that the flavor oscillation formula derived through this method matches, within the adopted approximation, the one obtained using the flavor Fock space approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05158v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Blasone, F. Giacosa, L. Smaldone, G. Torrieri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oscillations of Majorana neutrinos in supernova and CP violation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05171</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05171v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Leptonic CP violation is one of the most important topics in neutrino physics. CP violation in the neutrino sector is strongly related to the nature of neutrinos: whether they are Dirac or Majorana particles. In \cite{Popov:2021icg} we have shown that for Majorana neutrinos appearance of nonzero Majorana CP-violating phases combined with strong magnetic field during supernova core-collapse can induce new resonances in neutrino oscillations, for example in $\nu_e \to \bar{\nu}_\tau$ channel. In this paper we further study new resonances in Majorana neutrino oscillations, in particular energy dependence of amplitudes of resonant oscillations. Our findings suggest a potential astrophysical setup for studying the nature of neutrino masses and leptonic CP violation and may be important for future neutrino experiments, such as JUNO, Hyper-Kamiokande and DUNE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05171v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physics of Particles and Nuclei Letters (2024) Vol.21, No.3, pp. 430-433</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. Popov, A. Studenikin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Standard Model lifetime is slightly shorter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05180v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revisit the decay rate of the electroweak vacuum in the Standard Model with the full one-loop prefactor. We focus on the gauge degrees of freedom and derive the degeneracy factors appearing in the functional determinant using group theoretical arguments. Our treatment shows that the transverse modes were previously overcounted, so we revise the calculation of that part of the prefactor. The new result modifies the gauge fields' contribution by $7\%$ and slightly decreases the previously predicted lifetime of the electroweak vacuum, which remains much longer than the age of the universe. Our discussion of the transverse mode degeneracy applies to any calculation of functional determinants involving gauge fields in four dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05180v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pietro Baratella, Miha Nemev\v{s}ek, Yutaro Shoji, Katarina Trailovi\'c, Lorenzo Ubaldi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signatures of Bulk Neutrinos in the Early Universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05266v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Neutrino masses and quantum gravity are strong reasons to extend the standard model of particle physics. A large extra dimension can be motivated by quantum gravity and can explain the small neutrino masses with new singlet states that propagate in the bulk. In such a case, a Kaluza-Klein tower of sterile neutrinos emerges. We revisit constraints on towers of sterile neutrinos that come from cosmological observables such as the effective number of noninteracting relativistic species and the dark matter density. These limits generically rule out micron-sized extra dimensions. We explore the weakening of these constraints to accommodate an extra dimension close to the micron size by assuming that the universe reheated after inflation to a low temperature. We discuss how such a possibility can be distinguished in the event of a positive signal in a cosmological observable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05266v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David McKeen, John Ng, Michael Shamma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predictions and Tests for Semi-leptonic Decays of Beauty Hadrons,</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05456</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05456v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We compare the features of the semi-leptonic decays $B\to D^{(*)} l \bar{\nu}_l$ and $\Lambda_b\to \Lambda_c l \bar{\nu}_l$, with $l$ = $e$, $\mu$ and $\tau$. Firstly, we study such processes according to the $\ell-s$ scheme. Then, we write the angular distributions of those decays in the helicity formalism; we focus especially on the case of $l$ = $\tau$ and suggest for each decay some tests for distinguishing among the various Dirac operators which may explain the tension with the standard model. In particular, as regards the $\Lambda_b$ semi-leptonic decay, we single out five observables, which assume different values for each new-physics interaction; one such observable is related to the longitudinal polarization of the $\tau-\bar{\nu}_\tau$ system, which can be compared with the $D^*$ longitudinal polarization in the $B\to D^* l \bar{\nu}_l$ decay. Moreover, we perform a phenomenological analysis of the decays, particularly of $\Lambda_b$, starting from an assumption which agrees with previous theoretical calculations and has a predictive power about the total widths of several decays; we give also a theoretical explanation to some results that were found in preceding analyses about the above mentioned $B$-decays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05456v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elvio Di Salvo, Ziad J. Ajaltouni, Flavio Fontanelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New ideas in nonperturbative QCD -- I</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05584v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The recent development of the Field Correlator Method (FCM) is discussed, with applications to the most interesting areas of QCD physics obtained in the lattice data and experiment. These areas include: a) the connection of colorelectric confinement with the basic quark and gluon condensates; b) the explicit form of the colorelectric deconfinement at a growing temperature $T$; c) the theory of the colormagnetic confinement at all temperatures; d) the theory of strong decays, the theory of pdf and jets in the instantaneous formalism with confinement. We demonstrate that the FCM with instantaneous formalism and confinement (instead of the light cone formalism and pure perturbation theory) can provide the way to the theory of QCD, which helps to describe world data without phenomenological parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05584v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. S. Lukashov, Yu. A. Simonov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparative Study of tau neutrinos event numbers in INO and JUNO detectors from Bartol Flux</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05601v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To expand our understanding of neutrino physics, scientific researchers of astroparticle Physics directs their goal of detecting atmospheric tau neutrinos in the GeV range. The effort will fundamentally unlock the nature of these elusive particles while also investigating muon neutrinos and tau neutrino oscillations. The Jiangmen Underground Neutrino Observatory (JUNO), which has already started its operations in 2024, and the India-based Neutrino Observatory (INO), which is not active right now but has future objectives in conducting research, have both emerged as key players in this field. These experiments used theoretical and experimental methodologies to understand the properties and behaviour of atmospheric tau neutrinos. The JUNO experiment, which has an estimated ability to detect around 50 events per year, and the INO, which used an impressive 50,000-ton iron slab as a detector, will contribute significantly in this domain. The detection of all tau neutrinos charged-current (CC) interactions with the detection material, which is divided into former and later events based on the timeline corresponding to scattering and capture in the detector; moreover, the KamLAND experiment is also capable of detecting these tau neutrinos decays, however, in smaller proportions, which could be possibly confused with background signals emerging from oscillations. This has been studied for both experiments for tau neutrinos nuclei cross-sections, and its standard value is taken as a base for calculations. Both INO and JUNO have 5 sigma sensitivity, which was exposed for 5 to 10 years.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05601v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kartik Joshi, Satyajit Jena</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photon induced proton and anti-proton pair production with ultraperipheral heavy ion collisions at RHIC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05618</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05618v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate proton-antiproton ($p\bar{p}$) pair production via photon-photon fusion in the ultra-peripheral collisions at RHIC, employing a joint impact parameter and transverse momentum dependent formalism. We consider proton exchange, $s$-channel resonance and hand-bag mechanisms, predicting differential distributions of $p\bar p$ production. Our theoretical predictions can be tested against future measurements at RHIC, to enhance our understanding of photon-photon interactions in strong electromagnetic fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05618v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng Zhang, Li-Mao Zhang, Ding Yu Shao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating Parton Fragmentation on Quantum Computers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05683v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Parton fragmentation functions (FFs) are indispensable for understanding processes of hadron production ubiquitously existing in high-energy collisions, but their first principle determination has never been realized due to the insurmountable difficulties in encoding their operator definition using traditional lattice methodology. We propose a framework that makes a first step for evaluating FFs utilizing quantum computing methodology. The key element is to construct a semi-inclusive hadron operator for filtering out hadrons of desired types in a collection of particles encoded in the quantum state. We illustrate the framework by elaborating on the Nambu-Jona-Lasinio model with numeral simulations. Remarkably, We show that the semi-inclusive hadron operator can be constructed efficiently with a variational quantum algorithm. Moreover, we develop error mitigation techniques tailed for accurately calculating the FFs in the presence of quantum noises. Our work opens a new avenue for investigating QCD hadronization on near-term quantum computers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05683v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianyin Li, Hongxi Xing, Dan-Bo Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resummation of relativistic corrections to heavy quarkonium $+\,\gamma$ production at $Z$ factory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05729</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05729v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cross sections of the heavy quarkonium production process $e^+e^-\to H + \gamma$ at the c.m. energy of $Z^0$-boson resonance are calculated at leading order in $\alpha_s$ with relativistic corrections resummed within the framework of nonrelativistic QCD (NRQCD). $S$- and $P$-wave charmonia and bottomonia are considered. For $J/\psi(\Upsilon)$ production, the result of vector-meson-dominance (VMD) approach is also given. Relativistic contributions to charmonium production are of the same magnitude as next-to-leading order QCD corrections, decreasing cross section 20-30%. Relativistic corrections to bottomonium production are negligible, not exceeding 2%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05729v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Trunin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LAYCAST: LAYered CAvern Surface Tracker at future electron-positron colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05770</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05770v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a detector concept, LAYered CAvern Surface Tracker (LAYCAST), to be installed on the ceiling and the wall of the cavern hosting the main experiment of future electron-positron colliders such as CEPC and FCC-ee. With detailed and realistic considerations of the design of such a new experiment, the proposed detector is dedicated to extending the sensitivity reach of the main detector to various theoretical scenarios of long-lived particles (LLPs). We study carefully four such scenarios involving a light scalar boson $X$, the heavy neutral lepton $N$, the lightest neutralino $\tilde{\chi}^0_1$ in the R-parity-violating supersymmetry, and the axion-like particle $a$. Long-lived light scalar bosons are considered to be produced from the Standard-Model (SM) Higgs boson's decay ($h \to X X$) at the center-of-mass energy $\sqrt{s} =$ 240 GeV, while the other three types of LLPs are produced either from $Z$-boson decays (viz. $Z \to \nu\, N, ~\tilde{\chi}^0_1\, \tilde{\chi}^0_1 $) or direct scattering process ($ e^- e^+ \to ~\gamma\, a$) at $\sqrt{s} =$ 91.2 GeV, where $\gamma$ and $\nu$ denote the SM photon and neutrino, respectively. With Monte-Carlo simulations, we derive the sensitivities of the proposed experiment to these LLPs and the corresponding signal-event numbers. Our findings show that LAYCAST can probe large new parameter space beyond both current bounds and the expected reach of the main experiments at CEPC and FCC-ee. Comparison with existing works in similar directions is also made.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05770v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ye Lu, Ying-nan Mao, Kechen Wang, Zeren Simon Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long Range Azimuthal Correlation, Entanglement and Bell Inequality Violation by Spinning Gluons at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05880</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05880v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We apply the recently developed concept of the nucleon energy-energy correlator (NEEC) for the gluon sector to investigate the long-range azimuthal angular correlations in proton-proton collisions at the LHC. The spinning gluon in these collisions will introduce a significant nonzero $\cos(2\phi)$ asymmetries in both Higgs Boson and top quark pair productions. The genesis of the $\cos(2\phi)$ correlation lies in the intricate quantum entanglement. Owing to the substantial $\cos(2\phi)$ effect, the NEEC observable in Higgs Boson and $t{\bar t}$ production emerges as a pivotal avenue for delving into quantum entanglement and scrutinizing the Bell inequality at high-energy colliders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05880v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxun Guo, Xiaohui Liu, Feng Yuan, Hua Xing Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Possible mixing of a diquark-antidiquark with a $p \bar p$ hadronic molecule</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05920</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05920v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss the possibility that the two nearby resonances observed by BESIII partially below the \,$p\bar p$\, threshold might be due to mixing between two metastable states with the same $J^{PC}=0^{-+}$ quantum numbers, but rather different internal structure. One is a $p \bar p$ hadronic molecule and the other a bound state of a light-quark diquark and an antidiquark, both with spin 1 and isospin 0, a composite color antitriplet and triplet, respectively. The doubling of resonances, one of which may be interpreted as a hadronic molecule, while the other arises from $q \bar q$ annihilation in a state with vacuum quantum numbers may be a more general feature than the specific case considered here.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05920v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marek Karliner, Jonathan L. Rosner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using $\Lambda_b^0(6146)$ and $\Lambda_b^0(6152)$ as probes to investigate possible $\bar{B}^{*}N$ and $\bar{D}^{*}N$ molecules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05991v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Heavy quark symmetry can help us identify the internal structure of hadrons and predict new particles. In this study, we examine the strong decay modes of the observed $\Lambda_b^0(6146)$ and $\Lambda_b^0(6152)$, assuming these two states are molecular states primarily composed of $\bar{B}^{*}N$ component. The partial decay widths of the $\bar{B}^{*}N$ molecular state into the $\pi\Sigma_b$ and $\pi\Sigma_b^{*}$ final states through hadronic loops are calculated using effective Lagrangians. Our results, when compared with LHCb observations, support the interpretation of $\Lambda_b^0(6146)$ as a molecule primarily composed of $\bar{B}^{*}N$ components. However, the decay width of $\Lambda_b^0(6152)$ cannot be accurately reproduced within the molecular state framework. Based on the above results and heavy quark symmetry, we predict the existence of $\bar{B}^{*}N$ molecular states with $J^p=5/2^{+}$, which are the heavy quark spin symmetry partners of $\Lambda_b(6146)$, with masses in the range of 6195-6200 MeV. And the main decay is $\pi\Sigma_b^{*}$ channel. Moreover, there must existence of a $\bar{D}^{*}N$ molecule with $J^p=3/2^{+}$, possible corresponding to the experimentally observed $\Lambda_c(2860)^{+}$. If $\Lambda_c(2880)^{+}$ is indeed the heavy quark flavor symmetry partner of $\Lambda_b(6152)$, it would exhibit a conventional three-quark structure. Therefore, we also propose the search for a $\bar{D}^{*}N$ molecule with a spin-parity of $J^p=5/2^{+}$, which would be the heavy-quark spin partner state of $\Lambda_c(2860)^{+}$. It should be noted that these baryons may be mixed states, containing both molecular and three-quark components. These results can aid experiments in exploring the internal structure of these baryons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05991v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing-wen Feng, Cai Cheng, Yin Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards NNPDFpol2.0</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06083</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06083v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We review the recent efforts in the NNPDF Collaboration towards a new global extraction of polarized parton distributions functions (pPDF). Polarized PDFs are highly relevant for the interpretation of current and future polarized high-energy experiments, including the upcoming Electron-Ion Collider (EIC). We present a recent study of the role played by heavy quark effects in polarized DIS, where we apply the FONLL general-mass variable-flavour-number scheme for the first time in a polarized setup and demonstrate the significant impact of charm mass corrections, specifically for the polarized gluon distribution. We show preliminary results (DIS-only) of this new pPDF release, NNPDFpol2.0, based on the NNPDF4.0 fitting machinery and the associated new theory prediction pipeline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06083v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felix Hekhorn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring alignment phenomenon through the transverse momentum disbalance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06114v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The hypothesis of the relation between the observed alignment of spots in the X-ray films in cosmic ray emulsion experiments and the selection procedure of the highest-energy particles itself together with the transverse momentum conservation is tested in the framework of the HYDJET++ model. It is shown that the high degree of alignment can appear at the reasonable values of transverse momentum disbalance of selected most energetic particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06114v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. P. Lokhtin, A. V. Nikolskii, A. M. Snigirev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precision calculations of the $D_{(s)}D_{(s)}V$ and $B_{(s)}B_{(s)}V$ couplings from light-cone sum rules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06209v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an improved calculation of the $HHV$ ($H=D_{(s)},\, B_{(s)}$, $V= \rho$, $K^\ast$, $\omega$, and $\phi$) coupling constants $g_{HHV}$ beyond leading order in $\alpha_s$ from QCD light-cone sum rules (LCSRs) by means of the light-cone distribution amplitudes (LCDAs) of light vector mesons. Near the light-cone, the next-to-leading order QCD corrections for the vacuum-to-vector-meson correlation function are included at leading power in $\delta_V = m_V/m_Q$ ($Q=b,c$) within the framework of hard-collinear factorization. The higher-twist corrections from two-particle and three-particle vector meson LCDAs are systematically incorporated at leading order in $\alpha_s$ by applying the method of background field in LCSRs. Based on these improvements, we perform a systematic computation of the strong coupling constants $g_{H HV}$ and extract the effective coupling $\beta$ of the heavy meson chiral perturbation theory (HM$\chi$PT). Furthermore, we accomplish the analysis for the relation between the coupling $g_{HHV}$ and the residue of the $H\to V$ transition form factor $A_0$ at heavy pseudoscalar pole. Additionally, we provide a detailed investigation of the $SU(3)$ flavour symmetry breaking effects and conduct a comparative analysis with results from previous studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06209v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hua-Yu Jiang, Su-Ping Jin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic complex potential of a quarkonium from deep learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06285</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06285v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Utilizing an emergent metric developed from deep learning techniques, we determine the complex potential associated with static quarkonium. This study explores the disintegration process of quarkonium by analyzing the real component of this potential, which is crucial for understanding its stability in various conditions. We show that the dissociation length, the critical distance at which a quark and antiquark pair disintegrate, decreases as the temperature increases. Furthermore, our assessment of the imaginary component of the potential indicates an increase in the magnitude of the imaginary potential for quarkonium as temperatures rise. This enhancement contributes to the quarkonium's suppression within the quark-gluon plasma, mirroring the anticipated outcomes from QCD. Our findings not only confirm the theoretical predictions but also demonstrate the efficacy of deep learning methods in advancing our understanding of high-energy particle physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06285v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahdi Mansouri, Kazem Bitaghsir Fadafan, Xun Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological structures, dark matter and gravitational waves in $E_6$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06308</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06308v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss the appearance of topological structures from the spontaneous breaking of $E_6$ to the Standard Model via its maximal subgroup $SO(10) \times U(1)_\psi$. They include dumbbells, metastable strings, as well as domain walls bounded by necklaces. We provide a novel scenario for producing metastable strings based on the symmetry breaking $U(1)_\psi \longrightarrow Z_8 \longrightarrow Z_4$. The metastable string arises from the merger of $Z_8$ strings that bound a domain wall. An unbroken gauge $Z_2$ symmetry from $SO(10)$ breaking yields viable stable dark matter candidates as well as topologically stable strings. We discuss the gravitational wave emission from two varieties of cosmic strings, namely the superheavy metastable ones and the intermediate scale topologically stable cosmic strings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06308v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rinku Maji, Qaisar Shafi, Amit Tiwari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dilatonic Couplings and the Relic Abundance of Ultralight Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06395</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06395v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Models of scalar field dark matter where the scalar is a dilaton have a special behaviour, since non-trivial couplings, $d$, to matter result in a contribution to the potential for the field which is proportional to the trace of the stress-energy tensor. We look in more detail at the dilaton mass, $m_\phi$, and initial conditions required to yield the correct relic abundance for couplings that are not already excluded by terrestrial experiments. In minimal models with only couplings accessible to terrestrial searches, we find that dilaton dark matter with $m_{\phi} \gtrsim 10^{-10}$ eV requires couplings suppressed compared to constraints from equivalence principle (EP) tests and fifth force searches in order to not produce too much dark matter, improving on the strongest current experimental constraints by up to $\sim {\cal O}(10)$, with consequences for the proposed mechanical resonator dilaton DM searches. In non-minimal or universally coupled models, the unconstrained couplings of the dilaton to e.g. the top quark can strongly influence the relic abundance at all masses. In particular, this implies that atom interferometry searches at masses $m_\phi\approx 10^{-19}\text{ eV}$ are unable to constrain the early Universe behaviour or UV physics of the dilaton. We also find that dilatonic couplings allow for compatibility of $m_\phi \gtrsim 10^{-7}\text{ eV}$ with an observably large tensor-to-scalar ratio in the cosmic microwave background, which is not possible for a decoupled scalar of the same mass.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06395v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmad Alachkar, Malcolm Fairbairn, David J. E. Marsh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental Bounds on Deformed Muon Lifetime Dilation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05150v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyze Planck scale induced modifications of the relativistic time dilation using data from the Muon Storage Ring experiment at CERN. By examining the lifetimes of muons, we establish, for the first time, a constraint on such quantum gravity-inspired deformations using this channel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05150v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Iarley P. Lobo, Christian Pfeifer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Implication of Enhanced Cosmic Ray Diurnal Anisotropy on the Global Simultaneity of Forbush Decreases: A Statistical Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05160v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The short-term rapid CR flux depressions, generally referred to as Forbush decreases (FDs), are the most spectacular time-intensity CR variation. The need for analytical transformation of the observational CR time series data, to account for FDs and other recurrence tendencies such as periodicities and cycles, was noted since the 1930s'. Nevertheless, it has been recently observed that harmonic analysis, which is capable of transforming raw CR data into different frequencies, is rarely exploited. Predominant in the literature are the ordinary Fourier and power spectral analyses, generally used to calculate the positive vectors (amplitude and phase) of the periodic diurnal CR anisotropy. In the two approaches, the days immediately connected with FDs are frequently removed to minimize unusual changes in the amplitude of the vectors as well as a spurious time of maximum. However, there is a paucity of publications that adjust for the influence of enhanced CR diurnal anisotropy on the magnitude and timing of FDs. Recently, in an attempt to test the global FD event simultaneity, a combination of numerical filtering and fast Fourier transform techniques was deployed to account for these superposition tendencies in daily CR data, including the intractable CR diurnal anisotropy. However, an extremely sensitive version of the software would be required to analyze high-resolution CR hourly averages. As a way of achieving accurate detection and precise timing of FD signals, the computer algorithms were technically improved and employed in a long-term statistical investigation. To appreciate the implemented extremely sensitive statistical technique, several validation analyses, including FD-based solar-terrestrial correlation, comparison of FD catalogues, and Frobush event simultaneity test were conducted.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05160v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Publication of the Astronomical Society of Nigeria (PASN) 07, pg 44 - 55 (2022)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>O. Okike, J. A. Alhassan, I. O. Eya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2D BAO vs 3D BAO: Hints for new physics?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05453v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the era of tensions, when precision cosmology is blooming, numerous new theoretical models are emerging. However, it's crucial to pause and question the extent to which the observational data we rely on are model-dependent. In this work, we study the comoving position of the acoustic peak, a cornerstone standard ruler in cosmology. We considered BAO observational datasets from two distinct teams and calculated the product $hr_d$ with the help of each BAO data set along with SN I-a data from the Pantheon Plus sample. Our conclusion at present is that 2D and 3D BAO datasets are compatible with each other. Considering, no systematics in BAO, interpreting $\Omega_{m0}-hr_d$ plane may require physics beyond $\Lambda$CDM not just while using observational BAO data but also while observing it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05453v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Ruchika</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The History of Primordial Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05736v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We overview the history of primordial black hole (PBH) research from the first papers around 50 years ago to the present epoch. The history may be divided into four periods, the dividing lines being marked by three key developments: inflation on the theoretical front and the detection of microlensing events by the MACHO project and gravitational waves by the LIGO/Virgo/KAGRA project on the observation front. However, they are also characterised by somewhat different focuses of research. The period 1967-1980 covered the groundbreaking work on PBH formation and evaporation. The period 1980-1996 mainly focussed on their formation, while the period 1996-2016 consolidated the work on formation but also collated the constraints on the PBH abundance. In the period 2016-2024 there was a shift of emphasis to the search for evidence for PBHs and - while opinions about the strength of the purported evidence vary - this has motivated more careful studies of some aspects of the subject. Certainly the soaring number of papers on PBHs in this last period indicates a growing interest in the topic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05736v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bernard J. Carr, Anne M. Green</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bubbles kick off primordial black holes to form more binaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05838v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Primordial black holes (PBHs) may form before cosmological first-order phase transitions, leading to inevitable collisions between PBHs and bubble walls. In this Letter, we have simulated for the first time the co-evolution of an expanding scalar wall passing through a black hole with full numerical relativity. This black hole-bubble wall collision yields multiple far-reaching phenomena including the PBH mass growth, gravitational wave radiations, and momentum recoil that endows PBHs with additional velocities, approximately doubling the formation rate for PBH binaries and hence strengthening the observational constraints on the PBH abundances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05838v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zi-Yan Yuwen, Cristian Joana, Shao-Jiang Wang, Rong-Gen Cai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimal Cuts and Genealogical Constraints on Feynman Integrals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05943v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce an efficient method for deriving hierarchical constraints on the discontinuities of individual Feynman integrals. This method can be applied at any loop order and particle multiplicity, and to any configuration of massive or massless virtual particles. The resulting constraints hold to all orders in dimensional regularization, and complement the extended Steinmann relations -- which restrict adjacent sequential discontinuities -- by disallowing ordered pairs of discontinuities from appearing even when separated by (any number of) other discontinuities. We focus on a preferred class of hierarchical constraints, which we refer to as \emph{genealogical constraints}, that govern what singularities can follow from certain \emph{minimal cuts} that act as the primogenitors of the discontinuities that appear in Feynman integrals. While deriving the full set of hierarchical constraints on a given Feynman integral generally requires identifying all solutions to the (blown up) Landau equations, these genealogical constraints can be worked out with only minimal information about what singularities may appear. We illustrate the power of this new method in examples at one, two, and three loops, and provide evidence that genealogical constraints restrict the analytic structure of Feynman integrals significantly more than the extended Steinmann relations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05943v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Holmfridur S. Hannesdottir, Luke Lippstreu, Andrew J. McLeod, Maria Polackova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The matrix model of two-color one-flavor QCD: The ultra-strong coupling regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06055</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06055v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Using variational methods, we numerically investigate the matrix model for the two-color QCD coupled to a single quark (matrix-QCD$_{2,1}$) in the limit of ultra-strong Yang-Mills coupling ($g =\infty$). The spectrum of the model has superselection sectors labelled by baryon number $B$ and spin $J$. We study sectors with $B=0,1,2$ and $J=0,1$, which may be organized as mesons, (anti-)diquarks and (anti-)tetraquarks. For each of these sectors, we study the properties of the respective ground states in both chiral and heavy quark limits, and uncover a rich quantum phase transition (QPT) structure. We also investigate the division of the total spin between the glue and the quark and show that glue contribution is significant for several of these sectors. For the $(B,J)=(0,0)$ sector, we find that the dominant glue contribution to the ground state comes from reducible connections. Finally, in the presence of non-trivial baryon chemical potential $\mu$, we construct the phase diagram of the model. For sufficiently large $\mu$, we find that the ground state of the theory may have non-zero spin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06055v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nirmalendu Acharyya, Prasanjit Aich, Arkajyoti Bandyopadhyay, Sachindeo Vaidya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Generational Black Hole Population Analysis with an Astrophysically Informed Mass Function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06109</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06109v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyze the population statistics of black holes in the LIGO/Virgo/KAGRA GWTC-3 catalog using a parametric mass function derived from simulations of massive stars experiencing pulsational pair-instability supernovae (PPISN). Our formalism enables us to separate the black hole mass function into sub-populations corresponding to mergers between objects formed via different astrophysical pathways, allowing us to infer the properties of black holes formed from stellar collapse and black holes formed via prior mergers separately. Applying this formalism, we find that this model fits the data better than the powerlaw+peak model with Bayes factor $ 9.7\pm0.1$. We measure the location of the lower edge of the upper black hole mass gap to be $M_{\rm BHMG}=84.05_{-12.88}^{+17.19}{\rm M}_{\odot}$, providing evidence that the $35{\rm M}_{\odot}$ Gaussian peak detected in the data using other models is not associated with the PPISN pile-up predicted to precede this gap. Incorporating spin, we find that the normalized spins of stellar remnant black holes are close to zero while those of higher generation black holes tend to larger values. All of these results are in accordance with the predictions of stellar structure theory and black hole merger scenarios. Finally, we combine our mass function with the spectral siren method for measuring the Hubble constant to find $H_0=36.19_{-10.91}^{17.50}$ km/s/Mpc and discuss potential explanations of this low value. Our results demonstrate how astrophysically-informed mass functions can facilitate the interpretation of gravitational wave catalog data to provide information about black hole formation and cosmology. Future data releases will improve the precision of our measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06109v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yannick Ulrich, Djuna Croon, Jeremy Sakstein, Samuel McDermott</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higgs cross-section ( including di-Higgs ) with CMS and ATLAS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06172v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Since the discovery of the Higgs boson in 2012 by the ATLAS and CMS Collaborations a lot of progress has been made in verifying the nature of this new bosonic particle. Still, questions remain as to whether this new particle is the standard model (SM) Higgs boson, and whether it gives us hints of where physics beyond the SM (BSM) might be hidden. This overview tries to tackle these questions by looking at three types of analyses 1) Total cross section measurements of the various Higgs boson production and decay modes, allowing us access to the various Higgs boson couplings to SM bosons and fermions, 2) Differential Higgs boson cross section measurements such as in the STXS framework allowing for a model independent search for BSM and, finally, 3) The searches for di-Higgs production which give access to the trilinear Higgs self coupling $\lambda$ and the Higgs potential itself.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06172v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Torben Lange (on behalf of the ATLAS,CMS Collaborations)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implications of DES 5YR SNe Dataset for $\Lambda$CDM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06389</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06389v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Dark Energy Survey five-year supernovae data (DES 5YR SNe) in conjunction with Planck CMB and Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) BAO data has detected a strong dynamical dark energy deviation from the $\Lambda$CDM model. Here, we shift the focus of DES data to the pressureless matter sector in the $\Lambda$CDM model by studying the matter density parameter $\Omega_m$. Employing frequentist profile likelihoods, we demonstrate that $\Omega_m$ increases with effective redshift in the DES dataset at up to $2.5 \sigma$ level. At the highest redshifts, one encounters negative dark energy densities $\Omega_m &gt; 1$. Our findings corroborate earlier observations in Pantheon and Pantheon+ datasets with an independent SNe dataset with a higher effective redshift. In an appendix, we confirm that curvature $\Omega_k$ decreases with effective redshift disfavouring a flat Universe in higher redshift DES SNe at $&gt; 3 \sigma$. Our choice of $\Omega_k$ prior leads to an underestimation of the tension with a flat Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06389v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eoin \'O Colg\'ain, Saeed Pourojaghi, M. M. Sheikh-Jabbari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for Pseudo-Dirac neutrinos from Astrophysical sources in IceCube data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06476v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyze IceCube public data from its IC86 configuration, namely PSTracks event selection, to search for pseudo-Dirac signatures in high-energy neutrinos from astrophysical sources. Neutrino flux from astrophysical sources is reduced in the pseudo-Dirac scenario due to conversion of active-to-sterile neutrinos as compared to the neutrino oscillation scenario of only three active neutrinos over astrophysical distances. We fit IceCube data using astrophysical flux models for three point-like sources in both scenarios and constrain the active-sterile mass-square-difference in the absence of any evidence for pseudo-Dirac scenario. We find that a common mass-squared-difference $\delta m^2$ for all three flavors can be constrained as $\delta m^2 \lesssim 4 \times 10^{-19}~eV^2$ for the source NGC 1068, $\delta m^2 \lesssim 8 \times 10^{-20}~eV^2$ for the source TXS 0506+056, and $\delta m^2 \lesssim 2.3 \times 10^{-21}~eV^2$ for the source PKS 1424+240 at 90% C.L. A stacking analysis gives a constrain on $\delta m^2 \le 2.3 \times 10^{-21}~eV^2$ at 90% CL which is dominated by the constraint obtained from PKS 1424+240.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06476v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Khushboo Dixit, Luis Salvador Miranda, Soebur Razzaque</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Macroscopic quantum superpositions in superconducting circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06492v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A possible route to test whether macroscopic systems can acquire quantum features using superconducting circuits is here presented. It is shown that under general assumptions a classical test current pulse of fixed energy and adjustable length acquires quantum features after interacting with the quantum vacuum of the photon field. Further, it is shown that the mere existence of vacuum fluctuations can lead to the breakdown of energy and momentum conservation, and as the length of the pulse grows with respect to the characteristic size of the quantum system, the test pulse undergoes quantum-to-classical transition. This model differs from previous ones for its simplicity and points towards a new way of creating correlated systems suitable for quantum-based technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06492v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vitoria A. de Souza, Caio C. Holanda Ribeiro, Vitorio A. De Lorenci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermion Mass Hierarchies, Large Lepton Mixing and Residual Modular Symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2102.07488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2102.07488v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In modular-invariant models of flavour, hierarchical fermion mass matrices may arise solely due to the proximity of the modulus $\tau$ to a point of residual symmetry. This mechanism does not require flavon fields, and modular weights are not analogous to Froggatt-Nielsen charges. Instead, we show that hierarchies depend on the decomposition of field representations under the residual symmetry group. We systematically go through the possible fermion field representation choices which may yield hierarchical structures in the vicinity of symmetric points, for the four smallest finite modular groups, isomorphic to $S_3$, $A_4$, $S_4$, and $A_5$, as well as for their double covers. We find a restricted set of pairs of representations for which the discussed mechanism may produce viable fermion (charged-lepton and quark) mass hierarchies. We present two lepton flavour models in which the charged-lepton mass hierarchies are naturally obtained, while lepton mixing is somewhat fine-tuned. After formulating the conditions for obtaining a viable lepton mixing matrix in the symmetric limit, we construct a model in which both the charged-lepton and neutrino sectors are free from fine-tuning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2102.07488v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP04(2021)206</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>P. P. Novichkov, J. T. Penedo, S. T. Petcov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter from Evaporating Primordial Black Holes in the Early Universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.11288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.11288v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Primordial Black Holes (PBH) could dominate in the early universe and, evaporating before Big bang Nucleosynthesis, can provide new freeze in mechanism of dark matter (DM) production. The proposed scenario is considered for two possible mechanisms of PBH formation and the corresponding continuous PBH mass spectra so that the effect of non-single PBH mass spectrum is taken into account in the results of PBH evaporation, by which PBH dominance in the early universe ends. We specify the conditions under which the proposed scenario can explain production of dark matter in very early Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.11288v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pratik Chattopadhyay, Arnab Chaudhuri, Maxim Yu. Khlopov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Earth-Catalyzed Detection of Magnetic Inelastic Dark Matter with Photons in Large Underground Detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.08478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.08478v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Inelastic dark matter with moderate splittings, $\mathcal{O}({\rm few} \; {\rm to} \; 150)$ keV, can upscatter to an excited state in the Earth, with the excited state subsequently decaying, leaving a distinctive monoenergetic photon signal in large underground detectors. The photon signal can exhibit sidereal-daily modulation, providing excellent separation from backgrounds. Using a detailed numerical simulation, we examine this process as a search strategy for magnetic inelastic dark matter with the dark matter mass near the weak scale, where the upscatter to the excited state and decay proceed through the same magnetic dipole transition operator. At lower inelastic splittings, the scattering is dominated by moderate mass elements in the Earth with high spin, especially $^{27}$Al, while at larger splittings, $^{56}$Fe becomes the dominant target. We show that the proposed large volume gaseous detector CYGNUS will have excellent sensitivity to this signal. Xenon detectors also provide excellent sensitivity through the inelastic nuclear recoil signal, and if a future signal is seen, we show that the synergy among both types of detection can provide strong evidence for magnetic inelastic dark matter. In the course we have calculated nuclear response functions for elements relevant for scattering in the Earth, which are publicly available on GitHub.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.08478v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Eby, Patrick J. Fox, Graham D. Kribs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Migdal-type effect in the dark matter absorption process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.10566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.10566v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a new mechanism of absorption of dark matter particles in atoms which resembles the Migdal effect of inelastic dark matter scattering. In this process, atom may be ionized upon absorption of a scalar particle through the scalar-nucleon Yukawa-type interaction. The crucial difference from the inelastic dark matter scattering on atoms is that the total energy of the particle, including its rest mass $mc^2$-term, is transferred to the electron. As a result, the emitted electron kinetic energy is about six orders in magnitude bigger than that in the dark matter scattering process. This absorption process allows one to probe dark matter particles with a relatively small mass, in the range from 1 to 100 keV, that cannot be detected in the scattering process. It is also possible to detect hypothetical scalar particles emitted from the Sun. We calculate absorption cross sections of this process in Na, Si, Ar, Ge, I, Xe, and Tl target atoms and extract limits on the scalar-nucleon interaction constant from null results of XENONnT experiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.10566v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. A. Dzuba, V. V. Flambaum, I. B. Samsonov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physical Signatures of Fermion-Coupled Axion Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.11601v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the presence of axion dark matter, fermion spins experience an "axion wind" torque and an "axioelectric" force. We investigate new experimental probes of these effects and find that magnetized analogs of multilayer dielectric haloscopes can explore orders of magnitude of new parameter space for the axion-electron coupling. We also revisit the calculation of axion absorption into in-medium excitations, showing that axioelectric absorption is screened in spin-polarized targets, and axion wind absorption can be characterized in terms of a magnetic energy loss function. Finally, our detailed theoretical treatment allows us to critically examine recent claims in the literature. We find that axioelectric corrections to electronic energy levels are smaller than previously estimated and that the purported electron electric dipole moment due to a constant axion field is entirely spurious.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.11601v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP05(2024)314</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 05 (2024) 314</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Asher Berlin, Alexander J. Millar, Tanner Trickle, Kevin Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetar-powered Neutrinos and Magnetic Moment Signatures at IceCube</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.14113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.14113v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The IceCube collaboration pioneered the detection of $\mathcal{O}{(\text{PeV})}$ neutrino events and the identification of astrophysical sources of high-energy neutrinos. In this study, we explore scenarios in which high-energy neutrinos are produced in the vicinity of astrophysical objects with strong magnetic field, such as magnetars. While propagating through such magnetic field, neutrinos experience spin precession induced by their magnetic moments, and this impacts their helicity and flavor composition at Earth. Considering both flavor composition of high-energy neutrinos and Glashow resonance events we find that detectable signatures may arise at neutrino telescopes, such as IceCube, for presently unconstrained neutrino magnetic moments in the range between $\mathcal{O}(10^{-15})~\mu_B$ and $\mathcal{O}(10^{-12})~\mu_B$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.14113v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ting Cheng, Hao-Jui Kuan, Ying-Ying Li, Vedran Brdar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniform rate inflation on the brane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.17409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.17409v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a model of uniform rate inflation on the brane. The potential is given by a hyperbolic cosine function plus a negative cosmological constant. The equation of motion is solved analytically without using slow-roll approximation. The result is that the inflaton field is rolling at a constant speed. The prediction for cosmological perturbations depends on the field value at the end of inflation. The experimental constraints could be satisfied in the parameter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.17409v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2024/05/105</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP05(2024)105</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Chia-Min Lin, Rei Tamura, Keiko I. Nagao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous diffusion of the heavy quarks through the fractional Langevin equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.03757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.03757v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The dynamics of heavy quarks within the hot QCD medium have been revisited, considering the influence of anomalous diffusion. This study has been conducted using the framework of the fractional Langevin equation involving the Caputo fractional derivative. We introduce a numerical scheme for the fractional Langevin equation and demonstrate that the mean square displacement of the particle exhibits anomalous diffusion, deviating from a linear relationship with time. Our analysis calculates various entities, such as mean squared momentum, momentum spread, and the nuclear suppression factor, $R_{AA}$. Notably, our findings indicate that superdiffusion strongly suppresses the $R_{AA}$ compared to normal diffusion in the hot QCD medium. The possible impacts on other parameters are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.03757v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.114004</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jai Prakash</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electromagnetic properties of vector doubly charmed tetraquark states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.04798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.04798v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We conduct a systematic study of the electromagnetic properties of multiquark systems with undetermined internal structures. Motivated by the recent observation of the $T_{cc}^+$ state, we apply the light-cone version of the QCD sum rule method to extract the magnetic dipole moments of several possible doubly-charmed vector tetraquark states. When analyzing the magnetic dipole moment of these states, they are modeled to have the diquark-antidiquark configurations. The magnetic dipole moments for the members are extracted as $ \mu_{T_{cc \bar{u} \bar{d}}} = 1.17^{+0.44}_{-0.32} \, \mu_N$, $ \mu_{T_{cc \bar{u} \bar{s}}} = 1.35^{+0.50}_{-0.37} \, \mu_N$, $ \mu_{T_{cc \bar{d} \bar{s}}} = -2.69^{+1.02}_{-0.75} \, \mu_N$, $ \mu_{T_{cc \bar{u} \bar{u}}} = 1.33^{+0.56}_{-0.40} \, \mu_N$, $ \mu_{T_{cc \bar{d} \bar{d}}} = 1.41^{+0.57}_{-0.43} \, \mu_N$ and $ \mu_{T_{cc \bar{s} \bar{s}}} = 1.44^{+0.53}_{-0.41} \, \mu_N$. Comparing the results obtained for the magnetic dipole moments of the $T_{cc \bar{u} \bar{d}}$ state with the $T_{cc \bar{u} \bar{s}}$ state, the $U$-symmetry is seen to be broken at about $\%15$, while for the $T_{cc \bar{d} \bar{d}}$ and $T_{cc \bar{s} \bar{s}}$ states, this symmetry is minimally broken. The obtained results may be useful to determine the true nature of these new interesting states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.04798v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>U. \"Ozdem, K. Azizi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Properties of the ground and excited states of triply heavy spin-1/2 baryons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.14348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.14348v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the triply heavy spin-1/2 baryons with quark contents $ ccb $ and $ bbc $, and calculate their mass and residue using QCD sum rules. In the calculations, we consider the ground (1S), first orbitally excited (1P) and first radially excited (2S) states. Aiming to achieve higher accuracies in the results, we perform the computations by taking into account the non-perturbative operators up to eight mass dimensions. We compare our results with the predictions of other theoretical studies existing in the literature. The obtained results may help experimental groups in their search for these yet unseen, but previously predicted by the quark model, interesting particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.14348v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Z. Rajabi Najjar, K. Azizi, H. R. Moshfegh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark matter, CE$\nu$NS and neutrino new physics scrutinized by a statistical method in Xenon-based experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05819v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dark matter direct detection experiments are going to touch the neutrino floor with a good chance to measure coherent elastic neutrino-nucleus scattering (CE$\nu$NS) and a probe of neutrino-related new physics ($\nu$NP). In this study, we emphatically investigate the simultaneous presence of dark matter and $\nu$NP revealing a response resembling of Standard Model neutrino backgrounds in Xenon-based dark matter experiments. Demonstrated by three U(1) extension models, we figure out that dark matter signals can be distinguished from an excess or a depletion of neutrino contributions from $\nu$NP by a statistically defined distinction method in nuclear and electronic recoil spectra. We also present the influence of $\nu$NP on the exclusion limits for spin-independent dark matter-nucleon interactions. Our work might pave the way for new physics discrimination in future dark matter experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05819v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian Tang, Bing-Long Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbative Unitarity and the 4-Point Vertices in the Constructive Standard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07977v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We find a complete set of 4-point vertices in the Constructive Standard Model (CSM). This set is smaller than in Feynman diagrams as the CSM does not need or allow any additional 4-point vertices (or contact terms) beyond what is present in Feynman diagrams and, furthermore, it does not need or allow a 4-point vertex for A,Z,W+,W- or A,A,W+,W-, in addition to the already known absence of the 4-gluon vertex. We show that with this set of 4-point vertices, perturbative unitarity is satisfied in the CSM. Additionally, we show that many constructive diagrams are not Feynman diagrams rewritten in spinor form. In fact, we show that there is a significant rearrangement of contributions from the diagrams in constructive calculations relative to Feynman diagrams, for some processes. In addition to the already known or expected rearrangement in diagrams involving external photons, we also find that diagrams involving a 4-vector-boson vertex are also significantly different than their Feynman counterparts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07977v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Neil Christensen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New method for the solution of the two-body Dirac equation for the positronium bound states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00444v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A new theoretical method is developed to solve the two-body bound-state Dirac equation for positronium. Only Coulomb potential was included in the Dirac Hamiltonian. It is shown that the two-body Dirac Hamiltonian can be written in the Hermitian matrix form of the 4$\times$4 size and diagonalized in the momentum-state representation. Numerical results for the energy spectrum of the para- and ortho-positronium ground states performed within the variational method using the harmonic oscillator basis functions are in good agreement with a high-precision finite-element method of T.C. Scott et al. After the Fourier transformation into the coordinate-state representation the bound state wave functions of the para-Ps and ortho-Ps do not contain any singularity at the origin in contrast to the method mentioned above. The weights of the large-small and small-large components of the ground state wave functions are estimated to be of order 10$^{-6}$, while the weight of the small-small component is of order 10$^{-12}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00444v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. M. Tursunov, Sh. G. Norbutaev, B. A. Fayzullaev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light-quark mass dependence of the $\Lambda(1405)$ resonance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02720v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the light-quark mass dependence of the $\Lambda(1405)$ resonance at leading order in a renormalizable framework of covariant chiral effective field theory. The meson-baryon scattering amplitudes, which are obtained by solving the scattering equation within time-ordered perturbation theory, follow the quark mass trajectory of the Coordinated Lattice Simulations consortium. At $M_\pi\approx 200$ MeV and $M_K\approx 487$ MeV, our parameter-free prediction of $\Lambda(1405)$ poles is consistent with the recent lattice results of BaSc Collaboration [Phys. Rev. Lett. 132, 051901 (2024)]. Varying the pion mass from $135$ MeV to $400$ MeV, we present the evolution of double-pole positions of $\Lambda(1405)$: the higher pole remains a resonance around the $\bar{K}N$ threshold; whereas the lower pole undergoes a transition from resonance to a virtual state, and ultimately to a bound state of the $\pi\Sigma$ system, which could be verified by the forthcoming lattice QCD simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02720v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiu-Lei Ren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A semi-analytical $x$-space solution for parton evolution -- Application to non-singlet and singlet DGLAP equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18667v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a novel semi-analytical method for parton evolution. It is based on constructing a family of analytic functions spanning $x$-space which is closed under the considered evolution equation. Using these functions as a basis, the original integro-differential evolution equation transforms into a system of coupled ordinary differential equations, which can be solved numerically by restriction to a suitably chosen finite subsystem. The evolved distributions are obtained as analytic functions in $x$ with numerically obtained coefficients, providing insight into the analytic behavior of the evolved parton distributions. As a proof-of-principle, we apply our method to the leading order non-singlet and singlet DGLAP equation. Comparing our results to traditional Mellin-space methods, we find good agreement. The method is implemented in the code $\texttt{POMPOM}$ in $\texttt{Mathematica}$ as well as in $\texttt{Python}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18667v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juliane Haug, Oliver Sch\"ule, Fabian Wunder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inhomogenuous instabilities at large chemical potential in a rainbow-ladder QCD model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00205</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00205v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work we continue our efforts to study the existence of a phase with an inhomogeneous, i.e., spatially varying, chiral condensate in QCD. To this end we employ a previously established method of stability analysis of the two-particle irreducible effective action in a truncation that corresponds to a rainbow-ladder approximation of the quark-gluon interaction of QCD. If the analysis is restricted to homogeneous phases, the phase diagram features a first-order chiral transition in the lower-temperature regime. Performing the stability analysis along the lower-chemical-potential border of the corresponding spinodal region, we find that below a certain temperature the homogeneous chirally symmetric solution is unstable against inhomogeneous condensation. We argue that this instability may persist to chemical potentials above the homogeneous first-order phase boundary, in which case it signals the existence of an inhomogeneous ground state. Our methodology is also applicable for more sophisticated truncations of the QCD effective action.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00205v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Theo F. Motta, Julian Bernhardt, Michael Buballa, Christian S. Fischer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BCS in the Sky: Signatures of Inflationary Fermion Condensation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.09428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.09428v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a Bardeen-Cooper-Schrieffer (BCS)-like model in the inflationary background. We show that with an axial chemical potential, the attractive quartic fermion self-interaction can lead to a BCS-like condensation. In the rigid-de Sitter (dS) limit of inflation where backreaction from the inflaton and graviton is neglected, we perform the first computation of the non-perturbative effective potential that includes the full spacetime curvature effects in the presence of the chemical potential, subject to the mean-field approximation whose validity has been checked via the Ginzburg criterion. The corresponding BCS phase transition is always first-order, when the varying Hubble is interpreted as an effective Gibbons-Hawking temperature of dS spacetime. In the condensed phase, the theory can be understood from UV and IR sides as fermionic and bosonic, respectively. This leads to distinctive signatures in the primordial non-Gaussianity of curvature perturbations. Namely, the oscillatory cosmological collider signal is smoothly turned off at a finite momentum ratio, since different momentum ratios effectively probe different energy scales. In addition, such BCS phase transitions can also source stochastic gravitational waves, which are feasible for future experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.09428v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2024/04/022</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Xi Tong, Yi Wang, Chen Zhang, Yuhang Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological Correlators Through the Looking Glass: Reality, Parity, and Factorisation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.07769</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.07769v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the evolution of quantum fields during inflation, and show that the total-energy singularities appearing in the perturbative expansion of the late-time Wavefunction of the Universe are purely real when the external states are massless scalars and massless gravitons. Our proof relies on the tree-level approximation, Bunch-Davies initial conditions, and exact scale invariance (IR-convergence), but without any assumptions on invariance under de Sitter boosts. We consider all $n$-point functions and allow for the exchange of additional states of any mass and integer spin. Our proof makes use of a decomposition of the inflationary bulk-bulk propagator of massive spinning fields which preserves UV-convergence and ensures that the time-ordered contributions are purely real after we rotate to Euclidean time. We use this reality property to show that the maximally-connected parts of wavefunction coefficients, from which total-energy singularities originate, are purely real. In a theory where all states are in the complementary series, this reality extends to the full wavefunction coefficient. We then use our reality theorem to show that parity-odd correlators (correlators that are mirror asymmetric) are factorised and do not diverge when the total-energy is conserved. We pay special attention to the parity-odd four-point function (trispectrum) of inflationary curvature perturbations and use our reality/factorisation theorems to show that this observable is factorised into a product of cubic diagrams thereby enabling us to derive exact shapes. We present examples of couplings between the inflaton and massive spin-1 and spin-2 fields, with the parity-violation in the trispectrum driven by Chern-Simons corrections to the spinning field two-point function, or from parity-violating cubic interactions which we build within the Effective Field Theory of Inflation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.07769v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP05(2024)196</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>David Stefanyszyn, Xi Tong, Yuhang Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Raoul Gatto and Bruno Touschek's joint legacy in the rise of electron-positron physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.01293</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.01293v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Raoul Gatto and Bruno Touschek's collaboration in the establishment of electron positron colliders as a fundamental discovery tool in particle physics will be illustrated. In particular, we will tell the little-known story of how Gatto and Touschek's pioneering vision combined to provide the theoretical foundations for AdA, the first matter-antimatter collider, and how their friendship with Wolfgang Pauli and Gerhard L\"uders was crucial to their understanding of the CPT theorem, the basis for AdA's success. We will see how these two exceptional scientists shaped physics between Rome and Frascati, from the proposal to build AdA and, soon after in 1961, the larger machine ADONE, to the discovery of the $J/\Psi$ particle in 1974. We will also highlight Gatto and Touschek's contribution in mentoring an extraordinary cohort of students and collaborators whose work contributed to the renaissance of Italian theoretical physics after the Second World War and to the establishment of the Standard Model of particle physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.01293v2</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luisa Bonolis (MPIWG, Berlin), Franco Buccella (INFN Rome1), Giulia Pancheri (INFN-LNF,CREF)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strategies for simulating time evolution of Hamiltonian lattice field theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.11637v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Simulating the time evolution of quantum field theories given some Hamiltonian $H$ requires developing algorithms for implementing the unitary operator e^{-iHt}. A variety of techniques exist that accomplish this task, with the most common technique used so far being Trotterization, which is a special case of the application of a product formula. However, other techniques exist that promise better asymptotic scaling in certain parameters of the theory being simulated, the most efficient of which are based on the concept of block encoding.
  In this work we study the performance of such algorithms in simulating lattice field theories. We derive and compare the asymptotic gate complexities of several commonly used simulation techniques in application to Hamiltonian Lattice Field Theories. Using the scalar \phi^4 theory as a test, we also perform numerical studies and compare the gate costs required by Product Formulas and Signal Processing based techniques to simulate time evolution. For the latter, we use the the Linear Combination of Unitaries construction augmented with the Quantum Fourier Transform circuit to switch between the field and momentum eigenbases, which leads to immediate order-of-magnitude improvement in the cost of preparing the block encoding.
  The paper also includes a pedagogical review of utilized techniques, in particular Product Formulas, LCU, Qubitization, QSP, as well as a technique we call HHKL based on its inventors' names.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.11637v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siddharth Hariprakash, Neel S. Modi, Michael Kreshchuk, Christopher F. Kane, Christian W Bauer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast neutrino flavor conversions in a supernova: Emergence, evolution, and effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.19252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.19252v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Fast flavor conversions (FFCs) of neutrinos, which can occur in core-collapse supernovae (CCSNe), are multiangle effects. They depend on the angular distribution of the neutrino's electron lepton number (ELN). In this work, we present a comprehensive study of the FFCs by solving the multienergy and multiangle quantum kinetic equations with an extended set of collisional weak processes based on a static and spherically symmetric CCSN matter background profile. We investigate the emergence and evolution of FFCs in models featuring different ELN angular distributions, considering scenarios with two and three neutrino flavors. The spectrogram method is utilized to illustrate the small-scale spatial structure, and we show that this structure of neutrino flavor coherence and number densities in the nonlinear regime is qualitatively consistent with the dispersion relation analysis. On the coarse-grained level, we find that different asymptotic states can be achieved following the FFCs depending on the locations and shapes of the ELN distributions, despite sharing a common feature of the elimination of the ELN angular crossing. While equilibration among different neutrino flavors may be achieved immediately after the prompt FFCs, it is not a general outcome of the asymptotic state, as subsequent feedback effects from collisional neutrino-matter interactions come into play, particularly for cases where FFCs occur inside the neutrinosphere. The impacts of FFCs and the feedback effect on the net neutrino heating rates, the equilibrium electron fraction of CCSN matter, and the free-streaming neutrino energy spectra are quantitatively assessed. Other aspects including the impact of the vacuum term and the coexistence with other type of flavor instabilities are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.19252v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.123008</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Zewei Xiong, Meng-Ru Wu, Manu George, Chun-Yu Lin, Noshad Khosravi Largani, Tobias Fischer, Gabriel Mart\'inez-Pinedo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Simulation-Based Inference of the Neutron Star Equation of State directly from Telescope Spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00287</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00287v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Neutron stars provide a unique opportunity to study strongly interacting matter under extreme density conditions. The intricacies of matter inside neutron stars and their equation of state are not directly visible, but determine bulk properties, such as mass and radius, which affect the star's thermal X-ray emissions. However, the telescope spectra of these emissions are also affected by the stellar distance, hydrogen column, and effective surface temperature, which are not always well-constrained. Uncertainties on these nuisance parameters must be accounted for when making a robust estimation of the equation of state. In this study, we develop a novel methodology that, for the first time, can infer the full posterior distribution of both the equation of state and nuisance parameters directly from telescope observations. This method relies on the use of neural likelihood estimation, in which normalizing flows use samples of simulated telescope data to learn the likelihood of the neutron star spectra as a function of these parameters, coupled with Hamiltonian Monte Carlo methods to efficiently sample from the corresponding posterior distribution. Our approach surpasses the accuracy of previous methods, improves the interpretability of the results by providing access to the full posterior distribution, and naturally scales to a growing number of neutron star observations expected in the coming years.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00287v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Len Brandes, Chirag Modi, Aishik Ghosh, Delaney Farrell, Lee Lindblom, Lukas Heinrich, Andrew W. Steiner, Fridolin Weber, Daniel Whiteson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observational Constraints on the Dark Energy with a Quadratic Equation of State</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02000v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this study, we introduce a novel late-time effective dark energy model characterized by a quadratic equation of state (EoS) and rigorously examine its observational constraints. Initially, we delve into the background dynamics of this model, tracing the evolution of fluctuations in linear order. Our approach involves substituting the conventional cosmological constant with a dynamically effective dark energy fluid. Leveraging a diverse array of observational datasets encompassing the Planck 2018 Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB), Type Ia Supernovae (SNe), Baryon Acoustic Oscillations (BAO), and a prior on the Hubble constant $H_0$ (R21), we constrain the model parameters. We establish the model's consistency by comparing the Hubble parameter as a function of redshift against observational Hubble data (OHD), benchmarking its performance against the Standard $\Lambda$CDM model. Additionally, our investigation delves into studies of the model's dynamical behavior by computing cosmological parameters such as the deceleration parameter, relative Hubble parameter, and the evolution of the Hubble rate. Furthermore, employing Bayesian analysis, we determine the Bayesian Evidence for our proposed model compared to the reference $\Lambda$CDM model. While our analysis unveils the favorable behavior of the model in various observational tests, the well-known cosmological tensions persist when the full dataset combination is explored.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02000v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.dark.2024.101524</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Hossein Moshafi, Alireza Talebian, Ebrahim Yusofi, Eleonora Di Valentino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inclusive hadronic decay rate of the $\tau$ lepton from lattice QCD: the $\bar u s$ flavour channel and the Cabibbo angle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05404</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05404v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a lattice determination of the inclusive decay rate of the process $\tau\mapsto X_{us} \nu_\tau$ in which the $\tau$ lepton decays into a generic hadronic state $X_{us}$ with $\bar u s$ flavour quantum numbers. Our results have been obtained in $n_f=2+1+1$ iso-symmetric QCD with full non-perturbative accuracy, without any OPE approximation and, except for the presently missing long-distance isospin-breaking corrections, include a solid estimate of all sources of theoretical uncertainties. This has been possible by using the Hansen-Lupo-Tantalo method [1] that we have already successfully applied in [2] to compute the inclusive decay rate of the process $\tau\mapsto X_{ud} \nu_\tau$ in the $\bar u d$ flavour channel. By combining our first-principles theoretical results with the presently-available experimental data we extract the CKM matrix element $\vert V_{us}\vert$, the Cabibbo angle, with a $0.9$\% accuracy, dominated by the experimental error.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05404v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Alexandrou, S. Bacchio, A. De Santis, A. Evangelista, J. Finkenrath, R. Frezzotti, G. Gagliardi, M. Garofalo, B. Kostrzewa, V. Lubicz, S. Romiti, F. Sanfilippo, S. Simula, N. Tantalo, C. Urbach, U. Wenger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nuclear matrix elements of neutrinoless double-beta decay in covariant density functional theory with different mechanisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17722v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Nuclear matrix elements (NMEs) for neutrinoless double-beta ($0\nu\beta\beta$) decay in candidate nuclei play a crucial role in interpreting results from current experiments and in designing future ones. Accurate NME values serve as important nuclear inputs for constraining parameters in new physics, such as neutrino mass and the Wilson coefficients of lepton-number-violating (LNV) operators. In this study, we present a comprehensive calculation of NMEs for $0\nu\beta\beta$ decay in $^{76}$Ge, $^{82}$Se, $^{100}$Mo, $^{130}$Te, and $^{136}$Xe, using nuclear wave functions obtained from multi-reference covariant density functional theory (MR-CDFT). We employ three types of transition potentials at the leading order in chiral effective field theory. Our results, along with recent data, are utilized to constrain the coefficients of LNV operators. The results demonstrate that the combined NMEs based on the Feynman diagrams at the hadronic scale for the nonstandard mechanisms leads to the uncertainty by different nuclear models comparable to that for the standard mechanism. The use of NMEs from various nuclear models does not dramatically change the parameter space intervals for the coefficients, although MR-CDFT yields the most stringent constraint. Furthermore, our NMEs can also be used to perform a more comprehensive analysis with multiple isotopes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17722v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. R. Ding, Gang Li, J. M. Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid inflation from supersymmetry breaking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05269v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We extend a recently proposed framework, dubbed inflation by supersymmetry breaking, to hybrid inflation by introducing a waterfall field that allows to decouple the supersymmetry breaking scale in the observable sector from the inflation scale, while keeping intact the inflation sector and its successful predictions: naturally small slow-roll parameters, small field initial conditions and absence of the pseudo-scalar companion of the inflaton, in terms of one free parameter which is the first order correction to the inflaton K\"ahler potential. During inflation, supersymmetry is spontaneously broken with the inflaton being the superpartner of the goldstino, together with a massive vector that gauges the R-symmetry. Inflation arises around the maximum of the scalar potential at the origin where R-symmetry is unbroken. Moreover, a nearby minimum with tuneable vacuum energy can be accommodated by introducing a second order correction to the K\"ahler potential. The inflaton sector can also play the role of the supersymmetry breaking 'hidden' sector when coupled to the (supersymmetric) Standard Model, predicting a superheavy superparticle spectrum near the inflation scale. Here we show that the introduction of a waterfall field provides a natural way to end inflation and allows for a scale separation between supersymmetry breaking and inflation. Moreover, the study of the global vacuum describing low energy Standard Model physics can be done in a perturbative way within a region of the parameter space of the model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05269v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yermek Aldabergenov, Ignatios Antoniadis, Auttakit Chatrabhuti, Hiroshi Isono</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First constraints on the $L_\mu-L_\tau$ explanation of the muon $g-2$ anomaly from NA64-$e$ at CERN</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06982</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06982v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The inclusion of an additional $U(1)$ gauge $L_\mu-L_\tau$ symmetry would release the tension between the measured and the predicted value of the anomalous muon magnetic moment: this paradigm assumes the existence of a new, light $Z^\prime$ vector boson, with dominant coupling to $\mu$ and $\tau$ leptons and interacting with electrons via a loop mechanism. The $L_\mu-L_\tau$ model can also explain the Dark Matter relic abundance, by assuming that the $Z'$ boson acts as a ``portal'' to a new Dark Sector of particles in Nature, not charged under known interactions. In this work we present the results of the $Z'$ search performed by the NA64-$e$ experiment at CERN SPS, that collected $\sim 9\times10^{11}$ 100 GeV electrons impinging on an active thick target. Despite the suppressed $Z'$ production yield with an electron beam, NA64-$e$ provides the first accelerator-based results excluding the $g-2$ preferred band of the $Z'$ parameter space in the 1 keV $ &lt; m_{Z'} \lesssim 2$ MeV range, in complementarity with the limits recently obtained by the NA64-$\mu$ experiment with a muon beam.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06982v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu. M. Andreev, A. Antonov, D. Banerjee, B. Banto Oberhauser, J. Bernhard, P. Bisio, A. Celentano, N. Charitonidis, D. Cooke, P. Crivelli, E. Depero, A. V. Dermenev, S. V. Donskov, R. R. Dusaev, T. Enik, V. N. Frolov, A. Gardikiotis, S. N. Gninenko, M. H\"osgen, V. A. Kachanov, Y. Kambar, A. E. Karneyeu, G. Kekelidze, B. Ketzer, D. V. Kirpichnikov, M. M. Kirsanov, V. N. Kolosov, S. V. Gertsenberger, S. Girod, E. A. Kasianova, V. A. Kramarenko, L. V. Kravchuk, N. V. Krasnikov, S. V. Kuleshov, V. E. Lyubovitskij, V. Lysan, A. Marini, L. Marsicano, V. A. Matveev, R. Mena Fredes, R. Mena Yanssen, L. Molina Bueno, M. Mongillo, D. V. Peshekhonov, V. A. Polyakov, B. Radics, K. Salamatin, V. D. Samoylenko, H. Sieber, D. Shchukin, O. Soto, V. O. Tikhomirov, I. Tlisova, A. N. Toropin, M. Tuzi, P. Ulloa, P. V. Volkov, V. Yu. Volkov, I. V. Voronchikhin, J. Zamora-Sa\'a, A. S. Zhevlako</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete $Z_4$ symmetry in quantum gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00718</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00718v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the discrete $Z_4$ symmetry ${\hat {\bf i}}$, which takes place in the scenario of quantum gravity where the gravitational tetrads emerge as the order parameter. Under this symmetry operation $\hat {\bf i}$, the emerging tetrads are multiplied by the imaginary unit, $\hat {\bf i}\,e^a_\mu = - i e^a_\mu$. The existence of such symmetry and the spontaneous breaking of this symmetry are also supported by the consideration of the symmetry breaking scheme in the topological superfluid $^3$He-B. The order parameter $^3$He-B is the analogue of the tetrad field, but it has complex values. The $\hat {\bf i}$-symmetry operation changes the phase of the complex order parameter by $\pi/2$, which corresponds to the $Z_4$ discrete symmetry in quantum gravity. We also considered the alternative scenario of the breaking of this $Z_4$ symmetry, in which the $\hat {\bf i}$-operation changes sign of the scalar curvature, $\hat {\bf i} \,{\cal R} = - {\cal R}$, and thus the Einstein-Hilbert action violates the $\hat {\bf i}$-symmetry. In the alternative scenario of symmetry breaking, the gravitational coupling $K=1/16\pi G$ plays the role of the order parameter, which changes sign under $\hat {\bf i}$-transformation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00718v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. E. Volovik</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
