<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph</link>
    <description>hep-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 05:00:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Fermion-Portal Dark Matter at a High-Energy Muon Collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14235v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we provide a comprehensive study of fermion-portal dark matter models in the freeze-in regime at a future muon collider. For different possible non-singlet fermion portals, we calculate the upper bound on the mediator's mass arising from the relic abundance calculation and discuss the reach of a future muon collider in probing their viable parameter space in prompt and long-lived particle search strategies. In particular, we develop rudimentary search strategies in the prompt region and show that cuts on the invariant dilepton or dijet masses, the missing transverse mass $M_{T2}$, pseudorapidity and energy of leptons or jets, and the opening angle between the lepton or the jet pair can be employed to subtract the Standard Model background. In the long-lived particle regime, we discuss the signals of each model and calculate their event counts. In this region, the lepton-(quark-)portal model signal consists of charged tracks ($R$-hadrons) that either decay in the detector to give rise to a displaced lepton (jet) signature, or are detector stable and give rise to heavy stable charged track signals. As a byproduct, a pipeline is developed for including the non-trivial parton distribution function of a muon component inside a muon beam; it is shown that this leads to non-trivial effects on the kinematic distributions and attainable significances. We also highlight phenomenological features of all models unique to a muon collider and hope our results, for this motivated and broad class of dark matter models, inform the design of a future muon collider detector. We also speculate on suggestions for improving the sensitivity of a muon collider detector to long-lived particle signals in fermion-portal models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14235v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pouya Asadi, Samuel Homiller, Aria Radick, Tien-Tien Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Two Scales of New Physics in Loop-Induced Higgs Couplings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14237v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Probing new physics through precise measurements of Higgs boson couplings is a central objective of the particle collider program at the high-energy frontier. An anomaly in Higgs couplings induced solely by new fermions allows one to compute an upper bound on the mass scale of new bosons. This new bosonic scale is necessary to prevent Landau poles or vacuum instability. Consequently, a single anomalous measurement can provide insight into two distinct new physics scales. In this article, we apply this approach to the loop-induced couplings of the Higgs boson to digluons ($gg$), diphotons ($\gamma \gamma$), and $Z \gamma$, and we compare our results to the projected sensitivities of the HL-LHC and future lepton colliders. This work naturally extends our previous analysis of Higgs couplings to weak dibosons ($WW$ and $ZZ$).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14237v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Florian Nortier, Gabriele Rigo, Pablo Sesma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monopole Catalyzed Baryogenesis with a $\theta$ angle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14239v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Monopoles are generally expected in Grand Unified Theories (GUTs) where they can catalyze baryon decay at an unsuppressed rate by the Callan-Rubakov effect. For the first time, we show this catalysis effect can generate the observed baryon asymmetry at GeV scale temperatures. We study the minimal SU(5) GUT model and demonstrate that monopoles-fermion scattering with a $CP$-violating $\theta$-term leads to realistic baryogenesis even when $\theta\lesssim 10^{-10}$ is below the neutron EDM bound, potentially detectable in the future measurements. Our calculation also shows that to generate the observed baryon asymmetry, the abundance of the monopoles is below the current experiential bounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14239v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Daniel Brennan, Lian-Tao Wang, Huangyu Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noble Dark Matter: Surprising Elusiveness of Dark Baryons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14240</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14240v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dark matter could be a baryonic composite of strongly-coupled constituents transforming under SU(2)$_L$. We classify the SU(2)$_L$ representations of baryons in a class of simple confining dark sectors and find that the lightest state can be a pure singlet or a singlet that mixes with other neutral components of SU(2)$_L$ representations, which strongly suppresses the dark matter candidate's interactions with the Standard Model. We focus on models with a confining $\text{SU}(N_c)$ and heavy dark quarks constituting vector-like $N_f$-plet of SU(2)$_L$. For benchmark $N_c$ and $N_f$, we calculate baryon mass spectra, incorporating electroweak gauge boson exchange in the non-relativistic quark model, and demonstrate that above TeV mass scales, dark matter is dominantly a singlet state. The combination of this singlet nature with the recently discovered $\mathcal{H}$-parity results in an inert state analogous to noble gases, hence we coin the term Noble Dark Matter. Our results can be understood in the non-relativistic effective theory that treats the dark baryons as elementary states, where we find singlets accompanying triplets, 5-plets, or more exotic representations. This generalization of WIMP-like theories is more difficult to find or rule out than dark matter models that include only a single SU(2)$_L$ multiplet (such as a Wino), motivating new searches in colliders and a re-analysis of direct and indirect detection prospects in astrophysical observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14240v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pouya Asadi, Austin Batz, Graham D. Kribs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accuracy complements energy: electroweak precision tests at Tera-Z</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14241</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14241v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A Tera-$Z$ factory, such as FCC-ee or CEPC, will have indirect sensitivity to heavy new physics up to the tens of TeV scale through higher-order loop contributions to precision measurements at the $Z$ pole. These indirect quantum effects may provide complementary, or even better, sensitivity to potential deviations from the Standard Model that are typically thought to best be constrained at leading order at higher energies above the $Z$ pole. We show in the SMEFT framework how accuracy complements energy for operators that modify the Higgs and gauge boson two- and three-point functions, leading to improved projected sensitivities for models such as the real singlet scalar, weakly interacting massive particles, and a custodial weak quadruplet. A thorough Tera-$Z$ programme may thus anticipate aspects of physics runs at higher energies and provide a wider scope of quantum exploration of the TeV scale than had previously been appreciated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14241v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Maura, Ben A. Stefanek, Tevong You</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matching Z $\to$ Hadrons at NNLO with Sector Showers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14242</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14242v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider leading-colour 2-, 3- and 4-jet rates in hadronic $Z$-boson decay to derive matching conditions at next-to-next-to-leading order in the sectorised VINCIA parton shower. In particular, we present a full subtraction-based calculation of the matching coefficient required to obtain the NLO 3-jet rate. This is achieved through a judicious choice of the counter-terms, which optimises the numerical evaluation of the subtracted double-real matrix element. We additionally give a consistent prescription for incorporating interference effects due to multiple Born states. Finally, we briefly comment on higher-order uncertainty estimates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14242v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Basem Kamal El-Menoufi, Christian T. Preuss, Ludovic Scyboz, Peter Skands</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A common origin of the Higgs boson and the flavor hierarchies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14243v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a model that extends the electroweak gauge symmetry of the Standard Model in a non-universal way to $SU(2)_{L}^{\prime}\times U(1)_X \times SU(2)_{L}^{q_3}\times SU(2)_R^{\ell^3}$. This symmetry is spontaneously broken to $SU(2)_L\times U(1)_Y$ near the TeV scale by a condensate of a new composite sector. Charging appropriately the fermionic degrees of freedom of the composite sector, anomaly cancellation enforces the Standard Model fermions to be charged in such a way that the extended gauge interactions respect a $U(2)_q\times U(2)_e\times U(3)_u\times U(3)_d\times U(3)_\ell$ accidental flavor symmetry. In addition, from the same symmetry breaking, a composite Higgs boson emerges as a pseudo-Nambu-Goldstone boson of the strong dynamics of the new sector. Due to the extended gauge and the specific flavor symmetry, leading Yukawa couplings between Higgs and fermions can only be written for the third generation and higher dimension operators generate suppressed light-family Yukawa couplings. Furthermore, CKM mixing angles between third and light families result naturally suppressed while the PMNS ones, anarchic. The model thus provides a unified origin for the Higgs boson and the flavor hierarchies between third and light families.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14243v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Javier M. Lizana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secondary Lund jet plane as a gluon enriched sample</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14247</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14247v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a new strategy to obtain a high-purity sample of gluon-initiated jets at the LHC. Our approach, inspired by the Lund jet plane picture, is to perform a dijet selection where the two jets are collinear to each other and their momentum fraction share is highly asymmetric, and to measure the primary Lund plane density of emissions of the subleading jet. The subleading jet in this topology is practically equivalent to a secondary Lund jet plane. We demonstrate by means of fixed-order calculations that such a simple setup yields gluon jet fractions of around 90% for the subleading jet for both quark- and gluon-initiated jets. This observation is confirmed using hadron-level Monte Carlo generated events. We also show that the extracted gluon purities are highly resilient to the overall colour structure of the event, to the flavour of the hard-scattering process, and to the parton distribution functions. This strategy is well-suited for constraining the radiation pattern of gluon-initiated jets using a set of fiducial cuts that can readily be tested at the LHC, without relying on taggers or statistical demixing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14247v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cristian Baldenegro, Alba Soto-Ontoso, Gregory Soyez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From the EFT to the UV: the complete SMEFT one-loop dictionary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14253v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Effective field theories (EFTs) provide an excellent framework for the search of heavy physics beyond the Standard Model, using the so-called bottom-up and top-down approaches. However, the vastness of possible UV scenarios makes the complete connection between the two approaches a difficult challenge at the loop-level. UV/IR dictionaries fill precisely this gap, efficiently connecting the EFT with the UV. In this work we present the complete one-loop dictionary for the Standard Model EFT at dimension six for completions with an arbitrary number of heavy fermions and scalars. Our results (as well as several new functionalities) are added to the previously partial package SOLD. In this new form, SOLD is prepared to serve as an important guiding tool for systematic and complete phenomenological studies. To illustrate this, we use the package to explore possible explanations for the tension on the measurement of $\mathcal{B}(B\rightarrow K \overline{\nu}\nu)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14253v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guilherme Guedes, Pablo Olgoso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Interplay of Constraints from $B_s$, $D$, and $K$ Meson Mixing in $Z^\prime$ Models with Implications for $b\to s \nu\bar\nu$ Transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14254v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Within $Z^\prime$ models, neutral meson mixing severely constrains beyond the Standard Model (SM) effects in flavour changing neutral current (FCNC) processes. However, in certain regions of the $Z^\prime$ parameter space, the contributions to meson mixing observables become negligibly small even for large $Z^\prime$ couplings. While this a priori allows for significant new physics (NP) effects in FCNC decays, we discuss how large $Z^\prime$ couplings in one neutral meson sector can generate effects in meson mixing observables of other neutral mesons, through correlations stemming from $\text{SU(2)}_L$ gauge invariance and through Renormalization Group (RG) effects in the SM Effective Field Theory~(SMEFT). This is illustrated with the example of $B_s^0-\bar B_s^0$ mixing, which in the presence of both left- and right-handed $Z^\prime bs$ couplings $\Delta_L^{bs}$ and $\Delta_R^{bs}$ remains SM-like for $\Delta_R^{bs}\approx 0.1\,\Delta_L^{bs}$. We show that in this case, large $Z^\prime bs$ couplings generate effects in $D$ and $K$ meson mixing observables, but that the $D$ and $K$ mixing constraints and the relation between $\Delta_R^{bs}$ and $\Delta_L^{bs}$ are fully compatible with a lepton flavour universality~(LFU) conserving explanation of the most recent $b\to s\ell^+\ell^-$ experimental data without violating other constraints like $e^+ e^-\to\ell^+\ell^-$ scattering. Assuming LFU, invariance under the $\text{SU(2)}_L$ gauge symmetry leads then to correlated effects in $b\to s\nu\bar\nu$ observables presently studied intensively by the Belle~II experiment, which allow to probe the $Z^\prime$ parameter space that is opened up by the vanishing NP contributions to $B_s^0-\bar B_s^0$ mixing. In this scenario the suppression of $B\to K(K^*)\mu^+\mu^-$ branching ratios implies {\em uniquely} enhancements of $B\to K(K^*)\nu\bar\nu$ branching ratios up to $20\%$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14254v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrzej J. Buras, Peter Stangl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum entropy and QCD factorization for low-$Q^2$ $\nu$DIS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14257v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Deeply inelastic scattering (DIS) is an essential process for exploring the structure of visible matter and testing the standard model. At the same time, the theoretical interpretation of DIS measurements depends on QCD factorization theorems whose validity deteriorates at the lower values of $Q^2$ and $W^2$ typical of neutrino DIS in accelerator-based oscillation searches. For this reason, progress in understanding the origin and limits of QCD factorization is invaluable to the accuracy and precision of predictions for these upcoming neutrino experiments. In these short proceedings, we introduce a novel approach based on the quantum entropy associated with continuous distributions in QCD, using it to characterize the limits of factorization theorems relevant for the description of neutrino DIS. This work suggests an additional avenue for dissecting factorization-breaking dynamics through the quantum entropy, which could also play a role in quantum simulations of related systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14257v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henry Bloss, Brandon Kriesten, T. J. Hobbs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indirect Detection of Hot Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14264v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cosmologically stable, light particles that came into thermal contact with the Standard Model in the early universe may persist today as a form of hot dark matter. For relics with masses in the eV range, their role in structure formation depends critically on their mass. We trace the evolution of such hot relics and derive their density profiles around cold dark matter halos, introducing a framework for their indirect detection. Applying this framework to axions -- a natural candidate for a particle that can reach thermal equilibrium with the Standard Model in the early universe and capable of decaying into two photons -- we establish stringent limits on the axion-photon coupling $g_{a \gamma} $ using current observations of dwarf galaxies, the Milky Way halo, and galaxy clusters. Our results set new bounds on hot axions in the $\mathcal{O}(1-10)\,$eV range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14264v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeff A. Dror, Pearl Sandick, Barmak Shams Es Haghi, Fengwei Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radiative neutrino masses from dim-7 SMEFT: a simplified multi-scale approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14268v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Lepton-number-violating interactions occur in the Standard Model Effective Field Theory (SMEFT) at odd dimensions starting from the dimension-5 Weinberg operator. Although the operators at dimension-7 and higher are more suppressed by the heavy new scale, they can be crucial when traditional seesaw mechanisms leading to tree-level dimension-5 contributions are absent. We identify all minimal tree-level UV-completions for dimension-7 $\Delta L=2$ SMEFT operators without covariant derivatives and propose a new simplified approach for estimating the radiative neutrino masses arising from such operators. This dimensional-regularisation-based approach provides a more accurate estimate for the loop neutrino masses when the new physics fields are hierarchical in mass, as compared to the cut-off-regularisation-based approach often employed in the literature. This allows us to identify viable regions of parameter space in the full list of relevant simplified models close to the current limits set by neutrinoless double beta decay and the LHC that would previously have been thought to be excluded by neutrino-mass constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14268v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K\r{a}re Fridell, Luk\'a\v{s} Gr\'af, Julia Harz, Chandan Hati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Massive graviton dark matter searches with long-baseline atom interferometers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14282</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14282v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Atom interferometers offer exceptional sensitivity to ultra-light dark matter (ULDM) through their precise measurement of phenomena acting on atoms. While previous work has established their capability to detect scalar and vector ULDM, their potential for detecting spin-2 ULDM remains unexplored. This work investigates the sensitivity of atom interferometers to spin-2 ULDM by considering several frameworks for massive gravity: a Lorentz-invariant Fierz-Pauli case and two Lorentz-violating scenarios. We find that coherent oscillations of the spin-2 ULDM field induce a measurable phase shift through three distinct channels: coupling of the scalar mode to atomic energy levels, and vector and tensor effects that modify the propagation of atoms and light. Atom interferometers uniquely probe all of these effects, while providing sensitivity to a different mass range from laser interferometers. Our results demonstrate the potential of atom interferometers to advance the search for spin-2 dark matter through accessing unexplored parameter space and uncovering new interactions between ULDM and atoms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14282v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diego Blas, John Carlton, Christopher McCabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signals of nonrenormalizable Lorentz and CPT violation at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14305</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14305v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We examine nonrenormalizable Lorentz- and CPT-violating effective operators applied to the quark sector of the Standard Model. Using Drell-Yan events collected by the ATLAS and CMS Collaborations, several constraints are extracted from time-independent modifications of the cross section on the $Z$-boson pole. The sensitivity to time-dependent modifications are also estimated by simulating a sidereal-time analysis. Our results suggest a dedicated search can improve on constraints from deep inelastic scattering by up to three orders in magnitude.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14305v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrico Lunghi, Nathaniel Sherrill</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulation of thermal conduction by asymmetric dark matter in realistic stars and planets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14342v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dark matter captured in stars can act as an additional heat transport mechanism, modifying fusion rates and asteroseismoloigcal observables. Calculations of heat transport rates rely on approximate solutions to the Boltzmann equation, which have never been verified in realistic stars. Here, we simulate heat transport in the Sun, the Earth, and a brown dwarf model, using realistic radial temperature, density, composition and gravitational potential profiles. We show that the formalism developed in arXiv:2111.06895 remains accurate across all celestial objects considered, across a wide range of kinematic regimes, for both spin-dependent and spin-independent interactions where scattering with multiple species becomes important. We further investigate evaporation rates of dark matter from the Sun, finding that previous calculations appear robust. Our Monte Carlo simulation software Cosmion is publicly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14342v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hannah Banks, Stephanie Beram, Rashaad Reid, Aaron C. Vincent</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NNLO fits of top-quark mass using total, single-differential and double-differential $t\bar{t}+X$ cross-section data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14348v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We describe the fits of the top-quark mass value at NNLO using as input the double-differential distributions in rapidity and invariant mass of $t\bar{t}$ pairs obtained by the ATLAS and CMS collaborations from unfolding of their experimental data to the parton level, compared to NNLO theory predictions. We consider different state-of-the-art PDF sets, finding results of the fits compatible among each other within uncertainties. On the other hand, we observe some tension among the fits to different datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14348v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Alekhin, M. V. Garzelli, J. Mazzitelli, S. -O. Moch, O. Zenaiev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using SimTeEx to simplify polynomial expressions with tensors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14390v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Computations with tensors are ubiquitous in fundamental physics, and so is the usage of Einstein's dummy index convention for the contraction of indices. For instance, $T_{ia}U_{aj}$ is readily recognized as the same as $T_{ib}U_{bj}$, but a computer does not know that T[i,a]U[a,j] is equal to T[i,b]U[b,j]. Furthermore, tensors may have symmetries which can be used to simply expressions: if $U_{ij}$ is antisymmetric, then $\alpha T_{ia}U_{aj}+\beta T_{ib}U_{jb}=\left(\alpha-\beta\right)T_{ia}U_{aj}$. The fact that tensors can have elaborate symmetries, together with the problem of dummy indices, makes it complicated to simplify polynomial expressions with tensors. In this work I will present an algorithm for doing so, which was implemented in the Mathematica package SimTeEx (Simplify Tensor Expressions). It can handle any kind of tensor symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14390v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renato M. Fonseca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Wave Detection With Plasma Haloscopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14450</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14450v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Searches for high frequency gravitational waves using cavities based on the Gertsenshtein effect were recently proposed, building off existing axion dark matter experiments. In particular, the sensitivity of axion dark matter experiments using metamaterial plasmas (tunable plasma haloscopes) to gravitational waves has not been explored in detail. Here we perform a full analysis of gravitational wave detection in plasma haloscopes, showing that the baseline design of experiments such as ALPHA is several orders of magnitude less sensitive than previously thought. We show how simple changes to the experiment can recover that sensitivity and lead to a powerful gravitational wave detector in the order of $(10-50)$ GHz frequency range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14450v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rodolfo Capdevilla, Graciela B. Gelmini, Jonah Hyman, Alexander J. Millar, Edoardo Vitagliano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limits on an Exotic Higgs Decay From a Recast ATLAS Four-Lepton Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14452v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ATLAS collaboration, using 139 fb$^{-1}$ of 13 TeV collisions from the Large Hadron Collider, has placed limits on the decay of a $Z$ boson to three dark photons. We reproduce the results of the ATLAS analysis, and then recast it as a limit on a exotic Higgs decay mode, in which the Higgs boson decays via a pair of intermediate (pseudo)scalars $a$ to four dark photons $V$ (or some other spin-one meson). Across the mass range for $m_a$ and $m_V$, we find limits on the exotic Higgs branching fraction BR$(H\to aa \to VVVV)$ in the range of $4\times 10^{-5}$ to $1 \times 10^{-4}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14452v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junyi Cheng, Rabia Husain, Lingfeng Li, Matthew J. Strassler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyper Stealth Dark Matter and Long-Lived Particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14540</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14540v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A new dark matter candidate is proposed that arises as the lightest baryon from a confining $SU(N)$ gauge theory which equilibrates with the Standard Model only through electroweak interactions. Surprisingly, this candidate can be as light as a few GeV. The lower bound arises from the intersection of two competing requirements: i) the equilibration sector of the model must be sufficiently heavy, at least several TeV, to avoid bounds from colliders, and ii) the lightest dark meson (that may be the dark $\eta'$, $\sigma$, or the lightest glueball) has suppressed interactions with the SM, and must decay before BBN. The low energy dark sector consists of one flavor that is electrically neutral and an almost electroweak singlet. The dark matter candidate is the lightest baryon consisting of $N$ of these light flavors leading to a highly suppressed elastic scattering rate with the SM. The equilibration sector consists of vector-like dark quarks that transform under the electroweak group, ensuring that the dark sector can reach thermal equilibrium with the SM in the early Universe. The lightest dark meson lifetimes vary between $10^{-3} \lesssim c \tau \lesssim 10^7$~meters, providing an outstanding target for LHC production and experimental detection. We delineate the interplay between the lifetime of the light mesons, the suppressed direct detection cross section of the lightest baryon, and the scale of equilibration sector that can be probed at the LHC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14540v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George T. Fleming, Graham D. Kribs, Ethan T. Neil, David Schaich, Pavlos M. Vranas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral vortical catalysis constrained by LQCD simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14541v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Evidences of vortical effects have been recently found by experiments in heavy ion collisions, instigating new insights into the phase diagram of quantum chromodynamics. Considering the effect of rotations, lattice QCD data shows that the temperatures for deconfinement and chiral symmetry restoration should increase with real angular velocity, and the dominant effects are related to gluonic degrees of freedom. These findings could be essential for quark models in rotating systems that lack gluonic interactions, which predicts the decreasing of the chiral temperature transition with the angular velocity. To address this issue properly, in this work we apply the two-flavor Nambu--Jona-Lasinio model to explore the phase diagram in a rotating rigid cylinder with constant angular velocity in the mean field approximation. To circumvent the absence of gluons, we propose the application of an effective coupling dependent of the angular velocity, fitted to match the pseudocritical temperature of chiral phase transition in the model through lattice QCD data. Our results indicate that the running coupling induces the enhancement of the chiral condensate as a function of angular velocity, strengthening the breaking of chiral symmetry, an effect previously dubbed as chiral vortical catalysis. For the chiral susceptibility we observe stronger fluctuations around the transition temperature when we consider the running coupling. The phase diagram is affected by these findings shifting the critical end point (CEP) to higher temperatures and chemical potentials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14541v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rodrigo M. Nunes, Ricardo L. S. Farias, William R. Tavares, Varese S. Tim\'oteo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unconventional Searches for Exotic Particles at Future Lepton Colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14560v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The main aim of the the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) experiments is to search for exotic particles with masses in the TeV range as predicted by Beyond Standard Model (BSM) theories. However, there is no hint of BSM around TeV scale so far. Hence, it is possible that the exotic particles are heavier and larger centre of mass energy is needed to observe them. Alternatively, the future lepton colliders offer a comparatively cleaner environment than the LHC which is advantageous to detect light exotic particles. Lepton colliders, like the International Linear Collider, provide the opportunity to detect exotic particles at energies below the TeV scale. The Muon Collider, once fully operational, will have the capability to observe exotic particles at and beyond the TeV scale. The search for BSM particles typically assumes a minimal scenario where only one type of BSM particle couples with the Standard Model (SM) sector. But there are theories which involve such interactions of multiple BSM particles. Here I discusses a specific model featuring a fermionic quintuplet and a scalar quartet that interact before decaying into SM particles. This model yields distinctive signatures characterized by high lepton and jet multiplicities, making it a promising candidate for detection at future lepton colliders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14560v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/epjconf/202431501034</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>EPJ Web Conf. 315 (2024) 01020</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nilanjana Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultraviolet Completion of a Two-loop Neutrino Mass Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14562v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Zee-Babu model is an economical framework for neutrino mass generation as two-loop quantum corrections. In this work, we present a UV completion of this model by embedding it into an $SU(5)$ unified framework. Interestingly, we find that loop-induced contributions to neutrino masses arising from colored scalars are just as important as those from color-neutral ones. These new states, which are required from gauge coupling unification and neutrino oscillation data to have masses below $\mathcal{O}(10^3)$ TeV, may be accessible to future collider experiments. Additionally, the model can be probed in proton decay searches. Our Markov chain Monte Carlo analysis of model parameters shows a high likelihood of observable $p \rightarrow e^+ \pi^0$ decay signal in the first decade of Hyper-Kamiokande operation. The model predicts a vector-like down-type quark at the TeV scale, utilized for realistic fermion mass generation and gauge coupling unification. The model is UV-complete in the sense that it is a unified theory which is realistic and asymptotically free that can be extrapolated to the Planck scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14562v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. S. Babu, Shaikh Saad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electric Dipole Moments From Missed Dark Matter Scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14664v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Axion-like particles are a well-motivated candidate for ultralight dark matter. Because dark matter must be non-relativistic, the effects of its scattering with Standard Model particles are negligible and generally go unnoticed. However, due to the large occupation number of ultralight dark matter, the sum of all scatterings leads to a classical field-like interaction with Standard Model particles. In the case of an axion-like particle, this scattering imparts a parity violating effect. If this collective scattering with axion-like particles is inserted into the one-loop quantum electrodynamics diagram, the parity violation imparted by this scattering will convert the anomalous magnetic moment contribution into an electric dipole moment. This contribution is quite large and leads to a prediction inconsistent with precision measurements of the proton and electron electric dipole moments, unless their couplings to the axion-like particles are very weak. As a result, the constraints on the couplings of axion-like particle dark matter to the electron and proton are improved by as much as eleven and six orders of magnitude, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14664v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jason L. Evans</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffuse Supernova Neutrino Background and Neutrino Non-Radiative Decay: a Bayesian Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14681v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Neutrinos being massive could undergo non-radiative decay, a property for which the diffuse supernova neutrino background has a unique sensitivity. We extend previous analyses to explore our ability to disentangle predictions for the diffuse supernova neutrino background in presence or absence of neutrino non-radiative two-body decay. In a three-neutrino framework, we give predictions of the corresponding neutrino fluxes and the expected number of events in the Super-Kamiokande+Gadolinium, the Hyper-Kamiokande, the JUNO and the DUNE experiments. In our analysis, we employ supernova simulations from different groups and include current uncertainties from both the evolving core-collapse supernova rate and the fraction of failed supernovae. We perform the first Bayesian analysis to see our ability to disentangle the cases in presence and absence of neutrino decay. To this aim we combine the expected events in inverse beta-decay and the neutrino-argon detection channels. We also discuss neutrino-electron, neutrino-proton and of neutrino-oxygen scattering. Our investigation covers the different possible decay patterns for normal mass ordering, both strongly-hierarchical and quasi-degenerate as well as the inverted neutrino mass ordering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14681v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noah Roux, M. Cristina Volpe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the soft rescattering parameters in $B$ decays involving a scalar meson with QCD factorization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14759v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, the soft rescattering parameters in the $B^\pm\rightarrow \pi^\pm\pi^+\pi^-$ and $B^\pm\rightarrow K^\pm\pi^+\pi^-$ decays with the light scalar meson $f_0(500)$ as the intermediate resonance are studied within the QCD factorization. Considering the interference effect between $\rho(770)^0$ and $f_0(500)$, we utilize the experimentally more direct event yields for fitting and get the soft rescattering parameters $|\rho_k^{SP}|=3.29\pm1.01$ and $|\rho_k^{PS}|=2.33\pm0.73$ in $B\rightarrow PS$ and $B\rightarrow SP$ decays ($P$ and $S$ denote pseudoscalar and scalar mesons, respectively), respectively. We also study the branching ratios and $CP$ asymmetries in the decay modes involving other scalar mesons, including $f_0(980)$, $a_0(980)$, $a_0(1450)$ and $K_0^*(1430)$, to test the rationality of the values of $|\rho_k^{SP}|$ and $|\rho_k^{PS}|$. Meanwhile, the wealth of experimental data facilitate the examination of the forward-backward asymmetry induced $CP$ asymmetries (FB-CPAs), and the localized $CP$ asymmetries (LACPs). We investigate these asymmetries resulting from the interference between $\rho(770)^0$ and $f_0(500)$ for $B^\pm\rightarrow \pi^\pm\pi^+\pi^-$ and $B^\pm\rightarrow K^\pm\pi^+\pi^-$ decays when the invariant mass of $\pi^+\pi^-$ locates in the low-energy region $0.445\mathrm{GeV}&lt;m_{\pi\pi}&lt;0.795\mathrm{GeV}$. Our theoretical results of FB-CPAs and LACPs align with the experimental findings. We propose that the interference between $\rho(770)^0$ and $f_0(500)$ can be extended to other beauty and charmed mesons decays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14759v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing-Juan Qi, Zhen-Yang Wang, Zhen-Hua Zhang, Ke-Wei Wei, Xin-Heng Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Baryonic Axion in neutron-antineutron oscillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14823v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The accidental baryonic symmetry is expected to be broken and required from the observed matter-antimatter asymmetry. The neutron-antineutron oscillating system is the hallmark of $\Delta \mathcal{B} = 2$ models which have the benefits of not inducing proton decay. We study this system in a framework allowing the most general couplings to understand how a dark matter candidate such as the axion may couple to the oscillation. In particular a Rabi resonance phenomenon occurs, and this effect is unconstrained for Axion Like Particles (ALPs) models. Regarding the QCD axion, its Goldstone nature leads to a robust exclusion of the majority of scenarios allowed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14823v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Th\'eo Brugeat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Status of two-loop automation in OpenLoops</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14856v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The calculation of hard scattering amplitudes up to NLO is automated in numerical tools, such as OpenLoops. The LHC and future experiments, however, demand high-precision predictions at NNLO and beyond for a wide range of particle processes. Hence, the development of a fully automated tool for numerical NNLO calculations is an important goal. In order to perform a numerical calculation, we decompose $D$-dimensional two-loop amplitudes into Feynman integrals with four-dimensional numerators and $(D-4)$-dimensional remainders, which contribute to the finite result through the interaction with the poles of Feynman integrals and are reconstructed during the subtraction procedure for these poles from universal rational terms. The integrals with four-dimensional numerators are further decomposed into loop momentum tensor integrals and tensor coefficients. We present the status of OpenLoops with respect to these building blocks. The algorithm for the construction of the tensor coefficients is implemented for QED and QCD corrections to the SM in a fully automated way. Recently, the renormalisation procedure and the reconstruction of the interplay of $(D-4)$-dimensional numerator parts with UV poles through two-loop rational counterterms has been implemented and validated using an in-house library for the reduction of simple tensor integrals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14856v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PoS(LL2024)073</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Natalie Sch\"ar, Max F. Zoller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predictions of masses for light hybrid baryons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14878v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Within the method of parity-projected QCD sum rules, we study the mass spectra of light hybrid baryons with $I(J^{P})=1/2(1/2^{\pm}), 3/2(1/2^{\pm}), 1/2(3/2^{\pm}), 3/2(3/2^{\pm})$ by constructing the local $qqqg$ interpolating currents. We calculate the correlation functions up to dimension eight condensates at the leading order of $\alpha_{s}$. The stable QCD Lapalce sum rules can be established for the positive-parity $N_{1/2^+}, \Delta_{3/2^+}, \Delta_{1/2^+}$ and negative-parity $N_{1/2^-}, N_{3/2^-}, \Delta_{1/2^-}$ channels to extract their mass spectra. The lowest-lying hybrid baryons are predicted to be the negative-parity $N_{1/2^-}$ state around 2.28 GeV and $\Delta_{1/2^-}$ state around 2.64 GeV. These hybrid baryons mainly decay into conventional baryon plus meson final states. We propose to search for the light hybrid baryons through the $\chi_{cJ}/\Upsilon$ decays via the three-gluon emission mechanism in BESIII and BelleII experiments. Our studies of the light hybrid baryons will be useful for understanding the excited baryon spectrum and the behavior of gluonic degrees of freedom in QCD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14878v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qi-Nan Wang, Ding-Kun Lian, Wei Chen, Hui-Min Yang, Hua-Xing Chen, J. Ho, T. G. Steele</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light scalars within the $\mathcal{CP}$-conserving Aligned-two-Higgs-doublet model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14906v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article we study the possibility that neutral and charged scalars lighter than the 125 GeV Higgs boson might exist within the framework of the $\mathcal{CP}$-conserving Aligned-two-Higgs-doublet model. Depending on which new scalar (scalars) is (are) light, seven different scenarios may be considered. Using the open-source code HEPfit, which relies on Bayesian statistics, we perform global fits for all seven light-mass scenarios. The constraints arising from vacuum stability, perturbativity, electroweak precision observables, flavour observables, Higgs signal strengths, and direct-detection results at the LEP and the LHC are taken into account. Reinterpreted data from slepton searches are considered too. It turns out that the seven scenarios contain sizeable regions of their parameter space compatible with all current data. Although not included in the global fits, the possible implications of $(g-2)_\mu$ are also addressed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14906v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio M. Coutinho, Anirban Karan, V\'ictor Miralles, Antonio Pich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust estimates of theoretical uncertainties at fixed-order in perturbation theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14910</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14910v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Calculations truncated at a fixed order in perturbation theory are accompanied by an associated theoretical uncertainty, which encodes the missing higher orders (MHOU). This is typically estimated by a scale variation procedure, which has well-known shortcomings. In this work, we propose a simple prescription to directly encode the missing higher order terms using theory nuisance parameters (TNPs) and estimate the uncertainty by their variation. We study multiple processes relevant for Large Hadron Collider physics at next-to-leading and next-to-next-to-leading order in perturbation theory, obtaining MHOU estimates for differential observables in each case. In cases where scale variations are well-behaved we are able to replicate their effects using TNPs, while we find significant improvement in cases where scale variation typically underestimates the uncertainty.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14910v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew A. Lim, Rene Poncelet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining $B$-Mesogenesis models with inclusive and exclusive decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14947v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The $B$-Mesogenesis model explains the matter-antimatter asymmetry and leads to the right amount of dark matter in the Universe. In particular, this model predicts new decay channels of the $b$ quark. We investigate the modification of inclusive $b$-hadron decay rates and of the lifetimes of different $B$ mesons due to these new decay channels and compare our results with available predictions for exclusive $B$ meson decays. We find a small surviving parameter space where the $B$-Mesogenesis model is working and which has not been excluded by experiment. Experimental investigations in the near future should be able to test this remaining parameter space and thus either exclude or confirm the $B$-Mesogenesis model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14947v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Lenz, Ali Mohamed, Zachary W\"uthrich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Line operators in the G2HDM model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14949</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14949v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We describe the global structure of a particle model with dark matter called G2HDM, which incorporates a dark sector represented by $SU(2)_{H} \times U(1)_{X}\;$. The gauge group of such model is $\tilde{G}=U(1)_{Y} \times SU(2)_{L} \times SU(3)_{C} \times SU(2)_{H} \times U(1)_{X} \;$, with an ambiguity that it may actually be $G= \tilde{G} / {\Gamma} \;$, where $\Gamma$ is a subgroup of its center. We also describe how the electric and magnetic charges depend on $\Gamma$ and the periodicity of theta angles for any choice of $G$. Finally, we describe the minimal charges that arise after electroweak symmetry breaking for any choice of $\Gamma$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14949v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rui Yang, Jiaming Guo, Linghai Li, Tzu-Chiang Yuan, Xun Xue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modification of jets travelling through a brick-like medium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14983</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14983v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is a continued open question how there can be an azimuthal anisotropy of high $p_\perp$ particles quantified by a sizable $v_2$ in p+Pb collisions when, at the same time, the nuclear modification factor $R_\text{AA}$ is consistent with unity. We address this puzzle within the framework of the jet quenching model \textsc{Jewel}. In the absence of reliable medium models for small collision systems we use the number of scatterings per parton times the squared Debye mass to characterise the strength of medium modifications. Working with a simple brick medium model we show that, for small systems and not too strong modifications, $R_\text{AA}$ and $v_2$ approximately scale with this quantity. We find that a comparatively large number of scatterings is needed to generate measurable jet quenching. Our results indicate that the $R_\text{AA}$ corresponding to the observed $v_2$ could fall within the experimental uncertainty. Thus, while there is currently no contradiction with the measurements, our results indicate that $v_2$ and $R_\text{AA}$ go hand-in-hand. We also discuss departures from scaling, in particular due to sizable inelastic energy loss.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14983v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chiara Le Roux, Jos\'e Guilherme Milhano, Korinna Zapp</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutrino electromagnetic properties and sterile dipole portal in light of the first solar CE$\nu$NS data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14991v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Despite being neutral particles, neutrinos can acquire non-zero electromagnetic properties from radiative corrections that can be induced by the presence of new physics. Electromagnetic neutrino processes induce spectral distortions in neutrino scattering data, which are especially visible at experiments characterized by low recoil thresholds. We investigate how neutrino electromagnetic properties confront the recent indication of coherent elastic neutrino-nucleus scattering (CE$\nu$NS) from $^8$B solar neutrinos in dark matter direct detection experiments. We focus on three possibilities: neutrino magnetic moments, neutrino electric charges, and the active-sterile transition magnetic moment portal. We analyze recent XENONnT and PandaX-4T data and infer the first \cevns-based constraints on electromagnetic properties using solar $^8$B neutrinos.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14991v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valentina De Romeri, Dimitrios K. Papoulias, Gonzalo Sanchez Garcia, Christoph A. Ternes, Mariam T\'ortola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Screening masses of positive- and negative-parity hadron ground-states, including those with strangeness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15045</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15045v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using a symmetry-preserving treatment of a vector $\times$ vector contact interaction (SCI) at nonzero temperature, we compute the screening masses of flavour-SU(3) ground-state $J^P=0^\pm$, $1^\pm$ mesons, and $J^P=1/2^\pm$, $3/2^\pm$ baryons. We find that all correlation channels allowed at $T=0$ persist when the temperature increases, even above the QCD phase transition. The results for mesons qualitatively agree with those obtained from the contemporary lattice-regularised quantum chromodynamics (lQCD) simulations. One of the most remarkable features is that each parity-partner-pair degenerates when $T&gt;T_c$, with $T_c$ being the critical temperature. For each pair, the screening mass of the negative parity meson increases monotonously with temperature. In contrast, the screening mass of the meson with positive parity is almost invariant on the domain $T\lesssim T_c/2$; when $T$ gets close to $T_c$, it decreases but soon increases again and finally degenerates with its parity partner, which signals the restoration of chiral symmetry. We also find that the $T$-dependent behaviours of baryon screening masses are quite similar to those of the mesons. For baryons, the dynamical, nonpointlike diquark correlations play a crucial role in the screening mass evolution. We further calculate the evolution of the fraction of each kind of diquark within baryons respective to temperature. We observe that, at high temperatures, only $J=0$ scalar and pseudoscalar diquark correlations can survive within $J^P=1/2^\pm$ baryons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15045v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Chen, Fei Gao, Si-xue Qin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints and Sensitivities for Dipole-Portal Heavy Neutral Leptons from ND280 and its Upgrade</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15051</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15051v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report new constraints and sensitivities to heavy neutral leptons (HNLs) with transition magnetic moments, also known as dipole-portal HNLs. This is accomplished using data from the T2K ND280 near detector in addition to the projected three-year dataset of the upgraded ND280 detector. Dipole-portal HNLs have been extensively studied in the literature and offer a potential explanation for the $4.8\sigma$ MiniBooNE anomaly. To perform our analysis, we simulate HNL decays to $e^+e^-$ pairs in the gaseous time projection chambers of the ND280 detector and its upgrade. Recasting an ND280 search for mass-mixed HNLs, we find that ND280 data places world-leading constraints on dipole-portal HNLs in the 390-743\,{\rm MeV} mass range, disfavoring the region of parameter space favored by the MiniBooNE anomaly. The addition of three years of ND280 upgrade data will be able to disfavor the MiniBooNE solution at the $5 \sigma$ confidence level and extend the world-leading constraints to dipole-portal HNLs in the 148-860\,{\rm MeV} mass range. Our analysis suggests that ND280 data excludes dipole-portal HNLs as a solution to the MiniBooNE excess, motivating a dedicated search within the T2K collaboration and potentially highlighting the need for alternative explanations for the MiniBooNE anomaly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15051v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ming-Shau Liu, Nicholas Kamp, Carlos A. Arg\"uelles</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leptoquark-induced radiative masses for active and sterile neutrinos within the framework of the 3-3-1 model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15055</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15055v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we introduce the minimal set of leptoquarks into the 3-3-1 model with right-handed neutrinos, capable of generating radiative masses for active neutrinos. As a main consequence, the standard neutrinos acquire small Majorana masses at the one-loop level, while right-handed (sterile) neutrinos obtain small Majorana masses at the two-loop level, naturally making them light particles as well. Additionally, we discuss the viability of this scenario and several other interesting phenomenological consequences, including its impact on $B$-meson physics and rare Higgs decays, both of which are also induced by the leptoquarks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15055v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Doff, Jo\~ao Paulo Pinheiro, C. A. de S. Pires</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General Form of Effective Operators from Hidden Sectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15067</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15067v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We perform a model-independent analysis of the dimension-six terms that are generated in the low energy effective theory when a hidden sector that communicates with the Standard Model (SM) through a specific portal operator is integrated out. We work within the Standard Model Effective Field Theory (SMEFT) framework and consider the Higgs, neutrino and hypercharge portals. We find that, for each portal, the forms of the leading dimension-six terms in the low-energy effective theory are fixed and independent of the dynamics in the hidden sector. For the Higgs portal, we find that two independent dimension-six terms are generated, one of which has a sign that, under certain conditions, is fixed by the requirement that the dynamics in the hidden sector be causal and unitary. In the case of the neutrino portal, for a single generation of SM fermions and assuming that the hidden sector does not violate lepton number, a unique dimension-six term is generated, which corresponds to a specific linear combination of operators in the Warsaw basis. For the hypercharge portal, a unique dimension-six term is generated, which again corresponds to a specific linear combination of operators in the Warsaw basis. For both the neutrino and hypercharge portals, under certain conditions, the signs of these terms are fixed by the requirement that the hidden sector be causal and unitary. We perform a global fit of these dimension-six terms to electroweak precision observables, Higgs measurements and diboson production data and determine the current bounds on their coefficients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15067v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aqeel Ahmed, Zackaria Chacko, Ina Flood, Can Kilic, Saereh Najjari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monodromic transparency of axion domain walls</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15085v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revisit the study of light interacting with QCD axion domain walls from the perspective of the non-linear axion coupling to photons, $g(a) F \tilde F$, which encodes the effects related to the breaking of the axion shift symmetry including the well-known mixing with meson states. As the axion makes an $\mathcal{O}(1)$ excursion of its fundamental period around strings and domain walls, the standard linear coupling to photons is generally insufficient to accurately describe the interaction of light with the defects, and one needs to consider the full structure of $g(a)$. We take this into account in evaluating the friction experienced by axion domain walls moving in a thermal bath of photons, as well as in deriving the birefringent properties of the walls. This clarifies some results in the literature dealing with a special cancellation that takes place for the QCD axion with the electromagnetic and color anomaly as predicted by minimal Grand Unified Theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15085v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simone Blasi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry breaking effects in pion couplings to constituent quarks currents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15104v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Pseudoscalar and axial neutral and charged pion-constituent quark coupling constants are investigated with nondegenerate quark masses in different kinematical points, off shell and on shell pions and constituent quarks. For the neutral pion, mixing effects are introduced by means of the pion mixing to states $P_0$ and $P_8$, that give rise to the $\pi^0-\eta-\eta'$ meson mixing, and mixing of quark currents via corresponding mixing interactions. The relative behavior of charged and neutral pion coupling constants to quarks may be nearly the same - in the framework of the constituent quark model - as the pion-nucleon coupling constants if mixings are introduced. A very small pion coupling to strange quark current is also obtained. The dependence of the positive and negative pion-constituent quark coupling constant on the non-degeneracy of quark masses, for emission and absorption processes, is identified.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15104v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabio L. Braghin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmology-Independent Constraints on Irreducible Magnetic Monopole Background</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15132v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a novel mechanism for the irreducible production of magnetic monopoles from interactions of cosmic rays and interstellar medium (ISM). Resulting monopoles drain energy from galactic magnetic fields, disrupting their formation and sustainability. We generalize conventional Parker bounds to monopoles with extended energy spectrum and, considering cosmic ray ISM monopole production, set novel constraints from disruption of Milky Way Galactic magnetic fields and their seeds. Further, we set first constraints on disruption of galactic magnetic fields and their seeds of Andromeda galaxy, with results being competitive with distinct existing bounds. Unlike Parker limits of previous works that relied on cosmological monopoles, our constraints are independent of cosmological monopole production or their primordial abundance. Besides, we estimate new constraints on dipole magnetic moments generated from cosmic ray ISM interactions. We discuss implications for monopoles with generalized magnetic charges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15132v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Syuhei Iguro, Varun Mathur, Ian M. Shoemaker, Volodymyr Takhistov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discriminating between Pseudoscalar Higgs and Toponium States at the LHC and Beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15138</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15138v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss ways to discriminate at hadron colliders between a quasi-bound toponium state and a pseudoscalar Higgs boson A, as predicted in many extensions of the Standard Model. We apply the discussion to the excess of t tbar threshold events recently observed at the LHC by the CMS collaboration \cite{CMS}, which could be due to either possibility. Working in an effective theory in which only an additional pseudoscalar A boson is present in the spectrum, with a mass close to the 2 m_t threshold and a significant coupling to top quarks, we discuss the interference between A production in the dominant gluon-fusion process gg \to A with subsequent A\to t tbar decays, and the QCD continuum background, gg\to t tbar. While this interference is absent in the case of toponium, it is essential for evaluating the A interpretation of the CMS excess. It is difficult to resolve the peak/dip structure that it generates because of the experimental smearing of the t tbar invariant mass spectrum. However, by comparing the total A production rates for different integration domains of the t tbar invariant mass or, eventually, at different center of mass energies, one may be able to observe its effects. We then discuss additional mechanisms for A production in pp collisions, including loop-induced production in association with the lighter h boson, gg \to hA, and production in association with top-quark pairs, gg/q\bar q \to t tbar. A These mechanisms have small cross sections at the LHC, and their observation will necessitate higher luminosities or collider energies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15138v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdelhak Djouadi, John Ellis, Jeremie Quevillon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A holographic study on QCD phase transition and neutron star properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15149v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the QCD phase transition and its phase structure within Einstein-Maxwell-Dilaton-scalar system and compare the results with those obtained from the Einstein-Maxwell-Dilaton system. It is shown that both models reproduce behavior consistent with lattice QCD. In particular, the Einstein-Maxwell-Dilaton-scalar system exhibits a first-order phase transition in the pure gauge sector, aligning with predictions from Yang-Mills theory. Based on these models, we construct a holographic model for neutron stars, incorporating leptons to satisfy electric charge neutrality, and examine the cold equation of state, the mass-radius relation, and tidal deformability of neutron stars. It is demonstrated that the Einstein-Maxwell-Dilaton-scalar system enables us to describe neutron star properties that meet current astrophysical constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15149v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin-Yi Liu, Yong-Liang Ma, Yue-Liang Wu, Zhen Fang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Determining $\alpha_s(m_Z)$ from Dijets in $e^+e^-$ Thrust</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15164v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We update a previous N$^3$LL$^\prime$+${\cal O}(\alpha_s^3)$ determination of the strong coupling from a global fit to thrust data by including newly available perturbative ingredients, upgrading the renormalization scales to include a fully canonical scaling region, and implementing the log resummation in a way which ensures the integrated cross section is unaffected by the the leading $1/Q$ hadronization power corrections. Detailed discussions are provided concerning the stability of the results under variations of the fit range and the importance of summing up higher-order logarithmic terms for convergence and stability. We show that high-precision results can be achieved even when carrying out a more conservative fit by restricting the dataset to a region which is more clearly dominated by dijet events. This leads to $\alpha_s(m_Z) = 0.1136 \pm 0.0012$ with $\chi^2/{\rm dof}=0.86$, fully compatible with earlier results using a larger fit range. We also demonstrate that a number of additional effects associated to power corrections have a small impact on this fit result, including modifications to the renormalon substraction scheme for dijet power corrections and the inclusion of three-jet power correction models. The fit is also shown to provide very good agreement with data outside the fit range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15164v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel A. Benitez, Andre H. Hoang, Vicent Mateu, Iain W. Stewart, Gherardo Vita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flavor at FASER: Discovering Light Scalars Beyond Minimal Flavor Violation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15197</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15197v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a simple class of flavored scalar models, in which the couplings of a new light scalar to standard-model fermions are controlled by the flavor symmetry responsible for fermion masses and mixings. The scalar couplings are then aligned with the Yukawa matrices, with small but nonzero flavor-violating entries. $D$-meson decays are an important source of scalar production in these models, in contrast to models assuming minimal flavor violation, in which $B$ and $K$ decays dominate. We show that FASER2 can probe large portions of the parameter space of the models, with comparable numbers of scalars from $B$ and $D$ decays in some regions. If discovered, these particles will not only provide evidence of new physics, but they may also shed new light on the standard model flavor puzzle. Finally, the richness of theoretical models underscores the importance of model-independent interpretations. We therefore analyze the sensitivity of FASER and other experimental searches in terms of physical parameters:~(i) the branching fractions of heavy mesons to the scalar, and (ii) $\tau/m$, where $\tau$ and $m$ are the scalar's lifetime and mass, respectively. The results are largely independent of the new particle's spin and can be used to extract constraints on a wide variety of models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15197v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reuven Balkin, Noam Burger, Jonathan L. Feng, Yael Shadmi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C-R-T Fractionalization in the First Quantized Hamiltonian Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11958v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent research has revealed that the CRT symmetry for fermions exhibits a fractionalization distinct from the $\mathbb{Z}_2^{\mathcal{C}}\times\mathbb{Z}_2^{\mathcal{R}}\times\mathbb{Z}_2^{\mathcal{T}}$ for scalar bosons. In fact, the CRT symmetry for fermions can be extended by internal symmetries such as fermion parity, thereby forming a group extension of the $\mathbb{Z}_2$ direct product. Conventionally, a Majorana fermion is defined by one Dirac fermion with trivial charge conjugation. However, when the spacetime dimension $d+1=5,6,7\bmod8$, the real dimension of Majorana fermion (dim$_{\mathbb{R}}\chi_{\mathcal{C}\ell(d,0)}$) aligns with the real dimension of Dirac fermion (dim$_{\mathbb{R}}\psi_{\mathcal{C}\ell(d)}$), rather than being half, which necessitates the introduction of a symplectic Majorana fermion, defined by two Dirac fermions with trivial charge conjugation. To include these two types of Majorana fermions, we embed the theory in $n_{\mathbb{R}}$ and define the Majorana fermion field as a representation of the real Clifford algebra with 8-fold periodicity. Within the Hamiltonian formalism, we identify the 8-fold CRT-internal symmetry groups across general dimensions. Similarly, Dirac fermion field is defined as a representation of the complex Clifford algebra with 2-fold periodicity. Interestingly, we discover that the CRT-internal symmetry groups exhibit an 8-fold periodicity that is distinct from that of the complex Clifford algebra. In certain dimensions where distinct mass terms can span a mass manifold, the CRT-internal symmetries can act non-trivially upon this mass manifold. Employing domain wall reduction method, we are able to elucidate the relationships between symmetries across different dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11958v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang-Yang Li, Zheyan Wan, Juven Wang, Shing-Tung Yau, Yi-Zhuang You</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semi-Analytic Modeling of Dark Matter Subhalo Encounters with Thin Stellar Streams: Statistical Predictions for GD-1-like Streams in CDM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13144v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Stellar streams from disrupted globular clusters are dynamically cold structures that are sensitive to perturbations from dark matter subhalos, allowing them in principle to trace the dark matter substructure in the Milky Way. We model, within the context of $\Lambda$CDM, the likelihood of dark matter subhalos to produce a significant feature in a GD-1-like stream and analyze the properties of such subhalos. We generate a large number of realizations of the subhalo population within a Milky Way mass host halo, accounting for tidal stripping and dynamical friction, using the semi-analytic code SatGen. The subhalo distributions are combined with a GD-1-like stream model, and the impact of subhalos that pass close to the stream are modeled with Gala. We find that subhalos with masses in the range $5\times 10^6 M_{\odot} - 10^8 M_{\odot}$ at the time of the stream-subhalo encounter, corresponding to masses of about $4 \times 10^7 M_{\odot} - 8 \times 10^8 M_{\odot}$ at the time of infall, are the likeliest to produce gaps in a GD-1-like stream. We find that gaps occur on average $\sim$1.8 times per realization of the host system. These gaps have typical widths of $\sim(7 - 27)$ deg and fractional underdensities of $\sim (10 - 30)\%$, with larger gaps being caused by more-massive subhalos. The stream-subhalo encounters responsible for these have impact parameters $(0.1 - 1.5)$ kpc and relative velocities $\sim(170 - 410)$ km/s. For a larger host-halo mass, the number of subhalos increases, as do their typical velocities, inducing a corresponding increase in the number of significant stream-subhalo encounters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13144v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Duncan K. Adams, Aditya Parikh, Oren Slone, Rouven Essig, Manoj Kaplinghat, Adrian M. Price-Whelan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher-order dissipative anisotropic magnetohydrodynamics from the Boltzmann-Vlasov equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14202v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We apply the method of moments to the relativistic Boltzmann-Vlasov equation and derive the equations of motion for the irreducible moments of arbitrary tensor-rank of the invariant single-particle distribution function. We study two cases, in the first of which the moments are taken to be irreducible with respect to the little group associated with the time-like fluid four-velocity, while in the second case they are assumed to be also irreducible with respect to a space-like four-vector orthogonal to the fluid four-velocity, which breaks the spatial isotropy to a rotational symmetry in the plane transverse to this vector. A systematic truncation and closure of the general moment equations leads, in the first case, to a theory of relativistic higher-order dissipative resistive magnetohydrodynamics. In the second case, we obtain a novel theory of dissipative resistive anisotropic magnetohydrodynamics, where the momentum anisotropy is in principle independent from that introduced by the external magnetic field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14202v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Etele Moln\'ar, Dirk H. Rischke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Dark Matter Through the Dust of the Milky Way Part I: Dust Correction and Phase Space Density</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14236</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14236v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Boltzmann equation relates the equilibrium phase space distribution of stars in the Milky Way to the Galaxy's gravitational potential. However, observations of stellar populations are biased by extinction from foreground dust, which complicates measurements of the potential in the disk and towards the Galactic center. Using the kinematics of Red Clump and Red Branch stars in Gaia DR3, we use machine learning to simultaneously estimate both the unbiased stellar phase space density and the gravitational potential. The unbiased phase space density is obtained through a learned "dust efficiency factor" -- an observational selection function that accounts for dust extinction. The potential and the dust efficiency are parameterized by fully connected neural networks and are completely data driven. We validate the dust efficiency using a recent three-dimensional dust map in this work, and examine the potential in a companion paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14236v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Putney, David Shih, Sung Hak Lim, Matthew R. Buckley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of DESI BAO Data on Inflationary Parameters: stability against late-time new physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14290v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, I investigate the impact of Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) Baryonic Acoustic Oscillations (BAO) data on cosmological parameters, focusing on the inflationary spectral index $n_s$, the amplitude of scalar perturbations $A_s$, and the matter density parameter $\omega_m$. By examining different models of late-time new physics, the inflationary parameters were revealed to be stable when compared with the baseline dataset that used the earlier BAO data from the SDSS collaboration. When combined with Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) and type Ia supernovae (SNeIa), DESI BAO data leads to a slight reduction in $\omega_m$ (less than 2\%) and modest changes in $A_s$ and $n_s$, if compared with the same combination but using SDSS BAO data instead, suggesting a subtle shift in matter clustering. These effects may be attributed to a higher expansion rate from dynamical dark energy, changes in the recombination period, or modifications to the matter-radiation equality time. Further analyses of models with dynamical dark energy and free curvature show a consistent trend of reduced $\omega_m$, accompanied by slight increases in both $n_s$ and $H_0$. The results emphasize the importance of the DESI BAO data in refining cosmological parameter estimates and highlight the stability of inflationary parameters across different late-time cosmological models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14290v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simony Santos da Costa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a differential $\mathrm{t\bar{t}W}$ cross section measurement at CMS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14303v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Top quark pair production in association with a W boson is a rare standard model process that has proven to be an intriguing puzzle for theorists and experimentalists alike. Recent measurements, performed at $\sqrt{s}$ = 13 TeV, by both the ATLAS and CMS Collaborations at the CERN LHC, find cross section values that are consistently higher than the latest state-of-the-art theory predictions. In this presentation, both experimental and theoretical challenges in the pursuit of a better understanding of this process are discussed. Furthermore, a framework for a future differential measurement to be performed with the Run 2 CMS data (collected in 2016-2018) is proposed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14303v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Marckx (for the CMS Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Free streaming of warm wave dark matter in modified expansion histories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14322</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14322v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In models of warm dark matter, there is an appreciable population of high momentum particles in the early universe, which free stream out of primordial over/under densities, thereby prohibiting the growth of structure on small length scales. The distance that a dark matter particle travels without obstruction, known as the free streaming length, depends on the particle's mass and momentum, but also on the cosmological expansion rate. In this way, measurements of the linear matter power spectrum serve to probe warm dark matter as well as the cosmological expansion history. In this work, we focus on ultra-light wave wave dark matter (WWDM) characterized by a typical comoving momentum $q_\ast$ and mass $m$. We first derive constraints on the WWDM parameter space $(q_\ast, m)$ using Lyman-$\alpha$ forest observations due to a combination of the free-streaming effect and the white-noise effect. We next assess how the free streaming of WWDM is affected by three modified expansion histories: early matter domination, early dark energy, and very early dark energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14322v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew J. Long, Moira Venegas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diversity and universality: evolution of dwarf galaxies with self-interacting dark matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14621v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Dark matter halos with self-interacting dark matter (SIDM) experience a unique evolutionary phenomenon, in that their central regions eventually collapse to high density through the runaway gravothermal process after initially forming a large and low-density core. When coupled with orbital evolution, this is expected to naturally produce a large diversity in dark-matter halos' inner mass distribution, potentially explaining the diversity problem of dwarf galaxies. However, it remains unknown how the diversity in SIDM dark-matter halos propagates to the more easily observed luminous matter at the center of the halo, especially the stellar component. In this work, we use idealized N-body simulations with two species of particles (dark matter and stars) to study the response of the stellar properties of field and satellite dwarf galaxies to SIDM evolution and orbital effects on their halos. Galaxies' stellar components, including galaxy size, mass-to-light ratio, and stellar velocity dispersion, display a much larger scatter in SIDM than the standard cold dark matter (CDM) model. Importantly, we find signs of universality in the evolution pathways, or ``tidal tracks'', of SIDM dwarf satellites, which are physically interpretable and potentially parameterizable. This type of tidal-track model can be layered onto larger-scale, cosmological simulations to reconstruct the evolution of populations of SIDM dwarfs in cases where high-resolution simulations of galaxies are otherwise prohibitively expensive.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14621v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhichao Carton Zeng, Annika H. G. Peter, Xiaolong Du, Andrew Benson, Jiaxuan Li, Charlie Mace, Shengqi Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Solar Heavy Neutrinos with Heliospheric Electrons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14752</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14752v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We search for an excess of electrons and positrons in the interplanetary space from the decays of heavy neutrinos produced in nuclear reactions in the Sun. Using measurements of the electron spectra in the MeV range from the Ulysses and SOHO satellites, we report the strongest direct upper bound to date on the mixing between heavy neutral leptons with MeV masses and electron neutrinos, reaching $U_e^2\simeq 10^{-6}$ at $M_N=10$ MeV. Our sensitivity is predominantly constrained by the uncertainties in the propagation of electrons and positrons, particularly the diffusion coefficient in the inner Solar System, as well as the uncertainties in the astrophysical background. Enhancing our understanding of either of these factors could lead to a significant improvement in sensitivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14752v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Drewes, Jan Heisig, Valentin Weber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Differential cross section measurements of top quark pair production for variables of the dineutrino system with the CMS experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14806v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Differential top quark pair cross sections are measured in the dilepton final state as a function of kinematic variables associated to the dineutrino system. The measurements are performed making use of the Run 2 dataset collected by the CMS experiment at the CERN LHC collider, corresponding to proton-proton collisions recorded at center of mass energy of 13 TeV and an integrated luminosity of 138 fb$^{-1}$. The measured cross sections are found in agreement with theory predictions and Monte Carlo simulations of standard model processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14806v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sandra Consuegra Rodr\'iguez (on behalf of the CMS Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Deep Underground Neutrino Experiment (DUNE) program</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14941</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14941v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Deep Underground Neutrino Experiment (DUNE) is a next-generation long-baseline neutrino oscillation experiment aimed at determining the neutrino mass hierarchy and the CP-violating phase. The DUNE physics program also includes the detection of astrophysical neutrinos and the search for signatures beyond the Standard Model, such as nucleon decays. DUNE consists of a near detector complex located at Fermilab and four 17 kton Liquid Argon Time Projection Chamber (LArTPC) far detector modules to be built 1.5 km underground at SURF, approximately 1300 km away. The detectors are exposed to a wideband neutrino beam generated by a 1.2 MW proton beam with a planned upgrade to &gt; 2 MW. Two 770 ton LArTPCs (ProtoDUNEs) have been operated at CERN for over 2 years as a testbed for DUNE far detectors and have been optimized to take new cosmic and test-beam data in 2024-2025. The DUNE and ProtoDUNE experiments and physics goals, as well as recent progress and results, are presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14941v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. Gil-Botella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Terrestrial Very-Long-Baseline Atom Interferometry: Summary of the Second Workshop</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14960v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This summary of the second Terrestrial Very-Long-Baseline Atom Interferometry (TVLBAI) Workshop provides a comprehensive overview of our meeting held in London in April 2024, building on the initial discussions during the inaugural workshop held at CERN in March 2023. Like the summary of the first workshop, this document records a critical milestone for the international atom interferometry community. It documents our concerted efforts to evaluate progress, address emerging challenges, and refine strategic directions for future large-scale atom interferometry projects. Our commitment to collaboration is manifested by the integration of diverse expertise and the coordination of international resources, all aimed at advancing the frontiers of atom interferometry physics and technology, as set out in a Memorandum of Understanding signed by over 50 institutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14960v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam Abdalla (Maril), Mahiro Abe (Maril), Sven Abend (Maril), Mouine Abidi (Maril), Monika Aidelsburger (Maril), Ashkan Alibabaei (Maril), Baptiste Allard (Maril), John Antoniadis (Maril), Gianluigi Arduini (Maril), Nadja Augst (Maril), Philippos Balamatsias (Maril), Antun Balaz (Maril), Hannah Banks (Maril), Rachel L. Barcklay (Maril), Michele Barone (Maril), Michele Barsanti (Maril), Mark G. Bason (Maril), Angelo Bassi (Maril), Jean-Baptiste Bayle (Maril), Charles F. A. Baynham (Maril), Quentin Beaufils (Maril), Slyan Beldjoudi (Maril), Aleksandar Belic (Maril), Shayne Bennetts (Maril), Jose Bernabeu (Maril), Andrea Bertoldi (Maril), Clara Bigard (Maril), N. P. Bigelow (Maril), Robert Bingham (Maril), Diego Blas (Maril), Alexey Bobrick (Maril), Samuel Boehringer (Maril), Aleksandar Bogojevic (Maril), Kai Bongs (Maril), Daniela Bortoletto (Maril), Philippe Bouyer (Maril), Christian Brand (Maril), Oliver Buchmueller (Maril), Gabriela Buica (Maril), Sergio Calatroni (Maril), Lo Calmels (Maril), Priscilla Canizares (Maril), Benjamin Canuel (Maril), Ana Caramete (Maril), Laurentiu-Ioan Caramete (Maril), Matteo Carlesso (Maril), John Carlton (Maril), Samuel P. Carman (Maril), Andrew Carroll (Maril), Mateo Casariego (Maril), Minoas Chairetis (Maril), Vassilis Charmandaris (Maril), Upasna Chauhan (Maril), Jiajun Chen (Maril), Maria Luisa (Maril),  Chiofalo, Donatella Ciampini, Alessia Cimbri, Pierre Clad, Jonathon Coleman, Florin Lucian Constantin, Carlo R. Contaldi, Robin Corgier, Bineet Dash, G. J. Davies, Claudia de Rham, Albert De Roeck, Daniel Derr, Soumyodeep Dey, Fabio Di Pumpo, Goran S. Djordjevic, Babette Doebrich, Peter Dornan, Michael Doser, Giannis Drougakis, Jacob Dunningham, Alisher Duspayev, Sajan Easo, Joshua Eby, Maxim Efremov, Gedminas Elertas, John Ellis, Nicholas Entin, Stephen Fairhurst, Mattia Fani, Farida Fassi, Pierre Fayet, Daniel Felea, Jie Feng, Robert Flack, Chris Foot, Tim Freegarde, Elina Fuchs, Naceur Gaaloul, Dongfeng Gao, Susan Gardner, Barry M. Garraway, Carlos L. Garrido Alzar, Alexandre Gauguet, Enno Giese, Patrick Gill, Gian F. Giudice, Eric P. Glasbrenner, Jonah Glick, Peter W. Graham, Eduardo Granados, Paul F. Griffin, Jordan Gue, Saida Guellati-Khelifa, Subhadeep Gupta, Vishu Gupta, Lucia Hackermueller, Martin Haehnelt, Timo Hakulinen, Klemens Hammerer, Ekim T. Hanimeli, Tiffany Harte, Sabrina Hartmann, Leonie Hawkins, Aurelien Hees, Alexander Herbst, Thomas M. Hird, Richard Hobson, Jason Hogan, Bodil Holst, Michael Holynski, Onur Hosten, Chung Chuan Hsu, Wayne Cheng-Wei Huang, Kenneth M. Hughes, Kamran Hussain, Gert Huetsi, Antonio Iovino, Maria-Catalina Isfan, Gregor Janson, Peter Jeglic, Philippe Jetzer, Yijun Jiang, Gediminas Juzeliunas, Wilhelm Kaenders, Matti Kalliokoski, Alex Kehagias, Eva Kilian, Carsten Klempt, Peter Knight, Soumen Koley, Bernd Konrad, Tim Kovachy, Markus Krutzik, Mukesh Kumar, Pradeep Kumar, Hamza Labiad, Shau-Yu Lan, Arnaud Landragin, Greg Landsberg, Mehdi Langlois, Bryony Lanigan, Christophe Le Poncin-Lafitte, Samuel Lellouch, Bruno Leone, Marek Lewicki, Yu-Hung Lien, Lucas Lombriser, Elias Lopez Asamar, J. Luis Lopez-Gonzalez, Adam Lowe, Chen Lu, Giuseppe Gaetano Luciano, Nathan Lundblad, Cristian de J. Lpez Monjaraz, Maena Mackoit-Sinkeviien, Michele Maggiore, Anirban Majumdar, Konstantinos Makris, Azadeh Maleknejad, Anna L. Marchant, Agnese Mariotti, Christos Markou, Barnaby Matthews, Anupam Mazumdar, Christopher McCabe, Matthias Meister, Giorgio Mentasti, Jonathan Menu, Giuseppe Messineo, Bernd Meyer-Hoppe, Salvatore Micalizio, Federica Migliaccio, Peter Millington, Milan Milosevic, Abhay Mishra, Jeremiah Mitchell, Gavin W. Morley, Noam Mouelle, Juergen Mueller, David Newbold, Wei-Tou Ni, Christian Niehof, Johannes Noller, Senad Odzak, Daniel K. L. Oi, Andreas Oikonomou, Yasser Omar, Chris Overstreet, Julia Pahl, Sean Paling, Zhongyin Pan, George Pappas, Vinay Pareek, Elizabeth Pasatembou, Mauro Paternostro, Vishal K. Pathak, Emanuele Pelucchi, Franck Pereira dos Santos, Achim Peters, Annie Pichery, Igor Pikovski, Apostolos Pilaftsis, Florentina-Crenguta Pislan, Robert Plunkett, Rosa Poggiani, Marco Prevedelli, Vishnupriya Puthiya Veettil, Johann Rafelski, Juhan Raidal, Martti Raidal, Ernst Maria Rasel, Sebastien Renaux-Petel, Andrea Richaud, Pedro Rivero-Antunez, Tangui Rodzinka, Albert Roura, Jan Rudolph, Dylan Sabulsky, Marianna S. Safronova, Mairi Sakellariadou, Leonardo Salvi, Muhammed Sameed, Sumit Sarkar, Patrik Schach, Stefan Alaric Schaeffer, Jesse Schelfhout, Manuel Schilling, Vladimir Schkolnik, Wolfgang P. Schleich, Dennis Schlippert, Ulrich Schneider, Florian Schreck, Ariel Schwartzman, Nico Schwersenz, Olga Sergijenko, Haifa Rejeb Sfar, Lijing Shao, Ian Shipsey, Jing Shu, Yeshpal Singh, Carlos F. Sopuerta, Marianna Sorba, Fiodor Sorrentino, Alessandro D. A. M Spallicci, Petruta Stefanescu, Nikolaos Stergioulas, Daniel Stoerk, Jannik Stroehle, Hrudya Thaivalappil Sunilkumar, Zoie Tam, Dhruv Tandon, Yijun Tang, Dorothee Tell, Jacques Tempere, Dylan J. Temples, Rohit P Thampy, Ingmari C. Tietje, Guglielmo M. Tino, Jonathan N. Tinsley, Ovidiu Tintareanu Mircea, Kimberly Tkalec, Andrew J. Tolley, Vincenza Tornatore, Alejandro Torres-Orjuela, Philipp Treutlein, Andrea Trombettoni, Christian Ufrecht, Juan Urrutia, Tristan Valenzuela, Linda R. Valerio, Maurits van der Grinten, Ville Vaskonen, Veronica Vazquez-Aceves, Hardi Veermae, Flavio Vetrano, Nikolay V. Vitanov, Wolf von Klitzing, Sebastian Wald, Thomas Walker, Reinhold Walser, Jin Wang, Yan Wang, C. A. Weidner, Andr Wenzlawski, Michael Werner, Lisa Woerner, Mohamed E. Yahia, Efe Yazgan, Emmanuel Zambrini Cruzeiro, M. Zarei, Mingsheng Zhan, Shengnan Zhang, Lin Zhou, Erik Zupanic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal dilepton polarization and dynamics of the QCD plasma in relativistic heavy-ion collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15052v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the first theoretical study of the polarization of lepton pairs produced in $\sqrts = 5.02 $ TeV Pb+Pb collisions at the LHC, using next-to-leading order (NLO) dilepton emission rates. These calculations employ a multi-stage framework to simulate the evolution of relativistic heavy-ion collisions, and to explore the sensitivity of polarization to early times. It is found that the intermediate invariant-mass dileptons are indeed probes of the thermal equilibration process, and go beyond the reach of hadronic observables. We compute the polarization anisotropy coefficient obtained with LO dilepton rates, and show that the LO and NLO results differ radically, both in trend and in magnitude, at low and intermediate lepton pair invariant masses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15052v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiang-Yu Wu, Han Gao, Bailey Forster, Charles Gale, Greg Jackson, Sangyong Jeon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Composite Dark Energy and the Cosmological Tensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15124</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15124v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The standard cosmological model currently in force, aka $\Lambda$CDM, has been plagued with a variety of tensions in the last decade or so, which puts it against the wall. At the core of the $\Lambda$CDM we have a rigid cosmological term, $\Lambda$, for the entire cosmic history. Recently, the results from the DESI collaboration suggested the possibility that dark energy (DE) should be dynamical rather than just a cosmological constant. Using a generic $w_0w_a$CDM parameterization, DESI favors quintessence behavior at $\sim 3\sigma$ c.l. However, to alleviate the tensions the DE needs more features. In the proposed $w$XCDM model of [43] the DE is actually a composite cosmic fluid with two components $(X,Y)$ acting sequentially: first $X$ (above a transition redshift $z_t$) and second $Y$ (below $z_t$). Fitting the model to the data, we find that the late component $Y$ behaves as quintessence, like DESI. However, to cure the $H_0$ and growth tensions, $X$ must behave as `phantom matter' (PM), which in contrast to phantom DE provides positive pressure at the expense of negative energy density. Using the SNIa (considering separately Pantheon$+$ and DESY5), cosmic chronometers, transversal BAO, LSS data, and the full CMB likelihood from Planck 2018, we find that both tensions can be completely cut down. We also compare the $w$XCDM with our own results using the standard $w$CDM and $w_0w_a$CDM parameterizations of the DE. In all cases, model $w$XCDM performs much better. Finally, we have repeated our analysis with BAO 3D data (replacing BAO 2D), and we still find that the dynamical DE models (including composite ones) provide a much better fit quality compared to $\Lambda$CDM. The growth tension is alleviated again, but in contrast, the $H_0$-tension remains significant, which is most likely reminiscent of the internal conflict in the BAO sector.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15124v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adria G\'omez-Valent, Joan Sol\`a Peracaula</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supernovae evidence for foundational change to cosmological models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15143v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a new, cosmologically model-independent, statistical analysis of the Pantheon+ type Ia supernovae spectroscopic dataset, improving a standard methodology adopted by Lane et al. We use the Tripp equation for supernova standardisation alone, thereby avoiding any potential correlation in the stretch and colour distributions. We compare the standard homogeneous cosmological model, i.e., $\Lambda$CDM, and the timescape cosmology which invokes backreaction of inhomogeneities. Timescape, while statistically homogeneous and isotropic, departs from average Friedmann-Lema\^{\i}tre-Robertson-Walker evolution, and replaces dark energy by kinetic gravitational energy and its gradients, in explaining independent cosmological observations. When considering the entire Pantheon+ sample, we find very strong evidence ($\ln B&gt; 5$) in favour of timescape over $\Lambda$CDM. Furthermore, even restricting the sample to redshifts beyond any conventional scale of statistical homogeneity, $z &gt; 0.075$, timescape is preferred over $\Lambda$CDM with $\ln B&gt; 1$. These results provide evidence for a need to revisit the foundations of theoretical and observational cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15143v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnrasl/slae112</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>MNRAS Letters 537 (2025) L55</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Antonia Seifert, Zachary G. Lane, Marco Galoppo, Ryan Ridden-Harper, David L. Wiltshire</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial Gravitational Wave Probes of Non-Standard Thermal Histories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15144v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Primordial gravitational waves propagate almost unimpeded from the moment they are generated to the present epoch. Nevertheless, they are subject to convolution with a non-trivial transfer function. Within the standard thermal history, shifts in the temperature-redshift relation combine with damping effects by free streaming neutrinos to non-trivially process different wavelengths during radiation domination, with subsequently negligible effects at later times. Presuming a nearly scale invariant primordial spectrum, one obtains a characteristic late time spectrum, deviations from which would indicate departures from the standard thermal history. Given the paucity of probes of the early universe physics before nucleosynthesis, it is useful to classify how deviations from the standard thermal history of the early universe can be constrained from observations of the late time stochastic background. The late time spectral density has a plateau at high frequencies that can in principle be significantly enhanced or suppressed relative to the standard thermal history depending on the equation of state of the epoch intervening reheating and the terminal phase of radiation domination, imprinting additional features from bursts of entropy production, and additional damping at intermediate scales via anisotropic stress production. In this paper, we survey phenomenologically motivated scenarios of early matter domination, kination, and late time decaying particles as representative non-standard thermal histories, elaborate on their late time stochastic background, and discuss constraints on different model scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15144v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Annet Konings, Mariia Marinichenko, Oleksii Mikulenko, Subodh P. Patil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Waves From Dark Binaries With Finite-Range Dark Forces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15158v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper calculates the stochastic gravitational wave background from dark binaries with finite-range attractive dark forces, complementing previous works which consider long-range dark forces. The finiteness of the dark force range can dramatically modify both the initial distributions and evolution histories of the binaries. The generated gravitational wave spectrum is enhanced in the intermediate frequency regime and exhibits interesting "knee" and "ankle" features, the most common of which is related to the turn on of the dark force mediator radiation. Other such spectral features are related to changes in the binary merger lifetime and the probability distribution for the initial binary separation. The stochastic gravitational wave background from sub-solar-mass dark binaries is detectable by both space- and ground-based gravitational wave observatories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15158v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Bai, Sida Lu, Nicholas Orlofsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capturing the Page Curve and Entanglement Dynamics of Black Holes in Quantum Computers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15180v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Understanding the Page curve and resolving the black hole information puzzle in terms of the entanglement dynamics of black holes has been a key question in fundamental physics. In principle, the current quantum computing can provide insights into the entanglement dynamics of black holes within some simplified models. In this regard, we utilize quantum computers to investigate the entropy of Hawking radiation using the qubit transport model, a toy qubit model of black hole evaporation. Specifically, we implement the quantum simulation of the scrambling dynamics in black holes using an efficient random unitary circuit. Furthermore, we employ the swap-based many-body interference protocol for the first time and the randomized measurement protocol to measure the entanglement entropy of Hawking radiation qubits in IBM's superconducting quantum computers. Our findings indicate that while both entanglement entropy measurement protocols accurately estimate the R\'enyi entropy in numerical simulation, the randomized measurement protocol has a particular advantage over the swap-based many-body interference protocol in IBM's superconducting quantum computers. Finally, by incorporating quantum error mitigation techniques, we establish that the current quantum computers are robust tools for measuring the entanglement entropy of complex quantum systems and can probe black hole dynamics within simplified toy qubit models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15180v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Talal Ahmed Chowdhury, Kwangmin Yu, Muhammad Asaduzzaman, Raza Sabbir Sufian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Golden Probe of the Top Yukawa</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1505.01168</link>
      <description>arXiv:1505.01168v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We perform a preliminary study of the ability of the Higgs decay to four leptons to shed light on the top quark Yukawa couplings. In particular we examine whether the $h\to 4\ell$ `golden channel' is sensitive to the $CP$ properties of the top quark couplings to the Higgs boson. We show that kinematic distributions are sensitive to interference of the next-to-leading order electroweak corrections with the tree level $ZZ$ contribution. This translates into a sensitivity to the top quark Yukawa couplings such that meaningful constraints on their $CP$ properties can begin to be obtained once $\sim 300$ fb$^{-1}$ of data has been collected at $\sim 14$ TeV, with significant improvements at higher luminosity or with a higher energy hadron collider. This makes the $h\to4\ell$ channel a useful probe of the top quark Yukawa couplings that is qualitatively different from already established searches in $h\to V\gamma$ two body decays, $tth$, and $gg\to h$. We also briefly discuss other potential possibilities for probing the top Yukawa $CP$ properties in $h\to2\ell\gamma$ and $\ell^+\ell^-\to h Z, h\gamma$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1505.01168v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.92.053003</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 92, 053003 (2015)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yi Chen, Daniel Stolarski, Roberto Vega-Morales</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Muon $g-2$ Anomaly from Vector-like Leptons in a 2-Higgs-doublet + Scalar Singlet Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.05566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.05566v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We revisit an economical model for the $g-2$ anomaly featuring a vector-like charged fermion, a scalar doublet and a scalar singlet in the light of new results from Fermilab. The phenomenological implications for lepton-flavor universality, Higgs decays, and charged lepton-flavor violating decays are discussed in detail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.05566v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-024-13617-5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The European Physical Journal C, Volume 84, article number 1254, (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tim Brune, Thomas W. Kephart, Heinrich P\"as</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Repercussions of the Peccei-Quinn axion on QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.08310</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.08310v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The axion, originally postulated by Peccei and Quinn to solve the strong CP problem, has become of great interest in particle and astroparticle phenomenology. Yet it has a problem. It is widely assumed that the axion leaves the nonperturbative features of QCD unscathed. This is, however, not the case. On the contrary, the axion extension is found to be in conflict with seminal results on the low-energy properties of QCD. The key is that the anomalous coupling of the axion to the gauge bosons can be integrated out, leaving behind a path integral over topologically trivial gauge potentials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.08310v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gerrit Schierholz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter (H)eats Young Planets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.02495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.02495v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the effect of dark matter annihilation on the formation of Jovian planets. We show that dark matter heat injections can slow or halt Kelvin-Helmholtz contraction, preventing the accretion of hydrogen and helium onto the solid core. The existence of Jupiter in our solar system can therefore be used to infer constraints on dark matter with relatively strong interaction cross sections. We derive novel constraints on the cross section for both spin-dependent and spin-independent dark matter. We highlight the possibility of a positive detection using future observations by JWST, which could reveal strongly varying planet morpholoiges close to our Galactic Center.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.02495v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2024/11/046</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 11 (2024), 046</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Djuna Croon, Juri Smirnov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study of two-body doubly charmful baryonic $B$ decays with $SU(3)$ flavor symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.16919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.16919v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Within the framework of $SU(3)$ flavor symmetry, we investigate two-body doubly charmful baryonic $B\to{\bf B}_c\bar{\bf B}'_c$ decays, where ${\bf B}_c\bar{\bf B}'_c$ represents the anti-triplet charmed dibaryon. We determine the $SU(3)_f$ amplitudes and calculate ${\cal B}(B^-\to \Xi_c^0\bar \Xi_c^-)=(3.4^{+1.0}_{-0.9})\times 10^{-5}$ and ${\cal B}(\bar B^0_s\to \Lambda_c^+\bar \Xi_c^-)=(3.9^{+1.2}_{-1.0})\times 10^{-5}$ induced by the single $W$-emission configuration. We find that the $W$-exchange amplitude, previously neglected in studies, needs to be taken into account. It can cause a destructive interfering effect with the $W$-emission amplitude, alleviating the significant discrepancy between the theoretical estimation and experimental data for ${\cal B}(\bar B^0\to\Lambda_c^+\bar\Lambda_c^-)$. To test other interfering decay channels, we calculate ${\cal B}(\bar B^0_s\to \Xi_c^{0(+)}\bar \Xi_c^{0(+)})=(3.0^{+1.4}_{-1.1})\times 10^{-4}$ and ${\cal B}(\bar B^0\to \Xi_c^0\bar \Xi_c^0)=(1.5^{+0.7}_{-0.6})\times 10^{-5}$. We estimate non-zero branching fractions for the pure $W$-exchange decay channels, specifically ${\cal B}(\bar B^0_s\to \Lambda_c^+\bar \Lambda_c^-)=(8.1^{+1.7}_{-1.5})\times 10^{-5}$ and ${\cal B}(\bar B^0\to \Xi_c^+\bar \Xi_c^-)=(3.0\pm 0.6)\times 10^{-6}$. Additionally, we predict ${\cal B}(B^+_c\to \Xi_c^+\bar \Xi_c^0)=(2.8^{+0.9}_{-0.7})\times 10^{-4}$ and ${\cal B}(B^+_c\to \Lambda_c^+\bar \Xi_c^0)=(1.6^{+0.5}_{-0.4})\times 10^{-5}$, which are accessible to experimental facilities such as LHCb.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.16919v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP11(2023)117</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP11, 117 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Kuo Hsiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Algebraic Roadmap of Particle Theories, Part I: General construction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.12377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.12377v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Expanding the results of [1], [2], [3], we demonstrate a network of algebraic connections between six well-known particle theories. These are the Spin(10) model, the Georgi-Glashow model, the Pati-Salam model, the Left-Right Symmetric model, the Standard Model both pre- and post-Higgs mechanism.
  A new inclusion of a quaternionic reflection within the network further differentiates $W^{\pm}$ bosons from the $Z^0$ boson in comparison to the Standard Model. It may introduce subtle new considerations for the phenomenology of electroweak symmetry breaking.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.12377v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. Furey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum entanglement and Bell inequality violation at colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.07972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.07972v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The study of entanglement in particle physics has been gathering pace in the past few years. It is a new field that is providing important results about the possibility of detecting entanglement and testing Bell inequality at colliders for final states as diverse as top-quark, $\tau$-lepton pairs and $\Lambda$-baryons, massive gauge bosons and vector mesons. In this review, after presenting definitions, tools and basic results that are necessary for understanding these developments, we summarize the main findings -- as published by the beginning of year 2024 -- including analyses of experimental data in $B$ meson decays and top-quark pair production. We include a detailed discussion of the results for both qubit and qutrits systems, that is, final states containing spin one-half and spin one particles. Entanglement has also been proposed as a new tool to constrain new particles and fields beyond the Standard Model and we introduce the reader to this promising feature as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.07972v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alan J. Barr, Marco Fabbrichesi, Roberto Floreanini, Emidio Gabrielli, Luca Marzola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information divergences to parametrize astrophysical uncertainties in dark matter direct detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04959v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Astrophysical uncertainties in dark matter direct detection experiments are typically addressed by parametrizing the velocity distribution in terms of a few uncertain parameters that vary around some central values. Here we propose a method to optimize over all velocity distributions lying within a given distance measure from a central distribution. We discretize the dark matter velocity distribution as a superposition of streams, and use a variety of information divergences to parametrize its uncertainties. With this, we bracket the limits on the dark matter-nucleon and dark matter-electron scattering cross sections, when the true dark matter velocity distribution deviates from the commonly assumed Maxwell-Boltzmann form. The methodology pursued is general and could be applied to other physics scenarios where a given physical observable depends on a function that is uncertain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04959v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gonzalo Herrera, Andreas Rappelt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collider imprint of vector-like leptons in light of anomalous magnetic moment and neutrino data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11862v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the impact of incorporating vector-like leptons into the Standard Model, aiming to address longstanding puzzles related to the anomalous magnetic moments of the muon and electron while maintaining consistency with neutrino masses and mixings. We find that among the various representations of vector-like leptons permitted by the Standard Model gauge symmetry, only weak doublets and singlets offer satisfactory solutions, all associated with a significantly constrained parameter space. Our analysis delves into the associated parameter space, identifying representative benchmark scenarios suitable for collider studies. These setups yield a distinctive six-lepton signature whose associated signals can easily be distinguished from the Standard Model background, providing a clear signal indicative of new physics models featuring vector-like leptons. Our work hence sheds light on the potential implications of vector-like leptons in resolving discrepancies inherent to the Standard Model, while also offering insights into experimental avenues for further exploration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11862v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-024-13659-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. C 84, 1284 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Parham Dehghani, Mariana Frank, Benjamin Fuks</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nucleon Consumption and Mass-Energy Conversion Induced by Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00445v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose the nucleon consumption induced by dark matter (DM) as a new scenario to overcome the energy threshold of direct detection. It can be realized with proton ($\chi + p \rightarrow \chi + \ell^+$) or neutron ($\chi + n \rightarrow \chi + \nu$) target. Both effective operators and concrete models are provided to illustrate the idea. Since the initial DM and nucleon velocity is only $10^{-3}$ and $1/4$ of the speed of light, respectively, the cross section and hence event rate are determined by the involved particle masses and not affected by the nucleon Fermi motion. Of the two realizations, the proton consumption has richer phenomena with both charged lepton and the daughter nuclei de-excitation to allow double or even triple coincidence to significantly suppress the background. We also illustrate the projected sensitivities at DM and neutrino experiments such as PandaX-4T, DUNE, JUNO, and Hyper-K.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00445v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shao-Feng Ge, Xiao-Dong Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global analysis of fragmentation functions to charged hadrons with high-precision data from the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04422v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Fragmentation functions (FFs) are essential non-perturbative QCD inputs for predicting hadron production cross sections in high energy scatterings. In this study, we present a joint determination of FFs for light charged hadrons through a global analysis at next-to-leading order (NLO) in QCD. Our analysis incorporates a wide range of precision measurements from the LHC, as well as data from electron-positron collisions and semi-inclusive deep inelastic scatterings. By including measurements of jet fragmentation at the LHC in our global analysis, we are able to impose strong constraints on the gluon FFs. A careful selection of hadron kinematics is applied to ensure the validity of factorization and perturbative calculations of QCD. In addition, we introduce several methodological advances in fitting, resulting in a flexible parametrization form and the inclusion of theoretical uncertainties from perturbative calculations. Our best-fit predictions show very good agreement with the global data, with $\chi^2/N_{pt}\sim 0.90$. We also generate a large number of Hessian error sets to estimate uncertainties and correlations of the extracted FFs. FFs to charged pions (kaons and protons) are well constrained for momentum fractions down to 0.01 (0.1). Total momentum of partons carried by light charged hadrons are determined precisely. Their values for $u$, $d$ quarks and gluon saturate at about 50\% for a lower cut of the momentum fraction of 0.01. Pulls from individual datasets and impact of various choices of the analysis are also studied in details. Additionally, we present an update of the FMNLO program used for calculating hadron production cross sections. Our FFs, including the error sets (denoted as NPC23), are publicly available in the form of LHAPDF6 grids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04422v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.114019</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jun Gao, ChongYang Liu, XiaoMin Shen, Hongxi Xing, Yuxiang Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dispersive determination of the fourth generation lepton masses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07813v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We continue our previous determination of the masses of the sequential fourth generation quarks in an extension of the Standard Model, and predict the mass $m_4$ ($m_L$) of the fourth generation neutrino $\nu_4$ (charged lepton $L$) by solving the dispersion relation associated with heavy fermion decays. The results $m_4\approx 170$ GeV and $m_L\approx 270$ GeV are extracted from the dispersive analyses of the $t\to d e^+\nu_4$ and $L^-\to \nu_1 \bar t d$ decay widths, respectively, where $t$ ($d$, $e^+$, $\nu_1$) denotes a top quark (down quark, positron, light neutrino). The predictions are cross-checked by examining the $L^-\to \nu_4 \bar u d$ decay, $\bar u$ being an anti-up quark. It is shown that the fourth generation leptons with the above masses survive the current experimental bounds from Higgs boson decays into photon pairs and from the oblique parameters. We also revisit how the existence of the fourth generation leptons impacts the dispersive constraints on the neutrino masses and the Pontecorvo-Maki-Nakagawa-Sakata (PMNS) matrix elements. It is found that the unitarity of the $3\times 3$ PMNS matrix holds well up to corrections of $O(m_\nu^2/m_W^2)$, $m_\nu$ ($m_W$) being a light neutrino (the $W$ boson) mass, whose mixing angles and $CP$ phase prefer the values $\theta_{12}\approx 34^\circ$, $\theta_{23}\approx 47^\circ$, $\theta_{13}\approx 5^\circ$ and $\delta\approx 200^\circ$ in the normal-ordering scenario for neutrino masses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07813v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hsiang-nan Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing exotic long-lived particles from the prompt side using the CONTUR method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18710v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A method to derive constraints on new physics models featuring exotic long-lived particles using detector-corrected measurements of prompt states is presented. The CONTUR workflow is modified to either account for the fraction of long-lived particles which decay early enough to be reconstructed as prompt, or to be sensitive to the recoil of such particles against a prompt system. This makes it possible to determine how many of signal events would be selected in the RIVET routines which encapsulate the fiducial regions of dozens of measurements of Standard Model processes by the ATLAS and CMS collaborations. New constraints are set on several popular exotic long-lived particle models in the very short-lifetime or very long-lifetime regimes, which are often poorly covered by direct searches. The probed models include feebly-interacting dark matter, hidden sector models mediated by a heavy neutral scalar, dark photon models and a model featuring photo-phobic axion-like particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18710v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louie Corpe, Andreas Goudelis, Simon Jeannot, Si Hyun Jeon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Charm Yukawa Coupling through $ch$ Associated Production at the Hadron Colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19797</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19797v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: At present, the study of the charm-quark Yukawa coupling at the Large Hadron Collider mainly focuses on the Higgs decay processes. Such signal suffers from overwhelming QCD background and derives its sensitivity primarily from the $Vh$ associated production channel. In addition, sensitivity to a possible CP phase in charm-quark Yukawa at the hadron collider is not discussed. We investigate the charm-Higgs associated production signal, that contains a potentially detectable interference term between $cch$ Yukawa coupling mediated diagrams and $ggh$ coupling mediated diagram. Such interference term is sensitive to the relative CP phase between contributing diagrams. High dimensional kinematic information are exploited by machine learning techniques to separate the different contribution, and sensitivity on the coupling is derived. Assuming a real $\kappa_c$ modification framework, 1$\sigma$ bound of $-5.6 &lt; \kappa_c &lt; 5.6$ (HL-LHC) and $-1.51 &lt; \kappa_c &lt; 1.62$ (FCC) are achieved. When allowing for CP-phase in the charm Yukawa, a combined 1$\sigma$ bound of $0.32&lt;|\kappa_c|&lt;1.69$, $-77^\circ &lt; \alpha &lt; 77^\circ$ (HL-LHC) and $0.70&lt;|\kappa_c|&lt;1.29$, $-55^\circ &lt; \alpha &lt; 55^\circ$ (FCC) can be achieved on the magnitude and CP phase of the coupling respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19797v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nuoyu Dong, Hongsheng Hou, Zhuoni Qian, Bowen Wang, Qingjun Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining Light QCD Axions with Isolated Neutron Star Cooling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07740v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The existence of light QCD axions, whose mass depends on an additional free parameter, can lead to a new ground state of matter, where the sourced axion field reduces the nucleon effective mass. The presence of the axion field has structural consequences, in particular, it results in a thinner (or even prevents its existence) heat-blanketing envelope, significantly altering the cooling patterns of neutron stars. We exploit the anomalous cooling behavior to constrain previously uncharted regions of the axion parameter space by comparing model predictions with existing data from isolated neutron stars. Notably, this analysis does not require the light QCD axion to be the dark matter candidate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07740v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.251002</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.Lett.133:251002,2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Antonio G\'omez-Ba\~n\'on, Kai Bartnick, Konstantin Springmann, Jos\'e A. Pons</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarization effects in the elastic $e \vec p \to \vec e p$ and $\vec e \vec p \to e p$ processes in the case of parallel spins</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.09249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.09249v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the one-photon exchange approximation, we analyze polarization effects in the elastic $\vec e \vec p \to e p$ and $ e \vec p \to \vec e p$ processes in the case when the spin quantization axes of a target proton at rest and an incident or scattered electron are parallel. To do this, in the kinematics of the SANE Collaboration experiment, using the J. Kelly and I. Qattan parametrizations for the Sachs form factor ratio $R\equiv \mu_p G_E/G_M$, a numerical analysis was carried out of the dependence of the longitudinal polarization degree transferred to the scattered electron in the $e \vec p \to \vec e p$ process and double spin asymmetry in the $\vec e \vec p \to e p$ process on the square of the momentum transferred to the proton as well as on the scattering angle of the electron. It is established that the difference in the longitudinal polarization degree of the scattered electron in the $ e \vec p \to \vec e p$ process in the case of conservation and violation of the scaling of the Sachs form factors can reach 70 \%. This fact can be used to set up polarization experiments of a new type to measure the ratio $R$. For double spin asymmetry in the $\vec e \vec p \to e p$ process, the corresponding difference does not exceed 2.32 \%. This fact means that it's not sensitive to the effects of the Sachs form factor scaling violation and could be used as test for the $R\approx 1$ equality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.09249v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. V. Galynskii, V. V. Bytev, V. M. Galynsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultralight dark matter detection with levitated ferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15330v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Levitated ferromagnets act as ultraprecise magnetometers, which can exhibit high quality factors due to their excellent isolation from the environment. These instruments can be utilized in searches for ultralight dark matter candidates, such as axionlike dark matter or dark-photon dark matter. In addition to being sensitive to an axion-photon coupling or kinetic mixing, which produce physical magnetic fields, ferromagnets are also sensitive to the effective magnetic field (or "axion wind") produced by an axion-electron coupling. While the dynamics of a levitated ferromagnet in response to a DC magnetic field have been well studied, all of these couplings would produce AC fields. In this work, we study the response of a ferromagnet to an applied AC magnetic field and use these results to project their sensitivity to axion and dark-photon dark matter. We pay special attention to the direction of motion induced by an applied AC field, in particular, whether it precesses around the applied field (similar to an electron spin) or librates in the plane of the field (similar to a compass needle). We show that existing levitated ferromagnet setups can already have comparable sensitivity to an axion-electron coupling as comagnetometer or torsion balance experiments. In addition, future setups can become sensitive probes of axion-electron coupling, dark-photon kinetic mixing, and axion-photon coupling, for ultralight dark matter masses $m_\mathrm{DM}\lesssim\mathrm{feV}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15330v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.115029</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 115029 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Saarik Kalia, Dmitry Budker, Derek F. Jackson Kimball, Wei Ji, Zhen Liu, Alexander O. Sushkov, Chris Timberlake, Hendrik Ulbricht, Andrea Vinante, Tao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Far-from-equilibrium attractors in kinetic theory with two different relaxation times</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18566v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We solve a Boltzmann equation for massless quark and gluon fluids in a transversally homogeneous, longitudinally boost-invariant expansion. Quarks can be out of chemical equilibrium and the relaxation times of the two species are assumed to be connected by Casimir scaling. We numerically calculate moments of the distribution functions, identifying their early- and late-time attractors and reconstructing also the full distributions. These attractors appear when the system is still far from local thermalization, before hydrodynamics traditionally would be expected to apply. We also analyze the evolution of entropy production for different initial momentum anisotropies and quark abundances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18566v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ferdinando Frasc\`a, Andrea Beraudo, Michael Strickland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Truth, beauty, and goodness in grand unification: a machine learning approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06718</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06718v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the flavour sector of the supersymmetric $SU(5)$ Grand Unified Theory (GUT) model using machine learning techniques. The minimal $SU(5)$ model is known to predict fermion masses that disagree with observed values in nature. There are two well-known approaches to address this issue: one involves introducing a 45-representation Higgs field, while the other employs a higher-dimensional operator involving the 24-representation GUT Higgs field. We compare these two approaches by numerically optimising a loss function, defined as the ratio of determinants of mass matrices. Our findings indicate that the 24-Higgs approach achieves the observed fermion masses with smaller modifications to the original minimal $SU(5)$ model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06718v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shinsuke Kawai, Nobuchika Okada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-component secluded WIMP dark matter and Dirac neutrino masses with an extra Abelian gauge symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02027v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Scenarios for secluded WIMP dark matter models have been extensively studied in simplified versions. This paper shows a complete UV realization of a secluded WIMP dark matter model with an extra Abelian gauge symmetry that includes two-component dark matter candidates, where the dark matter conversion process plays a significant role in determining the relic density in the Universe. The model contains two new unstable mediators: a dark Higgs and a dark photon. It generates Dirac neutrino masses and can be tested in future direct detection experiments of dark matter. The model is also compatible with cosmological and theoretical constraints, including the branching ratio of Standard model particles into invisible, Big Bang nucleosynthesis restrictions, and the number of relativistic degrees of freedom in the early Universe, even without kinetic mixing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02027v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kimy Agudelo, Diego Restrepo, Andr\'es Rivera, David Suarez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extended Poincare Symmetry Dictates Massive Scattering Amplitudes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03762v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We identify an extended Poincare symmetry $ISO(2) \times ISO(3,1)$ for on-shell massive scattering amplitudes, transforming under the $U(2)$ Little group symmetry. Thus the one-particle state involves in both spin and transversality $t$ (related to chirality), and the spin-spinors are extended to the spin-transverality spinors. The massive spin-$s$ spinors with different transversality can be related by the $SO(5,1)$ symmetry, although the $U(2)$ Little group breaks the symmetry explicitly. The three-point massive amplitudes can be fully determined from the $T^\pm$ and $m$ generators, diagrammatically denoted as the mass insertion and chirality flip, which provide correspondence between massless ultraviolet and massive chiral-eigenstate amplitudes. Thus the massless on-shell technique can be utilized to construct higher-point tree- and loop-level massive amplitudes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03762v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Han Ni, Yi-Ning Wang, Chao Wu, Jiang-Hao Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Encyclopaedia Inflationaris</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1303.3787</link>
      <description>arXiv:1303.3787v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The current flow of high accuracy astrophysical data, among which are the Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) measurements by the Planck satellite, offers an unprecedented opportunity to constrain the inflationary theory. This is however a challenging project given the size of the inflationary landscape which contains hundreds of different scenarios. Given that there is currently no observational evidence for primordial non-Gaussianities, isocurvature perturbations or any other non-minimal extension of the inflationary paradigm, a reasonable approach is to consider the simplest models first, namely the slow-roll single field models with minimal kinetic terms. This still leaves us with a very populated landscape, the exploration of which requires new and efficient strategies. It has been customary to tackle this problem by means of approximate model independent methods while a more ambitious alternative is to study the inflationary scenarios one by one. We have developed the publicly available runtime library ASPIC to implement this last approach. The ASPIC code provides all routines needed to quickly derive reheating-consistent observable predictions within this class of scenarios. ASPIC has been designed as an evolutive code which presently supports 118 different models. In this paper, for each of the ASPIC models, we present and collect new results in a systematic manner, thereby constituting the first Encyclopaedia Inflationaris.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1303.3787v5</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.dark.2014.01.003 10.1016/j.dark.2024.101653</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Dark Univ. 5-6 (2014) 75-235; Phys.Dark Univ. 46 (2024) 101653</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jerome Martin, Christophe Ringeval, Vincent Vennin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of the pre-equilibrium phase for the determination of nuclear geometry in high-energy isobar collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.03703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.03703v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Ultrarelativistic isobar collisions have been proposed as a useful tool to investigate nuclear structure. These systems are not created in equilibrium, rather undergo a pre-thermalization stage. In this stage, some of the initial structure information may be lost and additional effects introduced. The objective of this paper is to study this possibility in the extreme case of a "free-streaming" pre-equilibrium stage. We do this by computing estimators for ratios of various measured (or measurable) quantities (elliptic and triangular flows, mean transverse momentum and associated cumulants, correlators between elliptic or triangular flows and mean transverse momentum, symmetric cumulant and two-plane correlator) and study their sensitivity to the duration of the free-streaming stage. We find that the correlators between elliptic or triangular flows and mean transverse momentum, the so-called $\rho_2$ and $\rho_3$, are indeed sensitive to the duration of the free-streaming stage and that the normalized symmetric cumulant, $\varepsilon NSC(2,3)$ might also depend on this duration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.03703v4</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevC.110.064907</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review C, vol. 110, no. 6, p. 064907, Dec. 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fernando G. Gardim, Andr\'e V. Giannini, Fr\'ed\'erique Grassi, Kevin P. Pala, Willian M. Serenone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interacting Dark Energy after DESI Baryon Acoustic Oscillation measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15232</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15232v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the implications of the Baryon Acoustic Oscillations measurement released by the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) for Interacting Dark Energy (IDE) models characterized by an energy-momentum flow from Dark Matter to Dark Energy. By combining Planck-2018 and DESI data, we observe a preference for interactions, leading to a non-vanishing interaction rate $\xi=-0.32^{+0.18}_{-0.14}$, which results in a present-day expansion rate $H_0=70.8^{+1.4}_{-1.7}$ km/s/Mpc, reducing the tension with the value provided by the SH0ES collaboration to less than $\sim 1.3 \sigma$. The preference for interactions remains robust when including measurements of the expansion rate $H(z)$ obtained from the relative ages of massive, early-time, and passively-evolving galaxies, as well as when considering distance moduli measurements from Type-Ia Supernovae sourced from the Pantheon-plus catalog using the SH0ES Cepheid host distances as calibrators. Overall, the IDE framework provides an equally good, or better, explanation of both high- and low-redshift background observations compared to $\Lambda$CDM, while also yielding higher $H_0$ values that align more closely with the local distance ladder estimates. However, a limitation of the IDE model is that it predicts lower $\Omega_{m}$ and higher $\sigma_{8}$ values, which may not be fully consistent with large-scale structure data at the perturbation level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15232v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.251003</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>William Giar\`e, Miguel A. Sabogal, Rafael C. Nunes, Eleonora Di Valentino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The CONUS+ experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11912v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The CONUS+ experiment aims to detect coherent elastic neutrino-nucleus scattering (CEvNS) of reactor antineutrinos on germanium nuclei in the fully coherent regime, continuing on this way the CONUS physics program started at the Brokdorf nuclear power plant, Germany. The CONUS+ setup is installed in the nuclear power plant in Leibstadt, Switzerland, at a distance of 20.7 m from the 3.6 GW thermal power reactor core. The CEvNS signature will be measured with the same four point-contact high-purity germanium (HPGe) detectors produced for the former experiment, however refurbished and with optimized low energy thresholds. To suppress the background in the CONUS+ detectors, the passive and active layers of the original CONUS shield were modified such to fit better to the significantly changed background conditions at the new experimental location. New data acquisition and monitoring systems were developed. A direct network connection between the experiment and the Max-Planck-Institut fur Kernphysik (MPIK) makes it possible to control and monitor data acquisition in real time. The impact of all these modifications is discussed with particular emphasis on the resulting CEvNS signal prediction for the first data collection phase of CONUS+. Prospects of the planned upgrade in a second phase integrating new larger HPGe detectors are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11912v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> The CONUS Collaboration, N. Ackermann, S. Armbruster, H. Bonet, C. Buck, K. Fulber, J. Hakenmuller, J. Hempfling, G. Heusser, M. Lindner, W. Maneschg, K. Ni, M. Rank, T. Rink, E. Sanchez Garcia, I. Stalder, H. Strecker, R. Wink, J. Woenckhaus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetric Mass Generation with four SU(2) doublet fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02062v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study a single exactly massless staggered fermion in the fundamental representation of an $SU(2)$ gauge group. We utilize an nHYP-smeared fermion action supplemented with additional heavy Pauli-Villars fields which serve to decrease lattice artifacts. The phase diagram exhibits a clear two-phase structure with a conformal phase at weak coupling and a novel new phase, the Symmetric Mass Generation (SMG) phase, appearing at strong coupling. The SMG phase is confining with all states gapped and chiral symmetry unbroken. Our finite size scaling analysis provides strong evidence that the phase transition between these two phases is continuous, which would allow for the existence of a continuum SMG phase. Furthermore, the RG flows are consistent with a $\beta$-function that vanishes quadratically at the new fixed point suggesting that the $N_f=4$ flavor SU(2) gauge theory lies at the opening of the conformal window.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02062v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nouman Butt, Simon Catterall, Anna Hasenfratz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Energy Spectrum of Non-Newtonian Turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.03150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.03150v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The goal of this paper is to propose a theoretical framework to study homogeneous and isotropic turbulence in a viscoelastic fluid, regarded as a perturbation of a Newtonian incompressible fluid, where the fluid relaxation time, or else the Weissenberg number, plays the role of small parameter. We use a Martin-Siggia-Rose framework to obtain a formal expression for the velocity correlation function of the non-Newtonian flow, and we expand this formal expression to linear order in the relaxation time. The coefficients in this expansion are correlation functions of the base Newtonian flow. We do not derive these correlations, instead we replace them by their values according to K41 theory, which could be regarded as an extreme form of renormalization. While substantial work will be necessary to validate the model against numerical and experimental data, preliminary results are encouraging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.03150v3</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Esteban Calzetta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conditioned quantum-assisted deep generative surrogate for particle-calorimeter interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22870v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Particle collisions at accelerators such as the Large Hadron Collider, recorded and analyzed by experiments such as ATLAS and CMS, enable exquisite measurements of the Standard Model and searches for new phenomena. Simulations of collision events at these detectors have played a pivotal role in shaping the design of future experiments and analyzing ongoing ones. However, the quest for accuracy in Large Hadron Collider (LHC) collisions comes at an imposing computational cost, with projections estimating the need for millions of CPU-years annually during the High Luminosity LHC (HL-LHC) run \cite{collaboration2022atlas}. Simulating a single LHC event with \textsc{Geant4} currently devours around 1000 CPU seconds, with simulations of the calorimeter subdetectors in particular imposing substantial computational demands \cite{rousseau2023experimental}. To address this challenge, we propose a conditioned quantum-assisted deep generative model. Our model integrates a conditioned variational autoencoder (VAE) on the exterior with a conditioned Restricted Boltzmann Machine (RBM) in the latent space, providing enhanced expressiveness compared to conventional VAEs. The RBM nodes and connections are meticulously engineered to enable the use of qubits and couplers on D-Wave's Pegasus-structured \textit{Advantage} quantum annealer (QA) for sampling. We introduce a novel method for conditioning the quantum-assisted RBM using \textit{flux biases}. We further propose a novel adaptive mapping to estimate the effective inverse temperature in quantum annealers. The effectiveness of our framework is illustrated using Dataset 2 of the CaloChallenge \cite{calochallenge}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22870v5</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Quetzalcoatl Toledo-Marin, Sebastian Gonzalez, Hao Jia, Ian Lu, Deniz Sogutlu, Abhishek Abhishek, Colin Gay, Eric Paquet, Roger Melko, Geoffrey C. Fox, Maximilian Swiatlowski, Wojciech Fedorko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mode analysis of Nambu-Goldstone modes in U(1) charged first-order relativistic viscous hydrodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23837v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We conduct a mode analysis of a general U(1)-charged first-order relativistic hydrodynamics within the framework of the effective field theory of dissipative fluids in a Minkowski background. The most general quadratic action for collective excitations around hydrodynamic solutions -- specifically, the Nambu-Goldstone (NG) modes associated with the symmetry-breaking pattern induced by external fields -- is derived. It is found that the hydrodynamical frame invariants write the first-order dispersion relations in the low energy limit. In thermodynamical viscous fluids realized by integrating out fast modes, unitarity and local KMS symmetry for its underlying UV theory are guaranteed. Then, we find that first-order hydrodynamics are stable if the null energy condition is satisfied. As the NG modes nonlinearly realize the diffeomorphism symmetries, our mode analysis is valid in any coordinate systems, including Lorentz-transformed references. We also comment on the causal structure for the diffusive modes based on the retarded Green functions for the stochastic NG mode.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23837v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Atsuhisa Ota</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian evidence for two peaks in the sound speed in cold dense QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08760v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: I show that in addition to the well-known peak inside massive neutron stars, the sound speed in cold dense QCD matter likely exhibits another peak above neutron star densities before it asymptotes to $c_s=\sqrt{C_s}=\sqrt{1/3}$. Based on the framework reported in arxiv:2408.16738, this approach does not rely on any assumption about the ultra-dense matter not realized in nature. Current multimessenger observation of neutron stars favors the two-peak scenario with a Bayes factor $5.1_{-0.7}^{+0.9}$, where the uncertainties are systematics due to models of neutron star inner cores. This evidence grows to $27_{-8}^{+11}$ if the $2.6M_\odot$ component of GW190814 is a neutron star. The trough in $C_s$ separating the two peaks is inferred to be below $0.05^{+0.04}_{-0.02}$ (at the $50\%$ level) if $2.6M_\odot$ neutron stars exist. The second peak above $1/3$ beyond baryon chemical potential $\mu_B=1.6-1.9$ GeV most likely signals non-perturbative effects in cold quark matter, for instance color superconductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08760v3</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dake Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comment on "Sustainability Strategy for the Cool Copper Collider", arXiv:2307.04084</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12236</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12236v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The paper entitled "Sustainability Strategy for the Cool Copper Collider" by M. Breidenbach et al. defines a metric to weigh the electricity consumption and the carbon footprint of future Higgs factory concepts. We show that this metric is flawed in many respects and gives an incorrect representation of reality. We also demonstrates that, irrespective of the drawbacks of this particular estimator, the strategy consisting in using a metric as a multiplicative coefficient of the electricity consumption or the carbon footprint of an ensemble of colliders is fragile at best, and valueless when it comes to arguing in favour of or against such or such future Higgs Factory concept.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12236v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christophe Grojean, Patrick Janot</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
