<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph</link>
    <description>hep-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 05:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbative gravitational wave predictions for the real-scalar extended Standard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08951v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We perform a state-of-the-art study of the cosmological phase transitions of the real-scalar extended Standard Model. We carry out a broad scan of the parameter space of this model at next-to-next-to-leading order in powers of couplings. We use effective field theory to account for the necessary higher-order resummations, and to construct consistent real and gauge-invariant gravitational wave predictions. Our results provide a comprehensive account of the convergence of perturbative predictions for the gravitational wave signals in this model. For the majority of the parameter points in our study, we observe apparent convergence. While leading and next-to-leading order predictions of the gravitational wave amplitude typically suffer from relative errors between $10$ and $10^4$, at next-to-next-to-leading order the typical relative errors are reduced to between $0.5$ and $50$. Nevertheless, for those parameter points predicting the largest signals, potentially observable by future gravitational wave observatories, the validity of the perturbative expansion is in doubt.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08951v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oliver Gould, Paul Saffin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NLO SMEFT Electroweak Corrections to Higgs Decays to 4 Leptons in the Narrow Width Approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08952</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08952v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Some of the most precise measurements of Higgs boson couplings are from the Higgs decays to 4 leptons, where deviations from the Standard Model predictions can be quantified in the framework of the Standard Model Effective Field Theory (SMEFT). In this work, we present a complete next-to-leading order (NLO) SMEFT electroweak calculation of the rate for $H\rightarrow \ell^+\ell^- Z$ which we combine with the NLO SMEFT result for $Z\rightarrow\ell^+\ell^-$ to obtain the NLO rate for the $H\rightarrow$ 4 lepton process in the narrow width approximation. The NLO calculation provides sensitivity to a wide range of SMEFT operators that do not contribute to the rate at lowest order and demonstrates the importance of including correlations between the effects of different operators when extracting limits on SMEFT parameters. We show that the extraction of the Higgs tri-linear coupling from the decay $H\rightarrow \ell^+ \ell^- Z, \ Z\rightarrow \ell^+\ell^-$ in the narrow width approximation strongly depends on the contributions of other operators that first occur at NLO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08952v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sally Dawson, Matthew Forslund, Pier Paolo Giardino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Invisible decays of vector Charmonia and Bottomonia</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09124</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09124v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We compute the branching fractions of vector quarkonia ($V_Q=J/\psi, \psi', \Upsilon(nS)$) decays into neutrino pairs, considering both Dirac and Majorana types, within the Standard Model (SM) and beyond. The vector nature of quarkonium states yields a decay width in the SM that depends upon the weak vector coupling of the heavy quark, offering the possibility to measure the weak mixing angle at the quarkonia mass scales. If neutrinos have non-standard neutral weak couplings, this could help to distinguish the nature of neutrinos in principle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09124v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Hern\'andez-Tom\'e, C. S. Kim, G. L\'opez Castro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing generalization in high energy physics using white-box adversarial attacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09296v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Machine learning is becoming increasingly popular in the context of particle physics. Supervised learning, which uses labeled Monte Carlo (MC) simulations, remains one of the most widely used methods for discriminating signals beyond the Standard Model. However, this paper suggests that supervised models may depend excessively on artifacts and approximations from Monte Carlo simulations, potentially limiting their ability to generalize well to real data. This study aims to enhance the generalization properties of supervised models by reducing the sharpness of local minima. It reviews the application of four distinct white-box adversarial attacks in the context of classifying Higgs boson decay signals. The attacks are divided into weight space attacks, and feature space attacks. To study and quantify the sharpness of different local minima this paper presents two analysis methods: gradient ascent and reduced Hessian eigenvalue analysis. The results show that white-box adversarial attacks significantly improve generalization performance, albeit with increased computational complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09296v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Franck Rothen, Samuel Klein, Matthew Leigh, Tobias Golling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic dipole moments of the singly-heavy baryons with spin-$\frac{1}{2}$ and spin-$\frac{3}{2}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09405v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The electromagnetic characteristics of singly-heavy baryons at low energies are responsive to their internal composition, structural configuration, and the associated chiral dynamics of light diquarks. To gain further insight, experimentalists are attempting to measure the magnetic and electric dipole moments of charm baryons at the LHC. In view of these developments, we conducted an extensive analysis of the magnetic dipole moments of both $\rm{J^P}=\frac{1}{2}^+$ and $\rm{J^P}=\frac{3}{2}^+$ singly-heavy baryons by means of the QCD light-cone sum rules. Our findings have been compared with other phenomenological estimations that could prove a valuable supplementary resource for interpreting the singly-heavy baryon sector. To shed light on the internal structure of these baryons we study the contributions of the individual quark sectors to the magnetic dipole moments. It was observed that the magnetic dipole moments of the spin-$\frac{1}{2}$ sextet singly-heavy baryons are governed by the light quarks. Conversely, the role of the heavy quark is significantly enhanced for the spin-$\frac{1}{2}$ anti-triplet and spin-$\frac{3}{2}$ sextet singly-heavy baryons. The contribution of light and heavy quarks is observed to have an inverse relationship. The signs of the magnetic dipole moments demonstrate the interaction of the spin degrees of freedom of the quarks. The opposing signs of the light and heavy-quark magnetic dipole moments imply that the spins of these quarks are anti-aligned with respect to each other in the baryon. As a byproduct, the electric quadrupole and magnetic octupole moments of spin-$\frac{3}{2}$ singly-heavy baryons are also calculated. We ascertained the existence of non-zero values for the electric quadrupole and magnetic octupole moments of these baryons, indicative of a non-spherical charge distribution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09405v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>U. \"Ozdem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New physics search via angular distribution of $ \bar{B} \to D^* (\to D \pi) \tau (\to \ell \nu_\tau \bar{\nu}_\ell) \bar{\nu}_\tau$ decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09414v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The study of $\bar{B} \to D^* \tau {\bar{\nu}}_\tau$ angular distribution can be used to get information about new physics, which has been motivated by the presence of various $B$ anomalies. However, the inability to measure precisely the three-momentum of tau hinders this process, as the tau decay contains one or more undetected neutrinos. In this work, we present a measurable angular distribution of $\bar{B} \to D^* \tau {\bar{\nu}}_\tau$ by considering the additional decay $\tau \to \ell \nu_\tau \bar{\nu}_\ell$, where $\ell \in \{ e , \mu \}$. The full process used is $\bar{B} \to D^* (\to D \pi) \tau (\to \ell \nu_\tau \bar{\nu}_\ell) \bar{\nu}_\tau$, where only the $\ell$ and $D^*$ are reconstructed, and a fit to the experimental angular distribution of this process can be used to extract information on new physics parameters. To demonstrate, we generate simulated data for this process and perform a sensitivity study to obtain the expected statistical errors on new physics parameters from experiments in the near future. We obtained a sensitivity of the order of 5% for the right-handed current and around 6% for the tensor current. In addition, we use the recent lattice QCD data on $B \to D^*$ form factors and obtain correlations between form factors and new physics parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09414v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bhubanjyoti Bhattacharya, Thomas E. Browder, Alakabha Datta, Tejhas Kapoor, Emi Kou, Lopamudra Mukherjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulation of the process $e^+e^- \rightarrow W^+W^-$ with the heavy right-handed neutrino exchange at 1 TeV future lepton colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09418v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study potential contribution of the heavy right-handed neutrino exchange in the process $e^{+}e^{-} \rightarrow W^{+}W^{-}$. This process is sensitive to heavy neutrinos with masses larger than $\sqrt{s}$. The Monte Carlo simulation of the studied process is performed assuming the Seesaw type-I model, where heavy right-handed neutrinos (heavy neutral leptons, HNL) are introduced in the leptonic sector. Within the Standard Model (SM), the process has a large cross section described by diagrams with $s$-channel $Z / \gamma$ exchange and $t$-channel active neutrino exchange. Respectively, the $t$-channel right-handed neutrino exchange amplitude will interfere with these SM amplitudes. However, the angular distributions of the $W$ boson production and decay are different for the right-handed neutrino and SM amplitudes. That can be used to evaluate potential HNL contribution using the extended likelihood method. The simulation of the $e^{+}e^{-} \rightarrow W^{+}W^{-}$ process is performed at the 1 TeV center-of-mass energy and polarisation $P_{e^+e^-}$ of (20 %, -80 %), which is a standard option for the future linear $e^+e^-$ collider ILC. Both $W$ bosons are reconstructed from two hadronic jets. Simulation of the SM background processes is also done. The beam-induced backgrounds and the initial state radiation (ISR) effects are taken into account. The majority of background processes are effectively suppressed by the cuts on the invariant masses of two and four jets. Finally, we obtain upper limits on the mixing parameter $|V_{eN}|^2$ as a function of $M(N)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09418v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Drutskoy, E. Vasenin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Three-Point Energy Correlator in the Coplanar Limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09428v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Energy correlators are a type of observables that measure how energy is distributed across multiple detectors as a function of the angles between pairs of detectors. In this paper, we study the three-point energy correlator (EEEC) at lepton colliders in the three-particle near-to-plane (coplanar) limit. The leading-power contribution in this limit is governed by the three-jet (trijet) configuration. We introduce a new approach by projecting the EEEC onto the volume of the parallelepiped formed by the unit vectors aligned with three detected final-state particles. Analogous to the back-to-back limit of the two-point energy correlator probing the dijet configuration, the small-volume limit of the EEEC probes the trijet configuration. We derive a transverse momentum dependent (TMD) based factorization theorem that captures the soft and collinear logarithms in the coplanar limit, which enables us to achieve the next-to-next-to-next-to-leading logarithm (N$^3$LL) resummation. To our knowledge, this is the first N$^3$LL result for a trijet event shape. Additionally, we demonstrate that a similar factorization theorem can be applied to the fully differential EEEC in the three-particle coplanar limit, which provides a clean environment for studying different coplanar trijet shapes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09428v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anjie Gao, Tong-Zhi Yang, Xiaoyuan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a Global Analysis of the $b\to c\bar{u} q$ Puzzle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09458v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the nonleptonic decays $\bar{B}_s^0 \to D_s^{(*)+} \pi^-$ and $\bar{B}^0 \to D^{(*)+} K^-$ within the Weak Effective Theory (WET) up to mass-dimension six. We revisit the calculation of the hadronic matrix elements within QCD Factorization including the full set of WET operators. We recalculate the two-particle contributions to the hard-scattering kernels at next-to-leading order in $\alpha_s$, confirming recent results in the literature. We also calculate the three-particle contributions at leading order in $\alpha_s$, clarifying the procedure, refining the SM results in the literature, and providing for the first time the complete set of contributions within the WET. We use these results to perform a global phenomenological study of the effective couplings, putting bounds on the size of the WET Wilson coefficients in four distinct fit models. The fits include constraints from the nonleptonic $B$-meson decay width, which we calculate at the leading order for the full set of WET operators for the first time. This study is the first one to account for simultaneous variation of up to six effective couplings. We identify two distinct modes in all fit models and discuss how future measurements can be used to distinguish between them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09458v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Meiser, Danny van Dyk, Javier Virto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collider fingerprints of freeze-in production of dark matter amidst the fast expansion phase of Universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09464v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We examine a simple dark sector extension where the observed dark matter (DM) abundance arises from a freeze-in process through the decay of heavy vector-like quarks into a scalar dark matter candidate. The detection prospects of such DM are challenging due to the feeble nature of the interactions, but these vector-like quarks can be produced copiously at the LHC, where they decay to Standard Model quarks along with DM. Depending on the decay rate, this scenario is typically probed through long-lived particle or displaced vertex signatures, assuming a radiation-dominated background. An alternative hypothesis suggests that the Universe may have experienced a rapid expansion phase instead of the standard radiation-dominated one during freeze-in. This would significantly alter the dark matter phenomenology, requiring a substantial increase in the interaction rate to match the observed relic density, resulting in the rapid decay of the parent particle. As a result, much of the parameter space for this scenario is beyond the reach of traditional long-lived particle and displaced vertex searches. Due to this non-standard cosmic evolution, existing constraints do not cover the expanded dark matter parameter space. We propose a complementary search strategy to explore this scenario, offering additional limits alongside searches for long-lived particles and displaced vertices. In our search, we investigate the FIMP dark matter model at the LHC using boosted fatjets and significant missing transverse momentum. To improve precision, we include one-loop QCD corrections for LHC production processes and employ a boosted decision tree multivariate analysis, leveraging jet substructure variables to explore a vast parameter space for this minimally extended FIMP dark matter model at the 14 TeV LHC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09464v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anupam Ghosh, Partha Konar, Sudipta Show</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A ${\mathbb{CP}}^2$ SMEFT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09521v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An extension of the Standard Model is proposed, where the Higgs field is valued in the complex projective plane ${\mathbb{CP}}^2$, rather than ${\mathbb{C}}^2$. Its geometry is consistent with $SU(2) \times U(1)$ gauge symmetry. The leading terms in the Lagrangian, beyond those of the Standard Model, are much more tightly constrained than in general SMEFTs, and the $SO(4)$ residual symmetry of the Higgs sector is mildly broken.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09521v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. S. Manton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The strong CP puzzle and axions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09529v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the first part of this talk, after a brief presentation of the strong CP puzzle, the construction of axion models and their main phenomenological features are described. In the second part, the possibility to mix the Peccei-Quinn symmetry with baryon and lepton numbers is discussed, showing that the axion could ultimately play a role in other puzzles of the Standard Model like the smallness of neutrino masses or baryogenesis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09529v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on the hadronic light-by-light in corner kinematics for the muon $g-2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09578</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09578v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The dispersive approach to the hadronic light-by-light contribution to the muon $g-2$ involves an integral over three virtual photon momenta appearing in the light-by-light tensor. Building upon previous works, we systematically derive short-distance constraints in the region where two momenta are large compared to the third, the so-called Melnikov-Vainshtein or corner region. We include gluonic corrections for the different scalar functions appearing in a Lorentz decomposition of the underlying tensor, and explicitly check analytic agreement with alternative operator product expansions in overlapping regimes of validity, and observe a very strong pattern of cancellations for the final $g-2$ integrand. The last observation suggests that a very compact expression only containing the axial current form factors can give a good approximation of the corner region of the hadronic light-by-light.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09578v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johan Bijnens, Nils Hermansson-Truedsson, Antonio Rodr\'iguez-S\'anchez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One or two poles for the $\Xi(1820)$?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09610v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this talk, we present a new interpretation for the recently observed $\Xi(1820)$ resonance. We recall that the chiral unitary approach for the interaction of pseudoscalar mesons with the baryons of the decuplet predicts two states for the $\Xi(1820)$ resonance, one with a narrow width and the other one with a large width. We contrast this fact with the recent BESIII measurement of the $K^- \Lambda$ mass distribution in the $\psi(3686)$ decay to $K^- \Lambda \bar\Xi^+ $, which demands a width much larger than the average of the PDG, and show how the consideration of the two $\Xi(1820)$ states provides a natural explanation to this apparent contradiction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09610v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Molina, Wei-Hong Liang, Chu-Wen Xiao, Zhi-Feng Sun, E. Oset</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study of large extra dimension and neutrino decay at P2SO experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09628v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we examine two important new physics scenarios, \textit{i.e}, the theory of Large Extra Dimension (LED) and the theory of neutrino decay. We study LED in the context of P2SO, DUNE, and T2HK with emphasis on P2SO, whereas decay has been studied solely in the context of P2SO. For LED, in our study we find that the combination of P2SO, DUNE, and T2HK can provide a better bound than the current one only if all the oscillation parameters are measured with absolute certainty. However, for decay, one can obtain a better bound with P2SO as compared to ESSnuSB and MOMENT, but the bound obtained by P2SO is weak as compared to DUNE and T2HK. Regarding sensitivities to the current unknowns, if LED exists in nature, its impact on mass ordering, octant, and CP violation is very mild; however, decay can alter the sensitivities related to CP violation and octant in a non-trivial way.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09628v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Papia Panda, Priya Mishra, Samiran Roy, Monojit Ghosh, Rukmani Mohanta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Unified Description of Small, Peripheral, and Large Suppression Data from pQCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09647</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09647v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present quantitative predictions for the nuclear modification factor in both small and peripheral systems from an energy loss model that is constrained by light- and heavy-flavor suppression data from central heavy-ion collisions. We find nearly identical suppression for central $p / d + A$ collisions as for peripheral $A + A$ collisions, quantitatively consistent with the measured 20% suppression of neutral pions produced in $d + \mathrm{Au}$ collisions by PHENIX but dramatically inconsistent with the measured 20% enhancement of charged hadrons produced in $p + \mathrm{Pb}$ collisions by ATLAS. We demonstrate that this equivalence of central small system suppression and peripheral large system suppression is insensitive to the underlying energy loss model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09647v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Coleridge Faraday, W. A. Horowitz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the LHC Constraints on Gauge-Mediated Supersymmetry Breaking Scenarios</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09650v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Supersymmetry (SUSY) addresses several problems of the Standard Model, such as the naturalness problem and gauge coupling unification, and can provide cosmologically viable dark matter candidates. SUSY must be broken at high energy scales with mechanisms like gravity, anomaly, gauge mediation, etc. This paper revisits the Gauge Mediated SUSY Breaking (GMSB) scenarios in the context of data from the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) experiment. The ATLAS mono-photon search at 139 inverse femtobarn integrated luminosity at the 13 TeV LHC, in the context of a simplified General Gauge Mediation (GGM) scenario (which is a phenomenological version of GMSB with an agnostic approach to the nature of the hidden sector), relies on assumptions that do not hold across the entire parameter space. We identify a few crucial assumptions regarding the decay widths of SUSY particles into final states with gravitinos that affect the LHC limits on the masses of the SUSY particles. Our study aims to reinterpret the ATLAS constraints on the gluino-NLSP mass plane, considering all possible decay modes of SUSY particles in a realistic GGM model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09650v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kirtiman Ghosh, Katri Huitu, Rameswar Sahu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of invisible neutrino decay on the neutrino oscillation at long-baselines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09677v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article, we study the effect of invisible neutrino decay of the third neutrino state for accelerator neutrino experiments at two different baselines, 1300 km with a liquid argon time projection chamber (LArTPC) detector (similar to DUNE) and 2588 km with a water Cherenkov detector (similar to P2O). For such baselines, the matter effect starts to become important. Our aim is to ascertain the sensitivity to mass hierarchy and octant of $\theta_{23}$ in these two experiments in the presence of a decaying neutrino state. We compare and contrast the results of the two experimental setups. We find that, in general, hierarchy sensitivity decreases in the presence of decay. However, if we consider decay only in the opposite hierarchy (test scenario), in the 2588 km setup, the hierarchy sensitivity with the true hierarchy as IH is larger than the no decay case. We also study the dependence of hierarchy sensitivity with true $\theta_{23}$. We find that the dominant muon background in P2O plays an important role in how the hierarchy sensitivity depends on $\theta_{23}$. The octant sensitivity for both setups increases in the presence of decay except for the LArTPC setup in case true $\theta_{23}=49^\circ$. To understand the octant sensitivity results in the two setups, we check the synergy in sensitivity between electron and muon channels as a function of test $\theta_{23}$. We also study the degeneracies in the test $\theta_{23}-\delta_{CP}$ plane and find that combined analysis of the two setups removes all the degeneracies in the test $\theta_{23}-\delta_{CP}$ plane at $5\sigma$ significance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09677v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Animesh Chatterjee, Srubabati Goswami, Supriya Pan, Paras Thacker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Open B production at hadron colliders in NNLO+NNLL QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09684</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09684v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report on a calculation of open heavy-flavor production at hadron colliders which extends to next-to-next-to-leading order (NNLO) accuracy the classic NLO-accurate formalism developed almost 30 years ago under the acronym FONLL. The approach retains the exact heavy-flavor mass dependence at low transverse momentum, $p_T$, and resums collinear logarithms through next-to-next-to-leading log (NNLL) at high $p_T$. Provided are predictions for $B$-hadrons as well as $B$-decay products like $J/\Psi$ and muons. The main features of the NNLO+NNLL results are reduced scale dependence and moderate NNLO correction, consistent with perturbative convergence in a wide range of kinematic scales from few GeV up to asymptotically large values of $p_T$. The new calculation significantly improves the agreement with data for $B$-hadrons and muons. We uncover an intriguing discrepancy in $J/\Psi$ final states which may point to a lower value of the $B\to J/\Psi$ decay rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09684v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Micha{\l} Czakon, Terry Generet, Alexander Mitov, Rene Poncelet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reggeization in Color</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09692v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the high energy limit, $s\gg -t$, amplitudes in planar gauge theories Reggeize, with power law behavior $\big( \frac{s}{-t} \big)^{\alpha(t)}$ governed by the Regge trajectory $\alpha(t)$. Beyond the planar limit this simplicity is violated by "Regge cuts", for which practical organizational principles are still being developed. We use a top-down effective field theory organization based on color projection in the $t$ channel and rapidity evolution equations for collinear impact factors, to sum large $s\gg -t$ logarithms for Regge cut contributions. The results are matrix equations which are closed within a given color channel. To illustrate the method we derive in QCD with $SU(N_c)$ for the first time a closed 6$\times$6 evolution equation for the "decupletons" in the $\text{10}\oplus\overline{\text{10}}$ Regge color channel, a 2$\times$2 evolution equation for the "triantapentons" in the $\text{35}\oplus\overline{\text{35}}$ color channel, and a scalar evolution equation for the "tetrahexaconton" in the 64 color channel. More broadly, our approach allows us to describe generic Reggeization phenomena in non-planar gauge theories, providing valuable data for the all loop structure of amplitudes beyond the planar limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09692v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anjie Gao, Ian Moult, Sanjay Raman, Gregory Ridgway, Iain W. Stewart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nuclear correlation functions using first-principle calculations of lattice quantum chromodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08962v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Exploring nuclear physics through the fundamental constituents of the strong force -- quarks and gluons -- is a formidable challenge. While numerical calculations using lattice quantum chromodynamics offer the most promising approach for this pursuit, practical implementation is arduous, especially due to the uncontrollable growth of quark-combinatorics, the so-called Wick-contraction problem of nuclei. We present here two novel methods providing a state-of-the-art solution to this problem. In the first, we exploit randomized algorithms inspired from computational number theory to detect and eliminate redundancies that arise in Wick contraction computations. Our second method explores facilities for automation of tensor computations -- in terms of efficient utilization of specialized hardware, algorithmic optimizations, as well as ease of programming and the potential for automatic code generation -- that are offered by new programming models inspired by applications in machine learning (e.g., TensorFlow). We demonstrate the efficacy of our methods by computing two-point correlation functions for Deuteron, Helium-3, Helium-4 and Lithium-7, achieving at least an order of magnitude improvement over existing algorithms with efficient implementation on GPU-accelerators. Additionally, we discover an intriguing characteristic shared by all the nuclei we study: specific spin-color combinations dominate the correlation functions, hinting at a potential connection to an as-yet-unidentified symmetry in nuclei. Moreover finding them beforehand can reduce the computing time further and substantially. Our results, with the efficiency that we achieved, suggest the possibility of extending the applicability of our methods for calculating properties of light nuclei, potentially up to A ~12 and beyond.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08962v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debsubhra Chakraborty, Piyush Srivastava, Arpith Kumar, Nilmani Mathur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quark Star Mergers: The Equation of State of Decompressed Quark Matter and Observational Signatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09013v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quark stars are challenging to confirm or exclude observationally because they can have similar masses and radii as neutron stars. By performing the first calculation of the non-equilibrium equation of state of decompressed quark matter at finite temperature, we determine the properties of the ejecta from binary quark-star or quark star-black hole mergers. We account for all relevant physical processes during the ejecta evolution, including quark nugget evaporation and cooling, and weak interactions. We find that these merger ejecta can differ significantly from those in neutron star mergers, depending on the binding energy of quark matter. For relatively high binding energies, quark star mergers are unlikely to produce r-process elements and kilonova signals. We propose that future observations of binary mergers and kilonovae could impose stringent constraints on the binding energy of quark matter and the existence of quark stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09013v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiqiang Miao, Zhenyu Zhu, Dong Lai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classical Observables from Causal Response Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09016v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We revisit the calculation of classical observables from causal response functions, following up on recent work by Caron-Huot at al. [JHEP 01 (2024) 139]. We derive a formula to compute asymptotic in-in observables from a particular soft limit of five-point amputated response functions. Using such formula, we re-derive the formulas by Kosower, Maybee and O'Connell (KMOC) for the linear impulse and radiated linear momentum of particles undergoing scattering, and we present an unambiguous calculation of the radiated angular momentum at leading order. Then, we explore the consequences of manifestly causal Feynman rules in the calculation of classical observables by employing the causal (Keldysh) basis in the in-in formalism. We compute the linear impulse, radiated waveform and its variance at leading and/or next-to-leading order in the causal basis, and find that all terms singular in the $\hbar \to 0$ limit cancel manifestly at the integrand level. We also find that the calculations simplify considerably and classical properties such as factorization of six-point amplitudes are more transparent in the causal basis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09016v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shovon Biswas, Julio Parra-Martinez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geminga: A Window of the Role Played by Local Halo in the Cosmic Ray Propagation Process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09119</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09119v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: An emerging commonality among the recently observed pulsar halos is the presence of distinct radiation patterns at high energies, while no extended radiation is detected around the GeV energy band. This commonality suggests that pulsar halos play a crucial role in the local propagation of cosmic rays, making it necessary to investigate the underlying mechanisms of this phenomenon. This work focuses on the 3D propagation study of cosmic rays, incorporating the Geminga pulsar into our propagation model to investigate its contribution to different observational spectra. We consider Geminga a dominant local source of positrons, successfully reproducing the observed positron spectrum and multi-energy spectra of the Geminga halo. Through calculations of signal and background at different angles, we find that: (1) at low energies, the slow diffusion characteristic around the pulsar region leads to a low electron density in the extended area around Geminga, causing the background radiation to exceed the signal intensity far; (2) at high energies, the larger effective diffusion radius of high-energy electrons/positrons causes the signal from Geminga to dominate the local high-energy phenomena; (3) the observed fluctuation of diffuse gamma-ray radiation by LHAASO is likely due to the incomplete subtraction of radiation from the local halo. We hope LHAASO will detect more cosmic ray halo sources to validate our model further.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09119v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lin Nie, Yu-Hai Ge, Yi-Qing Guo, Si-Ming Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the consistency of Lorentz-Violating Yang-Mills theories: Gauge invariance and non-perturbative effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09398v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Previous investigations on the renormalizability properties of Lorentz-violating Yang-Mills (LVYM) theories in the Landau gauge have pointed out the necessity of the inclusion of a mass-like term for the gauge fields. If one aims at generalizing the theory to a more complicated gauge, such a mass-like term can bring severe issues regarding gauge-dependence of correlation functions of observables. We propose a Lorentz-violating Yang-Mills theory supplemented by a gauge-invariant mass term which generalizes the model in the Landau gauge. We discuss the foundational aspects of the model and highlight how it simplifies in the Landau gauge. Following the recent literature in pure Yang-Mills theories, we remark how the proposed massive extension of LVYM theories can be used as an effective model to access infrared properties within perturbation theory. Finally, we present a BRST-invariant formulation of the so-called Refined Gribov-Zwanziger action in the presence of Lorentz-violating terms in linear covariant gauges and the underlying tree-level gauge-field propagator which is enriched by the non-perturbative information carried by the elimination of Gribov copies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09398v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio D. Pereira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Improved Bound on Nonlinear Quantum Mechanics using a Cryogenic Radio Frequency Experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09611</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09611v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: There are strong arguments that quantum mechanics may be nonlinear in its dynamics. A discovery of nonlinearity would hint at a novel understanding of the interplay between gravity and quantum field theory, for example. As such, experiments searching for potential nonlinear effects in the electromagnetic sector are important. Here we outline such an experiment, consisting of a stream of random bits (which were generated using Rigetti's Aspen-M-3 chip) as input to an RF signal generator coupled to a cryogenic detector. Projective measurements of the qubit state, which is originally prepared in an equal superposition, serve as the random binary output of a signal generator. Thereafter, spectral analysis of the RF detector would yield a detectable excess signal predicted to arise from such a nonlinear effect. A comparison between the projective measurements of the quantum bits vs the classical baseline showed no power excess. This sets a new limit on the electromagnetic nonlinearity parameter $|\epsilon| \lessapprox 1.15 \times 10^{-12}$, at a 90.0% confidence level. This is the most stringent limit on nonlinear quantum mechanics thus far and an improvement by nearly a factor of 50 over the previous experimental limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09611v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleksandr Melnychuk, Bianca Giaccone, Nicholas Bornman, Raphael Cervantes, Anna Grassellino, Roni Harnik, David E. Kaplan, Geev Nahal, Roman Pilipenko, Sam Posen, Surjeet Rajendran, Alexander O. Sushkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The lowest-radiation environments in the Solar System: new opportunities for underground rare-event searches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09634v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study neutrino, muon, and gamma-ray fluxes in extraterrestrial environments in our Solar System via semi-analytical estimates and Monte Carlo simulations. In sites with negligible atmosphere, we find a strong reduction in the cosmic-ray-induced neutrino and muon fluxes relative to their intensities on Earth. Neutrinos with energies between 50 MeV and 100 TeV show particularly strong suppression, by as much as 10$^3$, even at shallow depths. The solar neutrino suppression increases as the square of the site's distance from the Sun. Natural radiation due to nuclear decay is also expected to be lower in many of these locations and may be reduced to effectively negligible levels in the liquid water environments. The sites satisfying these characteristics represent an opportunity for greatly extending the physics reach of underground searches in fundamental physics, such as searches for WIMP Dark Matter, neutrinoless double-beta decay, the diffuse supernova neutrinos, and neutrinos from nearby supernova. As a potential near-term target, we propose a measurement of muon and gamma-ray fluxes in an accessible underground lunar site such as the Mare Tranquillitatis Pit to perform a first measurement of the prompt component in cosmic-ray-induced particle production, and to constrain lunar evolution models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09634v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xilin Zhang, Jason Detwiler, Clint Wiseman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hadronic vacuum polarization for the muon $g-2$ from lattice QCD: Complete short and intermediate windows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09656v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present complete results for the hadronic vacuum polarization (HVP) contribution to the muon anomalous magnetic moment $a_\mu$ in the short- and intermediate-distance window regions, which account for roughly 10% and 35% of the total HVP contribution to $a_\mu$, respectively. In particular, we perform lattice-QCD calculations for the isospin-symmetric connected and disconnected contributions, as well as corrections due to strong isospin-breaking. For the short-distance window observables, we investigate the so-called log-enhancement effects as well as the significant oscillations associated with staggered quarks in this region. For the dominant, isospin-symmetric light-quark connected contribution, we obtain $a^{ll,\,{\mathrm{SD}}}_{\mu}(\mathrm{conn.}) = 48.116(16)(94)[96] \times 10^{-10}$ and $a^{ll,\,{\mathrm{W}}}_{\mu}(\mathrm{conn.}) = 207.06(17)(63)[66] \times 10^{-10}$. We use Bayesian model averaging combined with a global bootstrap to fully estimate the covariance matrix between the individual contributions. Our determinations of the complete window contributions are $a^{{\mathrm{SD}}}_{\mu} = 69.01(2)(21)[21] \times 10^{-10}$ and $a^{{\mathrm{W}}}_{\mu} = 236.57(20)(94)[96] \times 10^{-10}$. This work is part of our ongoing effort to compute all contributions to HVP with an overall uncertainty at the few permille level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09656v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexei Bazavov, David A. Clarke, Christine Davies, Carleton DeTar, Aida X. El-Khadra, Elvira G\'amiz, Steven Gottlieb, Anthony V. Grebe, Leon Hostetler, William I. Jay, Hwancheol Jeong, Andreas S. Kronfeld, Shaun Lahert, Jack Laiho, G. Peter Lepage, Michael Lynch, Andrew T. Lytle, Craig McNeile, Ethan T. Neil, Curtis T. Peterson, James N. Simone, Jacob W. Sitison, Ruth S. Van de Water, Alejandro Vaquero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Warm inflation with a heavy QCD axion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.13535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.13535v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose the first model of warm inflation in which the particle production emerges directly from coupling the inflaton to Standard Model particles. Warm inflation, an early epoch of sustained accelerated expansion at finite temperature, is a compelling alternative to cold inflation, with distinct predictions for inflationary observables such as the amplitude of fluctuations, the spectral tilt, the tensor-to-scalar ratio, and non-gaussianities. In our model a heavy QCD axion acts as the warm inflaton whose coupling to Standard Model gluons sources the thermal bath during warm inflation. Axion-like couplings to non-Abelian gauge bosons have been considered before as a successful microphysical theory with emerging thermal friction that can maintain finite temperature during inflation via sphaleron heating. However, the presence of light fermions charged under the non-Abelian group suppresses particle production, hindering a realization of warm inflation by coupling to QCD. We point out that the Standard Model quarks can be heavy during warm inflation if the Higgs field resides in a high-energy second minimum which restores efficient sphaleron heating. A subsequent large reheating temperature is required to allow the Higgs field to relax to its electroweak minimum.
  Exploring a scenario in which hybrid warm inflation provides the large reheating temperature, we show that future collider and beam dump experiments have discovery potential for a heavy QCD axion taking the role of the warm inflaton.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.13535v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2024/10/103</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP10(2024)103</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kim V. Berghaus, Matthew Forslund, Mark Vincent Guevarra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting general dark matter-bound-electron interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04855</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04855v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this Letter we revisit general dark matter (DM)-bound-electron interactions studied previously in the influential work [R. Catena {\it et al.,} Atomic responses to general dark matter-electron interactions, Phys. Rev. Res. 2, 033195 (2020)] For the most general DM-electron nonrelativistic or relativistic interactions for DM with spin up to 1, we find the average ionization matrix element squared can be organized into three terms, each of which is a product of a DM response function ($a_{0,1,2}$) and a linear combination ($\widetilde W_{0,1,2}$) of the four atomic response functions ($W_{1,2,3,4}$) given in that work, $ \widetilde W_0 = W_1, \, \widetilde W_1 = |\pmb{v}_0^\perp|^2 W_1 - 2 {m_e\, \pmb{q}\cdot \pmb{v}_0^\perp \over \pmb{q}^2} W_2 + W_3,\, \widetilde W_2 = { (\pmb{q}\cdot \pmb{v}_0^\perp)^2 \over \pmb{q}^2} W_1 - 2 {m_e\, \pmb{q}\cdot \pmb{v}_0^\perp \over \pmb{q}^2} W_2 + {m_e^2 \over \pmb{q}^2}W_4$. Furthermore, we find a crucial minus sign was missed for the calculation of $W_2$ in that work, which has significant phenomenological consequences when explaining experimental bounds on specific DM scenarios. Due to the corrected sign, there can be significant cancellations between the $W_2$ and $W_{3,4}$ terms, so that $\widetilde W_{1,2}$ are dominated by the usual response function $W_1$ in some cases. Many DM scenarios involving DM or electron axial-vector current can yield $W_2$ and thus are potentially affected by the sign. As an example, we show that the recent XENON1T constraint on the fermionic DM anapole moment is weakened by a factor of 2 or so. We also present a complete list of NR operators for spin-1 DM and compute their contributions to the DM response functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04855v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.L091701</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, L091701 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jin-Han Liang, Yi Liao, Xiao-Dong Ma, Hao-Lin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heavy quark mass near the phase transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.08535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.08535v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Assuming that the number densities of heavy flavor in hadron gas and in QGP are same at $T_c$, we obtain the effective mass of heavy quark at $T_c$ from the comparison with the hadron resonance gas model which well describes particle yield in heavy-ion collisions. We find that charm quark mass at vanishing baryon chemical potential is around 1.8 GeV which is much heavier than QCD bare mass and close to $D$ meson mass. The mass slightly increases with increasing baryon chemical potential and then decreases. On the other hand, anticharm quark mass constantly decreases with increasing baryon chemical potential. Bottom quark mass has a similar pattern. Extending the hadron resonance gas model to a bit higher temperature beyond $T_c$, the effective masses of charm and bottom quarks decrease with increasing temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.08535v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1402-4896/ad8cb0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physica Scripta 99, 125304 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Taesoo Song, Qi Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining the Higgs Potential with Neural Simulation-based Inference for Di-Higgs Production</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15847</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15847v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Determining the form of the Higgs potential is one of the most exciting challenges of modern particle physics. Higgs pair production directly probes the Higgs self-coupling and should be observed in the near future at the High-Luminosity LHC. We explore how to improve the sensitivity to physics beyond the Standard Model through per-event kinematics for di-Higgs events. In particular, we employ machine learning through simulation-based inference to estimate per-event likelihood ratios and gauge potential sensitivity gains from including this kinematic information. In terms of the Standard Model Effective Field Theory, we find that adding a limited number of observables can help to remove degeneracies in Wilson coefficient likelihoods and significantly improve the experimental sensitivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15847v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.056004</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Radha Mastandrea, Benjamin Nachman, Tilman Plehn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective theory tower for $\mu\rightarrow e$ conversion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13818v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present theoretical predictions for $\mu \rightarrow e$ conversion rates using a tower of effective field theories connecting the UV to nuclear physics scales. The interactions in nuclei are described using a recently developed nonrelativistic effective theory (NRET) that organizes contributions according to bound nucleon and muon velocities, $\vec{v}_N$ and $\vec{v}_\mu$, with $|\vec{v}_N| &gt; |\vec{v}_\mu|$. To facilitate the top-down matching, we enlarge the set of Lorentz covariant nucleon-level interactions mapped onto the NRET operators to include those mediated by tensor interactions, in addition to the scalar and vector interactions already considered previously, and then match NRET nonperturbatively onto the Weak Effective Theory (WET). At the scale $\mu \approx 2$ GeV WET is formulated in terms of $u$, $d$, $s$ quarks, gluons and photons as the light degrees of freedom, along with the flavor-violating leptonic current. We retain contributions from WET operators up to dimension 7, which requires the full set of 26 NRET operators. The results are encoded in the open-source Python- and Mathematica-based software suite MuonBridge, which we make available to the theoretical and experimental communities interested in $\mu \rightarrow e$ conversion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13818v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP11(2024)076</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 11 (2024) 076</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wick Haxton, Kenneth McElvain, Tony Menzo, Evan Rule, Jure Zupan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-loop Quarkonium Hamiltonian in Non-annihilation Channel</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00723</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00723v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We calculate the two-loop heavy quarkonium Hamiltonian within potential-NRQCD effective field theory in the non-annihilation channel. This calculation represents the first non-trivial step towards determining the N$^4$LO Hamiltonian in the weak coupling regime. The large amount of computation is systematically handled by employing the $\beta$ expansion, differential equations for master integrals, and adopting a single-step matching procedure, in contrast to the conventional two-step approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00723v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Go Mishima, Yukinari Sumino, Hiromasa Takaura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unitarization of electron scattering with an external potential at NLO in QED</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15382v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We have calculated the one-loop scattering amplitude of an electron by an external Coulomb potential in QED free of infrared divergences. This feature is achieved by applying the Faddeev-Kulish formalism, which implies a redefinition of both the asymptotic electronic states and of the $S$ matrix. Additionally, we have also derived the infrared-finite one-loop partial-wave amplitudes for this process by applying a recent method in the literature. Next, these partial-wave amplitudes are unitarized based on analyticity and unitarity by employing three different methods of unitarization: the algebraic $N/D$ method, the Inverse Amplitude Method and the first iterated $N/D$ method. Then, we have studied several partial waves both for physical momentum and for complex ones to look for bound-state poles. The binding momentum for the fundamental bound state in $S$ wave is discussed with special detail. This is a wide-ranging method for calculating nonperturbative partial-wave amplitudes for infinite-range interactions that could be applied to many other systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15382v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. A. Oller, Marcela Pel\'aez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$U(1)$-charged Dark Matter in three-Higgs-doublet models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02728</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02728v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore three-Higgs-doublet models that may accommodate scalar Dark Matter where the stability is based on an unbroken $U(1)$-based symmetry, rather than the familiar $\mathbb{Z}_2$ symmetry. Our aim is to classify all possible ways of embedding a $U(1)$ symmetry in a three-Higgs-doublet model. The different possibilities are presented and compared. All these models contain mass-degenerate pairs of Dark Matter candidates due to a $U(1)$ symmetry unbroken (conserved) by the vacuum. Most of these models preserve CP. In the CP-conserving case the pairs can be seen as one being even and the other being odd under CP or as having opposite charges under $U(1)$. Not all symmetries presented here were identified before in the literature, which points to the fact that there are still many open questions in three-Higgs-doublet models. We also perform a numerical exploration of the $U(1) \otimes U(1)$-symmetric 3HDM, this is the most general phase-invariant (real) three-Higgs-doublet model. The model contains a multi-component Dark Matter sector, with two independent mass scales. After imposing relevant experimental constraints we find that there are possible solutions throughout a broad Dark Matter mass range, 45-2000 GeV, the latter being a scan cutoff.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02728v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP11(2024)086</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>A. Kun\v{c}inas, P. Osland, M. N. Rebelo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SModelS v3: Going Beyond Z2 Topologies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12942</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12942v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: SModelS is a public tool for fast reinterpretation of LHC searches for new physics based on a large database of simplified model results. While previous versions were limited to models with a Z2-type symmetry, such as R-parity conserving supersymmetry, version 3 can now handle arbitrary signal topologies. To this end, the tool was fully restructured and now relies on a graph-based description of simplified model topologies. In this work, we present the main conceptual changes and novel features of SModelS v3, together with the inclusion of new experimental searches for resonant production of spin-1 and spin-0 mediators with decays to quarks or to dark matter. Applying these results to a model containing two mediators, we discuss the interplay of resonance and missing energy searches, and the model's coverage by the currently available simplified model results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12942v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Mahdi Altakach, Sabine Kraml, Andre Lessa, Sahana Narasimha, Timoth\'ee Pascal, Camila Ramos, Yoxara Villamizar, Wolfgang Waltenberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multicritical-Point Principle Is All You Need for Toponium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04672v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, the Yukawa coupling constant of a possible newly discovered top quark is predicted. For this purpose, this paper considers a pseudo scalar mediating top quarks. This new Yukawa coupling is used as a channel to decay into a top quark pair (toponium). For predicting the Yukawa coupling constant, the multicritical-point principle (MPP) is used to determine the effective potential. And a few remarks will be made on the non-perturbative effects of toponium. As a result, the coupling constant of a possible newly discovered top quark pair is predicted to be about $0.85$--$0.86$. The pseudo scalar field is also found to improve the vacuum stability associated with the Higgs field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04672v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoshiki Matsuoka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Tool to Detect Inhomogeneous Chiral Symmetry Breaking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02285</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02285v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this letter, we discuss a novel method to search for inhomogeneous chiral symmetry breaking in theories with fermions. The prime application we have in mind is QCD, but the method is also applicable for other theories including solid state applications. It is based on an extension of the chiral susceptibility to inhomogeneous phases and it works as a stability analysis. Our method allows us to determine when homogeneous solutions have the tendency to create spatially modulated condensates. As proof of principle, we apply this technique to a rainbow-ladder QCD model and confirm the conjectured shape of the instability region published in Ref. [1].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02285v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Theo F. Motta, Michael Buballa, Christian S. Fischer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 33311 Left-Right Bilepton Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08078v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We discuss extension of the electroweak gauge group to $SU(3)_L \times SU(3)_R \times U(1)_{XL} \times U(1)_{XR}$. This adds new leptons to the familiar 331-model. The explanation for three light quark-lepton families remains but new particles are introduced which have no TeV scale upper limit on their masses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08078v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Claudio Corian\`o, Paul H. Frampton, Dario Melle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The time evolution of light nuclei cumulants and ratios with a first-order phase transition in the UrQMD transport model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08444v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The UrQMD model with a density dependent equation of state, including a first-order phase transition, is used to study the time dependence of baryon number and proton number susceptibilities up to third order in heavy ion reactions of $E_{\mathrm{lab}}=2-3 A$ GeV. A significant deviation from the Gaussian fluctuations of the baryon number fluctuation in coordinate space is observed. The proton number fluctuations are always suppressed as they constitute only a small fraction of the total baryon number during the dense phase of the collision. It is found that the only measurable, but small, signal would be an enhancement of the third order (or higher) proton cumulant in a finite rapidity window $\Delta y$ that is larger than one unit of rapidity. In addition, it is found that the coordinate fluctuations will lead to an enhancement of cluster production due to the correlations in coordinate space. However, this enhancement is small and mainly occurs during the dense part of the collision before the system actually freezes out.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08444v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thiranat Bumnedpan, Jan Steinheimer, Tom Reichert, Christoph Herold, Ayut Limphirat, Marcus Bleicher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Renormalization Flow of Nonlinear Electrodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.06472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.06472v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the renormalization flow of generic actions that depend on the invariants of the field strength tensor of an abelian gauge field. While the Maxwell action defines a Gaussian fixed point, we search for further non-Gaussian fixed points or rather fixed functions, i.e., globally existing Lagrangians of the invariants. Using standard small-field expansion techniques for the resulting functional flow equation, a large number of fixed points is obtained, which - in analogy to recent findings for a shift-symmetric scalar field - we consider as approximation artifacts. For the construction of a globally existing fixed function, we pay attention to the use of proper initial conditions. Parametrizing the latter by the photon anomalous dimension, both the coefficients of the weak-field expansion are fully determined and those of the large-field expansion can be matched such that a global fixed function can be constructed for magnetic fields. The anomalous dimension also governs the strong-field limit. Our results provide evidence for the existence of a continuum of non-Gaussian fixed points parametrized by a small positive anomalous dimension below a critical value. We discuss the implications of this result within various scenarios with and without additional matter. For the strong-field limit of the 1PI QED effective action, where the anomalous dimension is determined by electronic fluctuations, our result suggests the existence of a singularity free strong-field limit, circumventing the standard conclusions connected to the perturbative Landau pole.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.06472v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.076010</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 076010 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Holger Gies, Julian Schirrmeister</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CMB-HD as a Probe of Dark Matter on Sub-Galactic Scales</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12220</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12220v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show for the first time that high-resolution CMB lensing observations can probe structure on sub-galactic scales. In particular, a CMB-HD experiment can probe out to k ~ 55 h/Mpc, corresponding to halo masses of about $10^8 M_{\odot}$. Over the range 0.005 h/Mpc &lt; k &lt; 55 h/Mpc, spanning four orders of magnitude, the total lensing signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) from the temperature, polarization, and lensing power spectra is greater than 1900. CMB-HD gains most of the lensing SNR at small scales from the temperature power spectrum, as opposed to the lensing spectrum. These lensing measurements allow CMB-HD to distinguish between cold dark matter (CDM) and non-CDM models that change the matter power spectrum on sub-galactic scales. We also find that CMB-HD can distinguish between baryonic feedback effects and non-CDM models due to the different way each impacts the lensing signal. The kinetic Sunyaev-Zel'dovich (kSZ) power spectrum further constrains non-CDM models that deviate from CDM on the smallest scales CMB-HD measures. For example, CMB-HD can detect 1 keV warm dark matter (WDM) at 30$\sigma$, or rule out about 7 keV WDM at 95% CL, in a $\Lambda$WDM + $N_{\rm{eff}} + \sum m_\nu + m_{\rm{WDM}} + \log_{10}T_{\rm{AGN}} + A_{\rm{kSZ}} + n_{\rm{kSZ}}$ model; here $T_{\rm{AGN}}$ characterizes the strength of the feedback, and $A_{\rm{kSZ}}$ and $n_{\rm{kSZ}}$ allow freedom in the amplitude and slope of the kinetic Sunyaev-Zel'dovich power spectrum. This work provides an initial exploration of what can be achieved with reasonable assumptions about systematic effects. We make the CMB-HD Fisher code used here publicly available, and note that it can be modified to use any non-CDM model that changes the matter power spectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12220v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amanda MacInnis, Neelima Sehgal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ringdown stability: greybody factors as stable gravitational-wave observables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01692v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The quasinormal mode spectrum of black holes plays a crucial role in the modelling of post-merger ringdown signals. However, the spectrum is extremely sensitive to small deformations of the system and describes the linear response only in a certain (not precisely defined) timeframe after the merger. We argue here that the greybody factors, recently shown to describe the ringdown spectral amplitude at relatively high frequencies, are instead stable under small perturbations of the system and free of certain ambiguities that plague the quasinormal mode spectrum. Our analysis also unveils a nontrivial interplay: while certain ringdown quantities are dominated by the contribution of spectrally unstable quasinormal modes, these modes conspire to produce stable observables. Thus, we propose a complementary approach to ringdown studies, which circumvents some limitations of the standard quasinormal mode description.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01692v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Romeo Felice Rosato, Kyriakos Destounis, Paolo Pani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Axion species scale and axion weak gravity conjecture-like bound</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16156v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: As a cutoff scale of quantum gravity, the species scale can be defined by the scale at which the perturbativity of the non-renormalizable gravitational interaction begins to break down. Since it is determined by the number of species in the effective field theory, we can find the close connection to the distance conjecture, which predicts the lowering of the cutoff at the asymptotic limit of the moduli space caused by the descent of a tower of states from UV. Meanwhile, the same kind of the cutoff scale can be obtained from any non-renormalizable interaction, in particular the interaction between the axion and the gauge field through the $\theta F\wedge F$ term. Demanding this `axion species scale' not to exceed the gravitational species scale, we obtain the bound $(8\pi^2/g^2)f \lesssim M_{\rm Pl}$. This is quite similar to the axion weak gravity conjecture bound, but can be applied to any gauge as well as the string interactions which are relevant to towers of states. We also investigate the implications of the (axion) species scale and the axion weak gravity conjecture-like bound by considering the Peccei-Quinn charge reduction of black hole through the interaction between black hole and the string or wormhole.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16156v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP11(2024)082</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 11 (2024) 082</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Min-Seok Seo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resonant excitation of eccentricity in spherical extreme-mass-ratio inspirals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02004</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02004v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Gravitational radiation reaction, has been one of the fundamental issues in general relativity. Over a span of decades, this process has been analyzed in the adiabatic limit, in order to comprehend how it drives extreme-mass-ratio binaries, that are prime targets for space-borne detectors. It has been shown that spherical orbits around Schwarzschild and Kerr black holes remain spherical (zero eccentricity) under the influence of gravitational radiation reaction. Here, we show that spherical orbits in non-Kerr black holes, that still preserve most of the good qualities and symmetries of Kerr spacetime, can access certain resonances in such a way that an initially spherical inspiral acquires non-zero eccentricity and becomes non-spherical. Therefore, the crossing of resonances under radiation reaction interrupts and even inverts, up to some small radius close to plunge, the process of circularization of orbits. The strength of resonant excitation of eccentricity depends on the initial position and inclination of the integrable extreme-mass-ratio system, as well as the integrability-breaking parameter introduced in the background spacetime that amplifies further the excitation. We find that the harmonics of gravitational waves emitted from these inspirals undergo a frequency modulation as the orbit `metamorphoses' from spherical to non-spherical, due to the effect of resonant eccentricity excitation. The gain that low-amplitude harmonics experience in these oligochromatic EMRIs, due to resonances, may be detectable with future spaceborne detectors and serves as an indicator of non-Kerrness of the background spacetime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02004v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Areti Eleni, Kyriakos Destounis, Theocharis A. Apostolatos, Kostas D. Kokkotas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shock breakouts from compact CSM surrounding core-collapse SN progenitors may contribute significantly to the observed $\gtrsim10$ TeV neutrino background</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14233v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Growing observational evidence suggests that enhanced mass loss from the progenitors of core-collapse supernovae (SNe) is common during $\sim1$ yr preceding the explosion, creating an optically thick circum-stellar medium (CSM) shell at $\sim10^{14.5}$ cm radii. We show that if such mass loss is indeed common, then the breakout of the SN shock through the dense CSM shell produces a neutrino flux that may account for a significant fraction of the observed $\gtrsim10$ TeV neutrino background. The neutrinos are created within a few days from the explosion, during and shortly after the shock breakout, which produces also large UV (and later X-ray) luminosity. The compact size and large UV luminosity imply a pair production optical depth of $\sim10^4$ for $&gt;100$ GeV photons, naturally accounting for the lack of a high-energy gamma-ray background accompanying the neutrino background. SNe producing $&gt;1$ neutrino event in a 1 km$^2$ detector are expected at a rate of $\lesssim0.1$/yr. A quantitative theory describing the evolution of the electromagnetic spectrum during a breakout, as the radiation-mediated shock is transformed into a collisionless one, is required to enable (i) using data from upcoming surveys that will systematically detect large numbers of young, $&lt;1$ d old SNe, to determine the pre-explosion mass loss history of the SN progenitor population, and (ii) a quantitative determination of the neutrino luminosity and spectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14233v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Waxman, T. Wasserman, E. Ofek, A. Gal-Yam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mass Spectra in ${\cal N}=1$ SQCD, in ${\cal N}=1$ SQCD-type theory and in softly broken ${\cal N}=2\rightarrow {\cal N}=1$ SQCD. And problems with the ${\cal N}=1$ Seiberg duality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19443v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Mass spectra are calculated for ${\cal N}=1$ SQCD and SQCD-type theories and for softly broken ${\cal N}=2$ SQCD in vacua with unbroken $Z_{(2N_c-N_F)\geq 2}$ symmetry. It is shown that the Seiberg ${\cal N}=1$ duality works, at best, for massless quarks within the conformal window only.
  Besides: a) the gauge invariant order parameter for scalar quarks is introduced which distinguishes confinement and higgs phases, b) the phase transition are described in ${\cal N}=1$ SQCD-type and broken ${\cal N}=2$ SQCD theories between confinement and higgs phases, c) the confinement mechanism is proposed for the ordinary YM and ${\cal N}=1$ SYM theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19443v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor L. Chernyak</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
