<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph</link>
    <description>hep-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 05:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Massive Helicity-Chirality Spinor Formalism from Massless Amplitudes with On-shell Mass Insertion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09062v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a helicity-chirality spinor formalism to describe scattering amplitudes for particles of any masses and spins. The massive spin-spinors introduced by Arkani-hamed-Huang-Huang have been extended to the spin/helicity-transversality spinors, in which a new quantum number transversality, closely related to chirality, is introduced by extending the Poincare symmetry. The massive helicity-chirality amplitudes can be written by the large and small components of massless spinors $\lambda$ and $\eta$ following the $\lambda \sim \sqrt{E}, \eta \sim \mathbf{m}/\sqrt{E}$ expansion order by order, which formulate the power counting rules of a large energy effective theory. Diagrammatically the mass expansion in amplitudes originates from the on-shell mass insertion: the helicity flip and chirality flip, which completely determines the three-point massive amplitudes. From the chirality-helicity unification at the UV, any massive helicity-chirality amplitude can be one-to-one corresponded to massless helicity amplitudes with (without) additional Higgs insertion. This UV-IR correspondence explains the mass enhancement in the weak decay processes $\pi^+ \to \mu^+ \nu$ and $t \to W^+ b$, and isolates the correct UV of the three-point massive QED $F\bar{F}\gamma$ amplitudes in Arkani-hamed-Huang-Huang formalism. From massless-massive correspondence, the massless on-shell techniques can be utilized to construct higher-point massive amplitudes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09062v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Han Ni, Yi-Ning Wang, Chao Wu, Jiang-Hao Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heavy neutral leptons and top quarks in effective field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09065</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09065v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the phenomenology of heavy neutral leptons (HNLs) at the LHC in effective field theory, concentrating on $d=6$ operators with top quarks. Depending on the operator choice and HNL mass, the HNLs will be produced either from proton-proton collisions in association with a single top, or via non-standard decays of top quarks. For long-lived HNLs we estimate the sensitivity reach of different detectors to various operators with top quarks and the HNLs for the high-luminosity phase of the LHC. For certain operators, ATLAS and some far detectors (MATHUSLA and ANUBIS) will be able to probe the associated new-physics scale as large as 12 TeV and 4.5 TeV, respectively, covering complementary HNL-mass ranges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09065v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rebeca Beltr\'an, Giovanna Cottin, Julian G\"unther, Martin Hirsch, Arsenii Titov, Zeren Simon Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The LHC as a TeV Muon Beam Dump: Muonphilic Scalars at FASER</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09071v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The FASER experiment was designed to study long-lived dark sector particles and neutrinos traveling in the forward direction at the LHC. Neutrinos are predominantly produced from meson decays, which also result in an intense energetic flux of muons in the forward direction regularly observed by FASER. So far, these muons are treated only as backgrounds to neutrino and new physics studies, and extensive effort is required to suppress them. In this study, we consider the opposite scenario and use muons produced in the forward direction to produce new muonphilic scalars, which can then be searched for at the FASER detector. To minimize the backgrounds for this search, we make use of an upgraded preshower component, which is expected to be installed at FASER before the end of Run 3, and is capable of spatially resolving two energetic photons. We find that FASER, and its upgrade, FASER2 can probe currently unconstrained regions of parameter space, including regions that can potentially explain the $(g-2)_{\mu}$ anomaly. This highlights the physics opportunities that the intense TeV muon beam at the LHC can bring.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09071v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roshan Mammen Abraham, Max Fieg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalar Rayleigh Dark Matter: current bounds and future prospects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09073</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09073v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dark Matter can interact with electroweak gauge bosons via higher-dimensional operators, in spite of being neutral under gauge interactions, much like neutral atoms interact with photons through Rayleigh scattering. This study explores effective interactions between a real scalar Dark Matter particle, singlet under the SM gauge group, and electroweak gauge bosons. We present a comprehensive analysis of current constraints and projected sensitivities from both lepton and hadron colliders as well as direct and indirect detection experiments in testing Rayleigh Dark Matter interactions. We find that, thanks to the complementarity between collider experiments and cosmological probes, thermally produced Rayleigh Dark Matter at the hundreds of GeV scale can be thoroughly tested with the next generation of experiments. For lighter candidates, upcoming forecasts will explore uncharted parameter space, significantly surpassing the thermal Dark Matter benchmark.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09073v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniele Barducci, Dario Buttazzo, Alessandro Dondarini, Roberto Franceschini, Giulio Marino, Federico Mescia, Paolo Panci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinematic Moments of $\bar{B}\to X_c \ell \bar{\nu}_\ell$ to Order $\mathcal{O}(\Lambda_{\rm QCD}^5/m_b^5)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09090</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09090v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the heavy-quark expansion (HQE) for inclusive semileptonic $\bar{B}$ decays, at tree level, by computing the fully differential decay rate up to order $\mathcal{O}(\Lambda_{\rm QCD}^5/m_b^5)$. We provide analytic results for the first three moments in the lepton energy, hadronic invariant mass and leptonic invariant mass ($q^2$) with a lower cut on the lepton energy in the $\bar{B}$ rest frame, as well as for the first three $q^2$ moments with a lower cut on $q^2$. By means of the lowest-lying state saturation ansatz we study the numerical behaviour of the HQE providing insights into the theoretical error budget associated with power corrections. Available CLEO data on the second central $q^2$ moment with a lower cut on the lepton energy present puzzling discrepancies with the theoretical expectations. This observation makes new measurements of these observables desirable, which could improve the precision of global fit analyses for the inclusive determination of $|V_{cb}|$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09090v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gael Finauri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Updated BBN Bounds on Hadronic Injection in the Early Universe: The Gravitino Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09120</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09120v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Late-decaying particles naturally arise in many extensions of the Standard Model, directly impacting key cosmological processes in the early universe, such as Big Bang Nucleosynthesis (BBN). BBN studies often consider electromagnetic energy injection episodes only, but in practice long-lived particles are also amenable to hadronic decays. The latter can greatly alter the predicted abundances of light elements such as $\mathrm{D}/\mathrm{H}$, $Y_p$, ${}^3\mathrm{He}/\mathrm{D}$, and ${}^7\mathrm{Li}/\mathrm{H}$. Incorporating up-to-date measurements, we place constraints on the primordial abundance of long-lived particles as a function of their lifetime. Lastly, we apply our results to the gravitino problem and set bounds on the reheating temperature, which controls the gravitino primordial abundance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09120v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucia Angel, Giorgio Arcadi, Matheus M. A. Paix\~ao, Farinaldo S. Queiroz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heavy quark symmetry behind $b \to c$ semileptonic sum rule</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09382v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Lepton flavor universality violations in semileptonic $b \to c$ transitions have garnered attention over a decade. For $R_{H_c}={\rm{BR}}(H_b\to H_c \tau\bar\nu_\tau)/{\rm{BR}}(H_b\to H_c \ell\bar\nu_\ell)$ with $\ell$ being $e,\, \mu$, a sum rule among $R_{D}$ $R_{D^*}$ and $R_{\Lambda_c}$ was proposed to check consistency in the experimental results independently of new physics models. We revisit this relation from the perspective of the heavy quark symmetry. We derive a sum rule holding exactly in the heavy quark limit and clarify how model-dependent corrections are introduced in a realistic situation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09382v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Motoi Endo, Syuhei Iguro, Satoshi Mishima, Ryoutaro Watanabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Taming Penguins: Towards High Precision Measurements in $\phi_d$ and $\phi_s$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09414v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Experimentally, the phases $\phi_d$ and $\phi_s$ are determined from CP asymmetry measurements in the "golden modes" $B_d^0\to J/\psi K_{\mathrm{S}}^0$ and $B_s^0\to J/\psi\phi$. At leading order, the theoretical interpretation of these measurements is straightforward. However, to reach high precision determinations of $\phi_d$ and $\phi_s$, which is essential in view of the searches for signs of beyond the SM physics, corrections from next-to-leading order effects need to be accounted for. These corrections primarily originate from so-called penguin topologies. Using the $SU(3)$ flavour symmetry, these corrections can be determined using suitably chosen control modes. Recent new CP asymmetry measurements from LHCb in $B\to DD$ and Belle-II in $B_d^0\to J/\psi\pi^0$ decays greatly improve our knowledge on the parameters describing the contribution from penguin topologies. These proceedings will discuss the current constraints on the penguin parameters in $B\to J/\psi X$ and $B\to DD$ decays, provide corrected determinations for $\phi_d$ and $\phi_s$, and highlight what can be expected at the end of the HL-LHC and Belle-II programmes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09414v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kristof De Bruyn, Robert Fleischer, Eleftheria Malami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of $a_0( 1710)$ in the $D_s^+\to\rho^+\phi,~~\rho^+\omega$ decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09422v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We look into the $D_s^+ \to \rho^+ \phi$ and $D_s^+ \to \rho^+ \omega$ weak decays recently measured by the BESIII collaboration, which proceed very differently in a first step of the weak decay. While the first reaction proceeds directly via external emission, the second one does not go via external nor internal emission, what prompted the experimental team to claim that it proceeds via $W-$annihilation. We show in this work that the unexpectedly large rate of the $D_s^+ \to \rho^+ \omega$, should it be due to $W-$annihilation, has a different explanation since is it naturally obtained once final state interaction of the $\rho^+ \phi, ~\rho^+ \omega$ and $K^{*+} \bar{K}^{*0}$ channels is taken into consideration. The interaction of these channels produces the $a_0(1710)$ resonance, predicted long ago as a molecular state of these coupled channels, and only recently observed, and it is the presence of this resonance what makes the effect of the final state interaction very important in the weak decays and provides a natural explanation of the experimental decay rates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09422v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing Song, Zi-Ying Yang, Eulogio Oset</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The flux of electron antineutrinos from supernova SN1987A data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09445v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: By adopting a state-of-the-art parameterized model of electron antineutrino emission, we have made some steps forward in the analysis of the thermodynamical properties and temporal structure of neutrino emission from core collapse SN1987A. Our analysis, unlike similar previous ones, takes into account the times, energies and angles of arrival of the detected events in a reliable framework which includes a finite ramp in the initial stage of the neutrino emission. The existence of the accretion phase is confirmed with a confidence level of about 99%, and the neutrons involved in the emission during accretion, for the first time, do not show significant tensions with expectations, being about 0.02 $M_\odot$. We determine the parameters of the cooling emission and discuss its duration, that compares well with theoretical expectations. We estimate the delay times between the first neutrino and the first event in the detectors. The goodness of fit checks, performed on the temporal, energy and angular distributions, show that the flux resulting from the best-fit analysis is compatible with the observed data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09445v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riccardo Maria Bozza, Vigilante di Risi, Giuseppe Matteucci, Veronica Oliviero, Giulia Ricciardi, Francesco Vissani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exclusive quarkonium photoproduction: predictions with the Balitsky-Kovchegov equation including the full impact-parameter dependence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09462v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ongoing Run 3 at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) is substantially increasing the luminosity delivered to the experiments during Run 1 and Run 2. The advent of the high-luminosity upgrade of the LHC (Run 4 to 6), as well as the improvements to all detectors, will allow for the collection of an unprecedented amount of data in the next decade. This opens the possibility of performing measurements which have been limited by the smallness of the available data samples. This is the case of multi-differential studies of $\Jpsi$, as well as of $\Upsilon$ excited states, in exclusive diffractive photon-induced interactions. Here, we present predictions for the cross-sections of these processes utilising the dipole amplitude from the Balitsky-Kovchegov (BK) equation solved in the target rapidity and including the full impact-parameter dependence. Cross-sections are computed as a function of the photon--proton centre-of-mass energy as well as a function of Mandelstam-$t$. Ratios of cross-sections for different states and for the same state at different Mandelstam-$t$ values are also presented. The contribution to these observables of the non-linear terms in the BK equation is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09462v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Cepila, J. G. Contreras, M. Vaculciak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational waves and dark matter with Witten effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09596</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09596v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the breaking of dark $SU(2)_d$ symmetry at different temperature scales, occurring after Peccei-Quinn symmetry breaking or following QCD symmetry breaking. We focus on assessing the potential of the hidden monopoles generated during this process to serve as dark matter candidate. Additionally, we examine the impact of axion-monopole interactions on the axion mass. When the phase transition occurs at extremely high temperature ($\sim 10^8 \mathrm{GeV}$), the contribution of monopoles to the axion mass through witten effect becomes non-negligible, playing a crucial role in accurately determining the axion relic density. Moreover, the stochastic gravitational wave background generated by dark phase transition and axionic domain wall collapse may offer a potential explanation for the low-frequency gravitational wave signals observed in PTA experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09596v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruiyu Zhou, Ligong Bian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scattering meets absorption in dark matter detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09642v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Direct detection experiments have started to explore dark matter scattering off electrons and nucleons through light mediators. Mediators with sub-keV masses are efficiently produced in the Sun and can be absorbed in the same detectors that probe dark matter scattering. We investigate the interplay of dark matter scattering and mediator absorption for two models with a dark photon as mediator. For Dirac dark matter, we find that scattering and absorption can be simultaneously observed at direct detection experiments in the near future. For atomic dark matter, we predict additional signals due to scattering of both dark atoms and constituents from ionized dark atoms. In both models, we determine the parameter space that respects bounds from cosmology and astrophysics, where the strongest constraints come from dark matter self-interactions. In this way, we identify viable targets for dark matter with light mediators at upcoming direct detection experiments. Distinguishing between the various signals, for instance by measuring energy distributions, will be crucial to reveal the underlying model in case of a discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09642v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pieter Braat, Anh Vu Phan, Marieke Postma, Susanne Westhoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dispersive analysis of the pion vector form factor without zeros</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09643v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We perform an updated analysis of $e^+e^-\to\pi^+\pi^-$ cross-section data using a dispersive representation of the pion vector form factor. We show that the available data are compatible with the assumption that the form factor is free of complex zeros and that under this assumption the largest systematic uncertainty in a previous analysis can be eliminated. We investigate both a constrained Omn\`es representation as well as a hybrid phase-modulus representation and we quantify the discrepancies in the hadronic vacuum polarization contribution to the anomalous magnetic moment of the muon based on different $e^+e^-$ data sets. We find that the dispersive constraints exacerbate these discrepancies. Together with the assumption of the absence of zeros, the pion charge radius becomes a useful observable to discriminate between the different data sets. This provides an opportunity for future improved lattice-QCD determinations to probe the discrepancies independently of full computations of hadronic vacuum polarization. We also reevaluate the two-pion contribution to Euclidean windows and we observe that systematic discrepancies between the data sets persist even at very long distances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09643v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas P. Leplumey, Peter Stoffer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining the Secluded and Catalyzed Annihilation Dark Matter with Fermi-LAT and Planck Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09647</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09647v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a dark matter (DM) model with a complex scalar charged under a hidden gauge symmetry, denoted as $U(1)_D$. The scalar field is the DM candidate while the $U(1)_D$ gauge field $A'$ plays the role of a mediator, which connects the dark sector to the standard model (SM) sector via a tiny kinetic mixing. We find that both the secluded and catalyzed annihilation scenarios can be realized in this model. The phenomenology of DM, including relic density, indirect detection (Fermi-LAT), and CMB (Planck) constraints, is discussed. We also extend our discussion to DM with other spins, including Dirac fermion and vector boson. Our analysis is carried out in two models, denoted as $U(1)_D \times U(1)_Y$ and $U(1)_D \times U(1)_{L_\mu-L_\tau}$, with the former corresponding to $A'$ kinetically mixing with the $U(1)_Y$ gauge field $B$ and the latter corresponding to $A'$ mixing with the $U(1)_{L_\mu-L_\tau}$ gauge field $Z'$. We find that, in previous studies, the indirect detection limits were overly restrictive because they only considered the simplified $2\mathrm{DM} \to 2\mathrm{SM}$ annihilation channel. In contrast, by performing a complete calculation of the gamma-ray and CMB constraints from the process $2\mathrm{DM} \to 2A' \to 4\mathrm{SM}$ in the models we consider, we observe weaker constraints in both the $U(1)_D \times U(1)_Y$ and $U(1)_D \times U(1)_{L_\mu-L_\tau}$ models, with the $U(1)_D \times U(1)_{L_\mu-L_\tau}$ model being subject to the weakest constraints overall since it involves less hadronic decay processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09647v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Hang Su, Chengfeng Cai, Hong-Hao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tensor meson transition form factors in holographic QCD and the muon $g-2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09699</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09699v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Despite the prominence of tensor mesons in photon-photon collisions, until recently their contribution to the hadronic light-by-light scattering part of the anomalous magnetic moment of the muon has been estimated at the level of only a few $10^{-12}$, with an almost negligible contribution to the error budget of the standard model prediction. A recent reanalysis within the dispersive approach has found that after resolving the issue of kinematic singularities in previous approaches, a larger result is obtained, a few $10^{-11}$, and with opposite sign as in previous results, when a simple quark model for the transition form factors is employed. In this paper, we present the first complete evaluation of tensor meson contributions within a hard-wall model in holographic QCD, which reproduces surprisingly well mass, two-photon width, and the observed singly virtual transition form factors of the dominant $f_2(1270)$, requiring only that the energy-momentum tensor correlator is matched to the leading OPE result of QCD. Due to a second structure function that is absent in the quark model, the result for $a_\mu$ turns out to be positive instead of negative, and also with a magnitude of a few $10^{-11}$. We discuss both pole and non-pole contributions arising from tensor meson exchanges in the holographic light-by-light scattering amplitude, finding that keeping all contributions improves dramatically the convergence of a sum over excited tensor mesons and avoids unnaturally large contributions from the first few excited modes at low energies. Doing so, the contribution from the lightest tensor mode becomes $a_\mu^T=5.9\times 10^{-11}$ ($5.4\times 10^{-11}$ from virtualities less than 1.5 GeV).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09699v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luigi Cappiello, Josef Leutgeb, Jonas Mager, Anton Rebhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Partonic distribution functions and amplitudes using tensor network methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09738v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Calculations of the parton distribution function (PDF) and distribution amplitude (DA) are highly relevant to core experimental programs as they provide non-perturbative inputs to inclusive and exclusive processes, respectively. Direct computation of the PDFs and DAs remains challenging because they are non-perturbative quantities defined as light-cone correlators of quark and gluon fields, and are therefore inherently time-dependent. In this work, we propose a uniform quantum strategy based on tensor network simulation techniques to directly extract these hadronic quantities from first principles using the matrix product state of the hadrons in the same setup. We present exemplary numerical calculations with the Nambu-Jona-Lasinio model in 1+1 dimensions and compare with available exact diagonalization and quantum circuit simulation results. Using tensor networks, we evaluate the PDF and DA at various strong couplings in the large-qubit limit, which is consistent with expectations at perturbative and non-relativistic limits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09738v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhong-Bo Kang, Noah Moran, Peter Nguyen, Wenyang Qian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid spin-dependent and hybrid-quarkonium mixing potentials at order $(1 /m_Q)^1$ from SU(3) lattice gauge theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08844v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the first lattice gauge theory results for hybrid spin-dependent and hybrid-quarkonium mixing potentials appearing at order $(1 /m_Q)^1$ in the Born-Oppenheimer Effective Field theory for hybrid mesons with gluon spin $\kappa^{PC} = 1^{+-}$. Specifically, we compute the four unknown potentials $V^{sa}_{11}(r)$, $V^{sb}_{10}(r)$, which are relevant for the hyperfine splitting in heavy hybrid meson spectra, as well as $V^\text{mix}_{\Sigma_u^-}(r)$ and $V^\text{mix}_{\Pi_u}(r)$, which describe the mixing of heavy hybrid mesons with ordinary quarkonium. We relate these potentials to matrix elements, which we extract from generalized Wilson loops with a chromomagnetic field insertion along one of the temporal lines and suitable hybrid creation operators replacing the spatial lines. We use gradient flow, which facilitates the renormalization of the matrix elements and has the additional benefit of significantly reducing statistical noise. We present results for gauge group SU(3) and lattice spacing $a=0.060$ fm. Our results demonstrate that a future combined continuum and zero-flow time extrapolation is possible within our setup, which will be necessary to reliably predict the hyperfine splitting of heavy hybrid mesons as well as their mixing with ordinary quarkonium through coupled channel Schr\"odinger equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08844v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carolin Schlosser, Marc Wagner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Remarks on brane-antibrane inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09074</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09074v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We provide an accessible review to the eta problem in brane-antibrane inflation and a recently proposed solution. The description of the antibrane by means of nonlinearly realized supersymmetry suggests a simple stabilization mechanism for the volume mode, based on the most general Kahler and superpotentials compatible with the symmetries of the problem. This work is a contribution to the proceedings of the second general meeting of the COST Action CA21106 (Cosmic WISPers) and is based on arXiv:2410.00097 .</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09074v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gonzalo Villa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological Interactions with Phantom Scalar Field: Revisiting Background Phase-Space Analysis with Compactified Variables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09177</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09177v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Energy transfer in the dark sector of the universe gives rise to new phenomena of special interest in modern cosmology. When dark energy is modeled as a phantom scalar field, interactions become crucial to avoid Big Rip singularities. In this work, we revisit the phase-space analysis of the field equations by introducing a new set of dimensionless variables distinct from the traditional Hubble normalization approach. These new variables define a compactified phase space for the evolution of physical parameters. We demonstrate that these compactified variables offer fresh insights into the phase-space analysis in gravitational theories, particularly when the dark energy fluid is allowed to possess a negative kinetic energy density.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09177v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Genly Leon, Daya Shankar, Amlan Halder, Andronikos Paliathanasis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The effect of accretion on scalar superradiant instability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09280v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Superradiance can lead to the formation of a black hole (BH) condensate system. We thoroughly investigate the accretion effect on the evolution of this system, and the gravitational wave signals it emits in the presence of multiple superradiance modes. Assuming the multiplication of the BH mass and scalar mass as a small number, we obtain the analytical approximations of all important quantities, which can be directly applied to phenomenological studies. In addition, we confirm that accretion could significantly enhance the gravitational wave (GW) emission and reduce its duration, and show that the GW beat signature is similarly modified.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09280v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yin-Da Guo, Shou-Shan Bao, Tianjun Li, Hong Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological Solutions in Scalar-Tensor theory via the Eisenhart-Duval lift</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09356</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09356v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We implement the Einsenhart-Duval lift in scalar-tensor gravity as a means to construct integrable cosmological models and analytic cosmological solutions. Specifically, we employ a geometric criterion to constrain the free functions of the scalar-tensor theory such that the field equations can be written in the equivalent form of linear equations. This geometric linearization is achieved by the introduction of an extended minisuperspace description. The results are applied to construct analytic solutions in modified theories of gravity such as the $f\left( R\right) $-theory and the hybrid metric-Palatini $f\left( \mathcal{R}\right) $-gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09356v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andronikos Paliathanasis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reassessing aspects of the photon's LQG-modified dispersion relations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09370v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Our present contribution sets out to investigate a scenario based on the effects of the Loop Quantum Gravity (LQG) on the electromagnetic sector of the Standard Model of Fundamental Interactions and Particle Physics (SM). Starting then from a post-Maxwellian version of Electromagnetism that includes LQG effects, we work out and discuss the influence of LQG parameters on classical quantities, such as the components of the stress-tensor. Furthermore, we inspect the propagation of electromagnetic waves and study optical properties of the QED vacuum in this scenario. Among these, we contemplate the combined effect between the LQG parameters and a homogeneous background magnetic field on the propagation of electromagnetic waves, considering in detail issues like group velocities and refractive indices of the QED vacuum. Finally, with the help of the LQG-extended photonic dispersion relations previously analyzed, we re-discuss the kinematics of the Compton effect and conclude that there emerges an interesting nonlinear profile in the wavelengths of both the incoming and the deflected photons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09370v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. A. L. Mour\~ao, G. L. L. W. Levy, J. A. Helay\"el-Neto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Unified View of Vacuum Decay Channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09714</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09714v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The tunneling potential formalism, an alternative to the standard Coleman Euclidean approach, offers in a natural way a unified view of vacuum decays. In particular, I show in this talk how Coleman's bounce is just a member of a continuous family of solutions that can also feature Hawking-Moss instantons, pseudo-bounces and bubble-of-nothing solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09714v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. R. Espinosa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generating particle physics Lagrangians with transformers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09729</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09729v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In physics, Lagrangians provide a systematic way to describe laws governing physical systems. In the context of particle physics, they encode the interactions and behavior of the fundamental building blocks of our universe. By treating Lagrangians as complex, rule-based constructs similar to linguistic expressions, we trained a transformer model -- proven to be effective in natural language tasks -- to predict the Lagrangian corresponding to a given list of particles. We report on the transformer's performance in constructing Lagrangians respecting the Standard Model $\mathrm{SU}(3)\times \mathrm{SU}(2)\times \mathrm{U}(1)$ gauge symmetries. The resulting model is shown to achieve high accuracies (over 90\%) with Lagrangians up to six matter fields, with the capacity to generalize beyond the training distribution, albeit within architectural constraints. We show through an analysis of input embeddings that the model has internalized concepts such as group representations and conjugation operations as it learned to generate Lagrangians. We make the model and training datasets available to the community. An interactive demonstration can be found at: \url{https://huggingface.co/spaces/JoseEliel/generate-lagrangians}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09729v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yong Sheng Koay, Rikard Enberg, Stefano Moretti, Eliel Camargo-Molina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Molecular $P_{\psi}$ pentaquarks from light-meson exchange saturation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.08211</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.08211v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Theoretical predictions for the spectrum of heavy meson-baryon bound states are a fundamental tool for disentangling the nature of the different pentaquark states that have been observed in experimental facilities. Here we explore this spectrum in a phenomenological model that describes the heavy meson-baryon interaction in terms of a contact-range interaction, where the coupling strength is saturated by the exchange of light scalar and vector mesons, i.e. $\sigma$, $\rho$ and $\omega$ exchanges. Saturation determines the couplings modulo an unknown proportionality constant that can be calibrated from a molecular candidate. If we use the $P_{\psi}^N(4312)$ as input, we predict a series of molecular pentaquarks including the $P_{\psi}^N(4440)$ and $P_{\psi}^N(4457)$, the recent $P_{\psi s}^{\Lambda}(4338)$ and the $P_{\psi s}^{\Lambda}(4459)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.08211v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.014012</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 111, 014012 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zi-Ying Yang, Fang-Zheng Peng, Mao-Jun Yan, Mario S\'anchez S\'anchez, Manuel Pavon Valderrama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dilution of Dark Matter Relic abundance due to First Order Electroweak Phase Transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.11230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.11230v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the effect of a first-order electroweak phase transition (FOEWPT), which is one of the prerequisites for electroweak baryogenesis, on the thermal relic abundance of the dark matter (DM) that freezes out before the occurrence of the phase transition in the complex singlet scalar extended $Z_3$-invariant type-II seesaw model that can simultaneously provide a DM candidate, explain the non-vanishing neutrino masses and the baryon asymmetry of the Universe. Such a phase transition around the electroweak scale leaves an impact on the relic density due to the release of entropy, particularly for a TeV-scale DM. We thus concentrate on the region of parameter space of the said model, which favors an FOEWPT in the early Universe and for which the DM is heavy such that its freeze-out temperature turns out to be larger than the phase transition temperature. We further study the dependencies of the dilution factor of the DM relic density on the model parameters, the nucleation temperature, the strength and the duration of the phase transition. Such a dilution might retrieve some of the regions of parameter space that were previously ruled out by the measured value of the DM relic density and/or the latest constraints from the DM direct-detection experiments. Furthermore, a direct connection is drawn between the dilution factor and the generation of stochastic gravitational waves as a result of an FOEWPT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.11230v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhojit Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring solutions to the muon g-2 anomaly in a 3-3-1 model under flavor constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05839v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The magnetic moment of the muon can receive significant two-loop contributions from a light pseudoscalar. Notably, the spectrum of scalars of 3-3-1 models include one pseudoscalar. However this scalar spectrum inevitably gives rise to flavor-changing neutral current (FCNC) processes. In this study, we examine, within the 3-3-1 model with right-handed neutrinos, whether such spectrum of scalars can account for the anomalous magnetic moment of the muon, considering the constraints imposed by $B$-meson decays, meson mixing, and invisible Higgs decays. Our principal finding reveals that a pseudoscalar with mass around 66 GeV and $\tan \beta =58$ can account for the $g-2$ anomaly without conflicting with flavor physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05839v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Doff, Joao Paulo Pinheiro, C. A. de S. Pires</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian technique to combine independently-trained Machine-Learning models applied to direct dark matter detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21008</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21008v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We carry out a Bayesian analysis of dark matter (DM) direct detection data to determine particle model parameters using the Truncated Marginal Neural Ratio Estimation (TMNRE) machine learning technique. TMNRE avoids an explicit calculation of the likelihood, which instead is estimated from simulated data, unlike in traditional Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) algorithms. This considerably speeds up, by several orders of magnitude, the computation of the posterior distributions, which allows to perform the Bayesian analysis of an otherwise computationally prohibitive number of benchmark points. In this article we demonstrate that, in the TMNRE framework, it is possible to include, combine, and remove different datasets in a modular fashion, which is fast and simple as there is no need to re-train the machine learning algorithm or to define a combined likelihood. In order to assess the performance of this method, we consider the case of WIMP DM with spin-dependent and independent interactions with protons and neutrons in a xenon experiment. After validating our results with MCMC, we employ the TMNRE procedure to determine the regions where the DM parameters can be reconstructed. Finally, we present CADDENA, a Python package that implements the modular Bayesian analysis of direct detection experiments described in this work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21008v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/01/038</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 01 (2025) 038</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>David Cerdeno, Martin de los Rios, Andres D. Perez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$n-\overline{n}$ Oscillation in $S^1/Z_2\times Z_2'$ Orbifold $SU(5)$ GUT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09489v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore the possibility of $B$ and $B-L$ violating processes, specifically proton decay and neutron-antineutron oscillation, using explicit realization of operators in the $SU(5)$ grand unified theory with an $S^1/Z_2 \times Z_2'$ orbifold space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09489v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2025.116802</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ankit Das, Sarthak Duary, Utpal Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advancing Tools for Simulation-Based Inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07315v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the benefit of modern simulation-based inference to constrain particle interactions at the LHC. We explore ways to incorporate known physics structures into likelihood estimation, specifically morphing-aware estimation and derivative learning. Technically, we introduce a new and more efficient smearing algorithm, illustrate how uncertainties can be approximated through repulsive ensembles, and show how equivariant networks can improve likelihood estimation. After illustrating these aspects for a toy model, we target di-boson production at the LHC and find that our improvements significantly increase numerical control and stability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07315v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henning Bahl, Victor Bres\'o, Giovanni De Crescenzo, Tilman Plehn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ensuring that toponium is glued, not nailed</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19180v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Hints of toponium might be incipient in LHC data, as given the vast numbers of t quarks produced, some survive on the exponential-decay tail long enough to fasten ttbar together. I here discuss a few differences between the standard Quantum Chromodynamics (QCD) binding (the ``glue'') and exotic short-range binding (the ``nail''). If the binding energy below threshold reaches the 3 GeV range the peak of the eta_t is distinct enough that a cross-section dip should be apparent in the line shape, should there only be one isolated resonance, but is filled by the excited QCD states adding about a pbarn to the cross section of ttbar production. Their effect for smaller binding energies is a tenuous increase in the cross section. A new-physics short-range interaction, on the other hand, yields a larger cross-section for equal binding energy (or hardly a visible bound state for similar cross section). This is due to its larger ttbar relative wavefunction at small distances. Finally, assuming that standard QCD plays out, I comment on what size of constraints on new-physics coefficients one can expect at given precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19180v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felipe J. Llanes-Estrada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational waves from supercooled phase transitions in conformal Majoron models of neutrino mass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02645</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02645v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study supercooled first-order phase transitions above the QCD scale in a wide class of conformal Majoron-like U(1)' models that explain the totality of active neutrino oscillation data and produce a detectable stochastic gravitational wave background (SGWB) at LIGO, LISA and ET. We place constraints on the U(1)' breaking scale and gauge coupling using current LIGO-Virgo-Kagra data. We find that strong supercooling can be ruled out in large regions of parameter space if a SGWB is not detected by these experiments. A null signal at LIGO and ET will disfavor a type-I seesaw scale above $10^{14}$ GeV, while a positive signal is a signature of heavy right-handed neutrinos. On the other hand, LISA will be sensitive to seesaw scales as low as a TeV, and could detect a SGWB even if the right-handed neutrinos are decoupled.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02645v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jo\~ao Gon\c{c}alves, Danny Marfatia, Ant\'onio P. Morais, Roman Pasechnik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Right-handed neutrino production through first-generation leptoquarks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19751v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The collider phenomenology of leptoquarks (LQs) and right-handed neutrinos (RHNs) has been studied extensively in the literature. Because of the gauge singlet nature, the production of RHNs at the LHC is typically suppressed by the tiny light-heavy neutrino mixing angles. In this study, we explore a promising scenario where the presence of an LQ mediator significantly enhances RHN production. We focus on first-generation scalar and vector LQs interacting with the first-generation RHN. The prospects are better for the first-generation scenario than the other generations because of the enhanced parton distribution functions (PDFs) of first-generation quarks. The enhanced PDFs boost the production cross sections of LQs, particularly their single and indirect productions. Incorporating all production modes of LQs that result in a pair of RHNs, we estimate the discovery prospects by analysing the monoelectron and dielectron channels arising from the decay of the RHN pair. We find that the indirect production of LQs is crucial in determining the discovery reach at the HL-LHC for the first-generation scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19751v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gokul Duraikandan, Rishabh Khanna, Tanumoy Mandal, Subhadip Mitra, Rachit Sharma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automation of Electroweak Corrections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05199</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05199v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This dissertation addresses a topic that I have worked on over the past decade: the automation of next-to-leading order electroweak corrections in the Standard Model of particle physics. After introducing the basic concepts and techniques of next-to-leading order QCD calculations that underpin the MadGraph5_aMC@NLO framework, I present a few key features relevant to the automated next-to-leading order electroweak contributions to short-distance cross sections, with an emphasis on the mixed QCD and electroweak coupling expansions. These include the FKS subtraction, the renormalization and electroweak input parameter schemes, and the complex mass scheme for dealing with unstable particles. Issues related to the initial or final photons and leptons are also discussed. Two remaining challenges are highlighted if one wishes to go beyond next-to-leading order computations. Some phenomenological applications at the LHC are given to demonstrate the relevance of electroweak corrections at colliders. Finally, an outlook on future studies concludes the dissertation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05199v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hua-Sheng Shao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searches for ultralight vector and axion dark matter with KAGRA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08930</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08930v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We have proposed using laser interferometric gravitational wave detectors to search for ultralight vector and axion dark matter. Vector dark matter can be probed through oscillating forces on suspended mirrors, while axion dark matter can be detected via oscillating polarization rotation of laser beams. This paper reviews these searches with the KAGRA detector in Japan, including the first vector dark matter search with KAGRA's 2020 data and installation of polarization optics for axion dark matter search during the upcoming 2025 observing run.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08930v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuta Michimura, Takumi Fujimori, Hiroki Fujimoto, Tomohiro Fujita, Kentaro Komori, Jun'ya Kume, Yusuke Manita, Soichiro Morisaki, Koji Nagano, Atsushi Nishizawa, Ippei Obata, Yuka Oshima, Hinata Takidera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ABJ anomaly as a U(1) symmetry and Noether's theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.03264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.03264v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Adler-Bell-Jackiw anomaly determines the violation of chiral symmetry when massless fermions are coupled to an abelian gauge field. In its seminal paper, Adler noticed that a modified chiral U(1) symmetry could still be defined, at the expense of being generated by a non-gauge-invariant conserved current. We show this internal U(1) symmetry has the special feature that it transforms the Haag duality violating sectors (or non-local operator classes). This provides a simple unifying perspective on the origin of anomaly quantization, anomaly matching, applicability of Goldstone theorem, and the absence of a Noether current. We comment on recent literature where this symmetry is considered to be either absent or non-invertible. We end by recalling the DHR reconstruction theorem, which states 0-form symmetries cannot be non-invertible for d&gt;2, and argue for a higher-form symmetry reconstruction theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.03264v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valentin Benedetti, Horacio Casini, Javier M. Magan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synchrotron radiation from cosmic string wakes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.12643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.12643v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Magnetic fields can be generated in cosmic string wakes due to the Biermann mechanism in the presence of neutrino inhomogeneities. As the cosmic string moves through the plasma the small magnetic field is amplified by the turbulence in the plasma. Relativistic charged particles which cross the magnetized wake of a cosmic string will therefore emit synchrotron radiation. The opening angle of the cosmic string is very small and so the wake appears like a relativistic jet. Assuming a homogeneous magnetic field in the wake of the string, we obtain the synchrotron emission from non thermal relativistic electrons in the wake of the string. The emitted radiation has a broad peak and is over a wide range of frequency. We show that the spectrum can be mapped to some of the unknown sources in different ranges of the current available catalogues.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.12643v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dilip Kumar, Soumen Nayak, Soma Sanyal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal, fast, and robust inference of reionization-era cosmology with the 21cmPIE-INN</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.04174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.04174v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Modern machine learning will allow for simulation-based inference from reionization-era 21cm observations at the Square Kilometre Array. Our framework combines a convolutional summary network and a conditional invertible network through a physics-inspired latent representation. It allows for an optimal and extremely fast determination of the posteriors of astrophysical and cosmological parameters. The sensitivity to non-Gaussian information makes our method a promising alternative to the established power spectra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.04174v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benedikt Schosser, Caroline Heneka, Tilman Plehn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for Pseudo-Dirac neutrinos from Astrophysical sources in IceCube data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06476v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We analyze IceCube public data from its IC86 configuration, namely PSTracks event selection, to search for pseudo-Dirac signatures in high-energy neutrinos from astrophysical sources. Neutrino flux from astrophysical sources is reduced in the pseudo-Dirac scenario due to the conversion of active-to-sterile neutrinos as compared to the neutrino oscillation scenario of only three active neutrinos over astrophysical distances. We fit IceCube data using astrophysical flux models for three point-like sources in both scenarios and constrain the active-sterile mass-square-difference in the absence of any evidence for pseudo-Dirac scenario. We find that a common mass-squared-difference $\delta m^2$ for all three flavors can be constrained as $\delta m^2 \lesssim 3 \times 10^{-19}~eV^2$ for the source NGC 1068, $\delta m^2 \lesssim 1.5 \times 10^{-20}~eV^2$ for the source TXS 0506+056, $\delta m^2 \lesssim 2.2 \times 10^{-21}~eV^2$ for the source PKS 1424+240 and $\delta m^2 \lesssim 8.5 \times 10^{-19}~eV^2$ for the source NGC 4151 at 90% C.L. A stacking analysis gives a constraint on $\delta m^2 \lesssim 2.2 \times 10^{-21}~eV^2$ at 90% CL which is dominated by the constraint obtained from PKS 1424+240.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06476v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Khushboo Dixit, Luis Salvador Miranda, Soebur Razzaque</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insights into Dark Matter Direct Detection Experiments: Decision Trees versus Deep Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10372v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The detection of Dark Matter (DM) remains a significant challenge in particle physics. This study exploits advanced machine learning models to improve detection capabilities of liquid xenon time projection chamber experiments, utilizing state-of-the-art transformers alongside traditional methods like Multilayer Perceptrons and Convolutional Neural Networks. We evaluate various data representations and find that simplified feature representations, particularly corrected S1 and S2 signals as well as a few shape-related features including the time difference between signals, retain critical information for classification. Our results show that while transformers offer promising performance, simpler models like XGBoost can achieve comparable results with optimal data representations. We also derive exclusion limits in the cross-section versus DM mass parameter space, showing minimal differences between XGBoost and the best performing deep learning models. The comparative analysis of different machine learning approaches provides a valuable reference for future experiments by guiding the choice of models and data representations to maximize detection capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10372v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/01/057</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 01 (2025) 057</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Daniel E. Lopez-Fogliani, Andres D. Perez, Roberto Ruiz de Austri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of the phase transition on Quark-Gluon Plasma with an extremely strong magnetic field in holographic QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00467v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the phase transition within an extremely strong magnetic background field, employing a holographic Quantum Chromodynamics (QCD) model with a focus on entropy and pressure properties. At relatively modest magnetic field strengths, our study discerns a crossover transition between the normal phase and the Quark-Gluon Plasma (QGP) phase as the temperature rises. In contrast, under the influence of an extremely strong magnetic field, a first-order phase transition is observed. A critical point is identified at $ (eB_c, T_c) \approx (2.8623 \, \text{GeV}^2, 0.1191 \, \text{GeV}) $, which corresponds to a second-order phase transition. This phase structure is found to be in qualitative agreement with lattice simulation predictions reported in [Phys. Rev. D \textbf{105}, 034511 (2022)]. Furthermore, we explore the impact of the magnetic field on the jet quenching parameter across various phases. At zero magnetic field ($ eB = 0$ ), the normalized jet quenching parameter $ \hat{q} / T^3 $ exhibits a monotonic increase with temperature. However, in the presence of a magnetic background field, the normalized jet quenching parameters not only display directional anisotropy but also experience a universal enhancement, particularly in the vicinity of the critical temperature region. This observation suggests that the jet quenching parameter could potentially act as an indicator of phase transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00467v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuanmin Cao, Hui Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multimessenger study of baryon-charged QCD matter in heavy-ion collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08501v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Multimessenger studies of heavy-ion collisions, using hadrons and electromagnetic probes, can reveal the properties of the created QCD matter from different perspectives. This study calculates the thermal dilepton invariant mass spectra and thermal photon transverse momentum spectra in Au+Au collisions at low beam energies from the Beam Energy Scan program, using a (3+1)-dimensional multistage hydrodynamic model calibrated by rapidity-dependent hadronic distributions. The effects of thermodynamic rapidity variation, baryon chemical potential, and fluid expansion on the spectra are explored. Methods for extracting temperature from photon and dilepton spectra are examined by comparison with the underlying hydrodynamic temperature. The possibility of combining photon and dilepton spectra to extract radial flow is also investigated. This study provides insights into measuring the thermodynamic properties of the created systems in heavy-ion collisions using multiple messengers through two fundamental interactions within the same framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08501v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lipei Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of a rare beta decay of the charmed baryon with a Graph Neural Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13515v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The beta decay of the lightest charmed baryon $\Lambda_c^+$ provides unique insights into the fundamental mechanism of strong and electro-weak interactions, serving as a testbed for investigating non-perturbative quantum chromodynamics and constraining the Cabibbo-Kobayashi-Maskawa (CKM) matrix parameters. This article presents the first observation of the Cabibbo-suppressed decay $\Lambda_c^+ \rightarrow n e^+ \nu_{e}$, utilizing $4.5~\mathrm{fb}^{-1}$ of electron-positron annihilation data collected with the BESIII detector. A novel Graph Neural Network based technique effectively separates signals from dominant backgrounds, notably $\Lambda_c^+ \rightarrow \Lambda e^+ \nu_{e}$, achieving a statistical significance exceeding $10\sigma$. The absolute branching fraction is measured to be $(3.57\pm0.34_{\mathrm{stat.}}\pm0.14_{\mathrm{syst.}})\times 10^{-3}$. For the first time, the CKM matrix element $\left|V_{cd}\right|$ is extracted via a charmed baryon decay as $0.208\pm0.011_{\rm exp.}\pm0.007_{\rm LQCD}\pm0.001_{\tau_{\Lambda_c^+}}$. This work highlights a new approach to further understand fundamental interactions in the charmed baryon sector, and showcases the power of modern machine learning techniques in experimental high-energy physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13515v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-024-55042-y</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Commun. 16, 681 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> BESIII Collaboration, M. Ablikim, M. N. Achasov, P. Adlarson, O. Afedulidis, X. C. Ai, R. Aliberti, A. Amoroso, Q. An, Y. Bai, O. Bakina, I. Balossino, Y. Ban, H. -R. Bao, V. Batozskaya, K. Begzsuren, N. Berger, M. Berlowski, M. Bertani, D. Bettoni, F. Bianchi, E. Bianco, A. Bortone, I. Boyko, R. A. Briere, A. Brueggemann, H. Cai, X. Cai, A. Calcaterra, G. F. Cao, N. Cao, S. A. Cetin, J. F. Chang, G. R. Che, G. Chelkov, C. Chen, C. H. Chen, Chao Chen, G. Chen, H. S. Chen, H. Y. Chen, M. L. Chen, S. J. Chen, S. L. Chen, S. M. Chen, T. Chen, X. R. Chen, X. T. Chen, Y. B. Chen, Y. Q. Chen, Z. J. Chen, Z. Y. Chen, S. K. Choi, G. Cibinetto, F. Cossio, J. J. Cui, H. L. Dai, J. P. Dai, A. Dbeyssi, R. E. de Boer, D. Dedovich, C. Q. Deng, Z. Y. Deng, A. Denig, I. Denysenko, M. Destefanis, F. De Mori, B. Ding, X. X. Ding, Y. Ding, Y. Ding, J. Dong, L. Y. Dong, M. Y. Dong, X. Dong, M. C. Du, S. X. Du, Y. Y. Duan, Z. H. Duan, P. Egorov, Y. H. Fan, J. Fang, J. Fang, S. S. Fang, W. X. Fang, Y. Fang, Y. Q. Fang, R. Farinelli, L. Fava, F. Feldbauer, G. Felici, C. Q. Feng, J. H. Feng, Y. T. Feng, M. Fritsch, C. D. Fu, J. L. Fu, Y. W. Fu, H. Gao, X. B. Gao, Y. N. Gao, Yang Gao, S. Garbolino, I. Garzia, L. Ge, P. T. Ge, Z. W. Ge, C. Geng, E. M. Gersabeck, A. Gilman, K. Goetzen, L. Gong, W. X. Gong, W. Gradl, S. Gramigna, M. Greco, M. H. Gu, Y. T. Gu, C. Y. Guan, A. Q. Guo, L. B. Guo, M. J. Guo, R. P. Guo, Y. P. Guo, A. Guskov, J. Gutierrez, K. L. Han, T. T. Han, F. Hanisch, X. Q. Hao, F. A. Harris, K. K. He, K. L. He, F. H. Heinsius, C. H. Heinz, Y. K. Heng, C. Herold, T. Holtmann, P. C. Hong, G. Y. Hou, X. T. Hou, Y. R. Hou, Z. L. Hou, B. Y. Hu, H. M. Hu, J. F. Hu, S. L. Hu, T. Hu, Y. Hu, G. S. Huang, K. X. Huang, L. Q. Huang, X. T. Huang, Y. P. Huang, T. Hussain, F. H\"olzken, N. H\"usken, N. in der Wiesche, J. Jackson, S. Janchiv, J. H. Jeong, Q. Ji, Q. P. Ji, W. Ji, X. B. Ji, X. L. Ji, Y. Y. Ji, X. Q. Jia, Z. K. Jia, D. Jiang, H. B. Jiang, P. C. Jiang, S. S. Jiang, T. J. Jiang, X. S. Jiang, Y. Jiang, J. B. Jiao, J. K. Jiao, Z. Jiao, S. Jin, Y. Jin, M. Q. Jing, X. M. Jing, T. Johansson, S. Kabana, N. Kalantar-Nayestanaki, X. L. Kang, X. S. Kang, M. Kavatsyuk, B. C. Ke, V. Khachatryan, A. Khoukaz, R. Kiuchi, O. B. Kolcu, B. Kopf, M. Kuessner, X. Kui, N. Kumar, A. Kupsc, W. K\"uhn, J. J. Lane, P. Larin, L. Lavezzi, T. T. Lei, Z. H. Lei, M. Lellmann, T. Lenz, C. Li, C. Li, C. H. Li, Cheng Li, D. M. Li, F. Li, G. Li, H. B. Li, H. J. Li, H. N. Li, Hui Li, J. R. Li, J. S. Li, K. Li, L. J. Li, L. K. Li, Lei Li, M. H. Li, P. R. Li, Q. M. Li, Q. X. Li, R. Li, S. X. Li, T. Li, W. D. Li, W. G. Li, X. Li, X. H. Li, X. L. Li, X. Y. Li, X. Z. Li, Y. G. Li, Z. J. Li, Z. Y. Li, C. Liang, H. Liang, H. Liang, Y. F. Liang, Y. T. Liang, G. R. Liao, L. Z. Liao, Y. P. Liao, J. Libby, A. Limphirat, C. C. Lin, D. X. Lin, T. Lin, B. J. Liu, B. X. Liu, C. Liu, C. X. Liu, F. Liu, F. H. Liu, Feng Liu, G. M. Liu, H. Liu, H. B. Liu, H. H. Liu, H. M. Liu, Huihui Liu, J. B. Liu, J. Y. Liu, K. Liu, K. Y. Liu, Ke Liu, L. Liu, L. C. Liu, Lu Liu, M. H. Liu, P. L. Liu, Q. Liu, S. B. Liu, T. Liu, W. K. Liu, W. M. Liu, X. Liu, X. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. Liu, Y. B. Liu, Z. A. Liu, Z. D. Liu, Z. Q. Liu, X. C. Lou, F. X. Lu, H. J. Lu, J. G. Lu, X. L. Lu, Y. Lu, Y. P. Lu, Z. H. Lu, C. L. Luo, J. R. Luo, M. X. Luo, T. Luo, X. L. Luo, X. R. Lyu, Y. F. Lyu, F. C. Ma, H. Ma, H. L. Ma, J. L. Ma, L. L. Ma, M. M. Ma, Q. M. Ma, R. Q. Ma, T. Ma, X. T. Ma, X. Y. Ma, Y. Ma, Y. M. Ma, F. E. Maas, M. Maggiora, S. Malde, Y. J. Mao, Z. P. Mao, S. Marcello, Z. X. Meng, J. G. Messchendorp, G. Mezzadri, H. Miao, T. J. Min, R. E. Mitchell, X. H. Mo, B. Moses, N. Yu. Muchnoi, J. Muskalla, Y. Nefedov, F. Nerling, L. S. Nie, I. B. Nikolaev, Z. Ning, S. Nisar, Q. L. Niu, W. D. Niu, Y. Niu, S. L. Olsen, Q. Ouyang, S. Pacetti, X. Pan, Y. Pan, A. Pathak, P. Patteri, Y. P. Pei, M. Pelizaeus, H. P. Peng, Y. Y. Peng, K. Peters, J. L. Ping, R. G. Ping, S. Plura, V. Prasad, F. Z. Qi, H. Qi, H. R. Qi, M. Qi, T. Y. Qi, S. Qian, W. B. Qian, C. F. Qiao, X. K. Qiao, J. J. Qin, L. Q. Qin, L. Y. Qin, X. S. Qin, Z. H. Qin, J. F. Qiu, Z. H. Qu, C. F. Redmer, K. J. Ren, A. Rivetti, M. Rolo, G. Rong, Ch. Rosner, S. N. Ruan, N. Salone, A. Sarantsev, Y. Schelhaas, K. Schoenning, M. Scodeggio, K. Y. Shan, W. Shan, X. Y. Shan, Z. J. Shang, J. F. Shangguan, L. G. Shao, M. Shao, C. P. Shen, H. F. Shen, W. H. Shen, X. Y. Shen, B. A. Shi, H. Shi, H. C. Shi, J. L. Shi, J. Y. Shi, Q. Q. Shi, S. Y. Shi, X. Shi, J. J. Song, T. Z. Song, W. M. Song, Y. J. Song, Y. X. Song, S. Sosio, S. Spataro, F. Stieler, Y. J. Su, G. B. Sun, G. X. Sun, H. Sun, H. K. Sun, J. F. Sun, K. Sun, L. Sun, S. S. Sun, T. Sun, W. Y. Sun, Y. Sun, Y. J. Sun, Y. Z. Sun, Z. Q. Sun, Z. T. Sun, C. J. Tang, G. Y. Tang, J. Tang, M. Tang, Y. A. Tang, L. Y. Tao, Q. T. Tao, M. Tat, J. X. Teng, V. Thoren, W. H. Tian, Y. Tian, Z. F. Tian, I. Uman, Y. Wan, S. J. Wang, B. Wang, B. L. Wang, Bo Wang, D. Y. Wang, F. Wang, H. J. Wang, J. J. Wang, J. P. Wang, K. Wang, L. L. Wang, M. Wang, N. Y. Wang, S. Wang, S. Wang, T. Wang, T. J. Wang, W. Wang, W. Wang, W. P. Wang, X. Wang, X. F. Wang, X. J. Wang, X. L. Wang, X. N. Wang, Y. Wang, Y. D. Wang, Y. F. Wang, Y. L. Wang, Y. N. Wang, Y. Q. Wang, Yaqian Wang, Yi Wang, Z. Wang, Z. L. Wang, Z. Y. Wang, Ziyi Wang, D. H. Wei, F. Weidner, S. P. Wen, Y. R. Wen, U. Wiedner, G. Wilkinson, M. Wolke, L. Wollenberg, C. Wu, J. F. Wu, L. H. Wu, L. J. Wu, X. Wu, X. H. Wu, Y. Wu, Y. H. Wu, Y. J. Wu, Z. Wu, L. Xia, X. M. Xian, B. H. Xiang, T. Xiang, D. Xiao, G. Y. Xiao, S. Y. Xiao, Y. L. Xiao, Z. J. Xiao, C. Xie, X. H. Xie, Y. Xie, Y. G. Xie, Y. H. Xie, Z. P. Xie, T. Y. Xing, C. F. Xu, C. J. Xu, G. F. Xu, H. Y. Xu, M. Xu, Q. J. Xu, Q. N. Xu, W. Xu, W. L. Xu, X. P. Xu, Y. C. Xu, Z. P. Xu, Z. S. Xu, F. Yan, L. Yan, W. B. Yan, W. C. Yan, X. Q. Yan, H. J. Yang, H. L. Yang, H. X. Yang, T. Yang, Y. Yang, Y. F. Yang, Y. F. Yang, Y. X. Yang, Z. W. Yang, Z. P. Yao, M. Ye, M. H. Ye, J. H. Yin, Z. Y. You, B. X. Yu, C. X. Yu, G. Yu, J. S. Yu, T. Yu, X. D. Yu, Y. C. Yu, C. Z. Yuan, J. Yuan, J. Yuan, L. Yuan, S. C. Yuan, Y. Yuan, Z. Y. Yuan, C. X. Yue, A. A. Zafar, F. R. Zeng, S. H. Zeng, X. Zeng, Y. Zeng, Y. J. Zeng, Y. J. Zeng, X. Y. Zhai, Y. C. Zhai, Y. H. Zhan, A. Q. Zhang, B. L. Zhang, B. X. Zhang, D. H. Zhang, G. Y. Zhang, H. Zhang, H. Zhang, H. C. Zhang, H. H. Zhang, H. H. Zhang, H. Q. Zhang, H. R. Zhang, H. Y. Zhang, J. Zhang, J. Zhang, J. J. Zhang, J. L. Zhang, J. Q. Zhang, J. S. Zhang, J. W. Zhang, J. X. Zhang, J. Y. Zhang, J. Z. Zhang, Jianyu Zhang, L. M. Zhang, Lei Zhang, P. Zhang, Q. Y. Zhang, R. Y. Zhang, S. H. Zhang, Shulei Zhang, X. D. Zhang, X. M. Zhang, X. Y. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Y. T. Zhang, Y. H. Zhang, Y. M. Zhang, Yan Zhang, Z. D. Zhang, Z. H. Zhang, Z. L. Zhang, Z. Y. Zhang, Z. Y. Zhang, Z. Z. Zhang, G. Zhao, J. Y. Zhao, J. Z. Zhao, L. Zhao, Lei Zhao, M. G. Zhao, N. Zhao, R. P. Zhao, S. J. Zhao, Y. B. Zhao, Y. X. Zhao, Z. G. Zhao, A. Zhemchugov, B. Zheng, B. M. Zheng, J. P. Zheng, W. J. Zheng, Y. H. Zheng, B. Zhong, X. Zhong, H. Zhou, J. Y. Zhou, L. P. Zhou, S. Zhou, X. Zhou, X. K. Zhou, X. R. Zhou, X. Y. Zhou, Y. Z. Zhou, J. Zhu, K. Zhu, K. J. Zhu, K. S. Zhu, L. Zhu, L. X. Zhu, S. H. Zhu, S. Q. Zhu, T. J. Zhu, W. D. Zhu, Y. C. Zhu, Z. A. Zhu, J. H. Zou, J. Zu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inflationary observables in $F(R)$ gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19030</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19030v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present phenomenological signatures for a modified gravity model f(R), constructed with linear, quadratic, cubic and quartic terms. The obtained signatures satisfy current phenomenological bounds reported by PLANCK and BICEP3. Furthermore, two of the model solutions $\sigma_1$ and $\sigma_2$ seem to favor a much lower value for the tensor-to-scalar ratio $0.0005&lt;r_{\sigma_1}&lt;0.0015$ and $r_{\sigma_2}&lt;0.00015$ than the current reported experimental bounds. The results we obtained are quantitatively similar to those presented in previous studies for $R^3$ models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19030v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrique Diaz, Oscar Meza-Aldama</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
