<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph</link>
    <description>hep-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 05:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Deep learning optimal molecular scintillators for dark matter direct detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00091</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00091v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Direct searches for sub-GeV dark matter are limited by the intrinsic quantum properties of the target material. In this proof-of-concept study, we argue that this problem is particularly well suited for machine learning. We demonstrate that a simple neural architecture consisting of a variational autoencoder and a multi-layer perceptron can efficiently generate unique molecules with desired properties. In specific, the energy threshold and signal (quantum) efficiency determine the minimum mass and cross section to which a detector can be sensitive. Organic molecules present a particularly interesting class of materials with intrinsically anisotropic electronic responses and $\mathcal{O}$(few) eV excitation energies. However, the space of possible organic compounds is intractably large, which makes traditional database screening challenging. We adopt excitation energies and proxy transition matrix elements as target properties learned by our network. Our model is able to generate molecules that are not in even the most expansive quantum chemistry databases and predict their relevant properties for high-throughput and efficient screening. Following a massive generation of novel molecules, we use clustering analysis to identify some of the most promising molecular structures that optimise the desired molecular properties for dark matter detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00091v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cameron Cook, Carlos Blanco, Juri Smirnov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite width effects in nonleptonic D-decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00117v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many analyses of two-body non-leptonic decays of $D$-mesons rely on flavor SU(3) symmetry relations and fits of experimental data of decays rates to extract the universal transition amplitudes. Such fits assume that the final state mesons are well-defined asymptotic states of QCD. We develop a technique to take into account the finite width effects of the final state mesons and study their effects on the extracted values of transition amplitudes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00117v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Girish Kumar, Sudheer Muhammad, Alexey A. Petrov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermi-ball in a multicomponent dark matter framework and its gravitational wave signatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00131v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It has been known that under-abundant dark matter density of an inert doublet can be replenished by an additional dark matter component, say, a fermion. We find that such a scenario can lead to the formation of stable Fermi-balls through coexisting minima of the finite temperature scalar potential. More importantly, we demonstrate that the Fermi-balls contribute sizeably to the dark matter relic density. In addition, the aforesaid coexisting minima open up the possibility of a first-order phase transition. This, in turn, triggers emission of gravitational waves that can be tested at the proposed BBO and U-DECIGO detectors. Therefore, the present study becomes a concrete setup to embed Fermi-balls in a realistic two-component dark matter model, and, to test the same using gravitational wave signatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00131v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nabarun Chakrabarty, Indrani Chakraborty, Himadri Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Update on non-unitary mixing in the recent NO$\nu$A and T2K data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00146v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this letter, we have used a non-unitary mixing scheme to resolve the tension between NO$\nu$A and T2K data. It is demonstrated that the results of NO$\nu$A and T2K can be explained by the effects by non-unitary mixing arising from $\alpha_{00}$ and $\alpha_{10}$. For $\alpha_{00}$ there is a large overlap between the allowed NO$\nu$A and T2K regions for NH on the $\sin^2\theta_{23}-\delta_{\rm CP}$ plane at $1\,\sigma$. However, the tension still exists. NO$\nu$A rules out unitary mixing at a $3\,\sigma$ level, whereas T2K strongly prefers unitary mixing. For $\alpha_{10}$, the tension can be \textbf{well resolved} with the best-fit point for NH at $|\alpha_{10}|=0.06$ for both experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00146v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Yue Yu, Zishen Guan, Ushak Rahaman, Nikolina Ilic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UHECR measurements and physics at man-made accelerators: mutual constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00178</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00178v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Measurements of the products of UHECR interactions with the Earth's atmosphere, as obtained in Extended Air Shower experiments, offer important information concerning hadronic interactions, which for some aspects overlaps and for many others complements the information extracted by measurements of collisions at human-made accelerators. In this contribution I discuss some of the constraints that the UHE astroparticle and accelerator fields exercise one over each other, emphasizing the importance of further new measurements, through new experiments or observations, in both fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00178v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maria Vittoria Garzelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complete definition of $N \rightarrow \Delta$ transition generalized parton distributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00185</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00185v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revisit the definition of the leading-twist chiral-even generalized parton distributions (GPDs) for $N \to \Delta$ baryon transitions. We identify and address deficiencies in previous definitions of the transition GPDs inspired by the transition form factors of the vector and axial-vector currents. Through systematic analysis of all possible covariant structures, respecting discrete symmetries and the baryon spinor equations of motion, we derive complete sets of independent structures for the transition matrix elements of the vector and axial-vector partonic operators. They contain additional structures proportional to the light-cone vector, corresponding to transition GPDs of vanishing first moment, which were not included in previous parametrizations. Their presence is confirmed independently by the light-front multipole expansion and the cross-channel SO(3) partial-wave analysis of the transition matrix elements. Our analysis provides a complete definition of the $N \to \Delta$ transition GPDs for use in theoretical and phenomenological studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00185v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>June-Young Kim, Kirill M. Semenov-Tian-Shansky, Ho-Yeon Won, Sangyeong Son, Christian Weiss</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Possible explanations of the observed $\Lambda_c$ resonances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00268v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inspired by the latest experimental progress, we systematically study the OZI-allowed two-body strong decay properties of $1P$-, $1D$-, $2S$- and $2P$-wave $\Lambda_c$ baryons within the $j $-$j$ coupling scheme in the framework of the quark pair creation model. The calculations indicate that: (i) Taking the observed states $\Lambda_c(2595)^+$ and $\Lambda_c(2625)^+$ as the $1P$-wave $\lambda$-modes states $\Lambda_c|J^P=1/2^-,1\rangle_{\lambda}$ and $\Lambda_c|J^P=3/2^-,1\rangle_{\lambda}$, respectively, we can reproduce the experimental data well in theory. (ii) Combining with the measured mass and the decay properties of $\Lambda_c(2860)^+$, this excited state can be explained as $1D$-wave $\lambda$-mode state $\Lambda_c|J^P=3/2^+,1\rangle_{\lambda\lambda}$. (iii) The newly observed state $\Lambda_c(2910)^+$ may be assigned as one of the $1P$-wave $\rho$-mode states $\Lambda_c|J^P=3/2^-,2\rangle_{\rho}$ or $\Lambda_c|J^P=5/2^-,2\rangle_{\rho}$. Meanwhile, we notice that the partial decay width ratio between $\Sigma_c\pi$ and $\Sigma_c^*\pi$ for the two candidates is significantly different. Hence, experimental progress in this ratio measurement may shed light on the nature of $\Lambda_c(2910)^+$. (iv) According to the properties of $\Lambda_c(2765)^+$, we find that the $2S$-wave $\lambda$-mode state $\Lambda_{c1}|J^P=1/2^+,0\rangle_{\lambda}$ may be a potential candidate. (v) The $2P$-wave $\lambda$-mode state $\Lambda_{c1}|J^P=3/2^-,1\rangle_{\lambda}$ is mostly likely to be a good assignment of the controversial state $\Lambda_c(2940)^+$. Both the total decay width and partial decay ratio between $pD^0$ and $\Sigma_c\pi$ are in good agreement with the observations. (vi) In addition, for the missing $\Lambda_c$ excitations, we obtain their strong decay properties and hope that's useful for future experimental exploration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00268v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Bin Zhang, Li-Ye Xiao, Xian-Hui Zhong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermion Masses and Mixing in Pati-Salam Unification with $S_3$ Modular Symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00302</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00302v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Modular invariance has recently paved new promising directions in flavor model building. Motivated by this development, we present in this work the first implementation of the $S_3$ modular symmetry within the Pati-Salam unification framework, addressing the flavor structure of quarks and leptons. Assigning left- and right-handed matter fields as $S_3$ doublets or singlets, we propose three benchmark models that achieve compelling fits to sixteen observables including charged fermion mass ratios and flavor mixing parameters. Light neutrino masses arise via the type-I seesaw mechanism, and neutrino oscillation parameters are explored in light of the latest NuFIT-6.0 results. All models favor a normal neutrino mass ordering, with the atmospheric mixing angle lie in the lower octant. For models I and III, the effective Majorana mass $m_{\beta\beta}$ is within the reach of upcoming neutrinoless double-beta decay experiments, while it is too small to be detected in model II. Predicted leptonic CP-violating phases, the sum of active neutrino masses, and Majorana phases span wide but distinctive ranges, enabling future experiments to test and differentiate the proposed models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00302v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed Belfkir, Mohamed Amin Loualidi, Salah Nasri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct Measurement of Dark Matter Mass through the Scattering of a High-Energy Matter Beam</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00308</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00308v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In case of a successful scattering event of a high-energy matter beam on a Dark Matter (DM) particle, the DM mass can be directly measured without probing the New Physics (NP) interaction. The letter adopts a model-independent kinematical analysis to formulate the DM mass as a function of experimentally readable quantities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00308v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bibhabasu De</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Bjorken sum rule: heavy quarks and analytic coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00456</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00456v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the results of [1], where good agreement was obtained between calculations within the framework of analytic QCD and experimental data on polarized Bjorken sum rule. The heavy quark contributions are taken into account.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00456v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. R. Gabdrakhmanov, N. A. Gramotkov, A. V. Kotikov, O. V. Teryaev, D. A. Volkova, I. A. Zemlyakov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DW-genesis: generating the baryon number from domain walls</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00491v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that axionic domain walls, when they couple to the lepton number, can generate a net baryon and lepton number through the mechanism of spontaneous baryogenesis. We study systematically the baryon asymmetry produced by these domain walls (DWs) at annihilation, and refer to this process as DW-genesis. We find that the baryon number is maximised when the DW network collapses approximately at the moment when the $L$-violating interaction decouples. We explore the expected gravitational wave signal from the DW network annihilation and the prospects for detecting it, but conclude that successful DW-genesis is typically in tension with observable GW signal. Morever, we briefly discuss a possible suppression induced by the cancellation between the asymmetry created by "opposite" axionic domain walls attached to the string.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00491v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Vanvlasselaer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing $B^+ \to K^+$ semi-leptonic FCNC decay with new physics effects under PQCD approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00512v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, the Belle II Collaboration reported the branching fraction $\mathcal{B}(B^+ \to K^+ \nu \bar{\nu})=(2.3\pm0.7)\times10^{-5}$ with a significance of $3.5\sigma$, which is $2.7\sigma$ above the SM expectation. Motivated by this measurement, we calculate this decay channel at the NLO and twist-3 level using the PQCD approach. By combining the lattice QCD data and our results, we obtain form factors with improved accuracy. Using these form factors, we precisely estimate the branching ratios of $B^+ \to K^+$ semileptonic FCNC decays, including $B^+ \to K^+\nu\bar\nu$ and $B^+ \to K^+\ell^+\ell^-$. To explain the anomalies in these two processes, we introduce a leptoquark model as a new physics scenario. Using five possible types of leptoquarks, we successfully explain the latest experimental measurements, and further constraints on the leptoquarks are derived.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00512v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao-Qi Zhang, Jin Sun, Zhi-Peng Xing, Rui-Lin Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A holographic analysis of the pion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00526v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inspired by light-front holography, we compute the pion mass, charge radius, decay constant, electromagnetic form factor and electromagnetic transition form factor. To do so, we model the longitudinal quark dynamics using potentials due to 't Hooft and to Li &amp; Vary. We find a longitudinal wavefunction that is rather more peaked about $x \sim 1/2$ than in previous studies. We also explore the strong degeneracy between these two potentials and conclude by noting that one scenario that accords well with the data also maps onto an equation previously noted by Vegh that describes the dynamics of a four-segmented string in $\mathrm{AdS}_3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00526v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeff Forshaw, Ruben Sandapen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconstructing the electro-weak theory from a gauge theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00540</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00540v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: U(4) local transformations on the four Weyl spinors forming the isospin doublet of Dirac fermions are assumed as symmetries of the standard model. With the Lorentz transformations considered simultaneously, the symmetry group is enlarged in order to form a closed Lie algebra. In this framework, the chirality mixing gauge components with certain constraints collectively are identified as the Higgs field in the standard model. The scalar-appearance of the gauge-natured Higgs field and its varying coupling constants with the fermions, i.e. the mass-ratio parameters, are also given natural explanation. Additionally, a background of a constant right-handed gauge component is postulated to obtain the symmetry-breaking Higgs potential, which leads to a possible explanation of the parity violation in weak interactions. Further, the new framework provides an alternative perspective to understand the hyper symmetry U(1)Y , as a combination of a simultaneous phase rotation on both the left and right handed fermions and a rotation in the third direction of SU(2)R on the right-handed fermions. At last, a topological term involving the Higgs field is found to exist.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00540v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lu Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite size effects on the phase diagram and the baryon fluctuations via momentum space constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00548v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The effect of the finite system size on the QCD phase diagram was studied with various momentum space constraints within a mean-field quark-meson model. On the one hand side, the choice of the scenario -- low-momentum cutoff and discretization with periodic or antiperiodic boundary conditions -- and the presence of the vacuum fluctuations were found to strongly affect the volume dependence of the CEP. On the other hand, its location is significantly shifted in each case for linear sizes below $L\approx 10$ fm. This is also reflected in the conserved charge fluctuations, which were investigated along the phase boundary using multiple scenarios for the finite size effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00548v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gy\H{o}z\H{o} Kov\'acs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$B_c$, $B_s$ and $D_s$ production at lepton-hadron colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00550v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Within the framework of nonrelativistic quantum chromodynamics, this study examines the electroproduction processes $e+p\to e+B_c+\overline{c}+b$, $e+p\to e+B_s+\overline{s}+b$, and $e+p\to e+D_s+\overline{c}+s$ at lepton-hadron colliders. The differential cross sections in $\cos\theta$ and $p_T^2$ at HERA are presented. The results indicate that the production of $B_c$ is feasible at the EIC, whereas it is not at HERA. The cross sections for $B_s$ and $D_s$ are notably significant at HERA, yet they exhibit sensitivity to variations in quark mass and renormalization scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00550v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiwei Hu, Cong-Feng Qiao, Li-Ping Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The structure of quark mass corrections in the $gg \rightarrow HH$ amplitude at high-energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00587</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00587v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The leading and next-to-leading order QCD predictions for Higgs boson pair production at hadron colliders suffer from a significant mass renormalisation scheme uncertainty related to the choice of the top-quark mass. The functional dependence of the result on the value of the intermediate quark mass can be understood in the high-energy limit using the Method of Regions and the tools of Soft-Collinear Effective Theory. In this work, we study the origin of the sizeable logarithmic mass corrections in the $gg \to HH$ amplitudes at leading and next-to-leading power in the limit $s,|t|,|u| \gg m_t^2 \gg m_H^2$. We argue that the mass corrections follow a predictable factorised pattern that can be exploited to simplify their computation. We present results for the leading power leading logarithmic corrections, our analysis leads to a significant reduction in the theoretical uncertainty of the double Higgs production amplitudes at high-energy due to the top-quark mass scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00587v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Jaskiewicz, Stephen Jones, Robert Szafron, Yannick Ulrich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vector meson production associated with a lepton pair in $e^+$ $e^-$ annihilation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00592v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate a novel production mechanism of vector mesons, exemplified by the production of a neutral vector meson associated with a lepton pair in $e^+e^-$ annihilation, i.e., $e^+e^-\to V l^+l^-$ ($V=J/\psi, \rho^0, \omega, \phi$, and $l=\mu, \tau$). These vector meson production channels can be precisely accounted within QED. The production rates of these processes are dominated by those diagrams where the vector meson is emitted from either the incident electron or positron, which exhibit a $\ln^2 m_l^2$ enhancement stemming from the triple collinear limit of leptons. Our numerical analysis indicates that the corresponding production rates are substantial enough to warrant the observation of these novel vector meson production channels at BESIII and Belle II experiments in near future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00592v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Jia, Yang Liu, Juliang Lu, Guang Tang, Xiaonu Xiong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Leptogenesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00607v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the standard lore, the baryon asymmetry of the present universe is attributed to the leptogenesis from the sterile right-handed neutrino with heavy Majorana mass decaying into the Standard Model's leptons at the very early universe -- called the Majorana fermion's leptogenesis; while the electroweak sphaleron causes baryogenesis at a later time. In this work, we propose a new mechanism, named topological leptogenesis, to explain the lepton asymmetry. Topological leptogenesis replaces some of the sterile neutrinos by introducing a new gapped topological order sector (whose low-energy exhibits topological quantum field theory with long-range entanglement) that can cancel the baryon minus lepton $({\bf B} - {\bf L})$ mixed gauge-gravitational anomaly of the Standard Model. Then the Beyond-the-Standard-Model dark matter consists of topological quantum matter, such that the gapped non-particle excitations of extended line and surface defect with fractionalization and anyon charges can decay into the Standard Model particles. In addition, gravitational leptogenesis can be regarded as an intermediate step (between Majorana particle leptogenesis and topological non-particle leptogenesis) to mediate such decaying processes from the highly entangled gapped topological order excitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00607v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juven Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LHC and HL-LHC Bounds on Visible and Invisible Decays in the $B-L$ Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00610v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we use publicly available data from ATLAS collaboration collected at LHC run 2 at a center-of-mass energy of $\sqrt{s}=13$TeV with an integrated luminosity of $139 fb^{-1}$ to derive lower mass limits on the $Z^\prime$ gauge boson associated with the B-L gauge symmetry. Using dilepton data we find that $M_{Z^\prime} &gt; 4$TeV ($6$TeV) for $g_{BL}=0.1$ ($g_{BL}=0.5$) in the absence of invisible decays. Once invisible decays are turned on these limits are substantially relaxed. Assuming an invisible branching ratio of $BR_{inv}=0.9$, the LHC bound is loosened up to $M_{Z^\prime}&gt; 4.8$TeV for $g_{BL}=0.5$. This analysis confirms that the LHC now imposes stricter constraints than the longstanding bounds established by LEP. We also estimate the projected HL-LHC bounds that will operate with at $\sqrt{s}=14$TeV and a planned integrated luminosity of $\mathcal{L}=3 ab^{-1}$ that will probe $Z^\prime$ masses up to $7.5$TeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00610v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Farinaldo S. Queiroz, Jilberto Zamora-Saa, Ricardo C. Silva, Y. M. Oviedo-Torres</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncertainties in tellurium-based dark matter searches stemming from nuclear structure uncertainties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00621v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using tellurium dioxide as a target, we calculate uncertainties on 90% upper confidence limits of Galilean effective field theory (Galilean EFT) couplings to a WIMP dark matter particle due to uncertainties in nuclear shell models. We find that these uncertainties in naturally-occurring tellurium isotopes are comparable across the different Galilean EFT couplings to uncertainties in xenon, with some reaching over 100%. We also consider the effect these nuclear uncertainties have on estimates of the annual modulation of dark matter from these searches, finding that the uncertainties in the modulation amplitude are proportional to the non-modulating upper confidence limit uncertainties. We also show that the determination of the modulation phase is insensitive to changes in the nuclear model for a given isotope.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00621v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel J. Heimsoth, Rebecca Kowalski, Danielle H. Speller, Calvin W. Johnson, A. Baha Balantekin, Susan N. Coppersmith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing the Froggatt-Nielsen Mechanism with Lepton Violation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00629v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Froggatt-Nielsen (FN) mechanism offers an elegant explanation for the observed masses and mixings of Standard Model fermions. In this work, we systematically study FN models in the lepton sector, identifying a broad range of charge assignments ("textures") that naturally yield viable masses and mixings for various neutrino mass generation mechanisms. Using these textures, we consider higher-dimensional operators consistent with a FN origin and find that natural realizations predict distinct patterns in lepton flavor- and number-violating observables. For Dirac and Majorana neutrinos, FN-related correlations can lead to detectable rates of charged lepton flavor violation at next-generation low-energy experiments. Majorana and type-I seesaw models predict measurable rates of neutrinoless double beta decay. Determination of inverted neutrino mass ordering would exclude the Dirac neutrino FN scenario. Only a small minority of purely leptonic FN models predict detectable flavor violation at future muon colliders, though it is possible that a combined analysis with the quark sector will reveal motivated signals. These findings highlight the power of the FN mechanism to link neutrino mass generation to testable leptonic observables, offering new pathways for the experimental exploration of lepton number and underscoring the importance of next-generation low-energy probes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00629v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Claudia Cornella, David Curtin, Gordan Krnjaic, Micah Mellors</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strangeness in the proton from W+charm production and SIDIS data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00665v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We perform a global QCD analysis of unpolarized parton distribution functions (PDFs) in the proton, including new $W +\,$charm production data from $pp$ collisions at the LHC, which have been suggested for constraining the strange quark PDF. In particular, we assess the impact of the $W +\,$charm data relative to that of semi-inclusive pion and kaon production data in lepton-nucleon deep-inelastic scattering. Compared with a baseline global fit that does not include these datasets, we find that semi-inclusive deep-inelastic scattering and $W +\,$charm data combined favor a larger strange distribution, but smaller than the SU(3) symmetric sea suggested in previous analyses of ATLAS data. Combined, the ratio of strange to nonstrange sea quark distributions is $R_s = (s+\bar s)/(\bar u+\bar d) \approx \{ 0.72,\, 0.48,\, 0.26 \}$ for $x = \{ 0.01,\, 0.04,\, 0.1 \}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00665v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Trey Anderson, W. Melnitchouk, N. Sato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generic symmetry analysis of charmonium decay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00670v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For charmonium's decaying to the final states involving merely light quarks, in light of SU(3) flavor symmetry, a systematic parametrization scheme is established, which involving binary decays, ternary decays and radiative decays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00670v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>X. H. Mo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collins-Soper Kernel in the QCD Instanton Vacuum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00678v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We outline a general framework for evaluating the non-perturbative soft functions in the QCD instanton vacuum. In particular, from the soft function we derive the Collins-Soper (CS) kernel, which drives the rapidity evolution of the transverse-momentum-dependent parton distributions. The resulting CS kernel, when supplemented with the perturbative contribution, agrees well with recent lattice results and some phenomenological parameterizations. Moreover, our CS kernel depends logarithmically on the large quark transverse separation, providing a key constraint on its phenomenological parametrization. Finally, a lattice calculation can be directly compared to our generic results in Euclidean signature, thus providing a new approach for evaluating the soft function and extracting the CS kernel by analytical continuation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00678v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Yang Liu, Ismail Zahed, Yong Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring QGP-like phenomena with Charmonia in $p+p$ collisions at $\sqrt{s} = 13$ TeV</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00753v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In ultra-relativistic collisions of nuclei at the Large Hadron Collider, the created QCD environment rapidly changes, leading to a non-adiabatic evolution of the quantum states involved. Considering this, we first examine the pre-equilibrium state of QCD matter and its effect on the initially produced charmonium using a temperature-independent Hamiltonian. As the QCD matter reaches local thermal equilibrium, this Hamiltonian transforms to its finite temperature counterpart. To model the pre-equilibrium stage, we use the bottom-up thermalization approach to determine the effective temperature of the QCD matter, followed by a Gubser-type expansion for the thermalized medium. Additionally, we consider collisional damping, gluonic dissociation, and regeneration mechanisms, which specifically modify the charmonium yield in the thermalized medium. Mainly, the gluonic dissociation and collisional damping cause a reduction in the yield conversely, regeneration through gluonic de-excitation enhances the yield of charmonium. Further, we explore the combined effects of these mechanisms on the collective yield of charmonium states with transverse momentum ($p_{\rm T}$) and event multiplicity in the proton-proton collisions at $\sqrt{s} = 13$ TeV. Based on our findings, we contend that the combined effects of these mechanisms can serve as a robust probe for determining the possible existence of a thermalized QCD medium in such a small collision system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00753v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Captain R. Singh, Partha Bagchi, Raghunath Sahoo, Jan-e Alam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Generalized CP Symmetry, One Zero Texture in Neutrino Mass Matrix and Neutrinoless Double Beta Decay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00776v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we explore the impact of one zero textures on the neutrino mass matrix, focusing on their ability to constrain neutrino parameters such as mixing angles, Dirac and Majorana phases, and mass eigenstates. We investigate one zero textures within the framework of generalized CP symmetry associated with the complex tribimaximal matrix. By combining these approaches, we derive predictive neutrino mass matrices and elucidate correlations between various parameters. Additionally, we analyze neutrinoless double beta decay in the context of one zero textures, in the light of current and future experimental data. Our analysis shows that sum of the three neutrino masses in the inverted hierarchy is inconsistent with cosmological bounds provided by the Planck data, $\Sigma m_i &lt; 0.12\,\text{eV}$. We also include bounds from the DESI/SDSS+Pantheon+DES-SN dataset (\( \Sigma m_i &lt; 0.17\,\text{eV} \)) in the $\Lambda$CDM + Fluid DR + $\sum m_\nu$ model at 95\% confidence level, which completely disfavors the inverted hierarchy. Our findings highlight the enhanced predictability and testability of neutrino mass models that incorporate generalized CP symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00776v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Priya, Simran Arora, B. C. Chauhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trilepton and tetralepton bound and resonant states: the QED counterpart of multiquark states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00871v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work presents the first prediction of tetralepton resonant states containing muons, extending beyond the simplest tetralepton system, dipositronium ($\mathrm{Ps}_2$). With the rapid advancements in experimental facilities, the production and study of these intriguing states may be within reach. We perform a comprehensive analysis of S-wave trilepton and tetralepton systems within the framework of a QED Coulomb potential. We employ the Gaussian expansion method to solve the three- or four-body Schr\"odinger equation and utilize the complex scaling method to identify resonant states. We uncover a series of bound and resonant states in the trilepton systems $e^+e^+e^-$, $\mu^+\mu^+\mu^-$, $e^+e^+\mu^-$, and $\mu^+\mu^+e^-$, as well as the tetralepton systems $e^+e^+e^-e^-$, $\mu^+\mu^+\mu^-\mu^-$, and $\mu^+\mu^+e^-e^-$. The energies of these states range from $-30$ eV to $-1$ eV below the total mass of three or four leptons, with their widths varying from less than $0.01$ eV to approximately $0.07$ eV. Additionally, we calculate the spin configurations and root mean square radii of these states, providing insight into their spatial structures. No bound or resonant states are found in the trilepton $e^+\mu^+e^-$, $\mu^+e^+\mu^-$ systems, nor in the tetralepton $\mu^+e^+\mu^-e^-$ system. A comparison with fully heavy tetraquark systems reveals that the additional color degree of freedom in QCD results in the absence of low-energy bound and resonant states. However, this extra degree of freedom allows for a broader range of $J^{PC}$ quantum numbers to produce resonant states, highlighting the rich complexity of QCD systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00871v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yao Ma, Lu Meng, Liang-Zhen Wen, Shi-Lin Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forecast constraints on the axion-photon coupling from interstellar medium heating</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00992v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In interstellar media characterized by a nonrelativistic plasma of electrons and heavy ions, we study the effect of axion dark matter coupled to photons on the dynamics of an electric field. In particular, we assume the presence of a background magnetic field aligned in a specific direction. We show that there is an energy transfer from the oscillating axion field to photons and then to the plasma induced by forced resonance. This resonance is most prominent for the axion mass $m_{\phi}$ equivalent to the plasma frequency $\omega_p$. Requiring that the heating rate of the interstellar medium caused by the energy transfer does not exceed the observed astrophysical cooling rate, we place forecast constraints on the axion-photon coupling $g$ for several different amplitudes of the background magnetic field $B_0$. By choosing a typical value $B_0=10^{-5}$ G, we find that, for the resonance mass $m_{\phi}=\omega_p$, the upper limit of $g$ can be stronger than those derived from other measurements in the literature. With increased values of $B_0$, it is possible to put more stringent constraints on $g$ for a wider range of the axion mass away from the resonance point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00992v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Makoto Amakawa, Tomohiro Fujita, Shinji Tsujikawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for single production of vector-like quarks decaying into $Wb$ at a future muon-proton collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01026</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01026v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate the single production of the Vector-Like Quarks (VLQs) $T$ and $Y$, with charge $+2/3$e and $-4/3$e, respectively, both decaying into $Wb$ at a future $\mu p$ collider with $\sqrt{s}=5.29, 6.48$, and 9.16 TeV. We focus on two final states, where the $W$ boson decays leptonically or hadronically (in the latter case, it is highly boosted, leading to a fat $W$-jet). By performing a detailed signal-to-background analysis in presence of detector simulations, the $5\sigma$ discovery prospects and 95\% CL exclusion limits are mapped over parameter space regions of the model accommodating such new heavy quarks, assuming an integrated luminosity of 100 fb$^{-1}$ at each of the aforementioned energies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01026v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin-Zhong Han, Yao-Bei Liu, Stefano Moretti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$S$, $T$, $U$ Parameters in The B-LSSM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01060v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using the pinch technique, we compute the one-loop vertices of weak interactions in the B-LSSM and incorporate their pinch contributions into the gauge boson self-energies. Compared to the definitions of the $S$, $T$, and $U$ parameters in the Standard Model based on the $SU(2)_L\otimes U(1)_Y$ group, the corresponding parameters in the B-LSSM are modified. We provide these redefined $S$, $T$, and $U$ parameters and demonstrate the convergence of the results. In the framework of the low-energy effective Lagrangian for weak interactions, the $S$, $T$, and $U$ parameters can be expressed as functions of certain parameters in the B-LSSM. The updated experimental and fitting results constrain the parameter space of the B-LSSM strongly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01060v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sheng-Kai Cui, Ke-Sheng Sun, Yu-Li Yan, Jin-Lei Yang, Tai-Fu Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Studying the $B^{0} \to J/\psi h_{1}$ decays with $h_{1}(1170)-h_{1}(1415)$ mixing in the perturbative QCD approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01075v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the $B^{0} \to J/\psi h_{1}$ decays for the first time by using perturbative QCD approach up to the presently known next-to-leading order accuracy. The vertex corrections present significant contribution to the amplitude. In the calculation, the mixing between two light axial-vector mesons $h_{1}(1170)$ and $h_{1}(1415)$ are also studied in detail. The observables including the branching ratios, polarization fractions and $CP$ asymmetries are predicted and discussed explicitly. It is found that the $B^{0} \to J/\psi h_{1}$ decays have relatively large branching fractions, which are generally at the order of ${\cal O}(10^{-6}\sim10^{-3})$, and thus are possible to be observed by the LHCb and Belle-II experiments in the near future. Moreover, they are very sensitive to the mixing angle $\theta$ and can be used to test the values of $\theta$. In addition, some ratios between the branching fractions of $B^{0} \to J/\psi h_{1}$ decays can provide much stronger constraints on $\theta$ due to their relatively small theoretical errors. The $B^{0} \to J/\psi h_{1}$ decays are generally dominated by the longitudinal polarization contributions, specifically, $f_{L}(B^{0} \to J/\psi h_{1})&gt;80\%$, except for the case that $\theta\sim 35^\circ$ and $-55^\circ$. Unfortunately, the direct $CP$ asymmetries of $B^{0} \to J/\psi h_{1}$ decays are too small to be observed soon even if the effect of $\theta$ is considered. The future precise measurements on $B^{0} \to J/\psi h_{1}$ decays are expected for testing these theoretical findings and exploring the interesting nature of $h_{1}(1170)$ and $h_{1}(1415)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01075v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qin Chang, De-Hua Yao, Xin Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A coupled-channel perspective analysis on bottom-strange molecular pentaquarks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01077</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01077v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: At present work, we systematically study various bottom-strange molecular pentaquarks to search for possible bound states and resonances by adopting one-boson-exchange model within complex scaling method. According to our calculations, we predict several bound and resonant states for bottom baryon $Y_{b}(\Lambda_b,\Sigma_b) \bar K^{(*)}$ and $Y_{b} K^{(*)}$ systems. In particular, a bound state in the $I(J^P)=1/2(1/2^-)$ $\Sigma_{b}\bar{K}/\Lambda_{b}\bar{K}^*/\Sigma_{b}\bar{K}^*$ system may correspond to the particle $\Xi_{b}(6227)$. Meanwhile, the predicted bound state with $6303\sim6269~\rm{MeV}$ in the $I(J^P)=1/2(1/2^-)\Sigma_bK/\Lambda_bK^*/\Sigma_bK^*$ system is flavor exotic and does not appear in the spectroscopy of conventional baryons, which provides a practical way to clarify the nature of particle $\Xi_b(6227)$. We highly hope that our proposals can offer helpful information for the future experimental searches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01077v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qing-Fu Song, Qi-Fang L\"u, Xiaonu Xiong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gluon mass scale through the Schwinger mechanism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01080</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01080v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It has long been argued that the action of the Schwinger mechanism in the gauge sector of Quantum Chromodynamics leads to the generation of a gluon mass scale. Within this scenario, the analytic structure of the fundamental vertices is modified by the creation of scalar colored excitations with vanishing mass. In the limit of zero momentum transfer, these terms act as massless poles, providing the required conditions for the infrared stabilization of the gluon propagator, and producing a characteristic displacement to the associated Ward identities. In this article we offer an extensive overview of the salient notions and techniques underlying this dynamical picture. We place particular emphasis on recent developments related to the exact renormalization of the mass, the nonlinear nature of the pole equation, and the key role played by Fredholm's alternatives theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01080v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. N. Ferreira, J. Papavassiliou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of QCD sum rules coupling constants on neutron stars structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01234v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a detailed investigation on the structure of neutron stars, incorporating the presence of hyperons within a relativistic model under the mean-field approximation. Employing coupling constants derived from QCD sum rules, we explore the particle fraction in beta equilibrium and establish the mass-radius relationship for neutron stars with hyperonic matter. Additionally, we compute the stellar Love number ($\mathcal{K}_{2}$) and the tidal deformability parameter ($\varLambda$), providing valuable insights into the dynamical properties of these celestial objects. Through comparison with theoretical predictions and observational data, our results exhibit good agreement, affirming the validity of our approach. These findings contribute significantly to refining the understanding of neutron star physics, particularly in environments containing hyperons, and offer essential constraints on the equation of state governing such extreme astrophysical conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01234v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Moradi Jangal, H. R. Moshfegh, K. Azizi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Di-$\pi^0$ Production and Generalized Distribution Amplitudes at Future Electron-Ion Colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01267v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Generalized distribution amplitudes (GDAs) offer valuable insights into the three-dimensional structure of hadrons, delineating the amplitudes associated with the transition from a quark-antiquark pair to a hadron pair. Currently, hadron GDAs can be probed in electron-positron collisions, with experimental feasibility demonstrated at facilities such as Belle and BESIII. In this study, we put forth the proposition that hadron GDAs can also be investigated in electron-hadron collisions at forthcoming Electron-Ion Colliders (EICs), specifically through the subprocess $\gamma^*\gamma \to h_1 h_2$. In this framework, a quasi-real photon, emitted by the ion, exhibits a photon flux proportional to the square of the ion's electric charge. Consequently, we anticipate that the cross sections in EICs will be substantially larger than those in electron-positron collisions. We present numerical calculations pertaining to di-$\pi^0$ production employing the equivalent photon approximation (EPA). Our findings suggest that, within the same kinematic region, electron-proton ($e$-$p$) collisions at the EIC could yield an event rate comparable to that of Belle II, while electron-gold ($e$-Au) collisions are expected to generate an even greater number of events. This enhanced event rate facilitates a high-precision examination of di-$\pi^0$ GDAs at the EIC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01267v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bing'ang Guo, Jing Han, Ya-Ping Xie, Xurong Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational waves from color restoration in a leptoquark model of radiative neutrino masses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01286v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the first-order phase transitions and the emerging stochastic gravitational wave spectrum in a minimal leptoquark extension of the Standard Model that explains active neutrino oscillation data while satisfying current flavor physics constraints. This model exhibits diverse phase transition patterns, including color symmetry-breaking scenarios in the early Universe. Strong correlations between model parameters and gravitational-wave signals yield testable predictions for future experiments such as LISA, BBO, and DECIGO. Specifically, a detectable signal in the mHz$\unicode{x2013}$0.1~Hz frequency range features color-restoration and leptoquark masses near $1.5~\mathrm{TeV}$. With this article, we also present the first application in the literature of \texttt{Dratopi}. This is a soon-to-be-released tool for phase transition analysis using the dimensional reduction formalism, that interfaces the \texttt{DRalgo} package with \texttt{Python} and a slightly modified version of \texttt{CosmoTransitions}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01286v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M{\aa}rten Bertenstam, Marco Finetti, Ant\'onio P. Morais, Roman Pasechnik, Johan Rathsman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-loop dimension Six Effective Action: Integrating Out Heavy Scalar</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01313v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For the first time, we present the model-independent two-loop effective action up to dimension six after integrating out heavy scalar(s) employing the Heat-Kernel method. We compute the effective operators that emerge at two-loop for two example models: heavy electroweak complex Triplet and Doublet scalars. We present our results on the SILH basis. We also capture the effect in the fermion sector. For these two scenarios, we compute all the fermionic effective operators up to dimension six.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01313v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nilabhra Adhikary, Jaydeb Das, Debmalya Dey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Responses of the Standard Model Gauge Group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21196v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Built upon the previous work on the 4d anomalies and 5d cobordism invariants (namely, 5d invertible field theory [iTFT] or symmetry-protected topological state [SPTs]) of the Standard Model [SM] gauge theory with compatible (SU(3)$\times$SU(2)$\times$U(1))/$\mathbb{Z}_q$ gauge group for $q=1,2,3,6$, we further enumerate lower-dimensional iTFT / SPTs in 4d, 3d, 2d, and 1d. While the 4d SPTs are interesting gapped phases attachable to the SM, those integer classes of SPTs (either the torsion or the free cobordism class) are not universal and are difficult to detect. However, fractional SPTs are more universal and can be detected by a topological response similar to the Hall conductance under an appropriate symmetry twist background field. We find a nontrivial symmetry-extension from a magnetic 1-symmetry U(1)$_{[1]}^m$ by an electric 1-symmetry $\mathbb{Z}_{6/q,[1]}^e$ introducing the $k \in \mathbb{Z}_{6/q}$ fractionalization class. While we also introduce the background fields for Baryon minus Lepton number $({\bf B}-{\bf L})$ like 0-symmetries of U(1)$_{{\bf Q} - N_c {\bf L}}$, U(1)$_X$, and $\mathbb{Z}_{4,X}$, that introduces two more data $\alpha \in 1,3$ and $\beta \in 1,5$ for the SMs. We present their Hall conductance response data (denoted as $\sigma, \sigma'$, and $\sigma''$ respectively), between 0-symmetry and 1-symmetry background fields, and show their fractional dependence on the SM data $(q,\alpha,\beta, k)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21196v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheyan Wan, Juven Wang, Yi-Zhuang You</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Erratum: Exact solutions to the fermion propagator Schwinger-Dyson equation in Minkowski space with on-shell renormalization for quenched QED \newline [Phys. Rev. D 96, 036021 (2017)]</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00077</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00077v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: With the introduction of a spectral representation, the Schwinger--Dyson equation (SDE) for the fermion propagator is formulated in Minkowski space in QED. After imposing the on-shell renormalization conditions, numeric solutions for the fermion propagator spectral functions are obtained in four dimensions with a renormalizable version of the Gauge Technique Ansatz for the fermion-photon vertex in the quenched approximation in the Yennie gauge. Despite the limitations of this model, having an explicit solution provides a guiding example of the fermion propagator with the correct analytic structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00077v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shaoyang Jia, Michael R. Pennington</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scattering of wave dark matter by supermassive black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00090</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00090v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent simulations of wave dark matter around black hole binaries revealed the formation of a universal density profile that co-rotates with the binary. We derive this profile from first principles, interpreting it as the steady state of a scattering process. We find that the scattering becomes particularly efficient when the ratio of the binary separation to the dark matter's de Broglie wavelength assumes certain discrete values, which can be interpreted as bound state resonances. After estimating the amount of dark matter that undergoes this type of scattering off supermassive black hole binaries at galactic centers, we demonstrate that the process can induce an observable modification of the slope of the Pulsar Timing Array spectrum. This opens up a new possibility to gain insights on the nature of dark matter from observations of low-frequency gravitational waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00090v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Maria Tomaselli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards the BBGKY hierarchy: a scheme beyond the Boltzmann equation and application to a weakly confined QCD gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00099v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In classical kinetic theory, the BBGKY hierarchy is an infinite chain of integro-differential equations that describes the full time-reversal-invariant (Liouville) system of interacting (quasi)-particles in terms of $N$-particle distribution functions. In this work, instead of truncating the hierarchy at the lowest level, as is done by the Boltzmann equation, we develop a scheme similar to the relaxation time approximation that is in principle able to account for the entire chain of equations. We then explicitly investigate its truncation at the second level of the BBGKY hierarchy and, within this scheme, study the spectra of conserved operator correlation functions in a gas of weakly confined hadrons. We also discuss how these higher levels account for parts of the operator spectra `deeper in the ultra-violet regime' and compare them to known results derived from the holographic duality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00099v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sa\v{s}o Grozdanov, Alexander Soloviev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feynman Diagrams from Conformal Integrals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00101v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that momentum space Feynman diagrams involving internal massless fields can be cast as conformal integrals. This leads to a classification of all Feynman diagrams into conformal families, labelled by conformal integrals. Computing the conformal integral in each family suffices to compute all the Feynman diagrams in the family exactly. Using known exact results for some conformal integrals, we present the solutions to the other Feynman diagrams in the corresponding families. These are answers to either finite or dimensionally regularized Feynman diagrams to all orders in the regularization parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00101v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siddharth G. Prabhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian analysis of hybrid neutron star EoS constraints within a nonlocal color superconducting quark matter model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00115v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a physics-informed Bayesian analysis of equation of state constraints using observational data for masses, radii and tidal deformability of pulsars and a generic class of hybrid neutron star equation of state with color superconducting quark matter on the basis of a recently developed nonlocal chiral quark model. The nuclear matter phase is described within a relativistic density functional model of the DD2 class and the phase transition is obtained by a Maxwell construction. We find the region in the two-dimensional parameter space spanned by the vector meson coupling and the scalar diquark coupling, where three conditions are fulfilled: 1) the Maxwell construction can be performed, 2) the maximum mass of the hybrid neutron star is not smaller than 2.0 M$_\odot$ and 3) the onset density of the phase transition is not below the nuclear saturation density $n_0=0.15$ fm$^{-3}$. The result of this study shows that the favorable neutron star equation of state has low onset masses for the occurrence of a color superconducting quark matter core between $0.5-0.7~M_\odot$ and maximum masses in the range $2.15 - 2.22~M_\odot$. In the typical mass range of $1.2 - 2.0~M_\odot$, the radii of these stars are between 11.9 and 12.4 km, almost independent of the mass. In principle, hybrid stars would allow for larger maximum masses than provided by the hadronic reference equation of state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00115v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Ayriyan, David Blaschke, Juan Pablo Carlomagno, Gustavo A. Contrera, Ana Gabriela Grunfeld</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring DHCAL design and performance with Graph Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00128v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the context of a gaseous-based DHCAL, we investigate the potential of using Graph Neural Networks (GNN) for hadron energy reconstruction and particle identification (PID) in future collider experiments. For PID, we demonstrate an accuracy of approximately 90% for neutrons and pions, and near 100% for neutral kaons and protons. The energy resolution for these hadrons is studied up to 50 GeV, with an additional investigation into the resolution as a function of the incoming particle angle and readout granularity using pions. Compared to traditional analysis methods, our results suggest that improved performance could be achieved even with coarser detector granularity, potentially making future DHCAL systems more cost-effective.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00128v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Borysova, D. Zavazieva, N. Kakati, E. Gross, S. Bressler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial Black Hole Formation from Power Spectrum with Finite-width</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00295v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Primordial Black Holes (PBHs) can form from gravitational collapse of large overdensities in the early Universe, giving rise to rich phenomena in astrophysics and cosmology. We develop a novel, general, and accurate method based on theory of density contrast peaks to calculate the abundance of PBHs for a broad power spectrum of curvature perturbations with Gaussian statistics. By introducing a window function to account for relevant perturbation scales for PBHs of different masses, as well as a filter function circumventing overproduction of small PBHs, we find that previous studies might have dramatically overestimated the abundance of PBHs by up to $\mathcal{O}(10)$ orders of magnitude.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00295v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shi Pi, Misao Sasaki, Volodymyr Takhistov, Jianing Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tricritical behavior of a relativistic field theory in one dimension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00518</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00518v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The tricritical behavior in a class of one-dimensional (1D) field theories that exhibit spontaneous symmetry breaking at zero temperature and chemical potential is analyzed. In the Gross-Neveu (GN)-type models of massless fermions the discrete chiral symmetry is spontaneously broken. After doping, the symmetry is restored at a critical chemical potential. We investigate the temperature effects on this doped 1D system under an external constant Zeeman magnetic field $B_0$. We find that $B_0$ suppresses the gapless behavior present for certain values of chemical potential and is able to induce a gapless-gapped phase transition at a critical field strength. We also discuss about the consequences of the consideration of inhomogeneous condensates to the tricritical point, within the Ginzburg-Landau expansion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00518v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heron Caldas, A. L. Mota</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The phase diagram of quantum chromodynamics in one dimension on a quantum computer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00579v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The quantum chromodynamics (QCD) phase diagram is key to answering open questions in physics, from states of matter in neutron stars to the early universe. However, classical simulations of QCD face significant computational barriers, such as the sign problem at finite matter densities. Quantum computing offers a promising solution to overcome these challenges. Here, we take an important step toward exploring the QCD phase diagram with quantum devices by preparing thermal states in one-dimensional non-Abelian gauge theories. We experimentally simulate the thermal states of SU(2) and SU(3) gauge theories at finite densities on a trapped-ion quantum computer using a variational method. This is achieved by introducing two features: Firstly, we add motional ancillae to the existing qubit register to efficiently prepare thermal probability distributions. Secondly, we introduce gauge-invariant measurements to enforce local gauge symmetries. This work marks the first lattice gauge theory quantum simulation of QCD at finite density and temperature for two and three colors, laying the foundation to explore QCD phenomena on quantum platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00579v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton T. Than, Yasar Y. Atas, Abhijit Chakraborty, Jinglei Zhang, Matthew T. Diaz, Kalea Wen, Xingxin Liu, Randy Lewis, Alaina M. Green, Christine A. Muschik, Norbert M. Linke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinematically-enhanced interpolating operators for boosted hadrons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00729</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00729v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose to use interpolating operators for lattice quantum chromodyanmics (QCD) calculations of highly-boosted pions and nucleons with kinematically-enhanced ground-state overlap factors at large momentum. Because this kinematic enhancement applies to the signal but not the variance of the correlation function, these interpolating operators can achieve better signal-to-noise ratios at large momentum. We perform proof-of-principle calculations with boosted pions and nucleons using close-to-physical and larger quark masses to explore the utility of our proposal. Results for effective energies and matrix elements, as well as Lanczos ground-state energy estimators, are consistent with theoretical expectations for signal-to-noise improvement at large momenta.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00729v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rui Zhang, Anthony V. Grebe, Daniel C. Hackett, Michael L. Wagman, Yong Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isospin effect on the liquid-gas phase transition for finite nuclei</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00760v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The phenomenon of nuclear liquid-gas phase transition is a topic of contemporary interest. In heavy-ion collisions, there is no direct way of accessing the thermodynamic variables like pressure, density, free energy, entropy etc., and unambiguous detection of phase transition becomes difficult. A peak in the first order derivative of total multiplicity with respect to temperature (commonly abbreviated as the multiplicity derivative) has been established as a new experimentally accessible signature of the nuclear liquid-gas phase transition. In this work, the effect of isospin asymmetry in the fragmenting system, as well as the nuclear equation of state, on the multiplicity derivative and specific heat at constant volume is investigated within the framework of the Canonical Thermodynamical Model (CTM) with a semi-microscopic cluster functional.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00760v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Mallik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prospects for measuring neutrino mass with 21-cm forest</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00769</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00769v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Both particle physics experiments and cosmological observations have been used to explore neutrino properties. Cosmological researches of neutrinos often rely on the early-universe cosmic microwave background observations or other late-universe probes, which mostly focus on large-scale structures. We introduce a distinct probe, the 21-cm forest, that differs from other probes in both time and scale. Actually, the 21-cm forest is a unique tool for studying small-scale structures in the early universe. Below the free-streaming scale, massive neutrinos suppress the matter power spectrum, influencing small-scale fluctuations in the distribution of matter. The one-dimensional (1D) power spectrum of the 21-cm forest can track these fluctuations across different scales, similar to the matter power spectrum, providing an effective method to probe neutrino mass. Although heating effects in the early universe can also impact the 1D power spectrum of the 21-cm forest, we assess the potential of the 21-cm forest as a tool for measuring neutrino mass, given that the temperature of the intergalactic medium can be constrained using other methods within a certain range. We also discuss the impact of cosmological parameters on our results. In the ideal scenario, the 21-cm forest observation will have the ability to constrain the total neutrino mass to around 0.1 eV. With the accumulation of observational data and advancements in observational technology, the 21-cm forest holds great promise as an emerging and potent tool for measuring neutrino mass.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00769v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yue Shao, Guo-Hong Du, Tian-Nuo Li, Xin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First-order phase transition in dynamical 3-flavor QCD at imaginary isospin</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00792v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We revisit QCD with three mass-degenerate quark flavors at an imaginary isospin chemical potential set to 4 pi T/3. This choice corresponds to a special point in the parameter space, where the theory possesses an exact Z(3) center symmetry. Through a finite-size scaling analysis, we demonstrate that in this case the finite temperature QCD transition is of first order and entails singular behavior both in the Polyakov loop and in the quark condensate. Our results are based on simulations with stout-smeared staggered quarks and a dedicated multi-histogram analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00792v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gergely Endrodi, Guy D. Moore, Alessandro Sciarra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimating the track-reconstruction efficiency in phenomenological proposals of long-lived-particle searches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00857</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00857v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Phenomenological proposals of searches for new, long-lived particles face a challenge when estimating the reconstruction efficiency of displaced charged-particle tracks. The efficiency depends not only on the charged-particle's momentum vector, but also on its production point in relation to the detector boundary and substructure elements. Phenomenological studies generally do not have access to GEANT4-based simulation, which is used for calculating the efficiency in experimental analyses. To address this need, we have developed TrackEff, a python software package for estimating the track-reconstruction efficiency. The default detector geometry within TrackEff is that of the Belle~II drift chamber. However, tunable parameters enable modification of the geometry to correspond to other tracker configurations. TrackEff uses a simplified model of the tracker to determine the number of detector hits associated with each track. The user can then decide whether the track would be detected based on the number of hits, potentially in association with any other information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00857v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emilie Bertholet, Abner Soffer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$B \to \rho \ell \bar{\nu}$ resonance form factors from $B \to \pi\pi \ell \bar{\nu}$ in lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00903v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The decay $B \to \rho \ell \bar{\nu}$ is an attractive process for determining the magnitude of the smallest CKM matrix element, $|V_{ub}|$, and can provide new insights into the origin of the long-standing exclusive-inclusive discrepancy in determinations of this Standard-Model parameter. This requires a nonperturbative QCD calculation of the $B \to \rho$ form factors $V$, $A_0$, $A_1$, and $A_{12}$. The unstable nature of the $\rho$ resonance has prevented precise lattice QCD calculations of these form factors to date. Here, we present the first lattice QCD calculation of the $B \to \rho$ form factors in which the $\rho$ is treated properly as a resonance in $P$-wave $\pi \pi$ scattering. To this end, we use the Lellouch-L\"uscher finite-volume formalism to compute the $B \to \pi \pi$ form factors as a function of both momentum transfer and $\pi \pi$ invariant mass, and then analytically continue to the $\rho$ resonance pole. This calculation is performed with $2+1$ dynamical quark flavors at a pion mass of approximately 320 MeV, and demonstrates a clear path toward results at the physical point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00903v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luka Leskovec, Stefan Meinel, Marcus Petschlies, John Negele, Srijit Paul, Andrew Pochinsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>White Paper on Software Infrastructure for Advanced Nuclear Physics Computing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00905v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This White Paper documents the discussion and consensus conclusions of the workshop "Software Infrastructure for Advanced Nuclear Physics Computing" (SANPC 24), which was held at Jefferson Lab on June 20-22, 2024. The workshop brought together members of the US Nuclear Physics community with data scientists and funding agency representatives to discuss the challenges and opportunities in advanced computing for Nuclear Physics in the coming decade. Opportunities for sustainable support and growth are identified within the context of existing and currently planned DOE and NSF programs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00905v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Boehnlein, J. Carlson, I. Cloet, J. Detwiler, M. Diefenthaler, R. Edwards, K. Godbey, R. Hix, P. M. Jacobs, K. Originos, T. Papenbrock, M. Ploskon, C. Ratti, B. Sawatzky, R. Soltz, T. Wenaus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 15: Open Questions and Future Directions in Titan Science</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00971</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00971v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this chapter we attempt to distill the very large number of possible future inquiries of Titan into a relatively concise list of twenty high level questions - each of which of would necessarily entail a multitude of more specific investigations and studies. While this list does not encompass all possible open questions, and is divided into topics according to our preference and not in any way uniquely, we believe that it does however span a wide range of the most intriguing topics about Titan, and may form some sort of guide especially for those embarking into Titan studies for the first time. At the end of this chapter we return to explore how these four techniques may be used to answer the large, high-level open questions in Titan science.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00971v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/B978-0-323-99161-2.00012-7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chapter 15 of book: "Titan after Cassini-Huygens", Editors: Rosaly M.C. Lopes, Charles Elachi, Ingo Mueller-Wodarg, Anezina Solomonidou. Paperback ISBN: 9780323991612 Elsevier, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Conor A. Nixon, Natalie Carrasco, Christophe Sotin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Role of Electric Dominance for Particle Injection in Relativistic Reconnection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00979v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Magnetic reconnection in relativistic plasmas -- where the magnetization $\sigma\gg1$ -- is regarded as an efficient particle accelerator, capable of explaining the most dramatic astrophysical flares. We employ two-dimensional (2D) particle-in-cell simulations of relativistic pair-plasma reconnection with vanishing guide field and outflow boundaries to quantify the impact of the energy gain occurring in regions of electric dominance ($E&gt;B$) for the early stages of particle acceleration (i.e., the ``injection'' stage). We calculate the mean fractional contribution $\zeta(\epsilon^\ast,\epsilon_{\rm T}$) by $E&gt;B$ fields to particle energization up to the injection threshold energy, $\epsilon^\ast=\sigma/4$; here, $\epsilon_{\rm T}$ is the particle energy at time $T$. We find that $\zeta$ monotonically increases with $\sigma$ and $\epsilon_{\rm T}$; for $\sigma\gtrsim 50$ and $\epsilon_{\rm T}/\sigma\gtrsim 8$, we find that $\gtrsim 80\%$ of the energy gain obtained before reaching $\epsilon^\ast=\sigma/4$ occurs in $E&gt;B$ regions. We find that $\zeta$ is independent of simulation box size $L_x$, as long as $\epsilon_{\rm T}$ is normalized to the maximum particle energy, which scales as $\epsilon_{\rm max}\propto L_{\rm x}^{1/2}$ in 2D. The distribution of energy gains $\epsilon_{\chi}$ acquired in $E&gt;B$ regions can be modeled as $dN/d\epsilon_{\chi}\propto\epsilon_{\chi}^{-0.35}\exp[-(\epsilon_{\chi}/0.06\,\sigma)^{0.5}]$. Our results help assess the role of electric dominance in relativistic reconnection with vanishing guide fields, which may be realized in the magnetospheres of black holes and neutron stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00979v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanya Gupta, Navin Sridhar, Lorenzo Sironi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamics of charmed hadrons across chiral crossover from lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01300v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We use up to fourth-order charm fluctuations and their correlations with net baryon number, electric charge, and strangeness fluctuations, calculated within the framework of lattice QCD, to study the continuum partial pressure contributions of charmed baryons and mesons. We show that, at and below the chiral crossover temperature, these partial pressures receive enhanced contributions from experimentally unobserved charmed hadrons predicted by the Quark Model. Additionally, we demonstrate that at the chiral crossover, the Hadron Resonance Gas description breaks down, signaling the onset of charm deconfinement. We present evidence for the survival of low-lying non-radial $1S$ and $1P$ hadron-like excitations above the chiral crossover. Finally, we investigate the continuum partial pressure contribution of charm quark-like excitation that emerges at the chiral crossover and calculate its temperature-dependent in-medium mass.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01300v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sipaz Sharma, Frithjof Karsch, Peter Petreczky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Observatory Study of Young Stellar Energetic Flares (MORYSEF): No Evidence For Abnormally Strong Stellar Magnetic Fields After Powerful X-ray Flares</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01321v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explore the empirical power-law relationship between X-ray luminosity (Lx) and total surface magnetic flux (Phi), established across solar magnetic elements, time- and disk-averaged emission from the Sun, older active stars, and pre-main-sequence (PMS) stars. Previous models of large PMS X-ray flares, lacking direct magnetic field measurements, showed discrepancies from this baseline law, which MHD simulations attribute to unusually strong magnetic fields during flares. To test this, we used nearly simultaneous Chandra X-ray and HET-HPF near-infrared observations of four young Orion stars, measuring surface magnetic fields during or just after powerful PMS X-ray flares. We also modeled these PMS X-ray flares, incorporating their measured magnetic field strengths. Our findings reveal magnetic field strengths at the stellar surface typical of non-flaring PMS stars, ruling out the need for abnormally strong fields during flares. Both PMS and solar flares deviate from the Lx-Phi law, with PMS flares exhibiting a more pronounced deviation, primarily due to their much larger active regions on the surface and larger flaring loop volumes above the surface compared to their solar counterparts. These deviations likely stem from the fact that powerful flares are driven by magnetic reconnection, while baseline X-ray emission may involve less efficient mechanisms like Alfven wave heating. Our results also indicate a preference for dipolar magnetic loops in PMS flares, consistent with Zeeman-Doppler imaging of fully convective stars. This requirement for giant dipolar loops aligns with MHD predictions of strong dipoles supported by polar magnetic surface active regions in fast-rotating, fully convective stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01321v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantin V. Getman (Pennsylvania State University), Oleg Kochukhov (Uppsala University), Joe P. Ninan (Tata Institute of Fundamental Research), Eric D. Feigelson (Pennsylvania State University), Vladimir S. Airapetian (NASA/GSFC/SEEC), Abygail R. Waggoner (University of Virginia), L. Ilsedore Cleeves (University of Virginia), Jan Forbrich (University of Hertfordshire), Sergio A. Dzib (Max-Planck-Institut fur Radioastronomie), Charles J. Law (University of Virginia), Christian Rab (Max-Planck-Institut fur Extraterrestrische Physik), Daniel M. Krolikowski (University of Arizona)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large lepton number violation at colliders: predictions from the minimal linear seesaw mechanism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.06080</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.06080v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Small neutrino masses can be sourced by a tiny vacuum expectation value of a leptophilic Higgs doublet, and mediated by Quasi-Dirac heavy neutrinos. In such simplest linear seesaw picture the neutrino mass mediators can be accessible to colliders. We describe novel charged Higgs and heavy neutrino production mechanisms that can be sizeable at $e^+ e^-$, $e^- \gamma$, $pp$, or muon colliders and discuss some of the associated signatures. The oscillation length of the heavy neutrino mediators is directly related to the light neutrino mass ordering. Moreover, lepton number violation can be large despite the smallness of neutrino masses, and may shed light on the Majorana nature of neutrinos and the significance of basic symmetries in weak interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.06080v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2024.139204</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Aditya Batra, Praveen Bharadwaj, Sanjoy Mandal, Rahul Srivastava, Jos\'e W. F. Valle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precision prediction of a democratic up-family philic KSVZ axion model at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.08662</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.08662v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we study the $SU(2)_L$ singlet complex scalar extended KSVZ model that, in addition to providing a natural solution to the strong-CP problem, furnishes two components of dark matter that satisfy observer relic density without fine-tuning the model's parameters. A colored vector-like quark (VLQ) is naturally present in the KSVZ axion model, providing a rich dark matter and collider phenomenology. In this extended model, scalar dark matter interacts with the Standard Model up-type quarks (up, charm, top) through VLQ. We explore the possibility of democratic Yukawa interaction of the VLQ with all up-type quarks and scalar dark matter candidate. We also employ next-to-leading order NLO-QCD correction on dominant production channels for VLQ pair production to study a unique search at the LHC, generating a pair of boosted tops with sizeable missing transverse momentum. Such corrections are significant and reduce factorization and renormalization scale uncertainties substantially. The NLO fixed order results are matched with the Pythia8 parton shower. After being pair-produced, each VLQ decays into a dark matter and a top quark. We conducted a multivariate analysis using jet substructure variables of boosted top fatjets with a significant missing transverse momentum signal. This analysis allows us to explore a substantial parameter space of this model at the 14 TeV LHC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.08662v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.dark.2024.101746</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Anupam Ghosh, Partha Konar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tamed loops: A way to obtain finite loop results without UV divergences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.18104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.18104v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For loops with UV divergences, assuming that the physical contributions of loops from UV regions are insignificant, a method of UV-free scheme described by an equation is introduced to derive loop results without UV divergences in calculations, i.e., a route of the analytic continuation $\mathcal{T}_\mathrm{F} \to \mathcal{T}_\mathrm{P}$ besides the traditional route $\infty - \infty$ in mathematical structure. This scheme provides a new perspective to an open question of the hierarchy problem of Higgs mass, i.e., an alternative interpretation without fine-tuning within the standard model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.18104v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lian-Bao Jia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing the light scalar meson as a non-$q\bar q$ state in semileptonic $D$ decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.06091</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.06091v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: While the light scalar mesons ($S_0$) are considered to be either ordinary $q\bar q$ or exotic tetraquark states, we investigate the semileptonic decays $D\to S_0 e^+\nu_e$, by taking into account the resonant effects of $S_0\to M_1 M_2$, where $S_0=a_0(980)$, $f_0(980)$, and $f_0(500)/\sigma_0$, and $M_{1(2)}$ represents a pseudoscalar meson. For the first time, the $D\to S_0$ form factors in the two quark structures are both presented. Subsequently, we calculate ${\cal B}(D_s^+\to \sigma_0 e^+\nu_e,\sigma_0\to\pi^+\pi^-)=(20.3\pm 1.8\pm 0.5)\times 10^{-4}$ in the $q\bar q$ structure, showing significant $9\sigma$ deviations from the experimental upper limit of $3.3\times 10^{-4}$. In contrast, ${\cal B}(D_s^+\to \sigma_0 e^+\nu_e,\sigma_0\to\pi^+\pi^-)=(0.58^{+1.43}_{-0.57}\pm 0.01)\times 10^{-4}$ in the $q^2\bar q^2$ structure is within the allowed experimental range. Clearly, the light scalar meson is tested as a non-$q\bar q$ state. We hence demonstrate a highly sensitive new approach for exploring the true nature of scalar mesons, which can be extended to non-leptonic $D$ decays as well as $B$ meson decays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.06091v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP12(2024)226</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP12(2024)226</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Kuo Hsiao, Shu-Qi Yang, Wen-Juan Wei, Bai-Cian Ke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-interacting dark matter implied by nano-Hertz gravitational waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.16966</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.16966v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The self-interacting dark matter (SIDM) paradigm offers a potential solution to the small-scale structure problems faced by collision-less cold dark matter. This framework incorporates self-interactions among dark matter particles, typically mediated by a particle with a MeV-scale mass. Recent evidences of nano-Hertz gravitational waves from pulsar timing arrays (PTAs) such as NANOGrav, CPTA, EPTA, and PPTA suggest the occurrence of a first-order phase transition (FOPT) at a MeV-scale temperature. Considering the close proximity between these two scales, we propose that the mediator mass in the SIDM model originates from the spontaneous breaking of a $U(1)'$ symmetry, which is driven by the FOPT indicated by PTA data. Consequently, the alignment of these two scales is believed to be deeply connected by the same underlying physics. By extensively exploring the parameter space, remarkably, we find that the parameter space favored by SIDM just provides an explanation for the PTA data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.16966v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengcheng Han, Ke-Pan Xie, Jin Min Yang, Mengchao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Softly Broken Hidden Symmetry in Every Renormalizable Field Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.05859</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.05859v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is pointed out that every renormalizable field theory has a symmetry which is hidden in plain sight. In all practical cases, it is also broken softly, either explicitly or spontaneously. The soft explicit breaking mass terms may be assumed naturally small compared to the scalar mass-squared terms. Implications for extensions of the standard model are discussed. New left-right model of radiative Dirac neutrino mass is proposed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.05859v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ernest Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confinement Bubble Wall Velocity via Quasiparticle Determination</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.03849</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.03849v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Lattice simulations reveal that the deconfinement-confinement (D-C) phase transition (PT) of the hot pure $SU(N&gt;2)$ Yang-Mills system is first order. This system can be described by a pool of quasigluons moving in the Polyakov loop background, and in this picture, we establish an effective distribution function for quasigluons, which encodes interactions among quasigluons and in particular the confinement effect. With it, we made the first attempt to calculate the confinement bubble wall velocity $v_w$ at the microscopical level, and we obtained a small velocity $v_w\sim 0.04$ using two different approaches, which is qualitatively consistent with others results like holography.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.03849v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhaofeng Kang, Jiang Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytic continuations and numerical evaluation of the Appell $F_1$, $F_3$, Lauricella $F_D^{(3)}$ and Lauricella-Saran $F_S^{(3)}$ and their Application to Feynman Integrals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02237v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present our investigation of the study of two variable hypergeometric series, namely Appell $F_{1}$ and $F_{3}$ series, and obtain a comprehensive list of its analytic continuations enough to cover the whole real $(x,y)$ plane, except on their singular loci. We also derive analytic continuations of their 3-variable generalization, the Lauricella $F_{D}^{(3)}$ series and the Lauricella-Saran $F_{S}^{(3)}$ series, leveraging the analytic continuations of $F_{1}$ and $F_{3}$, which ensures that the whole real $(x,y,z)$ space is covered, except on the singular loci of these functions. While these studies are motivated by the frequent occurrence of these multivariable hypergeometric functions in Feynman integral evaluation, they can also be used whenever they appear in other branches of mathematical physics. To facilitate their practical use, we provide four packages: $\texttt{AppellF1.wl}$, $\texttt{AppellF3.wl}$, $\texttt{LauricellaFD.wl}$, and $\texttt{LauricellaSaranFS.wl}$ in $\textit{MATHEMATICA}$. These packages are applicable for generic as well as non-generic values of parameters, keeping in mind their utilities in the evaluation of the Feynman integrals. We explicitly present various physical applications of these packages in the context of Feynman integral evaluation and compare the results using other packages such as $\texttt{FIESTA}$. Upon applying the appropriate conventions for numerical evaluation, we find that the results obtained from our packages are consistent. Various $\textit{Mathematica}$ notebooks demonstrating different numerical results are also provided along with this paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02237v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cs.MS</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.cpc.2024.109386</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Comput.Phys.Commun. 306 (2025) 109386</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Souvik Bera, Tanay Pathak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of torsion in long-baseline neutrino oscillation experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09105v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work we investigate the effect of curved spacetime on neutrino oscillation. In a curved spacetime, the effect of curvature on fermionic fields is represented by spin connection. The spin connection consists of a non-universal ``contorsion" part which is expressed in terms of vector and axial current density of fermions. The contraction of contorsion part with the tetrad fields, which connects the internal flat space metric and the spacetime metric, is called torsion. In a scenario where neutrino travels through background of fermionic matter at ordinary densities in a curved spacetime, the Hamiltonian of neutrino oscillation gets modified by the torsional coupling constants $\lambda_{21}^{\prime}$ and $\lambda_{31}^{\prime}$. The aim of this work is to study the effect of $\lambda_{21}^{\prime}$ and $\lambda_{31}^{\prime}$ in DUNE and P2SO. In our study we, (i) discuss the effect of torsional coupling constants on the neutrino oscillation probabilities, (ii) estimate the capability of P2SO and DUNE to put bounds on these parameters and (iii) study how the physics sensitivities get modified in presence of torsion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09105v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Papia Panda, Dinesh Kumar Singha, Monojit Ghosh, Rukmani Mohanta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Next-to-Next-to-Leading Order QCD Corrections to Polarized Semi-Inclusive Deep-Inelastic Scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09959v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Polarized semi-inclusive deep-inelastic scattering (SIDIS) is a key process in the quest for a resolution of the proton spin puzzle. We present the complete results for the polarized SIDIS process at next-to-next-to-leading order (NNLO) in perturbative quantum chromodynamics. Our analytical results include all partonic channels for the scattering of polarized leptons off hadrons and a spin-averaged hadron identified in the final state. A numerical analysis of the NNLO corrections illustrates their significance and the reduced residual scale dependence in the kinematic range probed by the future Electron-Ion-Collider EIC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09959v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.211905</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 133, 211905 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Saurav Goyal, Roman N. Lee, Sven-Olaf Moch, Vaibhav Pathak, Narayan Rana, V. Ravindran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tetraquarks from Intrinsic Heavy Quarks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09018</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09018v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A number of new four-quark states containing from one to four charm or anti-charm quarks have been observed recently. Many of these new states have been discovered at the LHC. The production of these states via intrinsic charm in the proton is investigated. The tetraquark masses obtained in this approach, while dependent on the internal transverse momenta of the partons in the state, are shown to agree well with the measured masses. These calculations can provide some insight into the nature of the tetraquark candidates, whether as a bound meson pair or as a looser configuration of four individual partons. The kinematic distributions of these states as a function of rapidity and transverse momentum are also studied. The possible cross sections for these states are finally considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09018v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 110 (2024) 7, 074036</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>R. Vogt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electric field induction in quark-gluon plasma due to thermoelectric effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12510v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Relativistic heavy-ion collisions produce quark-gluon plasma (QGP), which is locally thermalized. Due to electrically charged particles (quarks), QGP exhibits interesting thermoelectric phenomena during its evolution, resulting in an electromagnetic (EM) field in the medium. In this study, for the first time, we estimate the induced electric field in QGP due to the thermoelectric effect. This phenomenon can induce an EM field even in QGP produced by the head-on heavy-ion collision. In peripheral heavy-ion collisions, the presence of a spectator current generates a transient magnetic field at the early stage, which disrupts the isotropy of the induced electric field. For the numerical estimation, we use a quasiparticle-based model that incorporates the lattice quantum chromodynamics equation of state for QGP. The induced electric field is estimated with cooling rates derived from Gubser hydrodynamic flow. Thermoelectric coefficients such as Seebeck, magneto-Seebeck, and Nernst coefficients play a crucial role in determining the induced field. Additionally, we account for the temperature evolution of QGP using different hydrodynamic cooling rates to calculate the transport coefficients. We also estimate the transport coefficients and the induced electric field in the presence of an external time-varying magnetic field, including the quantum effect of Landau quantization, and explore the effects of the intensity and decay parameter of the magnetic field on the induced electric field. Our findings reveal that the space-time profile of the induced electric field is zero at the center and increases as we go away from the center. During the early stages of evolution, the electric field can reach a maximum value of $eE \approx 1~m_\pi^2$, decreasing in strength over time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12510v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.114051</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review D 110, 114051 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kamaljeet Singh, Jayanta Dey, Raghunath Sahoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutrino Tomography of the Earth: the Earth Total Mass, Moment of Inertia and Hydrostatic Equilibrium Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13727</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13727v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the implications of the constraints following from the precise knowledge of the total Earth mass, $M_\oplus$, and moment of inertia, $I_\oplus$, and from the requirement that Earth be in hydrostatic equilibrium (EHE), in the neutrino tomography studies of the Earth density structure. In order to estimate the sensitivity of a given neutrino detector to possible deviations of the inner core (IC), outer core (OC), core (IC + OC) and mantle Earth densities from those obtained using geophysical and seismological data and described by the preliminary reference Earth model (PREM), in the statistical analyses performed within the neutrino tomography studies one typically varies the density of each of these structures. These variations, however, must respect the $M_\oplus$, $I_\oplus$ and EHE constraints. Working with PREM average densities we derive the $M_\oplus$, $I_\oplus$ and EHE constraints on the possible density variations when one approximates the Earth density structure with i) three layers - mantle, outer core and inner core, and ii) four layers - upper mantle, lower mantle, outer core and inner core. We get drastically different results in the two cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13727v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. T. Petcov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$W-$mass and Muon $g-2$ in Inert 2HDM Extended by Singlet Complex Scalar</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00181v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The deviations of the recent measurements of the muon magnetic moment and the $W-$boson mass from their SM predictions hint to new physics beyond the SM. In this article, we address the observed discrepancies in the $W$-boson mass and muon anomalous magnetic moment in the Inert Two Higgs Doublet Model (I2HDM) extended by a complex scalar field singlet under the SM gauge group. The model is constrained from the existing LEP data and the measurements of partial decay widths to gauge bosons at LHC. It is shown that a large subset of this constrained parameter space of the model can simultaneously accommodate the $W$-boson mass and also explain the muon $g-2$ anomaly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00181v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.115040</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 110 (2024) 11, 115040</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hrishabh Bharadwaj, Mamta Dahiya, Sukanta Dutta, Ashok Goyal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutrinoless Double Beta Decay from Scalar Leptoquarks: Interplay with Neutrino Mass and Flavor Physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04670v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We perform a comprehensive analysis of neutrinoless double beta decay and its interplay with low-energy flavor observables in a radiative neutrino mass model with scalar leptoquarks $S_1(\bar{3},1,1/3)$ and $\widetilde{R}_2(3,2,1/6)$. We carve out the parameter region consistent with constraints from neutrino mass and mixing, collider searches, as well as measurements of several flavor observables, such as muon and electron anomalous magnetic moments, charged lepton flavor violation and rare (semi)leptonic kaon and $B$-meson decays, including the recent anomalies in $R_{D^{(*)}}$ and $B\to K\nu\bar{\nu}$ observables. We perform a global analysis to all existing constraints and show the (anti)correlations between all relevant Yukawa couplings satisfying these restrictions. We find that the most stringent constraint on the parameter space comes from $\mu \to e$ conversion in nuclei and $K^{+} \rightarrow\, \pi^{+}\nu \bar{\nu}$ decay. We also point out a tension between the muon and electron $(g-2)$ anomalies in this context. Taking benchmark values from the combined allowed regions, we study the implications for neutrinoless double beta decay including both the canonical light neutrino and the leptoquark contributions. We find that for normal ordering of neutrino masses, the leptoquark contribution removes the cancellation region that occurs for the canonical case. The effective mass in presence of leptoquarks can lie in the desert region between the standard normal and inverted ordering cases, and this can be probed in future ton-scale experiments like LEGEND-1000 and nEXO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04670v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. S. Bhupal Dev, Srubabati Goswami, Chayan Majumdar, Debashis Pachhar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Small Neutrino Masses from a Decoupled Singlet Scalar Field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13595</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13595v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a unified solution with $Z_4$ discrete symmetry for small neutrino masses and stability of dark matter. The Standard Model is extended with an inert doublet scalar, a dark singlet scalar, a spurion scalar and right-handed neutrinos, which all transform nontrivially under $Z_4$. After the $Z_4$ symmetry is broken to $Z_2$ by the VEV of the spurion, much below the mass scale of the dark singlet scalar, a small lepton number violating coupling for the inert doublet is generated at tree level, so small neutrino masses are obtained at one-loops for relatively light new fields. We discuss the important roles of the $Z_4$ symmetry for neutrino masses, dark matter physics and thermal leptogenesis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13595v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jongkuk Kim, Seong-Sik Kim, Hyun Min Lee, Rojalin Padhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Fox-Wolfram Moment of Jet Production in Relativistic Heavy Ion Collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20680</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20680v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the first theoretical investigation of Fox-Wolfram moments (FWMs) for multi-jet production in relativistic heavy ion collisions. In this work, jet productions in p+p collisions are computed with a Monte Carlo event generator SHERPA, while the Linear Boltzmann Transport model is utilized to simulate the multiple scattering of energetic partons in the hot and dense QCD matter. The event-normalized distributions of the lower-order FWM, $H_1^T$ in p+p and Pb+Pb collisions are calculated. It is found that for events with jet number $n_\text{jet} = 2$ the $H_1^T$ distribution in Pb+Pb is suppressed at small $H_1^T$ while enhanced at large $H_1^T$ region as compared to p+p. For events with $n_\text{jet}&gt;2$, the jet number reduction effect due to jet quenching in the QGP decreases the $H_1^T$ distribution at large $H_1^T$ in Pb+Pb relative to p+p. The medium modification of the Fox-Wolfram moment $H_1^T$ for events with $n_\text{jet}\ge 2$ are also presented, which resemble those of events with $n_\text{jet} = 2$. Its reason is revealed through the relative contribution fractions of events with different final-state jet numbers to $H_1^T$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20680v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Xi Kong, Ben-Wei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutrino Nonstandard Interactions and Lepton Flavor Universality violation at SND@LHC via charm production</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11897</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11897v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we explore the effect of neutrino nonstandard interactions (NSI) involving the charm quark at SND@LHC. Using an effective description of new physics in terms of four-fermion operators involving a charm quark, we constrain the Wilson coefficients of the effective interaction from two and three-body charmed meson decays. In our fit, we include charmed meson decays not only to pseudoscalar final states but also to vector final states and include decays to the $\eta$ and $\eta^\prime$ final states. We also consider constraints from charmed baryon decays. We then study the effect of new physics in neutrino scattering processes, involving charm production at SND@LHC, for various benchmark new physics couplings obtained from the low energy fits. Finally, we also study the effects of lepton universality violation (LUV) assuming that the new physics coupling is not lepton universal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11897v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP12(2024)113</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 12(2024)113</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bhubanjyoti Bhattacharya, Alakabha Datta, Elena Graverini, Lopamudra Mukherjee, Divya Sachdeva, John Waite</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating the $p$-$\Omega$ Interaction and Correlation Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15493v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Motivated by experimental measurements, we investigate the $p$-$\Omega$ correlation functions and interactions on the basis of a quark model. By solving the inverse scattering problem with channel coupling, we renormalize the coupling to other channels into an effective single-channel $p$-$\Omega$ potentials. The effects of Coulomb interaction and spin-averaging are also discussed. According to our results, the depletion of the $p$-$\Omega$ correlation functions, which is attributed to the $J^P = 2^+$ bound state not observed in the ALICE Collaboration's measurements [Nature \textbf{588}, 232 (2020)], can be explained by the contribution of the attractive $J^P = 1^+$ component in spin-averaging. So far, we have provided a consistent description of the $p$-$\Omega$ system from the perspective of the quark model, including the energy spectrum, scattering phase shifts, and correlation functions. The existence of the $p$-$\Omega$ bound state has been supported by all three aspects. Additionally, a sign of the $p$-$\Omega$ correlation function's subtle sub-unity part can be seen in experimental measurements, which warrants more precise verification in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15493v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ye Yan, Qi Huang, Youchang Yang, Hongxia Huang, Jialun Ping</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What we can learn from the angular differential rates (only) in semileptonic $B \to D^* \ell \nu_\ell$ decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10492v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a simple approach to the study of semileptonic $B \to D^* \ell \nu_\ell$ decays based on the angular distributions of the final state particles only. Our approach is model independent and never requires the knowledge of $\vert V_{cb} \vert$. By studying such distributions in the case of light leptons, a comparison between results from different data sets from the Belle and BelleII Collaborations and between data and Standard Model calculations is also given for several interesting quantities. A good consistency is observed between some of the experimental results and the theoretical predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10492v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Martinelli, S. Simula, L. Vittorio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resummed jet mass distribution with trimming in Z+jet events at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12260v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we calculate the resummed jet mass distribution up to next-to-leading logarithmic accuracy for jets defined with the trimming groomer in Z+jet events at the LHC. We compute at fixed order and to all orders the large logarithms, both in the jet mass and $z_{\mathrm{cut}}$ trimming variable, including non-global and clustering logarithms. We conduct phenomenological studies at $\mathcal{O}(\alpha_s)$, validating our results by comparing them with the fixed-order Monte Carlo program MCFM, which provides NLO predictions for hadron colliders. The resummation of non-global logarithms is estimated in the large-$\mathrm{N_c}$ limit. Our resummed result is compared to Monte Carlo parton shower simulations from Pythia 8, Herwig ++ and Sherpa 2 event generators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12260v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP12(2024)179</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 12 (2024) 179</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Safa Gaid, Yazid Delenda, Rachik Soualah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Induced gravitational waves, metastable cosmic strings and primordial black holes in GUTs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13584v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore the cosmological and astrophysical implications of a realistic hybrid inflation model based on flipped $SU(5)$. The model contains superheavy metastable cosmic strings arising from a waterfall field that encounters a limited number of $e$-foldings during the inflationary phase. In addition to the gravitational waves emitted by the metastable strings, there also appear scalar induced gravitational waves linked to the waterfall phase transition. These two independent sources of gravitational waves can yield a combined spectrum that is compatible with the recent PTA measurements, and with additional features that can be probed in future experiments. We also show the appearance of primordial black holes with mass on the order of $10^{29}$ g from the waterfall phase transition, and with an abundance that can be tested in the gravitational lensing experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13584v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rinku Maji, Ahmad Moursy, Qaisar Shafi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Threshold resummation for double-deeply virtual Compton scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11686</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.11686v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The threshold region for double-deeply virtual Compton scattering (DDVCS) is discussed. I derive a resummation formula for the (partonic) threshold logarithms in the flavor non-singlet case. The resummations can be done by using (re)factorization theorems for the coefficient functions near the partonic thresholds. As a byproduct, we obtain the leading term in the threshold limit of the two-loop coefficient function in double-deeply-virtual Compton scattering, which agrees with the recent result from explicit calculation, providing a highly non-trivial cross-check.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.11686v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jakob Schoenleber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-extensive Hard Thermal Loop Resummation and Its Applications: Analysis in Zero and Finite Magnetic Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17090</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17090v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The impact of non-extensive statistics on the hard thermal loop (HTL) resummation technique is investigated, in the absence and presence of a magnetic field. By utilizing the non-extensive bare propagators in the real-time formalism of finite temperature field theory, we determine the non-extensive deformations of both HTL gluon self-energies and resummed gluon propagators at the one-loop order. We observe that the introduction of non-extensivity results in distinct shifts in the Debye masses for the retarded/advanced and symmetric gluon self-energies. Applying the non-extensive modified resummed gluon propagators to obtain the dielectric permittivity of a quark-gluon plasma (QGP), we thereby derive the static heavy quark potential, which incorporates both short-range Yukawa and long-range string-like interactions between heavy quarks and the QGP medium. The real part of the potential exhibits increased screening as the non-extensive parameter $q$ ($q \geq 1$) increases, reducing the binding energies of heavy quarkonia. Furthermore, including non-extensivity enhances the magnitude of the imaginary part of the potential, causing a broadening in the decay widths of heavy quarkonia. Based on these observations, we estimate the melting temperatures of heavy quarkonia. Our results indicate that non-extensivity lowers the melting temperatures of heavy quarkonia, thus facilitating their dissociation, whereas the presence of a magnetic field inhibits this dissociation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17090v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>He-Xia Zhang, Yu-Xin Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological Non-Gaussianity from Neutrino Seesaw</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16033v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The neutrino mass generation via conventional seesaw mechanism is realized at high scales around $O(10^{14})$GeV and probing new physics of the seesaw scale poses a great challenge. A striking fact is that the neutrino seesaw scale is typically around the cosmological inflation scale. In this work, we propose a framework incorporating inflation and neutrino seesaw in which the inflaton primarily decays into right-handed neutrinos after inflation. This decay process is governed by the inflaton interaction with the right-handed neutrinos that respects the shift symmetry. Under the neutrino seesaw mechanism, fluctuations of the Higgs field can modulate the inflaton decays, contributing to the curvature perturbation. We investigate the induced non-Gaussian signatures and demonstrate that such signatures provides an important means to probe the high-scale neutrino seesaw mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16033v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingtao You, Linghao Song, Hong-Jian He, Chengcheng Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confronting the seesaw mechanism with neutrino oscillations: a general and explicit analytical bridge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17698v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: With the help of a full Euler-like block parametrization of the flavor structure for the canonical seesaw mechanism, we present the first general and explicit analytical calculations of the two neutrino mass-squared differences, three flavor mixing angles and the effective Dirac CP-violating phase responsible for the primary behaviors of neutrino oscillations. Such model-independent results will pave the way for testing the seesaw mechanism at low energies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17698v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhi-zhong Xing, Jing-yu Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Light Bosonic Dark Matter with Transmon Qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20850v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the constraints of the transmon qubit, an improved version of the charge qubit, on bosonic light dark matters. Phonon excitations induced by the scattering or absorption of dark matter on a superconductor may destroy the Cooper pair, leading to the production of quasiparticles made by the electron. By measuring the production rate of the quasiparticle density, one may read out the coupling between dark matter and ordinary matter, assuming that these quasiparticles are solely induced by dark matter interactions. For the first time, we show constraints on the parameter space of the dark photon, light scalar dark matter, and axion-like particles from the measurement of quasiparticles in transmon qubit experiments. This study offers insights for the development of quantum qubit experiments aimed at the direct detection of dark matter in underground laboratories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20850v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Chao, Yu Gao, Ming-jie Jin, Xiao-sheng Liu, Xi-lei Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Proof of Chiral Symmetry Breaking from Anomaly Matching in QCD-like Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02930</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.02930v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We critically reconsider the argument based on 't Hooft anomaly matching that aims at proving chiral symmetry breaking in confining four-dimensional QCD-like theories with $N_c&gt;2$ colors and $N_f$ flavors. The main line of reasoning relies on a property of the solutions of the anomaly matching and persistent mass equations called $N_f$-independence. In previous works, the validity of $N_f$-independence was assumed based on qualitative arguments, but it was never proven rigorously. We provide a detailed proof and clarify under which (dynamical) conditions it holds. Our results are valid for a generic spectrum of massless composite fermions including baryons and exotics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.02930v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 110 (2024) 11, 114035</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Luca Ciambriello, Roberto Contino, Andrea Luzio, Marcello Romano, Ling-Xiao Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast Neutrino Flavor Conversions can Help and Hinder Neutrino-Driven Explosions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.11207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.11207v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present the first simulations of core-collapse supernovae in axial symmetry with feedback from fast neutrino flavor conversion (FFC). Our schematic treatment of FFCs assumes instantaneous flavor equilibration under the constraint of lepton-number conservation individually for each flavor. Systematically varying the spatial domain where FFCs are assumed to occur, we find that they facilitate SN explosions in low-mass (9-12 solar masses) progenitors that otherwise explode with longer time delays, whereas FFCs weaken the tendency to explode of higher-mass (around 20 solar masses) progenitors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.11207v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.131.061401</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 131, 061401 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jakob Ehring (MPI Physik, MPI Astrophysik, TUM Garching), Sajad Abbar (MPI Physik), Hans-Thomas Janka (MPI Astrophysik), Georg Raffelt (MPI Physik), Irene Tamborra (Niels Bohr Institute)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of entanglement entropy at SU($N$) deconfined quantum critical points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.02547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.02547v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Over the past two decades, the enigma of the deconfined quantum critical point (DQCP) has attracted broad attention across the condensed matter, quantum field theory, and high-energy physics communities, as it is expected to offer a new paradigm in theory, experiment, and numerical simulations that goes beyond the Landau-Ginzburg-Wilson framework of symmetry breaking and phase transitions. However, the nature of DQCP has been controversial. For instance, in the square-lattice spin-1/2 $J$-$Q$ model, believed to realize the DQCP between N\'eel and valence bond solid states, conflicting results, such as first-order versus continuous transition, and critical exponents incompatible with conformal bootstrap bounds, have been reported. The enigma of DQCP is exemplified in its anomalous logarithmic subleading contribution in its entanglement entropy (EE), which was discussed in recent studies. In the current work, we demonstrate that similar anomalous logarithmic behavior persists in a class of models analogous to the DQCP. We systematically study the quantum EE of square-lattice SU($N$) DQCP spin models. Based on large-scale quantum Monte Carlo computation of the EE, we show that for a series of $N$ smaller than a critical value, the anomalous logarithmic behavior always exists in the EE, which implies that the previously determined DQCPs in these models do not belong to conformal fixed points. In contrast, when $N\ge N_c$ with a finite $N_c$ that we evaluate to lie between $7$ and $8$, the DQCPs are consistent with conformal fixed points that can be understood within the Abelian Higgs field theory with $N$ complex components.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.02547v5</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Menghan Song, Jiarui Zhao, Meng Cheng, Cenke Xu, Michael M. Scherer, Lukas Janssen, Zi Yang Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Influence of Fractional Derivatives on Thermodynamic Properties by Studying the CPSEHP Interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.05508</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.05508v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The parametric Nikiforov-Uvarov (N-U) method is employed in conjunction with a generalized fractional derivative (GFD) to investigate the energy eigenvalues and the total normalized wave function associated with the Coulomb plus screened exponential hyperbolic potential (CPSEHP) in terms of Jacobi polynomials. This potential exhibits maximum effectiveness at lower values of the screening parameter. To explore the thermal and superstatistical characteristics, the derived energy eigenvalues are directly incorporated into the partition function (Z) and subsequently used to determine other thermodynamic quantities, including vibrational mean energy (U), specific heat capacity (C), entropy (S), and free energy (F). Comparisons with previous studies are conducted. The classical case is recovered from the fractional case by setting alpha = beta = 1, consistent with prior work. Our results demonstrate that the fractional parameter plays a crucial role in governing the thermal and superstatistical properties within the framework of this model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.05508v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Abu-Shady, Sh. Y. Ezz-Alarab</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring primordial black holes and gravitational waves with R-symmetric GUT Higgs inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.13924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.13924v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study investigates the realization of R-symmetric Higgs inflation within the framework of no-scale-like supergravity, aiming to elucidate the formation of primordial black holes and observable gravitational waves within a class of GUT models. We explore the possibility of an ultra-slow-roll phase in a hybrid inflation framework, where the GUT Higgs field primarily takes on the role of the inflaton. The amplification of the scalar power spectrum gives rise to scalar-induced gravitational waves and the generation of primordial black holes. The predicted stochastic gravitational wave background falls within the sensitivity range of existing and upcoming gravitational wave detectors, while primordial black holes hold the potential to explain the abundance of dark matter. Furthermore, we highlight the significance of the leading-order nonrenormalizable term in the superpotential of achieving inflationary observables consistent with the latest experimental data. Additionally, the predicted range of the tensor-to-scalar ratio, a key measure of primordial gravitational waves, lies within the observational window of future experiments searching for B-mode polarization patterns in cosmic microwave background data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.13924v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2024.139229</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Lett. B 861 (2025) 139229</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nadir Ijaz, Mansoor Ur Rehman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Travelling-wave, Quasi-periodic, Longulent States and Persistent Whiskered Tori of the Galerkin-regularized Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20277v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Travelling-wave, quasi-periodic and ``longulent'' states of the Galerkin-regularized systems preserving finite Fourier modes are exposed. The longulent states are characterized by solitonic structures, called ``longons'', accompanied by disordered components, which is associated to presumably whiskered tori according to the \textit{a-posteriori} Kolmogorov-Arnold-Moser (KAM) theorem. On-torus invariants are introduced for constructing the KAM tori, towards a pseudo-integrability theory. Persistence of the whiskered tori is also numerically demonstrated by replacing the dispersion in the Korteweg-de Vries with a high-order (hyper)dispersion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20277v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian-Zhou Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-hydrodynamics of electrons in graphene and magnetization due to thermal vorticity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07764v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We examine the framework of relativistic spin-hydrodynamics in the context of electron hydrodynamics in graphene. We develop a spin-hydrodynamic model for a (2 + 1)-dimensional system of fermions under the condition of small spin polarization. Our analysis confirms that thermal vorticity, which satisfies the global equilibrium condition, is also a solution to the spin-hydrodynamic equations. Additionally, we calculate the magnetization of the system in global equilibrium and introduce a novel phenomenon - thermovortical magnetization - resulting from thermal vorticity, which can be experimentally observed in graphene.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07764v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amaresh Jaiswal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Unknowns of the Diffuse Supernova Neutrino Background Hinder New Physics Searches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.16367v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Neutrinos traveling over cosmic distances are ideal probes of new physics. We leverage on the approaching detection of the diffuse supernova neutrino background (DSNB) to explore whether, if the DSNB showed departures from theoretical predictions, we could attribute such modifications to new physics unequivocally. In order to do so, we focus on visible neutrino decay. Many of the signatures from neutrino decay are degenerate with astrophysical unknowns entering the DSNB modeling. Next generation neutrino observatories, such as Hyper-Kamiokande, JUNO, as well as DUNE, will set stringent limits on a neutrino lifetime over mass ratio $\tau/m \sim 10^{9}$-$10^{10}$ s eV$^{-1}$ at $90\%$ C.L., if astrophysical uncertainties and detector backgrounds were to be fully under control. However, if the lightest neutrino is almost massless and the neutrino mass ordering is normal, constraining visible decay will not be realistically possible in the coming few decades. We also assess the challenges of distinguishing among different new physics scenarios (such as visible decay, invisible decay, and quasi-Dirac neutrinos), all leading up to similar signatures in the DSNB. This work shows that the DSNB potential for probing new physics strongly depends on an improved understanding of the experimental backgrounds at next generation neutrino observatories as well as progress in the DSNB modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.16367v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miller MacDonald, Pablo Mart\'inez-Mirav\'e, Irene Tamborra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flavor Physics at CEPC: a General Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19743v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We discuss the landscape of flavor physics at the Circular Electron-Positron Collider (CEPC), based on the nominal luminosity outlined in its Technical Design Report. The CEPC is designed to operate in multiple modes to address a variety of tasks. At the $Z$ pole, the expected production of 4 Tera $Z$ bosons will provide unique and highly precise measurements of $Z$ boson couplings, while the substantial number of boosted heavy-flavored quarks and leptons produced in clean $Z$ decays will facilitate investigations into their flavor physics with unprecedented precision. We investigate the prospects of measuring various physics benchmarks and discuss their implications for particle theories and phenomenological models. Our studies indicate that, with its highlighted advantages and anticipated excellent detector performance, the CEPC can explore beauty and $\tau$ physics in ways that are superior to or complementary with the Belle II and Large-Hadron-Collider-beauty experiments, potentially enabling the detection of new physics at energy scales of 10 TeV and above. This potential also extends to the observation of yet-to-be-discovered rare and exotic processes, as well as testing fundamental principles such as lepton flavor universality, lepton and baryon number conservation, etc., making the CEPC a vibrant platform for flavor physics research. The $WW$ threshold scan, Higgs-factory operation and top-pair productions of the CEPC further enhance its merits in this regard, especially for measuring the Cabibbo-Kobayashi-Maskawa matrix elements, and Flavor-Changing-Neutral-Current physics of Higgs boson and top quarks. We outline the requirements for detector performance and considerations for future development to achieve the anticipated scientific goals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19743v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaocong Ai, Wolfgang Altmannshofer, Peter Athron, Xiaozhi Bai, Lorenzo Calibbi, Lu Cao, Yuzhi Che, Chunhui Chen, Ji-Yuan Chen, Long Chen, Mingshui Chen, Shanzhen Chen, Xuan Chen, Shan Cheng, Cheng-Wei Chiang, Andreas Crivellin, Hanhua Cui, Olivier Deschamps, S\'ebastien Descotes-Genon, Xiaokang Du, Shuangshi Fang, Yu Gao, Li-Sheng Geng, Pablo Goldenzweig, Jiayin Gu, Feng-Kun Guo, Yuchen Guo, Zhi-Hui Guo, Tao Han, Hong-Jian He, Jibo He, Miao He, Yanping Huang, Gino Isidori, Quan Ji, Jianfeng Jiang, Xu-Hui Jiang, Jernej F. Kamenik, Tsz Hong Kwok, Gang Li, Geng Li, Haibo Li, Haitao Li, Hengne Li, Honglei Li, Liang Li, Lingfeng Li, Qiang Li, Shu Li, Xiaomei Li, Xin-Qiang Li, Yiming Li, Yubo Li, Yuji Li, Zhao Li, Hao Liang, Zhijun Liang, Libo Liao, Zoltan Ligeti, Jia Liu, Jianbei Liu, Tao Liu, Yi Liu, Yong Liu, Zhen Liu, Xinchou Lou, Peng-Cheng Lu, Alberto Lusiani, Hong-Hao Ma, Kai Ma, Yaxian Mao, David Marzocca, Juan-Juan Niu, Soeren Prell, Huirong Qi, Sen Qian, Wenbin Qian, Zhuoni Qian, Qin Qin, Ariel Rock, Jonathan L. Rosner, Manqi Ruan, Dingyu Shao, Chengping Shen, Xiaoyan Shen, Haoyu Shi, Liaoshan Shi, Zong-Guo Si, Cristian Sierra, Huayang Song, Shufang Su, Wei Su, Michele Tammaro, En Wang, Fei Wang, Hengyu Wang, Jian Wang, Jianchun Wang, Kun Wang, Lian-Tao Wang, Wei Wang, Xiaolong Wang, Xiaoping Wang, Yadi Wang, Yifang Wang, Yuexin Wang, Xing-Gang Wu, Yongcheng Wu, Rui-Qing Xiao, Ke-Pan Xie, Yuehong Xie, Zijun Xu, Haijun Yang, Hongtao Yang, Lin Yang, Shuo Yang, Zhongbao Yin, Fusheng Yu, Changzheng Yuan, Xing-Bo Yuan, Xuhao Yuan, Chongxing Yue, Xi-Jie Zhan, Kaili Zhang, Liming Zhang, Xiaoming Zhang, Yang Zhang, Yanxi Zhang, Yongchao Zhang, Yu Zhang, Zhen-Hua Zhang, Zhong Zhang, Mingrui Zhao, Qiang Zhao, Xu-Chang Zheng, Yangheng Zheng, Chen Zhou, Pengxuan Zhu, Yongfeng Zhu, Xunwu Zuo, Jure Zupan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of the hard exclusive $\pi^{0}$ muoproduction cross section at COMPASS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19923v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A new and detailed measurement of the cross section for hard exclusive neutral-pion muoproduction on the proton was performed in a wide kinematic region, with the photon virtuality $Q^2$ ranging from 1 to 8 (GeV/$c$)$^{\rm\, 2}$ and the Bjorken variable $x_{\rm Bj}$ ranging from 0.02 to 0.45. The data were collected at COMPASS at CERN using 160 GeV/$c$ longitudinally polarised $\mu^+$ and $\mu^-$ beams scattering off a 2.5 m long liquid hydrogen target. From the average of the measured $\mu^+$ and $\mu^-$ cross sections, the virtual-photon--proton cross section is determined as a function of the squared four-momentum transfer between the initial and final state proton in the range 0.08 (GeV/$c$)$^{\rm\, 2}$ $&lt; |t| &lt;$ 0.64 (GeV/$c$)$^{\rm\, 2}$. From its angular distribution, the combined contribution of transversely and longitudinally polarised photons are determined, as well as transverse--transverse and longitudinal--transverse interference contributions. They are studied as functions of four-momentum transfer $|t|$, photon virtuality $Q^2$ and virtual-photon energy $\nu$. The longitudinal--transverse interference contribution is found to be compatible with zero. The significant transverse--transverse interference contribution reveals the existence of a dominant contribution by transversely polarized photons. This provides clear experimental evidence for the chiral-odd GPD $\overline{E}_T$. In addition, the existence of a non-negligible contribution of longitudinally polarized photons is suggested by the $|t|$-dependence of the cross section at $x_{\rm Bj} &lt; $ 0.1 . Altogether, these results provide valuable input for future modelling of GPDs and thus of cross sections for exclusive pseudo-scalar meson production. Furthermore, they can be expected to facilitate the study of next-to-leading order corrections and higher-twist contributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19923v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. D. Alexeev, M. G. Alexeev, C. Alice, A. Amoroso, V. Andrieux, V. Anosov, K. Augsten, W. Augustyniak, C. D. R. Azevedo, B. Badelek, J. Barth, R. Beck, J. Beckers, Y. Bedfer, J. Bernhard, M. Bodlak, F. Bradamante, A. Bressan, W. -C. Chang, C. Chatterjee, M. Chiosso, S. -U. Chung, A. Cicuttin, P. M. M. Correia, M. L. Crespo, D. D'Ago, S. Dalla Torre, S. S. Dasgupta, S. Dasgupta, F. Delcarro, I. Denisenko, O. Yu. Denisov, M. Dehpour, S. V. Donskov, N. Doshita, Ch. Dreisbach, W. D\"unnweber, R. R. Dusaev, D. Ecker, D. Eremeev, P. Faccioli, M. Faessler, M. Finger, M. Finger Jr., H. Fischer, K. J. Fl\"othner, W. Florian, J. M. Friedrich, V. Frolov, L. G. Garcia Ord\`o\~nez, O. P. Gavrichtchouk, S. Gerassimov, J. Giarra, D. Giordano, M. Gorzellik, A. Grasso, A. Gridin, M. Grosse Perdekamp, B. Grube, M. Gr\"uner, A. Guskov, P. Haas, D. von Harrach, M. Hoffmann, N. d'Hose, C. -Y. Hsieh, S. Ishimoto, A. Ivanov, T. Iwata, V. Jary, R. Joosten, P. J\"org, E. Kabu\ss, F. Kaspar, A. Kerbizi, B. Ketzer, G. V. Khaustov, F. Klein, J. H. Koivuniemi, V. N. Kolosov, K. Kondo Horikawa, I. Konorov, A. Yu. Korzenev, A. M. Kotzinian, O. M. Kouznetsov, A. Koval, Z. Kral, F. Kunne, K. Kurek, R. P. Kurjata, K. Lavickova, S. Levorato, Y. -S. Lian, J. Lichtenstadt, P. -J. Lin, R. Longo, V. E. Lyubovitskij, A. Maggiora, N. Makke, G. K. Mallot, A. Maltsev, A. Martin, J. Marzec, J. Matou\v{s}ek, T. Matsuda, C. Menezes Pires, F. Metzger, W. Meyer, M. Mikhasenko, E. Mitrofanov, D. Miura, Y. Miyachi, R. Molina, A. Moretti, A. Nagaytsev, D. Neyret, M. Niemiec, J. Nov\'y, W. -D. Nowak, G. Nukazuka, A. G. Olshevsky, M. Ostrick, D. Panzieri, B. Parsamyan, S. Paul, H. Pekeler, J. -C. Peng, M. Pe\v{s}ek, D. V. Peshekhonov, M. Pe\v{s}kov\'a, S. Platchkov, J. Pochodzalla, V. A. Polyakov, C. Quintans, G. Reicherz, C. Riedl, D. I. Ryabchikov, A. Rychter, A. Rymbekova, V. D. Samoylenko, A. Sandacz, S. Sarkar, I. A. Savin, G. Sbrizzai, H. Schmieden, A. Selyunin, L. Sinha, D. Sp\"ulbeck, A. Srnka, M. Stolarski, M. Sulc, H. Suzuki, S. Tessaro, F. Tessarotto, A. Thiel, F. Tosello, A. Townsend, T. Triloki, V. Tskhay, B. Valinoti, B. M. Veit, J. F. C. A. Veloso, B. Ventura, A. Vidon, A. Vijayakumar, M. Virius, M. Wagner, S. Wallner, K. Zaremba, M. Zavertyaev, M. Zemko, E. Zemlyanichkina, M. Ziembicki</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
