<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph</link>
    <description>hep-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 04:00:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Absence of Majorana-Weyl fermions in $d=4$ and the theory of Majorana fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14998v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is customary to identify $\psi_{+}=\nu_{R} + C\overline{\nu_{R}}^{T}$ with a Majorana fermion on the basis of chirality changing charge conjugation $\tilde{C}: \nu_{R}\rightarrow C\overline{\nu_{R}}^{T}$ and parity $\tilde{P}: \nu_{R}\rightarrow i\gamma^{0}\nu_{R}$. The theorem on the absence of a Majorana-Weyl fermion in $d=4$ states $\tilde{C}\gamma_{5}\tilde{C}^{-1}= -\gamma_{5}$ with $\tilde{C}=C\gamma_{4}^{T}$, and thus the charge conjugation of the equivalent Majorana $\psi_{+}=(\frac{1+\gamma_{5}}{2})\nu_{R} + (\frac{1-\gamma_{5}}{2})C\overline{\nu_{R}}^{T}$ vanishes without auxiliary $\gamma_{5}\rightarrow - \gamma_{5}$.
  To be consistent with the theorem, it is common to use a doublet representation of chirality preserving charge conjugation $\hat{C}:\nu_{R,L}\rightarrow C\overline{\nu_{L,R}}^{T}$ and parity $\hat{P}: \nu_{R,L}\rightarrow i\gamma^{0}\nu_{L,R}$ in theory containing both $\nu_{R,L}$. In the type I seesaw model, the latter formulation is applicable but $\psi_{+}=\nu_{R} + C\overline{\nu_{R}}^{T}$ is not a Majorana fermion. An analogue of the Bogoliubov transformation converts $\psi_{\pm}=\nu_{R, L} \pm C\overline{\nu_{R, L}}^{T}$, which are obtained by a precise diagonalization of the seesaw model, to Majorana fermions $\psi_{M_{1,2}}=(\psi \pm C\overline{\psi}^{T})/\sqrt{2}$ with a Dirac-type fermion $\psi$, as originally defined by Majorana. A chiral projection $[(1+\gamma_{5})/2] \psi_{M_{1}}$ of a Majorana fermion is not a chiral fermion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14998v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuo Fujikawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adiabatic hydrodynamization and quasinormal modes of nonthermal attractors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15016v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nonthermal attractors characterize the emergent self-similar evolution of far-from-equilibrium quantum systems, from nuclear collisions to cold-atom experiments. Within the adiabatic hydrodynamization framework, the approach to the nonthermal attractor can be understood as the decay of excited states of an effective Hamiltonian. We use an exactly solvable case of the Boltzmann equation -- the longitudinally expanding overoccupied gluon plasma dominated by small-angle elastic collisions -- to map the eigenmodes in adiabatic hydrodynamization to the quasinormal mode spectrum of the nonthermal attractor. If generalized, this equivalence may be used as a discovery tool for new phenomena in out-of-equilibrium systems. A byproduct of our analysis is the analytic prescaling solutions for systems undergoing strong longitudinal expansion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15016v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matisse De Lescluze, Michal P. Heller, Aleksas Mazeliauskas, Bruno Scheihing-Hitschfeld, Clemens Werthmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radiative Correction from Secret Neutrino Interactions and Implications for Neutrino-Scattering Experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15023</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15023v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: New, neutrinophilic mediators are one potential extension beyond the Standard Model of particle physics. Often, studies of neutrinophilic mediator consist of searching for direct evidence of its production and/or its tree-level virtual effect for generating strong neutrino self-interaction. In this work, we focus instead on the fact that such new mediators \textit{also} lead to deviations in neutrino-matter scattering via radiative corrections. With a mediator mass well below the electroweak scale, these effects are potentially observable in a variety of contexts, including coherent elastic neutrino-nucleus scattering (CEvNS), neutrino deeply-inelastic scattering ($\nu$DIS), and neutrino-electron scattering (e.g., at Borexino). Additionally, such effects lead to new contributions to the $Z$-boson decay width and to non-standard neutrino interactions relevant for long-baseline oscillation experiments. We explore all of these scenarios in some depth, building on the rich phenomenology associated with neutrinophilic mediators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15023v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saeid Foroughi-Abari, Kevin J. Kelly, Yue Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atomic Quantum Sensors for High-Frequency Gravitational Wave Searches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15031v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High-frequency gravitational waves represent an unexplored frontier of gravitational physics. While pulsar timing arrays reach nHz frequencies and ground-based interferometers probe the audio band, the regime above the MHz scale remains essentially untested. We propose a hybrid detection framework in which gravitons convert to photons via the Gertsenshtein effect in strong magnetic fields; the resulting electromagnetic signal is resonantly enhanced in a cavity and read out by atomic quantum sensors. Our approach combines multiple channels, including long-coherence Raman interferometry in alkali atoms, microwave Rydberg transitions, photoionization-based detection, and inner-shell electronic resonances. We derive the graviton-photon conversion probability, compute the induced photon flux, and estimate the shot-noise-limited spectral strain noise density. Depending on configuration, the projected shot-noise-limited sensitivity ranges from $\sqrt{S_{h, {\rm min}}} \sim 10^{-22}{\rm\,Hz^{-1/2}}$ in conservative microwave implementations to $\sqrt{S_{h, {\rm min}}} \sim 10^{-37}{\rm\,Hz^{-1/2}}$ in aggressive optical Raman schemes, potentially surpassing the cosmological bound from Big Bang Nucleosynthesis for stochastic backgrounds, while coherent bursts remain unconstrained and detectable. Such reach allows to test scenarios involving primordial black holes, topological defects, violent phase transitions, and (p)reheating, motivating advances in high-$Q$ cavities, strong-field magnets, and quantum-limited atomic sensors, with broad impact across quantum metrology and fundamental physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15031v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi-fu Cai, Luca Visinelli, Sheng-Feng Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Radiative Corrections on Starobinsky Inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15137v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We analyze radiative corrections to the Starobinsky model of inflation arising from self-interactions of the inflaton, and from its Yukawa couplings, $y$, to matter fermions, and dimensionful trilinear couplings, $\kappa$, to scalar fields, which could be responsible for reheating the Universe after inflation. The inflaton self-interactions are found to be of higher order in the Hubble expansion rate during inflation, and hence unimportant for CMB observations. In contrast, matter couplings to the Starobinsky inflaton can have significant effects on the spectral index of scalar CMB perturbations, $n_s$, and on the tensor-to-scalar ratio, $r$. Using a renormalization-group improved analysis of the effective inflationary potential, we find that the Planck measurement of $n_s$ constrains the inflaton coupling to light fermions in the Einstein frame: $y &lt; 4.5 \times 10^{-4}$, corresponding to an upper limit on the reheating temperature $T_{\rm RH} &lt; 2 \times 10^{11}~{\rm GeV}$, whereas the ACT DR6 measurement of $n_s$ corresponds to $3.8 \times 10^{-4} &lt; y &lt; 5.6 \times 10^{-4}$ and $1.7 \times 10^{11} ~{\rm GeV} &lt; T_{\rm RH} &lt; 2.8 \times 10^{11}~{\rm GeV}$, while the upper limits on $r$ provide weaker constraints. Planck data also imply a constraint on a trilinear inflaton coupling to light scalars in the Einstein frame: $\kappa \leq 4 \times 10^{12}~{\rm GeV}$, corresponding to $T_{\rm RH} \leq 4.2 \times 10^{13}~{\rm GeV}$. We further present constraints on inflaton couplings to massive fermions and scalars, and analyze constraints on couplings in the Jordan frame.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15137v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John Ellis, Tony Gherghetta, Kunio Kaneta, Wenqi Ke, Keith A. Olive</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing di-jet resonance searches via a final-state radiation jet tagging algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15151v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article, we investigate the possibility of enhancing the di-jet resonance searches by tagging the final state radiation (FSR) jet, using an event-level deep neural network. It is found that solely relying on the 4-momenta of the leading three jets allows the algorithm to achieve good discriminating power that can identify the hardest FSR jet in signal, while rejecting other soft jets. Once the invariant mass is corrected with the tagged FSR jet, the mass resolution of the signal is greatly enhanced, and the sensitivity of the search is also improved by 10-20%. By crafting the input variables carefully, the algorithm introduces minimal mass sculpting for the background, and its applicability extends to a broad mass range. This work proves that FSR jet tagging can potentially enhance the di-jet resonance searches, suiting various stages of the physics programmes at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) and High-Luminosity LHC (HL-LHC).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15151v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bing-Xuan Liu, Yu-Xuan Shen, Yuan-Shun-Zi Sui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study of $P$ and $CP$ symmetries in $\Xi^+_c\rightarrow \Xi^-\pi^+\pi^+$ at electron-positron collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15320v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Symmetry studies represent one of the most promising frontiers in particle physics research. This investigation focuses on exploring $P$ and $CP$ symmetries in the charm system through the measurement of asymmetry decay parameters in the three-body decay of $\Xi_c^{+}$. Incorporating electron and positron beam polarization effects and utilizing the helicity formalism, we characterize the decay of $\Xi_c^{+}$ and its secondary hyperons through asymmetry decay parameters. The complete angular distribution formula for these decays has been systematically derived. Our study evaluates the sensitivity of the asymmetry parameters for the $\Xi_c^{+} \to \Xi^{-}\pi^{+}\pi^{+}$ decay channel under various data sample sizes and beam polarization scenarios. These findings establish a robust theoretical framework for future experimental studies at the STCF, providing valuable insights for symmetry investigations in the charm sector.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15320v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunlu Wang, Yunlong Xiao, Pengcheng Hong, Ronggang Ping</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The detection of cosmic neutrino background with helicity-changing decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15377v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this talk, we present the investigation of the invisible decays of a heavy massive neutrino into a lighter neutrino and a massless Nambu-Goldstone boson, i.e., $\nu_i^{} \to \nu_j^{} + \phi$. The total decay rates are calculated in the most general case, where the individual helicities of both parent and daughter neutrinos are specified. We then examine the evolution of the number densities of cosmological relic neutrinos throughout the expansion of the Universe, and explore the consequent impacts on the capture rates in PTOLEMY-like experiments. The total event rates can be significantly modified compared to those in the scenario of stable neutrinos, with helicity-changing decays playing an especially important role in the Dirac neutrino case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15377v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jihong Huang, Shun Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence of Heavy-Flavor PDFs at Small x and Its Impact on Future ep Colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15427v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the first quantitative demonstration of the statistical convergence of heavy-flavor parton distribution functions at small x across modern NNLO global fits. Using the latest NNPDF4.0, CT18, and MSHT20 sets, we find a maximal relative deviation of 16.8 percent at x = 1e-6 and Q = 100 GeV, corresponding to nearly a factor-of-two improvement over the approximately 30 percent spread in pre-2013 determinations. This convergence, stabilized by consistent alpha_s and scale treatments, marks a transition of the heavy-flavor sector into a statistically controlled regime of small-x QCD. We further show that this precision directly reduces PDF-driven uncertainties in heavy-quark electroproduction at future ep colliders (LHeC and FCC-eh) by about a factor of two and enhances the theoretical stability of leptophilic new-physics searches such as a neutral Z_l gauge boson. These findings establish a link between the precision frontier of QCD and the discovery potential of next-generation lepton-hadron facilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15427v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. O. Kara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $\gamma^\ast\to \eta\gamma$ and $\gamma^\ast\to \eta'\gamma$ form factors to NNLO accuracy in perturbative QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15643v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We use conformal symmetry to calculate the NNLO anomalous dimension matrix (three loops) for flavor-singlet axial-vector QCD operators for spin $N \le 8$ from a set of gauge-invariant two-point correlation functions. Combining this result with the recent calculation of the two-loop coefficient functions, we carry out the calculation of the $\gamma\gamma^\ast\to \eta$ and $\gamma\gamma^\ast\to \eta'$ form factors at large momentum transfers to the NNLO accuracy in perturbative QCD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15643v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. M. Braun, K. G. Chetyrkin, A. N. Manashov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Composite Structure and Spin-Orbit Coupling with GPDs in ${}^{4}$He</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15838v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we derive a relation between the generalized parton distributions (GPDs) of a spin-0 composite hadron and the GPDs of its spin-$\tfrac{1}{2}$ constituents. The method decomposes matrix elements of the composite parent into matrix elements of its constituents, weighted by the Wigner distributions of the constituents inside the composite parent. Exploiting the boost invariance of the light-front Wigner distributions, we derive the dictionary between rest-frame and boosted-frame kinematics and use it to perform a Pauli matrix decomposition of the spin degree of freedom. The constraints of unbroken rotational, parity, and time-reversal invariance lead to a master integral for the quark GPDs of the spin-0 composite target. We also identify a novel $\Delta\vec{L}\cdot\vec{S}$ form of spin-orbit coupling responsible for GPD mixing in composite hadrons which is absent in the case of transverse momentum dependent parton distributions (TMDs) of composite hadrons. We then apply the framework to a composite ${}^{4}$He target with simple phenomenological models to identify possible experimental signatures of composite-structure effects in light nuclei. The framework we have constructed here can be readily extended to the case of generalized TMDs (GTMDs), while the phenomenological framework is applicable both to analyses of light nucleus data and as training input for AI-assisted applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15838v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Garcia Vallejo, Matthew D. Sievert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diabatic Dynamical Diquark Model of Hidden-Strangeness Tetraquarks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15844v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We generalize our recent analysis of hidden-strangeness tetraquarks within the dynamical diquark model from its adiabatic form (in which each state is described solely by a diquark-antidiquark potential) to its diabatic form (which incorporates effects of di-hadron thresholds upon the states). We tabulate all relevant thresholds and compute the di-hadron content of each predicted state. Our results produce no particular hidden-strange tetraquark candidate whose structure is dominated by di-hadron structure, in contrast to the charm sector, where many exotic states are strongly associated with such thresholds. Multiple states above 2~GeV with peculiar decay properties, including $\phi(2170)$, $f_2(2340)$, and $\eta(2370)$, continue to serve as excellent hidden-strange tetraquark candidates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15844v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shahriyar Jafarzade, Richard F. Lebed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of Isolation Criteria on Prompt Photon Production in Relativistic Nuclear Collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14633v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Prompt photon measurements in relativistic nuclear collisions serve as an essential comparative basis for heavy ion studies enabling the separation of medium induced effects. However, the identification of prompt photons is experimentally challenging due to substantial backgrounds from photons produced in hadron decays and jet fragmentation. Appropriate isolation criteria are applied to suppress these background contributions. We analyze prompt photon spectra using the JETPHOX framework to quantify the relative contributions of fragmentation and direct production mechanisms to the total photon yield. We perform a systematic study of the impact of isolation criteria on prompt photon production in relativistic nuclear collisions with emphasis on their dependence on beam energy and photon transverse momentum. The fragmentation contribution is found to be substantially large particularly for $p_T &lt; 15$ GeV and the isolation criterion plays a crucial role in the analysis of prompt photons in that $p_T$ region. A dynamical isolation criterion suppresses the fragmentation component more effectively than a fixed one in this region. Furthermore, the isolation criterion shows a stronger dependence on beam energy and photon $p_T$ than on system size. These observations emphasize the importance of employing carefully selected and consistent isolation criteria when comparing experimental data with theoretical calculations especially for observables sensitive to fragmentation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14633v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sinjini Chandra, Rupa Chatterjee, Zubayer Ahammed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-species Dark Matter with Warmth and Randomness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15046</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15046v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a general analytic framework for the evolution of cosmic structure in multi-species dark matter models that simultaneously incorporates finite velocity dispersion and Poisson fluctuations. Our approach accommodates arbitrary numbers of dark matter components with distinct mass fractions, velocity distributions, and number densities -- ranging from cold particles to warm species and sparse populations such as primordial black holes or solitons. The framework is based on solving a truncated BBGKY hierarchy, whose solution is obtained by solving Volterra integral equations. We provide an efficient algorithm to solve for the total, as well as inter- and intra-species power spectra. Worked examples with two-component mixtures illustrate how isocurvature (initially Poisson) and adiabatic spectra evolve differently depending on the properties of the warm or sparse fraction. This evolution is controlled by the free-streaming and Jeans scales, and the results match analytic estimates and $N$-body simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15046v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mustafa A. Amin, M. Sten Delos, Kiaxin Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Ultra-Slow-Roll Inflation in Composite Pseudo-Nambu-Goldstone Boson Models: Implications for Primordial Black Holes and Gravitational Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15460v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study inflation driven by a scalar potential arising from composite-sector dynamics, inspired by generalized composite Higgs models. The introduction of a non-minimal coupling, possessing the same functional form as the potential, induces a flattening at large field values that enables successful inflation. We analyze the conditions for ultra-slow-roll inflation, which leads to enhanced curvature perturbations, by combining analytical criteria near the inflection point with comprehensive numerical scans of the parameter space. The region consistent with Cosmic Microwave Background constraints and yielding approximately $N_e \approx 55\text{-}60$ e-folds also predicts primordial black holes with masses in the range $10^3\text{-}10^5\,\mathrm{g}$. Although such ultra-light primordial black holes are typically expected to have evaporated, recent proposals invoking evaporation suppression via memory-burden effects could allow their survival as viable dark matter candidates. Under this assumption, the induced gravitational wave signal peaks in a frequency gap between standard interferometers and resonant-cavity experiments, motivating exploration of this observational frontier.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15460v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Merchand</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Elementary Operator for Kaon Photoproduction on the Nucleon and Nuclei</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15482</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15482v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A new elementary operator for kaon photoproduction on the nucleon and nuclei has been developed within a Feynman diagrammatic framework. By fitting the unknown coupling strengths at the electromagnetic and hadronic vertices of the baryon resonances to all available experimental data across the six isospin channels, the model achieves excellent agreement with the data. The operator includes 26 nucleon resonances in the $K\Lambda$ channels and 17 additional $\Delta$ resonances in the $K\Sigma$ channels. For applications to nuclear reactions, such as hypernuclear photoproduction, the operator is formulated in Pauli space, allowing a straightforward implementation of the nonrelativistic approximation. Several alternative forms for expressing the operator output are proposed. In one of them, the spin operators and photon polarization vectors are separated from the operator, since both are frame dependent, thereby enhancing its versatility in nuclear applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15482v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Terry Mart, Jovan Alfian Djaja</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativistic tidal divergences in circular orbits and the dynamics of light rings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15705v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Tidal forces acting on orbiting bodies arise from inhomogeneities in the gravitational field, generating stresses that can deform or even disrupt these objects. In this work, we analyze relativistic tidal forces associated with ultracompact objects described by static and spherically symmetric spacetimes, focusing on observers in circular geodesic motion. We show that, in contrast to the case of radial geodesics, tidal forces diverge as the orbit approaches null circular geodesics. As illustrative examples, we study two uniform-density stellar models: one isotropic and another supported purely by tangential stresses. We conjecture that the divergence of tidal forces near light rings may play a role in the nonlinear stability of ultracompact, horizonless objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15705v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor F. C. Vieira, Rafael P. Bernar, Caio F. B. Macedo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of neutrino decays on the Cosmic Neutrino Background anisotropies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15818v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The anisotropies of the Cosmic Neutrino Background (C$\nu$B) offer an ideal tool to test non-standard neutrino interactions, since they directly trace the perturbations in the neutrino distribution function. Here, we study how invisible neutrino decays impact the C$\nu$B anisotropies, in a framework where neutrinos decay non-relativistically to dark radiation and lighter neutrinos in a manner consistent with the measured mass splittings. For this purpose, we perform the first implementation of such a late-time neutrino decay scenario within a linear Einstein-Boltzmann solver, and compute the C$\nu$B angular power spectra from the Boltzmann hierarchy solutions for a range of lifetimes and decay channels. We find that neutrino decays leave very strong signatures on the C$\nu$B angular spectra, about two orders of magnitude larger than on the CMB angular spectra, particularly for lifetimes comparable to the age of the Universe. We show that a future polarized tritium target run of the PTOLEMY experiment, with sufficient counting statistics to measure just the first $\sim 15$ multipoles of the neutrino sky map, could test neutrino decay models that remain undetectable with CMB data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15818v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicola Terzaghi, Guillermo Franco Abell\'an, Fabian Zimmer, Shin'ichiro Ando</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$B-L$ model in light of the CDF II result</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.01522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.01522v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent CDF II collaboration's result on $W$ mass measurements contradict Standard Model prediction, requiring new physics to explain this anomaly. Such new physics may manifest through tree-level or loop-level corrections to the mass of the $W$ boson. In this work, we investigate the possibility that the CDF-II result is indicative of new physics not directly changing the $W$ boson mass but rather the $Z$ boson mass. Since the $Z$ boson mass goes as an input into the Standard Model prediction for $W$ boson mass, this change in $Z$ mass ultimately leads to the discrepancy between the CDF-II measurement and the Standard Model expectation. We demonstrate this idea through one of the simplest and most studied $U(1)$ gauge extensions of the Standard Model, namely the gauged $U(1)_{B-L}$ extension. We demonstrate that $B-L$ extended models can explain the revised best-fit values for $S$, $T$, and $U$ following the CDF II results. We studied the parameter space of models with and without mixing between neutral gauge bosons. We also reviewed the dark matter constraints and demonstrated that there is parameter space that is compatible with the current $W$ boson mass, relic abundance, and direct detection experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.01522v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6471/ae095a</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J.Phys.G 52(2025) 10,105003</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sanjoy Mandal, Hemant Prajapati, Rahul Srivastava</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Femtoscopy can tell whether $Z_c(3900)$ and $Z_{cs}(3985)$ are resonances or virtual states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18607v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: There have been extended and heated discussions on the nature of the two exotic states, $Z_c(3900)$ and $Z_{cs}(3985)$, particularly whether they are near-threshold resonances, virtual states, or bound states. In this work, we demonstrate for the first time that the femtoscopic technique can be employed to distinguish between these three scenarios. More concretely, based on the Koonin-Pratt formula with a Gaussian source, we show that the low-momentum $D^0D^{*-}$/$D^0D_s^{*-}$ correlation functions significantly differ in the three scenarios. The high-momentum results exhibit distinct characteristics in the resonant and virtual state scenarios, especially in small collision systems of 1 fm, as produced in $pp$ collisions at the LHC. We hope that these discoveries will stimulate further experimental studies and help clarify the nature of the many exotic states that have been discovered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18607v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhi-Wei Liu, Jun-Xu Lu, Ming-Zhu Liu, Li-Sheng Geng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for GeV Gamma-Ray Polarization and Axion-Like Particles with AMS-02</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10531</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10531v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the detectability of GeV-band gamma-ray polarization with the AMS-02 experiment and its proposed successor AMS-100, from Galactic and extragalactic sources. Characterizing gamma-ray polarization in this energy range could shed light on gamma-ray emission mechanisms in the sources; physics beyond the Standard Model, such as the presence of axion-like particles (ALPs), could also induce a distinctive energy-dependent polarization signal due to propagation effects in magnetic fields. We present estimates for the minimum detectable polarization from bright sources and the forecast reach for axion-like particles (ALPs). We show that AMS-02 will have sensitivity to gamma-ray polarization only for the brightest steady-state Galactic sources, such as the Vela and Geminga pulsars; it is not expected to be capable of detecting polarization in Galactic or extragalactic sources that have been previously proposed as good targets for ALP searches with gamma-ray intensity measurements. However, AMS-100 observing the extragalactic source NGC1275 would be expected to probe new parameter space even for unfavorable B-field models, with prospects to measure the energy-dependence of such a signal. For Galactic sources, polarization measurements could provide a unique test of scenarios where ALPs induce energy-dependent features in the photon intensity. However, in the absence of a bright transient source (such as a Galactic supernova), the parameter space that would be probed by this approach with ten years of AMS-100 data is already nominally excluded by other experiments, although this conflict may be avoided in specific ALP models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10531v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiuyuan Zhang, Yi Jia, Tracy R. Slatyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The exclusive production of a fully heavy tetraquark and a photon in electron-positron collision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.16777v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The exclusive production of fully heavy tetraquark ($T(bb\bar{b}\bar{b})$, $T(cc\bar{c}\bar{c})$ and $T(bc\bar{b}\bar{c})$) in association with a hard photon in electron-positron collisions is calculated within the framework of non-relativistic QCD. Both inner structures of molecule-like state and compact state with $J=0,1,2$ for the fully heavy tetraquark are discussed. We find that it is dismal to observe any fully heavy tetraquarks in either the compact configuration or the molecule-like configuration through such exclusive processes at either Belle II or future Z factories like CEPC and FCC-ee.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.16777v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao Liang, Jun Jiang, Shi-Yuan Li, Yan-Rui Liu, Zong-Guo Si</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A $B-$anomaly motivated $Z^\prime$ boson at the energy and precision frontiers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21319v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: TeV-scale $Z^\prime$ bosons with family-dependent couplings can explain some anomalies inferred from $B-$meson measurements of processes involving the $b \rightarrow s \ell^+\ell^-$ transition. A $Z^\prime$ originating from kinetically-mixed spontaneously broken $U(1)_{B_3-L_2}$ gauge symmetry has been shown to greatly ameliorate global fits~\cite{Allanach:2024ozu} in a `flavour-preferred' region of parameter space. We provide an exploration of this region at the high luminosity (HL-)LHC with particular attention to which signals could be verified across different discovery modes. Even if the HL-LHC does not discover the $Z^\prime$ boson in a resonant di-lepton channel, a FCC-ee $Z$-pole run would detect oblique corrections to the electroweak precision observables (EWPOs). Changes due to $Z^\prime$-induced non-oblique corrections are unlikely to be detected, to within experimental precision. In any case, the extended discovery potential offered by a 100 TeV $pp-$collider would afford sensitivity to the entire flavour-preferred region and enable a fine-grained and forensic analysis of the~model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21319v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2025.139928</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Lett. B 870 (2025) 139928</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ben Allanach, Christoph Englert, Wrishik Naskar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Scotogenic Parameter Spaces and Mapping Uncharted Dark Matter Phenomenology with Multi-Objective Search Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08862v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a novel artificial intelligence approach to explore beyond Standard Model parameter spaces by leveraging a multi-objective optimisation algorithm. We apply this methodology to a non-minimal scotogenic model which is constrained by Higgs mass, anomalous magnetic moment of the muon, dark matter relic density, dark matter direct detection, neutrino masses and mixing, and lepton flavour violating processes. Our results successfully expand on the phenomenological realisations presented in previous work. We compare between multi- and single-objective algorithms and we observe more phenomenologically diverse solutions and an improved search capacity coming from the former. We use novelty detection to further explore sparsely populated regions of phenomenological interest. These results suggest a powerful search strategy that combines the global exploration of multi-objective optimisation with the exploitation of single-objective optimisation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08862v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP10(2025)116</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP10(2025)116</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Abreu de Souza, Nuno Filipe Castro, Miguel Crispim Rom\~ao, Werner Porod</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Analytic Prescription for $t$-channel Singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10890v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The $t$-channel singularity is a divergence in the scattering amplitude which occurs when a stable particle propagating in $t$-channel scattering process becomes an on-shell state. Such situations appear either in the system of collider experiments or in the context of the cosmological particle production. No scheme which is generally applicable is known. In this work, we propose a new formulation to identify and remove the source of the divergence. The scheme is fully analytical and various applications can be expected. This work provides a valuable tool in this research field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10890v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kento Asai, Nagisa Hiroshima, Joe Sato, Ryusei Sato, Masaki J. S. Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unwinding the rare $\Omega$ sector: Fragmentation of fully charmed baryons from HL-LHC to FCC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00776v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: By adopting a hadron-structure-oriented approach, we present and discuss the release of the novel OMG3Q1.0 set of collinear fragmentation functions for fully charmed, rare $\Omega$ baryons. Our methodology combines diquark-like proxy model inputs for both charm-quark and gluon channels, calculated at the initial energy scales, with a DGLAP evolution that ensures a consistent treatment of heavy-quark thresholds, following directly from the HF-NRevo scheme. We complement our work with a phenomenological study of NLL/NLO$^+$ resummed $\Omega_{3c}$ plus jet distributions using (sym)JETHAD at the HL-LHC and the future FCC. Unraveling the production mechanisms of rare, yet-unobserved hadrons, as provided by the OMG3Q1.0 functions, stands as a key asset for deepening our understanding of QCD at future high-energy hadron colliders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00776v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/sb8n-9nt6</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Giovanni Celiberto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$CP$ violation in two-body hadronic $\Lambda_b$ decays in the PQCD approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.07197</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.07197v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We systematically investigate the $CP$-averaged branching ratios and $CP$ violations (CPVs) for the two-body hadronic decays $\Lambda_b\to ph$, where $h$ runs through the mesons $\pi^-$, $\rho^-$, $a_1^-(1260)$, $K^-$, $K^{\ast -}$, $K_1^-(1270)$ and $K_1^-(1400)$, in the perturbative QCD approach to order $\alpha_s^2$ in the strong coupling. Various topological amplitudes are obtained by incorporating subleading-twist hadron distribution amplitudes, which exhibit reasonable hierarchical patterns, sizable strong phases, and non-negligible higher-power corrections. The predicted direct CPVs in $\Lambda_b\to p\pi^-,pK^-$, different from those in similar $B$ meson decays, are as small as the current data. The low CPV in $\Lambda_b\to p\pi^-$ results from the cancellation between the $S$- and $P$-wave CPVs, while the one in $\Lambda_b\to pK^-$ is determined by the tiny $S$-wave CPV. However, individual partial-wave CPVs can exceed $10\%$, consistent with direct CPVs in $B$ meson decays. The CPVs in the $\Lambda_b\to pK_1^-(1270),pK_1^-(1400)$ channels are relatively larger. In particular, CPVs above $20\%$ appear in the up-down asymmetries associated with the final-state angular distributions of $\Lambda_b\to pK_1^-(1270),pK_1^-(1400)$, followed by the secondary $K_1\to K\pi\pi$ decays. These observables offer promising prospects for firmly establishing baryon CPVs. The decay asymmetry parameters of $\Lambda_b\to ph$ are also predicted for future experimental confrontations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.07197v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Jie Han, Ji-Xin Yu, Ya Li, Hsiang-nan Li, Jian-Peng Wang, Zhen-Jun Xiao, Fu-Sheng Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WIMP/FIMP dark matter and primordial black holes with memory burden effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20071v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The lifetime of primordial black holes (PBHs), which formed in the early universe, can be extended by the memory burden effect. Light PBHs may exist today and be candidates for dark matter (DM). We assume that DM is made of thermally produced weakly interacting massive particles (WIMPs), WIMPs produced via the Hawking radiation of PBHs, and PBHs that survived Hawking evaporation via the memory burden effect. Feebly interacting massive particles (FIMPs) are alternatives to WIMPs. This paper shows that a small memory burden is preferable if the thermal production of WIMPs or FIMPs is much larger than the effect of PBH particle production via Hawking radiation. In addition, we show that the lower limit of the DM mass, called the warm DM (WDM) constraint, decreases with the memory burden effect of PBHs. Results suggest that the WDM constraint is more effective for FIMPs than for WIMPs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20071v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Teruyuki Kitabayashi, Amane Takeshita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flux of Extragalactic Dark Matter in Direct Detection Experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.01190v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We calculate the contribution of extragalactic dark matter to the local dark matter density and flux in the Milky Way. By analyzing the Galactic escape velocity as a function of direction, we establish the criterion for separating dark matter particles bound to the Milky Way and those originating from the Local Group environment. Our analysis reveals that approximately 25% of dark matter particles in the Solar neighborhood have an extragalactic origin, contributing nearly 38% of the total mass flux. The directional dependence of this extragalactic component shows significant anisotropy across the sky, with implications for direct detection experiments. We provide quantitative predictions for detection rates and signatures that could help identify the extragalactic dark matter component in current and future experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.01190v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shokhruz Kakharov, Abraham Loeb</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More visualisation of decay-time-dependent asymmetries in multibody B-meson decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04850v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Methods have been proposed recently to weight data in order to allow visualisation of CP-violation effects in transitions of neutral B mesons to multibody final states that are not CP-eigenstates. These are useful since integration of the unweighted data over the phase space would otherwise wash out the effects of interest. A similar method, elaborated upon here, with a different weighting function can also be used to visualise CP-conserving $B_{(s)}^0$--$\overline{B}{}_{(s)}^0$ oscillations, rather than the CP-violating asymmetries. Together with the other weighting functions, this new method could be useful, for example, to demonstrate the accuracy of the calibration of the flavour tagging algorithms that are crucial for analyses such as the measurement of the CP-violating phase in $B_s^0 \to J/\!\psi\phi$ decays. Their application to the formalism in common use for such decays is explicitly demonstrated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04850v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-025-14812-8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J C85 (2025) 1156</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tim Gershon, Thomas Latham, Peilian Li, Andy Morris, Wenbin Qian, Mark Whitehead, Ao Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Walker in the Early Universe: A Strongly Coupled Sector Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06454</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.06454v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore the phenomenology of the ``Dark Walker'' -- an $\text{SU}(3)$ theory with eight flavors of massless fundamental fermions in the dark sector. During inflation, its walking dynamics generate primordial non-Gaussianities through the exchange of unparticles, while accounting for the current dark matter relic abundance if we consider freeze-in of Dark Walker coupled to the Standard Model through the Higgs portal. This provides a simple yet predictive example linking strongly coupled inflationary dynamics to present-day dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.06454v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prospects for relic neutrino detection using nuclear spin experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20357v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Direct detection of the cosmic neutrino background (C$\nu$B) remains one of the most formidable experimental challenges in modern physics. In this work, we extend recent studies of C$\nu$B-induced coherent transitions in polarised nuclear spin ensembles. Adopting an open quantum system framework, we model coherent neutrino effects in large spin ensembles using a Lindblad master equation that also incorporates realistic experimental imperfections such as local dephasing and imperfect polarisation. We solve the Lindblad equation numerically by way of a fast and computationally inexpensive method that can be extended to an arbitrarily large number of spins. Using our numerical solutions, we forecast the sensitivities of future experiments such as CASPEr to the local C$\nu$B overdensity parameter $\delta_\nu$. Our findings indicate that a CASPEr-like experiment, though primarily aimed at axion dark matter search, could also constrain the C$\nu$B overdensity to $\delta_\nu \sim 10^{13}$ in configurations achievable by currently planned experimental efforts, and down to $\delta_\nu \sim 10^{11}$ in the most optimised scenario. While C$\nu$B detection remains out of reach in the foreseeable future, our results highlight the potential of using quantum sensing to probe fundamental physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20357v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yeray Garcia del Castillo, Giovanni Pierobon, Dipan Sengupta, Yvonne Y. Y. Wong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropy and multiplicity of hadrons in the high energy limit within dipole cascade models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07898v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate and compare QCD dipole cascade models, the 1D Mueller dipole model, its high energy limit and its generalization that follows from studies of 1D systems with conformal symmetry. To address the ambiguity stemming from different definitions of the rapidity ranges in experimental measurements, we propose the entropy as the function of the logarithm of the average multiplicity, $S(\ln\langle n \rangle)$, as a universal observable. From the solutions of the models, we calculate both the entropy and the average charged particle multiplicity and compare to data measured in proton-proton collisions. We obtained these quantities directly from the measured multiplicity distributions and determine the model parameters via fits. We find that the generalized dipole model provides a significantly better description of the data than the 1D Mueller model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07898v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Krzysztof Kutak, S\'andor L\"ok\"os</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collins-type fragmentation energy correlator in semi-inclusive deep inelastic lepton-hadron scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18892v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We initiate a systematic study of fragmentation energy correlators (FECs), which generalize traditional fragmentation functions and encode non-perturbative information about transverse dynamics in parton fragmentation processes. We define boost-invariant, non-perturbative FECs and derive a corresponding collinear factorization formula. A spin decomposition of the FECs is carried out, analogous to that of transverse-momentum-dependent fragmentation functions. In this work we focus particularly on the Collins-type quark FEC, which is sensitive to chiral symmetry breaking and characterizes the azimuthal asymmetry in the fragmentation of a transversely polarized quark. We perform a next-to-leading-order calculation of the corresponding hard coefficient in semi-inclusive deep-inelastic scattering for the quark non-singlet component, thereby validating the consistency of our theoretical framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18892v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qing-Hong Cao, Zhite Yu, C. -P. Yuan, Shutao Zhang, Hua Xing Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbative unitarity for models with singlet and doublet scalars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02434</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02434v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We provide a complete description of unitarity bounds on the gauge-scalar sectors of models with extra $SU(2)$ doublet, neutral singlet, and charged singlet scalars. Such additions are very frequent in models beyond the Standard Model, and, in particular, they are almost universal in models explaining the dark matter problem. We propose a specific classification and minimal set of scattering matrices containing all the relevant information. We also developed a Mathematica implementation of our results, BounDS, and we use it to fully study a number of simple cases, comparing with the literature, when available. The Mathematica notebook BounDS is provided via a public GitHub repository.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02434v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carolina T. Lopes, Andr\'e Milagre, Jo\~ao P. Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surveying the complex three Higgs doublet model with Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02445v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The couplings of the 125 GeV Higgs are being measured with higher precision as the Run 3 stage of LHC continues. Models with multiple Higgs doublets allow potential deviations from the SM predictions. For more than two doublets, there are five possible types of models that avoid flavor changing neutral couplings at tree level by the addition of a symmetry. We consider a softly broken Z2xZ2 three-Higgs doublet model with explicit CP violation in the scalar sector, exploring all five possible types of coupling choices and all five mass orderings of the neutral scalar bosons. The phenomenological study is performed using a Machine Learning black box optimization algorithm that efficiently searches for the possibility of large pseudoscalar Yukawa couplings. We identify the model choices that allow a purely pseudoscalar coupling in light of all recent experimental limits, including direct searches for CP-violation, thus motivating increased effort into improving the experimental precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02445v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael Boto, Jo\~ao A. C. Matos, Jorge C. Rom\~ao, Jo\~ao P. Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the sign-changeable interaction between dark energy and dark matter with DESI baryon acoustic oscillations and DES supernovae data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07361v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: There is a possibility of interaction between dark energy and dark matter, and this interaction may also undergo a sign change during the evolution of the universe. In this paper, we utilize the latest observational data to constrain models of a sign-changeable interaction. The data we employ, in addition to the cosmic microwave background data, also encompass the first-year baryon acoustic oscillation data from DESI and the type Ia supernova data of the full 5-year observation from DES. To achieve high generality, we investigate four interacting dark energy (IDE) models with different forms of the interaction term $Q$: (i) IDE1 with $Q = \beta(a)H\rho_{\rm de}$; (ii) IDE2 with $Q = \beta(a)H\rho_{\rm c}$; (iii) IDE3 with $Q = \beta(a)H_0\rho_{\rm de}$; (iv) IDE4 with $Q = \beta(a)H_0\rho_{\rm c}$. From the analysis, we observe that $\beta(z) &gt; 0$ at early times and $\beta(z) &lt; 0$ at late times, with the coupling $\beta(z)$ crossing the non-interacting line $\beta(z) = 0$ during cosmic evolution at the 2$\sigma$ confidence level for the IDE1, IDE3, and IDE4 models. However, for the IDE2 model, $\beta(z)$ remains consistently negative and does not cross $\beta(z) = 0$ at the 2$\sigma$ confidence level. Our findings indicate that the energy transfer is from dark matter to dark energy when dark matter dominates the universe, and from dark energy to dark matter when dark energy dominates, for the IDE1 and IDE3 models. Furthermore, Bayesian evidence suggests that the IDE1 and IDE3 models are moderately preferred over the $\Lambda$CDM model. The overall outcomes of this study clearly indicate that, based on current observational data, the sign-changeable IDE models are quite compelling and merit further attention.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07361v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11433-025-2771-5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Sci. China-Phys. Mech. Astron. 69, 210413 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tian-Nuo Li, Guo-Hong Du, Yun-He Li, Peng-Ju Wu, Shang-Jie Jin, Jing-Fei Zhang, Xin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cabibbo-Kobayashi-Maskawa unitarity deficit reduction via finite nuclear size</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17070v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We revisit the extraction of the $|V_{ud}|$ CKM matrix element from the superallowed transition decay rate of $^{26m}$Al$\rightarrow$$^{26}$Mg, focusing on finite nuclear size effects. The decay rate dependence on the $^{26m}$Al charge radius is found to be four times higher than previously believed, necessitating precise determination. However, for a short-lived isotope of an odd $Z$ element such as $^{26m}$Al, radius extraction relies on challenging many-body atomic calculations. We performed the needed calculations, finding an excellent agreement with previous ones, which used a different methodology. This sets a new standard for the reliability of isotope shift factor calculations in many-electron systems. The $\mathcal{F}t$ value obtained from our analysis is lower by $2.2\,\sigma$ than the corresponding value in the previous critical survey, resulting in an increase in $|V_{ud}|^2$ by $0.9\,\sigma$. Adopting $|V_{ud}|$ from this decay alone reduces the CKM unitarity deficit by one standard deviation, irrespective of the choice of $|V_{us}|$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17070v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/z8g6-9j25</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.Res.7(2025)4,L042002</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M Gorchtein, V Katyal, B Ohayon, B K Sahoo, CY Seng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational waves from low-scale cosmic strings without scaling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.04537v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Cosmic strings are predicted in many extensions of the Standard Model and constitute a plausible source of gravitational waves (GWs) from the early Universe. In a previous article arXiv:2405.10937v2, we pointed out that the GW spectrum from a population of string loops in the scaling regime can exhibit a sharp cutoff frequency associated with the fundamental oscillation mode of string loops. In this paper, we study the effect of particle decay due to kink-kink collisions and cusps on the GW spectrum in the nonscaling scenario introduced in Ref. arXiv:1911.12066. We find analytical conditions for the existence of a cutoff frequency in the fundamental spectrum and provide expressions for this frequency. In large regions of parameter space, our results in the nonscaling model turn out to be identical to those in the scaling model. Finally, we demonstrate how the spectrum changes when transitioning from the regime with a cutoff frequency to the regime without a cutoff frequency. Our analytical estimates are validated at qualitatively different benchmark points by comparing them with numerical spectra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.04537v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/bv4k-xkmt</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 112, 083517 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kai Schmitz, Tobias Schr\"oder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Method for high-precision determination of the nucleon axial structure using lattice QCD: Removing $\pi N$-state contamination</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06854</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06854v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We performed a precise calculation of physical quantities related to the axial structure of the nucleon using 2+1 flavor lattice QCD gauge configuration (PACS10 configuration) generated at the physical point with lattice volume larger than $(10\;{\mathrm{fm}})^4$ by the PACS Collaboration. The nucleon matrix element of the axial-vector current has two types of the nucleon form factors, the axial-vector ($F_A$) form factor and the induced pseudoscalar ($F_P$) form factor. Recently lattice QCD simulations have succeeded in reproducing the experimental value of the axial-vector coupling, $g_A$, determined from $F_A(q^2)$ at zero momentum transfer $q^2=0$, at a percent level of statistical accuracy. However, the $F_P$ form factor so far has not reproduced the experimental values well due to strong $\pi N$ excited-state contamination. Therefore, we proposed a simple subtraction method for removing the so-called leading $\pi N$-state contribution, and succeeded in reproducing the values obtained by two experiments of muon capture on the proton and pion electro-production for $F_P(q^2)$. The novel approach can also be applied to the nucleon pseudoscalar matrix element to determine the pseudoscalar ($G_P$) form factor with the help of the axial Ward-Takahashi identity. The resulting form factors, $F_P(q^2)$ and $G_P(q^2)$, are in good agreement with the prediction of the pion-pole dominance model. In the new analysis, the induced pseudoscalar coupling $g_P^\ast$ and the pion-nucleon coupling $g_{\pi NN}$ can be evaluated with a few percent accuracy including systematic uncertainties using existing data calculated at two lattice spacings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06854v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/2y8x-5lyc</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yasumichi Aoki (for the PACS Collaboration), Ken-Ichi Ishikawa (for the PACS Collaboration), Yoshinobu Kuramashi (for the PACS Collaboration), Shoichi Sasaki (for the PACS Collaboration), Kohei Sato (for the PACS Collaboration), Eigo Shintani (for the PACS Collaboration), Ryutaro Tsuji (for the PACS Collaboration), Hiromasa Watanabe (for the PACS Collaboration), Takeshi Yamazaki (for the PACS Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ECFA Higgs, electroweak, and top Factory Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.15390v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The ECFA Higgs, electroweak, and top Factory Study ran between 2021 and 2025 as a broad effort across the experimental and theoretical particle physics communities, bringing together participants from many different proposed future collider projects. Activities across three main working groups advanced the joint development of tools and analysis techniques, fostered new considerations of detector design and optimisation, and led to a new set of studies resulting in improved projected sensitivities across a wide physics programme. This report demonstrates the significant expansion in the state-of-the-art understanding of the physics potential of future e+e- Higgs, electroweak, and top factories, and has been submitted as input to the 2025 European Strategy for Particle Physics Update.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.15390v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.23731/CYRM-2025-005</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>H. Abidi, J. A. Aguilar-Saavedra, S. Airen, S. Ajmal, M. Al-Thakeel, G. L. Alberghi, J. Alcaraz Maestre, J. Alimena, S. Alshamaily, J. Altmann, W. Altmannshofer, Y. Amhis, A. Amiri, A. Andreazza, S. Antusch, O. Arnaez, K. A. Assamagan, S. Aumiller, K. Azizi, P. Azzi, P. Azzurri, E. Bagnaschi, Z. Baharyioon, H. Bahl, V. Balagura, D. Barducci, M. J. Basso, P. Bechtle, L. Bellagamba, M. Berggren, G. Bernardi, J. Bhom, L. Biermann, F. Blekman, B. Bliewert, M. Bordone, V. Boudry, D. Boye, I. Bozovic, J. Braathen, J. -C. Brient, G. Brodbek, E. Brost, P. Bruckman, B. Brudnowski, M. Bulliri, E. Bulyak, J. M. Burridge, P. N. Burrows, D. Buttazzo, G. Cacciapaglia, V. Cairo, O. Cakir, A. C. Canbay, F. Canelli, J. M. Carceller, C. Carloni Calame, N. F. Castro, V. Cavaliere, E. Celada, F. G. Celiberto, M. Cepeda, G. Chachamis, M. Chala, C. Charlot, H. -C. Cheng, M. Chiesa, M. Chrzaszcz, W. Chung, M. Cobal, I. Combes, A. E. Connelly, C. Cornella, F. Cornet-Gomez, I. Corredoira, A. J. Costa, T. Critchley, E. Curtis, D. d'Enterria, M. Dam, V. Dao, A. Das, S. Dasu, J. Davighi, J. de Blas, N. De Filippis, A. De Moor, A. De Vita, M. M. Defranchis, C. L. Del Pio, M. Delmastro, H. Denizli, A. Desai, K. Dewyspelaere, M. Di Carlo, S. D. Dittmaier, D. Dobur, A. Dondarini, M. Drewes, B. Dudar, H. Duran Yildiz, G. Durieux, J Dutta, U. Einhaus, W. Elmetenawee, C. Englert, F. Erben, B. A. Erdelyi, J. Eysermans, S. Farrington, H. Fatehi, A. Filipe Silva, M. C. Fouz, R. Franceschini, B. Francois, A. Freitas, K. Fujii, J. Fuster, M. G. Gabelmann, F. Gaede, A. Gall\'en, G. Ganis, D. Garcia, S. Gascon-Shotkin, K. Gautam, Y. Georis, S. Giappichini, P. Goldenzweig, R. Gonzalez Suarez, E. G. Gorini, L. Gouskos, F. G. Grancagnolo, L. Gray, R. Gr\"ober, A. Greljo, A. V. Gritsan, A. Grohsjean, C. Grojean, J. Gu, G. Guerrieri, J. Hajer, C. Hays, J. Hayward, S. Heinemeyer, K. Hidaka, G. Iakovidis, A. Ilg, A. Irles, M. Ishino, G. Isidori, A. Jafari, R. Jafariseyedabad, A. J\"uttner, D. Jeans, X. -H. Jiang, E. Jourd'huy, G. Kacarevic, A. Kaczmarska, J. Kalinowski, K. K\"oneke, S. Keilbach, M. Kenzie, V. Keus, H. Khanpour, J. Kieseler, W. Kilian, B. Kilminster, J. Klamka, J. Klari\'c, M. Klute, P. Kontaxakis, P. Koppenburg, A. Korajac, K. Kr\"oninger, S. Kuberski, M. Kucharczyk, T. H. Kwok, T. Lagouri, J Lahiri, M. Larson, C. Leonidopoulos, T. Lesiak, A. Li, C. Li, L. Li, J. Liao, J. List, P. Lo Chiatto, V. Lukashenko, A. Lusiani, Y. Ma, A. Macchiolo, R. Madar, T. Madlener, A. -M. Magnan, P. Malecki, M. Malekhosseini, A. Maloizel, F. Maltoni, L. S. Mandacar\'u Guerra, L. Mantani, G. Marchiori, G. Marino, D. Marzocca, J. P. M\'arquez, A. Mehta, K. Mekala, C. Meroni, F. Mescia, A. B. Meyer, G. Milutinovic-Dumbelovic, K. M. Mimasu, V. Miralles, T. Miralles, M. Miralles L\'opez, W. Mitaroff, V. A. Mitsou, A. Mohammadi, M. Mohammadi Najafabadi, G. Montagna, S. Monteil, G. Moortgat-Pick, N. Morange, M. Moreno Ll\'acer, T. Mori, K. Mota Amarilo, T. Murata, E. Musumeci, J. Nakajima, S. Narita, M. T. N\'u\~nez Pardo de Vera, C. -H Nee, J. Nesbitt, A. Nesterenko, O. Nicrosini, M. Nourbakhsh, D. Ntounis, C. Ochando, T. Ohl, N. Okada, V. A. Okorokov, B. M. S. Oliveira, W. Ootani, M. Ouchemhou, F. Palla, P. Panci, O. Panella, G. Panizzo, B. Pattnaik, R. P\"oschl, R. Perez-Ramos, F. Piccinini, A. Pilkington, M. Pinamonti, N. Pinto, L. Pintucci, S. Plaetzer, V. Plakkot, M. A. Pleier, E. Ploerer, G. Polesello, Z. Polonsky, P. Poulose, M. Presilla, A. Price, M. P. Primavera, F. M. Procacci, D. Protopopescu, W. P{\l}aczek, K. Radchenko Serdula, L. R\"ohrig, M. Reboud, L. Reichenbach, S. Renner, J. Reuter, F. Richard, G. Ripellino, T. Robens, A. Robson, J. Rojo, A. Rossia, S. Rostami, M. Ruan, A. Ruiz Jimeno, F. Sabatini, A. Sabio Vera, A. Saibel, A. Sailer, K. Sakurai, R. Salerno, M. A. Sanchis, S. Sasikumar, D. Schulte, A. Schwartzman, R. Schwienhorst, A. Sciandra, F. Sefkow, T. Seino, N. Selimovi\'c, M. Selvaggi, A. Senol, A. Sfyrla, Y. Shi, A. Si\'odmok, J. Silva, F. Simon, Y. Sirois, T. Sj\"ostrand, P. Skands, L. Skinnari, K. Skovpen, M. Skrzypek, V. Slokenbergs, J. Smiesko, I. Smiljanic, S. Snyder, Y. Soreq, M. Spira, T. Suehara, O. Sumensari, R. H. Szafron, M. Szewc, R. Tagami, H. Taibi, T. Takeshita, M. Tammaro, M. D. Tat, J. ter Hoeve, M. Thomas, S. Thor, J. Tian, A. Tishelman-Charny, S. Tizchang, L. Toffolin, A. Tolosa-Delgado, J. Torndal, J. T. Tsang, I. Turk Cakir, M. Tytgat, F. Ucci, N. Valle, M. Vande Voorde, I. Veli\v{s}\v{c}ek, M. Vellasco, A. Verduras Schaeidt, C. Vernieri, C. Verollet, A. Vicini, I. Vidakovic, M. Vos, E. Vryonidou, N. Vukasinovic, B. F. L. Ward, N. Wardle, Z. Was, G. Weiglein, X. -K. Wen, A. R. Wiederhold, A. Wiedl, G. Wilkinson, S. Williams, G. W. Wilson, Z. Wu, J. Xiao, B. Yan, F. Yu, Z. Yu, C. -P. Yuan, R. Zanzottera, A. F. Zarnecki, M. Zaro, K. Zembaczynski, D. Zerwas, Y. Zhang, Y. Zhang, X. Zuo, J. Zurita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decaying superfluid turbulence near an anomalous non-thermal fixed point</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21285</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21285v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Anomalously slow coarsening in a dilute two-dimensional (2d) superfluid -- associated with a non-thermal fixed point in the closed system's universal dynamics and driven by three-vortex collisions which initiate vortex-pair annihilations -- is found to exhibit spatial scaling characteristics of Kraichnan-Kolmogorov turbulence. During a universal interval, when the characteristic length scale related to the inter-defect distance grows as $\ell_\text{v}\sim t^{\,\beta}$, with $\beta\approx1/5$, moments of the superfluid velocity circulation around an area of extent $r$ scale as predicted by classical turbulence theory, $\Gamma^{p}(r)\sim r^{4p/3}$. Intermittency corrections seen for higher values of $p$ are found to be consistent with values measured for fully developed, classical turbulence. Hence, we link the decaying quantum turbulence cascade in a closed superfluid to universal dynamics close to a non-thermal fixed point. The decay exponent $\beta$ clearly deviates from values known for classical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21285v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niklas Rasch, Thomas Gasenzer</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
