<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph</link>
    <description>hep-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 04:00:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Spacetime Grand Unified Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11564v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Standard Model of particle physics is derived from first principles starting from the free Dirac Lagrangian. All known fermionic particle species plus three right handed neutrinos are obtained from ideals of a $C\ell_{8}$ algebra, with gauge symmetries arising as rotations of creation-annihilation operators and vacua. Triality originates both the strong force and three particle families with a mass hierarchy. Lorentz and gauge transformations are unified while avoiding the Coleman-Mandula theorem. Chirality stems unavoidably from rotations leaving the vacua invariant, with a predicted Weinberg angle of $\sin^2(\theta_W)=3/8$. The theory is anomaly-free and devoid of proton decay.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11564v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gon\c{c}alo M. Quinta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Making the Subdominant Dominant: Gravothermal Pile-Up of Collisional Dark Matter Around Compact Objects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11601v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The dark matter may consist of multiple species that interact differently. We show that a species that is cosmologically subdominant but highly collisional can pile up and become dominant in deep gravitational wells, such as those of white dwarfs and neutron stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11601v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reza Ebadi, Erwin H. Tanin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electromagnetic Dirac Cogenesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11607v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a novel cogenesis mechanism by utilising the two-body decay of heavy vector-like fermions to dark matter (DM) $\chi$ and right chiral part of light Dirac neutrino $\nu_R$ via the electromagnetic dipole operator. This leads to generation of asymmetry in dark fermion $\chi$ as well as $\nu_R$ with the latter getting transferred to left-handed lepton doublets via Yukawa interactions with a neutrinophilic Higgs doublet. While lepton asymmetry is converted into baryon asymmetry of the Universe via electroweak sphalerons, the dark fermion asymmetry results in asymmetric dark matter. Since CP asymmetries in lepton and dark sector are equal and opposite due to net lepton number conservation, DM mass is restricted to a fixed value $\sim \mathcal{O}(1)$ GeV. Long-lived nature of DM keeps indirect detection prospects at gamma-ray telescopes alive while thermalised light Dirac neutrinos lead to observable dark radiation at cosmic microwave background (CMB) experiments. Heavy vector-like fermions can be probed at terrestrial experiments via their electromagnetic dipole interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11607v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debasish Borah, Arnab Dasgupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QED-IR as Topological Quantum Theory of Dressed States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11668v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate quantum electrodynamics in the infrared regime (QED-IR) using the adiabatic approximation and the framework of the functional Berry phase. In this approach, the physical state space is exact, nonperturbatively dressed, and endowed with a topological structure. Electrons do not exist as bare particles, but as topologically protected electron-photon clouds, defining a new kind of infrared quantum. These clouds are weakly bound in energy -- with a binding scale estimated at \( \Lambda_{\text{IR}} \sim 0.2 \, \text{eV} \) -- and remain stable provided photon energies remain below this threshold. Crucially, the theory becomes exactly solvable in this regime due to the quantization of the functional Berry flux, which governs the infrared dynamics of the dressed states.
  When hard (high-energy) processes are involved, this topological protection is lifted, and the theory smoothly recovers conventional perturbative QED. In contrast, in the deep infrared, the electromagnetic interaction never fully vanishes, leading to observable effects. We argue that the energy required to dissolve the infrared electron-photon cloud in QED is approximately \( 0.2 \, \text{eV} \), well above the thermal energy of the cosmic microwave background (CMB). However, the observed temperature anisotropies correspond to fluctuations near \( 10^{-9} \, \text{eV} \), which may lie at the threshold for perturbing, but not destroying, the topological structure of the dressed state. This suggests that CMB deviations could reflect residual topological imprints of the functional infrared dynamics. Finally, we propose that analogous cloud-like structures may manifest in other quantum systems governed by low-energy photon dynamics, such as atomic and molecular environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11668v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Gamboa, F. Mendez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comprehensive investigation on baryon number violating nucleon decays involving an axion-like particle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11844v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we systematically investigate baryon number violating (BNV) nucleon decays into an axion-like particle (ALP), within a low energy effective field theory extended with an ALP, named as aLEFT. Unlike previous studies in the literature, we consider contributions to nucleon decays from a complete set of dimension-eight BNV aLEFT operators involving light $u,\,d,\,s$ quarks. We perform the chiral irreducible representation (irrep) decomposition of all those interactions under the QCD chiral group $\rm SU(3)_{\tt L}\times SU(3)_{\tt R}$, and match them onto the recently developed chiral framework to obtain nucleon-level effective interactions among the ALP, octet baryons, and octet pseudoscalar mesons. Within this framework, we derive general expressions for the decay widths of nucleon two- and three-body decays involving an ALP. We then analyze the momentum distributions for the three-body modes and find that the operators belonging to the newly identified chiral irreps $\pmb{6}_{\tt L(R)}\times \pmb{3}_{\tt L(R)}$ exhibit markedly different behavior compared to that in the usual irreps $\pmb{8}_{\tt L(R)}\times \pmb{1}_{\tt L(R)}$ and $\pmb{3}_{\tt L(R)}\times \bar{\pmb{3}}_{\tt L(R)}$. Furthermore, due to the lack of direct constraints on those exotic decay modes, we reanalyze the experimental data collected by Super-Kamiokande and establish bounds on the inverse decay widths of these new modes by properly accounting for experimental efficiencies and Cherenkov threshold effects. Our recasting constraints are several orders of magnitude more stringent than the inclusive bounds used in the literature. Based on these improved bounds, we set stringent limits on the associated effective scales across a broad range of ALP mass and predict stringent bounds on certain neutron and hyperon decays involving an ALP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11844v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Qi Fan, Yi Liao, Xiao-Dong Ma, Hao-Lin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fully strange tetraquark states via QCD sum rules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11874v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we have systematically explored the mass spectrum of fully strange tetraquark candidates within the framework of QCD sum rules, focusing on states with quantum numbers $J^{PC}=0^{++}$, $0^{-+}$, $0^{--}$, $1^{--}$, $1^{+-}$, and $1^{++}$. The analysis reveals the existence of fully strange tetraquark states with masses ranging from approximately $2.08$ to $3.12$ GeV. These predictions are confronted with existing experimental observations of potential fully strange tetraquark resonances, notably the $X(2300)$ recently reported by the BESIII Collaboration, which may be interpreted as a fully strange tetraquark state. Furthermore, the possible decay modes of these fully strange tetraquark states are analyzed, providing guidance for their identification in current and future high energy experiments such as BESIII, Belle II, and LHCb.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11874v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bing-Dong Wan, Ji-Chong Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A radiative lepton model in a non-invertible fusion rule</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11951v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a new mechanism in which electron and muon masses are induced at one-loop level after dynamically violating the symmetry of the Ising fusion rule. In the neutrino sector, while the neutrino mass is generated at one-loop level, the Ising fusion rule plays a role in stabilizing the particles inside the loop. As a result, the symmetry works like a $Z_2$ symmetry that is not broken at any loop order. Subsequently, we discuss the lepton flavor violating processes, muon anomalous magnetic dipole moment, and relic density of dark matter, where we specify our dark matter candidate to be a singlet boson and briefly analyze the relic density by estimating the DM annihilation cross section. Finally, we present results for both the DM cross section and the muon $g-2$, satisfying the neutrino oscillation data as well as the constraints of lepton flavor violations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11951v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingqian Chen, Chao-Qiang Geng, Hiroshi Okada, Jia-Jun Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High spin kaons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12072v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The COMPASS Collaboration recently reported the observation of strange-meson spectra in the reaction $K^- + p \to K^- \pi^- \pi^+ + p$ and found $K_3$ and $K_4$ states, with masses of $2119 \pm 13 ^{+45}_{-12}$ MeV and $2210 \pm 40 ^{+80}_{-30}$ MeV, respectively. This discovery has significantly renewed interest, prompting a detailed and systematic study of high-spin kaons. In this work, we analyze the mass spectrum and the Okubo-Zweig-Iizuka-allowed two-body strong decay properties of high-spin kaons having $J^P=3^{\pm}, 4^{\pm}$, and $5^{\pm}$ within the framework of the modified Godfrey-Isgur model and the $^3P_0$ model. Moreover, we identify critical decay channels, which may serve as useful guidance for future experimental studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12072v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ya-Rong Wang, Hao Chen, Xiao-Hai Liu, Cheng-Qun Pang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Torsion induced current-scalaron coupling in Einstein-Cartan gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12151v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the matter current couplings with the scalar degrees of freedom originated from the torsion in Einstein-Cartan (EC) gravity. It has been shown in previous studies that the presence of the operators consisting of torsion components up to dimension four can naturally induce a (pseudo-)scalar degree of freedom, the scalaron. In this work, we consider the couplings between torsion and matter currents in this framework, and show that they can lead to couplings between these currents and the scalaron in the equivalent metric theory. We consider both gauge-invariant and gauge-dependent currents, showing general results and several concrete examples. These results are useful for the discussion of particle production processes after inflation in the EC framework, such as reheating and baryogenesis, and show the connection to the QCD $\theta$ term.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12151v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minxi He, Muzi Hong, Kyohei Mukaida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bias with a Timer: Axion Domain Wall Decay and Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12268v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the interplay of the post-inflationary QCD axion and a light scalar field for the axion domain wall decay and dark matter (DM). The scalar field possesses a nonzero vacuum expectation value (VEV) during inflation, so that its interaction with the axion effectively serves as an explicit Peccei-Quinn (PQ) violating term. At a temperature below the PQ phase transition, the effective PQ violating interaction generates the axion potential which generally contains multiple degenerate vacua leading to the formation of the axion string-domain wall networks. The following QCD phase transition provides another contribution to the axion potential making domain walls decay before they dominate the Universe. Later, the scalar field starts to relax to the minimum of its potential with a vanishing VEV, turning off the effective PQ violating interaction so that the axion potential is aligned with the QCD vacuum. We keep track of the evolution of the axion-scalar system and discuss the production of the axion DM through the domain wall decay and the (trapped) misalignment. We find that the string-wall network in some cases can decay due to its structural instability, rather than the volume pressure, and the correct axion DM abundance is realized with the decay constant larger than that of the conventional post-inflationary QCD axion without fine tuning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12268v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sally Yuxuan Hao, Shota Nakagawa, Yuichiro Nakai, Motoo Suzuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No Hiding in the Dark: Cosmological Bounds on Heavy Neutral Leptons with Dark Decay Channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12270v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Heavy neutral leptons (HNLs) are well-motivated new physics candidates. The mixing of sub-GeV HNLs with active neutrinos is severely constrained by cosmology. In particular, the success of Big Bang Nucleosynthesis (BBN) requires the HNL lifetime to be shorter than about 0.02 sec if they were in thermal equilibrium, thus excluding a wide range of mixing angles accessible to terrestrial experiments. In order to justify the laboratory searches in this cosmologically-forbidden region, it is often argued that adding new dark sector decay modes of HNLs can evade the stringent BBN constraint. Here we rule out this possibility and show that, contrary to the naive expectation, HNLs with significant dark decay modes actually lead to stronger cosmological bounds. This is mainly because of the increase in the extra radiation energy density in the Universe around the BBN epoch, which causes observable effects in the primordial helium fraction and $\Delta N_{\rm eff}$. Our result has major implications for laboratory searches of HNLs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12270v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. S. Bhupal Dev, Quan-feng Wu, Xun-Jie Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boosted dark matter versus dark matter-induced neutrinos from single and stacked blazars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12278</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12278v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The physics responsible for the production of observed high-energy neutrinos have not been established so far, neither for the diffuse astrophysical ones nor for those detected from single blazars. We recently proposed that both could be explained by deep inelastic scatterings between sub-GeV dark matter (DM) around blazars and protons within their jets. Here, we compute the proton-recoil signals at the neutrino detectors Super-Kamiokande, KamLAND, Borexino, JUNO, Hyper-Kamiokande and DUNE induced by DM that is itself boosted by the scatterings with protons in blazar jets. We do it for the four cases of vector, axial, scalar and pseudoscalar mediators of DM-quark interactions. We perform the analysis for the single blazar TXS 0506+056 and for a sample of more than 300 stacked blazars. We find that searches for such blazar-boosted DM leave room for a variety of DM models to explain observations of high-energy neutrinos. We check that the depletion of the DM spike induced by DM-proton and DM-DM interactions does not compromise the DM interpretation for high-energy neutrinos, but challenges other blazar-DM signals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12278v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Giovanni De Marchi, Alessandro Granelli, Filippo Sala, Jacopo Nava</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bulk viscosity and $n$-component fluids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12365v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the hydrodynamics of out-of-equilibrium dense viscous fluids is of key importance to accurate descriptions of physical systems such as compact stars, particularly their mergers. We consider a near-equilibrium relativistic fluid with $n$ independent and small chemical potentials restoring the system back towards equilibrium. By diagonalising the evolution equation for the out-of-equilibrium chemical potentials, we construct an explicit evolution equation for the bulk scalar of the system in second-order hydrodynamics in terms of equilibrium quantities. We find expressions for the $2n$ transport quantities and show that in the rest frame of the fluid, the system admits a Green's function corresponding to an $n$-component fluid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12365v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saga S\"appi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do Cosmic String Segments Emit Gravitational Waves?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12386v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cosmic strings are predicted in various extensions of the Standard Model, including grand unified theories. Depending on the symmetry-breaking pattern, they can be either topologically stable or metastable. Intriguingly, metastable strings have been proposed as a possible origin of the gravitational wave (GW) background observed by recent pulsar timing array experiments. When metastable strings decay, they fragment into segments with monopoles and antimonopoles attached at their endpoints. The monopole and antimonopole are strongly pulled by the string tension. Violent oscillations of these segments have been considered as a potential GW source, in addition to contributions from string loops. We show that, in realistic situations, the monopoles frequently collide with thermal fluctuations on the string segments, which act as a resistance and prevent the oscillation. As a result, we find that the contribution from string segments to the GW background is negligible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12386v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akifumi Chitose, Masahiro Ibe, Shunsuke Neda, Satoshi Shirai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phenomenological Modeling of the $^{163}$Ho Calorimetric Electron Capture Spectrum from the HOLMES Experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09240</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09240v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive phenomenological analysis of the calorimetric electron capture (EC) decay spectrum of $^{163}$Ho as measured by the HOLMES experiment. Using high-statistics data, we unfold the instrumental energy resolution from the measured spectrum and model it as a sum of Breit-Wigner resonances and shake-off continua, providing a complete set of parameters for each component. Our approach enables the identification and tentative interpretation of all observed spectral features, including weak and overlapping structures, in terms of atomic de-excitation processes. We compare our phenomenological model with recent ab initio theoretical calculations, finding good agreement for both the main peaks and the spectral tails, despite the limitations of current theoretical and experimental precision. The model delivers an accurate description of the endpoint region, which is crucial for neutrino mass determination, and allows for a realistic treatment of backgrounds such as pile-up and tails of low-energy components. Furthermore, our decomposition facilitates the generation of Monte Carlo toy spectra for sensitivity studies and provides a framework for investigating systematic uncertainties related to solid-state and detector effects. This work establishes a robust foundation for future calorimetric neutrino mass experiments employing $^{163}$Ho, supporting both data analysis and experimental design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09240v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Ahrens, B. K. Alpert, D. T. Becker, D. A. Bennett, E. Bogoni, M. Borghesi, P. Campana, R. Carobene, A. Cattaneo, A. Cian, H. H. Corti, N. Crescini, M. De Gerone, W. B. Doriese, M. Faverzani, L. Ferrari Barusso, E. Ferri, J. Fowler, G. Gallucci, S. Gamba, J. D. Gard, H. Garrone, F. Gatti, A. Giachero, M. Gobbo, A. Irace, U. K\"oster, D. Labranca, M. Lusignoli, F. Malnati, F. Mantegazzini, B. Margesin, J. A. B. Mates, E. Maugeri, E. Monticone, R. Moretti, A. Nucciotti, G. C. O'Neil, L. Origo, G. Pessina, S. Ragazzi, M. Rajteri, C. D. Reintsema, D. R. Schmidt, D. S. Swetz, Z. Talip, J. N. Ullom, L. R. Vale</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherent State Path Integral Reveals Unexpected Vacuum Structure in Thermal Field Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11608</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11608v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct the path integral formulation of the partition function for a free scalar thermal field theory using coherent states, first in the ladder operator basis and then in the field operator basis. In so doing, we provide for the first time a mapping in quantum field theory between the field-basis coherent states and ladder-basis coherent states. Using either basis, one finds terms missed in the usual path integral derivation, which we identify as the vacuum energy contribution to the partition function. We then extend the field-basis coherent state method to the interacting $\phi^4$ theory. In addition to the vacuum energy contribution, one finds a coupling of a vacuum expectation value to the mass term that is absent in the existing literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11608v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rens Roosenstein, Maximilian Attems, W. A. Horowitz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing the effective action approach to bubble nucleation in holography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11622v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The nucleation of bubbles during a first-order phase transition has recently been explored using holographic duality, which can provide an important complement to standard perturbative methods. These computations typically require finding static and spatially inhomogeneous saddle points, known as critical bubbles, which correspond in the gravitational dual to solutions of nonlinear partial differential equations. A computationally simpler alternative is to use the gravitational dual to derive the effective action of the boundary theory in a derivative expansion, and then solve the resulting lower-dimensional equations of motion. Once the effective action, typically truncated at two derivatives, is obtained, the holographic theory can be set aside, and bubble solutions can be found from ordinary differential equations. In this paper, we test this approach in a simple holographic setup: a probe scalar field in a black brane background with nonlinear multi-trace boundary conditions. We compute critical bubble solutions both from the effective action and by solving the full gravitational equations, and find good agreement between the two methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11622v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oscar Henriksson, Niko Jokela, Xin Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Instability of regular planar black holes in four dimensions arising from an infinite sum of curvature corrections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11803v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In four-dimensional scalar-tensor theories derived via dimensional regularization with a conformal rescaling of the metric, we study the stability of planar black holes (BHs) whose horizons are described by two-dimensional compact Einstein spaces with vanishing curvature. By taking an infinite sum of Lovelock curvature invariants, it is possible to construct BH solutions whose metric components remain nonsingular at $r=0$, with a scalar-field derivative given by $\phi'(r)=1/r$, where $r$ is the radial coordinate. We show that such BH solutions suffer from a strong coupling problem, where the kinetic term of the even-parity scalar-field perturbation associated with the timelike coordinate vanishes everywhere. Moreover, we find that these BHs are subject to both ghost and Laplacian instabilities for odd-parity perturbations near $r=0$. Consequently, the presence of these pathological features rules out regular planar BHs with the scalar-field profile $\phi'(r)=1/r$ as physically viable and stable configurations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11803v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio De Felice, Shinji Tsujikawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating Universal Relations in Compact Stars featuring $\Delta-$Admixed Exotic Dense Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11956</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11956v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The dense material in a compact star from a supernova remnant is beyond terrestrial experimentation, so phenomenological modeling is used to match astrophysical observations. This is crucial due to the complex sensitivity of compact star features to dense matter properties. Despite modeling flexibility, certain universal relationships among compact star features hold true, regardless of the matter model. Our study examines these universal relationships, focusing on the moment of inertia, tidal Love number, and quadrupole moment, as well as correlations between non-radial oscillation frequencies and star compactness. We consider baryonic stars with cores of heavier baryons. Our findings show that baryonic stars with cores of heavier baryons follow the universal relations, and the f-mode oscillation frequency's universality relative to tidal deformability is notable, with an error margin under 1$\%$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11956v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jspc.2025.100084</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Jour. Sub. Part. Cos. 4, 100084 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Vivek Baruah Thapa, Anil Kumar, Vishal Parmar, Monika Sinha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scrutinizing the cosmogenic origin of the KM3-230213A event: A Multimessenger Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11993</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11993v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The recent detection of the neutrino event KM3-230213A ($\sim$~220 PeV) by the KM3NeT/ARCA telescope, the most energetic ever observed, could represent the long-awaited evidence for a cosmogenic origin, arising from the interaction of an ultra-high-energy cosmic ray with background photons. Its secure confirmation would mark a major advance in high-energy astrophysics. We perform a self-consistent multimessenger transport calculation of protons and their secondary $\gamma$-rays and neutrinos from cosmologically evolving sources, confronting predictions with data from the Pierre Auger Observatory, IceCube, KM3NeT, and the Fermi-LAT isotropic $\gamma$-ray background. A steep sub-ankle proton component saturates the diffuse $\gamma$-ray background and is disfavoured, whereas a hard proton spectrum extending beyond $10^{20}$~eV with evolution $\propto (1+z)^3$ reproduces KM3-230213A without violating any limits. This scenario requires a proton fraction $\lesssim 10$\% at $3\times 10^{19}$~eV and excludes faster-evolving sources. Joint UHE-neutrino and $\gamma$-ray observations thus sharpen constraints on extragalactic cosmic-ray sources and set targets for AugerPrime and next-generation neutrino telescopes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11993v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Cermenati, Antonio Ambrosone, Roberto Aloisio, Denise Boncioli, Carmelo Evoli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter Clumps as Sources of Gravitational-Wave Glitches in LIGO/Virgo/KAGRA data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12227</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12227v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the hypothetical possibility that non-stationary glitch features in the noise of ground-based gravitational-wave detectors could be produced by small dark matter clumps that pass through the earth in the vicinity of gravitational-wave detectors. We first derive the gravitational-wave strain that would be generated by the passage of such a dark matter clump. We find that the strain is primarily sourced by the Newtonian gravitational acceleration of the mirrors toward the clump and by the Shapiro time delay of the photons in the laser beams as they pass through the gravitational potential created by the dark matter clump. We also find that the Newtonian acceleration effect dominates the gravitational-wave strain for both ground and space-based interferometers. We then compare our dark matter clump, gravitational-wave strain model to 84 Koi-Fish glitches detected during the second observing run of the LIGO/Virgo/KAGRA collaboration through a Markov Chain Monte Carlo Bayesian analysis. We find that all glitches but 9 can be confidently rejected as having originated from dark matter clumps. For the remaining glitches, the dark matter hypothesis cannot be excluded, and the maximum \textit{a posteriori} parameters yield minimum densities of about $10^{-7} {\rm{g}}/{\rm{cm}}^3$, within the model. These results allow us to place the first direct upper limits with gravitational-wave detectors on the local over-density of dark matter in the form of clumps in the local neighborhood of Earth, namely $\rho_{{\rm DM} \, {\rm clumps}} \lesssim 10^{-15} {\rm{g}}/{\rm{cm}}^{-3}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12227v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ezequiel Alvarez, Scott Perkins, Federico Ravanedo, Nicolas Yunes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The asymptotically-free gauge theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12348v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show how to classify the asymptotically-free gauge theories in four spacetime dimensions, focussing here on the case of purely fermionic matter. The classification depends on the fact (which we prove) that both the dimension and Dynkin index of irreducible representations of a simple Lie algebra are strictly increasing functions of each Dynkin label. This implies not only that the number of asymptotically-free representations of any one semisimple Lie algebra is finite, but also that they can be written down in a systematic fashion using tables for the asymptotically-free irreducible representations of simple Lie algebras, which we supply. These tables show that at most two out of a possible ten Dynkin labels can be non-zero and that no Dynkin label can exceed four. The extension to bosonic matter or supersymmetric theories is straightforward.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12348v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Gripaios, Khoi Le Nguyen Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The BAO-CMB Tension and Implications for Inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12459v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The scalar spectral index $n_s$ is a powerful test of inflationary models. The tightest constraint on $n_s$ to date derives from the combination of cosmic microwave background (CMB) data with baryon acoustic oscillation (BAO) data. The resulting $n_s$ constraint is shifted significantly upward relative to the constraint from CMB alone, with the consequence that previously preferred inflationary models are seemingly disfavored by $\gtrsim 2 \sigma$. Here we show that this shift in $n_s$ is the combined effect of a degeneracy between $n_s$ and BAO parameters exhibited by CMB data and the tension between CMB datasets and DESI BAO data under the assumption of the standard cosmological model. Given the crucial role of $n_s$ in discriminating between inflationary models, we urge caution in interpreting CMB+BAO constraints on $n_s$ until the BAO-CMB tension is resolved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12459v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elisa G. M. Ferreira, Evan McDonough, Lennart Balkenhol, Renata Kallosh, Lloyd Knox, Andrei Linde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charged lepton flavour violation from inverse seesaw with flavour and CP symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19734v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study charged lepton flavour violation in a scenario in which light neutrino masses are generated via the inverse seesaw mechanism with 3+3 gauge singlet fermions, Ni and Sj, i,j=1,2,3. Lepton mixing is predicted with the help of the flavour symmetries Delta (3 n^2) and Delta (6 n^2) combined with CP. In the neutral lepton sector, the non-trivial flavour structure is only encoded in the Dirac neutrino Yukawa matrix (the coupling relating left-handed lepton doublets and gauge singlets Ni). Current experimental bounds on the processes mu -&gt; e gamma, mu -&gt; 3 e, mu-e conversion in nuclei and the tau lepton decays tau -&gt; l gamma and tau -&gt; 3 l, l=e, mu, do not constrain the considered parameter space of this scenario. Prospective limits on the decay mu -&gt; 3 e and mu-e conversion in aluminium instead can markedly reduce the available parameter space. We also comment on the effects of the heavy sterile states on light neutrino masses and lepton mixing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19734v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. P. Di Meglio, C. Hagedorn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconducting strings in the two-Higgs doublet model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.03300v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present superconducting vortex solutions in the two-Higgs doublet model which has a gauged $U(1)$ Higgs-family symmetry. We write down an ansatz for the solution and study its basic properties, for the case of both global and gauged symmetries. We demonstrate its prima-facie stability using 3D numerical simulations of a global version of the theory, observing the flow of current along the string. We discuss how generic such a phenomena might be and the possible consequences if such a model is found in nature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.03300v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2025.139714</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PLB 868 (2025) 139714</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Richard Battye, Steven Cotterill</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single Higgs boson production in association with a top quark through FCNSI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20242</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20242v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the production and possible detection of a single Higgs boson in association with a top quark in proton-proton collisions ($pp \to th + X$) at the High-Luminosity Large Hadron Collider. This process absent in the Standard Model is predicted by other models such as the Two-Higgs Doublet Model of type III, which is the theoretical framework adopted in this work. Promising results are found for specific scenarios of the model parameter space, which consist mainly of the parameters $\tan\beta$, $\cos(\alpha-\beta)$ and the parameter $\chi_{tc}$, responsible for the Flavor-Changing Neutral Scalar Interactions (FCNSI). Using the machine learning \textit{Boosted Decision Trees} algorithm and considering a systematic uncertainty of $5\%$, we predict \textit{signal significances} at level of $5\sigma$ for $\tan\beta=1$, $\cos(\alpha-\beta)=0.1$, $\chi_{tc}=5$, and integrated luminosities {$\mathcal{L}_{\rm int}\gtrsim2700~fb^{-1}$}. Likewise, we also predict a \textit{signal significance} $\sigma\approx 4.4$ for $\tan\beta=1$, $\cos(\alpha-\beta)=0.1$, $\chi_{tc}=3$, and integrated luminosities $\mathcal{L}_{\rm int} = 3000~fb^{-1}$, which consider the upper limit given by HL-LHC projection on $\mathcal{BR}(t\to ch)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20242v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2025.139553</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>V. M. L\'opez-Guerrero, M. A. Arroyo-Ure\~na, J. L. D\'iaz-Cruz, O. F\'elix-Beltr\'an, T. A. Valencia-P\'erez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin alignment of quarkonia in vortical quark-gluon plasma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05866v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The spin alignment of $J/\psi$ with respect to event plane in relativistic heavy ion collisions exhibits a significant signal. We propose a possible mechanism for spin alignment through spin dependent dissociation of quarkonia in a vortical quark-gluon plasma. The spin dependent dissociation is realized through inelastic scattering between constituents of quarkonium and those of quark-gluon plasma polarized by the vorticity. The spin dependent dissociation rate is found to depend on the directions of vorticity, quantization axis, and quark momentum. We implement our results in a dissociation dominated evolution model for quarkonia in the Bjorken flow, finding the spin $0$ state is slightly suppressed compared to the average of the other two, which is consistent with the sign found in experiments. We also find absence of logarithmic enhancement in binding energy in the vortical correction to dissociation rate, which is understood from the requirement that a spin dependent dissociation can only come from quark coupling to a pair of chromomagnetic and chromoelectric field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05866v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1674-1137/adcc8c</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chin. Phys. C,49,084105 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yuhao Liang, Shu Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tomography of Pions and Kaons in the QCD Vacuum: Transverse Momentum Dependent Parton Distribution Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09789</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09789v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We evaluate the pion and kaon transverse momentum dependent parton distribution functions (TMDPDFs) in the instanton liquid model (ILM), a model of the QCD vacuum at low resolution. The relevant TMDs are factored into a constituent quark distribution times a rapidity dependent soft factor from staple-shaped Wilson lines, for fixed parton longitudinal momentum and transverse separation. The results are evolved to higher rapidities using the Collins-Soper (CS) kernel and higher resolution using renormalization group evolution. The comparison to existing extractions of pion TMDs from Drell-Yan (DY) data is briefly discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09789v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Yang Liu, Ismail Zahed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on Anomalous Quartic Gauge Couplings via Electroweak Production of $\gamma\gamma jj$ at Future Proton-Proton Colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20248</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20248v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The investigation of quartic gauge couplings provides a crucial test of the Standard Model and serves as a potential window into new physics at higher energy scales. Within the framework of Effective Field Theory, deviations from the SM can be parameterized through dimension-8 operators. In this study, we analyze the process $pp \rightarrow \gamma\gamma jj$ at the High-Luminosity Large Hadron Collider (HL-LHC) and the Future Circular Collider in hadron mode (FCC-hh) to probe the sensitivity to anomalous quartic gauge couplings (aQGCs), particularly $f_{T8}/\Lambda^4$ and $f_{T9}/\Lambda^4$. Monte Carlo simulations of signal and relevent backgrouds are performed using MadGraph for event generation, Pythia for parton showering and hadronization, and Delphes for detector simulation. A multivariate analysis based on Boosted Decision Trees is employed to optimize the signal-to-background discrimination, incorporating a comprehensive set of kinematic and reconstructed variables of the final state particles. Additionally, we evaluate unitarity-violating effects associated with dimension-8 operators by imposing energy cutoffs on the di-photon invariant mass. The expected exclusion and discovery significances are computed, accounting for systematic uncertainties to ensure a realistic assessment of collider reach. Our findings indicate that the FCC-hh offers significantly improved sensitivity compared to the HL-LHC and current experimental results by ATLAS, reinforcing its potential for probing aQGCs. Notably, even under a 10\% systematic uncertainty, our projected limits for FCC-hh at 95\% confidence level surpass the current best constraints reported by the ATLAS collaboration, highlighting the enhanced discovery prospects at future high-energy colliders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20248v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Senol, M. Tekin, B. S. Ozaltay, H. Denizli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlated study on some $B_{c}\rightarrow \text{ }P$ and $B_{c}\rightarrow\text{ }S$ wave channels in light of new inputs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01693v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study investigates the decay modes of the $B_c$ meson, focusing on semileptonic and nonleptonic decay into S and P wave charmonia. The primary objective is to extract the shape parameter of the $B_{c}$ meson distribution amplitude through a data-driven approach, utilizing the lattice results on $B_{c}\rightarrow\eta_{c},J/\psi$ semileptonic form factors and yielding an estimate of ${\omega_B}_c = 0.998(34)$ for the same. We use the form factors derived from the modified perturbative QCD framework in the analysis. This result and various other inputs on the radiative decays of the P wave charmonia enable us to estimate the $q^2$ shapes of the $B_{c}\rightarrow\chi_{c0},\chi_{c1}$ and $h_{c}$ form factors using pole expansion parametrization. Using these results, we have obtained predictions of LFUV observables $R(\chi_{c0})=0.169(11)$, $R(\chi_{c1})=0.126(2)$ and $R(h_{c})=0.113(3)$. Finally, we have presented predictions for branching ratios of some nonleptonic decay modes of the $B_{c}$ meson into S and P wave charmonia in the same modified perturbative QCD framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01693v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP07(2025)144</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of High Energy Physics, Volume-07(2025), Article-144</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Utsab Dey, Soumitra Nandi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudorapidity density distributions of charged particles and transverse momentum spectra of identified particles in pp collisions in PACIAE 4.0 model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06539v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The pseudorapidity density distributions of charged particles and the transverse momentum spectra of identified particles in proton-proton (pp) collisions at the center-of-mass energies ranging from $\sqrt{s}=200$ GeV to 13 TeV have been systematically studied using the newly released parton and cascade model PACIAE 4.0 based on PYTHIA 8.3. The available experimental data are well reproduced across all analyzed aspects. This theoretical method can be easily extended to anywhere the experimental data for pp collisions are currently unavailable. Furthermore, since pp collisions serve as the baseline for heavy-ion collisions, our results can provide a valuable resource for both experimentalists and theorists.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06539v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Z. Xie, A. K. Lei, H. Zheng, W. C. Zhang, D. M. Zhou, Z. L. She, Y. L. Yan, B. H. Sa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tomography of the Rho meson in the QCD Instanton Vacuum: Transverse Momentum Dependent Parton Distribution Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11959v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We analyse the rho meson unpolarized and polarized transverse momentum dependent parton distribution functions (TMDPDFs) in the instanton liquid model (ILM). The corresponding TMDs in ILM are approximated by a constituent quark beam function in the leading Fock state multiplied by a rapidity-dependent factor resulting from the staple-shaped Wilson lines, for fixed longitudinal momentum, transverse separation, and rapidity. At the resolution of the ILM, all of the rho meson TMDs are symmetric in parton x for fixed transverse momentum, and Gaussian-like in the transverse momentum for fixed parton x. The latter is a direct consequence of the profiling of the quark zero modes in the ILM. The evolved TMDs at higher rapidity using the Collins-Soper kernel, and higher resolution using the renormalization group (RG), show substantial skewness towards low parton x.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11959v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Yang Liu, Ismail Zahed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining the 3HDM Parameter Space using Active Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.07489v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: One of the standard ways to study scenarios beyond the Standard Model involves extending the Higgs Sector. This work examines the Three Higgs Doublet Model (3HDM) in a Type-Z or democratic setup, where each Higgs doublet couples exclusively to a specific type of fermion. The particle spectrum of the 3HDM includes four charged Higgs bosons, two CP-odd scalars, and three CP-even scalars. This work investigates the allowed mass and coupling parameter space in the Type-Z 3HDM after imposing all theoretical and experimental constraints. We extract the allowed parameter space under three distinct alignment-limit conditions or mass hierarchies leveraging machine learning techniques. Specifically, we analyze scenarios where the 125 GeV Higgs is the lightest, an intermediary, or the heaviest CP-even Higgs boson. Our findings indicate that while a single lighter CP-even Higgs boson below 125 GeV still remains a possibility, the presence of two lighter Higgses is ruled out.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.07489v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nipun Batra, Baradhwaj Coleppa, Akshat Khanna, Santosh Kumar Rai, Agnivo Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlating the $B$ anomalies to $K\to \pi\nu\bar\nu$ and $B\to K\nu\bar\nu$ via leptoquarks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05552</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.05552v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Leptoquark models are prime candidates for new physics (NP) explanations of the long-standing anomalies in semi-leptonic $B$ decays; $b\to c \tau \bar\nu$ (encoded in $R(D^{(\ast)})$) and $b\to s\ell\bar\ell (\ell=e,\mu)$ transitions. Furthermore, Belle II and NA62 reported weaker-than-expected limits on $B^+ \to K^+ \nu\bar\nu$ and $K^+ \to \pi^+ \nu \bar\nu$, respectively. While the $R(D^{(\ast)})$ and $b\to s\ell \bar\ell$ measurements can be explained with NP contributions at the $O(10\%)$ level, the neutrino channels suggest that the NP effect could be comparable in size to the Standard Model one. In this context, we consider the two types of leptoquark models with minimal sets of the couplings that can best describe the semi-leptonic $B$ anomalies and lead at the same time to effects in the neutrino modes, the singlet-triplet scalar leptoquark model ($S_1+S_3$) and the singlet vector leptoquark model ($U_1$). More specifically, the neutrino channels pose non-trivial constraints on the parameter space, and we find that large effects (i.e., accounting for the current central value) in $B\to K^{(*)}\nu\bar\nu$ are only possible in the $S_1+S_3$ setup, while both models can account for the central value of $K^+\to \pi^+\nu\bar\nu$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.05552v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Crivellin, Syuhei Iguro, Teppei Kitahara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling the inert Triplet desert region with a pNGB Dark Matter and its Gravitational Wave signatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16521v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we extend the scalar sector of the conventional hyperchargeless inert triplet model (ITM) to include a second dark matter (DM) candidate, which appears to be a pseudo-Nambu-Goldstone boson (pNGB). The usual ITM with an extended scalar sector offers a DM candidate along with novel signatures at different experiments, e.g., colliders, gravitational wave detectors, etc. Nevertheless, hitherto unseen experimental detections have placed stringent constraints on the ITM parameter space. Moreover, triplet masses lighter than $1.9$ TeV, consistent with the existing or upcoming collider sensitivity reach, are already excluded from the DM observable, as they yield an underabundant relic density due to a strong $SU(2)_L$ gauge annihilation. Inclusion of a pNGB DM, via a complex $SU(2)_L$ scalar singlet and through the soft-breaking of a $U(1)$ symmetry, helps to revive the sub-TeV regime of the triplet DM. This resurgence relies on a proficient conversion between the two DM species. Using this inter-conversion, with the triplet DM as the lighter one between the two, we show that it is possible to push the triplet DM contribution to $50\% - 60\%$ of the total relic density. This offers a significant improvement over the traditional ITM with a single DM candidate, where the same can at most reach $10\% - 20\%$. Besides, the concerned bipartite DM framework also offers the possibility of a first-order phase transition along various constituent field directions. Among these, the one along the real $SU(2)_L$ singlet direction can be a strong one which subsequently yields detectable gravitational wave signals at the upcoming space-based gravitational wave detectors such as LISA, BBO, DECIGO, etc., alongside distinctive and complementary signatures at the various DM and collider quests.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16521v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pankaj Borah, Pradipta Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light Scalars in the Extended Georgi-Machacek Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.06427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.06427v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We perform global fits of the CP-conserving Georgi-Machacek (GM) and extended Georgi-Machacek (eGM) models, incorporating a light CP-even beyond the Standard Model (BSM) scalar within the mass range of $90$ GeV to $100$ GeV. These fits combine the Higgs signal strengths and direct search limits from ATLAS and CMS at $\sqrt{s} = 8$ and $13$ TeV, $B$-physics observables, and theoretical constraints arising from next-to-leading order (NLO) unitarity and BFB constraints. From the global fit, we show that the LHC diphoton and LEP $b\bar{b}$ excesses around $95$ GeV are well compatible with the $125$ GeV Higgs data. Whereas the CMS ditau excess is incompatible with the $125$ GeV Higgs signal strength data in both the CP-conserving GM and eGM models. We present the results from the combined fit, including the $95$ GeV Higgs signal strength data. In the eGM model, the triplet VEV cannot exceed $12$ GeV for additional BSM scalar masses below $160$ GeV and approximately $20$ GeV for additional BSM scalar masses above $160$ GeV. The masses of additional BSM scalars cannot exceed $600$ GeV. The maximum mass splitting is of around $120$ GeV within the members of each custodial multiplet, and up to $250$ GeV between the members of different multiplets. In the GM model, these constraints become more stringent: the triplet VEV is limited to below $15$ GeV, which tightens to $4$ GeV once the BSM scalar masses are below $160$ GeV. Masses of the quintet $m_5$ and the triplet $m_3$ are restricted to be below $530$ GeV and $320$ GeV, respectively. A mass hierarchy, $m_5 &gt; m_3$, is favoured in the high-mass region, with the mass splitting constrained to be less than $210$ GeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.06427v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Poulami Mondal, Subrata Samanta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymmetric muon-antimuon emission from $Z^0$ decays: a clear magnetometer in relativistic heavy-ion collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.11370v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that a very clear signal of the presence of a strong magnetic field during the early stage of a high-energy heavy-ion collision is provided by the decay of the $Z^0$ into dimuon pairs. We find that the process is highly anisotropic, producing pairs mainly out of plane, as signaled by a negative value of $v_2$, and leads to an antimuon transverse momentum distribution which peaks at a higher value of the transverse momentum compared to the peak of the muon transverse momentum distribution. We also show that the process does not produce a significant distortion of the $Z^0$ spectral function. The signal can be identified by comparing the dimuon-invariant mass and the individual muon and antimuon spectra produced in semicentral heavy-ion collisions with the corresponding scaled spectra produced in p+p collisions at the $Z^0$ peak.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.11370v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alejandro Ayala, Ana Julia Mizher, Javier Rend\'on</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropy from decoherence: a case study using glasma-based occupation numbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04809v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We compute the entropy-per-particle, $S/N$, produced by the decoherence of a coherent state interacting with an environment, using an analytical open quantum system approach. The coherent state considered is characterized by occupation numbers borrowed from the glasma fields produced in the early stages of high-energy nuclear collisions. The environment is modeled as the vacuum, and decoherence arises from the interaction of the state with vacuum fluctuations. We describe the system-environment interaction via a phase-damping model, which represents continuous measurements on the system without altering its energy or particle number. Starting from the occupation numbers typical of the Glasma in high-energy proton-nucleus and nucleus-nucleus collisions, we find that the final $S/N$ after decoherence is lower than that of a two-dimensional thermal bath of ultrarelativistic gluons, except for proton-nucleus collisions at small values of $g\mu$. Our results indicate that quantum decoherence alone does not generate sufficient entropy to transform the initial coherent state into a thermalized gluon bath.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04809v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriele Coci, Gabriele Parisi, Salvatore Plumari, Marco Ruggieri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark monopoles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.06697v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Monopoles have been a subject of much theoretical and experimental research since they were proposed to symmetrize Maxwell's equations. However, no experimental signature of their existence has been detected. Many mechanisms have been proposed to explain this lack of success. In here we generalize QED to a two photon theory where the magnetic photon and the monopole belong to dark matter. A naive mixing interaction produces duality and generates experimental consequences for indirect monopole detection via the magnetic charge of the electron.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.06697v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vicente Vento</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-particle cumulant distribution: a probe of "true" elliptic flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11026</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11026v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we have shown the two-particle correlations of charged hadrons in d-Au collisions at 200 GeV. These correlations were studied at different multiplicities and pseudorapidity intervals. The two-particle correlations arise due to Color Reconnections, resonance decays, jet correlations, and "jet-like" correlations of low-energy partons in softer interactions. These correlations are inversely proportional to multiplicity but remain unaffected (slowly increase) for larger pseudorapidity windows. We treated these correlations as distributions and calculated their skewness and kurtosis. The non-flow distributions deviate greatly from a Gaussian distribution and have high skewness and kurtosis. The "true" elliptic flow distributions resemble Gaussian distributions; they have significantly lower skewness and kurtosis. We suggest that if the two-particle cumulant flow is treated as a distribution, its skewness and kurtosis can be instrumental in distinguishing true flow and non-flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11026v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Satya Ranjan Nayak, Akash Das, B. K. Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From 100 kpc to 10 Gpc: Dark Matter self-interactions before and after DESI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18252v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider Dark Matter self-interactions mediated by ultralight scalars. We show that effectively massless mediators lead to an enhancement of the matter power spectrum, while heavier mediators lead to a suppression, together with a feature around their Jeans scale. We derive the strongest present constraints by combining Planck and BOSS data. The recent DESI measurements of Baryon Acoustic Oscillations exhibit a mild $2\sigma$ preference for long-range self-interactions, as strong as $4$ per mille of the gravitational coupling. Full-shape analyses of forthcoming DESI and Euclid data will confirm or disprove such a hint.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18252v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/gc78-96l5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 112, 023525 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Salvatore Bottaro, Emanuele Castorina, Marco Costa, Diego Redigolo, Ennio Salvioni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Radial Oscillation Modes in Hybrid Stars with Hyperons and Delta Baryons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12002v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the effects of hyperons, delta baryons, and quark matter phase transitions on $f$-mode oscillations in neutron stars. Using the density-dependent relativistic mean-field model (DDME2) for the hadronic phase and the density-dependent quark mass (DDQM) model for the quark phase, we construct hadronic and hybrid equations of state (EoSs) consistent with astrophysical constraints. Including hyperons and delta baryons soften the EoS, reducing maximum mass, while phase transition to the quark matter further softens the EoS, decreasing the speed of sound and hence the maximum mass. We confirm the well-known overestimation of $f$-mode frequencies by the Cowling approximation (by about 10-30\%) compared to full General Relativity calculation, and show that this discrepancy persists across models including hyperons, $\Delta$ baryons, and a phase transition to quark matter. While the discrepancy generally decreases with stellar mass, it increases near the maximum mass in the presence of a phase transition compared to EoSs without this phenomenology. We derive universal relations connecting the frequencies of the $f$-mode to the average density, compactness, and tidal deformability, finding significant deviations due to hyperons and delta baryons. These deviations could provide distinct observational signatures in gravitational wave data, offering new insights into dense matter physics and advancing gravitational wave asteroseismology of neutron star interiors. Empirical relations for mass-scaled and radius-scaled frequencies are also provided, highlighting the importance of GR calculations for accurate modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12002v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/7qns-616m</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review D 112, 023013 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ishfaq Ahmad Rather, Kau D. Marquez, Prashant Thakur, Odilon Louren\c{c}o</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical friction in ultralight dark matter: Plummer sphere perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15428v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In models of dark matter composed of feebly interacting ultralight bosons in the state of Bose-Einstein condensate, the dynamical friction force acting on circularly moving globular clusters modelled as Plummer spheres is determined. Analytic expressions for both radial and tangential components of the dynamical friction force are given. We reveal that the dynamical friction force for the Plummer sphere deviates from that for a point probe of the same mass for a significantly large ratio of the Plummer sphere radius to its orbital radius, as well as for large values of the Mach number.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15428v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1402-4896/adebb7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physica Scripta 100, 075039 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>V. M. Gorkavenko, A. I. Yakimenko, A. O. Zaporozhchenko, E. V. Gorbar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prospects for probing dark matter particles and primordial black holes with the Hongmeng mission using the 21 cm global spectrum at cosmic dawn</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19257v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Probing dark matter particles and primordial black holes remains a pivotal challenge in modern cosmology. Exotic energy injections from dark matter annihilation, decay, and PBH Hawking evaporation can alter the thermal and ionization histories of the early universe, leaving distinctive imprints on the 21 cm global spectrum. We assess the potential of the upcoming space project, the Hongmeng mission, to probe dark matter particles and PBHs using the 21 cm global spectrum. Under ideal conditions with 1000 hours of integration time and negligible foreground residuals, the Hongmeng project can reach sensitivities to dark matter annihilation cross sections and decay lifetimes to $\langle \sigma v \rangle \sim 10^{-28}\,\mathrm{cm^3\,s^{-1}}$ and $\tau \sim 10^{28}\,\mathrm{s}$, respectively, for dark matter particles with a mass of $10\,\mathrm{GeV}$. It can also probe PBHs with masses of $10^{16}\,\mathrm{g}$ and abundances as low as $f_{\mathrm{PBH}} \simeq 10^{-6}$. These results indicate that the Hongmeng mission can improve current constraints on dark matter annihilation, decay, and PBH Hawking radiation by nearly two orders of magnitude. Moreover, the Hongmeng mission surpasses current limits on sub-GeV dark matter probing and enables the probing of Hawking radiation from PBHs with masses above $10^{17}\,\mathrm{g}$, which remain undetectable through conventional cosmological means. Overall, the upcoming Hongmeng project holds great promise for advancing the investigation of both dark matter and PBHs, potentially deepening our understanding of the nature of dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19257v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/07/039</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 07 (2025) 039</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Meng-Lin Zhao, Sai Wang, Xin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Super light-by-light scattering in vacuum induced by intense vortex lasers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.14286v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Collision of ultra-intense optical laser and X-ray free electron laser (XFEL) pulses is a promising approach to detecting nonlinear vacuum polarization (VP), a long-standing prediction of quantum electrodynamics remaining to be tested. Identifying the signals induced by polarized vacuum relies on purifying the X-ray polarization and poses significant challenges due to strongly reduced signal and low signal-to-noise ratio (SNR). Here we propose an approach that allows one to directly detect VP signals without the need for an X-ray polarizer. We identify a new VP effect in collision of an X-ray probe with an intense laser in a vortex mode, which we call the super light-by-light scattering (super-LBL), through which signal photons are kicked out of the X-ray background with large tangential momentum. Super-LBL originates from the gradient force of the vortical vacuum current in azimuthal direction and induces momentum exchange beyond the transverse momentum of laser-photon. This effect efficiently sets the scattered signal photons apart from the X-ray background, producing observable signals with both the strength and SNR more than two orders of magnitude higher than those from the known VP effects. This finding paves the way for single-shot detection of nonlinear VP phenomena with current ultra-intense laser and XFEL technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.14286v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhigang Bu, Lingang Zhang, Shiyu Liu, Baifei Shen, Ruxin Li, Igor P. Ivanov, Liangliang Ji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limitations of the paraxial beam model in the study of quantum vacuum signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04368v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Studies of nonlinear quantum vacuum signals often model the driving laser fields as paraxial beams. This in particular holds for analytic approaches. While this allows for reliable predictions in most situations, there are also notable exceptions. A prominent example is the overestimation of the polarization-flipped signal photon yield in the collision of two equally focused, parallel polarized laser beams by a factor of about six. In the present work, we identify the origin of this deficiency and devise a strategy to obtain accurate closed-form expressions also in cases challenging the conventional (leading order) paraxial beam model. We demonstrate the potential of our approach on the example of two linearly polarized laser pulses colliding at a generic collision angle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04368v3</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/bmxl-776l</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 111, 096026 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Felix Karbstein, Fabian Sch\"utze</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring $\Delta$-resonance in neutron stars: implications from astrophysical and nuclear observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07256</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07256v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study presents the first comprehensive Bayesian inference of neutron star matter, incorporating $\Delta$-resonances alongside hyperons and nucleons within a density-dependent relativistic hadron (DDRH) framework. Using constraints from nuclear saturation properties, chiral effective field theory ($\chi$EFT), NICER radius measurements, and tidal deformability data from GW170817, we systematically explore the impact of $\Delta$-resonances on the equation of state (EoS) of dense matter and neutron star observables. Our results demonstrate that the inclusion of $\Delta$-baryons softens the EoS at low densities while maintaining sufficient stiffness at high densities to support $2M_{\odot}$ neutron stars. This naturally reconciles neutron star radius constraints with the recent observation of the low-mass compact object in HESS J1731-347 while simultaneously exhibiting excellent agreement with GW170817 tidal deformability constraints, reinforcing the astrophysical viability of $\Delta$-admixed neutron stars. Additionally, $\Delta$-resonances are found to populate the outer layers of the neutron star core, which may have implications for neutron star mergers and their cooling. Furthermore, we show that the presence of $\Delta$-baryons might significantly influence neutron star cooling via the direct Urca process. We also investigate quasi-normal $f$-mode oscillations within a fully general relativistic framework, revealing strong correlations between the $f$-mode frequency, neutron star compactness, and tidal deformability. With the inclusion of $\Delta$-resonances and adherence to astrophysical constraints, we obtain $f_{1.4} = 1.97^{+0.17}_{-0.22}$ kHz and the damping time $\tau_{f_{1.4}} = 0.19^{+0.05}_{-0.03}$ s at the $1\sigma$ confidence level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07256v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/643w-c2ly</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 112, 023016 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Vishal Parmar, Vivek Baruah Thapa, Monika Sinha, Ignazio Bombaci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compatibility of recent $\Xi$-nuclear bound state signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.15820v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: J-PARC E05 reported recently a hint of a $\Xi^--{^{11}{\rm B}}$ nuclear state in the ${^{12}}{\rm C}(K^-,K^+){^{12}_{\Xi}}{\rm Be}$ spectrum, bound by $B_{\Xi^-}=8.9\pm 1.4 {^{+3.8}_{-3.1}}$ MeV. Using a density-dependent $\Xi$-nuclear optical potential $V_{\rm opt}^{\Xi}(\rho)$ we explore to what extent a $\Xi^-_{1s}$ assignment of this nuclear state is compatible with $\Xi^-_{1s}$ and $\Xi^-_{1p}$ nuclear-state interpretations of $\Xi^-$ capture events in light emulsion-nuclei experiments. We find that the only acceptable $\Xi^-_{1s}$ assignment at present, barring an abnormally strong repulsive $\rho^2$ component of $V_{\rm opt}^{\Xi}(\rho)$, is that for the $\Xi^--{^{11}{\rm B}}$ signal. This finding supports reassigning $\Xi^-$ capture events in $^{14}$N, originally assigned as $\Xi^-_{1s}-{^{14}{\rm N}}$ nuclear states, to $\Xi^0_{1p}-{^{14}{\rm C}}$ nuclear states. The depth of $V_{\rm opt}^{\Xi}(\rho)$ at nuclear-matter density $\rho_0=0.17$ fm$^{-3}$ is then $-V_{\rm opt}^{\Xi}(\rho_0)\sim 21$ MeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.15820v3</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2025.139728</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Lett. B 868 (2025) 139728</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>E. Friedman, A. Gal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multipositivity Bounds for Scattering Amplitudes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.05553v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Lorentz invariance, unitarity, and causality enforce powerful constraints on the theory space of physical scattering amplitudes. However, virtually all efforts in this direction have centered on the very simplest case of four-point scattering. In this work, we derive an infinite web of "multipositivity bounds" that nonlinearly constrain all tree-level higher-point scattering amplitudes under similarly minimal assumptions. Our construction rules out several deformations of the string and implies mixed-multiplicity bounds on the Wilson coefficients of planar effective field theories. Curiously, an infinite class of multipositivity bounds is exactly saturated by the amplitudes of the open string.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.05553v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/wt4x-2149</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 112, 016017 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Clifford Cheung, Grant N. Remmen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parameter inference of microlensed gravitational waves using neural spline flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20996v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: When gravitational waves (GWs) propagate near massive objects, they undergo gravitational lensing that imprints lens model dependent modulations on the waveform. This effect provides a powerful tool for cosmological and astrophysical studies. However, conventional Bayesian parameter inference methods for GWs are computationally expensive, especially for lensed events with additional lens parameters, necessitating more efficient approaches. In this work, we explore the use of neural spline flows (NSFs) for posterior inference of microlensed GWs, and successfully apply NSFs to the inference of 11-dimensional lens parameters. Our results demonstrate that compared with traditional methods like Bilby dynesty that rely on Bayesian inference, the NSF network we built not only achieves inference accuracy comparable to traditional methods for the main parameters, but also can reduce the inference time from approximately 3 days to 0.8 s on average. Additionally, the network exhibits strong generalization for the spin parameters of GW sources. It is anticipated to become a powerful tool for future low-latency searches for lensed GW signals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20996v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheng Qin, Tian-Yang Sun, Bo-Yuan Li, Jing-Fei Zhang, Xiao Guo, Xin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement features from heavy particle scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03555v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The amount of information propagated by intermediate heavy particles exhibits characteristic features in inelastic scatterings with $n\geq 3$ final particles. As the total energy increases, the entanglement entropy, between its decay products and other final particles, exhibits a universal sharp dip, suppressed by its small decay rate. This indicates an entanglement suppression from a low-energy effective theory to a channel dominated by an on-shell heavy particle. As demonstrations of these entanglement features, we study concrete models of $2\to 3$ and $2\to 4$ scatterings, which shed light on the entanglement structure beyond the area law derived for $2\to 2$ scattering. In practice, these features may be probed by suitably marginalizing the phase-space distribution of final particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03555v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chon Man Sou, Yi Wang, Xingkai Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anisotropic Diffusion of $e^\pm$ in Pulsar Halos over Multiple Coherence of Magnetic Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08526v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The slow particle diffusion in pulsar halos, inferred from TeV gamma-ray surface brightness profiles, is attributed to cross-field diffusion under the anisotropic diffusion model. This model assumes sub-Alfv\'enic interstellar turbulence in the surrounding medium of the pulsar and a rough alignment of the line-of-sight of observers towards the pulsars with the local mean magnetic field direction in the halo. In this model, the expected morphology of a pulsar halo is highly dependent on the properties of the interstellar magnetic field. We investigate the anisotropic diffusion of electron-positron pairs across multiple coherence of magnetic fields in pulsar halos in this work. We focus particularly on their influences on the predicted gamma-ray surface brightness profile and the asymmetry of the halo's morphology, as well as the observational expectations by the Large High Altitude Air Shower Observatory (LHAASO). Our results indicate that the requirement of a specific magnetic field geometry can be alleviated when accounting for a limited (and realistic) coherence length of the magnetic field in the model. Also, the halo's morphology may appear less asymmetric, especially after being smoothed by the point spread function of instruments. It largely relaxes the tension between the asymmetric morphology of halos predicted by the model and lack of apparent asymmetric halos detected so far. Our findings demonstrate the important influence of the coherence length of interstellar magnetic field on the distribution of particles around their accelerators, and the consequence on the measured source morphology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08526v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/add6a4</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Kai Yan, Sha Wu, Ruo-Yu Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
