<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph</link>
    <description>hep-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 05:08:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Electroweak Baryogenesis with \texttt{BARYONET}: a self-contained review of the WKB approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21915v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive, self-contained pedagogical computation of the baryon asymmetry of the Universe within electroweak baryogenesis (EWBG), from the derivation of the semiclassical, CP-dependent force to the formulation and solution of the transport equations obtained from the Boltzmann equations$-$all implemented in the open-source code \texttt{BARYONET}. Our analysis follows the semiclassical WKB approach, where spatially varying complex masses across expanding bubble walls feel CP-violating forces that bias plasma transport. Starting from the stationary Boltzmann equation in the wall frame and projecting onto a hierarchy of velocity moments, we derive a compact, fluid-like system of coupled differential equations for chemical potentials and velocity perturbations. After obtaining the solutions, one can define the left-handed baryon chemical potential, which acts as the source term for the weak sphalerons. These processes generate the baryon asymmetry in front of the wall, which is subsequently frozen once it passes through it.
  We validate the framework against established formalisms and provide benchmarks in representative scenarios, including singlet extensions of the Standard Model, two-Higgs-doublet models, and Higgs$-\phi^6$ constructions. The resulting \texttt{BARYONET} implementation delivers an automated, reproducible pipeline for WKB-based baryogenesis studies, connecting formal derivations with phenomenological applications.
  In parallel, we revisit standard EWBG ingredients$-$\emph{diffusion constants}, \emph{Yukawa/helicity-flip rates}, and \emph{strong/weak sphaleron rates}$-$to clarify conventions, update numerical inputs, and present a pedagogical derivation, ensuring transparent reproducibility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21915v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giulio Barni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superhorizon Isocurvature as a Window into Dark Matter Production</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21917v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the presence of primordial isocurvature perturbations, for example in a separate dark radiation sector, the superhorizon evolution of curvature perturbations becomes nontrivial. If the dark sector is radiation-like and constitutes a significant fraction of the energy density, its isocurvature can imply isocurvature in the inflaton sector even without direct interactions between the sectors. In this article, we revisit superhorizon curvature and isocurvature evolution in the long-wavelength limit systematically, drawing a simple picture of how to understand the nature of these fluctuations from first principles and without brute-force cosmic perturbation theory. We show how the described setup is able to source isocurvature in simple models of dark matter such as freeze-in and freeze-out and demonstrate that future measurements of matter and neutrino isocurvature can potentially discriminate between these two mechanisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21917v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher Gerlach, Wolfram Ratzinger, Pedro Schwaller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seafloor Topography Enhances KM3NeT Sensitivity to ANITA-like Events</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21929v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article, we introduce the concept of \textit{topographic enhancement} in the context of ultra-high-energy neutrino detection by underwater neutrino telescopes. We demonstrate that the local topography around KM3NeT/ARCA can increase the detection efficiency in scenarios involving long-lived particles by up to a factor of $\sim 3$ due to the presence of an underwater mountain range in the direction of Malta. We consider a simplified model-independent approach that parametrizes the new physics able to generate both track-like and cascade-like signals in neutrino telescopes. When explaining the KM3-230213A event with a diffuse dark flux hypothesis, including its azimuthal direction--in addition to the zenith angle--provides additional constraints on the parameter space. In this effective model, the observations by KM3NeT and ANITA-IV can be simultaneously explained and the global tension with the lack of a corresponding detection in IceCube is reduced to 2.4 sigma. This work underscores the importance of incorporating topographic effects in the design and optimization of next-generation neutrino telescopes, as is done in the context of mountain-based detectors such as TAMBO. We present a numerical code which can be used to easily extend this topographical analysis to other experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21929v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos A. Arg\"uelles, Toni Bert\'olez-Mart\'inez, Alba Burgos-Mond\'ejar, Anne-Katherine Burns, Jacobo Lopez-Pavon, Jordi Salvado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Four loop renormalization of 3-quark operators in QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21940v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We renormalize generalized 3-quark operators that relate to baryon states using the method devised by Kr\"{a}nkl and Manashov at four loops in the MSbar scheme. The anomalous dimensions of the four core operators used to compute nucleon matrix elements are determined and their associated critical exponents are studied in the conformal window using the Banks-Zaks expansion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21940v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. A. Gracey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bubble wall velocity with out-of-equilibrium corrections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21942</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21942v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study how out-of-equilibrium effects modify the steady-state propagation of bubble walls during a cosmological first-order electroweak phase transition. Going beyond the local thermal equilibrium approximation, we numerically solve the coupled system of scalar field, hydrodynamic and Boltzmann equations using a spectral algorithm that allows a first-principle treatment of the collision integral. This approach enables a quantitative assessment of non-equilibrium perturbations in the plasma and their backreaction on the wall motion. Focusing on the singlet extension of the Standard Model as a minimal benchmark scenario, we find that out-of-equilibrium corrections substantially enhance the effective friction on the expanding front, leading to slower wall velocities and broader wall profiles compared to the equilibrium case. These modifications have significant implications for cosmological observables. For instance, they enhance the efficiency of electroweak baryogenesis, thus improving the viability of baryon asymmetry generation within realistic parameter regions that can also be probed by future gravitational wave interferometers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21942v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlo Branchina, Angela Conaci, Stefania De Curtis, Luigi Delle Rose</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interactions of Neutrino Wave Packets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22005v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The low energy effective field theory of interacting neutrinos derived from the Standard Model may be framed as a pointlike interaction and thereby modeled on a lattice of neutrino momenta. We identify a path to take a continuum limit of this lattice problem in the Center of Momentum frame. In this limit, the weak interaction is found to become trivial between incoming plane waves describing ultrarelativistic particles, unless finite neutrino wave packet sizes are taken into consideration. We follow up with an analytic treatment of interacting neutrino wave packets, demonstrating the importance of the wave packet size for characterizing neutrino-neutrino scattering in dense environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22005v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael J. Cervia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Potential of discovering $\Xi_{cc}^+$ in $\Lambda_b $ decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22181v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose to search for $\Xi_{cc}^+$ in the decay $\Lambda_b \to \Xi_{cc}^+ D^-$, which serves as a tagged and reconstructible source of $\Xi_{cc}^+$, providing an experimentally clean environment for its discovery. A possible fully charged final state is $[(pK^- K^- \pi^+)_{\Xi^0_c} \pi^ + ]_{\Xi_{cc}^+} \,(K^+ \pi^- \pi^-)_{D^-}$, where the subscripts indicate the parent hadron in the decay chain. We estimate the branching fraction to be ${\cal B}(\Lambda_b \to \Xi_{cc}^+ D^-) = ( 5.1 \pm 3.9) \times 10^{-4}$, while the fully charged final state corresponds to an effective branching fraction of order $10^{-8}$. These results indicate that LHCb has the potential to discover the $\Xi_{cc}^+$. The prospects for observing $\Omega_{cc}^+$ are also briefly discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22181v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao-Qiang Geng, Xiang-Nan Jin, Chia-Wei Liu, Xin-Yi Liu, Xiao Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matching NLL to NLO in Higgs and Z plus jet at the LHC and FCC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22445v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present updated predictions for rapidity and transverse-momentum spectra in Higgs-plus-jet production at proton colliders, combining NLO fixed-order QCD with next-to-leading energy-logarithmic resummation. Preliminary results for the $Z$-boson case are also discussed. Our study underscores the importance of improving fixed-order predictions for Higgs- and $Z$-plus-jet observables to meet the precision demands of Higgs and electroweak measurements at the LHC and future FCC energies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22445v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Giovanni Celiberto, Luigi Delle Rose, Alessandro Papa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heavy-Flavor Fragmentation and Jet Structure from HF-NRevo: Bridging to Heavy-Ion Collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22449</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22449v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present recent progress on the Heavy-Flavor Non-Relativistic Evolution (HF-NRevo) framework, designed to describe leading-power fragmentation of heavy-flavored hadrons at moderate to large transverse momentum. Starting from NLO NRQCD calculations for all partonic channels into pseudoscalar quarkonia, we construct the NRFF1.0 collinear fragmentation functions via DGLAP evolution in a variable-flavor number scheme. We outline future prospects in the heavy-ion context, where HF-NRevo can serve as a baseline for modeling in-medium modifications of heavy-flavor fragmentation in nuclear collisions. Its accurate modeling of the partonic hierarchy and threshold effects makes it ideally suited to explore jet-quenching sensitivity, energy-loss mechanisms, and the emergence of medium-modified fragmentation functions in the quark-gluon plasma. Moreover, it provides a natural baseline for implementing in-medium hadronization scenarios, including quarkonium regeneration and fragmentation-function apparent-shape distortion. These developments provide new handles for exploring heavy-flavor dynamics at the HL-LHC and future collider facilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22449v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Giovanni Celiberto, Francesca Lonigro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collectivity in pPb Collisions with Femtoscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22456</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22456v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Collisions of protons with lead nuclei (pPb), such as those measured by the LHCb experiment, provide a unique environment to study the surprising emergence of collective, fluid-like phenomena in small systems. A key signature of this hydrodynamic behavior is the predicted formation of a toroidal vorticity structure. In this work, I use two-particle femtoscopic correlations of non-identical hadrons, specifically proton-pion ($p\pi^+$) pairs, as a novel probe for this phenomenon. Previous works indicate that the collective flow of the system is consistent with the formation of a vortex ring created by the passage of the proton through the lead nucleus, which modifies the collective flow profile. I establish that the resulting emission asymmetry between protons and pions, driven by their mass difference and differential response to the vortical flow, is directly linked to the initial vorticity and can be measured using femtoscopy. This method therefore presents a new, sensitive observable for characterizing the rotational dynamics of the matter created in small collision systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22456v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleh Savchuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Refined Low-Energy Supernova Constraints on Lepton Flavor Violating Axions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22523v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The supernova (SN) core, characterized by its extreme temperature and density, serves as a unique laboratory for new-physics searches. Low-energy supernovae (LESNe) provide particularly powerful probes, as their low explosion energies place stringent limits on any additional energy deposition in the mantle by new particles. We present refined LESN constraints on lepton-flavor-violating (LFV) axions and axion-like particles (ALPs) with electron-muon couplings. We consider four production channels in the SN: muon decay, lepton bremsstrahlung, electron-muon coalescence, and semi-Compton scattering, the last of which is investigated here for the first time in the context of LFV-ALPs. We find that muon decay dominates in the low-mass regime, electron-muon coalescence in the high-mass regime, and semi-Compton scattering in the intermediate-mass range. To derive accurate limits, we compute both the energy transfer from the SN core to the mantle and the energy loss due to ALP production in the mantle, which can be substantial for both large and small couplings -- the latter case, to our knowledge, not previously noted in the literature. We find that LESNe provide the most stringent constraints on the parameter space for ALP masses above $\sim 110$ MeV. These refined results strengthen previous SN bounds and highlight the exceptional sensitivity of LESNe to LFV new physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22523v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zi-Miao Huang, Changqian Li, Zuowei Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the light charged Higgs boson, pseudoscalar Higgs boson, and $Z^\prime$ boson in the $U(1)_F$ model at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22537v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this papar, we study the production and decay of a charged Higgs boson, a pseudoscalar Higgs boson, and a $Z'$ boson at the LHC within the flavor-dependent model (FDM), at the LHC. Considering the constraints from perturbative unitarity and experimental measurements (e.g., the flavor physics data, higgs signal strengths, electroweak precision observables), we investigate the relevant processes by analyzing several common LHC search channels. Motivated by the excess in $t \to b\bar{b}c$ reported by ATLAS, which suggests a charged Higgs boson with a mass near 130 GeV and consistent with B-anomaly expectations, we perform a dedicated simulation for a charged Higgs around this mass. Our results support the experimental hint and predict that this particle has a high discovery potential at the future High-Luminosity Large Hadron Collider (HL-LHC). In contrast, for the pseudoscalar and $Z'$ bosons predicted in our model, they remain beyond the reach of current experiments as well as the expected sensitivity at a 14 TeV collider with an integrated luminosity of 300 fb$^{-1}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22537v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhan Cao, Zhong-Jun Yang, Jin-Lei Yang, Tai-Fu Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some Properties of Multi-Component Axion Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22569</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22569v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a mechanism for multi-component dark matter (DM) that originates from axion mixing. In this context, multi-component DM implies that the cold DM is composed of the QCD axion and many ultra-light axion-like particles (ALPs). This framework can be realized in the type IIB string axiverse with hierarchical axion masses and decay constants. Our investigation reveals that in the light QCD axion scenario, the energy density of the lightest ALP often dominates after mixing, invalidating the canonical light axion scenario. On the other hand, in the heavy QCD axion scenario, both the QCD axion and non-lightest ALPs may dominate, depending on the ALP decay constants. Under certain conditions, the canonical heavy axion scenario remains valid. Finally, we briefly discuss a theoretical framework featuring $\sim\mathcal{O}(100)$ axions, with hierarchical axion masses and decay constants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22569v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hai-Jun Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Information Meets High-Energy Physics: Probing Neutrinos and Beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22625v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This review explores the interplay between quantum information theory and high-energy physics, emphasizing how decoherence effects and unconventional neutrino oscillation patterns may unveil fundamental properties such as the Dirac or Majorana nature of neutrinos and potential CPT violation. It further discusses the use of entanglement measures as novel probes of axion-mediated interactions, outlining interdisciplinary strategies to test the limits of the Standard Model and explore new physics beyond it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22625v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raoul Serao, Gianpaolo Torre, Antonio Capolupo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent spin polarization from $\rho$ meson condensation in rotating hadronic matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22755v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The behavior of vector mesons in extreme environments provides a unique probe of non-perturbative Quantum Chromodynamics. We investigate the conditions for Bose-Einstein condensation (BEC) of spin-1 $\rho$ mesons in dense rotating hadronic matter, a regime relevant to the peripheral heavy-ion collisions and the interiors of rapidly rotating neutron stars. When the $\rho$ meson chemical potential ($\mu_\rho$) approaches its effective mass ($m_\rho^*$), a phase transition to BEC occurs. We demonstrate that this transition is non-trivially influenced by global rotation, which couples to the spin of the $\rho$ mesons, leading to a macroscopic spin alignment of the condensate along the axis of rotation. This interplay between condensation and rotation results in distinct polarization patterns, which can serve as a possible signature of a BEC in experiments. The results suggest that rapidly rotating neutron stars may harbor an anisotropic, spin-polarized $\rho$-condensed phase, which could impact their equation of state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22755v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kshitish Kumar Pradhan, Dushmanta Sahu, Raghunath Sahoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mass and Decay-Constant Evolution of Heavy Quarkonia and $B_c$ States from Thermal QCD Sum Rules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22870v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We analyze the thermal behavior of heavy vector and axial-vector mesons ($J/\psi$, $\Upsilon$, and $B_c$) within the finite-temperature QCD sum-rule framework. Using updated PDG-2024 quark masses, modern lattice-informed gluon condensates, and a temperature-dependent continuum threshold constrained by vacuum stability, we compute the evolution of the masses $m(T)$ and decay constants $f(T)$ up to $T/T_c \lesssim 0.9$. The extracted zero-temperature limits reproduce experimental and LHCb values within 1\%. Near the critical temperature, the relative suppression follows a clear hierarchy $\Upsilon &lt; J/\psi &lt; B_c$, consistent with their binding energies and lattice spectral trends. The predicted $1P$--$1S$ splitting for the $B_c$ system, $0.477~\mathrm{GeV}$, matches the LHCb observation of orbitally excited $B_c^{+}$ states. The results provide a coherent finite-temperature baseline for future extensions including radiative, higher-dimensional, and width effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22870v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enis Yazici</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Axion in the minimal SO(10) GUT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22962v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The QCD axion is investigated within the minimal supersymmetric SO(10) grand unified theory, where the Yukawa sector involves Higgs multiplets ${\bf 10}$ and $\overline{{\bf 126}}$. The relative phase between the VEVs of $({\bf 10,1,3})\subset\overline{{\bf 126}}$ and $({\bf \overline{10},1,3})\subset{\bf 126}$ under ${\rm SU}(4)_C\times{\rm SU}(2)_L\times{\rm SU}(2)_R$ is identified with the axion. The Peccei-Quinn and $B-L$ symmetry breaking scales coincide through $|\langle\Delta_R\rangle|=|\langle\overline{\Delta}_R\rangle|$. The scalar partner of the lightest right-handed neutrino plays the role of the inflaton, realizing hybrid inflation consistent with the observed CMB density fluctuations. After inflation, both fields acquire VEVs, and the domain-wall problem is resolved through the Lazarides-Shafi mechanism, which naturally restricts the model to three generations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22962v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takeshi Fukuyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective Theory for Light Portal Dark Matter Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22966</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22966v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a general framework for the computation of light portal dark matter direct detection, incorporating a consistent treatment of finite momentum transfer. In this framework, dark matter interacts with Standard Model matter through a light mediator, which simultaneously serves as the force carrier for dark matter self-interaction, potentially with a distinct coupling strength. The corresponding effective theory relevant for detecting this class of dark matter is systematically constructed. Our analysis focuses on light (semi)relativistic dark matter, which may originate from cosmic-ray boosting and can be probed in high threshold experiments such as large-volume neutrino detectors. In this context, the nucleon matrix elements of the effective operators at finite momentum transfer are required, made available through recent advances in lattice QCD and related nonperturbative methods. The relativistic Fermi gas model is used to convert the nucleon-level momentum transfer to the nuclear level, thereby incorporating nuclear effects pertinent to heavy target experiments. To demonstrate the utility of the framework, we present ultraviolet-complete examples featuring spin-1 and spin-2 portal dark matter. For these models, we compute the differential cross sections with respect to momentum transfer, adopting parameter choices that address the so-called core-cusp problem in astrophysical observations via dark matter self-interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22966v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qing Chen, Shuang-Yong Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bose-Einstein Condensate Cosmology within the Framework of QCD Axion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22974</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22974v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bose-Einstein Condensation (BEC) cosmology is analyzed in the framework of a string-inspired axion model. The dispersion relation of the axionic mode includes both gravitational and self-interaction terms, the latter being small in magnitude but crucial for inducing instability of the condensate. The generation rate of BEC around redshift $z\approx 30$ is primarily governed by gravity, consistent with a phenomenological value $\Gamma\approx 10^{-31}$ eV adopted in previous work and realizable for the QCD axion. The relation between this early BEC epoch and the later formation of supermassive black holes at $z\approx 5$ is also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22974v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takeshi Fukuyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gross-Llewellyn Smith sum rule with analytic coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23025v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the Gross-Llewellyn Smith sum rule within the framework of analytic QCD. A comparison is performed between experimental data, lattice calculations, and perturbative QCD based on conventional and analytic versions of perturbation theory with different parametrizations for the twist-four contribution. We show that conventional perturbation theory fails to reproduce the data, while the analytic version demonstrates good agreement with experiment and lattice calculations. We also discuss the relation between the Gross-Llewellyn Smith sum rule and the Bjorken sum rule.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23025v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. R. Gabdrakhmanov, N. A Gramotkov, A. V. Kotikov, O. V. Teryaev, D. A. Volkova, I. A. Zemlyakov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Landscape of Spontaneous CP Violation in Supersymmetric Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23033v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The strong CP problem remains one of the most important unresolved issues in the Standard Model. Spontaneous CP violation (SCPV) is a promising approach to the problem by assuming that CP is an exact symmetry of the Lagrangian but broken spontaneously at the vacuum, which enables the generation of the observed Cabibbo-Kobayashi-Maskawa (CKM) phase without reintroducing a nonzero strong CP phase. Supersymmetry (SUSY) provides a natural framework to accommodate such a mechanism, as SUSY can not only protect the scale of SCPV from radiative corrections but also suppress problematic higher-dimensional operators generating a strong CP phase. In the present study, we explore the realization of SCPV in two distinct SUSY scenarios. First, we investigate SCPV in the exact SUSY limit, extending the spurion formalism developed in non-supersymmetric theories and introducing a method to determine whether the given superpotential satisfies the necessary condition for SCPV. Second, we construct a model in which CP is spontaneously broken at an intermediate scale along pseudo-flat directions, stabilized by soft SUSY breaking and non-perturbative effects of a gauge theory. The latter setup predicts light scalars in the SCPV sector whose masses are determined by the SUSY breaking scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23033v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fangchao Liu, Shota Nakagawa, Yuichiro Nakai, Yaoduo Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for new physics effects in $\nu\bar{\nu}\gamma$ production at a Tera-Z factory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23065</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23065v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rare decays of the Z boson provide a sensitive probe for physics beyond the Standard Model (SM). This study investigates the $e^{+}e^{-} \to Z \to \nu\bar{\nu}\gamma$ process within the context of the Tera-Z programmes at future colliders such as the FCC-ee and CEPC. The SM predicts a one-loop branching ratio of $7.16 \times 10^{-10}$ for $Z \to \nu\bar{\nu}\gamma$, a value four times smaller than the current experimental limit from the LEP. To explore this window for new physics, we parameterize anomalous $Z\nu\bar{\nu}\gamma$ interactions using an Effective Field Theory framework, considering both dimension-6 and dimension-8 operators. A detailed simulation is performed by generating signal and background events with MadGraph, modeling particle showers with Pythia, and simulating detector effects with Delphes. The analysis employs key kinematic variables-including the photon energy ($E_\gamma$), missing transverse energy ($\not{E}_T$), and the missing transverse energy significance ($S_{\not{E}_T}$) to isolate the signal. The results yield upper limits on the anomalous couplings, from which we infer branching ratios for $Z \to \nu\bar{\nu}\gamma$ on the order of $10^{-9}$. This represents a significant improvement of several orders of magnitude over the LEP sensitivity. Consequently, this study demonstrates the unique potential of the Tera-Z runs not only to test the SM loop-level predictions with unprecedented precision but also to tightly constrain or reveal new anomalous interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23065v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Denizli, A. Senol, M. K\"oksal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Threshold effects as the origin of $Y(4500)$ observed in $e^+e^-\to J/\psi K^+K^-$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23099v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The BESIII collaboration has recently observed a resonant structure $Y(4500)$ in $e^{+}e^{-}\to J/\psi K^{+}K^{-}$, whose origin remains unresolved. In this study, we analyze the cross section line shape of $e^{+}e^{-}\to J/\psi K^{+}K^{-}$ by taking into account the $\psi(4415)$ state and intermediate charmed meson loops. By treating $\psi(4415)$ as both a pure $S$-wave state and $S$-$D$ mixed states, and introducing the $Z_{cs}^{(\prime)}$ resonance, we find that the $Y(4500)$ peak at $\sqrt{s}=4.5~\text{GeV}$ arises from the triangle singularity mechanism in the $Z_{cs}^{(\prime)}$-mediated rescattering processes, supporting its interpretation as a threshold effect rather than a conventional resonance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23099v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-Yun Wang, Liu-Lin Wang, Xiao-Hai Liu, Qiang Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing CP Violation through Vector Boson Fusion at High-Energy Muon Colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23257v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate CP-violating effects in electroweak interactions at future high-energy muon colliders within the Standard Model Effective Field Theory (SMEFT) framework. Focusing on four dimension-six CP-odd operators -- $ \mathcal{O}_{\widetilde{W}}, \mathcal{O}_{H\widetilde{W}}, \mathcal{O}_{H\widetilde{W}B}, \mathcal{O}_{H\widetilde{B}}$ -- we analyze vector boson fusion production of $W$ and Higgs bosons using CP-odd observables and their asymmetries. With detailed simulations including parton showering, hadronization, and detector effects, we derive exclusion sensitivities through a binned likelihood analysis. For example, at $\sqrt{s} = 3$ TeV with 2 ab$^{-1}$, the coefficient $C_{\widetilde{W}}$ can be constrained at the $\mathcal{O}(0.02)$ level, improving to $\mathcal{O}(0.008)$ at 10 TeV with 2 ab$^{-1}$, and $\mathcal{O}(0.003)$ with 10 ab$^{-1}$. These results significantly surpass current LHC and projected ILC sensitivities, demonstrating the unique potential of high-energy muon colliders to provide direct and model-independent probes of CP violation in the electroweak sector.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23257v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qing-Hong Cao, Jian-Nan Ding, Yandong Liu, Jin-Long Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generating Sizable Real and Imaginary $\tau$ Electric Dipole Moment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23348v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The CP-violating electric dipole moment~(EDM) of a fermion provides a powerful probe of new physics beyond the Standard Model~(SM). Among the charged leptons, the $\tau$ EDM remains the least constrained. When the photon has timelike momentum, the EDM develops an imaginary part. It imposes stronger constraints on new physics~(NP) than the real part. Although the current experimental bounds are several orders of magnitude above the Standard Model prediction, new physics can generate significantly larger values. Our analysis shows that an axion-like coupling of the $\tau$ lepton in the two-Higgs-doublet model can induce sizable real and imaginary components of the EDM, despite the stringent constraints imposed by current axion-like particle experiments. The predicted EDM values may approach the present experimental sensitivities, making them accessible to future measurements at Belle II and the Super Tau-Charm Facility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23348v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhong-Lv Huang, Xin-Yu Du, Xiao-Gang He, Chia-Wei Liu, Zi-Yue Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Production of Hyperons, Charmed Baryons, and Hadronic Molecule Candidates in Neutrino-Proton Reaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23370v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the production of hyperons, charmed baryons, and potential hadronic molecular states in neutrino-proton ($\bar{\nu}_\mu p$) reaction, a process characterized by a particularly clean final state. Employing effective Lagrangians, chiral perturbation theory, and a hadronic molecular model, we perform theoretical calculations for several relevant channels, including those leading to the formation of the hadronic molecular candidate $(\bar{D}N)$. Our results indicate that future neutrino facilities could serve as a complementary platform for exploring exotic baryonic states and provide valuable insights into the dynamics of strong interactions in the strange and charm sectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23370v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kai-sa Qiao, Bing-song Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigation of Resonances in the $\Sigma({1/2}^{-})$ System Based on the Chiral Quark Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23378v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate the resonance structures in the $\Sigma(1/2^-)$ system from both three-quark and five-quark perspectives within the framework of the chiral quark model. An accurate few-body computational approach, the Gaussian Expansion Method, is employed to construct the orbital wave functions of multiquark states. To reduce the model dependence on parameters, we fit two sets of parameters to check the stability of the results. The calculations show that our results remain stable despite changes in the parameters. In the three-quark calculations, two $\Sigma(1/2^-)$ states are obtained with energies around 1.8~GeV, which are good candidates for the experimentally observed $\Sigma(1750)$ and $\Sigma(1900)$. In the five-quark configuration, several stable resonance states are identified, including $\Sigma \pi$, $N \bar{K}$, and $N \bar{K}^{*}$. These resonance states survive the channel-coupling calculations under the complex-scaling framework and manifest as stable structures. Our results support the existence of a two-pole structure for the $\Sigma(1/2^-)$ system, predominantly composed of $\Sigma \pi$ and $N \bar{K}$ configurations, analogous to the well-known $\Lambda(1380)$-$\Lambda(1405)$ ($\Sigma \pi$-$N \bar{K}$) system. On the other hand, although the energy of the $N \bar{K}^{*}$ configuration is close to that of $\Sigma(1750)$ and $\Sigma(1900)$, the obtained width is not consistent with the experimental values. This suggests that the $N \bar{K}^{*}$ state needs to mix with three-quark components to better explain the experimental $\Sigma(1750)$ and $\Sigma(1900)$ states. According to our decay width calculations, the predicted two resonance states are primarily composed of $\Sigma \pi$ and $N \bar{K}$, with their main decay channel being $\Lambda \pi$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23378v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Yao, Xuejie Liu, Xiaoyun Chen, Yuheng Wu, Jialun Ping, Yue Tan, Qi Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudo-Nambu-Goldstone Dark Matter in Flux Compactification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23388</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23388v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a six-dimensional U(1)$_\chi$ gauge theory compactified on a magnetized torus, where the zero mode of the extra-dimensional gauge field (a Wilson-line (WL) scalar field) plays the role of a pseudo-Nambu-Goldstone (pNG) dark matter (DM) candidate. The pNG DM is naturally included by construction without introducing an additional scalar field. We show that the leading spin-independent DM-nucleus amplitude is suppressed by momentum transfer in our model as expected from the pNG DM model. This suppression allows the model to evade the current severe direct-detection bounds while achieving the observed thermal relic abundance in well-defined regions of parameter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23388v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kento Akamatsu, Takuya Hirose, Nobuhito Maru, Akio Nago</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pentaquarks on the light front, and their mixture with baryons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23404</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23404v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In previous papers we developed the light front formulation for Hamiltonians and wave functions (WFs) for mesons and baryons, with both confinement and chiral symmetry breaking. For baryons limited to the lowest Fock component with three quarks, the longitudinal WF is valued in an equilateral triangle with momentum fractions $x_i,i=1,2,3$. The WF was developed both numerically and using a basis function that diagonalizes the Laplacian with Dirichlet boundary conditions. In this paper we extend this analysis to $n$ quark states, and specialize to pentaquarks ($n=5$). We determine their masses and WFs, and address the mixing between baryons and pentaquarks, the issue central to understanding the observed antiquark sea of baryons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23404v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas Miesch, Edward Shuryak, Ismail Zahed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model-independent mass determination of near-threshold states from short-range production</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23468v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a novel observable for the precision measurements of a wide class of near-threshold dimer states: the short-range production rate of a dimer--spectator two-body system, composed of the given near-threshold state and one of its constituents. Within the framework of nonrelativistic effective field theory, these production rates exhibit characteristic line shapes for the specific partial wave and reach a model-independent minimum. This feature enables a precise extraction of their masses from experimental data, provided that the line shape can be resolved with sufficient accuracy. Applying this novel method to both the $T_{b\bar{b}1}(10610)B$ and $T_{b\bar{b}1}(10650)B^*$ systems allows for a precise determination of the binding energy $\delta$ of the $T_{b\bar{b}1}(10610)$ and $T_{b\bar{b}1}(10650)$ via the relation of $\delta=-{E_{\text{dip}}^{\text{exp}}}/{0.1983}$ once the respective dip position $E_{\text{dip}}^{\text{exp}}$ is experimentally identified.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23468v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yong-Hui Lin, Hans-Werner Hammer, Ulf-G. Mei{\ss}ner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Opportunities at FCC-ee for quark &amp; lepton flavour physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23488v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The FCC-ee phase of a Future Circular Collider is generating great interest due to its versatility, allowing the study of various electroweak thresholds, $Z$, $WW$, $ZH$, and $t \bar{t}$. Electroweak precision physics is complemented by flavour physics measurements based on the unprecedented statistics attainable at the $Z$ pole, and benefiting from the low-background experimental environment (similar to Belle II), and from the production of the full spectrum of hadron species together with large boosts (similar to LHCb). A wide range of measurements is possible, spanning a rich variety of physics cases in both quark and lepton flavour physics sectors. Other electroweak thresholds can also be considered in this endeavour. A commensurate effort from the theory community will be needed to interpret future measurements. I present an overview of the broad potential of the FCC-ee flavour physics program.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23488v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luiz Vale Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gaussian Processes for Inferring Parton Distributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21041v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The extraction of parton distribution functions (PDFs) from experimental or lattice QCD data is an ill-posed inverse problem, where regularization strongly impacts both systematic uncertainties and the reliability of the results. We study a framework based on Gaussian Process Regression (GPR) to reconstruct PDFs from lattice QCD matrix elements. Within a Bayesian framework, Gaussian processes serve as flexible priors that encode uncertainties, correlations, and constraints without imposing rigid functional forms. We investigate a wide range of kernel choices, mean functions, and hyperparameter treatments. We quantify information gained from the data using the Kullback Leibler divergence. Synthetic data tests demonstrate the consistency and robustness of the method. Our study establishes GPR as a systematic and non-parametric approach to PDF reconstruction, offering controlled uncertainty estimates and reduced model bias in lattice QCD analyses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21041v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yamil Cahuana Medrano, Herv\'e Dutrieux, Joseph Karpie, Kostas Orginos, Savvas Zafeiropoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QCD in strong magnetic fields: fluctuations of conserved charges and EoS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21731v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Strong magnetic fields can profoundly affect the equilibrium properties, characterized by the equation of state and bulk thermodynamics of strongly interacting matter. Although such fields are expected in off-central heavy-ion collisions, directly measuring their experimental imprints remains extremely challenging. To address this, we propose the baryon-electric charge correlations $\chi^{\rm BQ}_{11}$ and the chemical potential ratio $\mu_{\rm Q}/\mu_{\rm B}$ as magnetic-field-sensitive probes, based on (2+1)-flavor QCD lattice simulations at physical pion masses. Along the transition line, $\chi^{\rm BQ}_{11}$ and $(\mu_{\rm Q}/\mu_{\rm B})_{\rm LO}$ in Pb-Pb collisions increase by factors of 2.1 and 2.4 at $eB \simeq 8M_\pi^2$, respectively. To bridge theoretical predictions and experimental observations, we construct HRG-based proxies and apply systematic kinematic cuts to emulate STAR and ALICE detector acceptances. Furthermore, we extend this investigation to the QCD equation of state, and examine the leading-order thermodynamic coefficients for strangeness-neutral scenarios up to $eB \simeq 0.8 {\rm GeV}^2 \sim 45 m_{\pi}^2$, revealing intriguing non-monotonic structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21731v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heng-Tong Ding, Jin-Biao Gu, Arpith Kumar, Sheng-Tai Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Build an Empirical Speed Distribution for Dark Matter in the Solar Neighborhood</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21914v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The dark matter flux in a direct detection experiment depends on its local speed distribution. This distribution has been inferred from simulations of Milky Way-like galaxies, but such models serve only as proxies given that no simulation directly captures the detailed evolution of our own Galaxy. This motivates alternative approaches which obtain this distribution directly from observations. In this work, we utilize 98 Milky Way analogues from the IllustrisTNG50 simulation to develop and validate a procedure for inferring the dark matter speed distribution using the kinematics of nearby stars. We find that the dark matter that originated from old mergers, plus that from recent non-luminous accretions, is well described by a Maxwell-Boltzmann speed distribution centered at the local standard-of-rest velocity. Meanwhile, recently accreted dark matter from massive mergers has speeds that can be traced from the associated stellar debris of these events. The stellar populations systematically underestimate the velocity dispersion of their dark matter counterparts, but a simple kinematic boost brings the two into good alignment. Using the TNG50 host galaxies, we demonstrate that combining these two contributions provides an accurate reconstruction of the local dark matter speeds. As an application of the procedure to our own Galaxy, we utilize stellar kinematic data from Gaia to quantify how the dark matter remnants from the Milky Way's last major merger impact its speed distribution in the Solar neighborhood.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21914v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tal Shpigel, Dylan Folsom, Mariangela Lisanti, Lina Necib, Mark Vogelsberger, Lars Hernquist</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suppressed "lump" EM signature in radiation pressure dominated accreting massive black hole binaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21919v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the impact of radiation pressure on electromagnetic signatures of accreting massive black hole binaries (MBHBs) at milli-parsec separations, using 3D hyper-Lagrangian resolution hydrodynamical simulations. We model binaries embedded in a self-gravitating circumbinary disc that evolves following an adiabatic equation of state, including viscous heating and black-body cooling. Focusing on binaries with a total mass of $10^6 \, M_{\odot}$, eccentricities $e=0,0.45,0.9$ and mass ratios $q=1, 0.7$, we find that radiation pressure significantly affects both the spectral energy distributions (SEDs) and the light curves (LCs). The emission from the mini-discs shifts from the optical towards UV frequencies and with a peak luminosity orders of magnitude higher, while the circumbinary disc becomes colder and dimmer as a result of its geometrically thinner configuration. Temporal variability is affected as well: near UV and soft-X ray fluxes are higher and more variable. Crucially, radiation pressure suppresses the characteristic "lump" formation in equal-mass circular systems, while a lump is formed for higher eccentricities without imprinting any modulation on the flux. In the circular case we still find a modulation on the cavity edge timescale at a frequency $0.36 \, f_{\rm K}$, while in eccentric binaries, only robust orbital period modulations ($f=1,2 \, f_{\rm K}$) are observed, with no modulation associated with the cavity orbital motion. Moreover, the enhanced emission from the mini-discs and streams due to radiation pressure, one redshifted, results in brighter flux in the optical G band, proving detectability of MBHBs signatures even at higher redshift ($z=0.6-1.0$). Our results reveal that radiation pressure plays a crucial role in shaping MBHBs spectral and time-domain features, with implications for their identification in time-domain surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21919v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabiola Cocchiararo, Alessia Franchini, Alessandro Lupi, Alberto Sesana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Dark Energy Meets Varying Electron Mass: Implications for Phantom Crossing and the Hubble Constant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21931v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the interplay between varying electron mass ($m_e$) and dynamical dark energy by analysing the Chevallier-Polarski-Linder (CPL) parametrization and its non-crossing variants, both with and without a varying-$m_e$ component. Our aim is to assess whether the preference for late-time dynamics and phantom divide line (PDL) crossing persists when early-time physics is introduced, and whether these combined models improve the alleviation of the Hubble tension compared to the varying-$m_e$ extension alone. Using the latest CMB, BAO, and supernova datasets, we derive updated constraints on $\Lambda$CDM, CPL, and their extensions, and examine their impact on $H_0$ and the preference for late-time dynamics. We find that $\Lambda$CDM+$m_e$ yields the largest upward shift in $H_0$, while replacing $\Lambda$ with the CPL parametrization or its non-crossing variants provides modest improvements in the overall fit. The data consistently favour dynamical dark energy and a phantom divide line crossing at scale factors $a_{\rm c}\simeq0.6-0.9$, and these preferences remain robust, though somewhat weaker ($\gtrsim2\sigma$), when the electron mass is also allowed to vary. Among the late-time models, CPL performs better than its non-crossing variants, further reinforcing the evidence for a genuine phantom divide crossing. The alleviation of the $H_0$ tension in the varying-$m_e$ case arises from late-time data breaking the strong $\Omega_m$-$m_e$ degeneracy in the CMB, while the additional degrees of freedom in CPL models allow the late-time dynamics to absorb this impact, thereby weakening the degeneracy breaking and further lowering $H_0$ through their ability to yield a decreasing dark energy contribution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21931v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam Smith, Emre \"Oz\"ulker, Eleonora Di Valentino, Carsten van de Bruck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Avoiding PBH overproduction in inflation model with modified dispersion relation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22218</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22218v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Pulsar Timing Array (PTA) data of nano-Hertz gravitational waves released in 2023 implies that if such gravitational waves comes from the scalar perturbation induction at the end of inflation, the accompanied primordial black holes (PBHs) will be over-produced, with the fraction exceed the upper bound of unity. This is recognized as the ``overproduction problem", which calls for nontrivial features in the early universe. In this paper, we try to check out whether a modified dispersion relation (MDR) of the primordial perturbations can be helpful for solving the problem. From the constraint on PTA data, we obtain a posterior distribution of the parameters of primordial perturbation, and find that the MDR model, where the $k^4$ term becomes important at later time, can give rise to a broken-power-law (BPL) power spectrum which can alleviate the overproduction problem to nearly $2\sigma$ level. However, to improve furtherly into $1\sigma$ still needs small negative non-Gaussianity, e.g. $f_{\rm nl}\simeq -1$. The mass distribution of the PBHs generated is also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22218v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengrui Yang, Weixin Cai, Taotao Qiu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing GW231109_235456 and understanding its potential implications for population studies, nuclear physics, and multi-messenger astronomy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22290v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the gravitational-wave trigger GW231109_235456, a sub-threshold binary neutron star merger candidate observed in the first part of the fourth observing run of the LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA collaboration. Assuming the trigger is of astrophysical origin, we analyze it using state-of-the-art waveform models and investigate the robustness of the inferred source parameters under different prior choices in Bayesian inference. We assess the implications for population studies, nuclear physics, and multi-messenger astronomy. Analysing the component masses, we find that GW231109_235456 supports the proposed double Gaussian mass distribution of neutron star masses. Moreover, we find that the remnant most likely collapsed promptly to a black hole and that, because of the large distance, a possible kilonova connected to the merger was noticeably dimmer than AT2017gfo. In addition, we provide constraints on the equation of state from GW231109_235456 alone, as well as combined with GW170817 and GW190425. In our projections for the future, we simulate a similar event using the upcoming generation of gravitational-wave detectors. Our findings indicate that we can constrain the neutron star radius with an accuracy of 400 meters using the Einstein Telescope alone, or 300 meters when combined with the Cosmic Explorer, both at 90% credibility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22290v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thibeau Wouters, Anna Puecher, Peter T. H. Pang, Tim Dietrich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry principles of gravitational perturbations in thermal environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22346</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22346v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The instantaneous elastic response of gravitational perturbations to the thermal plasma can modify their dynamics near the horizon scale in the early universe. The obstacle is that there are several seemingly reasonable ways to introduce this contact term, reflecting an ambiguity in how one specifies the thermal initial state on a perturbed FLRW background. Diffeomorphism and Weyl invariance allow the (grand) canonical ensemble, defined in the decoupling limit of gravitational interactions, while excluding ensembles that break the Weyl identity, including those perturbed by the metric. With this consistent choice, primordial tensor modes exhibit stable damping, in agreement with Weinberg's kinetic theory analysis, providing a nontrivial consistency check and a robust basis for quantum-field-theoretic treatments of gravitational perturbations in thermal environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22346v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Atsuhisa Ota</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting ultralight dark matter in the Galactic Center with pulsars around Sgr A*</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22573</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22573v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ultralight dark matter (ULDM) model is a leading dark matter candidate that arises naturally in extensions of the Standard Model. In the Galactic Center, ULDM manifests as dense hydrogen-like boson clouds or self-gravitating soliton cores. We present the first study of the gravitational effects of these ULDM structures on pulsar orbits around Sgr A*, using pulsar timing as a precision dynamical probe, based on a comprehensive and practical framework that includes various kinds of black hole and orbital parameters. Our analysis shows that long-term pulsar monitoring -- one of the key objectives of future SKA science -- could detect a boson cloud with a total mass as low as $O(M_\odot)$ for boson mass $m \sim 10^{-18}\,\mathrm{eV}$, and probe a wide range of soliton core masses in the lower-mass regime, assuming a conservative timing precision of $\sigma_{\mathrm{TOA}}=1\,\mathrm{ms}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22573v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiang-Chuan Yu, Yan Cao, Zexin Hu, Lijing Shao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Axion-Photon conversion via circular polarization imprints in the CMB $V$-mode observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22592v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the presence of a background magnetic field, axions or axion-like particles (ALPs) can be resonantly converted to photons when their mass is nearly equal to the effective photon mass. In this paper, we propose a novel method to constrain the parameter space of ALPs by investigating the resulting imprints of axion-photon conversion in the cosmic microwave background (CMB) observations. We show that a helical magnetic field existing prior to the CMB epoch can generate an excess population of photons carrying net circular polarization due to the axion-photon conversion mechanism. Consequently, current measurements of the angular power spectrum of circular polarization ($V$-mode) in the CMB can be used to constrain the parameter space of ALP mass and its coupling to photons. In the optimistic scenario of a maximally helical magnetic field with strength $\sim {\rm nG}$, we find that CLASS observations at $40 \, {\rm GHz}$ can probe the previously unconstrained regions of axion-photon coupling corresponding to ALP masses in the range $10^{-10}-10^{-8} \, {\rm eV}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22592v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashu Kushwaha, Rajeev Kumar Jain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Gravitational Aspect of Information: The Physical Reality of Asymmetric "Distance"</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22664v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate that when a Brownian bridge is physically constrained to be canonical, its time evolution becomes identical to an m-geodesic on the statistical manifold of Gaussian distributions. This finding provides strong evidence that, akin to general relativity where free particles follow geodesics, purely random processes also follow ``straight lines" defined by the geometry of information. This geometric principle is a direct consequence of the dually flat structure inherent to information geometry, originating from the asymmetry of informational ``distance" (divergence) leading to the violation of metric compatibility. Our results suggest a geometric foundation for randomness and open the door to an equivalence principle for information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22664v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomoi Koide, Armin van de Venn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial black hole formation from collapsing domain walls with full general relativity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22759v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the dynamics of isolated closed domain walls with 3+1 numerical relativity. A closed wall shrinks due to its own surface tension, and its surface energy is converted to the kinetic energy, leading to implosion. Then, it can result in the formation of a black hole. First, we focus on spherically symmetric closed domain walls and clarify whether they finally evolve into black holes. Naively, the wall can collapse if its thickness is smaller than the Schwarzschild radius which is determined by the initial surface energy. Our numerical results support this naive criterion for the black hole formation, and indicate that more than 80% of the initial wall energy falls into the black hole. We also investigate the nonspherical collapse by considering the ellipsoidal configurations for the closed domain walls, and it turns out that black holes can be formed even when the ratio of semi-major to semi-minor axes is 1.5.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22759v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naoya Kitajima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Baryon and electric charge stoppings in nuclear collisions and the role of strangeness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22793v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It has been challenging to quantitatively understand the stopping of incoming nucleons in nuclear collisions, and recently it has been proposed that comparing the baryon stopping with electric charge stopping can help address the question. Here we focus on the $B/Q\times Z/A$ ratio, which can strongly depend on rapidity although its value is one for the full phase space. We find that this ratio is very sensitive to the difference between strange and anti-strange rapidity distributions (the $s-\bar s$ asymmetry), and slightly more anti-strange quarks at mid-rapidity would lead to a ratio well below one. This is the case for Zr+Zr and Ru+Ru isobar collisions at $200A$ GeV from a multi-phase transport (AMPT) model. Without the $s-\bar s$ asymmetry, the AMPT model would give a mid-rapidity $B/Q\times Z/A$ ratio at or above one. In addition, the AMPT model gives $B/\Delta Q\times \Delta Z/A&lt;1$ at mid-rapidity for isobar collisions at all centralities, which strongly contradicts the recent data from the STAR Collaboration. We further find that the $B/\Delta Q\times \Delta Z/A$ ratio is very sensitive to the net-light quark ($u,d$) stoppings, but it is less sensitive to the $s-\bar s$ asymmetry than the $B/Q\times Z/A$ ratio by a factor of 3.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22793v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mason Alexander Ross, Zi-Wei Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local gauge invariant operator on isometry breaking background</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22879v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Whereas local field operators play the crucial role in reconciling quantum mechanics and special relativity, they are not trivially compatible with the diffeomorphism invariance of gravity. In order to address this issue, we consider the background geometry which breaks the isometry spontaneously. Then the local gauge invariant operator can be constructed through the St\"uckelberg mechanism, where the fluctuation of the metric in the direction of the isometry breaking combines with that of matter whose classical solution breaks the isometry. This is equivalent to introducing the clock and the rod to promote the local field operators to the gauge invariant ones. A typical example is the curvature perturbation in quasi-de Sitter space arising from the spontaneous breaking of the timelike isometry. We also discuss the features of the local gauge invariant operator when the spacelike isometry is spontaneously broken. Meanwhile, even if the local gauge invariant operators exist, it does not guarantee the reliable construction of the gauge invariant operators on the local region like the island, which is regarded as an essential ingredient to resolve the black hole information paradox. This is because the fluctuation of the spacetime point is accumulated in time, which in fact also gives rise to eternal inflation in quasi-de Sitter space. In order to suppress the fluctuation at late time, the isometry must be strongly broken by the background. In the case of the evaporating black hole, it may be achieved by the transition to the higher dimensional black hole.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22879v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Min-Seok Seo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of XYZ particles at the BESIII Experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22921v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Charmonium is a bound state of a charmed quark and a charmed antiquark, and a charmoniumlike state is a resonant structure that contains at least a charmed quark-antiquark pair but has properties that are incompatible with a conventional charmonium state. The charmoniumlike states are also called XYZ particles to indicate their underlying nature is still unclear. The BESIII experiment has contributed significantly in the study of the XYZ particles, and here we review the discoveries of the Zc(3900), Zc(4020), and Zcs(3985) tetraquark states and the observations of several new vector charmoniumlike states at the BESIII experiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22921v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2025.117194</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Chang-Zheng Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The anomalous spin-statistics connection arising from pseudo-Hermiticity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22952</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22952v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We establish a new spin-statistics theorem for a class of free pseudo-Hermitian quantum field theories whose particles furnish unitary irreducible representations of the Poincar\'{e} group. In this framework, free pseudo-Hermitian fields with integer spin exhibit fermionic statistics, whereas those with half-integer spin exhibit bosonic statistics, opposite to the conventional case. This reversal arises from defining canonical field operators using pseudo-Hermitian conjugation rather than Hermitian conjugation, thereby circumventing the conventional spin-statistics theorem. The free fields retain locality, Lorentz covariance, and unitary evolution. However, interactions may violate unitarity due to the intrinsically non-Hermitian nature of the full Hamiltonian. We discuss potential resolutions to restore unitarity in interacting theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22952v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yao Bai, Cheng-Yang Lee, Ruifeng Leng, Siyi Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting Very High Energy Gamma-Ray Absorption in Cosmic Propagation under the Combined Effects of Axion-Like Particles and Lorentz Violation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23113v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Very high energy (VHE) gama rays above 100 GeV are expected to undergo significant attenuation during cosmic propagation due to pair production with thr extralactic background light (EBL). However, recent observations - particulary the tentative detection of gamma ray burst GRB 221009A up to 18 TeV by LHASSO and up to 251 TeV by Carpet-2, challenge the predictions of classical EBL absorption models. These exceptionally high-energy photons suggest the possibility of new physics affecting photon propagation over cosmological distances. In this context, the gamma-ray spectrum in the tens to hundreds of TeV range serves as a valuable probe for potential Lorentz invariance violation (LIV) effects or for modifications to photon attenuation due to axion-like particles (ALPs) mixing with photons in cosmic magnetic fields. However, both LIV and ALPs explanations, when considered separately, face certain limitations in fully accounting for the observed transparency. In this paper, we propose a unified framework that combines the effects of ALPs and LIV to explain the unexpectedly high survival probability of VHE photons. Specifically, we investigate the multi-wavelength spectrum of GRB 221009A under this synergistic scenario, demonstrating that for photons at 18 TeV and 251 TeV, the combined influence of ALPs with coupling $g_{a\gamma} = 13.353 \times 10^{-11}\ \mathrm{GeV}^{-1}$ and mass $m_a = 9.492 \times 10^{-7}\ \mathrm{eV}$, together with LIV characterized by energy scales $E_1 = 2.4~E_{\rm Planck}$ for $n = 1$ , can substantially enhance the photon survival probability. This synergy offers a compelling explanation for the observed VHE gamma-ray transparency in extreme astrophysical environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23113v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Longhua Qin, Jiancheng Wang, Chuyuan Yang, Huaizhen Li, Quangui Gao, Ju Ma, Ao Wang, Weiwei Na, Ming Zhou, Zunli Yuan, Chunxia Gu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A volcanic chronosequence as a time-resolved paleo-detector array to study the cosmic-ray flux in the Late Pleistocene and Holocene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23126</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23126v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a phenomenological study demonstrating the feasibility of using olivine xenoliths from the Cha\^ine des Puys as a time-resolved paleo-detector array to probe the cosmic-ray flux over the last 40,000 years. This volcanic region provides a unique chronosequence of samples brought to the surface by well-dated eruptions. By modeling the expected density of nuclear recoil tracks induced by cosmic-ray muons in olivine, we show that the signal is detectable and above backgrounds from natural radioactivity. We demonstrate that by analyzing samples with different exposure ages, it is possible to construct a time-differential measurement of the cosmic-ray flux. This method shows sensitivity to historical variations, such as the enhanced flux expected during the Laschamp geomagnetic excursion ($\sim$41~kyr) and the potential contribution from nearby supernovae, for which we use the Antlia supernova remnant precursor as a benchmark. This work establishes a new application of the paleo-detector technique for long-scale time-domain high-energy astrophysics and provides the direct scientific motivation for experimental efforts to measure these track records.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23126v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Claudio Galelli, Lorenzo Caccianiga, Lorenzo Apollonio, Paolo Magnani, Vincent Breton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recasting and Forecasting Dark Matter Limits Without Raw Data: A Generalized Algorithm for Gamma-Ray Telescopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23168v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a novel method for both forecasting and recasting upper limits (ULs) on dark matter (DM) annihilation cross sections, $\left&lt; \sigma v \right&gt;^{UL}$, or decay lifetime $\tau^{LL}$ . The forecasting method relies solely on the instrument response functions (IRFs) to predict ULs for a given observational setup, without the need for full analysis pipelines. The recasting procedure uses published ULs to reinterpret constraints for alternative DM models or channels. We demonstrate its utility across a range of canonical annihilation channels, including $b\bar{b}$, $W^+W^-$, $\tau^+\tau^-$, and $\mu^+\mu^-$, and apply it to several major gamma-ray experiments, including MAGIC, \textit{Fermi}-LAT, and CTAO. Notably, we develop a recasting approach that remains effective even when the IRF is unavailable by extracting generalized IRF-dependent coefficients from benchmark channels. We apply this method to reinterpret ULs derived from standard spectra (e.g., PPPC4DMID) in terms of more recent DM scenarios, including a Higgsino-like model with mixed final states and spectra generated with the CosmiXs model. Extensive Monte Carlo simulations and direct comparison with published results confirm the robustness and accuracy of our method, with discrepancies remaining within statistical uncertainties. The algorithm is generally applicable to any scenario where the expected signal model is parametric, offering a powerful tool for reinterpreting existing gamma-ray limits and efficiently exploring the DM parameter space in current and future indirect detection experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23168v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giacomo D'Amico, Michele Doro, Michela De Caria</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-strange and charmed hadrons: A novel probe for the QCD equation of state at high baryon densities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23353v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nuclear experiments near and below the threshold of hyperon production have shown that the production of Kaons is a sensitive probe for the dense QCD equation of state. At beam energies up to 1.5AGeV, strangeness production can probe the equation of state for densities up to approximately twice nuclear saturation. In this paper we will discuss the possibilities of extending this range in density by the study of multi-strange baryons as well as charmed hadrons in the SIS100 beam energy range up to 10AGeV. Here, densities up to five times nuclear saturation can be reached and the production of multi-strange and charmed hadrons shows a strong sensitivity to the equation of state. On the other hand a precise prediction of the effect of the equation of state will require knowledge of the fundamental production cross section near the elementary production threshold in p+p collisions which is yet not measured for the hadrons discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23353v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Steinheimer, Tom Reichert, Marcus Bleicher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anti-Flatness and Non-Local Magic in Two-Particle Scattering Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23426v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Non-local magic and anti-flatness provide a measure of the quantum complexity in the wavefunction of a physical system. Supported by entanglement, they cannot be removed by local unitary operations, thus providing basis-independent measures, and sufficiently large values underpin the need for quantum computers in order to perform precise simulations of the system at scale. Towards a better understanding of the quantum-complexity generation by fundamental interactions, the building blocks of many-body systems, we consider non-local magic and anti-flatness in two-particle scattering processes, specifically focusing on low-energy nucleon-nucleon scattering and high-energy Moller scattering. We find that the non-local magic induced in both interactions is four times the anti-flatness (which is found to be true for any two-qubit wavefunction), and verify the relation between the Clifford-averaged anti-flatness and total magic. For these processes, the anti-flatness is a more experimentally accessible quantity as it can be determined from one of the final-state particles, and does not require spin correlations. While the MOLLER experiment at the Thomas Jefferson National Accelerator Facility does not include final-state spin measurements, the results presented here may add motivation to consider their future inclusion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23426v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. E. P. Robin, M. J. Savage</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bose-Einstein Condensation and Dissipative Dynamics in a Relativistic Pion Gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.09288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.09288v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Pion condensation in ultra-relativistic collisions presents a compelling theoretical phenomenon with significant implications for the dynamics of hadronic matter. Various theoretical frameworks offer insight into the nature of high-temperature Bose-Einstein condensation (BEC). The present study investigates the dissipative behavior of a relativistic pion gas undergoing Bose-Einstein condensation (BEC) in ultra-relativistic heavy-ion collisions. Further, we obtain viscosity ($\eta$), bulk viscosity ($\zeta$), and speed of sound ($c_s$) by employing the Boltzmann transport equation with the relaxation time approximation. Findings show a substantial drop in $\eta/s$ and $\zeta/s$ with the fractional increase in condensation. This effect is becoming more evident in larger systems approaching the thermodynamic limit. Alongside the reduction in viscosities, the speed of sound also decreases with increasing condensation, indicating a softening of the equation of state. The analysis of finite-size effects reveals that larger systems exhibit more pronounced signatures of BEC. These results suggest that pion condensation can influence the hydrodynamic evolution of the hadronic phase in heavy-ion collisions, with consequential implications for interpreting collective flow observables and the underlying equation of state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.09288v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/4lh7-6nvj</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review D 112, 074031 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kshitish Kumar Pradhan, Dushmanta Sahu, Captain R. Singh, Raghunath Sahoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supersymmetric hybrid inflation and current-carrying metastable cosmic strings in $SU(4)_c \times SU(2)_L \times U(1)_R$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.11410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.11410v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct a realistic supersymmetric model for superheavy metastable cosmic strings (CSs) that can be investigated in the current pulsar timing array (PTA) experiments. It is based on shifted $\mu$-hybrid inflation in which the symmetry breaking $SU(4)_c \times SU(2)_L \times U(1)_R\rightarrow SU(3)_c\times SU(2)_L \times U(1)_{B-L}\times U(1)_R$ proceeds along an inflationary trajectory such that the topologically unstable primordial monopoles are inflated away. {{The breaking of $U(1)_{B-L} \times U(1)_R \rightarrow U(1)_Y$ after inflation ends yields the superheavy metastable CSs carrying the right handed neutrino zero modes that generate the stochastic gravitational wave background (SGWB), which we show is consistent with the current PTA data set and the LIGO O3 run}}. The scalar spectral index $n_s$ and the tensor-to-scalar ratio $r$ are compatible with the Planck 2018 and Atacama Cosmology Telescope measurements. Both reheating and leptogenesis are briefly discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.11410v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/d7zx-c7f7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 112, 083545- 23 October, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Adeela Afzal, Maria Mehmood, Mansoor Ur Rehman, Qaisar Shafi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AdS/CFT and the Double-Copy: A Unified Perspective Across Various Phenomenological Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.11418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.11418v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study utilizes theoretical tools including the double copy relation and AdS/CFT correspondence. Applying analogies, we establish a system to discuss the associations and equivalence relations among QCD, QED, and various (mixed) gauge field theory based quantum many-body effective models. By employing mathematical techniques on the background spacetime, these relations are extended to extreme regimes while ensuring model independence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.11418v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jia-rui Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First order electroweak radiative corrections to the decay of the polarised $W$ boson</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13810</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13810v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Analytic results for the next-to-leading order electroweak radiative corrections to the decay of the polarised $W$ boson into a pair of heavy quarks are presented. Finite fermion masses are taken into account throughout this calculation, and in performing the collinear limit for the final quark states and all light fermions taking part in this process, the importance of mass effects is demonstrated. This gives hints for the deviation of the total decay rate and the branching ratios into massive fermions between experimental measurements and theoretical predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13810v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/82vp-xcnp</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 112 (2025), 073009</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Maria Naeem, Stefan Groote</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining the Coexistence of Freeze-in Dark Matter and Primordial Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02935</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02935v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Particle dark matter and primordial black holes (PBH) might coexist with appreciable cosmic abundances, with both contributing to the observed dark matter density $\Omega_{\rm DM}$. Large populations of PBH (with $\Omega_{\rm PBH}\sim \Omega_{\rm DM}$) are tightly constrained for PBH heavier than $10^{-11} M_\odot$. However, large fractional abundances with $ f_{\rm PBH}\simeq \Omega_{\rm PBH}/\Omega_{\rm DM}\sim0.01$ are consistent with the limits on PBH for a wide range of PBH masses. Scenarios with significant populations of both particle dark matter and PBH are intriguing. Notably, if the particle dark matter has interactions with the Standard Model, new constraints arise due to pair-annihilations that are enhanced by the PBHs, resulting in dark matter indirect detection constraints on $f_{\rm PBH}$. Here we derive the bounds on mixed scenarios in which PBHs coexist with particle dark matter whose relic abundance is set via freeze-in (``FIMPs''). We show that while the restrictions on $f_{\rm PBH}$ are less constraining for FIMPs than WIMPs, modest bounds still arise for large classes of models. We examine both IR and UV freeze-in scenarios, including the case of ``superheavy'' particle dark matter with PeV scale mass.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02935v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prolay Chanda, Sagnik Mukherjee, James Unwin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emerging axion detection in artificial magnetoelectric materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08477</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08477v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Axions are considered a key component of dark matter, characterized by very weak couplings to fermions and Chern-Simons couplings to gauge fields. We propose a novel detection mechanism based on symmetry-breaking magnetoelectric materials with a linear axionic coupling between magnetization and ferroelectric polarization. The focus is on a strain gradient Sr2IrO4 film, where the breaking of space-inversion symmetry results in an emergent polar phase and an out-of-plane magnetic moment, exhibiting a flexomagnetoelectric effect. In this material, the linear P||M enables a direct coupling between the external axion field and the intrinsic axion-like field, which amplifies the weak electromagnetic signals induced by axions, paving the way for pioneering axion detection. In contrast to conventional detection techniques, this mechanism is expected to enhance the sensitivity of the axion-electron and axion-photon coupling, providing a novel platform for axion detection and advancing the study of dark matter through the magnetoelectric effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08477v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/andp.202500202</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ANNALEN DER PHYSIK (2025): e00202</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Runyu Lei, Chen-Hui Xie, Jiayi Liu, Zhong Liu, Xin Liu, Yu Gao, Sichun Sun, Jinxing Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can local White Dwarfs constrain Dark Matter interactions?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13629v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate whether nearby white dwarfs (WDs) can constrain dark matter (DM) interactions with ordinary matter. As experimental sensitivity improves, driven by the Gaia mission, the sample volume of nearby WDs has been increasing over recent years. We carefully select a sample of ten cold, isolated, non-magnetic WDs within 13~pc of the Sun. We model their carbon-oxygen interior using a finite temperature relativistic equation of state and model atmospheres to infer their core temperatures. This enables us to perform a thorough estimation of the DM capture rate and evaporation mass using actual astrophysical observations. Given the low local DM density, we focus on DM that annihilates into long-lived mediators, which escape the WD and later decay into photons. While \textit{Fermi}-LAT data shows no significant gamma-ray excess, future telescopes, CTA North \&amp; South, LHAASO, SWGO, could probe DM-nucleon cross sections down to $\sim 10^{-41}~\text{cm}^2$ for DM masses above the TeV scale. Our results are competitive with current direct detection bounds (e.g., LZ) in the multi-TeV regime. This work underscores the importance of systematic WD studies in the broader landscape of DM detection and demonstrates the synergy between astrophysical and terrestrial searches in exploring DM interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13629v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/10/093</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP10(2025)093</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pooja Bhattacharjee, Sandra Robles, Stephan A. Meighen-Berger, Francesca Calore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smooth hybrid inflation in light of ACT DR6 data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.15965v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Smooth hybrid inflation is a hybrid inflation model which is free from topological defects and predicts the density perturbation with the spectral index of about $0.97$. We show that the prediction on the spectral index is robust regardless the power of nonrenormalizable terms and meets with the latest results reported by Atacama Cosmology Telescope. Viable scenarios for baryogenesis and dark matter are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.15965v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/y9s8-7b5b</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 112, 083549 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nobuchika Okada, Osamu Seto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $\theta$-term effects on isospin asymmetric hot and dense quark matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.02697v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the impact of the CP-violating $\theta$ term on isospin symmetry breaking in quark matter and compact star properties using a two-flavor Nambu-Jona-Lasinio (NJL) model. By incorporating the $\theta$ parameter through the Kobayashi-Maskawa-'t Hooft (KMT) determinant interaction, we derive the thermodynamic potential and gap equations under finite temperature, baryon chemical potential, and isospin chemical potential. At zero temperature and baryon density, $\theta$ suppresses conventional chiral ($\sigma$) and pion ($\pi$) condensates while promoting pseudo-scalar ($\eta$) and scalar-isovector ($\delta$) condensates, thereby reducing the critical isospin chemical potential $\mu_I^{\text{crit}}$ for spontaneous symmetry breaking. For $\theta=\pi$, a first-order phase transition emerges at $\mu_I^{\text{crit}} = 0.021$ GeV, accompanied by CP symmetry restoration. Extending the investigation to finite temperature and baryon chemical potential reveals that these $\theta$-term-induced effects persist. Axion effects (modeled via $\theta\equiv a/f_a$) stiffen the equation of state (EOS) of non-strange quark stars, increasing their maximum mass and radii, in agreement with multimessenger constraints from pulsar observations and gravitational wave events. These results establish $\theta$ as a critical parameter modulating both the Quantum Chromodynamics (QCD) phase structure and compact star observables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.02697v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Zhang, Lu-Meng Liu, Mei Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fresh look at the nuclear transparency using the generalized parton distributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.06333v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Color transparency (CT) is a fundamental phenomenon in QCD in which hadrons produced in high-energy exclusive processes traverse nuclear matter with minimal interactions. Nuclear transparency, which quantifies this attenuation suppression, is a quantity with high sensitivity to CT effects and provides critical insights into QCD dynamics in nuclear environments. In this study, we revisit nuclear transparency using the framework of generalized parton distributions (GPDs). By constructing nuclear GPDs (nGPDs) through the incorporation of nuclear parton distribution functions, we calculate the nuclear transparency $ T(Q^2) $ for the carbon nucleus as a function of momentum transfer $ Q^2 $ considering various definitions and compare the results obtained with available experimental data. Our finding highlights the importance of choosing a physically motivated definition of nuclear transparency. Moreover, we emphasize that a more reliable determination of nGPDs requires a dedicated global analysis incorporating nuclear data. Such an approach is essential for improving the theoretical understanding of CT and for achieving consistency with experimental observations in the high-$ Q^2 $ regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.06333v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> The MMGPDs Collaboration, Muhammad Goharipour, Fatemeh Irani, K. Azizi, Dipangkar Dutta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electroweak corrections to Higgs+jet production in gluon fusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.20882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.20882v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the calculation of complete next-to-leading order electroweak corrections to the Higgs boson production in $gg\to g H$ channel. We apply the method of differential equations combined with the selection of optimized master integrals to accomplish the calculation of master integrals. We consider three distinct renormalization schemes. At leading order, the differential distributions and the total cross section show a strong dependence on the renormalization scheme. However, these discrepancies are considerably suppressed once electroweak corrections are taken into account. For $G_\mu$ scheme, the electroweak correction amounts to approximately $4.3\%$ of the total cross section. Importantly, we find that the EW corrections exhibit a strong dependence on Higgs transverse momentum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.20882v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP10(2025)194</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Long-Bin Chen, Hai Tao Li, Wen-Long Sang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoding the role of $\rho$ mesonic states for elucidating the $e^+e^-\to a_2(1320)\pi$ data and other reactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.21554v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, the BESIII Collaboration observed a $\rho$-like structure $Y(2044)$ in $e^+e^-\to a_2(1320)\pi$, suggesting that $Y(2044)$ may be a candidate of vector meson $\rho(2D)$ by comparing resonance parameters. However, the theoretical prediction for the combined branching ratio $\Gamma_{e^+e^-}\mathcal{B}_{a_2(1320)\pi}$ for the pure $\rho(2D)$ state is about two orders of magnitude smaller than the experimental value. To resolve this discrepancy and decipher the nature of $Y(2044)$, this work propose an $S$-$D$ mixing scheme to reanalyze the cross section of $e^+e^-\to a_2(1320)\pi$, and find that the aforementioned branching ratio discrepancy can be resolved. Our results show that the $Y(2044)$ structure can be reproduced by introducing four theoretically predicted $S$-$D$ mixing $\rho$ meson states $\rho_{3S-2D}^{\prime}$, $\rho_{3S-2D}^{\prime\prime}$, $\rho_{4S-3D}^{\prime}$, and $\rho_{4S-3D}^{\prime\prime}$ as intermediate resonances, in which dominant contribution arises from $\rho_{3S-2D}^{\prime\prime}$ and their inference effect is also significant. Furthermore, we reanalyzed five additional isospin vector processes $e^+e^-\to \omega\pi^0$, $e^+e^-\to f_1(1285)\pi^+\pi^-$, $e^+e^-\to \pi^+\pi^-$, $e^+e^-\to \rho \eta$, and $e^+e^-\to \eta^{\prime} \pi^+\pi^-$ based on the same $S$-$D$ mixing framework, and simultaneously reproduced their experimental cross section data. This work provides a unified framework to elucidate all observed $\rho$-like structures near 2 GeV in the $e^+e^-$ annihilation processes, and suggests that the $S$-$D$ mixing effect may be crucial for understanding the mass spectrum and decay behaviors of the higher $\rho$ meson states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.21554v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/pdfh-mk79</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 112 (2025) 7, 074021</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Qin-Song Zhou, Zi-Yue Bai, Jun-Zhang Wang, Hao Xu, Xiang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified description of sum rules and duality between CP phases and unitarity triangles through third-order rephasing invariants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00702v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this letter, we demonstrate that products of third-order rephasing invariants $V_{\alpha i} V_{\beta j} V_{\gamma k} / \det V$ of flavor mixing matrix $V$ reproduce all the nine angles of unitarity triangles and all the CP phases in the nine parameterizations of $V$. The sum rules relating the CP phases and angles are also decomposed into terms of these rephasing invariants. Furthermore, through ninth-order invariants, these fourth- and fifth-order invariants become equivalent, which can be regarded as a certain duality. For the phase matrix $\Delta$ and the angle matrix $\Phi$, $\Delta \pm \Phi$ are expressed in terms of even-permutations $X$ and odd-permutations $\Psi$ of third-order invariant. As a result, these are represented by the two concise matrix equations $\Phi = \Psi - {\rm X}$ and $\Delta = \Pi' - \Psi - {\rm X}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00702v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masaki J. S. Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherently Enhanced Axion-Photon Conversion via Seeded Photons for Short-Pulse Axion Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21417</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21417v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a seeded axion-photon conversion scheme to enhance the sensitivity of light-shining-through-a-wall (LSW) experiments for axion detection, where the axions are generated from short pulse lasers and the usual resonant cavity is not applicable. By injecting a weak, coherent seed electromagnetic (EM) field into the axion-photon conversion region, the axion-induced EM field can constructively interfere with the seed field, amplifying the number of regenerated photons to a level exceeding that of the unseeded scenario. We evaluate the expected signal enhancement, statistical limits from Poisson counting with seed fluctuations and background, and the potential improvement in coupling sensitivity. Compared to a standard LSW setup, the seeded scheme can achieve orders-of-magnitude higher photon yield per axion, potentially surpassing resonance-enhanced experiments in certain parameter regimes. This approach presents a promising pathway to extend the reach of laboratory axion searches, particularly in scenarios where the resonant cavities are impractical.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21417v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiangyan An, Min Chen, Jianglai Liu, Yipeng Wu, Peng Yuan, Wenchao Yan, Boyuan Li, Feng Liu, Zhengming Sheng, Jie Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Axion Perturbations: A General Analytical Treatment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07371v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Cosmological data provides us two key constraints on dark matter (DM): it must have a particular abundance, and it must have an adiabatic spectrum of density perturbations in the early universe. Many different cosmological scenarios have been proposed that establish the abundance of axion DM in qualitatively different ways. In this paper we emphasize that, despite this variety of backgrounds, the perturbations in axion DM can be understood from universal principles. How does a feebly interacting axion field acquire perturbations proportional to those of photons? How do the isocurvature power spectrum and non-Gaussianity depend on the background evolution of the universe? We answer these questions for a completely general choice of cosmological background and temperature-dependent axion potential. We show that the most general solution to the axion field equation on super-horizon scales is entirely determined by the family of background solutions for different initial field values $\theta_{\rm ini}$. This holds for both the component in the field perturbation solution contributing to the DM isocurvature perturbation (enhanced at late times by the sensitivity of the DM abundance to the initial condition, $\partial \Omega_a / \partial \theta_{\rm ini}$, which can be large for initial conditions near the hilltop), and the other component that contributes to the DM curvature perturbation. In particular, we explain that an unperturbed axion field in the early universe evolving into one with nontrivial adiabatic perturbations is guaranteed by Weinberg's theorem on adiabatic modes. These results have been derived before with various assumptions, such as a radiation dominated background or a quadratic potential. Our aim is to give a clear, simple derivation that is manifestly independent of those assumptions, and thus can be applied to any cosmological axion scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07371v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Itamar J. Allali, Priyesh Chakraborty, JiJi Fan, Matthew Reece</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncovering Singularities in Feynman Integrals via Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10099v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a machine-learning framework based on symbolic regression to extract the full symbol alphabet of multi-loop Feynman integrals. By targeting the analytic structure rather than reduction, the method is broadly applicable and interpretable across different families of integrals. It successfully reconstructs complete symbol alphabets in nontrivial examples, demonstrating both robustness and generality. Beyond accelerating computations case by case, it uncovers the analytic structure universally. This framework opens new avenues for multi-loop amplitude analysis and provides a versatile tool for exploring scattering amplitudes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10099v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuanche Liu, Yingxuan Xu, Yang Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Absence of Majorana-Weyl fermions in d=4 and the theory of Majorana fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14998v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is customary to identify $\psi_{+}=\nu_{R} + C\overline{\nu_{R}}^{T}$ with a Majorana fermion on the basis of chirality changing charge conjugation $\tilde{C}: \nu_{R}\rightarrow C\overline{\nu_{R}}^{T}$ and parity $\tilde{P}: \nu_{R}\rightarrow i\gamma^{0}\nu_{R}$. The theorem on the absence of a Majorana-Weyl fermion in $d=4$ states $\tilde{C}\gamma_{5}\tilde{C}^{-1}= -\gamma_{5}$ with $\tilde{C}=C\gamma_{4}^{T}$, and thus the charge conjugation of the equivalent Majorana $\psi_{+}=(\frac{1+\gamma_{5}}{2})\nu_{R} + (\frac{1-\gamma_{5}}{2})C\overline{\nu_{R}}^{T}$ vanishes without auxiliary $\gamma_{5}\rightarrow - \gamma_{5}$.
  To be consistent with the theorem, it is common to use a doublet representation of chirality preserving charge conjugation $\hat{C}:\nu_{R,L}\rightarrow C\overline{\nu_{L,R}}^{T}$ and parity $\hat{P}: \nu_{R,L}\rightarrow i\gamma^{0}\nu_{L,R}$ in theory containing both $\nu_{R,L}$. In the type I seesaw model, the latter formulation is applicable but $\psi_{+}=\nu_{R} + C\overline{\nu_{R}}^{T}$ is not a Majorana fermion. An analogue of the Bogoliubov transformation converts $\psi_{\pm}=\nu_{R, L} \pm C\overline{\nu_{R, L}}^{T}$, which are obtained by a precise diagonalization of the seesaw model, to Majorana fermions $\psi_{M_{1,2}}=(\psi \pm C\overline{\psi}^{T})/\sqrt{2}$ with a Dirac-type fermion $\psi$, as originally defined by Majorana. A chiral projection $[(1+\gamma_{5})/2] \psi_{M_{1}}$ of a Majorana fermion is not a chiral fermion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14998v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuo Fujikawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial Non-Gaussianity from Light Compact Scalars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07672v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the non-Gaussianities generated by light axions, or compact scalar fields, during inflation. To correctly calculate their impact on primordial statistics, we will argue that it is necessary to account for the periodicity, or gauge symmetry, of the compact scalars. We illustrate this point by comparing the predictions for the squeezed kinematic limit of the primordial bispectrum generated by two cases: a non-compact scalar $\sigma$ and a compact scalar $\varphi$. We demonstrate that while a light non-compact scalar predicts a bispectrum of the so-called local shape, the light compact scalar predicts a qualitatively different shape characterised by the ratio of the Hubble scale to its field-space circumference. In doing so, we show that ignoring the gauge symmetry of the compact scalar during inflation leads to spurious infrared enhancements which are softened by working with appropriate gauge-invariant operators. In addition, we connect our results for the primordial bispectrum with late-time cosmological observables and show that it is possible to measure the decay constant of the compact scalar using galaxy clustering measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07672v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Priyesh Chakraborty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Present Status of Inflationary Cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13646</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13646v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We give a brief review of the basic principles of inflationary theory and discuss the present status of the simplest inflationary models that can describe Planck/BICEP/Keck observational data by choice of a single model parameter. In particular, we discuss the Starobinsky model, Higgs inflation, and $\alpha$-attractors, including the recently developed $\alpha$-attractor models with $SL(2,\mathbb{Z})$ invariant potentials. We also describe inflationary models providing a good fit to the recent ACT data, as well as the polynomial chaotic inflation models with three parameters, which can account for any values of the three main CMB-related inflationary parameters $A_{s}$, $n_{s}$ and $r$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13646v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renata Kallosh, Andrei Linde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proton Structure Functions from Holographic Einstein-Dilaton Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13649</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13649v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the proton structure functions $F_1$ and $F_2$ in the context of holography. We develop a general framework that extends previous holographic calculations of $F_1$ and $F_2$ to the case where the bulk geometry stems from bottom-up Einstein-Dilaton models, which are commonly used in the literature to describe some properties of QCD in the strong coupling regime. We focus on a choice of the dilaton potential that leads to a holographic model able to reproduce known lattice QCD results for the glueball masses at zero temperature and pure Yang-Mills thermodynamics above deconfinement. Once the parameters of the background holographic model are fixed, we introduce probe fermionic and gauge fields in the bulk {\it a la} Polchinski and Strassler to determine the corresponding structure functions. This particular realization of the model can successfully describe the proton mass and provide results for $F_2$ at large $x$ in very good agreement with experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13649v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayrton da Cruz Pereira do Nascimento, Henrique Boschi-Filho, Jorge Noronha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinetic coupling and dark matter on the lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16984v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study a $U(1)\otimes U(1)$ system coupled to scalar fields. Initially the model is studied in a novel continuum formulation and study of the appropriate diagonalizations is performed. Three models are examined, in two of which the scalar field couples with both gauge fields while in the third one the scalar field couples only to the dark photon. The model is then treated on a space-time lattice. We determine the phase diagram for various values of the kinetic coupling parameter. Then there follows the determination of masses for the scalar fields and the massive gauge fields, as well as the fine structure constants for the massless gauge fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16984v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Farakos, V. Iconomou, G. Koutsoumbas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Quark Stars with Quark-Quark Phase Transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.00776v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We explore the possibility of phase transitions between different quark matter phases occurring within quark stars, giving rise to the hybrid quark stars (HybQSs). First, we obtain the generic phase diagram of possible mass-radius relation forms for the HybQSs. Then, utilizing a well-established general parameterization of interacting quark matter, we construct quark star models featuring sharp first-order quark-quark phase transitions of various types, in contrast to the hadron-quark transition in conventional hybrid stars. We systematically investigate how recent observations, such as the pulsar mass measurement $M_{\rm TOV}\gtrsim2M_{\odot}$ and the GW170817's tidal deformability bound $\Lambda_{1.4M_{\odot}}&lt;800$, constrain the viable parameter space. We also identified twin stars in some of the HybQS parameter space. Furthermore, we found that the quark-quark phase transitions in hybrid quark stars may also cause the deviation from the approximate universal relation between the dominant postmerger frequency $f_{\rm peak}$ and tidal deformability $\Lambda_{1.35M_{\odot}}$, which was previously believed to only be caused by the hadron-quark phase transitions in hybrid neutron stars. This work unveils new possibilities of phase transitions and the resulting new types of compact stars in realistic astrophysical scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.00776v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zongcan Yang, Tianxiong Zeng, Yan Yan, Wen-Li Yuan, Chen Zhang, Enping Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extraction of ground-state nuclear deformations from ultra-relativistic heavy-ion collisions: Nuclear structure physics context</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05208v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The collective-flow-assisted nuclear shape-imaging method in ultra-relativistic heavy-ion collisions has recently been used to characterize nuclear collective states. In this paper, we assess the foundations of the shape-imaging technique employed in these studies. We argue that some current UHIC nuclear imaging techniques neglect fundamental aspects of spontaneous symmetry-breaking and symmetry-restoration in colliding ions and incorrectly infer one-body multipole moments from studies of nucleonic correlations. Therefore, the impact of this approach on nuclear structure research has been overstated. Conversely, efforts to incorporate existing knowledge on nuclear shapes into analysis pipelines can be beneficial for benchmarking tools and calibrating models used to extract information from ultra-relativistic heavy-ion experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05208v3</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Dobaczewski, A. Gade, K. Godbey, R. V. F. Janssens, W. Nazarewicz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Construction of general $N$-body lattice operators with arbitrary momenta</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16070v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a systematic method for constructing lattice QCD operators for systems of an arbitrary number of particles with arbitrary momentum, spin, and internal quantum numbers. Explicit constructions are provided for one-, two-, three-, and four-hadron operators, covering all irreducible representations of the relevant lattice symmetry groups in both rest and moving frames. The construction procedure has been implemented in the open-source package \texttt{OpTion} (Operator construcTion), available at https://github.com/wittscien/OpTion. The paper and the package are designed to serve as a practical and extensible dictionary for future lattice QCD studies, as lattice calculations advance towards increasingly complex hadronic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16070v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP10(2025)210</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 10 (2025) 210</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Haobo Yan, Chuan Liu, Liuming Liu, Yu Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 300 TeV photon from GRB 221009A: a Hint at Non-linear Lorentz Invariance Violation?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07153</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.07153v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The air shower array Carpet-3 detected a 300 TeV photon from the direction of GRB 221009A at 4536 s after the Fermi-GBM trigger for this event. If the association with this gamma-ray burst is real, it poses two puzzles. First, why was this photon not absorbed by the extragalactic background light? ``New physics'' beyond the Standard Model is required to explain how it managed to reach Earth from a cosmological distance. Second, why was this photon detected when the VHE afterglow observed by LHAASO already faded? A novel astrophysical mechanism is required to explain this delay. In this work we show that Lorentz invariance violation (LIV), which arises as a low-energy limit of certain quantum gravity theories, can solve both puzzles. It shifts thresholds of particle interaction and changes the opacity of the extragalactic background, and cause energy-dependent variations of the photon velocity, which changes the photon time of flight. We investigate the LIV parameter space assuming that the 300 TeV photon is a part of the VHE afterglow detected by LHAASO in the TeV range. We identify viable solutions and place stringent two-sided constraints on the LIV energy scale required to resolve the observational puzzles. First-order LIV appears to be incompatible with the constraints set by analyzing the TeV afterglow of this GRB. Viable solutions emerge for higher orders. In particular, the commonly studied second-order subluminal LIV with $E_{\rm LIV2} = 1.30_{-0.35}^{+0.56} \times 10^{-7} E_{\rm Pl}$ (95.4% credibility level; $E_{\rm Pl}$ is the Planck energy) is consistent with all the observed data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.07153v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/cydc-6j4z</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>D. D. Ofengeim and T. Piran, Phys. Rev. D 112, 083055 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Dmitry D. Ofengeim, Tsvi Piran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Carpet-3 300 TeV Photon Event as an Evidence for Lorentz Violation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.08984v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The detection by the Carpet-3 Group of a 300 TeV photon, observed 4536 seconds after the prompt emission of the historic gamma-ray burst GRB 221009A, provides unprecedented opportunities to test Lorentz invariance violation (LV) at energy scales approaching the Planck regime. By analyzing the temporal and spatial properties of this ultra-high-energy photon in conjunction with lower-energy photons from other bursts and the same burst, we demonstrate consistency with subluminal LV scenarios characterized by an energy scale \( E_{\rm LV} \sim 3 \times 10^{17} \, \rm{GeV} \). This work bridges multi-year LV studies using GeV-TeV photons and establishes GRB 221009A as a pivotal laboratory for quantum spacetime phenomenology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.08984v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2025.139959</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Lett. B 870 (2025) 139959</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hanlin Song, Bo-Qiang Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward extracting scattering phase shift from integrated correlation functions V: complex $\phi^4$ field model in $3+1$ dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12881</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12881v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In Ref.~\cite{Guo:2024zal} and associated studies, a relativistic finite-volume formalism in $1+1$ dimensions is proposed to extract infinite-volume scattering phaseshift.
  It is based on the difference of integrated correlation functions (ICF) rather than energy spectrum in the finite volume, and can be regarded as complementary to the well-known L\"{uscher} formalism.
  In the present work, the formalism is further extended into $3+1$ dimensional spacetime. The aim is to explore and demonstrate the challenges in applying the formalism to more practical settings. Specifically, Monte Carlo simulations of a complex $\phi^4$ relativistic field model are carried out in both 2+1 and 3+1 dimensions on lattices of varying sizes, and phaseshifts for the contact interaction are extracted from the formalism using modest computing resources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12881v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peng Guo, Frank X. Lee, Andrei Alexandru</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imprints of screened dark energy on nonlocal quantum correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.18448v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate how screening mechanisms, reconciling light scalar fields driving cosmic acceleration with local fifth force constraints, can be probed via their impact on non-local quantum correlations between entangled spin pairs, whose evolution on a curved background is affected by General Relativity (GR) and screened modified gravity effects. We consider a gedankenexperiment featuring a pair of massive, spin-1/2 particles orbiting the Earth, evaluating their non-local correlations through spin observables associated to the Clauser-Horne-Shimony-Holt (CHSH) inequality. Using a general formalism developed earlier for curved space-time spin evolution, we compute the effects of screening on the CHSH inequality, finding its degree of violation to be suppressed relative to the flat space-time case. Applying this formalism to the chameleon, symmetron, and dilaton mechanisms, we identify currently unconstrained regions of parameter space where the screening contribution is comparable to that of GR. While detecting these effects will be challenging, our work provides a proof-of-principle for testing screened dark energy through quantum non-locality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.18448v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/y314-4x4s</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 112 (2025) 084011</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fabiano Feleppa, Gaetano Lambiase, Sunny Vagnozzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
