<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph</link>
    <description>hep-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Hunting and identifying coloured resonances in four top events with machine learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04318</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04318v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study prospects to search for pair or singly produced colour octet or colour sextet scalars which decay into two top quarks at the LHC. We focus on the same-sign lepton final state. We train a neural network comprising a simple multilayer perceptron combined with a convolutional neural network to optimize the separation of signal and background events. For LHC operated at 14 TeV and a luminosity of 3 ab$^{-1}$ we find an expected discovery reach of $m_8=1.8$ TeV and $m_6=1.92$ TeV for pair produced colour octets and sextets, respectively, and an expected exclusion reach of $m_8=2.02$ TeV and $m_6=2.14$ TeV. In a second step, we retrain the same network architecture to discriminate between signal processes. The network can clearly distinguish between the different colour representations. Moreover, we can also determine whether there is a significant contribution from single production to pair production for the same final state. The methodology can be applied to BSM candidates of different spin and colour representations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04318v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Flacke, Jeong Han Kim, Manuel Kunkel, Jun Seung Pi, Werner Porod</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>{\tt ggxy}: a flexible library to compute gluon-induced cross sections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04323</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04323v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the library {\tt ggxy}, written in {\tt C++}, which can be
  used to compute partonic and hadronic cross sections for gluon-induced
  processes with at least one closed heavy quark loop.
  It is based on analytic ingredients which avoids, to a large extent,
  expensive numerical integration. This results in significantly shorter
  run-times than other similar tools.
  Modifying input parameters, changing the renormalization scheme
  and varying renormalization and factorization scales is straightforward.
  In Version~1 of {\tt ggxy} we implement all routines which are needed to
  compute partonic and hadronic cross sections for Higgs boson pair production
  up to next-to-leading order in QCD. We provide flexible interfaces
  and allow the user to interact with the built-in amplitudes at
  various levels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04323v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Davies, Kay Sch\"onwald, Matthias Steinhauser, Daniel Stremmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secluded Dark Composites and Remnant Binding Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04331v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dark matter may freeze-out and undergo composite assembly while decoupled from the Standard Model. In this secluded composite scenario, while individual dark matter particles may be too weakly-coupled to detect, the assembled composite can potentially be detected since its effective coupling scales with number of constituents. We examine models and observables for secluded composites, and in particular we investigate the cosmological abundance of the composite binding field, which is generated during freeze-out annihilation and secluded composite assembly. This binding field could be discovered as a new relativistic species in the early universe or through later interactions as a subdominant dark component.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04331v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katarina Bleau, Yilda Boukhtouchen, Joseph Bramante, Rohan Kulkarni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the electromagnetic structure of the $P_c(4337)^+$ pentaquark: Insights from a diquark-diquark-antiquark picture for $J^P = \frac{1}{2}^-$ and $\frac{3}{2}^-$ states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04345</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04345v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, the electromagnetic structure of the hidden-charm pentaquark $P_c(4337)$ is investigated within the diquark-diquark-antiquark model using the QCD light-cone sum rule approach. The magnetic moments of the $ P_c(4337) $ state are calculated for the spin-parity assignments $ J^P = \frac{1}{2}^- $ and $\frac{3}{2}^-$. The results are found to be $ \mu_{P_c} = 1.76 \pm 0.44~\mu_N $ for the $ \frac{1}{2}^- $ case and $ \mu_{P_c} = -1.38 \pm 0.35~\mu_N $ for the $ \frac{3}{2}^- $ scenario. These findings offer important insights into the internal quark-gluon structure and electromagnetic features of this multiquark system. Beyond their theoretical relevance, the results serve as essential benchmarks for future experimental studies aimed at determining the quantum numbers and underlying configuration of the $ P_c(4337) $. Additionally, the electric quadrupole and magnetic octupole moments of the spin-$\frac{3}{2}$ state are extracted, indicating a non-spherical charge distribution for this exotic pentaquark.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04345v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>U. \"Ozdem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter Induced Proton Decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04370v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a novel theoretical framework in which proton decay is induced by the dark matter. While proton decay requires violation of the $B+L$ symmetry, dark matter stability often relies on the presence of an unbroken symmetry. These seemingly distinct phenomena are unified through the global $U(1)_{B+L}$ symmetry inherent in the Standard Model. Its spontaneous breaking leads to a residual $Z_4$ symmetry, which ensures dark matter stability and forbids proton decay at tree level. Consequently, proton decay occurs at the one-loop level, mediated by dark sector particles. The proton lifetime is linked with the dark matter, the heavier dark matter mass enhancing proton stability, and vice versa. The $\mathcal{O}$(TeV) masses of the mediators remain consistent with current proton lifetime limits, making them accessible to experimental searches. In particular, the leptoquark mediating proton decay, carrying exotic $B+L$ charges, leads to a distinctive signature in collider searches. By intertwining proton decay, dark matter stability, and collider phenomenology, this framework offers distinctive signatures that can be probed in current and future experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04370v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ranjeet Kumar, Rahul Srivastava</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Setting up stasis with gravitational interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04502v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An epoch known as cosmological stasis may have taken place in the early Universe. During matter-radiation stasis, a population of non-relativistic particles with different masses gradually decay into relativistic particles, and the effective equation of state $w$ remains approximately constant at a value between that of matter ($w=0$) and that of radiation ($w=1/3$). In this work, we investigate how to set up the appropriate initial conditions for stasis using gravitational interactions. We consider two scenarios: that the tower of non-relativistic particles is populated by the evaporation of primordial black holes (PBHs) and that the tower is populated by cosmological gravitational particle production (CGPP) during inflation. We calculate the abundance of particles on different levels of the tower to assess whether stasis is viable. We find that both scenarios can provide the needed initial conditions for stasis, and that they predict distinctive scaling exponents $\Omega_l \propto m_l^\alpha$ with mass $m_l$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04502v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew J. Long, Barmak Shams Es Haghi, Moira Venegas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on Noether's second theorem and the energy-momentum tensor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04510v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Through symmetry of the action under global spacetime translations, Noether's first theorem infamously entails an energy-momentum tensor (EMT) that is neither symmetric nor gauge-invariant. In a prior work [Phys. Rev. D 106, 125012 (2022)], I had obtained a symmetric and gauge-invariant EMT by using Noether's second theorem instead, with local spacetime translations as the symmetry group. However, the derivation therein was flawed, containing a faulty assumption about the transformation rule for spinor fields. In this work, I revisit the derivation of [Phys. Rev. D 106, 125012 (2022)], both correcting the faulty step and simplifying the derivation for broader accessibility. The end result is an EMT for quantum chromodynamics that is gauge-invariant, but not symmetric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04510v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam Freese</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounds and detection of MeV-scale dark matter annihilation to neutrinos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04568v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Current and most upcoming neutrino detectors can only reach a dark matter annihilation cross section to neutrinos larger than the standard freeze-out value, but they open intriguing detection avenues for non-standard dark matter paradigms. An important corollary of such non-standard scenarios is relic dark matter annihilation after neutrino decoupling, an effect that does not modify the neutrino temperature and was neglected in constraining the standard MeV-scale dark matter masses. By combining the contributions from entropy injection during neutrino decoupling and nonthermal neutrino energy release after decoupling, we derive significant constraints on the annihilation cross section to neutrinos, which in some mass regimes turn out to be stronger than the current bounds. Furthermore, we find that the lower bounds on dark matter masses become inconclusive under the recent data releases from the DESI, SPT-3G, and ACT collaborations. These bounds determine the extent to which upcoming neutrino detectors will probe dark matter annihilation into neutrinos.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04568v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shinya Kanemura, Shao-Ping Li, Dibyendu Nanda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Terrestrial Relic Neutrino Charge with Mach-Zehnder Interferometer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04621v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a novel method to probe the cosmic neutrino background (CNB) which has been shown to be accumulated on the surface of the earth. If such relic neutrino carries non-zero electric charge, Mach-Zehnder interferometer offers a suitable venue to unveil its interaction with photons. For neutrino mass equals to 0.05 eV, the sensitivity reach of our proposal could probe the fractional electric charge of the neutrino $\epsilon_{\nu}$ as low as $9.3 \times 10^{-11},\, 1.6 \times 10^{-16}$, and $2.9 \times 10^{-22}$ provided that the interferometer operates at standard quantum limit (SQL), the Heisenberg limit as well as super-Heisenberg limit, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04621v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chuan-Ren Chen, Chrisna Setyo Nugroho, Vincent Gene L. Otero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Line shape analysis of $\Lambda(1405)$ in $\gamma p \rightarrow K^+\Sigma^-\pi^+$ reaction using convolutional neural network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04622v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Interpreting peaks or dips that appear in an invariant mass distribution is a recurring challenge in hadron physics. These enhancements can be ambiguous, especially near a two-hadron threshold since kinematical and dynamical effects play an important role in their nature. One such enhancement is an exotic baryon $\Lambda(1405)$ which was first observed in 1973. Despite the few available experimental data, the statistics of the measurements of $\Lambda(1405)$ have improved for line shape analysis. The present consensus is that it is a structure of two poles both on the second Riemann sheet. However, there are still investigations of other pole structures corresponding to $\Lambda(1405)$. Lately, the use of a deep neural network in analyzing these line shapes has been proven to be effective, especially in distinguishing pole structures. Thus, in this study, we develop a convolutional neural network, a type of DNN, to determine the general pole structure that corresponds to $\Lambda(1405)$ found in the $\Sigma^-\pi^+$ invariant mass distribution measured by CLAS in their experiment involving the $\gamma p \rightarrow K^+\Sigma\pi$ reaction. The CNN is trained using a two-channel uniformized $S$-matrix allowing us to control the position and the corresponding Riemann sheet of the poles. Our preliminary results show that the trained CNN can accurately distinguish pole structures in the $\Sigma^-\pi^+$ invariant mass distribution and agrees with the present consensus of a two-pole structure. This supports the preceding works on the $\Lambda(1405)$ and requires a thorough analysis of $\Sigma^+\pi^-$ and $\Sigma^0\pi^0$ invariant mass spectra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04622v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vince Angelo A. Chavez, Denny Lane B. Sombillo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feature extraction in partial wave analysis using $K$-matrix approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04628v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Structures in the invariant mass distribution are often linked to unstable intermediate states or resonances. In experiments, many signals are detected which have broad, overlapping or intricate profiles, which makes their characterization a formidable task. To ascertain whether or not these enhancements are resonances, and to determine their physical parameters, such as the resonance mass, coupling strength, resonance width, and quantum numbers, a tool known as partial wave analysis (PWA) is employed. To ensure unitarity, and to account for superposing states and non-resonant effects in modeling the scattering amplitude, $K$-matrix parametrization is utilized. To factor in the centrifugal effects on the decay rates arising from breakup processes in nonzero angular momenta, the Blatt-Weisskopf barrier factors are incorporated into the formulation. In this study, $K$-matrix parametrized differential cross sections were generated within near-threshold and resonance energy ranges, which served as the training and validation datasets for the Deep Neural Network (DNN). The Fully-Connected Neural Network (FCNN) architecture is applied to facilitate the classification task of this work, which is the discrimination of dominating partial waves in the scattering processes. The DNN model was designed to encompass various two-hadron scattering phenomena. As a stepping-off point, the values of the thresholds, coupling constants, resonance masses and widths, scattering energy ranges, and the decay channels used in this study found their physical inspiration from pion-nucleon ($\pi$$N$) scattering system in the $S$, $P$, $D$, $F$, and $G$ partial waves. The results of the model's performance showed that the DNN can distinguish the partial wave with resonances from the other partial waves with purely non-resonant contributions, at an accuracy of $69\%$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04628v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam B. Mapa II, Denny Lane B. Sombillo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of closely spaced thresholds on line shapes with near-threshold enhancement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04630v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hidden-charm pentaquarks were first experimentally detected by LHCb in 2019, one of which is the exotic $P_{c\bar{c}}(4312)^{+}$ state. The nature of this state remains uncertain which may be attributed to the proximity of this observed enhancement to the meson-baryon thresholds. In this study, we introduce a coupled-channel approach using three-channel separable potential model to account for near-threshold effects on the observed signal. In particular, we assign $\Sigma_c^+\bar{D}^0$ and $\Sigma_c^{++}D^-$ as higher-mass channels for $P_{c \bar{c}}(4312)^+$ state. Moreover, this allows us to propose four pole configurations, where either a bound state or virtual state pole were placed near the higher-mass thresholds. Using this scheme, we study the near-threshold effects on the transition of different pole configurations across the unphysical Riemann sheets and examine their effects on the amplitude line shape. We found out that $P_{c \bar{c}}(4312)^+$ state may be interpreted as a virtual state below the $\Sigma_c^+\bar{D}^0$ which is consistent with our initial modeling assumptions. Our result also conforms with the previous analysis done by Joint Physics Analysis Center (JPAC) \cite{Fernandez-Ramirez:2019koa}, which leans toward similar interpretation. This may indicate that a model-dependent framework employing a relatively simple model, such as a separable potential, can somehow complement with some of the widely used parameterizations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04630v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Exan John D. F. Carpio, Denny Lane B. Sombillo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Axion-mediated photon-to-photon transitions in high finesse dielectric resonators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04666v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Axions are hypothetical particles that could address both the strong charge-parity problem in quantum chromodynamics and the enigmatic nature of dark matter. However, if axions exist, their mass remains unknown, and they are expected to interact very weakly with the electromagnetic field, which explains why they have not been detected yet. This study proposes a way to substantially augment the axion-photon interaction by confining the photons within high-quality-factor dielectric resonators, increasing their intensity and lifetime and thus the possibility of interacting with axions in the background. In view of this, we study resonant axion-mediated photonic transitions in millimeter-sized spherical dielectric resonators, based on fully analytical calculations to the first order in perturbation theory. Such resonators exhibit high lifetime Mie resonances in the microwave part of the spectrum, with a separation that can be tailored with the radius of the sphere to match the expected axion frequency, allowing axion-mediated photonic transitions when particular selection rules are fulfilled. Such transitions are expected to be enhanced by more than ten orders of magnitude in the presence of the resonator, compared to transitions occurring in homogeneous space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04666v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evangelos Almpanis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark matter and dark radiation from chiral $U(1)$ gauge symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04718</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04718v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a simple model of a dark sector with a chiral $U(1)$ gauge symmetry. The anomaly-free condition requires at least five chiral fermions. Some of the fermions acquire masses through a vacuum expectation value of a Higgs field, and they are stable due to an accidental symmetry. This makes them dark matter candidates. If the dark sector was once in thermal equilibrium with the Standard Model and dark radiation constraints are included, two-component dark matter may be needed since the number of massless fermions is restricted. To meet the requirements from dark matter direct detection experiments, the main component should be a Majorana fermion, and the secondary component should be a Dirac fermion. The amount of Dirac fermion dark matter must be sufficiently small to satisfy direct detection limits. We also discuss the possibility of testing an invisible dark photon at future lepton collider experiments, taking into account cosmological constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04718v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao He, Takaaki Nomura, Norimi Yokozaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark higher-form portals and duality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04795v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Light scalar or vector particles are among the most studied dark matter candidates. Yet, those are always described as scalar or vector fields. In this paper, we explore instead the embedding of the scalar particle in an antisymmetric rank-three tensor field, and the dark photon into an antisymmetric rank-two tensor field (a so-called Kalb-Ramond field), and construct minimal bases of effective interactions with Standard Model fields. Then, keeping phenomenological applications as our main objective, a number of theoretical aspects are clarified, in particular related to the impact of existing dualities among the corresponding free theories, and concerning their Stueckelberg representations. Besides, for the rank-two field, we present for the first time its full propagator, accounting for the possible presence of a pseudoscalar mass term. Thanks to these results, and with their different kinematics, gauge-invariant limits, and Lorentz properties, we show that these higher-form fields provide genuine alternative frameworks, with different couplings and expected signatures at low-energy or at colliders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04795v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cypris Plantier, Christopher Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Central exclusive production of $\eta$ and $\eta'$ mesons in diffractive proton-proton collisions at the LHC within the tensor-pomeron approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04846</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04846v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a study of the central exclusive production (CEP) of $\eta$ and $\eta'(958)$ mesons in diffractive proton-proton collisions at high energies. The amplitudes, including pomeron and $f_{2 \mathbb{R}}$ reggeon exchanges, are calculated within the tensor-pomeron model. Absorption effects are also taken into account at the amplitude level. We fit some undetermined model parameters (coupling constants and cutoff parameters in form factors) to the WA102 experimental data and then make predictions for the LHC energy $\sqrt{s} = 13$ TeV. Both, total cross sections and several differential distributions are presented. For $pp \to pp \eta$, we find an upper limit for the total cross section of 2.5 $\mu$b for pseudorapidity of the $\eta$ meson $|\eta_{M}| &lt; 1$ and 5.6 $\mu$b for $2 &lt; \eta_{M} &lt; 5$. For $pp \to pp \eta'$, we predict the cross section to be in the range of $0.3-0.7 \,\mu$b for pseudorapidity of the $\eta'$ meson $|\eta_{M}| &lt; 1$ and $0.9-2.1 \,\mu$b for $2 &lt; \eta_{M} &lt; 5$. This opens the possibility to study diffractive production of pseudoscalar mesons in experiments at the LHC. We also consider CEP of the pseudoscalars $\eta$ and $\eta'(958)$ and the pseudovector meson $f_{1}(1285)$ in diffractive proton-proton collisions in a theory with a scalar pomeron. We show that none of these particles can be produced in this way in the scalar-pomeron theory. Thus, experimental observation of any of these particles in the above CEP processes at the LHC would give striking evidence against a scalar character of the pomeron.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04846v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Piotr Lebiedowicz, Otto Nachtmann, Antoni Szczurek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extended locally monochromatic approximations of Strong-Field QED processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04889v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Strong-field QED (SFQED) probability rates in the locally monochromatic approximation (LMA) have become an indispensable tool for simulations of processes like gamma-ray emission or electron-positron pair production in laser-particle collisions. We revisit the LMA derivation and explicitly demonstrate that it is based on the separation of time scales, neglection of the long-range interference effects and subsequent averaging over the cycle scale. Doing so, we obtain unambiguously LMA rates for arbitrary polarizations of the plane wave background. Additionally, we partially restore the finite bandwidth effects that are lost in the LMA derivation. The bandwidth-restored result we refer to as the LMA$^+$ and show that it agrees with the full SFQED predictions better than the standard LMA. We use LMA$^+$ to address previously inaccessible observables and formulate a new limitation on the applicability of locally monochromatic approximations in general. We provide analytical results for the angular-integrated LMA$^+$ probability rate and the fully differential probability that account for the finite bandwidth effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04889v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikita Larin, Daniel Seipt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-perturbative determination of the sphaleron rate for first-order phase transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04939</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04939v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In many extensions of the Standard Model electroweak phase transitions at high temperatures can be described in a minimal dimensionally reduced effective theory with SU(2) gauge field and fundamental Higgs scalar. In this effective theory, all thermodynamic information is governed by two dimensionless ratios $x \equiv \lambda_3/g^2_3$ and $y\equiv m^2_3/g^4_3$, where $\lambda_3$, $m^2_3$ and $g_3$ are the effective thermal scalar self-interaction coupling, the thermal mass and the effective gauge-coupling, respectively. By using non-perturbative lattice simulations to determine the rate of sphaleron transitions in the entire $(x,y)$-plane corresponding to the Higgs phase, and by applying previous lattice results for the bubble nucleation, we find a condition $x(T_c) \lesssim 0.025$ to guarantee preservation of the baryon asymmetry, which translates to $v/T_c \equiv \sqrt{2 \langle \phi^\dagger \phi \rangle}/T_c \gtrsim 1.33$ for the (gauge-invariant) Higgs condensate. This indicates that viability of the electroweak baryogenesis requires the phase transition to be slightly stronger than previously anticipated. Finally, we present a general template for analysing such viability in a wide class of beyond the Standard Model theories, in which new fields are heavy enough to be integrated out at high temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04939v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jaakko Annala, Kari Rummukainen, Tuomas V. I. Tenkanen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward an advanced phenomenology of $\pi N$ transition distribution amplitudes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04961v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a new approach to modeling transition distribution amplitudes (TDAs) for the processes $e p \to e n \pi^+$ and $e p \to e p \pi^0$. The modeling is flexible, constrained by sparsely available experimental data, and satisfies theoretical requirements, including reduction to nucleon distribution amplitudes in the appropriate limit. We study the sensitivity of observable predictions to various modeling assumptions. We discuss unpolarized cross-sections, as well as the three non-vanishing polarization observables at leading twist, namely, the single transverse target spin asymmetry and the two double spin asymmetries that occur with a polarized lepton beam on either a longitudinally or transversely polarized target. The analysis is complemented by a simple Monte Carlo study to provide guidance for exploring exclusive processes in the so-called backward kinematics. Our work aims to highlight the importance of future measurements to better constrain TDAs and to support upcoming experimental proposals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04961v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Pire, K. Semenov-Tian-Shansky, P. Sznajder, L. Szymanowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing new physics scenarios using high energy events at NOvA far detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04984v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: NuMI Off-axis $\nu_e$ Appearance (NOvA) experiment is an ongoing long baseline neutrino oscillation experiment. The primary channels of interest are the $\nu_e$, $\bar{\nu}_e$ appearance, $\nu_\mu$, $\bar{\nu}_\mu$ disappearance channels analyzed in the energy window $1&lt; E_\nu &lt; 4$ GeV. However, NOvA far detector sees non-trivial high energy $\nu_e$, $\bar{\nu}_e$ events in the energy range $4 &lt; E_\nu &lt; 20$ GeV. These high energy events provide us with an opportunity to investigate the subleading new physics scenarios. In this context, we study the sensitivity of the NOvA experiment to constrain the non-standard interaction (NSI) parameters and environmental decoherence. We observe that by including high energy events (signal + background) the degeneracy around $\epsilon_{e\tau} \sim 1.6$ can be removed throughout the $\delta_{CP}$ and $\delta_{e\tau}$ range. Further, we examine the role of signal versus beam background events in removing this degeneracy. In addition, assuming environmental decoherence in nature we illustrate the uncertainty in the determination of $\theta_{23}$ considering events from $1&lt;E_\nu&lt;4$ GeV and $1&lt;E_\nu&lt;20$ GeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04984v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chinmay Bera, K. N. Deepthi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral perturbation theory for baryon-number-violating nucleon decay into a vector meson</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05052v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a recent work \cite{Liao:2025vlj} we identified generic baryon-number-violating (BNV) structures containing triple light quarks and achieved their leading-order chiral realizations involving octet pseudoscalars and baryons. Although many two-body nucleon decays into a vector meson have been experimentally searched for and stringently constrained, a consistent theoretical framework for their calculation is still lacking. In this Letter, we fill the gap by implementing chiral matching of all these triple-quark interactions onto hadronic interactions involving octet vector mesons, baryons, and pseudoscalars. This paves the way for a consistent and comprehensive study of all relevant BNV processes. As an illustration of application, we show how degeneracy in the parameter space of Wilson coefficients can be broken by synthesizing experimental constraints on nucleon decays into a vector or pseudoscalar meson when relevant hadronic low energy constants can be reasonably determined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05052v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi Liao, Xiao-Dong Ma, Hao-Lin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonperturbative Parameters of Inclusive $\Lambda_b$ Decays from Small Velocity Sum Rules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05134v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the nonperturbative parameters entering the heavy quark expansion for the inclusive decay rates of the $\Lambda_b$ baryon, focusing on the kinetic term $\hat{\mu}_\pi^2$ and the Darwin term $\hat{\rho}_D^3$. Recent evaluations have yielded an unexpectedly large Wilson coefficient associated with the dimension-six Darwin operator, which motivates a more detailed examination of the associated hadronic matrix element. We constrain $\hat{\mu}_\pi^2$ and $\hat{\rho}_D^3$ using Small Velocity Sum Rules for the inclusive semileptonic decay $\Lambda_b \to X_c e^- \bar{\nu}_e$. These sum rules relate moments of hadronic structure functions, computed via the Operator Product Expansion, to hadronic matrix elements of relevant exclusive transitions. Truncating the hadronic side to include the lowest-lying charmed baryon states with spin-parity $ J^P = 1/2^+, 1/2^-, 3/2^- $, we employ the corresponding lattice QCD form factors near zero recoil as inputs. By analysing zeroth and higher moments, we derive inequalities that define an allowed region in the $(\hat{\mu}_\pi^2, \hat{\rho}_D^3)$ plane. The derived constraints are consistent, within uncertainties, with estimates from spectroscopic relations and the nonrelativistic constituent quark model. This work refines the determination of key HQE parameters for $\Lambda_b$, with implications for precision predictions of heavy baryon lifetimes and inclusive decays of heavy baryons in general.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05134v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bla\v{z}enka Meli\'c, Ivan Ni\v{s}and\v{z}i\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SUSY meets SMEFT: Complete one-loop matching of the general MSSM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05201v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the complete one-loop matching of the Minimal Supersymmetric Standard Model (MSSM) onto the Standard Model Effective Field Theory (SMEFT), considering the most general case for the MSSM with conserved $R$-parity, which has 124 free parameters. The matching is performed with the Matchete package, which integrates out all superpartners at once with non-degenerate masses, while also retaining the most general flavor structure. Our results include all correlations among the different SMEFT Wilson coefficients that are governed by supersymmetry and thus provide a basis for future systematic and global studies of the MSSM parameter space employing EFT methods. A detailed discussion is provided on the treatment of the Higgs sector and electroweak symmetry breaking, along with the reduction of redundant operators in the EFT Lagrangian to the Warsaw basis. Furthermore, we validate against existing results in the literature and present a minimal phenomenological example. Extensive auxiliary material, including the code utilized for the matching, is available on GitHub.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05201v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sabine Kraml, Andre Lessa, Suraj Prakash, Felix Wilsch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pion-Nucleon Scattering in Baryon Chiral Perturbation Theory combined with the ${ 1/N_c}$ Expansion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05224</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05224v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work implements the combined BChPT and $1/N_c$ expansions for pion-nucleon elastic scattering. The effective theory is based on the baryon sector dynamical spin-flavor $SU(4)$ symmetry emergent in the large $N_c$ limit, whose breaking in controlled by the $1/N_c$ expansion. The non-commutativity of the chiral and $1/N_c$ expansions in unitarity corrections (loops) requires a linking of both expansions. As it was shown in the case of baryon masses and currents, the natural linking is the $\xi$-expansion, in which ${\cal{O}}(p)={\cal{O}}(1/N_c)={\cal{O}}(\xi)$. The spin-flavor symmetry requires that the ground state baryons span an $SU(4)$ symmetric irreducible representation which implies that in particular $N$ and $\Delta$ are active degrees of freedom in the effective theory.
  The scattering amplitude is expanded to the next-to-next to leading order in the $\xi$ expansion, corresponding to the one-loop contributions with the LO Lagrangian. The results are given for generic $N_c$ in order to demonstrate the consistency of the framework. The spin-flavor symmetry plays a central role in maintaining the consistency of the effective theory with respect to the $1/N_c$ expansion. This consistency manifests itself in an improvement in the convergence of the low energy expansion with respect to the case of the ordinary BChPT without an explicit dynamical $\Delta$, which is known to be inconsistent the constraints of $N_c$ scaling.
  Fits to the $\pi N\to \pi N$ S, P and D partial wave amplitudes from the SAID data base are finally used to test the framework and to determine the energy range of its applicability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05224v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Jayakodige, J. L. Goity</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2024 TASI Lectures: A Dark Matter Primer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05234v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: These notes are based on a sequence of 4 lectures delivered at the 2024 Theoretical Advanced Study Institute (TASI) and at the Universit\`a degli Studi di Padova. They are intended for graduate students at the early stages of their study of dark matter with some prior exposure to cosmology and quantum field theory. The primary aim is to offer an accessible introduction to dark matter and to lay the groundwork for exploring its phenomenology. These lectures are not intended to serve as a comprehensive review. We begin by motivating the study of dark matter through a discussion of the empirical evidence and the constraints it places on dark matter properties. This is followed by an overview of several canonical mechanisms for the production of cosmological dark matter, and a concluding section that surveys current experimental and observational efforts to detect it with a focus on direct detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05234v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tien-Tien Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Closing in on singly charged scalars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05258</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05258v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate current experimental constraints and future search prospects for a hypothetical spin-zero particle that carries unit electric charge: a singly charged scalar (SCS). In addition to providing useful benchmarks for collider searches, SCS particles are also well-motivated ingredients in relatively minimal dark sectors. We focus on scenarios in which the SCS decays promptly at colliders to a lepton plus either a neutrino or an invisible dark-sector particle of negligible mass. A promptly decaying SCS can easily have appreciable branching ratios to more than one lepton flavor while remaining consistent with constraints on lepton flavor violation. This broadens the allowed range of SCS masses to extend well beyond those for right-handed selectrons, smuons, or staus. For particular benchmark SCS branching ratios, we find that SCS masses above ~185 GeV and in a lower-mass window ~80-125 GeV are still allowed at 95% confidence level. We carry out Monte Carlo simulations to explore the potential of a boosted-decision-tree-based analysis to probe the surviving SCS parameter space in future searches at the (HL-)LHC, finding a significant increase in sensitivity relative to cut-based analyses both in the lower-mass window and at higher SCS masses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05258v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Snehadri Das, Will Howe, Brian Shuve, David Tucker-Smith, Ruby Yager</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for Hidden Sector Particles at Neutrino Telescopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05326v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the possibility of directly detecting light, long-lived hidden sector particles at the IceCube neutrino telescope. Such particles frequently arise in non-minimal hidden sectors that couple to the Standard Model through portal operators. We consider two distinct scenarios. In the first scenario, which arises from a neutrino portal interaction, a hidden sector particle is produced inside the detector by the collision of an energetic neutrino with a nucleon, giving rise to a visible cascade. This new state then decays into a hidden sector daughter, which can naturally be long-lived. The eventual decay of the daughter particle back to Standard Model states gives rise to a second cascade inside the detector. This scenario therefore gives rise to a characteristic "double bang" signal arising from the two distinct cascades. In the second scenario, which arises from a hypercharge portal interaction, a hidden sector particle is produced outside the detector by the collision of an atmospheric muon with a nucleon. This new state promptly decays into a pair of hidden sector daughters that are long-lived. If both daughters decay into Standard Model states inside the detector, we again obtain a double-bang signal from the two distinct cascades. We explore the reach of IceCube for these two scenarios and show that it has the potential to significantly improve the sensitivity to hidden sector models in the mass range from about a GeV to about 20 GeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05326v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sagar Airen, Zackaria Chacko, Can Kilic, Ram Purandhar Reddy Sudha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Momentum fraction and hard scale dependence of double parton scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05337v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The effective cross section of double parton scattering in high-energy hadron collisions has been measured in proton--proton collisions, with significant variation among final-state observables, contrary to the idea of a universal value. Building upon our previous work, we incorporate the dependence on both the parton longitudinal momentum fraction $x$ and the process energy hard scale $\mu$ into the transverse part of the double parton distributions, using a Gaussian profile. Employing the experimental data from the LHC and Tevatron experiments (covering different processes, kinematic configurations, and center--of--mass energies), we perform a global fit of the model, extracting the parameters that describe the proton structure. With this result, it becomes possible to calculate the effective cross section for others observables, and we provide predictions for future measurements at the LHC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05337v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joao Vitor C. Lovato, Edgar Huayra, Emmanuel G. de Oliveira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cross-Section Bootstrap: Unveiling the Froissart Amplitude</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04313v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We derive a universal bound on the integrated total scattering cross-section at \emph{finite} energies, expressed in terms of a single low-energy coefficient constrained by the non-perturbative S-matrix Bootstrap. At high energies, the bound is compared with proton-proton scattering data; at low energies, with numerical bootstrap results obtained by directly maximizing the cross-section. We conjecture that the amplitude saturating the cross-section at high energies lies at a strongly-coupled corner of the allowed space of low-energy parameters. This universal amplitude exhibits a rising total cross-section, a shrinking elastic differential cross-section with multiple diffractive minima, and a surprisingly rich spectrum of resonances aligning along Regge trajectories, including Pomeron-like and daughter trajectories, as well as unusual ``singular" trajectories in the forward limit which appear deeply interconnected with Froissart growth. Remarkably, the eikonal representation reveals that the scattering is localized within an annular region that slowly expands with energy, challenging the traditional ``disk" diffraction picture. Our results open the door to theoretical and phenomenological studies of \emph{soft} high-energy hadronic scattering via the S-matrix Bootstrap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04313v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Correia, Alessandro Georgoudis, Andrea L. Guerrieri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discretely Evanescent Dark Energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04317v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a new UV-complete dark energy model which is \underbar{\it neither} a cosmological constant nor a slowly rolling scalar field. Our dark energy is the flux of a top form in a hidden sector gauge theory similar to QCD. The top form controls the vacuum energy generated by dark sector CP violation. Its flux discharges by the nucleation of membranes that source it. The tension and charge of the membranes are set by the chiral symmetry breaking scale $\sim 10^{-3} eV$, and the dark energy is a transient. It decays on the order of the current age of the universe. The decays decrease dark energy discretely and randomly, instead of gradually like rolling scalars. Since the decay rate is close to the present Hubble scale, $\Gamma \ga H_0^4$, in a time $\sim {\cal O}(1/H_0)$ the cosmic acceleration may even cease altogether.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04317v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nemanja Kaloper</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Nonperturbative Hilbert Space of Quantum Gravity With One Boundary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04319v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We discuss a basis for the nonperturbative Hilbert space of quantum gravity with one asymptotic boundary. We use this basis to show that the Hilbert space for gravity with two disconnected boundaries factorizes into a product of two copies of the single boundary Hilbert space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04319v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vijay Balasubramanian, Tom Yildirim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncalibrated Cosmic Standards as a Robust Test on Late-Time Cosmological Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04333v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a minimally model-dependent framework for testing late-time cosmological models using Uncalibrated Cosmic Standards (UCS), including standard rulers and standard candles, without relying on absolute calibrations. The method exploits a tight, model-insensitive correlation between the sound horizons at recombination and the drag epoch. By avoiding dependence on pre-recombination physics and the amplitude of the Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) power spectra, the UCS framework reduces potential early-time biases while retaining much of the constraining power of full analyses. Applying UCS to the recent dynamical dark energy (DE) study that reported deviations from $\Lambda$CDM, we find the constraints shift systematically toward the $\Lambda$CDM case, suggesting the present of pre-recombination physics or systematics that likely affect the scale-dependence of the CMB spectra. We also observe a mild tension between uncalibrated standard rulers and candles, which can be largely mitigated by introducing a redshift-dependent magnitude bias in the supernova (SNe Ia) data. Our results highlights the importance of isolating post-recombination observables for testing late-time models in the era of precision cosmology, positioning UCS analysis as a robust framework for upcoming galaxy surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04333v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yihao Wang, Weikang Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical evolution of self-gravitating halos of self-interacting dark matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04334</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04334v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We discuss a modification of a recently developed numerical scheme for evolving spherically symmetric self-gravitating systems to include the effects of self-interacting dark matter. The approach is far more efficient than traditional N-body simulations and cross sections with different dependencies on velocity and scattering-angle are easily accommodated. To demonstrate, we provide results of a simulation, which runs quickly on a personal computer, that shows the expected initial flattening of the inner region of an NFW halo as well as the later gravothermal collapse instability that leads to a dense core at the galactic center. We note that this approach can also be used, with some augmentation, to simulate the dynamics in globular clusters by modeling gravitational hard scattering as a self-interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04334v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marc Kamionkowski, Kris Sigurdson, Oren Slone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The quark-gluon plasma: diagnosis with thermal hadron production from the early history until detailed characterization at high energy colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04733</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04733v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In nuclear collisions at relativistic energies, matter is created which resembles closely the matter that filled all space until about 15 microseconds after the big bang. Here we summarize selected aspects of the research that led to the establishment of this new sub-field of physics and briefly describe its current `state of the art' with emphasis on matter creation through thermal particle production. In particular, we will focus on particle production at low transverse momentum and explain how its analysis sheds light on one of the key open questions, i.e. what is the mechanism of hadronization of colored objects such as quarks and gluons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04733v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Braun-Munzinger, Krzysztof Redlich, Johanna Stachel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Ultralight Axion-like Dark Matter $-$ A PTA-PPA Synergy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04871v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ultralight axion-like dark matter (ALDM) is a leading candidate in the dark matter realm, characterized by its prominent wave properties on astronomical scales. Pulsar Timing Arrays (PTAs) and Pulsar Polarization Arrays (PPAs) aim to detect this dark matter through timing and polarization measurements, respectively, of pulsars. The PTA relies on gravitational effects, as the ALDM halo perturbs the spacetime metric within the Milky Way, while the PPA detects non-gravitational effects, namely cosmological birefringence induced by the ALDM Chern-Simons coupling with photons. These two methods complement each other, synergistically enhancing the pulsar array's capability to identify the ALDM signals in the data. In this article, we provide a foundational development of this synergy. We begin by revisiting previously derived two-point correlation functions for both PTA and PPA, and expand our analysis to include correlations between timing and polarization signals. We then construct likelihood functions for PTA and combined PTA-PPA analyses within a Bayesian framework, aimed at detecting the characteristic correlations of ALDM signals. We emphasize the non-Gaussianity of the ALDM timing signals, which arises from their non-linear dependence on the field, in contrast to the Gaussian nature of its polarization signals. To address the complexities introduced, we approach this investigation in two ways: one involves a Gaussian approximation with proper justifications, while the other derives the formalism from the generic Gaussian characteristics of the ALDM field. We anticipate that these efforts will lead to further developments in PTA and PTA-PPA analysis methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04871v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ximeng Li, Yonghao Liu, Zu-Cheng Chen, Shi Dai, Boris Goncharov, Xiao-Song Hu, Qing-Guo Huang, Tao Liu, Jing Ren, Yu-Mei Wu, Xiao Xue, Xingjiang Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On internal mechanical properties of Electroweak Magnetic Monopoles and their effects on stability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04872v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: By considering properties of the energy-momentum tensor of the electroweak magnetic monopole and its Born-Infeld extension, we attempt to make comments on the stability of these configurations. Specifically, we perform a study of the behaviour of the so-called internal force and pressure of these extended field-theoretic solitonic objects, which are derived from the energy-momentum tensor. Our method is slightly different from the so-called Laue's criterion for stability of nuclear matter, a local form of which had been proposed and applied in the earlier literature to the `t Hooft-Polyakov (HP) magnetic monopole, and found to be violated.By applying our method first to HP monopole, we also observe that, despite its topological stability, the total (finite) internal force (which has only radial components) is directed inwards, towards the centre of the monopole, which would imply instability. Thus this mechanical criterion for stability is arguably violated in the case of the HP monopole, as is the local version of Laue's criterion. The criterion is satisfied for the short-range part of the energy momentum tensor, in which the long-range part, due to the massless photon of the U(1) subgroup, is subtracted. Par contrast, the total internal force of the Cho-Maison (CM) electroweak monopole has both radial and angular components, which diverge at the origin, leading to rotational instabilities. Finally, by studying finite-energy extensions of the CM, either with non-minimal Higgs couplings with the hypercharge sector or hypercharge Born-Infeld type models, we find that the total force, integrated over space, is finite, but it has also angular components in the Born-Infeld case. The latter feature is interpreted as indicating that the Born-Infeld-CM monopole might be subject to rotations upon the action of perturbations, but it does not necessarily imply instabilities of the configuration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04872v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Farakos, G. Koutsoumbas, Nick E. Mavromatos, Alexandros Zarafonitis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gauge-invariant field strengths in $QCD$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04988</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04988v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Gauge-invariant field strengths, defined as parallel transports to infinity of ordinary field strengths, naturally emerge in a few physical phenomena governed by $QCD$. One of them is confinement of colour. Despite the arbitrariness in their definition coming from the freedom in the choice of the path of the parallel transport to infinity, the request of differentiability with respect to the position $x$ strongly constrains their correlation functions. Strong constraints also come from translation and Lorentz invariance. Gauge invariant field strengths also appear in the non abelian Stokes theorem, and allow to understand basic properties of the vacuum by use of lattice data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04988v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adriano Di Giacomo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Parton Distributions of Hadrons with Lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05025v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The strong force which binds hadrons is described by the theory of quantum chromodynamics (QCD). Determining the character and manifestations of QCD is one of the most important and challenging outstanding issues necessary for a comprehensive understanding of the structure of hadrons. Within the context of the QCD parton picture, the parton distribution functions (PDFs) have been remarkably successful in describing a wide variety of processes. However, these PDFs have generally been confined to the description of collinear partons within the hadron. New experiments and facilities provide the opportunity to additionally explore the three-dimensional structure of hadrons, which can be described by generalized parton distributions (GPDs), for example. In recent years, a breakthrough was made in calculating the Bjorken-$x$ dependence of PDFs in lattice QCD by using large-momentum effective theory (LaMET) and other similar frameworks. The breakthrough has led to the emergence and rapid development of direct calculations of Bjorken-$x$--dependent structure. In this review article, we show some of the recent progress made in lattice QCD in PDFs and GPDs and discuss future challenges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05025v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.ppnp.2025.104177</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Prog. Part. Nucl. Phys. 144 (2025) 104177</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Huey-Wen Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffeomorphism invariance of the effective gravitational action</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05100v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate on the diffeomorphism invariance of the effective gravitational action, focusing in particular on the path integral measure. In the literature, two different measures are mainly considered, the Fradkin-Vilkovisky and the Fujikawa one. With the help of detailed calculations, we show that, despite claims to the contrary, the Fradkin-Vilkovisky measure is diffeomorphism invariant, while the Fujikawa measure is not. In particular, we see that, contrary to naive expectations, the presence of $g^{00}$ factors in the Fradkin-Vilkovisky measure is necessary to ensure the invariance of the effective gravitational action. We also comment on results recently appeared in the literature, and show that formal calculations can easily miss delicate points.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05100v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlo Branchina, Vincenzo Branchina, Filippo Contino, Riccardo Gandolfo, Arcangelo Pernace</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous dimensions at small spins</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05132v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In perturbation theory, the anomalous dimensions of twist-two operators have poles at negative or small positive integer values of spin and therefore must be resummed at these points. It was observed earlier that a certain quadratic combination of the anomalous dimensions remains finite at the right-most singularities, providing an efficient tool for resummation. In this paper, we analyze the small-spin behavior of the anomalous dimensions for all types of twist-two operators in the $O(N)$-symmetric $\varphi^4$ model at the four-loop level, in the complex $\varphi^3$ model at the three-loop level, and the Gross-Neveu-Yukawa model at the two-loop level. We find that the behavior of the anomalous dimensions at singular points is consistent with theoretical expectations, and we present expressions for the resummed anomalous dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05132v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. N. Manashov, S. Moch, L. A. Shumilov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection Prospects of Millicharged Dark Matter in Unconventional Interferometer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04788v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a novel idea to discover millicharged particles (mCPs) captured by the earth during its existence. It has been demonstrated that the mCPs accumulation inside the earth leads to the enhancement of its number density much larger than the corresponding virial density. We propose to utilize an unconventional laser interferometer to probe these earth-bound mCPs through the detection of the photons's phase shift. We demonstrate that, for mCPs mass in the range between $1$ GeV to $10^{12}$ GeV, the sensitivity of probing their fractional electric charge $\epsilon$ could reach as low as $10^{-12}$ to $10^{-6}$ provided that mCPs number density is greater than $1~\text{cm}^{-3}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04788v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chrisna Setyo Nugroho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Establishing CP Violation in $b$-Baryon Decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02821v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is a long-standing puzzle why the {\it CP} violation (CPV) in the baryon system has not yet been definitively established as in the meson one. We demonstrate that individual partial-wave CPV in the $\Lambda_b\to p\pi^-$ and $pK^-$ decays can exceed $10\%$, but the destruction between the partial waves (the suppression by the small partial-wave weight) results in a small net direct CPV in the former (the latter) as measured currently. Our finding highlights the different dynamics responsible for CPVs in baryon and meson decays. We propose to probe the CPV observables associated with the angular distributions of the $\Lambda_b\to pa_1(1260)$, $pK_1(1270)$ decay products, which are large enough for being identified experimentally.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02821v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Jie Han, Ji-Xin Yu, Ya Li, Hsiang-nan Li, Jian-Peng Wang, Zhen-Jun Xiao, Fu-Sheng Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radiative corrections and Monte Carlo tools for low-energy hadronic cross sections in $e^+ e^-$ collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22882v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the results of Phase I of an ongoing review of Monte Carlo tools relevant for low-energy hadronic cross sections. This includes a detailed comparison of Monte Carlo codes for electron-positron scattering into a muon pair, pion pair, and electron pair, for scan and radiative-return experiments. After discussing the various approaches that are used and effects that are included, we show differential cross sections obtained with AfkQed, BabaYaga@NLO, KKMC, MCGPJ, McMule, Phokhara, and Sherpa, for scenarios that are inspired by experiments providing input for the dispersive evaluation of the hadronic vacuum polarisation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22882v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riccardo Aliberti, Paolo Beltrame, Ettore Budassi, Carlo M. Carloni Calame, Gilberto Colangelo, Lorenzo Cotrozzi, Achim Denig, Anna Driutti, Tim Engel, Lois Flower, Andrea Gurgone, Martin Hoferichter, Fedor Ignatov, Sophie Kollatzsch, Bastian Kubis, Andrzej Kup\'s\'c, Fabian Lange, Alberto Lusiani, Stefan E. M\"uller, J\'er\'emy Paltrinieri, Pau Petit Ros\`as, Fulvio Piccinini, Alan Price, Lorenzo Punzi, Marco Rocco, Olga Shekhovtsova, Andrzej Si\'odmok, Adrian Signer, Giovanni Stagnitto, Peter Stoffer, Thomas Teubner, William J. Torres Bobadilla, Francesco P. Ucci, Yannick Ulrich, Graziano Venanzoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Form factors of light pseudoscalar mesons from the perturbative QCD approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08783v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the electromagnetic and meson-photon transition form factors (TFF) of light pseudoscalar mesons from the perturbative QCD (pQCD) approach. To comprehensively account for both the longitudinal and transverse nonperturbative dynamics of hadronic constituents, we incorpoarate intrinsic transverse momentum distributions (iTMDs) alongside the conventional light-cone distribution amplitudes (LCDAs). The main motivations of this work are the disjointedness of electromagnetic form factors between the theoretical predictions and the experimental measurements, and the BaBar-Belle tension of pion-photon transition form factor in the large momentum transfers. Our calculation is carried out at the next-to-leading-order for the contributions from leading and subleading twist LCDAs, and leading order for the twist four contributions. Notably, this work presents the first systematic evaluation of higher-twist contributions to meson-photon TFFs. The key findings are: (a) iTMDs play a crucial role in describing form factor data, particularly in the small-to-intermediate momentum transfer region where they induce significant modifications to pQCD predictions. (b) The extracted transverse size parameters for valence quark states are found to be $\beta_\pi^2 = 0.51 \pm 0.04$ GeV$^{-2}$ and $\beta_K^2 = 0.30 \pm 0.05$ GeV$^{-2}$, the chiral mass of pion meson $m_0^\pi$ at $1$ GeV is determined to be $1.84 \pm 0.07$ GeV. (c) The meson-photon TFFs are predominantly governed by leading-twist LCDAs. The iTMDs-enhanced pQCD results show better agreement with Belle's pion TFF data across intermediate and large momentum transfers and favor a small $\eta-\eta^\prime$ mixing angle. (d) Remarkably, the inclusion of iTMDs extends the applicability of pQCD calculations down to a few GeV$^2$ for all considered form factors, significantly improving the theory-data consistency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08783v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian Chai, Shan Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feasibility study of true muonium observation with the existing Belle-II dataset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17753v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: True muonium ($\mu^+\mu^-$) is one of the cleanest bound states, being composed only of leptons, along with true tauonium and positronium. Unlike the latter, true muonium and true tauonium have not been observed so far. This article shows that the spin-0 state of true muonium (para-TM), decaying into two photons, can be observed at a discovery level of significance in the dataset already collected by the Belle-II experiment at the $\Upsilon (4S)$ peak, with certain assumptions on systematic uncertainties. Para-TM is produced via photon-photon fusion, and its observation is based on the detection of the photon pair resulting from its decay, on top of the continuum background due predominantly to light-by-light scattering. Trigger, acceptance and isolation cuts, along with calorimeter resolution and reconstruction efficiency, are taken into account during the Monte Carlo simulation of both signal and background. In order to separate signal and background, a machine learning method, based on extremely randomized trees, is trained on simulated events. Finally, the expected statistical significance of TM observation is evaluated, taking into account systematic uncertainties in a parametric fashion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17753v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruben Gargiulo, Elisa Di Meco, Stefano Palmisano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Type-II Seesaw Mechanism for Dirac Neutrinos and its Implications on $N_{\text{eff}}$ and Lepton Flavor Violation in a 3-3-1 model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01760v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study, we implement the type-II seesaw mechanism for Dirac neutrino masses within the framework of a 3-3-1 model. To this end, we introduce a scalar sextet and impose both lepton number conservation and invariance under a discrete $Z_2$ symmetry in the Lagrangian. This mechanism naturally generates small Dirac neutrino masses by allowing the soft breaking of the $Z_2$ symmetry through a unique term in the scalar potential, while preserving lepton number. Specifically, we explore the realization of this model at low-energy scales. Regarding flavor implications, we analyze its contributions to the rare decay processes $\mu \to e \gamma$ and $\mu \to \bar e ee$. In the cosmological context, we analyze the influence of right-handed neutrinos on the effective number of neutrino species, $N_\text{eff}$, through interactions mediated by the $Z^{\prime}$ boson. Our findings establish a lower bound of $m_{Z^{\prime}} &gt; 4.4$ TeV, which slightly exceeds the current lower limit set by the Large Hadron Collider (LHC).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01760v5</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vin\'icius Oliveira, Patricio Escalona, Lucia Angel, C. A. de S. Pires, Farinaldo S. Queiroz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin 1 Transverse Momentum Dependent Tensor Structure Functions in CLAS12</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20044</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20044v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose to analyze CLAS12 RG-C data to study the tensor transverse-momentum-dependent parton distribution functions (TMDs) on deuteron data. The deuteron is the lightest nucleus with spin-1, in essence a weakly bound system of two spin-1/2 nucleons. However, one of the most intriguing characteristics of the deuteron is that the tensor polarized structure provides direct access to the quark and gluon distribution of light nuclear system, which cannot be naively constructed from the proton and neutron. We will study the tensor polarized structure functions with the Semi-inclusive Deep Inelastic Scattering (SIDIS) $eD \arrow eP_{h}X$ and Inclusive processes in the available data on deuterated ammonia (ND3) target. We will perform the first ever SIDIS analysis extraction of the tensor structure functions, which can be interpreted in term of completely unexplored tensor polarized TMDs. Our analysis will focus on the extraction of the tensor structure functions b1 from inclusive process, and $F_{U(LL),T}$ and $F^{cos 2\phi_{h}}_{U(LL)}$ from SIDIS. These last two structure functions carry information related to two tensor-polarized TMDs, $f_{1LL}$ and $h^{\perp}_{1LL}$. These initial exploratory measurements of tensor-polarized structure functions will enable the first extraction of spin-1 TMDs and motivate more precise future measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20044v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiwan Poudel, Alessandro Bacchetta, Jian-Ping Chen, Dustin Keller, Ishara Fernando, Elena Long, David Ruth, Nathaly Santiesteban, Kalf Slifer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inclusive $\mathrm{D}^0$ photoproduction in ultraperipheral collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16108</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16108v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We compute the differential cross section for inclusive $\mathrm{D}^0$ production in ultraperipheral collisions within the Color Glass Condensate framework. Our predictions are found to be in relatively good agreement with the CMS data at small transverse momentum, which is the region of validity of our approach. Furthermore, we quantify saturation effects by a nuclear modification ratio $R_{pA}$ for $\mathrm{D}^0$ photoproduction and examine both analytically and numerically the collinear factorization limit of the $\mathrm{D}^0$ differential photoproduction cross section.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16108v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patricia Gimeno-Estivill, Tuomas Lappi, Heikki M\"antysaari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monte Carlo phase space integration of multiparticle cross sections with carlomat_4.5</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.00155v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Multidimensional phase space integrals must be calculated in order to obtain predictions for total or differential cross sections, or to simulate unweighted events of multiparticle reactions. The corresponding matrix elements, already in the leading order, receive contributions typically from dozens of thousands of the Feynman diagrams, many of which often involve strong peaks due to denominators of some Feynman propagators approaching their minima. As the number of peaks exceeds by far the number of integration variables, such integrals can practically be performed within the multichannel Monte Carlo approach, with different phase space parameterizations, each designed to smooth possibly a few peaks at a time. This obviously requires a lot different phase space parameterizations which, if possible, should be generated and combined in a single multichannel Monte Carlo procedure in a fully automatic way.A few different approaches to the calculation of the multidimensional phase space integrals have been incorporated in version 4.5 of the multipurpose Monte Carlo program carlomat. The present work illustrates how carlomat_4.5 can facilitate the challenging task of calculating the multidimensional phase space integrals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.00155v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karol Kolodziej</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Axion Superradiance in Dipole Magnetic Fields of Pulsars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.04209v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider constraints on the axion-photon coupling by superradiance due to a plasma instability in the magnetospheres of millisecond pulsars. We compute the growth rate of a superradiant axion cloud in a dipole magnetic field, and give a semi-analytical formula for the superradiance rate for the lowest state. By requiring the associated instability time to be longer than the characteristic age of the supermassive black-widow millisecond pulsar PSR J0952-0607, we examine the pulsar-timing array constraints on axions of mass $\sim 10^{-12}\text{ eV}$. We find that competitive axion bounds from plasma instabilities are unlikely unless a new high spin pulsar is discovered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.04209v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Topi Sirki\"a, Matti Heikinheimo, Kimmo Tuominen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A search for $B_{s0}^{*}$ and $B^{*}_{s1}$ through the $K^{-}p$ interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.18019v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The formation and properties of hadrons, particularly those involving heavy quarks, remain a central topic in particle physics due to the nonperturbative nature of Quantum Chromodynamics (QCD) at low energies. Heavy-quark symmetry (HQS) provides a valuable framework for understanding the behavior of heavy quarks in hadronic systems, offering insights into spin and flavor symmetries. However, discrepancies between HQS predictions and experimental observations -- particularly the absence of predicted $B^{(*)}\bar{K}$ molecular states, which should be the bottom counterparts of the observed $\bar{D}^{(*)}\bar{K}$ molecular states (corresponding to $D_{s0}^*(2317)^-$ and $D^*_{s1}(2460)^{-}$) -- challenge its universality. This study investigates the production of the $B_{s0}^{*}(5725)$ and $B_{s1}^{*}(5778)$ states, interpreted as molecular states containing $B\bar{K}$ and $B^{*}\bar{K}$ components, through the reactions $K^{-}p \to \Lambda_{b}^{0}B_{s0}^{*}$ and $K^{-}p \to \Lambda_{b}^{0}B_{s1}^{*}$. Using effective Lagrangians, we analyze the cross sections, incorporating $t$-channel $B^{(*)}$ meson exchanges and $K^{-}p$ initial-state interactions (ISI). Our results reveal significant ISI enhancements and energy-dependent production thresholds, with $B_{s0}^{*}(5725)$ exhibiting higher cross sections than $B_{s1}^{*}(5778)$. We suggest that the $B_{s0}^{*}(5725)$ state can be optimally searched for at beam energies around $12.90\,\mathrm{GeV}$ (or $12.93\,\mathrm{GeV}$), while the $B_{s1}^{*}(5778)$ state requires significantly higher energies for its production. These findings provide valuable guidance for experimental searches at facilities like CERN and J-PARC, offering a pathway to test HQS and explore the nature of exotic hadrons. The differences in production cross sections between molecular states and conventional quark-antiquark structures are also compared.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.18019v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Min Yuan, Yin Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semileptonic Decays of $D \to \rho l^+ \nu$ and $D_{(s)} \to K^\ast l^+ \nu$ from Light-Cone Sum Rules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01329v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the semileptonic decays of charmed mesons to light vector mesons within the framework of light-cone sum rules. Our calculation is performed at leading order in QCD coupling, incorporating contributions up to twist-five accuracy from both two-particle and three-particle light-cone distribution amplitudes. Transition form factors are predicted twist by twist to assess the convergence property of the operator product expansion. It is verified that the twist-four and twist-five contributions are indeed negligible for all the decays under consideration. Twist-three dominance is observed for some of the form factors, subject to heavy quark effective field theory interpretation. Branching ratios for the decays $D^+ \to \rho^0 \ell^+\nu_\ell$ , $D_s^+ \to K^{\ast0} \ell^+\nu_\ell$, $D^0 \to K^{\ast-} \ell^+\nu_\ell$ and $D^+ \to \bar{K}^{\ast0} \ell^+\nu_\ell$ are obtained, and a $10\%$--$20\%$ discrepancy from experimental measurements is found. Our finding indicates that the resonant-width and non-resonant QCD backgrounds effects should be potentially significant, implying the necessity to further implement their contributions in future precision studies of the semileptonic charm decays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01329v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wang Lin, Xiao-En Huang, Shan Cheng, De-Liang Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study of Heavy Hadron Production in Au + Au Collisions at a Center-of-Mass Energy of $\sqrt{s_{NN}}=200$ GeV</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03264v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Using the Monte Carlo HYDJET++ model, the transverse momentum ($p_{T}$) spectra of heavy hadrons ($D^{0}$, $\overline{D}^{0}$, $D^{+}$, $D^{-}$ and $\Lambda_{c}$), as well as the nuclear modification factors of $D^{0}$ and $D^{\pm}$, produced in Au + Au collisions at $\sqrt{s_{NN}} = 200$ GeV RHIC energy across various centrality bins, are presented. This study is motivated by the need to understand the centrality dependence of the charm enhancement factor ($\gamma_{c}$) and the roles of different hadronization mechanisms such as coalescence and fragmentation, in charm hadron production. To achieve the best description of heavy hadron production, several input parameters in both the soft and hard components of the model are tuned. The study finds a decreasing trend of $\gamma_{c}$ from central to peripheral collisions and a mass dependence across charm hadrons. Moreover, the model effectively reproduces experimental data of $p_{T}$ spectra at low and intermediate $p_{T}$, capturing key features of charm hadron production in the quark-gluon plasma medium. However, it overpredicts the data at high $p_{T}$, indicating the need for improvements in modeling heavy quark energy loss mechanisms. Further, the nuclear modification factors ($R_{AA}$ and $R_{CP}$) for $D^{0}$ mesons exhibit significant suppression in central collisions, which matches with experimental observations. This highlights the roles of collisional and radiative energy loss due to collective effects, such as coalescence and radial flow. The antiparticle-to-particle and mixed particle ratios are also presented, showing good agreement with experimental data and revealing limitations in baryon production due to the absence of heavy quark coalescence in HYDJET++.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03264v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sunidhi Saxena, Rajiv Gupta, Gauri Devi, Ajay Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Validity of a finite temperature expansion for dense nuclear matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01658</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01658v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work we provide a new, well-controlled expansion of the equation of state of dense matter from zero to finite temperatures ($T$) while covering a wide range of charge fractions ($Y_Q$), from pure neutron to isospin symmetric nuclear matter. Our expansion can be used to describe neutron star mergers using the equation of state inferred from neutron star observations. We discuss how knowledge from low-energy nuclear experiments and heavy-ion collisions can be directly incorporated into the expansion. We also suggest new thermodynamic quantities of interest that can be calculated from theoretical models or directly inferred by experimental data that can be used to infer the finite temperature equation of state. With our new method, we can quantify the uncertainty in our finite $T$ and $Y_Q$ expansions without making assumptions about the underlying degrees of freedom. We can reproduce results from a microscopic equation of state up to $T=100$ MeV for baryon chemical potential $\mu_B\gtrsim 1100$ MeV ($\sim1-2 \ n_{\rm sat}$) within $5\%$ error, with even better results for larger $\mu_B$ and/or lower $T$. We investigate the sources of numerical and theoretical uncertainty and discuss future directions of study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01658v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debora Mroczek, Nanxi Yao, Katherine Zine, Jacquelyn Noronha-Hostler, Liam Brodie, Veronica Dexheimer, Alexander Haber, Elias R. Most</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy Density Functional of Confined Quarks: an Improved Ansatz</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.01814v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Density Functional Theory (DFT) is a robust framework for modeling interacting many-body systems, including the equation of state (EoS) of dense matter. Many models, however, rely on energy functionals based on assumptions that have not been rigorously validated. We critically analyze a commonly used ansatz for confinement, where the energy functional scales with density as $U \propto n^{\frac{2}{3}}$ . Our findings, derived from a systematic non-local energy functional, reveal that this scaling does not capture the dynamics of confinement. Instead, the energy functional evolves from $n^2$ at low densities to $n$ at high densities, governed by an infrared cutoff. These results suggest that models relying on such assumptions should be revisited to ensure more reliable EoS construction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.01814v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Udita Shukla, Pok Man Lo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Assessing cosmological evidence for non-minimal coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07679</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.07679v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The recent observational evidence of deviations from the $\Lambda$-Cold Dark Matter ($\Lambda$CDM) model points towards the presence of evolving dark energy. The simplest possibility consists of a cosmological scalar field $\varphi$, dubbed quintessence, driving the accelerated expansion. We assess the evidence for the existence of such a scalar field. We find that, if the accelerated expansion is driven by quintessence, the data favour a potential energy $V(\varphi)$ that is concave, i.e., $m^2=d^2V/d\varphi^2&lt;0$. Furthermore, and more significantly, the data strongly favour a scalar field that is non-minimally coupled to gravity (Bayes factor $\log(B) = 7.34 \pm 0.6$), leading to time variations in the gravitational constant on cosmological scales, and the existence of fifth forces on smaller scales. The fact that we do not observe such fifth forces implies that either new physics must come into play on non-cosmological scales or that quintessence is an unlikely explanation for the observed cosmic acceleration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.07679v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William J. Wolf, Carlos Garc\'ia-Garc\'ia, Theodore Anton, Pedro G. Ferreira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black holes with electroweak hair -- the detailed derivation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09304v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a very detailed derivation of solutions describing hairy black holes within the gravity-coupled Weinberg-Salam theory, which were previously reported in \href{https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.171402}{Phys.Rev.Lett. 133 (2024) 171402}. These black holes support a strong magnetic field that polarizes the electroweak vacuum and creates a condensate of massive fields carrying superconducting currents along the black hole horizon. The currents, in turn, generate a ``corona'' of magnetic vortex segments attached to the horizon at both ends. The condensate and corona together constitute the black hole hair. The extremal solutions approach, in the far field, the magnetic Reissner-Nordstr\"om configuration, with a total mass that is {\it lower} than the total charge, $M&lt;|Q|$, due to the negative Zeeman energy of the condensate. This makes the removal of the hair energetically unfavorable. The maximally hairy black holes exhibit masses comparable to terrestrial values, with approximately 11\% of their total mass stored in the hair. Given that these solutions arise within a well-tested theoretical framework, they are likely to have physical relevance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09304v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Romain Gervalle, Mikhail S. Volkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predictability of quantum observables: Applications in QKD and top quarks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24502v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We quantify and optimize the predictability of local observables in bipartite quantum systems by employing the Bayes risk and the inference variance, two measures rooted in statistical learning theory. Specifically, we minimized these quantities when the prediction is improved by an additional quantum system, providing analytical expressions for arbitrary two-qubit states, and showcasing a connection with Einstein-Podolsky-Rosen steering criteria. Then, we embed our Bayes risk minimization into an entanglement-based quantum key distribution protocol, yielding asymptotically higher secure-key rates than standard BB84 under realistic noise. We applied these results to Bell states affected by local amplitude-damping noises, and spin correlation in top-antitop quark pairs from high-energy collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24502v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dennis I. Mart\'inez-Moreno, Miguel Castillo-Celeita, Diego G. Bussandri</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
