<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph</link>
    <description>hep-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 01:52:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Isospin sum rules for bottom-baryon weak decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13527v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Isospin symmetry, as the most precise flavor symmetry, can be used to extract information about hadronic dynamics. The effective Hamiltonian operators of bottom quark weak decays are zero under a series of isospin lowering operators $I_-^n$, which permits us to generate isospin sum rules without the Wigner-Eckhart invariants. In this work, we derive hundreds of isospin sum rules for the two- and three-body non-leptonic decays of bottom baryons. They provide hints for new decay modes and the isospin partners of pentaquark states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13527v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Chen Fu, Si-Jia Wen, Di Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a Robust Exclusion of the Sterile-Neutrino Explanation of Short-Baseline Anomalies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13594v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The sterile neutrino interpretation of the LSND and MiniBooNE neutrino anomalies is currently being tested at three Liquid Argon detectors: MicroBooNE, SBND, and ICARUS. It has been argued that a degeneracy between $\nu_\mu \to \nu_e$ and $\nu_e \to \nu_e$ oscillations significantly degrades their sensitivity to sterile neutrinos. Through an independent study, we show two methods to eliminate this concern. First, we resolve this degeneracy by including external constraints on $\nu_e$ disappearance from the PROSPECT reactor experiment. Second, by properly analyzing the full three-dimensional parameter space, we demonstrate that the stronger-than-sensitivity exclusion from MicroBooNE alone already covers the entire 2$\sigma$ preferred regions of MiniBooNE at the level of $2-3\sigma$. We show that upcoming searches at SBND and ICARUS can improve on this beyond the $4\sigma$ level, thereby providing a rigorous test of short-baseline anomalies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13594v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ohana Benevides Rodrigues, Matheus Hostert, Kevin J. Kelly, Bryce Littlejohn, Pedro A. N. Machado, Ibrahim Safa, Tao Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite-temperature bubble nucleation with shifting scale hierarchies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13597v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Focusing on supercooled phase transitions in models with classical scale symmetry, we formulate a state-of-the art framework for computing the bubble-nucleation rate, accounting for the presence of various energy scales. In particular, we examine the limitations of derivative expansions in constructing a thermal effective field theory for bubble nucleation. We show that for gauge field fluctuations, derivative expansions diverge after the leading two orders due to the strong variation in gauge field masses between the high- and low-temperature phases. By directly computing these contributions using the fluctuation determinant, we capture these effects while also accounting for large explicit logarithms at two loops, utilising the exact renormalisation group structure of the EFT. Finally, we demonstrate how this approach significantly improves nucleation rate calculations compared to leading-order results, providing a more robust framework for predicting gravitational-wave signals from supercooled phase transitions in models such as the SU(2)cSM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13597v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maciej Kierkla, Philipp Schicho, Bogumila Swiezewska, Tuomas V. I. Tenkanen, Jorinde van de Vis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct Detection of Fast-Moving Low-Mass Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13598v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We examine the signals produced by dark matter interactions with electrons, which play a crucial role in direct detection experiments employing heavy target materials, particularly in many well-motivated sub-GeV dark matter scenarios. When the momentum transfer to target electrons is comparable to or exceeds their binding energy, atomic effects related to electron ionization become essential for accurately determining signal rates - especially in the case of fast-moving dark matter. In this paper, we revisit and extend the atomic ionization formalism, systematically comparing different approaches used to formulate the ionization form factor and identifying their respective domains of validity. As practical applications, we explore detection prospects in xenon target experiments. To illustrate our findings, we consider a specific scenario involving boosted dark matter, which often leads to high-momentum electron recoils. Our analysis demonstrates that the choice of formalism can significantly influence the interpretation of experimental data, depending on the regions of parameter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13598v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haider Alhazmi, Doojin Kim, Kyoungchul Kong, Gopolang Mohlabeng, Jong-Chul Park, Seodong Shin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissecting Jet Modification in the QGP with Multi-Point Energy Correlators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13603v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Energy correlators have recently attracted significant attention in the study of heavy ion collisions due to their potential to robustly connect experimental measurements with an underlying quantum field theoretic description. While theoretical studies have so far primarily focused on the simplest two-point correlator, mapping out the dynamics of the quark-gluon plasma (QGP) will require developing a theoretical understanding of multi-point energy correlators. In this paper we present a systematic theoretical study of multi-point energy correlators for jets fragmenting in a dense quark-gluon plasma, accounting for both the medium's perturbative modification to the jet, and its hydrodynamical back-reaction. We consider both the scaling behavior of projected correlators, as well as the shape dependent three-point correlator, highlighting how both provide insight into interactions with the QGP. We discuss the parametric dependence of modifications on the medium scales, opening new opportunities to experimentally separate jet modifications from the medium response. Our results open the door to a systematic exploration of multi-point energy correlators in heavy ion collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13603v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jo\~ao Barata, Ian Moult, Andrey V. Sadofyev, Jo\~ao M. Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supernova Gamma-Ray Constraints from Heavy Sterile Neutrino Decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13607v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Heavy sterile neutrinos can be produced in core-collapse supernovae (CCSNe), which are superb particle generators because of their high densities and temperatures. If the sterile neutrinos are long-lived, these may be produced inside the supernova core and escape the stellar envelope, later decaying into SM particles like photons and neutrinos. In this work, we first improve the calculation of the $\gamma$-ray fluxes. We then revisit the bounds on the sterile neutrino parameter space from the non-observation of $\gamma$-rays from SN1987A by the Solar Maximum Mission (SMM) and constraints from the diffuse $\gamma$-ray background arising from sterile neutrino decays. We find that the constraints arising from both the SMM data and the diffuse $\gamma$-ray background are weaker than those that have previously appeared in the literature. Finally, we study the sensitivity of several present and near-future $\gamma$-ray telescopes such as e-ASTROGAM and Fermi-LAT, assuming a nearby future galactic CCSN. We show that future observations can probe mixing angles as low as $|U_{\tau/\mu4}|^2\sim 5\times10^{-17}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13607v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Garv Chauhan, R. Andrew Gustafson, Ian M. Shoemaker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Teaming up MET plus jet with Drell-Yan in the SMEFT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13638v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Standard Model Effective Field Theory (SMEFT) is a widely utilized framework for exploring new physics effects in a model-independent manner. In previous studies, Drell-Yan collider data has emerged as a promising signature due to its energy enhancement relative to Standard Model predictions. We present recent works, extending this approach by also considering the "missing energy + jet" signature, which can constrain related dineutrino couplings and similarly benefits from energy enhancement. The combination of these observables allows for constraining a broader selection of operators and helps resolve flat directions in a global analysis. Overall, the bounds probe the multi-TeV range, with the strongest reaching up to $10\; \text{TeV}$ for four-fermion interactions and $7 \;\text{TeV}$ for gluonic dipole interactions. Furthermore, we find that low energy flavor observables improve limits by up to a factor of three for dipole operators. We also estimate sensitivities to new physics at future hadron colliders including the $\sqrt{s} = 27 \;\text{TeV}$ HE-LHC and the $\sqrt{s} = 100 \; \text{TeV}$ FCC-hh.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13638v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gudrun Hiller, Lara Nollen, Daniel Wendler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy transfer by feebly interacting particles in supernovae: the trapping regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13653</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13653v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Feebly interacting particles, such as sterile neutrinos, dark photons, and axions, can be abundantly produced in the proto-neutron star (PNS) formed in core-collapse supernovae (CCSNe). These particles can decay into photons or charged leptons, depositing energy outside the PNS. Strong bounds on new particles can thus be derived from the observed luminosity of CCSNe, with even tighter bounds obtained from low-energy SNe observations. For the first time we highlight that, at sufficiently large couplings, particle production \textit{outside} the PNS must also be considered. Using the prototypical case of axions coupling to two photons, we show that at large couplings the energy transfer from PNS to its surroundings is diffusive rather than ballistic, substantially reducing the deposited energy. Our findings have implications for the parameter space of particles probed in beam dump experiments and for dark matter models involving a sub-GeV mediator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13653v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Damiano F. G. Fiorillo, Tetyana Pitik, Edoardo Vitagliano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for femtoscopic signatures of the $D \bar D (I=0) \ [X(3700)]$ bound state</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13668v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The femtoscopic $D \bar D $ correlations correlation functions are investigated to predict the signature of the not-yet-established $X(3700)$ state. Here it is interpreted as a bound state generated by solving the coupled-channel Bethe-Salpeter equations with the local hidden-gauge formalism. We prospect how the relevant properties and observables characterizing this state -- like the pole position, scattering lengths and compositeness -- might be affected by the variation of the parameters of the model. The amplitudes are then used as input into the momentum correlation functions of the $D^0 \bar D^0$ and $D^+ D^- $ pairs. We discuss how their behaviors encode the features of the $X(3700)$ state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13668v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luciano M. Abreu, Juan M. Torres-Rincon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Higgs Self-Coupling at FCC-ee</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13719v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Single Higgs production at FCC-ee probes the Higgs self-coupling at next-to-leading order (NLO). Extracting a bound requires a global analysis accounting for other possible new physics contributions up to NLO. We determine the FCC-ee sensitivity to Higgs self-coupling modifications $\delta\kappa_\lambda$ within the Standard Model Effective Field Theory (SMEFT) framework, including for the first time flavour, LEP, LHC, and FCC-ee observables in a global analysis with all leading NLO effects via one-loop renormalisation group evolution, as well as incorporating finite NLO contributions to electroweak precision and $ZH$ observables. The global sensitivity to $\delta\kappa_\lambda$ is estimated by marginalising over the effects of all other operators, bringing flavour considerations to the fore. We find that, under reasonable assumptions, FCC-ee sensitivity to $\delta\kappa_\lambda$ can exceed that of the HL-LHC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13719v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Maura, Ben A. Stefanek, Tevong You</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigations of symmetry breakings by multiple condensates on exotic chiral condensed phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13845v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Nambu-Goldstone modes on the exiotic chiral condensed phase with chiral and tensor-type quark-antiquark condensates are investigated by using of the two-point vertex functions. It is shown that one of the Nambu-Goldstone modes appears as a result of meson-mixing. As is well known, another method to find the Nambu-Goldstone modes is given by the use of the algebraic commutation relations between broken generators and massless modes obtained through the spontaneous symmetry breaking. This method is adopted to the cases of the chiral symmetry breakings due to the tensor-type condensate and the inhomogeneous chiral condensate. The result obtained by the use of the meson two-point vertex functions is obviously reproduced in the case of the tensor-type condensate. Furthermore, we investigate the general rules for determining the broken symmetries and the Nambu-Goldstone modes algebraically. As examples, the symmetry breaking pattern and the Nambu-Goldstone modes due to the tensor-type condensate or the inhomogeneous chiral condensate are shown by adopting the general rules developed in this paper in the algebraic method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13845v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Murakami (Kochi Univ. Japan), Kentaro Hayashi (Kochi Univ. Japan), Yasuhiko Tsue (Kochi Univ. Japan)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flavour Physics and CP Violation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14042</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14042v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: These lectures provide a concise introduction to flavor physics, within and beyond the Standard Model, with main focus on B-physics phenomenology and some recent developments. The first lecture is an introduction to the flavor sector of the Standard Model. The second lecture is devoted to B-meson mixing and rare B decays. The last lecture contains a general discussion about flavor physics beyond the Standard Model, with a highlighting of recent developments related to the idea of flavor deconstruction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14042v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gino Isidori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Double parton interactions initiated by direct photons in $\gamma p$ and $\gamma A$ collisions revisited</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14152</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14152v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the double parton scattering (DPS) initiated by direct photons in $\gamma p$ and $\gamma A$ collisions. We extend the previously known results for photoproduction to the case of electroproduction with nonzero photon virtuality $Q^2$, and then consider the DPS for both photo and electroproduction for HERA and IEC ( electron ion collider) kinematics. The number of DPS events at IEC is shown to be of the same order as in HERA and is even larger, with increase in luminocity compensating the decrease of the center of mass energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14152v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Blok (Technion), R. Segev (Technion)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The infrared-safe Minkowskian Curci-Ferrari model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14291v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss the existence of Landau-pole-free renormalization group trajectories in the Minkowskian version of the Curci-Ferrari model as a function of a running parameter $q^2$ associated to the four-vector $q$ at which renormalization conditions are imposed, and which can take both space-like ($\smash{q^2&lt;0}$) and time-like ($\smash{q^2&gt;0}$) values. We discuss two possible extensions of the infrared-safe scheme defined in Ref. [Phys. Rev. D, 84, 045018, 2011] for the Euclidean version of the model, which coincide with the latter in the space-like region upon identifying $\smash{Q^2\equiv-q^2}$ with the square of the renormalization scale in that reference. The first extension uses real-valued renormalization factors and leads to a flow in the time-like region with a similar structure as the flow in the space-like region (or in the Euclidean model), including a non-trivial fixed point and a family of trajectories bounded at all scales by the value of the coupling at this fixed point. Interestingly, the fixed point in the time-like region has a much smaller value of $\lambda\equiv g^2N/16\pi^2$ than the corresponding one in the space-like region, a value closer to the perturbative boundary $\smash{\lambda=1}$. However, in this real-valued infrared-safe scheme, the flow cannot connect the time-like and space-like regions. Thus, it is not possible to deduce the relevant time-like flow trajectory from the sole knowledge of a space-like flow trajectory. To try to cure this problem, we investigate a second extension of the Euclidean IR-safe scheme, which allows for complex-valued renormalization factors. We discuss under which conditions these schemes can make sense and study their ability to connect space- and time-like flow trajectories. In particular, we investigate to which types of time-like trajectories the perturbative space-like trajectories are mapped onto.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14291v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Santiago Oribe, Marcela Pel\'aez, Urko Reinosa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study of gravitational waves from phase transitions in three-component dark matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14300v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a dark matter model comprising three types of particles with distinct spins, along with a scalar field $\phi$ that mediates interactions between Standard Model particles and dark matter. It discusses the electroweak phase transition following the Big Bang, during which all particles are initially massless due to the inactive Higgs mechanism. As temperature decreases, the effective potential reaches zero at two points, leading to two minima at the critical temperature ($T_c$), and eventually to a true vacuum state. The formation of new vacuum bubbles, where electroweak symmetry is broken and particles acquire mass, generates gravitational waves as these bubbles interact with the fabric of space-time. The paper derives the gravitational wave frequency and detection range based on the model's parameters, aligning with observational data from the Planck satellite and detection thresholds from PandaX-4T. It concludes by comparing the predicted background gravitational wave density with the sensitivities of LISA and BBO detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14300v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Hossein Rahimi Abkenar, Ahmad Mohamadnejad, Reza Sepahvand</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudo-Goldstone Dark Matter from Primordial Black Holes: Gravitational Wave Signatures and Implications for KM3-230213A Event at KM3NeT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14332v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In many well-motivated new physics models, the pseudo-Nambu-Goldstone boson (pNGB) from U(1) symmetry breaking emerges as a promising dark matter candidate. Its coupling, suppressed by the symmetry breaking scale, prevents thermal equilibrium in the early Universe for high scale symmetry breaking. Thus, pNGB dark matter is predominantly produced via non-thermal mechanisms, such as the freeze-in process through a new portal coupling. In this work, we explore a novel mechanism for the production of pNGB dark matter even with feeble Higgs portal coupling-arising from Hawking radiation or superradiance of primordial black holes. We systematically investigate the production of light and heavy pNGB dark matter, both for Schwarzschild and Kerr black holes. We also discuss its potential gravitational wave signatures from domain wall collapse, density perturbations, and Hawking radiation. If the ultraviolet (UV) model is considered, the recent $\mathcal{O}$(100) PeV neutrino event KM3-230213A at KM3NeT can be naturally explained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14332v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siyu Jiang, Fa Peng Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leptogenesis in five-dimensional asymptotic Grand Unification models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14397v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Asymptotic grand unification models can be constructed in five dimensions compactified on an orbifold. We demonstrate that the parameter space of such models admit solutions that naturally achieve the baryon asymmetry via leptogenesis, these solutions indicating that the scale of the extra dimensions is much higher than the TeV scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14397v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timothe Alezraa, Giacomo Cacciapaglia, Aldo Deandrea</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutron portal to ultra-high-energy neutrinos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14419</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14419v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Current data on ultra-high-energy (UHE) cosmic rays suggest they are predominantly made of heavy nuclei. This indicates that the flux of neutrinos produced from proton collisions on the cosmic microwave background is small and hard to observe. Motivated by the recent extremely-high-energy muon event reported by KM3NeT, we explore the possibility of enhancing the energy-flux of cosmogenic neutrinos through nuclear photodisintegration in the presence of new physics. Specifically, we speculate that UHE neutrons may oscillate into a new state, dark (or mirror) neutron $n'$ that in turn decays injecting large amount of energy to neutrinos, $n\to n'\to \nu_\text{UHE}$. While this mechanism does not explain the tension between the KM3NeT event and null results from IceCube, it reconciles the experimental preference for a heavier cosmic ray composition with a large diffuse cosmogenic flux of UHE neutrinos.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14419v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gustavo F. S. Alves, Matheus Hostert, Maxim Pospelov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on violation of Lorentz symmetry with clock-comparison redshift experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13564v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Lorentz symmetry is a cornerstone of both the General relativity and Standard Model and its experimental verification deepens our understanding of nature. This paper focuses on the investigation of Lorentz violations with the context of clock comparison experiments in the framework of Standard Model Extension (SME). Considering matter-gravity coupling sector, we provide a generic frame to study the sensitivities of Lorentz-violating coefficients for three distinct types of clock redshift tests, including the traditional gravitational redshift test, null-redshift test I and null-redshift test II. Each of these tests is sensitivity to different combinations of Lorentz-violating coefficients. By using the current clock comparison results, we estimate the limits of SME coefficients at level of parts in $10^{4}$ down to parts in $10^{7}$. Better sensitivity may be achieved in the clock comparisons by using the state-of-the-art optical clocks. Additionally considering relativistic factors in null-redshift I, the frequency comparison result of E2 and E3 transitions of Yb$^{+}$ can set the limit $c^{e}_{00}=(7.4\pm9.3)\times10^{-9}$ in the electron sector. Our analysis demonstrates that clock-comparison redshift experiments may contribute to explore the vast parameters space on searching for the Lorentz violation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13564v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.055008</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review D 111 (2025) 055008 1-13</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Cheng-Gang Qin, Yu-Jie Tan, Xiao-Yu Lu, Tong Liu, Yan-Rui Yang, Qin Li, Cheng-Gang Shao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stringent Constraints on Self-Interacting Dark Matter Using Milky-Way Satellite Galaxies Kinematics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13650v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Self-interacting dark matter (SIDM) has been proposed to address small-scale challenges faced by the cold dark matter (CDM) paradigm, such as the diverse density profiles observed in dwarf galaxies. In this study, we analyze the kinematics of dwarf galaxies by incorporating the effects of gravothermal core collapse into SIDM models using a semi-analytical subhalo framework. Our analysis covers the stellar kinematics of both classical and ultrafaint dwarf galaxies. The results indicate a bimodal preference for small and large self-interaction cross sections in ultrafaint dwarf galaxies, while in classical dwarfs, larger cross sections progressively decrease the model's statistical support. The combined analysis decisively prefers CDM to SIDM when the self-interaction cross section per unit mass, $\sigma/m$, exceeds $\sim$0.2 cm$^2$/g, if a velocity-independent cross section is assumed. Our study significantly enhances our understanding of dark matter dynamics on small scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13650v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shin'ichiro Ando, Kohei Hayashi, Shunichi Horigome, Masahiro Ibe, Satoshi Shirai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SN 2023ixf in the Pinwheel Galaxy M101: From Shock Breakout to the Nebular Phase</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13974</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13974v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present photometric and spectroscopic observations of SN 2023ixf covering from day one to 442 days after explosion. SN 2023ixf reached a peak $V$-band absolute magnitude of $-18.2 \pm 0.07$, and light curves show that it is in the fast-decliner (IIL) subclass with a relatively short ``plateau'' phase (fewer than $\sim 70$ days). Early-time spectra of SN 2023ixf exhibit strong, very narrow emission lines from ionized circumstellar matter (CSM), possibly indicating a Type IIn classification. But these flash/shock-ionization emission features faded after the first week and the spectrum evolved in a manner similar to that of typical Type II SNe, unlike the case of most genuine SNe~IIn in which the ejecta interact with CSM for an extended period of time and develop intermediate-width emission lines. We compare observed spectra of SN 2023ixf with various model spectra to understand the physics behind SN 2023ixf. Our nebular spectra (between 200-400 d) match best with the model spectra from a 15 $\rm M_{\odot}$ progenitor which experienced enhanced mass loss a few years before explosion. A last-stage mass-loss rate of $\dot{M} = 0.01 \rm M_{\odot} yr^{-1}$ from the r1w6 model matches best with the early-time spectra, higher than $\dot{M} \approx 2.4 \times 10^{-3} \rm M_{\odot} yr^{-1}$ derived from the ionized H${\alpha}$ luminosity at 1.58 d. We also use SN 2023ixf as a distance indicator and fit the light curves to derive the Hubble constant by adding SN 2023ixf to the existing sample; we obtain H$_{0}=73.1^{+3.68}_{-3.50}$ km s$^{-1}$ Mpc$^{-1}$, consistent with the results from SNe~Ia and many other independent methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13974v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weikang Zheng, Luc Dessart, Alexei V. Filippenko, Yi Yang, Thomas G. Brink, Thomas De Jaeger, Sergiy S. Vasylyev, Schuyler D. Van Dyk, Kishore C. Patra, Wynn V. Jacobson-Galan, Gabrielle E. Stewart, Efrain Alvarado III, Veda Arikatla, Pallas Beddow, Andreas Betz, Emma Born, Kate Bostow, Adam J. Burgasser, Osmin Caceres, Evan M. Carrasco, Elma Chuang, Asia DeGraw, Elinor L. Gates, Eli Gendreau-Distler, Cooper Jacobus, Connor Jennings, Preethi R. Karpoor, Paul Lynam, Ann Mina, Katherine Mora, Neil Pichay, Jyotsna Ravi, Jon Rees, R. Michael Rich, Sophia Risin, Nathan R. Sandford, Alessandro Savino, Emma Softich, Christopher A. Theissen, Edgar P. Vidal, William Wu, Yoomee Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $\pi\pi$ scattering amplitude at large $N_\text{c}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13978v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the scaling of meson-meson scattering amplitudes with the number of colors, $N_\text{c}$. We use lattice calculations in a theory with $N_\text{f}=4$ degenerate flavors, with $N_\text{c}=3-6$ and pion mass $M_\pi\approx 560$ MeV. We focus on three different scattering channels, two of which have the same quantum numbers as some tetraquark candidates recently found at LHCb: the $T_{cs0}^0(2900)$, $T_{c\bar{s}0}^{++}(2900)$, $T_{c\bar{s}0}^0(2900)$ and $T_{c\bar{s}1}^0(2900)$ states. Finite-volume energies are extracted using a large set of operators, containing two-particle operators with the form of two pions or two vector mesons, and local tetraquark operators. The resulting energy spectra is used to constrain the infinite-volume scattering amplitude by means of L\"uscher's quantization condition. We consider polynomial parametrizations of the phase shift, as well as one-loop chiral perturbation theory (ChPT) predictions. We find that our lattice results follow the expected $N_\text{c}$ scaling and are sensitive to subleading $N_\text{c}$ corrections. In addition, we constrain the scaling of different combinations of low-energy constants from matching to large $N_\text{c}$ ChPT. The results for the channel corresponding to a $(\pi^+ D^+_s - K^+ D^+)$ state show evidence of a virtual bound state with energy $E_\text{virtual}=1.63(10)M_\pi$ for $N_\text{c}=3$, while this pole disappears at $N_\text{c}&gt;3$. This may be connected to the exotic states found in experiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13978v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jorge Baeza-Ballesteros, Pilar Hern\'andez, Fernando Romero-L\'opez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Propagation Times and Energy Losses of Cosmic Protons and Antiprotons in Interplanetary Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14025v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the heliospheric modulation of cosmic rays in interplanetary space, focusing on their propagation times and energy losses over the solar cycle. To perform the calculations, we employed a data-driven model based on the stochastic method. Our model was calibrated using time-resolved and energy-resolved data from several missions including AMS-02, PAMELA, EPHIN/SOHO, BESS, and data from Voyager-1. This approach allows us to calculate probability density functions for the propagation time and energy losses of cosmic protons and antiprotons in the heliosphere. Furthermore, we explore the temporal evolution of these probabilities spanning from 1993 to 2018, covering a full 22-year cycle of magnetic polarity, which includes two solar minima and two magnetic reversals. Our calculations were carried out for cosmic protons and antiprotons, enabling us to investigate the role of charge-sign dependent effects in cosmic ray transport. These findings provide valuable insights into the physical processes of cosmic-ray propagation in the heliosphere and contribute to a deeper understanding of the solar modulation phenomenon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14025v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/galaxies13020023</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Galaxies 2025, 13(2), 23</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nicola Tomassetti, Bruna Bertucci, Emanuele Fiandrini, Behrouz Khiali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Core-collapse supernova explosions hindered by eV-mass sterile neutrinos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14027v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Light sterile neutrinos, $\nu_s$, are often introduced to explain an anomalous deficit in the electron antineutrino flux from nuclear reactors. If they exist, sterile neutrinos would also be produced in collapsing massive stars through the active-sterile neutrino oscillation. In order to investigate the impacts of sterile neutrinos on supernova dynamics, we perform two-dimensional neutrino-radiation hydrodynamic simulations of stellar core-collapse coupled with the active-sterile oscillation. As the initial condition of our simulations, we adopt a blue supergiant model that is tuned to reproduce observational features of the SN 1987A progenitor to compare our models with observations of the event. It is found that the active-sterile oscillation reduces the $\nu_{e}$ and $\bar{\nu}_e$ fluxes and decreases the explosion energy. We also find that, if the mixing angle $\theta$ and the mass difference $\delta m_\mathrm{s}^2$ between $\nu_e$ and $\nu_s$ are large enough, the star fails to explode. This suggests that these mixing parameters relevant to sterile neutrinos could be constrained by supernova explodability, though other uncertainties in supernova theory need to be addressed to refine them. In addition, we predict neutrino signals from a nearby supernova event and find that the neutrino event number can significantly decrease because the $\nu_e$ and $\bar{\nu}_e$ fluxes are reduced. In particular, DUNE observations of $\nu_e$ will be useful to search for a signature of sterile neutrinos with a tiny mixing angle because a smaller mixing angle leads to a larger effect on the $\nu_e$ flux.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14027v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kanji Mori, Tomoya Takiwaki, Kazunori Kohri, Hiroki Nagakura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superallowed $0^+ \rightarrow 0^+$ $\beta$ decay studies at GANIL and upcoming opportunities with DESIR and S$^3$-LEB</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14082v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Corrected transition rates ($\mathcal{F}t^{0^+ \rightarrow 0^+}$) of $0^+ \rightarrow 0^+$ superallowed $\beta$ decays currently give the most precise value of $V_{ud}$, the dominant term of the Cabibbo-Kobayashi-Maskawa (CKM) quark mixing matrix. By setting stringent constrains on the CKM unitarity, these decays allow probing physics beyond the Standard Model in the electroweak sector. A recent global reevaluation of the $\mathcal{F}t^{0^+ \rightarrow 0^+}$ values has indicated a violation of CKM unitarity prompting reassessment of the theoretical radiative and isospin symmetry breaking corrections applied on the experimental transition rates $ft$. In this article we briefly discuss this current situation and the experimental program at GANIL geared towards constraining isospin symmetry breaking corrections. We conclude by presenting the opportunities that will be available at DESIR and S$^3$-LEB, the upcoming low-energy radioactive ion beam facilities at GANIL.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14082v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. M. Rebeiro, J. -C. Thomas, B. Blank</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lattice Monte Carlo meets lattice functional Renormalization Group: A quantitative comparison</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14149v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Lattice Monte Carlo (MC) simulations and the functional Renormalization Group (RG) are powerful approaches that allow for quantitative studies of non-perturbative phenomena such as bound-state formation, spontaneous symmetry breaking and phase transitions. While results from both methods have recently shown remarkable agreement for many observables, e.g., in Quantum Chromodynamics, an analysis of deviations in certain quantities turns out to be challenging. This is because calculations with the two methods are based on different approximations, regularizations and scale fixing procedures. In the present work, we present a framework for a more direct comparison by formulating the functional RG approach on a finite spacetime lattice. This removes all ambiguities of regularization, finite size and scale fixing procedures in concrete studies. By investigating the emergence of spontaneous symmetry breaking and phase transitions in a $Z(2)$ scalar theory in $d=1,2,3$ spacetime dimensions, we demonstrate at the example of the local potential approximation how this framework can be used to evaluate and compare the systematic errors of both approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14149v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niklas Zorbach, Jan Philipp Klinger, Owe Philipsen, Jens Braun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strategic White Paper on AI Infrastructure for Particle, Nuclear, and Astroparticle Physics: Insights from JENA and EuCAIF</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14192v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Artificial intelligence (AI) is transforming scientific research, with deep learning methods playing a central role in data analysis, simulations, and signal detection across particle, nuclear, and astroparticle physics. Within the JENA communities-ECFA, NuPECC, and APPEC-and as part of the EuCAIF initiative, AI integration is advancing steadily. However, broader adoption remains constrained by challenges such as limited computational resources, a lack of expertise, and difficulties in transitioning from research and development (R&amp;D) to production. This white paper provides a strategic roadmap, informed by a community survey, to address these barriers. It outlines critical infrastructure requirements, prioritizes training initiatives, and proposes funding strategies to scale AI capabilities across fundamental physics over the next five years.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14192v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sascha Caron, Andreas Ipp, Gert Aarts, G\'abor B\'ir\'o, Daniele Bonacorsi, Elena Cuoco, Caterina Doglioni, Tommaso Dorigo, Juli\'an Garc\'ia Pardi\~nas, Stefano Giagu, Tobias Golling, Lukas Heinrich, Ik Siong Heng, Paula Gina Isar, Karolos Potamianos, Liliana Teodorescu, John Veitch, Pietro Vischia, Christoph Weniger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Similarity of Loop Amplitudes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14330v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present an amplitude-generating formula in renormalizable quantum field theory. It reflects the self-similarity of loop amplitudes, in which an amplitude can also be a subamplitude of another. Amplitudes are generated by a small number of "irreducible" ones, which may replace tree-level couplings to form more complex amplitudes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14330v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kang-Sin Choi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>End-to-End Optimal Detector Design with Mutual Information Surrogates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14342v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a novel approach for end-to-end black-box optimization of high energy physics (HEP) detectors using local deep learning (DL) surrogates. These surrogates approximate a scalar objective function that encapsulates the complex interplay of particle-matter interactions and physics analysis goals. In addition to a standard reconstruction-based metric commonly used in the field, we investigate the information-theoretic metric of mutual information. Unlike traditional methods, mutual information is inherently task-agnostic, offering a broader optimization paradigm that is less constrained by predefined targets. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our method in a realistic physics analysis scenario: optimizing the thicknesses of calorimeter detector layers based on simulated particle interactions. The surrogate model learns to approximate objective gradients, enabling efficient optimization with respect to energy resolution. Our findings reveal three key insights: (1) end-to-end black-box optimization using local surrogates is a practical and compelling approach for detector design, providing direct optimization of detector parameters in alignment with physics analysis goals; (2) mutual information-based optimization yields design choices that closely match those from state-of-the-art physics-informed methods, indicating that these approaches operate near optimality and reinforcing their reliability in HEP detector design; and (3) information-theoretic methods provide a powerful, generalizable framework for optimizing scientific instruments. By reframing the optimization process through an information-theoretic lens rather than domain-specific heuristics, mutual information enables the exploration of new avenues for discovery beyond conventional approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14342v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kinga Anna Wozniak, Stephen Mulligan, Jan Kieseler, Markus Klute, Francois Fleuret, Tobias Golling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nuclear configurational complexity in high-energy hadron-hadron scatterings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14410v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates high-energy hadron-hadron scattering utilizing AdS/QCD correspondence, gravitational form factors, and the Brower-Polchinski-Strassler-Tan pomeron exchange kernel. We use the configurational complexity to estimate the slope of the total cross section for hadron-hadron interactions at the high-energy regime. Our approach agrees well with the phenomenological cross sections regulated by Pomeron exchange involving the pion-nucleon, nucleon-nucleon, and pion-pion, in data from the TOTEM collaboration (LHC). In the case of pion-nucleon and pion-pion scattering, the agreement for the global critical point of the configurational complexity has good accuracy within 2.3\%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14410v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Karapetyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: DR6 Power Spectra, Likelihoods and $\Lambda$CDM Parameters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14452v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present power spectra of the cosmic microwave background (CMB) anisotropy in temperature and polarization, measured from the Data Release 6 maps made from Atacama Cosmology Telescope (ACT) data. These cover 19,000 deg$^2$ of sky in bands centered at 98, 150 and 220 GHz, with white noise levels three times lower than Planck in polarization. We find that the ACT angular power spectra estimated over 10,000 deg$^2$, and measured to arcminute scales in TT, TE and EE, are well fit by the sum of CMB and foregrounds, where the CMB spectra are described by the $\Lambda$CDM model. Combining ACT with larger-scale Planck data, the joint P-ACT dataset provides tight limits on the ingredients, expansion rate, and initial conditions of the universe. We find similar constraining power, and consistent results, from either the Planck power spectra or from ACT combined with WMAP data, as well as from either temperature or polarization in the joint P-ACT dataset. When combined with CMB lensing from ACT and Planck, and baryon acoustic oscillation data from the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI Y1), we measure a baryon density of $\Omega_b h^2=0.0226\pm0.0001$, a cold dark matter density of $\Omega_c h^2=0.118\pm0.001$, a Hubble constant of $H_0=68.22\pm0.36$ km/s/Mpc, a spectral index of $n_s=0.974\pm0.003$, and an amplitude of density fluctuations of $\sigma_8=0.813\pm0.005$. We find no evidence for excess lensing in the power spectrum, and no departure from spatial flatness. The contribution from Sunyaev-Zel'dovich (SZ) anisotropy is detected at high significance; we find evidence for a tilt with suppressed small-scale power compared to our baseline SZ template spectrum, consistent with hydrodynamical simulations with feedback.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14452v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thibaut Louis, Adrien La Posta, Zachary Atkins, Hidde T. Jense, Irene Abril-Cabezas, Graeme E. Addison, Peter A. R. Ade, Simone Aiola, Tommy Alford, David Alonso, Mandana Amiri, Rui An, Jason E. Austermann, Eleonora Barbavara, Nicholas Battaglia, Elia Stefano Battistelli, James A. Beall, Rachel Bean, Ali Beheshti, Benjamin Beringue, Tanay Bhandarkar, Emily Biermann, Boris Bolliet, J Richard Bond, Erminia Calabrese, Valentina Capalbo, Felipe Carrero, Stephen Chen, Grace Chesmore, Hsiao-mei Cho, Steve K. Choi, Susan E. Clark, Nicholas F. Cothard, Kevin Coughlin, William Coulton, Devin Crichton, Kevin T. Crowley, Omar Darwish, Mark J. Devlin, Simon Dicker, Cody J. Duell, Shannon M. Duff, Adriaan J. Duivenvoorden, Jo Dunkley, Rolando Dunner, Carmen Embil Villagra, Max Fankhanel, Gerrit S. Farren, Simone Ferraro, Allen Foster, Rodrigo Freundt, Brittany Fuzia, Patricio A. Gallardo, Xavier Garrido, Martina Gerbino, Serena Giardiello, Ajay Gill, Jahmour Givans, Vera Gluscevic, Samuel Goldstein, Joseph E. Golec, Yulin Gong, Yilun Guan, Mark Halpern, Ian Harrison, Matthew Hasselfield, Erin Healy, Shawn Henderson, Brandon Hensley, Carlos Herv\'ias-Caimapo, J. Colin Hill, Gene C. Hilton, Matt Hilton, Adam D. Hincks, Ren\'ee Hlo\v{z}ek, Shuay-Pwu Patty Ho, John Hood, Erika Hornecker, Zachary B. Huber, Johannes Hubmayr, Kevin M. Huffenberger, John P. Hughes, Margaret Ikape, Kent Irwin, Giovanni Isopi, Neha Joshi, Ben Keller, Joshua Kim, Kenda Knowles, Brian J. Koopman, Arthur Kosowsky, Darby Kramer, Aleksandra Kusiak, Alex Lague, Victoria Lakey, Eunseong Lee, Yaqiong Li, Zack Li, Michele Limon, Martine Lokken, Marius Lungu, Niall MacCrann, Amanda MacInnis, Mathew S. Madhavacheril, Diego Maldonado, Felipe Maldonado, Maya Mallaby-Kay, Gabriela A. Marques, Joshiwa van Marrewijk, Fiona McCarthy, Jeff McMahon, Yogesh Mehta, Felipe Menanteau, Kavilan Moodley, Thomas W. Morris, Tony Mroczkowski, Sigurd Naess, Toshiya Namikawa, Federico Nati, Simran K. Nerval, Laura Newburgh, Andrina Nicola, Michael D. Niemack, Michael R. Nolta, John Orlowski-Scherer, Luca Pagano, Lyman A. Page, Shivam Pandey, Bruce Partridge, Karen Perez Sarmiento, Heather Prince, Roberto Puddu, Frank J. Qu, Damien C. Ragavan, Bernardita Ried Guachalla, Keir K. Rogers, Felipe Rojas, Tai Sakuma, Emmanuel Schaan, Benjamin L. Schmitt, Neelima Sehgal, Shabbir Shaikh, Blake D. Sherwin, Carlos Sierra, Jon Sievers, Crist\'obal Sif\'on, Sara Simon, Rita Sonka, David N. Spergel, Suzanne T. Staggs, Emilie Storer, Kristen Surrao, Eric R. Switzer, Niklas Tampier, Robert Thornton, Hy Trac, Carole Tucker, Joel Ullom, Leila R. Vale, Alexander Van Engelen, Jeff Van Lanen, Cristian Vargas, Eve M. Vavagiakis, Kasey Wagoner, Yuhan Wang, Lukas Wenzl, Edward J. Wollack, Kaiwen Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: DR6 Constraints on Extended Cosmological Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14454</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14454v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We use new cosmic microwave background (CMB) primary temperature and polarization anisotropy measurements from the Atacama Cosmology Telescope (ACT) Data Release 6 (DR6) to test foundational assumptions of the standard cosmological model and set constraints on extensions to it. We derive constraints from the ACT DR6 power spectra alone, as well as in combination with legacy data from Planck. To break geometric degeneracies, we include ACT and Planck CMB lensing data and baryon acoustic oscillation data from DESI Year-1, and further add supernovae measurements from Pantheon+ for models that affect the late-time expansion history. We verify the near-scale-invariance (running of the spectral index $d n_s/d\ln k = 0.0062 \pm 0.0052$) and adiabaticity of the primordial perturbations. Neutrino properties are consistent with Standard Model predictions: we find no evidence for new light, relativistic species that are free-streaming ($N_{\rm eff} = 2.86 \pm 0.13$, which combined with external BBN data becomes $N_{\rm eff} = 2.89 \pm 0.11$), for non-zero neutrino masses ($\sum m_\nu &lt; 0.082$ eV at 95% CL), or for neutrino self-interactions. We also find no evidence for self-interacting dark radiation ($N_{\rm idr} &lt; 0.134$), early-universe variation of fundamental constants, early dark energy, primordial magnetic fields, or modified recombination. Our data are consistent with standard BBN, the FIRAS-inferred CMB temperature, a dark matter component that is collisionless and with only a small fraction allowed as axion-like particles, a cosmological constant, and the late-time growth rate predicted by general relativity. We find no statistically significant preference for a departure from the baseline $\Lambda$CDM model. In general, models introduced to increase the Hubble constant or to decrease the amplitude of density fluctuations inferred from the primary CMB are not favored by our data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14454v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erminia Calabrese, J. Colin Hill, Hidde T. Jense, Adrien La Posta, Irene Abril-Cabezas, Graeme E. Addison, Peter A. R. Ade, Simone Aiola, Tommy Alford, David Alonso, Mandana Amiri, Rui An, Zachary Atkins, Jason E. Austermann, Eleonora Barbavara, Nicola Barbieri, Nicholas Battaglia, Elia Stefano Battistelli, James A. Beall, Rachel Bean, Ali Beheshti, Benjamin Beringue, Tanay Bhandarkar, Emily Biermann, Boris Bolliet, J Richard Bond, Valentina Capalbo, Felipe Carrero, Stephen Chen, Grace Chesmore, Hsiao-mei Cho, Steve K. Choi, Susan E. Clark, Nicholas F. Cothard, Kevin Coughlin, William Coulton, Devin Crichton, Kevin T. Crowley, Omar Darwish, Mark J. Devlin, Simon Dicker, Cody J. Duell, Shannon M. Duff, Adriaan J. Duivenvoorden, Jo Dunkley, Rolando Dunner, Carmen Embil Villagra, Max Fankhanel, Gerrit S. Farren, Simone Ferraro, Allen Foster, Rodrigo Freundt, Brittany Fuzia, Patricio A. Gallardo, Xavier Garrido, Martina Gerbino, Serena Giardiello, Ajay Gill, Jahmour Givans, Vera Gluscevic, Samuel Goldstein, Joseph E. Golec, Yulin Gong, Yilun Guan, Mark Halpern, Ian Harrison, Matthew Hasselfield, Adam He, Erin Healy, Shawn Henderson, Brandon Hensley, Carlos Herv\'ias-Caimapo, Gene C. Hilton, Matt Hilton, Adam D. Hincks, Ren\'ee Hlo\v{z}ek, Shuay-Pwu Patty Ho, John Hood, Erika Hornecker, Zachary B. Huber, Johannes Hubmayr, Kevin M. Huffenberger, John P. Hughes, Margaret Ikape, Kent Irwin, Giovanni Isopi, Neha Joshi, Ben Keller, Joshua Kim, Kenda Knowles, Brian J. Koopman, Arthur Kosowsky, Darby Kramer, Aleksandra Kusiak, Alex Lague, Victoria Lakey, Massimiliano Lattanzi, Eunseong Lee, Yaqiong Li, Zack Li, Michele Limon, Martine Lokken, Thibaut Louis, Marius Lungu, Niall MacCrann, Amanda MacInnis, Mathew S. Madhavacheril, Diego Maldonado, Felipe Maldonado, Maya Mallaby-Kay, Gabriela A. Marques, Joshiwa van Marrewijk, Fiona McCarthy, Jeff McMahon, Yogesh Mehta, Felipe Menanteau, Kavilan Moodley, Thomas W. Morris, Tony Mroczkowski, Sigurd Naess, Toshiya Namikawa, Federico Nati, Simran K. Nerval, Laura Newburgh, Andrina Nicola, Michael D. Niemack, Michael R. Nolta, John Orlowski-Scherer, Luca Pagano, Lyman A. Page, Shivam Pandey, Bruce Partridge, Karen Perez Sarmiento, Heather Prince, Roberto Puddu, Frank J. Qu, Damien C. Ragavan, Bernardita Ried Guachalla, Keir K. Rogers, Felipe Rojas, Tai Sakuma, Emmanuel Schaan, Benjamin L. Schmitt, Neelima Sehgal, Shabbir Shaikh, Blake D. Sherwin, Carlos Sierra, Jon Sievers, Crist\'obal Sif\'on, Sara Simon, Rita Sonka, David N. Spergel, Suzanne T. Staggs, Emilie Storer, Kristen Surrao, Eric R. Switzer, Niklas Tampier, Leander Thiele, Robert Thornton, Hy Trac, Carole Tucker, Joel Ullom, Leila R. Vale, Alexander Van Engelen, Jeff Van Lanen, Cristian Vargas, Eve M. Vavagiakis, Kasey Wagoner, Yuhan Wang, Lukas Wenzl, Edward J. Wollack, Kaiwen Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Association of 220 PeV Neutrino KM3-230213A with Gamma-Ray Bursts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14471v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently, the KM3NeT Collaboration released the detection of a 220 PeV neutrino from the celestial coordinates RA=94.3\degree~ and Dec=-7.8\degree~ on 13 February 2023 at 01:16:47 UTC \cite{KM3NeT:2025npi}. The source for this extra-ordinary cosmic neutrino, designated KM3-230213A, is not identified yet but there has been a speculation that it might be associated with a gamma-ray burst GRB~090401B \cite{Amelino-Camelia:2025lqn}. The purpose of this report is to search the association of this 220 PeV neutrino with potential GRB sources from a more general consideration of Lorentz invariance violation (LV) without fixed LV scale. We try to associate this extra-ordinary neutrino with potential GRBs within angular separation of 1\degree, 3\degree~ and 5\degree~ respectively and the results are listed in Table 1. We find the constraints $E_{\rm{LV}}\leq 5.3\times 10^{18}$~GeV for subluminal LV violation and $E_{\rm{LV}}\leq 5.6\times 10^{19}$~GeV for superluminal LV violation if KM3-230213A is a GRB neutrino.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14471v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruiqi Wang, Jie Zhu, Hao Li, Bo-Qiang Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativistic Fractons and their Dust</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14496v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We define a relativistic version of the global symmetries responsible for the restricted mobility of fracton quasiparticles. The theories have a symmetry current that is proportional to a vector field that spontaneously breaks Lorentz boost symmetry. We argue that the existence of a pressureless dust in the early universe could be a consequence of this symmetry. We provide an example of a fractonic scalar field with a quartic self-interaction evolving on a Friedmann-Robertson-Walker background and show that the interaction gives rise to a separately conserved fluid with equation of state $w=1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14496v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiuyue Liang, Tom Melia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $z_g$ distribution for heavy flavour jets in dense quark-gluon plasma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.15560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.15560v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the $z_g$ distribution for heavy flavour, i.e. bottom and charm quark, jets propagating through the dense QCD medium. We extend the late emission approximation for Armesto-Salgado-Wiedemann (ASW) formula to heavy flavours. % We consider both the normalised and $N_{\rm jet}$ normalised $z_g$ distributions, and the ratio of the latter distributions to the vacuum ones, called the R ratio. We demonstrate that since there is no collinear singularity in the medium, there is no principal need to use the Sudakov safety technique for medium-induced emission (MIE). We see that contrary to the vacuum case, the normalised $z_g$ distribution is sensitive to the dead cone angle value. In particular, for the case of $N_{jet}$ normalised distribution with $\theta_g\le \theta_{cut}$, it is possible to directly probe the dead cone gluons in the medium.
  Our results can be useful to guide the experimental measurements of the heavy flavour jet substructure in dense QCD medium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.15560v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boris Blok (Technion), Chang Wu (Technion)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark photon pair production via off-shell dark Higgs at FASER</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17760v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a dark photon model in which the dark U(1) gauge symmetry is spontaneously broken by a vacuum expectation value of a new scalar boson. We focus on the ForwArd Search ExpeRiment (FASER) and calculate its sensitivity to the dark photon produced from the off-shell decay of the new scalar boson. It is found that the off-shell production extends the sensitivity region beyond the kinematical threshold of the on-shell decay of the scalar boson, and that the sensitivity region can be spanned to unexplored region. We also show the parameter space in which perturbative calculation is valid for the unitarity of an S matrix.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17760v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP12(2024)124</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP12(2024)124</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Takeshi Araki, Kento Asai, Yohei Nakashima, Takashi Shimomura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Refined approaches in second leptogenesis for the baryon-lepton asymmetry discrepancy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19694</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19694v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The temperature-dependent mass of the heavy neutrino can lead to the second leptogenesis occurring below the electroweak scale, potentially explaining the large discrepancy between baryon and lepton asymmetries. We investigate this scenario further, exploring the intricate interplay of the weak interaction processes within this framework. It includes notable shifts in the dominant decay channels of heavy neutrinos around the electroweak symmetry breaking, along with the resonance behavior of the scattering processes near the $W/Z$ mass. The $CP$ asymmetry can also vary over cosmic history due to the temperature-dependent mass, allowing the $B-L$ asymmetry generation to be amplified in the late epoch. These findings elucidate how such alterations in the dynamics of second leptogenesis contribute to addressing the observed discrepancies in baryon-lepton asymmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19694v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>YeolLin ChoeJo, Kazuki Enomoto, Yechan Kim, Hye-Sung Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinguishing Beyond-Standard Model Effects in Neutrino Oscillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04234v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We systematically assess the DUNE experiment's ability to distinguish between various beyond-standard neutrino oscillation hypotheses pair combinations. For a pair comparison, we evaluate the statistical separation, where one hypothesis plays the role of the true signal while the other corresponds to the test signal. The beyond-standard neutrino oscillation hypotheses under scrutiny include neutrino decay (invisible and visible), non-standard interactions, quantum decoherence, and the violation of the equivalence principle. When taken as the true model, we found that either quantum decoherence or the violation of the equivalence principle are the easiest to differentiate compared to the rest of the hypotheses. Additionally, from our statistical test, we investigate potential discrepancies between the measured CP-violation phase $\delta_{CP}$ relative to its true value, which could occur for a given comparison. In our analysis, we will take the true values of $\delta_{CP}$ as $-90^\circ$ and $180^\circ$. Notably, even in cases where the beyond-standard neutrino oscillation hypotheses scenarios are statistically indistinguishable, the measured value can exhibit significant deviations from its true value.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04234v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Calatayud-Cadenillas, A. P\'erez-G, A. M. Gago</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous Ionization in the Central Molecular Zone by sub-GeV Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07515v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We demonstrate that the anomalous ionization rate observed in the Central Molecular Zone can be attributed to MeV dark matter annihilations into $e^+e^-$ pairs for galactic dark matter profiles with slopes $\gamma&gt;1$. The low annihilation cross-sections required avoid cosmological constraints and imply no detectable inverse Compton, bremsstrahlung or synchrotron emissions in radio, X and gamma rays. The possible connection to the source of the unexplained 511 keV line emission in the Galactic Center suggests that both observations could be correlated and have a common origin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07515v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.134.101001</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.Lett. 134 (2025) 10, 101001</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pedro De la Torre Luque, Shyam Balaji, Joseph Silk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of unpolarized transverse momentum dependent parton distributions of twist-3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09667v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We revisit the calculation of the evolution equations for four unpolarized twist-3 transverse momentum dependent (TMD) parton distribution functions (PDFs) at $\mathcal {O}(\alpha_s)$. Unlike the existing calculations in the literature, which are based on the background field method, we derive the evolution equations directly through diagram expansion. Additionally, instead of using the $\delta$ regulator, we employ the exponential regulator to regularize the rapidity divergences. We find that the evolutions of the four twist-3 TMD PDFs are governed by eight homogeneous equations. Our evolution kernels agree with one set of results in the literature, but differ from another by a sign. Considering the advantages of the exponential regulator in high-order perturbative calculations, our results are crucial for computing the twist-3 TMD PDFs at $\mathcal {O}(\alpha_s^2)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09667v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xue-Tao Liu, Ping-An Liu, Yu-Lu Liu, An-Ping Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the onset of hydrodynamization in peripheral p-Pb collisions at $\sqrt{s_{NN}} =$ 5.02 TeV</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15671v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: An attempt has been made to estimate the minimum size of the de-confined matter of Quark-Gluon Plasma (QGP) in small systems like p-Pb system that could be satisfactorily modeled with low-order hydrodynamics. The variation of second order transport coefficient of second order relativistic viscous hydrodynamics, the shear relaxation time has been utilized to study the sensitivity of experimental observables like elliptic flow coefficient. A representative system of p-Pb collisions at $\sqrt{s_{NN}} =$ 5.02 TeV, simulated with the state-of-art framework of JETSCAPE event generator was used to study the variation of elliptic flow coefficient for peripheral collisions. The soft sector dynamics was simulated using an initial condition, a pre-equilibrium stage, hydrodynamics and a hadron afterburner. The transverse momentum spectra and rapidity distribution was obtained for light flavored hadrons and compared with the experimental data. The increase in elliptic flow fluctuations indicate breakdown of fluid behavior at $dN/dy \approx 14$ for p-Pb collision at $\sqrt{s_{NN}} =$ 5.02 TeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15671v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikhil Hatwar, Sadhana Dash, Basanta Kumar Nandi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sterile-active resonance: A global qualitative picture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19022v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the $\nu$SM extended by adding an eV-scale sterile state, the $(3+1)$ model, the sterile-active level crossing entails the MSW resonance, here referred as the sterile-active (SA) resonance. In this paper, we construct an effective theory of SA resonance which involves only the sterile-active mixing angles and $\Delta m^2_{41}$, thanks to the given environment of high matter potential which freezes the $\nu$SM oscillations. We give our first attempt at an analytic treatment of the effective theory to illuminate the global picture of the SA resonance at a glance. We formulate a perturbative framework in which the structure of ``texture zeros'' of the $S$ matrix in the flavor space and the suppression by the small parameters $\sin \theta_{j 4}$ ($j=1,2,3$) allows us to reveal the flavor$-$event-type hierarchy of the resonance-effect strength in the probabilities. We have shown that the cascade events dominantly comes from the three paths through $P(\nu_{e} \rightarrow \nu_{e})$, $P(\bar{\nu}_{e} \rightarrow \bar{\nu}_{e})$, and $P(\bar{\nu}_{\mu} \rightarrow \bar{\nu}_{\tau})$, and a three-component fit is suggested to disentangle the SA resonance generation mechanisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19022v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark Brettell, Ivan Martinez-Soler, Hisakazu Minakata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncertainties in tellurium-based dark matter searches stemming from nuclear structure uncertainties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00621v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Using tellurium dioxide as a target, we calculate uncertainties on 90% upper confidence limits of Galilean effective field theory (Galilean EFT) couplings to a weakly-interacting massive particle (WIMP) dark matter candidate due to uncertainties in nuclear shell models. We find that these uncertainties in naturally-occurring tellurium isotopes are comparable across the different Galilean EFT couplings to uncertainties in xenon, with some reaching over 100%. We also consider the effect these nuclear uncertainties have on estimates of the annual modulation of dark matter from these searches, finding that the uncertainties in the modulation amplitude are proportional to the non-modulating upper confidence limit uncertainties. We also show that the determination of the modulation phase is insensitive to changes in the nuclear model for a given isotope.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00621v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.063045</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 111, 063045 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Daniel J. Heimsoth, Rebecca Kowalski, Danielle H. Speller, Calvin W. Johnson, A. Baha Balantekin, Susan N. Coppersmith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Studying the $B^{0} \to J/\psi h_{1}$ decays with $h_{1}(1170)-h_{1}(1415)$ mixing in the perturbative QCD approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01075v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the $B^{0} \to J/\psi h_{1}$ decays for the first time by using perturbative QCD approach up to the presently known next-to-leading order accuracy. The vertex corrections present significant contribution to the amplitude. In the calculation, the mixing between two light axial-vector mesons $h_{1}(1170)$ and $h_{1}(1415)$ are also studied in detail. The observables including the branching ratios, polarization fractions and $CP$ asymmetries are predicted and discussed explicitly. It is found that the $B^{0} \to J/\psi h_{1}$ decays have relatively large branching fractions, which are generally at the order of ${\cal O}(10^{-6}\sim10^{-3})$, and thus are possible to be observed by the LHCb and Belle-II experiments in the near future. Moreover, they are very sensitive to the mixing angle $\theta$ and can be used to test the values of $\theta$. In addition, some ratios between the branching fractions of $B^{0} \to J/\psi h_{1}$ decays can provide much stronger constraints on $\theta$ due to their relatively small theoretical errors. The $B^{0} \to J/\psi h_{1}$ decays are generally dominated by the longitudinal polarization contributions, specifically, $f_{L}(B^{0} \to J/\psi h_{1})&gt;80\%$, except for the case that $\theta\sim 35^\circ$ and $-55^\circ$. Unfortunately, the direct $CP$ asymmetries of $B^{0} \to J/\psi h_{1}$ decays are too small to be observed soon even if the effect of $\theta$ is considered. The future precise measurements on $B^{0} \to J/\psi h_{1}$ decays are expected for testing these theoretical findings and exploring the interesting nature of $h_{1}(1170)$ and $h_{1}(1415)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01075v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qin Chang, De-Hua Yao, Xin Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CP violation analysis of $D^0\to M^0 K \to M^0(\pi^\pm \ell^\mp \nu)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05689v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: CP violation in the charm sector is highly sensitive to new physics due to its small predicted value within the standard model. By this work, we investigated the CP violation in the cascade decay process $D^0(t_1) \to \pi^0 K(t_2) \to \pi^0(\pi^\pm \ell^\mp \nu)$. Our results indicate that the CP violation induced by the interference of unmixed $D$-meson decay amplitudes dominates, with a peak value reaching $5 \times 10^{-3}$. This is one order of magnitude larger than the sub-leading contribution, namely the double-mixing CP violation. Furthermore, the CP violation in the decay channel with the semileptonic final state $\pi^- \ell^+ \nu_\ell$ is one to two orders of magnitude larger than that in the channel with $ \pi^+ \ell^- \bar{\nu}_\ell$. We propose that the CP asymmetry of the combined two decay channels can be measured experimentally. The resulting value is approximately half of the CP violation observed in the $\pi^- \ell^+ \nu_\ell$ channel, with the dominant contribution still reaching the order of $10^{-3}$. This approach offers the advantage of eliminating the need for flavor tagging of the initial $D$ meson, thereby avoiding associated efficiency losses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05689v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-025-14024-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. C 85, 300 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Jie Song, Shi-Qi Wang, Qin Qin, Ya Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study $\Xi_c^+ \to \Lambda {\bar{K}}^0 \pi^+$ and search for the low-lying baryons $\Xi(1/2^-)$ and $\Sigma(1/2^-)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14385v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Since searches for the low-lying excited baryons $\Xi(1/2^-)$ and $\Sigma(1/2^-)$ are crucial to deepening our understanding of the light baryon spectrum, we have investigated the Cabibbo-favored process $\Xi_c^+ \to \Lambda {\bar{K}}^0 \pi^+$ by taking into account the $S$-wave pseudoscalar meson-octet baryon interactions within the chiral unitary approach, which could dynamically generate the resonances $\Xi(1/2^-)$ and $\Sigma(1/2^-)$. The contributions from the excited kaons are double Cabibbo-suppressed, and the contribution from the $\Sigma(1385)$ is also suppressed due to Korner-Pati-Woo theory, thus those states are expected to play negligible contributions in this process. We have predicted the $\bar{K}^0 \Lambda$ and $\pi^+\Lambda$ invariant mass distributions, which have the clear signals of the $\Xi(1/2^-)$ and $\Sigma(1/2^-)$. Thus, the $\Xi_c^+ \to \Lambda {\bar{K}}^0 \pi^+$ is an ideal process to search for the low-lying baryons $\Xi(1/2^-)$ and $\Sigma(1/2^-)$, and we make a call for a precise measurements of this process in experiments, such as Belle II, LHCb, and the proposed Super Tau-Charm Facility (STCF).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14385v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.054011</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D (2025) no.5, 054011</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ying Li, Wen-Tao Lyu, Guan-Ying Wang, Longke Li, Wen-Cheng Yan, En Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review of the QCD sum rules for exotic states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11351</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11351v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We review the exotic states, such as the $X$, $Y$, $Z$, $T$ and $P$ states, and present their possible assignments based on the QCD sum rules. We present many predictions which can be confronted to the experimental data in the future to diagnose the exotic states. Furthermore, we also mention other theoretical methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11351v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhi-Gang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Comprehensive Framework for Electroweak Phase Transitions: Thermal History and Dynamics from Bubble Nucleation to Percolation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00421v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The electroweak phase transition (EWPT) is crucial for cosmology and particle physics, with a profound impact on electroweak baryogenesis, symmetry breaking, and gravitational wave (GW) signals. However, many studies overlook key aspects of EWPT dynamics, leading to misidentified patterns and overestimated GW signals. To address these gaps, we present a comprehensive framework for analyzing EWPTs, focusing on the vacuum's thermal history and dynamics from bubble nucleation to percolation. Using the $\mathbb{Z}_2$-odd real scalar singlet model, we demonstrate the occurrence of spontaneous $\mathbb{Z}_2$ symmetry breaking in the high-temperature vacuum, leading to diverse EWPT processes, including multi-step transitions and inverse symmetry breaking. We identify four distinct EWPT patterns, each characterized by unique symmetry-breaking mechanisms and associated with bubbles exhibiting distinct field configurations, which can be analyzed using a formalism based on energy density distributions developed here. A key finding is that bubble nucleation fails in extremely strong phase transitions (PTs) with low nucleation rates, or in ultra-fast PTs involving inverse $s$-bubbles that collapse instantly upon formation, both of which lead to false vacuum trapping and the absence of observable GW signals. In first-order PTs where nucleation succeeds, stronger transitions occur later in the universe's evolution, while weaker transitions proceed more rapidly. Multi-step transitions involving (inverse) $\mathbb{Z}_2$ symmetry breaking give rise to complex transition sequences and exotic bubble dynamics, such as sequential nucleation or the coexistence of bubbles from different vacua -- phenomena with significant implications for GW spectra, dark matter, and baryogenesis. This work advances our understanding of EWPT dynamics and lays the groundwork for future studies of EWPTs in BSM physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00421v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haibin Chen, Yun Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Studying Bremsstrahlung in Polarized Background Field at EIC and EicC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04198v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Within the framework of quantum field theory, we have studied bremsstrahlung radiation in polarized electromagnetic fields. It reveals that the resulting photon beams are polarized, reflecting the properties of the background field. We propose to observe this phenomenon via the Bethe-Heitler process and provide numerical estimates at the Electron-Ion Collider and the Electron-Ion Collider in China.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04198v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cong Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prospects of future MeV telescopes in probing weak-scale Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04907v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Galactic weak-scale Dark Matter (DM) particles annihilating into lepton-rich channels not only produce gamma-rays via prompt radiation but also generate abundant energetic electrons and positrons, which subsequently emit through bremsstrahlung or inverse Compton scattering (collectively called `secondary-radiation photons'). While the prompt gamma-rays concentrate at high-energy, the secondary emission falls in the MeV range, which a number of upcoming experiments (AMEGO, E-ASTROGAM, MAST...) will probe. We investigate the sensitivity of these future telescopes for weak-scale DM, focusing for definiteness on observations of the galactic center. We find that they have the potential of probing a wide region of the DM parameter space which is currently unconstrained. Namely, in rather optimistic configurations, future MeV telescopes could probe thermally-produced DM with a mass up to the TeV range, or GeV DM with an annihilation cross section 2 to 3 orders of magnitude smaller than the current bounds, precisely thanks to the significant leverage provided by their sensitivity to secondary emissions. We comment on astrophysical and methodological uncertainties, and compare with the reach of high-energy gamma ray experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04907v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Cirelli, Arpan Kar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The effect of spacetime torsion on neutrino mixing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05851v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the framework of quantum field theory, we analyze the neutrino oscillations in the presence of a torsion background. We consider the Einstein Cartan theory and we study the cases of constant torsion and of linearly time-dependent torsion. We derive new neutrino oscillation formulae which depend on the spin orientation and the CP asymmetry formula. Experiment such as PTOLEMY which analyzes the cosmological background of neutrino, can provide insights into the effect shown here.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05851v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Capolupo, S. Monda, G. Pisacane, A. Quaranta, R. Serao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electron-positron annihilation into heavy leptons at two loops</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09245</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.09245v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We calculate the NNLO QED corrections to the $C$-even part of differential cross section of $e^+e^- \to \mu^+\mu^-$ process. We neglect power corrections in the electron mass and obtain the result in terms of Goncharov's polylogarithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.09245v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roman E. Gerasimov, Petr A. Krachkov, Roman N. Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One never walks alone: the effect of the perturber population on subhalo measurements in strong gravitational lenses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.09918</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.09918v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Analyses of extended arcs in strong gravitational lensing images to date have constrained the properties of dark matter by measuring the parameters of one or two individual subhalos. However, since such analyses are reliant on likelihood-based methods like Markov-chain Monte Carlo or nested sampling, they require various compromises to the realism of lensing models for the sake of computational tractability, such as ignoring the numerous other subhalos and line-of-sight halos in the system, assuming a particular form for the source model and requiring the noise to have a known likelihood function. Here we show that a simulation-based inference method calledTruncated Marginal Neural Ratio Estimation (TMNRE) makes it possible to relax these requirements by training neural networks to directly compute marginal posteriors for subhalo parameters from lensing images. By performing a set of inference tasks on mock data, we verify the accuracy of TMNRE and show it can compute posteriors for subhalo parameters marginalized over populations of hundreds of substructures, as well as lens and source uncertainties. We also find the \gls*{mlp} Mixer network works far better for such tasks than the convolutional architectures explored in other lensing analyses. Furthermore, we show that since \gls*{tmnre} learns a posterior function it enables direct statistical checks that would be extremely expensive with likelihood-based methods. Our results show that TMNRE is well-suited for analyzing complex lensing data, and that the full subhalo and line-of-sight halo population must be included when measuring the properties of individual dark matter substructures with this technique.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.09918v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stad2925</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, Volume 527, Issue 1, January 2024, Pages 66-78</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Adam Coogan, Noemi Anau Montel, Konstantin Karchev, Meiert W. Grootes, Francesco Nattino, Christoph Weniger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A search for super-imposed oscillations to the primordial power spectrum in Planck and SPT-3G 2018 data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19575v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We search for super-imposed oscillations linearly or logarithmically spaced in Fourier wavenumbers in Planck and South Pole Telescope (SPT-3G) 2018 temperature and polarization data. The SPT-3G temperature and polarization data provide a new window to test these oscillations at high multipoles beyond the Planck angular resolution and sensitivity. We consider both models with a constant and a Gaussian modulated amplitude, which correspond to three and four additional parameters beyond power-law primordial power spectrum for the templates considered, respectively. We find that each of the four models considered can provide an improved fit to Planck data, consistently with previous findings, and to SPT-3G data, always compared to power-law power spectrum. For a constant amplitude of the superimposed oscillations, we find tighter constraints on the amplitude of the oscillations from the combined Planck/SPT-3G data set than in each individual data sets. When the ranges of parameters which provide a better fit to Planck and SPT-3G data overlap, as in the case of Gaussian modulated oscillations, we find a larger $\Delta \chi^2 \sim - 17.5 \, (-14.7)$ for logarithmic (linear) oscillations - in a combined Planck/SPT-3G data set than %the one obtained in each individual data sets. These findings will be further tested with upcoming CMB temperature and polarization measurements at high multipoles provided by ongoing ground experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19575v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akhil Antony, Fabio Finelli, Dhiraj Kumar Hazra, Daniela Paoletti, Arman Shafieloo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charmoniumlike Channels $1^{+}$ with Isospin $1$ from Lattice and Effective Field Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09842</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09842v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Many exotic charmoniumlike mesons have already been discovered experimentally, of which the $Z_c$ mesons with $I=1$ are prominent examples. We investigate $J^{PC}=1^{+\pm}$ states with flavor $\bar cc\bar qq$ ($q=u,d$) in $I=1$ using lattice QCD. This is the first study of these mesons employing more than one volume and involving frames with nonzero total momentum. We utilize two $N_f=2+1$ CLS ensembles with $m_{\pi}\simeq 280\,$MeV. The simulations are performed with unphysical light quark masses at a single lattice spacing of $a\simeq 0.086\,$fm and omit $\psi(2S)\pi$, $\psi(3770)\pi$ and three-particle decay channels, so our results provide only qualitative insights. Resulting eigenenergies are compatible or just slightly shifted down with respect to noninteracting energies, where the most significant shifts occur for certain $D\bar D^*$ states. Both channels $1^{+\pm}$ have a virtual pole slightly below the threshold if $D\bar D^*$ is assumed to be decoupled from other channels. In addition, we perform a coupled channel analysis of $J/\psi\pi$ and $D\bar D^*$ scattering with $J^{PC}=1^{+-}$ within an effective field theory framework. The $J/\psi\pi$ and $D\bar D^*$ line shapes from BESIII and finite-volume energies from several lattice QCD simulations, including this work, are fitted simultaneously. All fits yield two poles relatively close to the $D\bar D^*$ threshold and reasonably reproduce the experimental $Z_c$ peaks. They also reproduce lattice energies up to slightly above the $D\bar D^*$ threshold, while reproduction at even higher energies is better for fits that put more weight on the lattice data. Our findings suggest that the employed EFT can reasonably reconcile the peaks in the experimental line shapes and the lattice energies, although those lie close to noninteracting energies. We also study $J/\psi\pi$ scattering in s wave and place upper bounds on the phase shift.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09842v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mitja Sadl, Sara Collins, Zhi-Hui Guo, M. Padmanath, Sasa Prelovsek, Lin-Wan Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impacts of dark energy on weighing neutrinos after DESI BAO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15640v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recently, DESI has released baryon acoustic oscillation (BAO) data, and DES has also published its five-year supernova (SN) data. These observations, combined with cosmic microwave background (CMB) data, support a dynamically evolving dark energy at a high confidence level. When using cosmological observations to weigh neutrinos, the results of weighing neutrinos will be significantly affected by the measurement of dark energy due to the degeneracy between neutrino mass and the dark-energy equation of state. Therefore, we need to understand how the dynamical evolution of dark energy in the current situation will affect the measurement of neutrino mass. In this work, we utilize these latest observations and other additional distance measurements to discuss the mutual influence between neutrinos and dark energy, then calculate the Bayes factor to compare models. We consider three neutrino mass hierarchies including degenerate hierarchy (DH), normal hierarchy (NH), and inverted hierarchy (IH), as well as three dark energy models including $\Lambda \rm CDM$, $w\rm CDM$, and $w_0w_a \rm CDM$ models. Cosmological data combined with the prior of particle physics experiments can provide strong to decisive evidence favoring the $w_0w_a {\rm CDM}+\sum m_\nu$ model with NH. In the $w_0w_a \rm CDM$ model, using the CMB+DESI+DESY5 data, we obtain constraints on the total neutrino mass, $\sum m_\nu&lt;0.171\ \rm eV,\ 0.204\ \rm eV,\ 0.220\ \rm eV$, for DH, NH, and IH, respectively. Furthermore, taking into account the neutrino hierarchy or incorporating additional distance measurements results in a more pronounced deviation from the $\Lambda$CDM model for dark energy. The latter, particularly, exhibits a deviation at a confidence level that surpasses $4\sigma$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15640v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guo-Hong Du, Peng-Ju Wu, Tian-Nuo Li, Xin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Axion-Photon Conversion Signals from Neutron Stars with Spacetime Curvature Accounted for in the Magnetosphere Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02263</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02263v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Axions are a well-motivated dark matter candidate. They may be detectable from radio line emission due to resonant conversion in neutron star magnetospheres. While radio data collection for this signal has begun, further efforts are required to solidify the theoretical predictions for the resulting radio lines. Usually, the flat spacetime Goldreich-Julian model of the neutron star magnetosphere is used, while a Schwarzschild geometry is assumed for the ray tracing. We assess the impact of incorporating the spacetime curvature into the magnetosphere model. We examine a range of neutron star and axion masses and find an average difference of $37\%$ and $22\%$ in radiated power compared to the standard Goldreich-Julian magnetosphere model for a $1\mu eV$ and $10\mu eV$ mass axion, respectively, in the case of a $2.2M_\odot$ mass neutron star. A much lesser difference is found for lower-mass neutron stars, as in that case axion-photon conversion occurs further from the Schwarzschild radius.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02263v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.063008</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jesse Satherley, Chris Gordon, Chris Stevens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PREFACE: A search for long-lived particles at the Large Hadron Collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.14598v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Standard Model (SM) fails to explain many problems (neutrino masses, dark matter, and matter-antimatter asymmetry, among others) that may be resolved with new particles beyond the Standard model (BSM). The fact that such new particles are not yet observed may be explained either by their too high mass or by very small coupling to SM particles. The latter case implies long lifetimes. Such long-lived particles (LLPs) would have signatures different from those of SM particles. Searches in the "central region" are covered by the LHC general purpose experiments. The forward small angle region far from the interaction point (IP) is unexplored. Such particles would have large energy $E$ = $\mathcal{O}$(1~TeV) and Lorentz time dilation factor $\gamma = E/m \approx 10^2 - 10^{3}$, hence long decay distances. A new class of specialized LHC detectors dedicated to LLP searches has been proposed for the forward regions. Among these experiments, FASER is already operational, and FACET is under consideration at a location 100 meters from IP5 (the CMS intersection). However, some features of FACET require a specially enlarged beam pipe, which cannot be implemented for Run 4. In this study, we explore a simplified version of the proposed detector, PREFACE, compatible with the standard LHC beam pipe in the HL-LHC in Run 4. Realistic Geant4 simulations are performed and the background is evaluated. A preliminary analysis of the physics potential with the PREFACE geometry indicates that several significant channels could be accessible with sensitivities comparable to FACET and other LLP searches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.14598v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Hacisahinoglu, S. Ozkorucuklu, M. Ovchynnikov, M. G. Albrow, A. Penzo, O. Aydilek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Similar Structure of Loop Amplitudes and Renormalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19300v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the self-similar structure of loop amplitudes in quantum field theory and apply it to amplitude generation and renormalization. A renormalized amplitude can be regarded as an effective coupling that recursively appears within another loop. It is best described as a vertex function from the effective action. It is a scale-dependent, finite, parametrically small and observable quantity appearing in the S-matrix. Replacing a tree-level coupling with a loop amplitude provides a systematic method of generating high-order loop amplitudes, guaranteeing no subamplitude divergence. This method also provides an alternative bottom-up proof to the traditional top-down recursive renormalization of general amplitudes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19300v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kang-Sin Choi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
