<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph</link>
    <description>hep-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 04:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Radially Excited Bottom Mesons in Heavy Quark Effective Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08069v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, Heavy Quark Effective Theory (HQET) is employed to investigate experimentally missing radially excited bottom-meson states. It is an extension of our previous work, in which we had applied HQET for the calculation of charm mesons. By incorporating both theoretical insights and available experimental data on charmed mesons with flavor-symmetry parameters, we computed masses of radially excited bottom-meson states with their strange partners. In addition, decay widths are calculated in the form of hadronic coupling constants $\tilde{\tilde{g}}_{HH}$, $\tilde{\tilde{g}}_{SH}$, $\tilde{\tilde{g}}_{TH}$. By comparing our decay width predictions with available total decay widths, we calculated upper bounds on the corresponding couplings. Regge trajectories are also constructed for our predicted data in planes ($J$, $M^2$ ) and ($n_r$, $M^2$ ), and estimate higher masses ($n = 4$) by fixing Regge slopes and intercepts. Future experimental findings can validate the results obtained in this work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08069v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ritu Garg, Preeti Bhall, K. K Vishwakarma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards AI-assisted Neutrino Flavor Theory Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08080</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08080v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Particle physics theories, such as those which explain neutrino flavor mixing, arise from a vast landscape of model-building possibilities. A model's construction typically relies on the intuition of theorists. It also requires considerable effort to identify appropriate symmetry groups, assign field representations, and extract predictions for comparison with experimental data. We develop an Autonomous Model Builder (AMBer), a framework in which a reinforcement learning agent interacts with a streamlined physics software pipeline to search these spaces efficiently. AMBer selects symmetry groups, particle content, and group representation assignments to construct viable models while minimizing the number of free parameters introduced. We validate our approach in well-studied regions of theory space and extend the exploration to a novel, previously unexamined symmetry group. While demonstrated in the context of neutrino flavor theories, this approach of reinforcement learning with physics software feedback may be extended to other theoretical model-building problems in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08080v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jason Benjamin Baretz, Max Fieg, Vijay Ganesh, Aishik Ghosh, V. Knapp-Perez, Jake Rudolph, Daniel Whiteson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovering the Higgsino at CTAO-North within the Decade</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08084</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08084v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate that higgsino dark matter (DM) could be discovered within the next few years using the Cherenkov Telescope Array Observatory's soon-to-be-operational northern site (CTAO-North). A 1.1 TeV thermal higgsino is a highly motivated yet untested model of DM. Despite its strong theoretical motivation in supersymmetry and beyond, the higgsino is notoriously difficult to detect; it lies deep within the neutrino fog of direct detection experiments and could pose a challenge even for a future muon collider. We show that, in contrast, higgsino detection could be possible within this decade with CTAO-North in La Palma, Spain. The Galactic Center is the region where the dominant DM annihilation signature emerges, but it only barely rises above the horizon at the CTAO-North site. However, we project that this challenge can be overcome with large-zenith-angle observations at the northern site, enabling the conclusive detection of a higgsino signal by 2030 for a range of DM density profiles in the inner Galaxy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08084v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shotaro Abe, Tomohiro Inada, Emmanuel Moulin, Nicholas L. Rodd, Benjamin R. Safdi, Weishuang Linda Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impostor Among $\nu$s: Dark Radiation Masquerading as Self-Interacting Neutrinos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08085v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multiple cosmological observations hint at neutrino self-interactions beyond the Standard Model, yet such interactions face severe constraints from terrestrial experiments. We resolve this tension by introducing a model where active neutrinos resonantly convert to self-interacting dark radiation after BBN but before CMB epoch. This exploits the fact that cosmological observables cannot distinguish between neutrinos and dark radiation with the same abundance and free-streaming properties. Our mechanism, based on a simple Type-I seesaw framework along with a keV-scale scalar mediator, achieves two objectives: (1) it produces strongly self-interacting dark radiation that imitates neutrino self-interactions favored by cosmological data, and (2) it depletes the active neutrino energy density, relaxing cosmological neutrino mass bounds and easing the tension with neutrino oscillation data. The model naturally evades laboratory constraints through suppression of the neutrino-mediator coupling by the squared mass ratio of active and sterile neutrinos. We demonstrate how this scenario is favored over $\Lambda$CDM by the combined Planck and DESI data, while being consistent with all other constraints. Our mechanism is testable in future laboratory probes of absolute neutrino mass and searches for sterile neutrinos.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08085v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anirban Das, P. S. Bhupal Dev, Christina Gao, Subhajit Ghosh, Taegyun Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-Dependent Precision Measurement of $B_s^0\rightarrow \phi \mu^+\mu^-$ Decay at FCC-$ee$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08089v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the feasibility of measuring time-dependent $C\!P$ violation in the rare flavor-changing neutral current (FCNC) decay $B_s^0 \rightarrow \phi(\rightarrow K^+K^-) \mu^+ \mu^-$ at the FCC-$ee$. In the Standard Model (SM), $C\!P$ violation in this mode arises only at higher orders and is highly suppressed. Extensions of the SM, collectively referred to as New Physics (NP), can introduce additional $C\!P$-violating phases that enhance such effects. The decay $B_s^0 \rightarrow \phi \mu^+ \mu^-$, mediated by the $b \rightarrow s \ell^+ \ell^-$ transition, is therefore a promising probe of NP. The FCC-$ee$, operating as a high-luminosity $Z$-factory, offers an optimal environment for this measurement due to its large event yield, clean conditions, efficient particle identification, and excellent vertex resolution. We perform a Monte Carlo study using Pythia and Delphes with the IDEA detector concept. A relative precision better than $\mathcal{O}(1\%)$ on the branching ratio and $\mathcal{O}(10^{-2})$ on the time-integrated $C\!P$ asymmetry is found to be achievable. We determine the projected sensitivities to the observables $D_f$, $C_f$, and $S_f$, which parameterize time-dependent $C\!P$ violation. In the untagged analysis, a precision of $\mathcal{O}(10^{-1})$ on $D_f$ can be reached. With flavor tagging, sensitivities to $C_f$ and $S_f$ improve to $\mathcal{O}(10^{-2})$. These measurements remain inaccessible to current flavor experiments. Interpreting the results within the Weak Effective Theory provides model-independent constraints on $C\!P$-violating NP. This study demonstrates that FCC-$ee$ enables first-time access to $C\!P$-sensitive observables previously beyond experimental reach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08089v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tsz Hong Kwok, Zachary Polonsky, Valeriia Lukashenko, Jason Aebischer, Ben Kilminster</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nucleon Decays into Light New Particles in Neutrino Detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08090</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08090v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Proton and neutron decays into light new particles $X$ can drastically change the experimental signatures and benefit from the complementarity of large water-Cherenkov neutrino detectors such as Super/Hyper-Kamiokande and tracking detectors such as JUNO and DUNE. The proton decays $p\to \ell^+ X$ and $p\to \pi^+ X$ with $m_X$ near phase-space closure lead to charged particles below Cherenkov threshold, rendering them practically invisible in Super- and Hyper-Kamiokande but not in JUNO and DUNE, which are therefore uniquely positioned for these baryon-number-violating signatures despite their smaller size. As an additional signature, such nucleon decays in Earth can produce a sizable flux of $X$ particles in underground detectors. We present a simple model in which nucleons decay into sub-GeV sterile neutrinos that subsequently decay through active-sterile neutrino mixing, with a promisingly large number of events in Super-Kamiokande even in the seesaw-motivated parameter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08090v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julian Heeck, Ian M. Shoemaker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unraveling Freeze-in Dark matter through the echoes of gravitational waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08106v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the quest to unravel the dark sector, feebly interacting freeze-in dark matter presents an intriguing possibility, plausibly explaining the consistent null results from various dark matter experiments. We propose a unique imprint in the form of gravitational waves generated during the freeze-in production of dark matter from heavy particle decay in the early universe. This characteristic gravitational wave signature can serve as a powerful probe for freeze-in dark matter. Our study indicates that future high-frequency gravitational wave experiments can detect these waves, offering a novel avenue to critically test the underlying conditions and requirements of this dark matter paradigm, which typically lie beyond the reach of current and planned dark matter detection experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08106v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Partha Konar, Sudipta Show</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter and CP Violation in Some Symmetry-Constrained 3HDMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08197</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08197v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multi-Higgs-doublet models can accommodate a dark matter candidate. An underlying symmetry not only ensures the candidate's stability but also helps control the number of free parameters. We consider two scenarios. First, we explore dark matter candidates in the $S_3$-symmetric three-Higgs-doublet model. Notably, our findings reveal that the cases we discuss allow for different dark matter mass ranges compared to other candidates within three-Higgs-doublet models. Additionally, we investigate an alternative to conventional stabilisation via discrete symmetries by examining stabilisation through continuous symmetries. This alternative approach exhibits a unique characteristic-the emergence of mass-degenerate states. We also explore the impact of CP violation in the $S_3$-symmetric three-Higgs-doublet model. Our analysis investigates how different representations of quarks under the $S_3$ group, combined with various vacuum configurations, lead to distinct phenomenological consequences, including the possibility of very light neutral scalars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08197v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Kun\v{c}inas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radiative decays of $P$-wave charmed baryons in the $SU(3)$ flavor $\bf6_F$ representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08335v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We perform a comprehensive investigation of the radiative decays of $P$-wave charmed baryons in the $SU(3)$ flavor $\mathbf{6}_F$ representation, employing the light-cone QCD sum rule approach within the framework of heavy quark effective theory. We analyze their electromagnetic transitions into ground-state charmed baryons via photon emission. When combined with the mass spectra and strong decay properties previously studied in Ref.~\cite{Yang:2021lce}, our results constitute a systematic and complete QCD sum rule analysis of the $P$-wave singly charmed baryons within the framework of heavy quark effective theory. As summarized in Table~\ref{tab:result}, several excited charmed baryons are found to possess suppressed strong decay widths, thereby rendering their radiative decay channels particularly significant for experimental identification and theoretical understanding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08335v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuan Luo, Hua-Xing Chen, Er-Liang Cui, Hui-Min Yang, Dan Zhou, Zhi-Yong Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reexamining the search for light ALPs at flavor and forward accelerator experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08342v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The axion-like particle (ALP) is a well-motivated extension of the Standard Model. In this work, we revisit the sensitivity of forward accelerator experiments to light long-lived ALPs, and analyze flavor constraints. Our analysis incorporates recent measurements of the rare decays $B\to K + X$ and $K\to \pi +X$, which place stringent bounds on quark flavor violation of a light ALP. We consider the complete list of hadronic modes in the calculation of the ALP decay rate and exclusive production channels based on recent improvements. The analysis includes the discussion of tree-level quark flavor-violating couplings in addition to a universal flavor-conserving ALP coupling to fermions and the electroweak ALP couplings. Our results demonstrate the complementarity of heavy meson decays and forward accelerator facilities in probing light ALPs. The interplay between two ALP couplings is also investigated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08342v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tong Li, Michael A. Schmidt, Man Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radiative decay of $\chi_{c1}$ states in effective Lagrangian approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08406v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The $\chi_{c1}(3872)$ state, first observed by the Belle collaboration with its quantum numbers identified as $J^{PC} = 1^{++}$, has been the subject of extensive research due to its intriguing properties. Several theoretical interpretations have been proposed to explain its unique characteristics, including the $\chi_{c1}(2P)$ assignment, a molecular $\bar{D}^{*}D/\bar{D}D^{*}$ configuration, a coupled-channel framework incorporating $c\bar{c}$ and di-meson degrees of freedom, and the compact tetraquark hypothesis. However, challenges remain in reconciling its mass coincidence with the threshold and the observed isospin violation within both the pure $c\bar{c}$ and compact tetraquark models. In this study, we examine the radiative decays of the $\chi_{c1}(1P)$ and $\chi_{c1}(3872)$ states in an effective field theory framework, incorporating triangle loops of $D$ and $D^{*}$ mesons. The model parameters are calibrated based on the observed branching fraction of the radiative decay mode $\chi_{c1}(1P) \to J/\psi \gamma$. Utilizing these fixed parameters, we predict the branching fractions $R_{\chi_{c1}(3872) \to J/\psi \gamma} \sim 10^{-1}$ and $R_{\chi_{c1}(3872) \to \psi(2S) \gamma} \sim 10^{-2}$, and the relative fraction $\mathcal{R}_{\Psi\gamma} \approx 0.109$. The work supports the argument that the $\chi_{c1}(3872)$ is unlikely a $c\bar{c}$ state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08406v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thanat Sangkhakrit, Attaphon Kaewsnod, Ayut Limphirat, Khanchai Khosonthongkee, Warintorn Sreethawong, Nopmanee Supanam, Yupeng Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An interpretation of the fully-charmed scalar state $X(6200)$ as a molecular di-meson</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08589v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The LHCb Collaboration recently observed new structures in the invariant mass spectrum of $J/\psi J/\psi$ meson pairs produced in proton-proton collisions, including a narrow peak around $6.2$ GeV. This study investigates the thermal behavior of this newly discovered fully-charm resonance, assuming it to be an $\eta_c\eta_c$ molecule with quantum numbers $J^{PC} = 0^{++}$. Employing thermal QCD sum rules up to dimension four, we analyze the temperature dependence of the mass and the decay constant. Our results indicate that both physical quantities decrease as the temperature rises. Notably, at zero temperature, the mass and decay constant of the state are consistent with those reported in the existing literature. These findings are expected to provide valuable insights for future experimental investigations in this field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08589v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\"O. E. Demircan, H. Da\u{g}, H. Sundu, J. Y. S\"ung\"u, E. V. Veliev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Axion-like particle constraints from preSN in future experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08610v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We extend the study of the search for ALP-photon emissions from a Supernovae (SNe) progenitor, the Red Supergiant Star (RGS), as Betelgeuse, arising through a combination of Bremsstrahlung, Compton, and Primako? processes, in the hard-X and MeV energy range, using the next proposed and future experiments, such as COMCUBE, GECCO, COSI, AMEGO-X, and e-ASTROGAM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08610v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.22323/1.474.0032</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PoS (2024) volume 474, pages 032</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Federica Giacchino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$D$ and $D^*$ mesons in isospin asymmetric nuclear medium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08707</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08707v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the properties of pseudoscalar $D$ and vector $D^*$ mesons in an isospin asymmetric nuclear medium using a hybrid approach that integrates the light-front quark model with the chiral SU(3) quark mean field model. The influence of isospin asymmetric nuclear medium is examined by utilizing the in-medium quark masses derived from the chiral SU(3) quark mean field model as an input in the light-front quark model to study the medium modification of $D$ mesons. We examine the impact of isospin asymmetry and baryon density at zero and finite temperature on the effective masses, weak decay constants, and distribution amplitudes of the pseudoscalar mesons $D^0$, $D^+$, $D_s$, and the vector mesons $D^{0*}$, $D^{+*}$, and $D_s^*$. Our results indicate significant medium-induced changes for pseudoscalar $D$ and vector $D^*$ mesons having $u/d$ as one of their constituent quarks, while a comparatively reduced effect is observed for mesons containing a strange quark. In contrast to temperature and isospin asymmetry, changes in the baryon density of the nuclear medium have a larger effect on different properties of $D$ and $D^*$ mesons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08707v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anshu Gautam, Dhananjay Singh, Navpreet Kaur, Satyajit Puhan, Suneel Dutt, Harleen Dahiya, Arvind Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement Suppression, Quantum Statistics and Symmetries in Spin-3/2 Baryon Scatterings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08960v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the interplay among entanglement suppression, quantum statistics and enhanced symmetries in the non-relativistic $S$-wave scattering involving the lowest-lying spin-3/2 baryons, which can be considered as four-dimensional qudits. These baryons form a ten-dimensional representation (decuplet) under the $\text{SU}(3)$ light-flavor symmetry and, in this limit, are considered indistinguishable under strong interactions. Treating the $S$-matrix in the spin-3/2 baryon-baryon scattering as a quantum logic gate in the spin space, we study the consequence of entanglement suppression and compute the entanglement power of the $S$-matrix. When the entanglement power vanishes, the $S$-matrix is either an Identity or a SWAP gate and spin-flavor symmetries and/or non-relativistic conformal invariance emerge, as previously observed in spin-1/2 baryons. In the case of scattering identical particles, the entanglement power never vanishes due to constraints from spin statistics, which we interpret as projection-valued measurements onto symmetric or antisymmetric Hilbert space and define the entanglement power accordingly. When the entanglement power is non-vanishing but sits at a global or local minimum, enhanced symmetries still emerge and the $S$-matrix can be interpreted as an Identity or a SWAP gate acting on the restricted Hilbert space allowed by quantum statistics. In general, when scattering identical spin-$s$ particles, we identify an enhanced $\text{SU}(2s+1)_{\text{spin}}$ symmetry for the Identity gate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08960v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tao-Ran Hu, Katsuyoshi Sone, Feng-Kun Guo, Testuo Hyodo, Ian Low</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Highest-Energy Neutrino Event Constrains Dark Matter-Neutrino Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08993</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08993v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dark Matter-neutrino interactions affect the propagation of astrophysical neutrinos, attenuating the flux of neutrinos arriving at Earth. Using the highest-energy neutrino event detected to date by the KM3NeT collaboration as an example, and assuming an extragalactic origin, we derive limits on these interactions at $E_\nu = 220^{+570}_{-110}\, \mathrm{PeV}$. Considering only the propagation on the Milky Way Dark Matter halo, we constrain the interaction cross section over the mass of the Dark Matter candidate to be, $\sigma_{\rm DM-\nu}/m_{\rm DM} \lesssim 10^{-22}$~cm$^2$~GeV$^{-1}$. If a transient source was positively identified, the high-energy neutrino would have crossed the dark-matter halo of the source host as well, resulting in more stringent constraints (e.g., up to $ \sim$ 6 orders of magnitude assuming the blazar PKS 0605-085 is the source). These bounds on the Dark Matter-neutrino interaction cross section are translated into limits on the mass of the Dark Matter candidate, the mass of the mediator, and the coupling strength for different simplified models. In particular, we find that the KM3-230213A high-energy event sets the most stringent constraints on models where the scattering cross section rises in the high-energy limit. We identify vector Dark Matter interacting with neutrinos via vector mediators as the most promising scenario, and show that high-energy neutrinos provide world-leading limits in this model, testing the region of parameter space motivated by thermal freeze-out.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08993v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Toni Bert\'olez-Mart\'inez, Gonzalo Herrera, Pablo Mart\'inez-Mirav\'e, Jorge Terol Calvo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Event generation at MEPS@NLO accuracy in neutral and charged current DIS at the EIC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08994</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08994v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the first hadron-level predictions at MEPS@NLO precision for both neutral and charged current DIS at the EIC and the first application of the MEPS@NLO technique to charged current DIS in general. We critically examine state-of-the-art inclusive predictions using multi-leg merging techniques, contrasting perturbative and non-perturbative uncertainties. We study typical kinematic DIS observables as well as jet measurements and 1-jettiness with realistic cuts implied by expected and past detector resolution. On the perturbative side, we see large corrections towards small virtualities and Bjorken-x, which can be captured by higher-multiplicity matrix elements and the merging procedure. Non-perturbative effects, while negligible in most jet observables, can reach similar size as the perturbative uncertainties around the peak of the 1-jettiness distributions especially at low values of $Q^2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08994v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Meinzinger, Daniel Reichelt, Federico Silvetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deconstructing resonant Higgs pair production at the LHC: effects of coloured and neutral scalars in the NMSSM test case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09006</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.09006v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study resonant production of pairs of Standard Model (SM)-like Higgs bosons, in the presence of new neutral Higgs states together with new coloured scalars (stops or sbottoms) in loops within the Next-to-Minimal Supersymmetric SM (NMSSM). This is used as a test case to prove that the Large Hadron Collider has sensitivity to a variety of effects stemming from interferences between resonant (heavy) Higgs diagrams and/or among these and non-resonant topologies involving loops of both tops and stops. These effects can alter significantly the naive description of individual $s$-channel Breit-Wigner resonances, leading to distortions of the latter which, on the one hand, may mask their presence but, on the other hand, could enable one to extract features of the underlying new physics scenario. This last aspect is made possible through a decomposition of the $gg\to hh$ signal process into all its amplitude components, each of which has a well-defined coupling structure. Ultimately, such effects can be traced back to the relevant Feynman diagrams and can enable a detailed interpretation of this process. To illustrate this, we introduce various Benchmark Points that exhibit potentially observable features during the current and/or upcoming runs of the LHC in one or more of the three customary di-Higgs decay channels: $b\bar bb\bar b$, $b\bar b \tau^+\tau^-$ and $b\bar b\gamma\gamma$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.09006v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Moretti, Luca Panizzi, J\"orgen Sj\"olin, Harri Waltari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinetically Coupled Dark Matter Condensates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08076v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Dark matter consisting of ultralight bosons can form a macroscopic Bose-Einstein condensate with distinctive observational signatures. While this possibility has been extensively studied for axions and axion-like particles $-$ pseudoscalars with masses protected by shift symmetry $-$ realistic models from string theory and other higher-dimensional theories predict more complex structures. Here we investigate a two-field generalization where an axion couples to a moduli field through its kinetic term, representing the phase and radial modes of a complex scalar field. We demonstrate that when this system forms a gravitationally bound Bose-Einstein condensate, the kinetic coupling produces dramatic modifications to cosmological evolution compared to the canonical single-field case. Most notably, the axion Jeans scale becomes dynamically dependent on the moduli field's evolution, fundamentally altering structure formation. By mapping existing observational constraints from canonical axion models to our two-field scenario, we identify regions of parameter space that are already excluded by current observations. In particular, consistency with observations requires that the moduli field must take on small field values, $\chi/M_{\rm pl} \ll 1$, throughout most of cosmic history for this class of axions to remain a viable description of all dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08076v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael W. Toomey, Savvas M. Koushiappas, Stephon Alexander</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbative K\"ahler Moduli Inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08083</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08083v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we present two classes of inflationary models in the framework of type IIB string theory. The inflatons correspond to blow-up K\"ahler modulus arising from compactifying type IIB on a Calabi-Yau. Using perturbative corrections, we first highlight a procedure for stabilising more than one K\"ahler modulus. For the case of two K\"ahler moduli, we explicitly construct two class of inflationary potentials within the K\"ahler cone which satisfy both EFT and cosmological constraints. The first class of models, arising from moduli redefinition of the blow-up mode, have a potential of the form $V(\phi)=V_0(1+C_1 \phi^{2/3})$ align with CMB data with scalar-to-tensor ratio $r\lesssim 10^{-2}$. The second class of models, which have been recently proposed in the name of loop blow-up inflation, have a form $V(\phi)=V_0(1+C_2\phi^{-2/3})$ also agrees with CMB data with scalar-to tensor-ratio $r\lesssim 10^{-8}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08083v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mishaal Hai, Ahmed Rakin Kamal, Noshin Ferdous Shamma, Md Shaikot Jahan Shuvo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dense Matter in Neutron Stars with eXTP</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08104v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this White Paper, we present the potential of the enhanced X-ray Timing and Polarimetry (eXTP) mission to constrain the equation of state of dense matter in neutron stars, exploring regimes not directly accessible to terrestrial experiments. By observing a diverse population of neutron stars - including isolated objects, X-ray bursters, and accreting systems - eXTP's unique combination of timing, spectroscopy, and polarimetry enables high-precision measurements of compactness, spin, surface temperature, polarimetric signals, and timing irregularity. These multifaceted observations, combined with advances in theoretical modeling, pave the way toward a comprehensive description of the properties and phases of dense matter from the crust to the core of neutron stars. Under development by an international Consortium led by the Institute of High Energy Physics of the Chinese Academy of Sciences, the eXTP mission is planned to be launched in early 2030.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08104v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ang Li, Anna L. Watts, Guobao Zhang, Sebastien Guillot, Yanjun Xu, Andrea Santangelo, Silvia Zane, Hua Feng, Shuang-Nan Zhang, Mingyu Ge, Liqiang Qi, Tuomo Salmi, Bas Dorsman, Zhiqiang Miao, Zhonghao Tu, Yuri Cavecchi, Xia Zhou, Xiaoping Zheng, Weihua Wang, Quan Cheng, Xuezhi Liu, Yining Wei, Wei Wang, Yujing Xu, Shanshan Weng, Weiwei Zhu, Zhaosheng Li, Lijing Shao, Youli Tuo, Akira Dohi, Ming Lyu, Peng Liu, Jianping Yuan, Mingyang Wang, Wenda Zhang, Zexi Li, Lian Tao, Liang Zhang, Hong Shen, Constan\c{c}a Provid\^encia, Laura Tolos, Alessandro Patruno, Li Li, Guozhu Liu, Kai Zhou, Lie-Wen Chen, Yizhong Fan, Toshitaka Kajino, Dong Lai, Xiangdong Li, Jie Meng, Xiaodong Tang, Zhigang Xiao, Shaolin Xiong, Renxin Xu, Shan-Gui Zhou, David R. Ballantyne, G. Fiorella Burgio, J\'er\^ome Chenevez, Devarshi Choudhury, Anthea F. Fantina, Duncan K. Galloway, Francesca Gulminelli, Kai Hebeler, Mariska Hoogkamer, Yves Kini, Aleksi Kurkela, Manuel Linares, J\'er\^ome Margueron, Melissa Mendes, Micaela Oertel, Alessandro Papitto, Juri Poutanen, Nanda Rea, Achim Schwenk, Isak Svensson, David Tsang, Aleksi Vuorinen, Nils Andersson, M. Coleman Miller, Luciano Rezzolla, Jirina R. Stone, Anthony W. Thomas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Behaviour of $\alpha$-attractors in Warm Inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08489v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The $\alpha$-attractor models of inflation have remained one of the preferred inflationary models for nearly a decade now. The unique attractor nature of these models in the $n_s-r$ plane have put these models in the sweet-spot of the $n_s-r$ measurement of Planck observations. In this article, we analyse the behaviour of such attractor models in a Warm Inflation setup to investigate whether the attractor nature of these models can be retained even when the dynamics deviates from the standard Cold inflationary dynamics. We have chosen to analyse these models in a strongly dissipative Warm inflation setup, namely the Minimal Warm Inflation, as in such a setup the inflationary dynamics significantly departs from the standard Cold inflation dynamics. We observe that the departure from the standard Cold inflation dynamics destroys the unique attractor nature of such models. The analysis clearly indicates that the attractor nature of these $\alpha$-attractor models is quite unique to the standard Cold inflationary dynamics. However, on a positive note, the analysis indicates that the $\alpha$-attractor models may be made in tune with the recent ACT results in Warm inflation for certain parameter ranges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08489v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dibya Chakraborty, Suratna Das</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for Long-Lived Particles in Free Neutron Experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08701v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explore the decay of free neutrons into exotic long-lived particles, whose decays could be detected in the next-generation free neutron experiments. We show that such a possibility is viable as long as the exotic particle is highly mass-degenerate with the neutron, avoiding exclusion by large-volume detectors. We estimate the number of observable events and identify the most promising final states from both theoretical and experimental perspectives. Our analysis highlights the unique capability of the HIBEAM-NNBAR experiment at the European Spallation Source to probe this unexplored region of parameter space, opening a new avenue for exploring physics beyond the Standard Model. We estimate that several events per year could be observed in the NNBAR experiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08701v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Meirose, R. Nieuwenhuis, R. Pasechnik, H. Gisbert, L. Vale Silva, D. Milstead</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heavy-heavy and heavy-light mesons in cold nuclear matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08946v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We review the in-medium modifications of effective masses (Lorentz scalar potentials or phenomenon of mass shift) of heavy-heavy and heavy-light mesons in symmetric nuclear matter and their nuclear bound states. We use a combined approach with the quark-meson coupling (QMC) model and an effective Lagrangian. As demonstrated by the cases of pionic and kaonic atoms, studies of meson-nucleus bound state can provide us with important information on chiral symmetry in dense nuclear medium. In this review, we treat the mesons, $K, K^*, D, D^*, B, B^*, \eta, \eta', \phi, \eta_c, J/\psi, \eta_b, \Upsilon$, and $B_c$, where our emphasys is on the heavy mesons. In addition, we also present some new results for the $B_c$-nucleus bound states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08946v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/sym17050787</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Symmetry 2025, 17(5), 787</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>J. J. Cobos-Mart\'inez, Guilherme N. Zeminiani, Kazuo Tsushima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Threshold resummation for the production of four top quarks at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03259</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.03259v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We compute the total cross section for $t\bar{t}t\bar{t}$ production at next-to-leading logarithmic (NLL$^{\prime}$) accuracy. This is the first time resummation is performed for a hadron-collider process with four colored particles in the final state. The calculation is matched to the next-to-leading order strong and electroweak corrections. The NLL$^{\prime}$ corrections enhance the total production rate by 26\%. The size of the theoretical error due to scale variation is reduced by close to a factor of two, bringing the theoretical error significantly below the current experimental uncertainty of the measurement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.03259v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Melissa van Beekveld, Anna Kulesza, Laura Moreno Valero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tamed loops: A way to obtain finite loop results without UV divergences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.18104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.18104v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For loops with UV divergences, assuming that the physical contributions of loops from UV regions are insignificant, a method of UV-free scheme described by an equation is introduced to derive loop results without UV divergences in calculations, i.e., a route of the analytic continuation $\mathcal{T}_\mathrm{F} \to \mathcal{T}_\mathrm{P}$ besides the traditional route $\infty - \infty$ in mathematical structure. This scheme provides a new perspective to an open question of the hierarchy problem of Higgs mass, i.e., an alternative interpretation without fine-tuning within the standard model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.18104v5</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lian-Bao Jia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$B_{s}^0\to K^0\overline{K}{}^0$ beyond the Standard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13506v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Within the Standard Model, the branching fraction of the rare decay $B_s\to K^0\bar K^0$ is related to other decay rates and CP asymmetries through the approximate $SU(3)$ flavor symmetry of the strong interactions and the heavy-quark limit. Three such relations were shown to be violated at a level of about $3\sigma$ each. By means of a systematic search for new-physics explanations of these puzzles, we find that possible solutions are highly fine-tuned and either excluded by other data or rather implausible. The tight correlation between $B_s\to K\bar K$ and $B\to\pi K$ decays, which is maintained even in the presence of flavor-specific new-physics operators, plays a central role in our analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13506v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 05 (2025) 210</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yuval Grossman, Yosef Nir, Matthias Neubert, Yogev Shpilman, Yehonatan Viernik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proton Lifetime in Minimal Supersymmetric SU(5) with Gauge Mediation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.06239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.06239v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we discuss the predicted proton lifetimes in minimal supersymmetric (SUSY) $SU(5)$ grand unified theory (GUT) with gauge mediated supersymmetry breaking (GMSB). We focus on the case of $\mathbf{5} + \mathbf{\bar{5}}$ messengers and determine the low-scale mass spectrum of the scalar particles and gauginos using the renormalization group equations. With the obtained mass spectrum, we calculate the dominant proton decay mode for SUSY $SU(5)$ GUT, $p \to K^+ \bar{\nu}$. In our setup, we assume the messenger scale to be $\mathcal{O}(10^3)$ TeV in order to obtain a proper Higgs mass in GMSB scenario. For this messenger scale, we find the proton lifetime is consistent with current experimental limits and can be tested by future proton decay experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.06239v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-025-14368-7</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jason L. Evans, Yoshihiro Shigekami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermomagnetic effects on light pseudo-scalar meson masses within the SU(3) Nambu-Jona--Lasinio model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05568v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We calculate the screening masses of pseudoscalar mesons in a hot and strongly magnetized medium within the framework of the SU(3) Nambu-Jona--Lasinio model, using a magnetic field-independent regularization scheme. Inverse magnetic catalysis (IMC) is implemented through the use of a magnetic field-dependent coupling $G(B)$, fitted to reproduce lattice quantum chromodynamics (QCD) results for the pseudocritical chiral transition temperature $T_c^B$. For the external homogeneous magnetic field considered, neutral screening masses separate in two types: perpendicular and parallel to the direction of the field, while for charged mesons only parallel energies can be defined for each Landau level. We obtain $m_{\mathrm{scr},\perp} &gt; m_{\mathrm{scr},\parallel}$, as expected from causality. Thermally, all screening energies are almost constant until some critical temperature, whose behavior is correlated with $T_c^B$. They rapidly increase around this value, keeping a steady enhancement afterward due to thermal excitation. Magnetically, neutral parallel masses are enhanced (suppressed) at high temperatures when considering $G(B)$ ($G$). Perpendicular ones display a non-monotonic magnetic behavior for $G$ (due to increasing $T_c^B$) when $T \lesssim 500$~MeV, but become magnetically enhanced when $T \gtrsim 500$~MeV. For $G(B)$ they always increase with $B$. Charged parallel energies are always magnetically enhanced, for both couplings. In the high-temperature limit, we show that both neutral and charged screening energies converge to $2\pi T$. At $B=0$ the model overestimates the remaining quark interaction in this regime. At $B\neq 0$ we find that, when IMC is accounted for, the interaction is suppressed as $B$ increases, a fact that appears to be at odds with currently available lattice QCD results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05568v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.114036</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 114036 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M\'aximo Coppola, William R. Tavares, Sidney S. Avancini, Joana C. Sodr\'e, Norberto N. Scoccola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Left-right asymmetry calculation comparisons and projected sensitivity to the weak mixing angle in polarized Bhabha scattering at 10.58 GeV</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16592v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Consideration is being given to upgrading the SuperKEKB electron-positron collider with the introduction of electron-beam polarization. This would enable a unique precision electroweak physics program that opens new ways to search for physics beyond the Standard Model. The upgrade would enable Belle II to make a number of high precision measurements, one of which is the left-right cross-section asymmetry in the $e^+e^-\rightarrow e^+e^-$ Bhabha scattering process. The expected level of precision in such a measurement will require the theoretical values of the asymmetry to be calculated at least to the next-to-leading order (NLO) level, and the implementation of simulation event generators with a similar level of precision. In this study, we compare the calculations of the ReneSANCe Monte Carlo generator with those of an independent NLO calculation to determine the level of agreement in this process. A 2.3% difference between the calculations is found and attributed to some higher-order effects being accounted for in the ReneSANCe generator. Using the published Belle II efficiency for selecting Bhabha events and assuming a 40 ab$^{-1}$ dataset having 70% polarization, the projected uncertainty on the weak mixing angle, sin$^2\theta_W$ , is calculated using ReneSANCe to be $\pm$0.00032 or better. Combining this with left-right asymmetry measurements from muons and taus under the assumption of lepton universality yields a projected overall uncertainty of $\pm$0.00019 on sin$^2\theta_W$ with SuperKEKB upgraded to have polarized electron beams.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16592v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/d462-zrcl</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Caleb Miller, J. Michael Roney</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-driven analysis of the $\gamma\gamma^*\rightarrow\pi^0$ system using mathematical models and the role of feedback-loop dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03403</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03403v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The data behavior of the pion-photon transition form factor (TFF) is discussed using a nonlinear mathematical model with two parameters $B$ and $C$. Analysis shows that the model's inherent inhibition provides a precondition for the asymptotic saturation of the TFF in agreement with perturbative QCD. Integral to this derivation is the use of a novel fundamental relation between the half-saturated TFF and its asymptotic limit given by $B$. This helps avoid the determination of the location of the TFF at infinite momentum by estimating instead the maximum slope of the curve at $Q^2=C$. In conjunction with the $1\sigma(B,C)$ confidence ellipse, this framework provides an improved fit to the Belle data by setting stronger constraints on the fitting parameters and taking into account the sensitivity to third-party events below Belle's kinematic coverage. Without inhibition, the slope of the TFF curve would continue to grow so that saturation towards the asymptotic QCD limit would not be achieved. In order to compare the key features of TFF fit models to upcoming high-precision data in a standardized way, a conformity protocol in terms of QCD-based criteria is worked out. Adopting a broader perspective, we show that the asymptotic saturation of an inhibited TFF fit curve is analogous to a mechanical system driven by a feedback-loop mechanism in control theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03403v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. G. Stefanis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $Z_c(3900)$ in hadronic molecule and triangle singularity at finite temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19374</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19374v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Studying exotic hadrons is a challenge against the conventional quark model, providing us with a good platform to deepen our understanding of the strong interaction. An inclusive study of the exotic hadrons in vacuum and at finite temperature is an intriguing approach to shed light on their nature. As a first step, we study the $Z_c(3900)$ in both the $D\bar{D}^\ast$ hadronic molecular and the triangle singularity pictures, and discuss the behaviors of $Z_c(3900)$ at finite temperature in these two different pictures. As the result, we show the properties that its mass becomes smaller and its width becomes larger when the temperature increases, which are seen commonly in the hadronic molecular picture and in the triangle singularity picture. The enhanced widths in hot medium indicate that the $Z_c(3900)$ will be dissociated at sufficiently high temperature. This feature is also reflected by the decrease of the effective couplings in the hadronic molecular picture. It is concluded that, not only in vacuum but also in hot medium, the behaviors of $Z_{c}(3900)$ are similar in the two different interpretations of $Z_c(3900)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19374v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/5nlp-vwrc</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ying Zhang, Atsushi Hosaka, Qian Wang, Shigehiro Yasui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Efimov states in $D^*D^*D^*$ and $DD^*D^*$ three-body systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19709v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Efimov effect is an intriguing three-body quantum phenomenon. Searching for Efimov states within the realms of nuclear and hadronic physics presents a challenge due to the inherent inability of natural physical systems to exhibit adjustable two-body scattering lengths. In this study, we examine the potential existence of Efimov states in the $D^*D^*D^*$ and $DD^*D^*$ three-hadron systems. Utilizing a pionless effective field theory framework, we determine that the presence of Efimov states in the spectrum of the $D^*D^*D^*$ system is contingent upon the existence of an $(I,J)=(1,2)$ $D^*D^*$ two-body bound system. If only the $T_{cc}^+$ and its heavy quark spin partner $T_{cc}^{*+}$ exist while there is no near-threshold pole in all other $S$-wave $D^{(*)}D^*$ scattering amplitudes, no Efimov effect is expected in the $D^{(*)}D^*D^*$ systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19709v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hai-Long Fu, Yong-Hui Lin, Feng-Kun Guo, Hans-Werner Hammer, Ulf-G. Mei{\ss}ner, Akaki Rusetsky, Xu Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hidden charmed decays of $X(3872)$ within the $D{\bar D}^*$ molecular framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20183v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The dipionic transition of the $X(3872)$ to the $\eta_c$ was investigated using an effective Lagrangian approach. In this study, the $X(3872)$ was assumed to be a $D\bar{D}^\ast + \text{c.c.}$ bound state with the quantum numbers $J^{PC}=1^{++}$ and to decay via triangle and box loops. It is found that the partial decay widths arising from the box loops are one order of magnitude greater than those from the triangle ones. The decay widths are model-dependent, as characterized by the cutoff parameter introduced in the form factor. Moreover, the charged and neutral $D\bar{D}^\ast$ configurations of the $X(3872)$ and its mass also influence the decay widths. With our model parameters, the decay widths for the $X(3872)\to\pi^+\pi^-\eta_c$ can reach up to several tens of keV. We hope that the current calculations within the molecular interpretation will be helpful for the future experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20183v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao-Dong Cai, Zhao-Sai Jia, Gang Li, Shi-Dong Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement Negativity of Spin-Orbit Correlations in a general Qubit-Qudit Setup</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21048</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21048v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the complete eigenvalue spectrum of the partially transposed density matrix for a pure bipartite quantum state acting on a generic $2 \otimes n$ Hilbert space. The spectrum contains four non-zero eigenvalues, as, \begin{eqnarray} \lambda_{1,2}=\pm \sqrt{A}, ~~~ \lambda_{3,4}= \frac{1}{2}(1\pm\sqrt{1-4 A}), \nonumber \end{eqnarray} where $A$ is the determinant of the reduced density matrix (traced over the larger subspace). As $0 \leqslant A \leqslant1/4$, only one is negative among the four non-trivial eigenvalues. Within this qubit-qudit framework, we further studied the negativity as a measure of entanglement for the case of spin-orbit correlation of partons inside a proton. The entanglement negativity for spin-orbit correlations is found to be related to the gluon helicity PDF and the Hermitian angle of the associated Hilbert space for linearly polarized protons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21048v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanskriti Agrawal, Raktim Abir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Concurrent Exploration of Axion-Like Particle Interactions with Gauge Bosons at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21305</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21305v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Axion-like particles (ALPs) are pseudo Nambu-Goldstone bosons associated with spontaneously broken global symmetries incorporated in the Standard Model (SM) Lagrangian in many models beyond the SM. The existence of a light ALP is plausible due to the long-standing problems that the SM has not been able to address, such as the dark matter (DM) problem and the observed matter-antimatter asymmetry. There are many proposals in recent decades considering the ALP as a solution to some of these shortcomings. Motivated by such potential, we search for ALPs with a mass of 1 MeV at the LHC in a model-independent fashion. We explore two complementary production modes: ALP production in association with a pair of electroweak gauge bosons ($ZZ$ or $WW$) and ALP production in association with a single gauge boson ($W$ or $Z$) plus jets. For the $VV+a$ final state, signal and dominant SM backgrounds are generated, and a realistic detector response simulation is performed. A multivariate analysis is employed to discriminate the $VV+a$ signal from background processes, and the expected $95\%$ confidence level (CL) exclusion limits in two-dimensional parameter spaces involving the ALP couplings are subsequently derived. The $V$+jets channel is interpreted using LHC measurements in regimes where the ALP escapes detection, appearing as missing energy. The two analyses are complementary: both the $VV+a$ and the $V$+jets channels probe simultaneously the ALP couplings to gluons and to electroweak gauge bosons. While the $VV+a$ channel offers clean multi-lepton final states and direct reconstruction of the $ZZ$ or $WW$ system, the $V$+jets channel benefits from larger production cross sections, enabling stronger constraints in certain regions of the parameter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21305v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2025.116969</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nucl.Phys.B 1018 (2025) 116969</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shirin Chenarani, Mojtaba Mohammadi Najafabadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Gaussianities and Primordial Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06151v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The most promising mechanism of generating PBHs is by the enhancement of power spectrum of the primordial curvature perturbation, which is usually accompanied by the the enhancement of non-Gaussianity that crucially changes the abundance of PBHs. In this review I will discuss how non-Gaussianity is generated in single field inflation as well as in the curvaton scenario, and then discuss how to calculate PBH mass function and induced gravitational waves (GWs) with such non-Gaussianities. When the PBH abundance is fixed, non-Gaussianity only has mild impact on the spectral shape of the induced GWs, which gives relatively robust predictions in the mHz and nHz GW experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06151v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-981-97-8887-3_7</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Shi Pi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Galaxy Tomography with the Gravitational Wave Background from Supermassive Black Hole Binaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05906v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The detection of a stochastic gravitational wave background by pulsar timing arrays suggests the presence of a supermassive black hole binary population. Although the observed spectrum generally matches predictions for orbital evolution driven by gravitational-wave emission in circular orbits, there is a preference for a spectral turnover at the lowest observed frequencies, which may point to a significant hardening phase transitioning from early environmental influences to later stages dominated by gravitational-wave emission. In the vicinity of these binaries, the ejection of stars or dark matter particles through gravitational three-body slingshots efficiently extracts orbital energy, leading to a low-frequency turnover in the spectrum. We model how the gravitational-wave spectrum depends on the initial inner galactic profile prior to scouring by binary ejections, accounting for a range of initial binary eccentricities. By analyzing the NANOGrav 15-year data, we find that a parsec-scale galactic center density of around $10^6\,M_\odot/\mathrm{pc}^3$ is favored across most of the parameter space, shedding light on environmental effects that shape black hole evolution and the combined matter density near galaxy centers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05906v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Chen (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Matthias Daniel (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Daniel J. D'Orazio (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Xuanye Fan (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Andrea Mitridate (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Laura Sagunski (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Xiao Xue (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Gabriella Agazie (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Akash Anumarlapudi (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Anne M. Archibald (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Zaven Arzoumanian (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Jeremy G. Baier (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Paul T. Baker (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Bence B\'ecsy (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Laura Blecha (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Adam Brazier (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Paul R. Brook (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Sarah Burke-Spolaor (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Rand Burnette (The NANOGrav Collaboration), J. Andrew Casey-Clyde (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Maria Charisi (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Shami Chatterjee (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Tyler Cohen (The NANOGrav Collaboration), James M. Cordes (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Neil J. Cornish (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Fronefield Crawford (The NANOGrav Collaboration), H. Thankful Cromartie (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Kathryn Crowter (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Megan E. DeCesar (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Paul B. Demorest (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Heling Deng (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Lankeswar Dey (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Timothy Dolch (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Elizabeth C. Ferrara (The NANOGrav Collaboration), William Fiore (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Emmanuel Fonseca (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Gabriel E. Freedman (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Emiko C. Gardiner (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Nate Garver-Daniels (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Peter A. Gentile (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Kyle A. Gersbach (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Joseph Glaser (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Deborah C. Good (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Kayhan G\"ultekin (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Jeffrey S. Hazboun (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Ross J. Jennings (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Aaron D. Johnson (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Megan L. Jones (The NANOGrav Collaboration), David L. Kaplan (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Luke Zoltan Kelley (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Matthew Kerr (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Joey S. Key (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Nima Laal (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Michael T. Lam (The NANOGrav Collaboration), William G. Lamb (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Bjorn Larsen (The NANOGrav Collaboration), T. Joseph W. Lazio (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Natalia Lewandowska (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Tingting Liu (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Duncan R. Lorimer (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Jing Luo (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Ryan S. Lynch (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Chung-Pei Ma (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Dustin R. Madison (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Alexander McEwen (The NANOGrav Collaboration), James W. McKee (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Maura A. McLaughlin (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Natasha McMann (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Bradley W. Meyers (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Patrick M. Meyers (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Chiara M. F. Mingarelli (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Cherry Ng (The NANOGrav Collaboration), David J. Nice (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Stella Koch Ocker (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Ken D. Olum (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Timothy T. Pennucci (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Benetge B. P. Perera (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Polina Petrov (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Nihan S. Pol (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Henri A. Radovan (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Scott M. Ransom (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Paul S. Ray (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Joseph D. Romano (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Jessie C. Runnoe (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Alexander Saffer (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Shashwat C. Sardesai (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Ann Schmiedekamp (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Carl Schmiedekamp (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Kai Schmitz (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Brent J. Shapiro-Albert (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Xavier Siemens (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Joseph Simon (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Magdalena S. Siwek (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Sophia V. Sosa Fiscella (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Ingrid H. Stairs (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Daniel R. Stinebring (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Kevin Stovall (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Abhimanyu Susobhanan (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Joseph K. Swiggum (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Jacob Taylor (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Stephen R. Taylor (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Jacob E. Turner (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Caner Unal (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Michele Vallisneri (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Rutger van Haasteren (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Sarah J. Vigeland (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Haley M. Wahl (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Caitlin A. Witt (The NANOGrav Collaboration), David Wright (The NANOGrav Collaboration), Olivia Young (The NANOGrav Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on axion-like particles using lattice QCD calculations of the rate for $J/\psi \to \gamma a$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06721</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06721v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A key search mode for axion-like particles (ALPs) that couple to charm quarks is $J/\psi \to \gamma a$. Here we calculate the form factor that allows the rate of this process to be determined using lattice QCD for the first time. Our calculations use the relativistic Highly Improved Staggered Quark (HISQ) action for the valence charm quarks on gluon field configurations generated by the MILC collaboration that include $u$, $d$, $s$ and $c$ HISQ quarks in the sea at four values of the lattice spacing and both unphysical and physical sea quark masses. We determine the form factor as a function of ALP mass with an uncertainty of less than 2\% across our full range of ALP masses from zero up to 95\% of the $J/\psi$ mass. This represents a substantial improvement in accuracy of the theoretical picture of this decay compared to the previously used tree-level and $\mathcal{O}(\alpha_s)$ perturbation theory. We use our form factor to determine constraints on ALP masses and couplings to charm quarks and photons in several different scenarios using recent experimental data from BESIII. Our calculation paves the way for further lattice QCD input on new physics constraints from radiative decays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06721v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/ldzk-b81n</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Brian Colquhoun, Christine T. H. Davies, G. Peter Lepage, Sophie Renner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral and deconfinement thermal transitions at finite quark spin polarization in lattice QCD simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18636</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18636v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the effect of finite spin quark density on the chiral and deconfinement thermal crossovers using numerical simulations of lattice QCD with two dynamical light quarks. The finite spin density is introduced by the quark spin potential in the canonical formulation of the spin operator. We show that both chiral and deconfinement temperatures are decreasing functions of the spin potential. We determine the parabolic curvatures of crossover temperatures in a limit of physical quark masses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18636v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. V. Braguta, M. N. Chernodub, A. A. Roenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of superradiance on relativistic Foldy-Wouthuysen densities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21404</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21404v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent interest in the studies of structured states obtained in relativistic electron beams has highlighted the use of two alternative descriptions, each based on a different wavefunction and the related space-time density. Although both wavefunctions obey the Dirac equation (one directly and the other through a Foldy-Wouthuysen transformation) they lead to different dynamics and properties, such as the presence or absence of spin-orbit interactions. In this work we investigate wavepacket dynamics for the Klein-Gordon equation, which displays the same ambiguity regarding the choice of different densities, in a setting involving Klein tunneling across a series of supercritical potential barriers. Relying on the superradiant character of this setting, we obtain solutions to the wavepacket dynamics indicating that the density based on a Foldy-Wouthuysen transformation of the wavefunction can be locally amplified outside the light-cone. In principle, the exponential increase of the charge due to the field inhomogeneities can lead to an arbitrarily large amplification over macroscopic distances. These results question the interpretation of the Foldy-Wouthuysen density as a fundamentally correct probability or charge density.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21404v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Daem, A. Matzkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
