<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>hep-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph</link>
    <description>hep-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/hep-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 04:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral functions in Minkowski quantum electrodynamics from neural reconstruction: Benchmarking against dispersive Dyson--Schwinger integral equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24728</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24728v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A Minkowskian physics-informed neural network approach (M--PINN) is formulated to solve the Dyson--Schwinger integral equations (DSE) of quantum electrodynamics (QED) directly in Minkowski spacetime. Our novel strategy merges two complementary approaches: (i) a dispersive solver based on Lehmann representations and subtracted dispersion relations, and (ii) a M--PINN that learns the fermion mass function $B(p^2)$, under the same truncation and renormalization configuration (quenched, rainbow, Landau gauge) with the loss integrating the DSE residual with multi--scale regularization, and monotonicity/smoothing penalties in the spacelike branch in the same way as in our previous work in Euclidean space. The benchmarks show quantitative agreement from the infrared (IR) to the ultraviolet (UV) scales in both on-shell and momentum-subtraction schemes. In this controlled setting, our M--PINN reproduces the dispersive solution whilst remaining computationally compact and differentiable, paving the way for extensions with realistic vertices, unquenching effects, and uncertainty-aware variants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24728v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rodrigo Carmo Terin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weak interactions and the gravitational collapse</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24800v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The chart of nuclei could be enlarged with a branch describing neutron stars that are huge nuclei of a few solar masses held together by
  gravity force and sustained by the pressure due to the degenerate Fermi sea. We contend in this manuscript that yet another branch
  could be added: objects with a large weak charge, with masses around $10^{-3}$ solar masses and having radii of a few meters, very compact,
  only slightly larger than their Schwarzchild radius, and sustained by the pressure generated by the weak force due to $Z$ exchange.
  This interaction, insignificant in normal neutron stars, could become dominant when ultrahigh densities are reached due to the action of gravity
  and lead to stable configurations if the appropriate conditions are met. They would constitute a physical realization of the equation of state
  proposed by Zeldovich some decades ago.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24800v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Domenec Espriu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leading large $N_c$ contributions to Lepton Number Violating Meson Decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24835</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24835v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Lepton number violating meson decays, such as $M_1^- \to M_2^+\ell_1^-\ell_2^-$, provide constraints on $d=9$ $\Delta L = 2$ operators. RGE-improved bounds on the Wilson coefficients of these operators have been presented in the literature, taking into account perturbative QCD one-loop corrections and the corresponding operator mixing. Here, we present for the first time the contribution of connected diagrams to the hadronic matrix elements $\langle M_2 | {\cal O}_h | M_1 \rangle$. These diagrams, usually overlooked under the assumption that $\langle M_2 | {\cal O}_h | M_1 \rangle \sim \langle M_2 | J_{q_3 q_4} | 0 \rangle \times \langle 0 |J_{q_1 q_2} | M_1 \rangle \gg \langle M_2 | J_{q_3 q_2} \times J_{q_1 q_4} | M_1 \rangle$, can give indeed a significant contribution to the matrix element. Including these connected diagrams is but the first step towards a full non-perturbative computation of the long-range QCD effects in these operators, that should be performed using lattice field theory techniques. However, connected diagrams represent the leading order in the $1/N_c$ expansion of the QCD non-perturbative effects and thus our work can be understood as a realistic, first approximation to a complete calculation of the long-range part of the matrix elements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24835v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Donini, Marcela Gonz\'alez, Martin Hirsch, Nicol\'as A. Neill</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of $\nu$SMEFT operators on low-scale leptogenesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24843v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the impact of higher-dimensional operators on low-scale leptogenesis (LG) via oscillations of right-handed neutrinos within the neutrino-extended Standard Model Effective Field Theory ($\nu$SMEFT) and discuss the connection to neutrinoless double beta decay ($0\nu\beta\beta$). Focusing on a dimension-six, lepton number conserving operator, we explore how new interactions can significantly alter the production and equilibration dynamics of right-handed neutrinos. We derive the relevant quantum kinetic equations incorporating both renormalizable and non-renormalizable interactions and perform a comprehensive numerical analysis for benchmark scenarios in both the oscillatory and overdamped regimes. Our results reveal that even in the absence of explicit lepton number violation by the operator, it can enhance or suppress the baryon asymmetry of the universe (BAU) by several orders of magnitude, depending on the EFT scale. We further connect these effects to predictions for $0\nu\beta\beta$ decay, demonstrating that the same operator can lead to enhanced decay rates, potentially within reach of the next generation of experiments. Our findings indicate that the observation of $0\nu\beta\beta$ could rule out a large part of the parameter space for successful low-scale LG within the $\nu$SMEFT, implying low RHN masses and low reheating temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24843v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaori Fuyuto, Julia Harz, Sascha Weber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Precise $\alpha_s$ Determination from the R-improved QCD Static Energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24846</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24846v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The strong coupling $\alpha_s$ is determined with high precision from fits to lattice QCD simulations on the static energy. Our theoretical setup relies on R-improving the three-loop fixed-order prediction for the static energy by removing its $u=1/2$ renormalon and summing up the associated large (infrared) logarithms which, in combination with radius-dependent renormalization scales (called profile functions) extends the validity of perturbation theory to distances up to $\sim 0.5\,$fm. Furthermore, we resum large ultrasoft logarithms to N$^3$LL accuracy using renormalization group evolution. We have checked that the standard four-loop R-evolution treats N$^4$LL and higher remnants in a non-symmetric way, hence we also account for this potential bias. Our estimate of the perturbative uncertainty is based on a random scan over the parameters specifying the profile functions and the treatment of R-evolution. We also devise a method to statistically combine into a single dataset results from independent simulations which use different lattice spacing and cover various ranges, which can be used to carry out fits in a much faster way. We explore the dependence of the extracted $\alpha_s$ value on the smallest and largest distances included in the dataset, on how R-evolution is treated, on how the fit is performed, and on the accuracy of ultrasoft resummation. From our final analysis, after evolving to the $Z$-pole we obtain $\alpha^{(n_f=5)}_s(m_Z)=0.1166\pm 0.0009$, compatible with the world average with similar incertitude.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24846v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose M. Mena-Valle, Vicent Mateu, Pablo G. Ortega</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heavy Quark Energy Loss in the Hybrid Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24847</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24847v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Heavy quarks offer an invaluable hard probe of the droplets of quark gluon plasma (QGP) formed in heavy ion collisions at the LHC and RHIC. Given their large mass, they are predominantly produced in hard scattering processes at the earliest moment of a collision and given their rarity they almost never annihilate with a heavy antiquark subsequently. This means that they experience, and probe, the entire history of the expanding, cooling, droplet of QGP from hydrodynamization through hadronization. Quantitative measurements of heavy quark final state observables therefore give us access to information about the transport properties of QGP as well as about medium modifications of hadronization. To date, the Hybrid strong/weak coupling Model of jet quenching has not included any implementation of the heavy-quark sector, which has made it impossible to confront its predictions with measurements of heavy quark and jet observables together, in a unified fashion. Here, we extend the Hybrid Model to investigate heavy quark observables for the first time. We introduce a strongly-coupled calculation of heavy-quark energy loss with the correct behavior when the heavy quarks are either ultrarelativistic or non-relativistic, Gaussian momentum broadening, and recombination of heavy quarks with medium partons using a local color neutralization model of hadronization. We compare our results for the suppression $R_{\rm AA}$ and azimuthal anisotropies $v_2$ of B- and D-mesons and $\Lambda_c$ baryons, the $R_{\rm AA}$ of B-tagged jets, as well as baryon-to-meson ratios, with available experimental data from ALICE, ATLAS and CMS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24847v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Beraudo, Jean F. Du Plessis, Daniel Pablos, Krishna Rajagopal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Super-Leading Logarithms in Top-Quark Pair Production at Hadron Colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24848v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To date, the appearance and resummation of "super-leading" logarithms in hadron-hadron collisions has been studied only for massless parton states. We extend the formalism to include an arbitrary number of massive final states. We derive the corresponding anomalous dimension and identify an additional Coulomb phase that gives rise to a new source of super-leading logarithms. We then perform a systematic leading-logarithmic resummation of these contributions for $2\to M$ processes. Finally, we analyze the numerical impact in partonic scattering processes for $t\bar{t}$ production, including a treatment of the Sommerfeld enhancement observed near threshold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24848v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Upalaparna Banerjee, Romy Gr\"unhofer, Matthias K\"onig, Yibei Li, Matthias Neubert, Josua Scholze</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A global analysis of ALP-mediated multiboson production at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24873v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Axion-like particles (ALPs) provide a well-motivated framework for physics beyond the Standard Model, coupling to gauge bosons through dimension-five operators protected by an approximate shift symmetry. At the LHC, such interactions lead to distinctive signatures in multiboson production, where the ALP appears as an off-shell mediator rather than a narrow resonance. In this work, we present the first global analysis of ALP-mediated multiboson processes, combining measurements of diphoton, ZZ, $W^+ W^-$, dijet, and vector-boson-fusion final states. On the theory side, motivated from a UV perspective, we assume that the ALP couples only to the gauge sector of the SM, and classify the ALP-multiboson vertices that directly govern collider observables. Our results show that the dijet channel dominates the sensitivity to ALP couplings and determines the limits on $c_{\tilde{G}}$, while diboson and VBF processes provide complementary constraints on the electroweak couplings. We further assess the validity of the EFT expansion given the multi-TeV scales probed in the data. This global study provides the most comprehensive picture to date of ALP-gauge interactions from multiboson production at the LHC, and highlights the opportunities for significant improvements with future high-luminosity datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24873v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabian Esser, Alexandre Salas-Bernardez, Maria Ubiali, Veronica Sanz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QCD chiral phase diagram from weak functional renormalization group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25081</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25081v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the QCD chiral phase transition at finite temperature and finite baryon density using the functional Renormalization Group (fRG). While conventional fRG studies often employ techniques such as dynamical bosonization to regularize divergences, we instead pursue the weak solution of the fRG equations which allows for non-analytic behavior in the flow to compute the pure fermionic potential $V_k(\psi,\bar{\psi})$ within the local potential approximation. This approach enables us to explore the effects of purely quark-level fluctuations on dynamical chiral symmetry breaking without introducing any auxiliary bosonic fields. Based on this framework, we present the resulting chiral phase diagram as a function of temperature and baryon chemical potential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25081v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuepeng Guan, Masatoshi Yamada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prospects for a fourth generation of leptons in a 13 TeV p-p collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25190v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the Standard Model, three discovered generations of leptons and quarks are known to date. However, speculations about existence of next generations have a strong foothold. In this study, we sequentially extrapolate the Standard Model to include a fourth generation of leptons (l4, nu4) with a massive Dirac neutrino. We perform MC simulated event generation of pp -&gt; l4 l4(bar) scattering processes at an LHC-like p-p collider with sqrt(s) = 13 TeV by considering l4 mass of 190 GeV and nu4 mass of 100 GeV with PYTHIA. We demonstrate mass constraints of sequential leptons from oblique parameters and study important jet and lepton kinematics in our simulation with CMS like constraints. Fourth generation neutrino is stable in this scenario making l4 -&gt; W nu4 the only dominant channel in collider searches. With the cut-flow, we achieve global excess of (1.46 +/- 0.068(stat.)) sigma and local excess of (3.33 +/- 0.241(stat.)) sigma in the 180-300 GeV signal window. Missing Transverse Energy (MET) provides clean signature of nu4. We assess discovery potential of the BSM lepton against lepton mass, center-of-mass energy (Ecom) and luminosities. Higher luminosities and Ecom are promising to probe BSM moderate mass lepton scenarios at present and future colliders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25190v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ramkrishna Joshi, Riddhiman Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of shell model interactions on WIMP-nucleus scattering observables for silicon and germanium targets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25197</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25197v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The nature of dark matter (DM) remains one of the biggest mysteries in physics today. Dark matter direct detection experiments look for nuclear recoil signals from DM-nucleus elastic scattering, which can be used to characterise DM. Nuclear modelling of the target nucleus may impact the predicted DM-nucleus scattering rates, and affect interpretation of experimental signals. In this work, we investigate the impact of nuclear shell model interactions on DM nuclear responses for silicon and germanium targets using a SuperCDMS-like experimental parameters. Nuclear uncertainties resulting from shell model interaction choice in the nuclear form factors are roughly retained at the scattering rate and exclusion limit levels for certain nuclear responses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25197v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raghda Abdel Khaleq, Madeleine J. Zurowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vorticity-induced effects from Wess-Zumino-Witten terms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25459v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study vorticity-induced effects arising from the Wess-Zumino-Witten terms for Nambu-Goldstone modes in chiral perturbation theory. We first provide an alternative derivation of the Wess-Zumino-Witten terms in the presence of external vector, axial-vector, and pseudoscalar fields using a derivative expansion of the fermion determinant. We then employ the previously found correspondence in which vorticity is treated as an axial-vector field coupled to Dirac fermions in flat spacetime. Using this, we derive vorticity-induced contributions for Nambu-Goldstone modes in the presence of electromagnetic fields at finite baryon and isospin chemical potentials, including a vorticity-induced current, a magnetic-field-induced angular momentum, and a vorticity-modified photon-pion coupling. We also briefly discuss the phenomenological implications of these vorticity-induced effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25459v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Geraint W. Evans, Naoki Yamamoto, Di-Lun Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NLO event generation for LHC neutrinos and application to flux measurements at FASER</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25486v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The LHC generates an intense beam of high-energy neutrinos in the forward direction, whose scientific potential has been left unexploited for many years. The FASER and SND@LHC experiments, operating since 2023, have recently measured LHC neutrinos for the first time. In this contribution we discuss how to produce accurate predictions, including NLO QCD corrections and modern parton shower algorithms, for present and future LHC neutrino experiments, including those at the proposed Forward Physics Facility (FPF). To this end, the energy and rapidity distribution of the LHC neutrinos is encoded in a LHAPDF grid interfaced to the neutrino DIS event generator in the POWHEG-BOX-RES framework. This Monte Carlo tool enables the modelling of differential distributions that are sensitive to hadronic final states, initial- and final-state radiation, and realistic acceptance and selection cuts. As a first application, we deploy this event generator to compute fast-interpolation grids and carry out a first determination of the LHC forward neutrino fluxes directly from FASER data using the NNPDF fitting methodology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25486v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Krack</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcement Learning techniques for the flavor problem in particle physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25495v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This short review discusses recent applications of Reinforcement Learning (RL) techniques to the flavor problem in particle physics. Traditional approaches to fermion masses and mixing often rely on extensions of the Standard Model based on horizontal symmetries, but the vast landscape of possible models makes systematic exploration infeasible. Recent works have shown that RL can efficiently navigate this landscape by constructing models that reproduce observed quark and lepton observables. These approaches demonstrate that RL not only rediscovers models already proposed in the literature but also uncovers new, phenomenologically acceptable solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25495v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Giarnetti, D. Meloni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resonant production of millicharged scalars in k2 &gt; 0 electromagnetic wave background</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25505</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25505v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the solution of the Klein-Gordon equation for a charged scalar timelike $(k_\mu=(\omega,0,0,n\omega))$ particle in an electromagnetic plane wave background which can be realized in a medium with a refractive index $n&lt;1$. We reduce the equation of motion to the Mathieu equation, which has resonant exponentially growing solutions for certain parameter ranges. We show that this resonance indeed occurs for small scalar masses. We apply our results to derive constraints on millicharged particles and compare them with existing experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25505v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ekaterina Dmitrieva, Petr Satunin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixed Electroweak-QCD Corrections to $H\to \gamma\gamma$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25516</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25516v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present for the first time the complete three-loop mixed electroweak-QCD ($\mathcal{O}(\alpha\alpha_s)$) corrections for the decay channel $H \to \gamma\gamma$, by implementing three different on-shell $\alpha$ schemes in computing the electroweak correction. Our studies indicate that the $\mathcal{O}(\alpha_s)$ correction amounts to approximately $1.7\%$ of the leading-order prediction for the diphoton width, while the $\mathcal{O}(\alpha)$ correction varies from $-4.8\%$ to $1.4\%$ depending on the specific $\alpha$ scheme. The three-loop mixed electroweak-QCD correction may reach $0.6\%$, $0.5\%$, and $0.2\%$ of the LO diphoton width in $\alpha(0)$, $\alpha(M_Z)$, and $G_\mu$ schemes, respectively, which is much more significant than the less-than-$0.1\%$ contribution from the three-loop QCD correction. It is also worth noting that the inclusion of the ${\cal O}(\alpha\alpha_s)$ correction significantly reduces the scheme dependence of the partial width from $0.6$ keV at leading order down to $0.03$ keV. The state-of-the-art Standard Model predictions are $\Gamma[H \to \gamma\gamma] = 9.389\div 9.420$ keV, providing a valuable theoretical benchmark for future Higgs factory collider program.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25516v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Long Sang, Feng Feng, Yu Jia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advanced parametrisations for hadronic form factors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25584v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The rich analytic structure of hadronic form factors makes a theoretically consistent yet easily applicable parametrisation cumbersome. Consequently, most parametrisations are limited to reproducing the simplest analytic features sufficient to describe form factors on their first Riemann sheet. Here, we introduce two novel form factor parametrisations that allow resonance poles and left-hand cuts on the second Riemann sheet to be studied, while also making the connection to partial-wave amplitudes manifest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25584v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nienke C. Balz, Florian Herren, Bastian Kubis, Simon Mutke, M\'eril Reboud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Out-of-equilibrium contributions to charm hadrons in a fluid-dynamic approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25601v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Building on previous studies that demonstrated the applicability of a fluid-dynamic description of charm quarks in the quark-gluon plasma, the present work extends the framework by computing the out-of-equilibrium contributions to the distribution function of charm hadrons. The analysis includes corrections arising from the initial out-of-equilibrium distribution of charm quarks after a free-streaming phase, as well as from the freeze-out surface within fluid dynamics. These results enable the exact computation of integrated yields and transverse momentum distributions of charm hadrons for different values of the spatial diffusion coefficient, thereby providing the basis for a systematic determination of the charm transport coefficients. In addition, the limits of applicability of the approach are identified by determining the transverse-momentum region in which charm hadrons are described by a well-defined, positive distribution function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25601v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rossana Facen, Federica Capellino, Eduardo Grossi, Andrea Dubla, Silvia Masciocchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$QQ\bar Q\bar Q$ Quark System and Gauge/String Duality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25605</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25605v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a stringy description of a system composed of two heavy quarks and two heavy antiquarks, mimicking that in pure $SU(3)$ gauge theory. We present both analytical and numerical studies of the string configurations for rectangular geometries. As an application, we analyze the two lowest Born-Oppenheimer potentials. Our results suggest that the ground state of the $QQ\bar Q\bar Q$ system is a mixed state of a hadronic molecule and a tetraquark state. For general geometries, we derive the asymptotic expression for the energy of the tetraquark configuration in the infrared limit and extend this result to multiquark configurations. Here we also demonstrate the universality of the string tension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25605v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleg Andreev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Muon Beam Dump Experiments explicate five-dimensional nature of $U(1)_{L_{\mu}-L_{\tau}}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25613</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25613v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We have investigated the prospects of probing the five-dimensional $U(1)_{L_\mu - L_\tau}$ interactions in present and future muon dump experiments, namely, NA64$_\mu$, M$^3$, MuSIC, and a future muon beam dump experiment. These experiments are classified into two categories: the first two can probe processes where feebly interacting massive particles go into invisible channels, while the latter two can probe processes where these states decay into muon pairs. These two types of experiments are complementary in that they allow exploration of different parameter regions of a model. In our scenario, the presence of multiple massive gauge bosons as Kaluza-Klein (KK) particles leads to an enhancement in the signal events compared to the corresponding four-dimensional scenario. In particular, the decay process into muon pairs enables mass reconstruction of the parent particle, making it possible to directly demonstrate the existence of multiple KK particles in at least some parameter regions. This can provide clear evidence that the origin of the $U(1)_{L_\mu - L_\tau}$ interaction lies in five dimensions. Furthermore, the muon $(g-2)$ value, which is now consistent with the SM, can be used to exclude specific parameter regions for new particles interacting with muons. We also carefully discuss the non-trivial effects arising from nonzero kinetic mixing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25613v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dibyendu Chakraborty, Arindam Chatterjee, Ayushi Kaushik, Kenji Nishiwaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extra dip in ultrahigh energy neutrino spectrum from generalized uncertainty principle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25635v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revisited the scenario of a resonant enhancement in the oscillation probability due to an interaction potential between neutrinos and dark matter with the novelty of the inclusion of the generalized uncertainty principle. It is shown that a new resonant conversion appears at higher energies. This effect could be tested with future neutrino data as new dips in the ultrahigh energy neutrino flux.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25635v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Barranco, Emiliano Dur\'an</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minijet thermalization and jet transport coefficients in QCD kinetic theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25669</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25669v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We apply weakly coupled QCD kinetic theory to investigate the thermalization of high-momentum on-shell partons (minijets) in a Quark-Gluon Plasma (QGP). Our approach incorporates isotropic hard thermal loop screening to model soft quark and gluon exchanges, allowing us to verify consistency with established analytic results of jet transport coefficients. We perform kinetic simulations of minijets propagating through a thermal gluon plasma, incorporating both collinear radiation and elastic scatterings. The resulting evolution is compared to predictions from jet transport coefficients, including the longitudinal and transverse jet-quenching parameters $\hat{q}$, energy loss, and the drag coefficient. We find that standard definitions of jet transport coefficients neglect the contributions from recoiling medium particles. Including these contributions restores consistency with the kinetic evolution. Finally, we show that the minijet thermalization time scales remarkably well with $\hat{q}$ and we produce a phenomenological estimate of the minijet quenching time in heavy-ion collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25669v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kirill Boguslavski, Florian Lindenbauer, Aleksas Mazeliauskas, Adam Takacs, Fabian Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimation of the Inverse Compton Scattering Background in MeV Gamma-Gamma Collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24759v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The MeV Gamma-Gamma Collider would provide a direct experimental platform for elastic light-by-light scattering ($\gamma\gamma \to \gamma\gamma$) and the Breit-Wheeler process with two real photons ($\gamma\gamma \to e^+e^-$). A Monte Carlo code, the Genie Background Evaluation Tool (GBET), has been developed to fully simulate two successive inverse Compton scatterings in the linear regime, including $e^- + \text{laser} \to e^-+ \gamma$ and $e^- + \gamma \rightarrow e^- + \gamma$. GBET overcomes the inherent information loss in traditional luminosity-spectrum-based chain simulations, preserving full particle-level information and achieving higher physical fidelity. The effectiveness of the code is verified by benchmarking against the simulation results of CAIN. GBET shows that the event rate of background photons generated by the first inverse Compton scattering is $6.24 \times 10^7$/s, with energies below 18 eV; the second inverse Compton scattering generates background electrons at 51.99/s and photons at 0.99/s, both with energies below 11 MeV. In addition, M{\o}ller scattering contributes background electrons at 0.56/s with energies around 200 MeV. The count rates of background electrons and positrons originating from the Breit-Wheeler process are 1312.2/s and 1314.3/s, respectively, with energy distributions ranging from 511 to 720 keV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24759v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ping Zhou, Meiyu Si, Yuanjie Bi, Illya Drebot, Yongsheng Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Covariance of Scattering Amplitudes from Counting Carefully</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24866v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Invariance of on-shell scattering amplitudes under field redefinitions is a well known property in field theory that corresponds to covariance of on-shell amputated connected functions. In recent years there have been great efforts to define a formalism in which the covariance is manifest at all stages of calculation, mainly resorting to geometrical interpretations. In this work covariance is analysed using combinatorial methods relying only on the properties of the tree level effective action, without referring to specific formulations of the Lagrangian. We provide an explicit proof of covariance of on-shell connected functions and of the existence of covariant Feynman rules and we derive an explicitly covariant closed formula for tree level on-shell connected functions with any number of external legs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24866v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Alminawi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The cosmological analysis of DES 3$\times$2pt data from the Effective Field Theory of Large-Scale Structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24878v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyze the Dark Energy Survey (DES) Year 3 data using predictions from the Effective Field Theory of Large-Scale Structure (EFTofLSS). Specifically, we fit three two-point observables (3$\times$2pt), galaxy clustering, galaxy-galaxy lensing, and cosmic shear, using the one-loop expressions for the projected angular correlation functions. We validate our pipeline against numerical simulations and we check for several internal consistencies before applying it to the observational data. Fixing the spectral tilt and the baryons abundance, we measure $S_8=0.833\pm 0.032$, $\Omega_m = 0.272\pm 0.022$, and $h = 0.773\pm 0.049$, to about $3.8\%$, $8.1\%$, and $6.3\%$, at $68\%$CL, respectively. While our results are consistent within $\lesssim 2\sigma$ with those from Planck and the BOSS full-shape analyses, they exhibit stronger tension with those from DES collaboration 3$\times$2pt analysis combined with a Big-Bang Nucleosynthesis prior, highlighting the impact of modeling, scale cuts, and choice of prior. The theory code and likelihood used for our analyses, \texttt{PyFowl}, is made publicly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24878v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guido D'Amico, Alexandre Refregier, Leonardo Senatore, Pierre Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isotensor $\pi\pi \pi$ scattering with a $\rho$ resonant subsystem from QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24894v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work presents a lattice quantum chromodynamics (QCD) determination of $\pi\pi\pi$ scattering amplitudes for the isospin-2 channel with angular momentum and parity $J^{P} = 1^+$. The calculation is performed using unphysically heavy light-quark masses, corresponding to a pion mass of $m_{\pi} \approx 400$~MeV, for which the $\rho$ meson manifests as a narrow resonance. The analysis employs a previously developed formalism that non-perturbatively relates the finite-volume spectra of two- and three-pion systems to their infinite-volume scattering amplitudes. We combine earlier lattice QCD results for $\pi\pi$ systems with isospins 1 and 2 with new determinations of the isospin-2 three-pion finite-volume spectrum, obtained for three cubic, periodic lattice volumes with box length ranging from $\approx 4/m_\pi$ to $6/m_\pi$. These combined data constrain the low-lying partial waves of the infinite-volume three-pion K matrix, from which we solve a set of coupled integral equations to extract the corresponding scattering amplitudes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24894v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ra\'ul A. Brice\~no, Maxwell T. Hansen, Andrew W. Jackura, Robert G. Edwards, Christopher E. Thomas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of the Three-Flavor Composition of Cosmic Neutrinos with IceCube</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24957</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24957v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neutrinos oscillate over cosmic distances. Using 11.4 years of IceCube data, the flavor composition of the all-sky neutrino flux from 5\,TeV--10\,PeV is studied. We report the first measurement down to the $\mathcal{O}$(TeV) scale using events classified into three flavor-dependent morphologies. The best fit flavor ratio is $f_e:f_{\mu}:f_{\tau}\,=\,0.30:0.37:0.33$, consistent with the standard three-flavor neutrino oscillation model. Each fraction is constrained to be $&gt;0$ at $&gt;$ 90\% confidence level, assuming a broken power law for cosmic neutrinos. We infer the flavor composition of cosmic neutrinos at their sources, and find production via neutron decay lies outside the 99\% confidence interval.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24957v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Abbasi, M. Ackermann, J. Adams, S. K. Agarwalla, J. A. Aguilar, M. Ahlers, J. M. Alameddine, S. Ali, N. M. Amin, K. Andeen, C. Arg\"uelles, Y. Ashida, S. Athanasiadou, S. N. Axani, R. Babu, X. Bai, J. Baines-Holmes, A. Balagopal V., S. W. Barwick, S. Bash, V. Basu, R. Bay, J. J. Beatty, J. Becker Tjus, P. Behrens, J. Beise, C. Bellenghi, B. Benkel, S. BenZvi, D. Berley, E. Bernardini, D. Z. Besson, E. Blaufuss, L. Bloom, S. Blot, I. Bodo, F. Bontempo, J. Y. Book Motzkin, C. Boscolo Meneguolo, S. B\"oser, O. Botner, J. B\"ottcher, J. Braun, B. Brinson, Z. Brisson-Tsavoussis, R. T. Burley, D. Butterfield, M. A. Campana, K. Carloni, J. Carpio, S. Chattopadhyay, N. Chau, Z. Chen, D. Chirkin, S. Choi, B. A. Clark, A. Coleman, P. Coleman, G. H. Collin, D. A. Coloma Borja, A. Connolly, J. M. Conrad, D. F. Cowen, C. De Clercq, J. J. DeLaunay, D. Delgado, T. Delmeulle, S. Deng, P. Desiati, K. D. de Vries, G. de Wasseige, T. DeYoung, J. C. D\'iaz-V\'elez, S. DiKerby, T. Ding, M. Dittmer, A. Domi, L. Draper, L. Dueser, D. Durnford, K. Dutta, M. A. DuVernois, T. Ehrhardt, L. Eidenschink, A. Eimer, P. Eller, E. Ellinger, D. Els\"asser, R. Engel, H. Erpenbeck, W. Esmail, S. Eulig, J. Evans, P. A. Evenson, K. L. Fan, K. Fang, K. Farrag, A. R. Fazely, A. Fedynitch, N. Feigl, C. Finley, L. Fischer, D. Fox, A. Franckowiak, S. Fukami, P. F\"urst, J. Gallagher, E. Ganster, A. Garcia, M. Garcia, G. Garg, E. Genton, L. Gerhardt, A. Ghadimi, T. Gl\"usenkamp, J. G. Gonzalez, S. Goswami, A. Granados, D. Grant, S. J. Gray, S. Griffin, S. Griswold, K. M. Groth, D. Guevel, C. G\"unther, P. Gutjahr, C. Ha, C. Haack, A. Hallgren, L. Halve, F. Halzen, L. Hamacher, M. Ha Minh, M. Handt, K. Hanson, J. Hardin, A. A. Harnisch, P. Hatch, A. Haungs, J. H\"au{\ss}ler, K. Helbing, J. Hellrung, B. Henke, L. Hennig, F. Henningsen, L. Heuermann, R. Hewett, N. Heyer, S. Hickford, A. Hidvegi, C. Hill, G. C. Hill, R. Hmaid, K. D. Hoffman, D. Hooper, S. Hori, K. Hoshina, M. Hostert, W. Hou, M. Hrywniak, T. Huber, K. Hultqvist, K. Hymon, A. Ishihara, W. Iwakiri, M. Jacquart, S. Jain, O. Janik, M. Jansson, M. Jeong, M. Jin, N. Kamp, D. Kang, W. Kang, A. Kappes, L. Kardum, T. Karg, M. Karl, A. Karle, A. Katil, M. Kauer, J. L. Kelley, M. Khanal, A. Khatee Zathul, A. Kheirandish, H. Kimku, J. Kiryluk, C. Klein, S. R. Klein, Y. Kobayashi, A. Kochocki, R. Koirala, H. Kolanoski, T. Kontrimas, L. K\"opke, C. Kopper, D. J. Koskinen, P. Koundal, M. Kowalski, T. Kozynets, A. Kravka, N. Krieger, J. Krishnamoorthi, T. Krishnan, K. Kruiswijk, E. Krupczak, A. Kumar, E. Kun, N. Kurahashi, N. Lad, C. Lagunas Gualda, L. Lallement Arnaud, M. Lamoureux, M. J. Larson, F. Lauber, J. P. Lazar, K. Leonard DeHolton, A. Leszczy\'nska, J. Liao, C. Lin, Q. R. Liu, Y. T. Liu, M. Liubarska, C. Love, L. Lu, F. Lucarelli, W. Luszczak, Y. Lyu, M. Macdonald, J. Madsen, E. Magnus, Y. Makino, E. Manao, S. Mancina, A. Mand, I. C. Mari\c{s}, S. Marka, Z. Marka, L. Marten, I. Martinez-Soler, R. Maruyama, J. Mauro, F. Mayhew, F. McNally, J. V. Mead, K. Meagher, S. Mechbal, A. Medina, M. Meier, Y. Merckx, L. Merten, J. Mitchell, L. Molchany, S. Mondal, T. Montaruli, R. W. Moore, Y. Morii, A. Mosbrugger, M. Moulai, D. Mousadi, E. Moyaux, T. Mukherjee, R. Naab, M. Nakos, U. Naumann, J. Necker, L. Neste, M. Neumann, H. Niederhausen, M. U. Nisa, K. Noda, A. Noell, A. Novikov, A. Obertacke, V. O'Dell, A. Olivas, R. Orsoe, J. Osborn, E. O'Sullivan, V. Palusova, H. Pandya, A. Parenti, N. Park, V. Parrish, E. N. Paudel, L. Paul, C. P\'erez de los Heros, T. Pernice, T. C. Petersen, J. Peterson, M. Plum, A. Pont\'en, V. Poojyam, Y. Popovych, M. Prado Rodriguez, B. Pries, R. Procter-Murphy, G. T. Przybylski, L. Pyras, C. Raab, J. Rack-Helleis, N. Rad, M. Ravn, K. Rawlins, Z. Rechav, A. Rehman, I. Reistroffer, E. Resconi, S. Reusch, C. D. Rho, W. Rhode, L. Ricca, B. Riedel, A. Rifaie, E. J. Roberts, M. Rongen, A. Rosted, C. Rott, T. Ruhe, L. Ruohan, D. Ryckbosch, J. Saffer, D. Salazar-Gallegos, P. Sampathkumar, A. Sandrock, G. Sanger-Johnson, M. Santander, S. Sarkar, M. Scarnera, P. Schaile, M. Schaufel, H. Schieler, S. Schindler, L. Schlickmann, B. Schl\"uter, F. Schl\"uter, N. Schmeisser, T. Schmidt, F. G. Schr\"oder, L. Schumacher, S. Schwirn, S. Sclafani, D. Seckel, L. Seen, M. Seikh, S. Seunarine, P. A. Sevle Myhr, R. Shah, S. Shah, S. Shefali, N. Shimizu, B. Skrzypek, R. Snihur, J. Soedingrekso, A. S{\o}gaard, D. Soldin, P. Soldin, G. Sommani, C. Spannfellner, G. M. Spiczak, C. Spiering, J. Stachurska, M. Stamatikos, T. Stanev, T. Stezelberger, T. St\"urwald, T. Stuttard, G. W. Sullivan, I. Taboada, S. Ter-Antonyan, A. Terliuk, A. Thakuri, M. Thiesmeyer, W. G. Thompson, J. Thwaites, S. Tilav, K. Tollefson, S. Toscano, D. Tosi, A. Trettin, A. K. Upadhyay, K. Upshaw, A. Vaidyanathan, N. Valtonen-Mattila, J. Valverde, J. Vandenbroucke, T. Van Eeden, N. van Eijndhoven, L. Van Rootselaar, J. van Santen, J. Vara, F. Varsi, M. Venugopal, M. Vereecken, S. Vergara Carrasco, S. Verpoest, D. Veske, A. Vijai, J. Villarreal, C. Walck, A. Wang, E. H. S. Warrick, C. Weaver, P. Weigel, A. Weindl, J. Weldert, A. Y. Wen, C. Wendt, J. Werthebach, M. Weyrauch, N. Whitehorn, C. H. Wiebusch, D. R. Williams, L. Witthaus, M. Wolf, G. Wrede, X. W. Xu, J. P. Yanez, Y. Yao, E. Yildizci, S. Yoshida, R. Young, F. Yu, S. Yu, T. Yuan, S. Yun-C\'arcamo, A. Zander Jurowitzki, A. Zegarelli, S. Zhang, Z. Zhang, P. Zhelnin, P. Zilberman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial black hole formation from the merger of oscillons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25300v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that the merger of oscillons results in a broad spectrum of the oscillon mass. A huge number of oscillon samples obtained from numerical lattice simulations reveal that the oscillon mass distribution has an exponential tail in a heavy-mass region. This enables us to infer the fractional abundance of heavy oscillons. Using the criterion for the primordial black hole (PBH) formation from the oscillon collapse obtained in previous studies, we estimate the abundance of PBHs and conclude that a sizable number of PBHs can be produced from oscillons. It can be an alternative PBH formation mechanism without employing the tuning of the inflaton potential to enhance the small-scale density fluctuations in the conventional PBH formation scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25300v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kentaro Kasai, Naoya Kitajima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Morphological Zoo of Inflationary Gravitational Wave Spectra imprinted by a Sequence of Post-Inflationary Epochs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25672v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The expansion history of the Universe prior to Big Bang Nucleosynthesis (BBN) remains largely unconstrained. The high-energy post-inflationary era may involve multiple distinct epochs, each characterized by a different equation of state (EoS). A key prediction of inflation is the generation of tensor perturbations that later manifest as a stochastic background of primordial gravitational waves (GWs). The large-scale amplitude and small-scale spectral tilt ($n_{\rm GW}$) of these GWs encode the inflationary energy scale and the subsequent expansion history, respectively. A soft post-inflationary EoS ($w&lt;1/3$) yields red-tilted GW spectra ($n_{\rm GW}&lt;0$), while a stiff EoS ($w&gt;1/3$) results in a blue-tilt ($n_{\rm GW}&gt;0$). In our previous work [arXiv:2407.07956], we developed an analytical framework for computing the GW spectral energy density, $\Omega_{\rm GW}(f)$, for multiple post-inflationary transitions ($w_1 \to w_2 \to \cdots \to w_n \to 1/3$), focusing on the parameter space relevant for future GW observations. In this paper, we extend that framework to systematically investigate the $morphological~diversity$ of inflationary GW spectra generated by multi-epoch post-inflationary histories. Remaining model agnostic, we demonstrate that a wide variety of spectral shapes, ranging from convex and concave monotonic profiles to multi-peaked non-monotonic spectra, can naturally emerge depending on the sequence and duration of these epochs. We also introduce GWInSpect, a publicly available Python package that computes $\Omega_{\rm GW}(f)$ for arbitrary sequences of EoS transitions, providing a practical tool to study the pre-BBN expansion history of the Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25672v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Swagat S. Mishra, Athul K. Soman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling flow-based approaches for topology sampling in $\mathrm{SU}(3)$ gauge theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25704</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25704v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a methodology based on out-of-equilibrium simulations to mitigate topological freezing when approaching the continuum limit of lattice gauge theories. We reduce the autocorrelation of the topological charge employing open boundary conditions, while removing exactly their unphysical effects using a non-equilibrium Monte Carlo approach in which periodic boundary conditions are gradually switched on. We perform a detailed analysis of the computational costs of this strategy in the case of the four-dimensional $\mathrm{SU}(3)$ Yang-Mills theory. After achieving full control of the scaling, we outline a clear strategy to sample topology efficiently in the continuum limit, which we check at lattice spacings as small as $0.045$ fm. We also generalize this approach by designing a customized Stochastic Normalizing Flow for evolutions in the boundary conditions, obtaining superior performances with respect to the purely stochastic non-equilibrium approach, and paving the way for more efficient future flow-based solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25704v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Claudio Bonanno, Andrea Bulgarelli, Elia Cellini, Alessandro Nada, Dario Panfalone, Davide Vadacchino, Lorenzo Verzichelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new conformal gauge theory of vector-spinors and spin-3/2 particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25709v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The unique off-shell fermionic gauge invariance of a vector-spinor field theory is found, and the invariant action is derived. The latter is Weyl invariant in any dimension in the massless limit, and it coincides with the singular point of the one-parameter family of Rarita-Schwinger Lagrangians. Pure gauge configurations are represented by gamma-trace vector-spinors, which can be gauged away in a global way. Previous claims that this theory is inconsistent are shown to be flawed, and the Velo-Zwanziger instability is proved to be absent. The theory propagates a massive spin-3/2 particle together with a spin-1/2 state whose mass is twice that of the j=3/2 mode. This physical prediction is derived in a consistent fashion both from the classical field equations in d=4 and from the causal construction of a gamma-traceless quantum vector-spinor field. The conformal anomaly is derived using known results for the heat kernel of non-minimal second-order operators, and it is shown that the a-anomaly has an opposite sign w.r.t. known results for lower spin fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25709v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dario Sauro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Basis light-front quantization approach to $\Lambda$ and $\Lambda_c$ and their isospin triplet baryons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.00355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.00355v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We obtain the masses, the electromagnetic properties, and the parton distribution functions (PDFs) of $\Lambda$, $\Lambda_c$, and their isospin triplet baryons, i.e, $\Sigma^0$, $\Sigma^+$, $\Sigma^-$ and $\Sigma_c^0$, $\Sigma_c^+$, $\Sigma_c^{++}$ from a light-front effective Hamiltonian in the leading Fock sector in the basis light-front quantization framework. The light-front wave functions of these baryons are given by the eigenstates of the effective Hamiltonian consisting of a three-dimensional confinement potential and a one-gluon exchange interaction with fixed coupling. The masses of these baryons in our approach are in the experimental range while isospin-dependent mass differences are too small. Meanwhile, the electromagnetic properties are in agreement with the available experimental data, the lattice QCD simulations, and the other theoretical calculations. We also present the gluon and the sea quark PDFs, which we generate dynamically from the QCD evolution of the valence quark distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.00355v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.106.114040</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Tiancai Peng, Zhimin Zhu, Siqi Xu, Xiang Liu, Chandan Mondal, Xingbo Zhao, James P. Vary</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Application of Fermion Quantum Number $F$ and Unit Electroweak Charge $F_0$ in the Electroweak Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.00009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.00009v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the previous work, the traditional flavor-related additive quantum numbers were substituted by the fermion quantum number and the unit electroweak charge, which are, same as the electric charge, conserved in electromagnetic interaction, weak interaction and strong interaction. The empirical selection rules in electroweak interaction were found that they can be interpreted by conservation of the fermion quantum number. In this paper, the weak isospin and the weak hypercharge in the electroweak theory are demonstrated to be equivalent to half of the fermion quantum number and the unit electroweak charge respectively. Therefore, we can unify the traditional flavor-related additive quantum numbers and the additive quantum numbers in the electroweak theory by using only two numbers. Furthermore, we can take a new point of view on the electroweak theory by using these two numbers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.00009v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.7546/giq-32-2025-47-58</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Xin-Hua Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A quantum machine learning classifier to search for new physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18847</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18847v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Due to the success of the Standard Model~(SM), it is reasonable to anticipate that the signal of new physics~(NP) beyond the SM is small. Consequently, future searches for NP and precision tests of the SM will require high luminosity collider experiments. Moreover, as precision tests advance, rare processes with many final-state particles require consideration which demand the analysis of a vast number of observables. The high luminosity produces a large amount of experimental data spanning a large observable space, posing a significant data-processing challenge. In recent years, quantum machine learning has emerged as a promising approach for processing large amounts of complex data on a quantum computer. In this study, we propose quantum searching neighbor~(QSN) and variational QSN~(VQSN) algorithms to search for NP. The QSN is a classification algorithm. The VQSN introduces variation to the QSN to process classical data. As applications, we apply the (V)QSN in the phenomenological study of the NP at the Large Hadron Collider and muon colliders. Examples are implemented on a real quantum hardware, which confirms reliable performance under noisy conditions. The results indicate that the VQSN demonstrates superior efficiency in the sense of computational complexity to a classical counterpart k-nearest neighbor algorithm, even when dealing with classical data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18847v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ji-Chong Yang, Shuai Zhang, Chong-Xing Yue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New physics effects in semileptonic $\bar{B_s} \to K^{*+}(\to K\pi) \ell^- \bar{\nu}_\ell$ decay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03238</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03238v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We analyze the new physics effects in semileptonic $\bar{B_s} \to K^{*+}(\to K\pi) \ell^- \bar{\nu}_\ell$ decay induced by the $b \to u \ell \nu_{\ell}$ quark level transition. We consider the vector, scalar and tensor new physics Lorentz structures in addition to the SM in effective field theory approach. Constraints on new physics parameters are obtained from experimental observations of both semileptonic and leptonic decays of $B$ mesons, which are governed by the underlyng $b \to u \ell \nu_\ell$ transition. We explore the new physics effects in differential branching fraction, lepton forward-backward asymmetry, fraction of longitudinal polarization of $K^*$ meson and normalized angular observables in $\bar{B_s} \to K^{*+}(\to K\pi) \ell^- \bar{\nu}_\ell$ decay.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03238v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shabana Khan, Dinesh Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Widen the Resonance: Probing a New Regime of Neutrino Self-Interactions with Astrophysical Neutrinos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07624</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07624v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Neutrino self-interactions beyond the standard model have profound implications in astrophysics and cosmology. In this Letter, we study an uncharted scenario in which one of the three neutrino species has a mass smaller than the temperature of the cosmic neutrino background. This results in a relativistic component that significantly broadens the absorption feature on the astrophysical neutrino spectra, in contrast to the sharply peaked absorption expected in the extensively studied scenarios assuming a fully nonrelativistic cosmic neutrino background. By solving the Boltzmann equations for neutrino absorption and regeneration, we demonstrate that this mechanism provides novel sensitivity to sub-keV mediator masses, well below the traditional $\sim 1$--100 MeV range. Future observations of the diffuse supernova neutrino background with Hyper-Kamiokande could probe coupling strengths down to $g \sim 10^{-8}$, surpassing existing constraints by orders of magnitude. These findings open new directions for discoveries and offer crucial insights into the interplay between neutrinos and the dark sector.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07624v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/9ddp-j1z9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 181002 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Isaac R. Wang, Xun-Jie Xu, Bei Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological Consequences of Domain Walls Biased by Quantum Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16414v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: One of the simplest standard model extensions leading to a domain wall network is a real scalar $S$ with a $Z_2$ symmetry spontaneously broken during universe evolution. Motivated by the swampland program, we explore the possibility that quantum gravity effects are responsible for violation of the discrete symmetry, triggering the annihilation of the domain wall network. We explore the resulting cosmological implications in terms of dark radiation, dark matter, gravitational waves, primordial black holes, and wormholes connected to baby universes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16414v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/7zmx-v16z</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 112 (2025) 7, 075007</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yann Gouttenoire, Stephen F. King, Rishav Roshan, Xin Wang, Graham White, Masahito Yamazaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigation of triply heavy spin-3/2 baryons in their ground and excited states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.06822</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.06822v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We calculate the masses and residues of triply heavy baryons with spin-3/2, including $\Omega^*_{ccc}$, $\Omega^*_{ccb}$, $\Omega^*_{bbc}$ and $\Omega^*_{bbb}$, using the QCD sum rules method. Our calculations primarily focus on obtaining the masses of the first three resonances, that is, the ground state (1S), the first orbital excited state (1P), and the first radial excited state (2S), for the mentioned baryons. We additionally determine the residues of these baryons, which serve as key parameters for studying their possible decay channels and interactions with other particles. To achieve higher accuracy compared to previous studies, we consider nonperturbative operators up to eight mass dimensions. We present our calculated outcomes in two distinct energy schemes, referred to as pole and $\mathrm{\overline{MS}}$. Given the absence of experimental data for these states, we compare our results with previous theoretical calculations that are reported in relevant studies employing various approaches. These results may provide valuable insights for experimental groups searching for the triply heavy baryons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.06822v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Z. Rajabi Najjar, K. Azizi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decays of the vector charmonium and bottomonium hybrids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00665v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The full widths of the vector charmonium and bottomonium hybrid mesons $H_{ \mathrm{c}}$ and $H_{\mathrm{b}}$, characterized by the quantum numbers $1^{ \mathrm{--}}$, are determined by analyzing their dominant strong decay modes: $H_{\mathrm{c}} \to D^{+}D^{-}$, $D_{0}\overline{D}_{0}$, $ D_{s}^{+}D_{s}^{-} $ and $H_{\mathrm{b}} \to B^{+}B^{-}$, $B_{0}\overline{B} _{0}$. To evaluate the partial widths of these channels, we employ the QCD three-point sum rule approach, which provides a reliable method for extracting the strong coupling constants at the relevant hybrid-meson-meson interaction vertices. Based on this analysis, the full widths of these hybrid quarkonia are found to be $\Gamma _{H_{\mathrm{c}}} =(234.1\pm 37.4)~ \mathrm{MeV} $ and $\Gamma _{H_{\mathrm{b}}} =(78.8\pm 15.4)~\mathrm{MeV} $ . These results are expected to facilitate the interpretation of future experimental data concerning the spectroscopy and decay patterns of exotic charmonium- and bottomonium-like hybrid mesons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00665v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Barsbay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Photon Cloud Induced from an Axion Cloud</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16036v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is known that the axion-photon coupling can lead to quantum stimulated emission of photons and classic exponential amplification of electromagnetic (EM) fields at half the axion mass frequency, when the axion density or the coupling constant is sufficiently large. In this work, we studied the EM photon cloud induced from an axion cloud around a Kerr black hole in the first order of the coupling constant classically. In the presence of a static EM background (like Wald extended solution valid in realistic astrophysical environment), we found that an EM photon cloud emerges, oscillating at the same frequency as the axion cloud and growing exponentially in accordance with the axion cloud when the superradiant condition for the axion field is satisfied. The evolution of the EM photon cloud with time and azimuthal angle is obtained analytically while the cross-sectional distribution is solved numerically. The induced EM field exhibits significantly different symmetries in contrast to the background EM field, which may serve as an indication of the existence of both an axion cloud and axion-photon coupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16036v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zi-Yu Tang, Eleftherios Papantonopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse Seesaw Model in Non-holomorphic Modular $A_4$ Flavor Symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.06945v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates an inverse seesaw model of neutrino masses based on non-holomorphic modular $A_4$ symmetry, extending the framework of modular-invariant flavor models beyond the conventional holomorphic paradigm. After the general theoretical framework is established, three concrete model realizations distinguished by their $A_4$ representation assignments and modular weight configurations for the matter fields are analyzed. Focusing on these three specific realizations, a comprehensive analysis of neutrino phenomenology is performed. By constraining the modulus parameter $\tau$ to the fundamental domain and systematically scanning the parameter space, regions compatible with current neutrino oscillation data are identified. The numerical results provide predictions for currently unmeasured quantities, including the absolute neutrino mass scale, Dirac CP-violating phase, and Majorana phases. These predictions establish specific, testable signatures for upcoming neutrino experiments, particularly in neutrinoless double beta decay and precision oscillation measurements. The framework offers a well-defined target for future experimental verification or exclusion, while demonstrating the phenomenological viability of non-holomorphic modular symmetry approaches to flavor structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.06945v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xianshuo Zhang, Yakefu Reyimuaji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fragmentation of fully heavy tetraquarks: The TQ4Q1.1 functions as a case study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09744</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09744v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We extend the study of exotic matter formation via the TQ4Q1.1 set of collinear, variable-flavor-number-scheme fragmentation functions for fully charmed or bottomed tetraquarks in three quantum configurations: scalar ($J^{PC} = 0^{++}$), axial vector ($J^{PC} = 1^{+-}$), and tensor ($J^{PC} = 2^{++}$). We adopt single-parton fragmentation at leading power and implement a nonrelativistic Quantum Chromodynamics (NRQCD) factorization scheme tailored to tetraquark Fock-state configurations. Short-distance inputs at the initial scale are modeled using updated calculations for both gluon- and heavy-quark-initiated channels. A threshold-consistent Dokshitzer-Gribov-Lipatov-Altarelli-Parisi (DGLAP) evolution is then applied via the novel Heavy-flavor nonrelativistic-evolution (HF-NRevo) hybrid scheme. We provide the first systematic treatment of uncertainties from nonperturbative color-composite long-distance matrix elements (LDMEs), as well as from perturbative hard-scattering (H-MHOUs) and fragmentation-scale inputs (F-MHOUs), assessed separately and in combination. To support phenomenology, we compute NLL/NLO$^+$ cross sections for tetraquark-jet systems at the HL-LHC and FCC within the hybrid collinear and high-energy factorization (HyF) as implemented in (sym)JETHAD, incorporating angular multiplicities as key observables sensitive to high-energy QCD dynamics. We also provide expected event yields based on realistic luminosity scenarios, offering a concrete benchmark for experimental searches. This work connects the investigation of exotic hadrons with state-of-the-art precision QCD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09744v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/375n-fw5h</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Giovanni Celiberto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing dark-state electromagnetic form factors at future linear electron-positron colliders with polarized beams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13944v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the electromagnetic form factors of electrically neutral dark-sector particles in this paper. Concretely speaking, we focus on operators that can lead to interactions of fermionic dark states with the Standard-Model (SM) photon, including both dimension-5 (the magnetic and electric dipole moments) and dimension-6 (the anapole moment and charge radius) operators. Correspondingly, instead of the SM-photon form factors, we employ hypercharge gauge-field form factors that can induce additional couplings to the SM $Z$-boson. Utilizing the mono-photon production channel at future linear electron-positron colliders, the International Linear Collider (ILC) and the Compact Linear Collider (CLIC), we demonstrate that tuning beam polarization allows for simultaneous enhancement of signal-event rates and suppression of dominant SM background events, i.e.~neutrino-induced processes, and hence improvement of sensitivity reach. Our analysis reveals that ILC and CLIC can probe electromagnetic form factors of dark-sector particles up to about two orders of magnitude beyond existing experimental limits. We also estimate, at the order-of-magnitude level, the validity range of the effective-field-theory (EFT) approach we adopt, finding that for the dimension-5 operators the EFT remains valid in most of the parameter regions to which the ILC and CLIC can be sensitive, while it breaks down in the entire sensitivity region for the dimension-6 operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13944v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhong Zhang, Yu Zhang, Zeren Simon Wang, Yunlan Ji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lepton parity dark matter and naturally unstable domain walls</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02642v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a simple and predictive setup that connects neutrino masses, dark matter (DM), and gravitational waves. A minimal lepton parity DM scenario is considered where the residual symmetry $(-1)^L$ from the type I seesaw acts as the dark parity $D=(-1)^{L+2j}$, ensuring DM stability without imposing any new symmetry. A singlet Majorana fermion $S$ with even lepton parity serves as the DM candidate, interacting via a real scalar $\sigma$ which is also even lepton parity. The scalar potential possesses an accidental $\mathcal{Z}_2$ symmetry, whose spontaneous breaking gives rise to unstable domain walls (DW) in the presence of explicit $\mathcal{Z}_2$ breaking terms allowed by the lepton parity. The subsequent DW annihilation generates a stochastic gravitational wave (GW) background potentially observable at different GW experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02642v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ernest Ma, Partha Kumar Paul, Narendra Sahu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inclusion of the Longitudinal Momentum-Transfer Component and Kinematic Factors in a diffraction approach for H(d,p)X Reactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.06579v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, within the framework of the Glauber-Sitenko approximation, an analysis of the differential cross section for deuteron breakup into a proton in the reaction H(d,p)X is presented. The study is carried out using various parameterizations of the deuteron wave function, including the single-Gaussian parametrization, the multi-Gaussian K2 parametrization, and models based on the Av18 and NijmI nucleon-nucleon potentials. Special attention is given to the effects of small longitudinal components of the transferred momentum (Qz &lt; 0.5 GeV/c) and the transverse momentum of the proton-neutron pair (p_perp &lt; 0.5 GeV/c) in the anti-laboratory reference frame. The results are compared with experimental data, particularly in the region of longitudinal momenta p\_3 = 0.25-0.5 GeV/c, where quark effects are expected to manifest. Preliminary estimates show a decrease in the cross section with increasing transverse momentum, as well as a relatively small shift (and growth) of the cross-section maximum due to the inclusion of the longitudinal component Qz.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.06579v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ya. D. Krivenko-Emetov, B. I. Sidorenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Addressing Local Realism through Bell Tests at Colliders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10979v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: One of the most notable aspects of quantum systems is that their components can exhibit correlations much stronger than those allowed by classical physics. Two examples of quantum correlations are quantum entanglement and Bell nonlocality, but generally there is a hierarchy of many types of quantum correlations. Among these correlations, Bell nonlocality holds a special place because it plays a dual role in distinguishing theories where local realism is a valid description. A Bell test, which is a test of local realism, typically needs to be augmented with assumptions to address possible loopholes in the experimental setup. In this work, we study Bell tests in experiments in which the detector reports the correct outcome with a specified probability. This mirrors the situation at high-energy colliders, where particle spins are not measured directly but inferred from the angular distributions of their decay products. We show that, in this setup, a test of local realism is not possible. Quantum correlations, however, are still present, measurable, and informative in high-energy colliders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10979v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Low</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the Scotogenic Dirac Model with FIMP Dark Matter and $\Delta N_{\rm eff}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.16362v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study a feebly interacting massive particle realization of the Scotogenic Dirac Model in which the lightest neutral fermion $N_1$ serves as a dark matter candidate, produced via the freeze-in or super-WIMP mechanism. The model generates Dirac neutrino masses at one loop, resulting in a rank-2 mass matrix that predicts one nearly massless neutrino. We analyze the DM relic density for various next-to-lightest odd particles (NLOPs), finding that coannihilation effects and enhanced annihilation channels are crucial for achieving the correct thermal freeze-out abundance of the NLOP. We provide a detailed analysis of the model's implications for the effective number of relativistic species, $\Delta N_{\mathrm{eff}}$, which receives contributions from both a thermal bath of right-handed neutrinos and non-thermal energy injection due to late NLOP decays. Through an extensive parameter scan, we identify viable parameter space for all NLOP candidates that satisfies constraints from DM relic density, lepton flavor violation, Big Bang Nucleosynthesis, Cosmic Microwave Background, and $\Delta N_{\mathrm{eff}}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.16362v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shu-Yuan Guo, Man-Yu Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Focused Angular $N$-Body Event Generator (FANG)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11105v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce FANG (Focused Angular $N$-body event Generator), a new Monte Carlo tool for efficient event generation in restricted Lorentz-Invariant Phase Space (LIPS). Unlike conventional approaches that sample the full $4\pi$ solid angle, FANG directly generates events in which selected final-state particles are constrained to fixed directions or finite angular regions in the laboratory frame. Because of the way the generator is constructed, angular constraints can be imposed directly in the laboratory frame while maintaining the correct LIPS structure, enabling differential and total cross sections or decay rates to be computed with high efficiency. The method is validated against analytic results and existing event generators, showing excellent agreement. By reducing the computational cost of full phase-space event generation by several orders of magnitude, FANG provides a robust and versatile framework applicable to particle, nuclear, and detector physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11105v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Itay Horin, Arik Kreisel, Or Alon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark matter: red or blue?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20423</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20423v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report the first calculation of light scattering on heavy dark matter (DM) particles. We show that despite the fact that DM has no direct coupling to photons, the light-DM($\gamma\chi$) ($m_\chi \sim 1$ TeV) cross-section is non-vanishing, albeit small. The cross section, calculated within the Standard Model (SM) framework, is particularly large in the case of heavy Weakly Interacting Massive Particles (WIMP). Combined with astrophysical observation, these results can constrain existing WIMP DM models in favor of lighter DM, $M_\chi&lt;&lt;M_{\mathrm{Planck}}$, (axions, composite DM, etc..) or non-weakly interacting pure gravitational DM. We also show that the energy dependence of light scattering on dark matter should make the DM colored - red in the case of weak-DM and blue for the gravitational-DM, when a white background light is passing through. Gravitational scattering of light on DM particles also leads to non-trivial polarization effects, which might be easier to detect than the deflection of light from the scattering on DM particles, $\gamma\chi\rightarrow\gamma\chi$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20423v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Acar, C. Isaacson, M. Bashkanov, D. P. Watts</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining the new contributions to electron $g-2$ in a radiative neutrino mass model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08504</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.08504v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We examine electron and muon anomalous magnetic dipole moments within a radiative neutrino mass model featuring TeV-scale scalar leptoquarks $S(3,1,-1/3)$ and $R(3,2,1/6)$. We utilize textures with decoupling electron and muon sectors, so that both electron and muon anomalous magnetic dipole moments could receive internal chiral enhancements from different heavy up-type quarks while in the same time evading the stringent $\mu\to e\gamma$ constraint. A successful fit to neutrino oscillation data requires the simultaneous presence of one- and two-loop neutrino mass contributions. This severely constrains the parameter space of the model, which results in a negligible new physics correction to the muon $g-2$. The electron $g-2$ discrepancy implied by the rubidium experiment, on the other hand, can be resolved within $2\sigma$ uncertainty provided that neutrino mass ordering is inverted. Lepton-flavor-violating tau decay rates, such as $\tau\to e\gamma$ and $\tau\to 3e$, are predicted to be within the sensitivities of next-generation experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.08504v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bayu Dirgantara, J. Julio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HOPPET v2 release note</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09310</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09310v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We document the three main new features in the v2 release series of the HOPPET parton distribution function evolution code, specifically support for N$^3$LO QCD evolution in the variable flavour number scheme, for the determination of hadronic structure functions for massless quarks up to N$^3$LO, and for QED evolution to an accuracy phenomenologically equivalent to NNLO QCD. Additionally we describe a new Python interface, CMake build option, functionality to save a hoppet table as an LHAPDF grid and update our performance benchmarks, including optimisations in interpolating PDF tables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09310v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Karlberg, Paolo Nason, Gavin Salam, Giulia Zanderighi, Fr\'ed\'eric Dreyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling the TMD shape function in $J/\psi$ electroproduction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11809v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The next-to-leading order hard function for quarkonium electroproduction is calculated within the framework of transverse-momentum-dependent (TMD) factorization in the low-transverse-momentum regime. The structure of the TMD shape function in quarkonium leptoproduction is analyzed through its operator-level definition. Particular attention is given to the convolution of the unpolarized TMD gluon distribution with the TMD shape function, thereby illustrating the latter's phenomenological role. Building on this framework, we provide predictions for the unpolarized differential cross-section of $J/\psi$ electroproduction at the future Electron-Ion Collider in the region of small transverse momentum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11809v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel G. Echevarria, Raj Kishore, Samuel F. Romera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for generalized neutrino interactions in direct detection experiments with E{\nu}ES</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17027v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the sensitivity of present and future direct detection experiments to generalized neutrino interactions (GNI) through elastic neutrino electron scattering. Using data from LUX-ZEPLIN, PandaX-4T, and XENONnT, we derive constraints on vector, axial-vector, scalar, and tensor effective couplings, and compare them with existing limits. Our results show that current xenon-based detectors already provide competitive bounds, with XENONnT offering the most stringent constraints due to its larger exposure and reduced backgrounds. Among the GNI couplings, the scalar contributions remain more weakly constrained, while tensor interactions yield the strongest limits. We also present projected sensitivities for the DARWIN experiment, showing potential improvements. These results demonstrate the capability of direct detection experiments, originally designed for dark matter searches, to provide complementary and competitive constraints on generalized neutrino interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17027v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jes\'us Miguel Celestino-Ram\'irez, F. J. Escrihuela, L. J. Flores, O. G. Miranda, R. S\'anchez-V\'elez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>B-Meson Anomalies: Effective Field Theory Meets Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17742</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17742v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Discrepancies between experimental measurements and Standard Model predictions in $B$-meson decays, especially in lepton flavor universality ratios like $R_{D^{(*)}}$, $R_{J/\psi}$ and branching ratios for processes like $B\to K^+\nu\bar\nu$, suggest possible new physics (NP). In this study, we use an effective field theory framework, assuming NP effects only affect a single generation in the interaction basis, leading to non-universal mixing when rotating to the mass basis. We perform a global fit to the current experimental data, exploring three scenarios characterized by different mixing patterns and constraints. Our analysis finds that the best fit involves mixing between the second and third quark generations, with no lepton sector mixing and independent coefficients for singlet and triplet four-fermion operators. To accurately capture the non-Gaussian nature of the resulting parameter distributions, we use a Machine Learning-based Monte Carlo algorithm, enabling the generation of representative samples that reflect the true underlying distributions. This work highlights the valuable role of Machine Learning in accurately modeling complex parameter distributions in particle physics analyses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17742v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alejandro Mir, Jorge Alda, Siannah Penaranda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sensitivity forecasts for gravitational-wave detectors to dark matter decaying into gravitons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18958v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dark matter may not be perfectly stable, and its decay could generate distinctive gravitational-wave signatures. In this work, we present model-independent predictions for the stochastic gravitational-wave background arising from the decay of ultralight dark matter into gravitons. Within this framework, we forecast the sensitivity reach of current and forthcoming gravitational-wave detectors to such signals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18958v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose A. R. Cembranos, \'Alvaro Cendal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the light charged Higgs boson, pseudoscalar Higgs boson, and $Z^\prime$ boson in the $U(1)_F$ model at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22537v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this papar, we study the production and decay of a charged Higgs boson, a pseudoscalar Higgs boson, and a $Z'$ boson at the LHC within the flavor-dependent model (FDM), at the LHC. Considering the constraints from perturbative unitarity and experimental measurements (e.g., the flavor physics data, higgs signal strengths, electroweak precision observables), we investigate the relevant processes by analyzing several common LHC search channels. Motivated by the excess in $t \to b\bar{b}c$ reported by ATLAS, which suggests a charged Higgs boson with a mass near 130 GeV and consistent with B-anomaly expectations, we perform a dedicated simulation for a charged Higgs around this mass. Our results support the experimental hint and predict that this particle has a high discovery potential at the future High-Luminosity Large Hadron Collider (HL-LHC). In contrast, for the pseudoscalar and $Z'$ bosons predicted in our model, they remain beyond the reach of current experiments as well as the expected sensitivity at a 14 TeV collider with an integrated luminosity of 300 fb$^{-1}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22537v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhan Cao, Zhong-Jun Yang, Jin-Lei Yang, Tai-Fu Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mass and Decay-Constant Evolution of Heavy Quarkonia and $B_c$ States from Thermal QCD Sum Rules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22870v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We analyze the thermal behavior of heavy vector and axial-vector mesons ($J/\psi$, $\Upsilon$, and $B_c$) within the finite-temperature QCD sum-rule framework. Using updated PDG-2024 quark masses, modern lattice-informed gluon condensates, and a temperature-dependent continuum threshold constrained by vacuum stability, we compute the evolution of the masses $m(T)$ and decay constants $f(T)$ up to $T/T_c \lesssim 0.9$. The extracted zero-temperature limits reproduce experimental and LHCb values within 1\%. Near the critical temperature, the relative suppression follows a clear hierarchy $\Upsilon &lt; J/\psi &lt; B_c$, consistent with their binding energies and lattice spectral trends. The predicted $1P$--$1S$ splitting for the $B_c$ system, $0.477~\mathrm{GeV}$, matches the LHCb observation of orbitally excited $B_c^{+}$ states. The results provide a coherent finite-temperature baseline for future extensions including radiative, higher-dimensional, and width effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22870v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enis Yazici</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prospects for a 95 GeV Higgs Boson at Future Higgs Factories with Transformer Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24662</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24662v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Several experimental analyses have reported mild excesses near 95 GeV that could indicate the presence of a light Higgs-like scalar. We study the phenomenology of such a state within the flipped Next-to-Two-Higgs-Doublet Model (N2HDM-F) at the proposed Circular Electron--Positron Collider (CEPC). The light scalar $S$ is investigated through the Higgsstrahlung process $e^+e^- \to Z(\mu^+\mu^-)S$ with $S\to\tau^+\tau^-$ and $S\to b \bar{b}$ decay modes. A full Monte Carlo simulation including detector effects is performed to estimate the discovery reach and precision measurement potential. To maximize the sensitivity, we employ particle-level transformer networks (ParT and MIParT) that exploit correlations among all reconstructed objects. Compared with a cut-based baseline, improves the expected measurement precision by a factor of 2.4 in the $\tau\tau$ channel and 1.4 in the $b b$ channel. For viable benchmark points in the N2HDM-F, the attainable precisions on the signal rate reach 1.0% and 0.63%, respectively. Interpreted in a model-independent framework, the CEPC can achieve a 5$\sigma$ discovery for $\mu_{\tau\tau}^{ZS}&gt;1.6\times10^{-2}$ and $\mu_{bb}^{ZS}&gt;4.2\times10^{-3}$, and reach a 1% precision for $\mu_{\tau\tau}^{ZS}&gt;0.96$ and $\mu_{bb}^{ZS}&gt;0.13$. These results highlight the potential of particle-level machine learning techniques in extending the light-Higgs exploration program at future lepton colliders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24662v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yabo Dong, Manqi Ruan, Kun Wang, Haijun Yang, Jingya Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Kalb-Ramond field and Gravitational Parity Violation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.14452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.14452v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Gravitational wave physics can probe theories that extend beyond General Relativity. Motivated by the attention on the Kalb-Ramond field as a dark matter candidate, in this work, we study a parity violating dimension four operator which couples the dual Riemann curvature to the 2-form field. After mapping the equations of motion for the right- and left-handed gravitational wave amplitudes to the novel parameterization presented in \cite{Jenks:2023pmk}, we discuss constraints on the model parameters in light of the coincident electromagnetic/gravitational wave signal of GW170817.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.14452v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tucker Manton, Stephon Alexander</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum simulation of the phase transition of the massive Thirring model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.00803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.00803v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent advancements in quantum computing technology have enabled the study of fermionic systems at finite temperature via quantum simulations. This presents a novel approach to investigating the chiral phase transition in such systems. Among these, the quantum minimally entangled typical thermal states~(QMETTS) algorithm has recently attracted considerable interest. The massive Thirring model, which exhibits a variety of phenomena at low temperatures, includes both a chiral phase transition and a topologically non-trivial ground state. It therefore raises the intriguing question of whether its phase transition can be studied using a quantum simulation approach. In this study, the chiral phase transition of the massive Thirring model and its dual topological phase transition are studied using the QMETTS algorithm. Numerical results are obtained on a classical computer simulating circuit-based quantum computations. The results show that QMETTS is able to accurately reproduce the phase transition and thermodynamic properties of the massive Thirring model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.00803v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP09(2025)120</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of High Energy Physics volume 2025, Article number: 120 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Qi Gong, Ji-Chong Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of strange molecular partners of $P_c$ states in $\gamma p \to K \Sigma$ reactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05811</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.05811v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Our previous studies revealed evidence of the strange molecular partners of $P_c$ states, $N(2080)3/2^-$ and $N(2270)3/2^-$, in the $\gamma p \to K^{*+} \Sigma^0 / K^{*0} \Sigma^+$ and $\gamma p \to \phi p$ reactions. Motivated by the differential cross-section data for $\gamma p \to K^+ \Sigma^0$ from CLAS 2010, which exhibits some bump structures at $W \approx$ 1875, 2080 and 2270 MeV, we extend our previous analysis by investigating the effects of $N(1535)1/2^-$, $N(1875)3/2^-$, $N(2080)1/2^- \&amp;\ 3/2^-$ and $N(2270)1/2^- , 3/2^- \&amp;\ 5/2^-$, as strange partners of $P_c$ molecular states, in the reactions $\gamma p \to K^+ \Sigma^0$ and $\gamma p \to K^0 \Sigma^+$. The theoretical model employed in this study utilizes an effective Lagrangian approach in the tree-level Born approximation. It contains the contributions from $s$-channel with exchanges of $N$, $\Delta$, $N^*$ (including the hadronic molecules with hidden strangeness), and $\Delta^*$; $t$-channel; $u$-channel; and the generalized contact term. The results based on the final fitted parameters are in good agreement with all available experimental data of both cross-sections and polarization observables for $\gamma p \to K^+ \Sigma^0$ and $\gamma p \to K^0 \Sigma^+$. Notably, the $s$-channel exchanges of molecules significantly contribute to the bump structures in cross-sections for $\gamma p \to K \Sigma$ at $W \approx$ 1900, 2080 and 2270 MeV, and show considerable coherence with contributions from $s$-channel exchanges of general resonances to construct the overall structures of cross-sections. More abundant experiments, particularly for the reaction $\gamma p \to K^0 \Sigma^+$, are necessary to further strengthen the constraints on the theoretical models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.05811v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian-Cheng Suo, Di Ben, Bing-Song Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Parton Distributions from Lattice QCD with Asymmetric Momentum Transfer: Unpolarized Quarks at Nonzero Skewness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17998v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We extend the formalism of asymmetric frames of reference for generalized parton distributions (GPDs) to the case of nonzero skewness, i.e., including longitudinal momentum transfer. The framework, based on Lorentz-invariant amplitudes and previously developed and numerically implemented for unpolarized, helicity and transversity GPDs at zero skewness, gives efficient access to a broad range of kinematics, making full mapping of GPDs from the lattice realistic. The general-skewness formalism is tested using lattice data with both transverse and longitudinal or only longitudinal momentum transfer, the latter being a special case with a reduced number of independent amplitudes. We extract the amplitudes in coordinate space and express the GPDs $H$ and $E$ in terms of these amplitudes. This is followed by reconstruction of quasi-distributions and their matching to the light cone. We further identify and discuss the principal challenges for nonzero skewness GPDs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17998v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Min-Huan Chu, Manuel Cola\c{c}o, Shohini Bhattacharya, Krzysztof Cichy, Martha Constantinou, Andreas Metz, Fernanda Steffens</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
