<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.ET updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.ET</link>
    <description>cs.ET updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.ET" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 04:00:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Omni 3D: BEOL-Compatible 3D Logic with Omnipresent Power, Signal, and Clock</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16608</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.16608v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents Omni 3D - a 3D-stacked device architecture that is naturally enabled by back-end-of-line (BEOL)-compatible transistors. Omni 3D arbitrarily interleaves metal layers for both signal/power with FETs in 3D (i.e., nFETs and pFETs are stacked in 3D). Thus, signal/power routing layers have fine-grained, all-sided access to the FET active regions maximizing 3D standard cell design flexibility. This is in sharp contrast to approaches such as back-side power delivery networks (BSPDNs), complementary FETs (CFETs), and stacked FETs. Importantly, the routing flexibility of Omni 3D is enabled by double-side routing and an interleaved metal (IM) layer for inter- and intra-cell routing, respectively. In this work, we explore Omni 3D variants (e.g., both with and without the IM layer) and optimize these variants using a virtual-source BEOL-FET compact model. We establish a physical design flow that efficiently utilizes the double-side routing in Omni 3D and perform a thorough design-technology-co-optimization (DTCO) of Omni 3D device architecture on several design points. From our design flow, we project 2.0x improvement in the energy-delay product and 1.5x reduction in area compared to the state-of-the-art CFETs with BSPDNs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.16608v1</guid>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suhyeong Choi, Carlo Gilardi, Paul Gutwin, Robert M. Radway, Tathagata Srimani, Subhasish Mitra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Alternative to Multi-Factor Authentication with a Triple-Identity Authentication Scheme</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19459v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The existing authentication system has two entry points (i.e., username and password fields) to interact with the outside, but neither of them has a gatekeeper, making the system vulnerable to cyberattacks. In order to ensure the authentication security, the system sets a third entry point and use an external MFA service to guard it. The crux of the problem is that the system has no internal mechanism to guard its own entry points as no identifiers can be defined for the username and password without using any personal information. To solve this problem, we open the hash algorithm of a dual-password login-authentication system to three login credentials. Therefore, the intermediate elements of the algorithm can be used to define an identifier to verify the user identity at each entry point of the system. As a result of the above setup, a triple-identity authentication is established, the key of which is that the readily available user's login name and password are randomly converted into a matrix of meaningless hash elements which are concealed, incommunicable, inaccessible, and independent of personal information. So the identifiers defined using such elements can be used by the system to verify the identities of the user at all the entry points of the system, thereby ensuring the authentication security without relying on MFA services.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19459v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suyun Borjigin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advancing Cyber Incident Timeline Analysis Through Rule Based AI and Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02572v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Timeline Analysis (TA) plays a crucial role in Timeline Forensics (TF) within the field of Digital Forensics (DF). It focuses on examining and analyzing time-based digital artefacts, such as timestamps derived from event logs, file metadata, and other relevant data, to correlate events linked to cyber incidents and reconstruct their chronological sequence. Traditional tools often struggle to efficiently handle the large volume and variety of data generated during DF investigations and Incident Response (IR) processes. This paper introduces a novel framework, GenDFIR, which combines Rule-Based Artificial Intelligence (R-BAI) algorithms with Large Language Models (LLMs) to enhance and automate the TA process. The proposed approach consists of two key stages: (1) R-BAI is used to identify and select anomalous digital artefacts based on predefined rules. (2) The selected artefacts are then transformed into embeddings for processing by an LLM with the assistance of a Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) agent. The LLM uses its capabilities to perform automated TA on the artefacts and predict potential incident outcomes. To validate the framework, we evaluated its performance, efficiency, and reliability. Several metrics were applied to simulated cyber incident scenarios, which were presented as forensic case documents. Our findings demonstrate the significant potential of integrating R-BAI and LLMs for TA. This innovative approach underscores the power of Generative AI (GenAI), particularly LLMs, and opens up new possibilities for advanced threat detection and incident reconstruction, marking a significant advancement in the field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02572v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fatma Yasmine Loumachi, Mohamed Chahine Ghanem</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
