<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.ET updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.ET</link>
    <description>cs.ET updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.ET" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2024 01:33:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>An Initial Study of Human-Scale Blockage in sub-THz Radio Propagation with Application to Indoor Passive Localization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16894v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper empirically investigates the body induced electromagnetic (EM) effects, namely the human body blockage, by conducting indoor measurement campaigns in the unexplored sub-THz W-band (75-110 GHz) and G-band (170-260 GHz). The proposed analysis focuses on both the alterations of channel frequency response induced by body presence, fully or partially obstructing the line-of-sight (LoS) between transmitter and recevier, as well as on the channel impulse response (CIR) for selected movements of the target, i.e. crossing the LoS of the radio link. Modelling of large scale parameters is also presented using a phantom body object. The proposed study has applications in device-free radio localization and radio frequency (RF) sensing scenarios where the EM radiation or environmental radio signals are collected and processed to detect and locate people without requiring them to wear any electronic devices. Although preliminary, the study reveals that discrimination of the blockage micro-movements is possible, achieving higher precision compared to classical RF sensing and localization using cm-scale wavelengths (2.4-6GHz bands).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16894v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Paonessa, G. Virone, S. Kianoush, A. Nordio, S. Savazzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Deep Learning for Predicting Microbial Fuel Cell Energy Output</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16939</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16939v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Soil microbial fuel cells (SMFCs) are an emerging technology which offer clean and renewable energy in environments where more traditional power sources, such as chemical batteries or solar, are not suitable. With further development, SMFCs show great promise for use in robust and affordable outdoor sensor networks, particularly for farmers. One of the greatest challenges in the development of this technology is understanding and predicting the fluctuations of SMFC energy generation, as the electro-generative process is not yet fully understood. Very little work currently exists attempting to model and predict the relationship between soil conditions and SMFC energy generation, and we are the first to use machine learning to do so. In this paper, we train Long Short Term Memory (LSTM) models to predict the future energy generation of SMFCs across timescales ranging from 3 minutes to 1 hour, with results ranging from 2.33% to 5.71% MAPE for median voltage prediction. For each timescale, we use quantile regression to obtain point estimates and to establish bounds on the uncertainty of these estimates. When comparing the median predicted vs. actual values for the total energy generated during the testing period, the magnitude of prediction errors ranged from 2.29% to 16.05%. To demonstrate the real-world utility of this research, we also simulate how the models could be used in an automated environment where SMFC-powered devices shut down and activate intermittently to preserve charge, with promising initial results. Our deep learning-based prediction and simulation framework would allow a fully automated SMFC-powered device to achieve a median 100+% increase in successful operations, compared to a naive model that schedules operations based on the average voltage generated in the past.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16939v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam Hess-Dunlop, Harshitha Kakani, Colleen Josephson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EON-1: A Brain-Inspired Processor for Near-Sensor Extreme Edge Online Feature Extraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17285</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17285v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For Edge AI applications, deploying online learning and adaptation on resource-constrained embedded devices can deal with fast sensor-generated streams of data in changing environments. However, since maintaining low-latency and power-efficient inference is paramount at the Edge, online learning and adaptation on the device should impose minimal additional overhead for inference. With this goal in mind, we explore energy-efficient learning and adaptation on-device for streaming-data Edge AI applications using Spiking Neural Networks (SNNs), which follow the principles of brain-inspired computing, such as high-parallelism, neuron co-located memory and compute, and event-driven processing. We propose EON-1, a brain-inspired processor for near-sensor extreme edge online feature extraction, that integrates a fast online learning and adaptation algorithm. We report results of only 1% energy overhead for learning, by far the lowest overhead when compared to other SoTA solutions, while attaining comparable inference accuracy. Furthermore, we demonstrate that EON-1 is up for the challenge of low-latency processing of HD and UHD streaming video in real-time, with learning enabled.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17285v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandra Dobrita (Imec Netherlands, Delft University of Technology), Amirreza Yousefzadeh (Imec Netherlands), Simon Thorpe (University of Toulouse), Kanishkan Vadivel (Imec Netherlands), Paul Detterer (Imec Netherlands), Guangzhi Tang (Imec Netherlands), Gert-Jan van Schaik (Imec Netherlands), Mario Konijnenburg (Imec Netherlands), Anteneh Gebregiorgis (Delft University of Technology), Said Hamdioui (Delft University of Technology), Manolis Sifalakis (Imec Netherlands)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KANQAS: Kolmogorov Arnold Network for Quantum Architecture Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17630v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum architecture search~(QAS) is a promising direction for optimization and automated design of quantum circuits towards quantum advantage. Recent techniques in QAS focus on machine learning-based approaches from reinforcement learning, like deep Q-network. While multi-layer perceptron-based deep Q-networks have been applied for QAS, their interpretability remains challenging due to the high number of parameters. In this work, we evaluate the practicality of KANs in quantum architecture search problems, analyzing their efficiency in terms of the probability of success, frequency of optimal solutions and their dependencies on various degrees of freedom of the network. In a noiseless scenario, the probability of success and the number of optimal quantum circuit configurations to generate the multi-qubit maximally entangled states are significantly higher than MLPs. Moreover in noisy scenarios, KAN can achieve a better fidelity in approximating maximally entangled state than MLPs, where the performance of the MLP significantly depends on the choice of activation function. Further investigation reveals that KAN requires a very small number of learnable parameters compared to MLPs, however, the average time of executing each episode for KAN is much higher.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17630v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akash Kundu, Aritra Sarkar, Abhishek Sadhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
