<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.ET updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.ET</link>
    <description>cs.ET updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.ET" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 04:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>L0-regularized compressed sensing with Mean-field Coherent Ising Machines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00366</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00366v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Coherent Ising Machine (CIM) is a network of optical parametric oscillators that solves combinatorial optimization problems by finding the ground state of an Ising Hamiltonian. As a practical application of CIM, Aonishi et al. proposed a quantum-classical hybrid system to solve optimization problems of L0-regularization-based compressed sensing (L0RBCS). Gunathilaka et al. has further enhanced the accuracy of the system. However, the computationally expensive CIM's stochastic differential equations (SDEs) limit the use of digital hardware implementations. As an alternative to Gunathilaka et al.'s CIM SDEs used previously, we propose using the mean-field CIM (MF-CIM) model, which is a physics-inspired heuristic solver without quantum noise. MF-CIM surmounts the high computational cost due to the simple nature of the differential equations (DEs). Furthermore, our results indicate that the proposed model has similar performance to physically accurate SDEs in both artificial and magnetic resonance imaging data, paving the way for implementing CIM-based L0RBCS on digital hardware such as Field Programmable Gate Arrays (FPGAs).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00366v1</guid>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mastiyage Don Sudeera Hasaranga Gunathilaka, Yoshitaka Inui, Satoshi Kako, Kazushi Mimura, Masato Okada, Yoshihisa Yamamoto, Toru Aonishi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Averting multi-qubit burst errors in surface code magic state factories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00146v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fault-tolerant quantum computation relies on the assumption of time-invariant, sufficiently low physical error rates. However, current superconducting quantum computers suffer from frequent disruptive noise events, including cosmic ray impacts and shifting two-level system defects. Several methods have been proposed to mitigate these issues in software, but they add large overheads in terms of physical qubit count, as it is difficult to preserve logical information through burst error events. We focus on mitigating multi-qubit burst errors in magic state factories, which are expected to comprise up to 95% of the space cost of future quantum programs. Our key insight is that magic state factories do not need to preserve logical information over time; once we detect an increase in local physical error rates, we can simply turn off parts of the factory that are affected, re-map the factory to the new chip geometry, and continue operating. This is much more efficient than previous more general methods, and is resilient even under many simultaneous impact events. Using precise physical noise models, we show an efficient ray detection method and evaluate our strategy in different noise regimes. Compared to existing baselines, we find reductions in ray-induced overheads by several orders of magnitude, reducing total qubitcycle cost by geomean 6.5x to 13.9x depending on the noise model. This work reduces the burden on hardware by providing low-overhead software mitigation of these errors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00146v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jason D. Chadwick, Christopher Kang, Joshua Viszlai, Sophia Fuhui Lin, Frederic T. Chong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Legal Framework for Natural Language Processing Model Training in Portugal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00536v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent advances in deep learning have promoted the advent of many computational systems capable of performing intelligent actions that, until then, were restricted to the human intellect. In the particular case of human languages, these advances allowed the introduction of applications like ChatGPT that are capable of generating coherent text without being explicitly programmed to do so. Instead, these models use large volumes of textual data to learn meaningful representations of human languages. Associated with these advances, concerns about copyright and data privacy infringements caused by these applications have emerged. Despite these concerns, the pace at which new natural language processing applications continued to be developed largely outperformed the introduction of new regulations. Today, communication barriers between legal experts and computer scientists motivate many unintentional legal infringements during the development of such applications. In this paper, a multidisciplinary team intends to bridge this communication gap and promote more compliant Portuguese NLP research by presenting a series of everyday NLP use cases, while highlighting the Portuguese legislation that may arise during its development.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00536v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R\'uben Almeida, Evelin Amorim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Achieving Optimum Received Power with Elementwise Updates in the Least Number of Steps for Discrete-Phase RISs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.07686</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.07686v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The problem of optimizing discrete phases in a reconfigurable intelligent surface (RIS) to maximize the received power at a user equipment is addressed. Necessary and sufficient conditions to achieve this maximization are given. These conditions are employed in an algorithm to achieve the maximization. New versions of the algorithm are given that are proven to achieve convergence in N or fewer steps whether the direct link is completely blocked or not, where N is the number of the RIS elements, whereas previously published results achieve this in KN or 2N number of steps where K is the number of discrete phases. Thus, for a discrete-phase RIS, the techniques presented in this paper achieve the optimum received power in the smallest number of steps published in the literature. In addition, in each of those N steps, the techniques presented in this paper determine only one or a small number of phase shifts with a simple elementwise update rule, which result in a substantial reduction of computation time, as compared to the algorithms in the literature. As a secondary result, we define the uniform polar quantization (UPQ) algorithm which is an intuitive quantization algorithm that can approximate the continuous solution with an approximation ratio of sinc^2(1/K) and achieve low time-complexity, given perfect knowledge of the channel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.07686v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/OJCOMS.2024.3386559</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Dogan Kutay Pekcan, Ender Ayanoglu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Dawn of AI-Native EDA: Opportunities and Challenges of Large Circuit Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07257v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Within the Electronic Design Automation (EDA) domain, AI-driven solutions have emerged as formidable tools, yet they typically augment rather than redefine existing methodologies. These solutions often repurpose deep learning models from other domains, such as vision, text, and graph analytics, applying them to circuit design without tailoring to the unique complexities of electronic circuits. Such an AI4EDA approach falls short of achieving a holistic design synthesis and understanding, overlooking the intricate interplay of electrical, logical, and physical facets of circuit data. This paper argues for a paradigm shift from AI4EDA towards AI-native EDA, integrating AI at the core of the design process. Pivotal to this vision is the development of a multimodal circuit representation learning technique, poised to provide a comprehensive understanding by harmonizing and extracting insights from varied data sources, such as functional specifications, RTL designs, circuit netlists, and physical layouts. We champion the creation of large circuit models (LCMs) that are inherently multimodal, crafted to decode and express the rich semantics and structures of circuit data, thus fostering more resilient, efficient, and inventive design methodologies. Embracing this AI-native philosophy, we foresee a trajectory that transcends the current innovation plateau in EDA, igniting a profound shift-left in electronic design methodology. The envisioned advancements herald not just an evolution of existing EDA tools but a revolution, giving rise to novel instruments of design tools that promise to radically enhance design productivity and inaugurate a new epoch where the optimization of circuit performance, power, and area (PPA) is achieved not incrementally, but through leaps that redefine the benchmarks of electronic systems' capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07257v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Chen (Huawei Noah's Ark Lab), Yiqi Chen (Peking University), Zhufei Chu (Ningbo University), Wenji Fang (Hong Kong University of Science and Technology), Tsung-Yi Ho (The Chinese University of Hong Kong), Ru Huang (Peking University, Southeast University), Yu Huang (Huawei HiSilicon), Sadaf Khan (The Chinese University of Hong Kong), Min Li (Huawei Noah's Ark Lab), Xingquan Li (Peng Cheng Laboratory), Yu Li (The Chinese University of Hong Kong), Yun Liang (Peking University), Jinwei Liu (The Chinese University of Hong Kong), Yi Liu (The Chinese University of Hong Kong), Yibo Lin (Peking University), Guojie Luo (Peking University), Zhengyuan Shi (The Chinese University of Hong Kong), Guangyu Sun (Peking University), Dimitrios Tsaras (Huawei Noah's Ark Lab), Runsheng Wang (Peking University), Ziyi Wang (The Chinese University of Hong Kong), Xinming Wei (Peking University), Zhiyao Xie (Hong Kong University of Science and Technology), Qiang Xu (The Chinese University of Hong Kong), Chenhao Xue (Peking University), Junchi Yan (Shanghai Jiao Tong University), Jun Yang (Southeast University), Bei Yu (The Chinese University of Hong Kong), Mingxuan Yuan (Huawei Noah's Ark Lab), Evangeline F. Y. Young (The Chinese University of Hong Kong), Xuan Zeng (Fudan University), Haoyi Zhang (Peking University), Zuodong Zhang (Peking University), Yuxiang Zhao (Peking University), Hui-Ling Zhen (Huawei Noah's Ark Lab), Ziyang Zheng (The Chinese University of Hong Kong), Binwu Zhu (The Chinese University of Hong Kong), Keren Zhu (The Chinese University of Hong Kong), Sunan Zou (Peking University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
