<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.ET updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.ET</link>
    <description>cs.ET updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.ET" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 05:00:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>BMG-Q: Localized Bipartite Match Graph Attention Q-Learning for Ride-Pooling Order Dispatch</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13448v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper introduces Localized Bipartite Match Graph Attention Q-Learning (BMG-Q), a novel Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning (MARL) algorithm framework tailored for ride-pooling order dispatch. BMG-Q advances ride-pooling decision-making process with the localized bipartite match graph underlying the Markov Decision Process, enabling the development of novel Graph Attention Double Deep Q Network (GATDDQN) as the MARL backbone to capture the dynamic interactions among ride-pooling vehicles in fleet. Our approach enriches the state information for each agent with GATDDQN by leveraging a localized bipartite interdependence graph and enables a centralized global coordinator to optimize order matching and agent behavior using Integer Linear Programming (ILP). Enhanced by gradient clipping and localized graph sampling, our GATDDQN improves scalability and robustness. Furthermore, the inclusion of a posterior score function in the ILP captures the online exploration-exploitation trade-off and reduces the potential overestimation bias of agents, thereby elevating the quality of the derived solutions. Through extensive experiments and validation, BMG-Q has demonstrated superior performance in both training and operations for thousands of vehicle agents, outperforming benchmark reinforcement learning frameworks by around 10% in accumulative rewards and showing a significant reduction in overestimation bias by over 50%. Additionally, it maintains robustness amidst task variations and fleet size changes, establishing BMG-Q as an effective, scalable, and robust framework for advancing ride-pooling order dispatch operations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13448v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yulong Hu, Siyuan Feng, Sen Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Throughput, Energy-Efficient RRAM-Based In-Memory Computing LPN Accelerator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10702v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: As a strong candidate for the post-quantum crypto-graphic (PQC) era, Learning Parity with Noise (LPN) has been extensively studied in the field of cryptography. However, the data transfer bottleneck between the computation and memory modules has significantly hindered the development of LPN-based cryptographic techniques due to large matrices. This work introduces an RRAM-based in-memory computing LPN accelerator aimed at overcoming data transfer bottlenecks, thereby executing LPN computation tasks efficiently. To ensure the high accuracy of the LPN AND operation, a folded current amplification circuit is proposed to address the leakage current issue caused by the limited high-resistance state of RRAM. Meanwhile, a Cumulative XOR Fast Computing Method is introduced to efficiently convert accumulated current values into LPN XOR operation results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10702v2</guid>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Yue, Yihao Chen, Zhelong Jiang, Zhigang Li, Gang Chen, Huaxiang Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defining Quantum Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.00089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.00089v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this research article, we survey existing quantum physics-related games and, based on this survey, propose a definition for the concept of quantum games. We define a quantum game as any type of rule-based game that either employs the principles of quantum physics or references quantum phenomena or the theory of quantum physics through any of three proposed dimensions: the perceivable dimension of quantum physics, the dimension of quantum technologies, and the dimension of scientific purposes, such as citizen science or education. We also discuss the concept of quantum computer games, which are games on quantum computers, as well as definitions for the concept of science games. Various games explore quantum physics and quantum computing through digital, analogue, and hybrid means, with various incentives driving their development. As interest in games as educational tools for supporting quantum literacy grows, understanding the diverse landscape of quantum games becomes increasingly important. We propose that the three dimensions of quantum games identified in this article be used for designing, analysing, and defining the phenomenon of quantum games.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.00089v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjqt/s40507-025-00308-7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>EPJ Quantum Technol. 12, 7 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Laura Piispanen, Marcel Pfaffhauser, James Wootton, Julian Togelius, Annakaisa Kultima</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
