<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.ET updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.ET</link>
    <description>cs.ET updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.ET" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 02:13:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Voice-based AI Agents: Filling the Economic Gaps in Digital Health Delivery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16229</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16229v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The integration of voice-based AI agents in healthcare presents a transformative opportunity to bridge economic and accessibility gaps in digital health delivery. This paper explores the role of large language model (LLM)-powered voice assistants in enhancing preventive care and continuous patient monitoring, particularly in underserved populations. Drawing insights from the development and pilot study of Agent PULSE (Patient Understanding and Liaison Support Engine) -- a collaborative initiative between IBM Research, Cleveland Clinic Foundation, and Morehouse School of Medicine -- we present an economic model demonstrating how AI agents can provide cost-effective healthcare services where human intervention is economically unfeasible. Our pilot study with 33 inflammatory bowel disease patients revealed that 70\% expressed acceptance of AI-driven monitoring, with 37\% preferring it over traditional modalities. Technical challenges, including real-time conversational AI processing, integration with healthcare systems, and privacy compliance, are analyzed alongside policy considerations surrounding regulation, bias mitigation, and patient autonomy. Our findings suggest that AI-driven voice agents not only enhance healthcare scalability and efficiency but also improve patient engagement and accessibility. For healthcare executives, our cost-utility analysis demonstrates huge potential savings for routine monitoring tasks, while technologists can leverage our framework to prioritize improvements yielding the highest patient impact. By addressing current limitations and aligning AI development with ethical and regulatory frameworks, voice-based AI agents can serve as a critical entry point for equitable, sustainable digital healthcare solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16229v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bo Wen, Chen Wang, Qiwei Han, Raquel Norel, Julia Liu, Thaddeus Stappenbeck, Jeffrey L. Rogers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Autocallable Options Pricing with Integration-Based Exponential Amplitude Loading</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19039</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19039v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive quantum algorithm tailored for pricing autocallable options, offering a full implementation and experimental validation. Our experiments include simulations conducted on high-performance computing (HPC) hardware, along with an empirical analysis of convergence to the classically estimated value. Our key innovation is an improved integration-based exponential amplitude loading technique that reduces circuit depth compared to state-of-the-art approaches. A detailed complexity analysis in a relevant setting shows an approximately 50x reduction in T-depth for the payoff component relative to previous methods. These contributions represent a step toward more efficient quantum approaches to pricing complex financial derivatives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19039v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>q-fin.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesca Cibrario, Ron Cohen, Emanuele Dri, Christian Mattia, Or Samimi Golan, Tamuz Danzig, Giacomo Ranieri, Hanan Rosemarin, Davide Corbelletto, Amir Naveh, Bartolomeo Montrucchio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implementing Credit Risk Analysis with Quantum Singular Value Transformation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19206v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The analysis of credit risk is crucial for the efficient operation of financial institutions. Quantum Amplitude Estimation (QAE) offers the potential for a quadratic speed-up over classical methods used to estimate metrics such as Value at Risk (VaR) and Conditional Value at Risk (CVaR). However, numerous limitations remain in efficiently scaling the implementation of quantum circuits that solve these estimation problems. One of the main challenges is the use of costly and restrictive arithmetic that must be implemented within the quantum circuit. In this paper, we propose using Quantum Singular Value Transformation (QSVT) to significantly reduce the cost of implementing the state preparation operator, which underlies QAE for credit risk analysis. We also present an end-to-end code implementation and the results of a simulation study to validate the proposed approach and demonstrate its benefits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19206v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davide Veronelli, Francesca Cibrario, Emanuele Dri, Valeria Zaffaroni, Giacomo Ranieri, Davide Corbelletto, Bartolomeo Montrucchio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SILS: Strategic Influence on Liquidity Stability and Whale Detection in Concentrated-Liquidity DEXs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19411v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Traditional methods for identifying impactful liquidity providers (LPs) in Concentrated Liquidity Market Makers (CLMMs) rely on broad measures, such as nominal capital size or surface-level activity, which often lead to inaccurate risk analysis. The SILS framework offers a significantly more detailed approach, characterizing LPs not just as capital holders but as dynamic systemic agents whose actions directly impact market stability. This represents a fundamental paradigm shift from the static, volume-based analysis to a dynamic, impact-focused understanding. This advanced approach uses on-chain event logs and smart contract execution traces to compute Exponential Time-Weighted Liquidity (ETWL) profiles and apply unsupervised anomaly detection. Most importantly, it defines an LP's functional importance through the Liquidity Stability Impact Score (LSIS), a counterfactual metric that measures the potential degradation of the market if the LP withdraws. This combined approach provides a more detailed and realistic characterization of an LP's impact, moving beyond the binary and often misleading classifications used by existing methods. This impact-focused and comprehensive approach enables SILS to accurately identify high-impact LPs-including those missed by traditional methods and supports essential applications like a protective oracle layer and actionable trader signals, thereby significantly enhancing DeFi ecosystem. The framework provides unprecedented transparency into the underlying liquidity structure and associated risks, effectively reducing the common false positives and uncovering critical false negatives found in traditional models. Therefore, SILS provides an effective mechanism for proactive risk management, transforming how DeFi protocols safeguard their ecosystems against asymmetric liquidity behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19411v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali RajabiNekoo, Laleh Rasoul, Amirfarhad Farhadi, Azadeh Zamanifar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Addressing the Minor-Embedding Problem in Quantum Annealing and Evaluating State-of-the-Art Algorithm Performance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13376v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study addresses the minor-embedding problem, which involves mapping the variables of an Ising model onto a quantum annealing processor. The primary motivation stems from the observed performance disparity of quantum annealers when solving problems suited to the processor's architecture versus those with non-hardware-native topologies. Our research has two main objectives: i) to analyze the impact of embedding quality on the performance of D-Wave Systems quantum annealers, and ii) to evaluate the quality of the embeddings generated by Minorminer, the standard minor-embedding technique in the quantum annealing literature, provided by D-Wave. Regarding the first objective, our experiments reveal a clear correlation between the average chain length of embeddings and the relative errors of the solutions sampled. This underscores the critical influence of embedding quality on quantum annealing performance. For the second objective, we evaluate Minorminer's embedding capabilities, the quality and robustness of its embeddings, and its execution-time performance. We also compare its performance with Clique Embedding, another algorithm developed by D-Wave, which is deterministic and designed to embed fully connected Ising models into quantum annealing processors, serving as a worst-case scenario. The results demonstrate that there is significant room for improvement for Minorminer, suggesting that more effective embedding strategies could lead to meaningful gains in quantum annealing performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13376v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aitor Gomez-Tejedor, Eneko Osaba, Esther Villar-Rodriguez</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
