<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.ET updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.ET</link>
    <description>cs.ET updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.ET" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 05:00:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Improving Simulation-Based Origin-Destination Demand Calibration Using Sample Segment Counts Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19528v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel approach to demand estimation that utilizes partial observations of segment-level track counts. Building on established simulation-based demand estimation methods, we present a modified formulation that integrates sample track counts as a regularization term. This approach effectively addresses the underdetermination challenge in demand estimation, moving beyond the conventional reliance on a prior OD matrix. The proposed formulation aims to preserve the distribution of the observed track counts while optimizing the demand to align with observed path-level travel times. We tested this approach on Seattle's highway network with various congestion levels. Our findings reveal significant enhancements in the solution quality, particularly in accurately recovering ground truth demand patterns at both the OD and segment levels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19528v1</guid>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arwa Alanqary, Chao Zhang, Yechen Li, Neha Arora, Carolina Osorio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum circuits for discrete-time quantum walks with position-dependent coin operator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.05271v3 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The aim of this paper is to build quantum circuits that implement discrete-time quantum walks having an arbitrary position-dependent coin operator. The position of the walker is encoded in base 2: with $n$ wires, each corresponding to one qubit, we encode $2^n$ position states. The data necessary to define an arbitrary position-dependent coin operator is therefore exponential in $n$.
  We first propose a circuit implementing the position-dependent coin operator, that is naive, in the sense that it has exponential depth and implements sequentially all appropriate position-dependent coin operators. We then propose a circuit that "transfers" all the depth into ancillae, yielding a final depth that is linear in $n$ at the cost of an exponential number of ancillae. The main idea of this linear-depth circuit is to implement in parallel all coin operators at the different positions.
  Finally, we extend the result of Ref. [2] from position-dependent unitaries which are diagonal in the position basis to position-dependent $2 \times 2$-block-diagonal unitaries: indeed, we show that for a position dependence of the coin operator (the block-diagonal unitary) which is smooth enough, one can find an efficient quantum-circuit implementation approximating the coin operator up to an error $\epsilon$ (in terms of the spectral norm), the depth and size of which scale as $O(1/\epsilon)$.
  A typical application of the efficient implementation would be the quantum simulation of a relativistic spin-1/2 particle on a lattice, coupled to a smooth external gauge field; notice that recently, quantum spatial-search schemes have been developed which use gauge fields as the oracle, to mark the vertex to be found [3, 4]. A typical application of the linear-depth circuit would be when there is spatial noise on the coin operator (and hence a non-smooth dependence in the position).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.05271v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ugo Nzongani, Julien Zylberman, Carlo-Elia Doncecchi, Armando P\'erez, Fabrice Debbasch, Pablo Arnault</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adjustable-depth quantum circuit for position-dependent coin operators of discrete-time quantum walks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.10460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.10460v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Discrete-time quantum walks with position-dependent coin operators have numerous applications. For a position dependence that is sufficiently smooth, it has been provided in Ref. [1] an approximate quantum-circuit implementation of the coin operator that is efficient. If we want the quantum-circuit implementation to be exact (e.g., either, in the case of a smooth position dependence, to have a perfect precision, or in order to treat a non-smooth position dependence), but the depth of the circuit not to scale exponentially, then we can use the linear-depth circuit of Ref. [1], which achieves a depth that is linear at the cost of introducing an exponential number of ancillas. In this paper, we provide an adjustable-depth quantum circuit for the exact implementation of the position-dependent coin operator. This adjustable-depth circuit consists in (i) applying in parallel, with a linear-depth circuit, only certain packs of coin operators (rather than all of them as in the original linear-depth circuit [1]), each pack contributing linearly to the depth, and in (ii) applying sequentially these packs, which contributes exponentially to the depth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.10460v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ugo Nzongani, Pablo Arnault</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comprehensive Digital Forensics and Risk Mitigation Strategy for Modern Enterprises</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19621v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Enterprises today face increasing cybersecurity threats that necessitate robust digital forensics and risk mitigation strategies. This paper explores these challenges through an imaginary case study of an organization, a global identity management and data analytics company handling vast customer data. Given the critical nature of its data assets, EP has established a dedicated digital forensics team to detect threats, manage vulnerabilities, and respond to security incidents. This study outlines an approach to cybersecurity, including proactive threat anticipation, forensic investigations, and compliance with regulations like GDPR and CCPA. Key threats such as social engineering, insider risks, phishing, and ransomware are examined, along with mitigation strategies leveraging AI and machine learning. By detailing security framework, this paper highlights best practices in digital forensics, incident response, and enterprise risk management. The findings emphasize the importance of continuous monitoring, policy enforcement, and adaptive security measures to protect sensitive data and ensure business continuity in an evolving threat landscape</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19621v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.21275/SR201211165829</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Journal of Science and Research (IJSR),2020</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shamnad Mohamed Shaffi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reachability in Restricted Chemical Reaction Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.12603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.12603v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The popularity of molecular computation has given rise to several models of abstraction, one of the more recent ones being Chemical Reaction Networks (CRNs). These are equivalent to other popular computational models, such as Vector Addition Systems and Petri-Nets, and restricted versions are equivalent to Population Protocols. This paper continues the work on core \emph{reachability} questions related to Chemical Reaction Networks; given two configurations, can one reach the other according to the system's rules? With no restrictions, reachability was recently shown to be Ackermann-complete, which resolved a decades-old problem.
  In this work, we fully characterize monotone reachability problems based on various restrictions such as the allowed rule size, the number of rules that may create a species ($k$-source), the number of rules that may consume a species ($k$-consuming), the volume, and whether the rules have an acyclic production order (\emph{feed-forward}). We show PSPACE-completeness of reachability with only bimolecular reactions in two-source and two-consuming rules. This proves hardness of reachability in a restricted form of Population Protocols. This is accomplished using new techniques within the motion planning framework.
  We give several important results for feed-forward CRNs, where rules are single-source or single-consuming. We show that reachability is solvable in polynomial time as long as the system does not contain special \emph{void} or \emph{autogenesis} rules. We then fully characterize all systems of this type and show that with void/autogenesis rules, or more than one source and one consuming, the problems become NP-complete. Finally, we show several interesting special cases of CRNs based on these restrictions or slight relaxations and note future significant open questions related to this taxonomy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.12603v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>q-bio.MN</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert M. Alaniz, Bin Fu, Timothy Gomez, Elise Grizzell, Andrew Rodriguez, Marco Rodriguez, Robert Schweller, Tim Wylie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Simulation of Boson-Related Hamiltonians: Techniques, Effective Hamiltonian Construction, and Error Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.06580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.06580v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A broad spectrum of physical systems in condensed-matter and high-energy physics, vibrational spectroscopy, and circuit and cavity QED necessitates the incorporation of bosonic degrees of freedom, such as phonons, photons, and gluons, into optimized fermion algorithms for near-future quantum simulations. In particular, when a quantum system is surrounded by an external environment, its basic physics can usually be simplified to a spin or fermionic system interacting with bosonic modes. Nevertheless, troublesome factors such as the magnitude of the bosonic degrees of freedom typically complicate the direct quantum simulation of these interacting models, necessitating the consideration of a comprehensive plan. This strategy should specifically include a suitable fermion/boson-to-qubit mapping scheme to encode sufficiently large yet manageable bosonic modes, and a method for truncating and/or downfolding the Hamiltonian to the defined subspace for performing an approximate but highly accurate simulation, guided by rigorous error analysis. In this pedagogical tutorial review, we aim to provide such an exhaustive strategy, focusing on encoding and simulating certain bosonic-related model Hamiltonians, inclusive of their static properties and time evolutions. Specifically, we emphasize two aspects: (1) the discussion of recently developed quantum algorithms for these interacting models and the construction of effective Hamiltonians, and (2) a detailed analysis regarding a tightened error bound for truncating the bosonic modes for a class of fermion-boson interacting Hamiltonians.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.06580v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bo Peng, Yuan Su, Daniel Claudino, Karol Kowalski, Guang Hao Low, Martin Roetteler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Decentraland Economy: Multifaceted Parcel Attributes, Key Insights, and Benchmarking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07533</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07533v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a comprehensive Decentraland parcels dataset, called IITP-VDLand, sourced from diverse platforms such as Decentraland, OpenSea, Etherscan, Google BigQuery, and various Social Media Platforms. Unlike existing datasets which have limited attributes and records, IITP-VDLand offers a rich array of attributes, encompassing parcel characteristics, trading history, past activities, transactions, and social media interactions. Alongside, we introduce a key attribute in the dataset, namely Rarity score, which measures the uniqueness of each parcel within the virtual world. Addressing the significant challenge posed by the dispersed nature of this data across various sources, we employ a systematic approach, utilizing both available APIs and custom scripts, to gather it. Subsequently, we meticulously curate and organize the information into four distinct fragments: (1) Characteristics, (2) OpenSea Trading History, (3) Ethereum Activity Transactions, and (4) Social Media. We envisage that this dataset would serve as a robust resource for training machine- and deep-learning models specifically designed to address real-world challenges within the domain of Decentraland parcels. The performance benchmarking of more than 20 state-of-the-art price prediction models on our dataset yields promising results, achieving a maximum R2 score of 0.8251 and an accuracy of 74.23% in case of Extra Trees Regressor and Classifier. The key findings reveal that the ensemble models perform better than both deep learning and linear models for our dataset. We observe a significant impact of coordinates, geographical proximity, rarity score, and few other economic indicators on the prediction of parcel prices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07533v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dipika Jha, Ankit K. Bhagat, Raju Halder, Rajendra N. Paramanik, Chandra M. Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural CRNs: A Natural Implementation of Learning in Chemical Reaction Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.00034</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.00034v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present Neural CRNs, an efficient, autonomous, and general-purpose implementation of learning within mass action chemical reaction systems. Unlike prior works, which transliterate discrete neural networks into chemical systems, Neural CRNs are a purely analog chemical system, which encodes neural computations in the concentration dynamics of its chemical species. Consequently, the chemical reactions in this system stay true to their nature, behaving as atomic end-to-end computational units, resulting in concise and efficient reaction network implementations. We demonstrate this efficiency by assembling a highly streamlined supervised learning procedure that requires only two clock phases. We further validate the robustness of our framework by constructing Neural CRN circuits for several linear and nonlinear regression and classification tasks. Furthermore, a minimal linear regression circuit is assembled using only 13 reactions and 15 species. Our nonlinear modeling circuits significantly advance the state-of-the-art through compact and simple implementations. The synergistic nature of our framework with the analog chemical computing hardware leaves ample room for optimizations and approximations in the computational model, several of which are discussed in this work. Our work introduces a novel paradigm for chemical computing and learning, providing a foundational platform for future adaptive biochemical circuits with applications in fields such as synthetic biology, bioengineering, and adaptive biomedicine.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.00034v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rajiv Teja Nagipogu, John H. Reif</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial-RAG: Spatial Retrieval Augmented Generation for Real-World Spatial Reasoning Questions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18470</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18470v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Spatial reasoning remains a challenge for Large Language Models (LLMs), which struggle with spatial data retrieval and reasoning. We propose Spatial Retrieval-Augmented Generation (Spatial-RAG), a framework that extends RAG to spatial tasks by integrating sparse spatial retrieval (spatial databases) and dense semantic retrieval (LLM-based similarity). A multi-objective ranking strategy balances spatial constraints and semantic relevance, while an LLM-guided generator ensures coherent responses. Experiments on a real-world tourism dataset show that Spatial-RAG significantly improves spatial question answering, bridging the gap between LLMs and spatial intelligence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18470v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dazhou Yu, Riyang Bao, Gengchen Mai, Liang Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
