<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.ET updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.ET</link>
    <description>cs.ET updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.ET" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 04:00:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Efficient Key-Value Cache Management for Prefix Prefilling in LLM Inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21919v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The increasing adoption of large language models (LLMs) with extended context windows necessitates efficient Key-Value Cache (KVC) management to optimize inference performance. Inference workloads like Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) and agents exhibit high cache reusability, making efficient caching critical to reducing redundancy and improving speed. We analyze real-world KVC access patterns using publicly available traces and evaluate commercial key-value stores like Redis and state-of-the-art RDMA-based systems (CHIME [1] and Sherman [2]) for KVC metadata management. Our work demonstrates the lack of tailored storage solution for KVC prefilling, underscores the need for an efficient distributed caching system with optimized metadata management for LLM workloads, and provides insights into designing improved KVC management systems for scalable, low-latency inference.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21919v1</guid>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yue Zhu, Hao Yu, Chen Wang, Zhuoran Liu, Eun Kyung Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online Voting using Point to MultiPoint Quantum Key Distribution via Passive Optical Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21756v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose using Point-to-Multipoint quantum key distribution (QKD) via time division multiplexing (TDM) and wavelength division multiplexing (WDM) in passive optical networks (PON) to improve the security of online voting systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21756v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bernardo A. Huberman, Jing Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large-Area Fabrication-aware Computational Diffractive Optics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22313v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Differentiable optics, as an emerging paradigm that jointly optimizes optics and (optional) image processing algorithms, has made innovative optical designs possible across a broad range of applications. Many of these systems utilize diffractive optical components (DOEs) for holography, PSF engineering, or wavefront shaping. Existing approaches have, however, mostly remained limited to laboratory prototypes, owing to a large quality gap between simulation and manufactured devices. We aim at lifting the fundamental technical barriers to the practical use of learned diffractive optical systems. To this end, we propose a fabrication-aware design pipeline for diffractive optics fabricated by direct-write grayscale lithography followed by nano-imprinting replication, which is directly suited for inexpensive mass production of large area designs. We propose a super-resolved neural lithography model that can accurately predict the 3D geometry generated by the fabrication process. This model can be seamlessly integrated into existing differentiable optics frameworks, enabling fabrication-aware, end-to-end optimization of computational optical systems. To tackle the computational challenges, we also devise tensor-parallel compute framework centered on distributing large-scale FFT computation across many GPUs. As such, we demonstrate large scale diffractive optics designs up to 32.16 mm $\times$ 21.44 mm, simulated on grids of up to 128,640 by 85,760 feature points. We find adequate agreement between simulation and fabricated prototypes for applications such as holography and PSF engineering. We also achieve high image quality from an imaging system comprised only of a single DOE, with images processed only by a Wiener filter utilizing the simulation PSF. We believe our findings lift the fabrication limitations for real-world applications of diffractive optics and differentiable optical design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22313v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaixuan Wei, Hector A. Jimenez-Romero, Hadi Amata, Jipeng Sun, Qiang Fu, Felix Heide, Wolfgang Heidrich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Kernel Learning for Small Dataset Modeling in Semiconductor Fabrication: Application to Ohmic Contact</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10803v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Modeling complex semiconductor fabrication processes such as Ohmic contact formation remains challenging due to high-dimensional parameter spaces and limited experimental data. While classical machine learning (CML) approaches have been successful in many domains, their performance degrades in small-sample, nonlinear scenarios. In this work, we investigate quantum machine learning (QML) as an alternative, exploiting quantum kernels to capture intricate correlations from compact datasets. Using only 159 experimental GaN HEMT samples, we develop a quantum kernel-aligned regressor (QKAR) combining a shallow Pauli-Z feature map with a trainable quantum kernel alignment (QKA) layer. All models, including seven baseline CML regressors, are evaluated under a unified PCA-based preprocessing pipeline to ensure a fair comparison. QKAR consistently outperforms classical baselines across multiple metrics (MAE, MSE, RMSE), achieving a mean absolute error of 0.338 Omega mm when validated on experimental data. We further assess noise robustness and generalization through cross-validation and new device fabrication. These findings suggest that carefully constructed QML models could provide predictive advantages in data-constrained semiconductor modeling, offering a foundation for practical deployment on near-term quantum hardware. While challenges remain for both QML and CML, this study demonstrates QML's potential as a complementary approach in complex process modeling tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10803v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zeheng Wang, Fangzhou Wang, Liang Li, Zirui Wang, Timothy van der Laan, Ross C. C. Leon, Jing-Kai Huang, Muhammad Usman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pilot-Quantum: A Quantum-HPC Middleware for Resource, Workload and Task Management</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18519v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: As quantum hardware advances, integrating quantum processing units (QPUs) into HPC environments and managing diverse infrastructure and software stacks becomes increasingly essential. Pilot-Quantum addresses these challenges as a middleware designed to provide unified application-level management of resources and workloads across hybrid quantum-classical environments. It is built on a rigorous analysis of existing quantum middleware systems and application execution patterns. It implements the Pilot Abstraction conceptual model, originally developed for HPC, to manage resources, workloads, and tasks. It is designed for quantum applications that rely on task parallelism, including (i) hybrid algorithms, such as variational approaches, and (ii) circuit cutting systems, used to partition and execute large quantum circuits. Pilot-Quantum facilitates seamless integration of QPUs, classical CPUs, and GPUs, while supporting high-level programming frameworks like Qiskit and Pennylane. This enables users to efficiently design and execute hybrid workflows across diverse computing resources. The capabilities of Pilot-Quantum are demonstrated through mini-apps -- simplified yet representative kernels focusing on critical performance bottlenecks. We demonstrate the capabilities of Pilot-Quantum through multiple mini-apps, including different circuit executions (e.g., using IBM\'s Eagle QPU and simulators), circuit cutting, and quantum machine learning scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18519v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pradeep Mantha, Florian J. Kiwit, Nishant Saurabh, Shantenu Jha, Andre Luckow</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
