<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.ET updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.ET</link>
    <description>cs.ET updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.ET" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 02:36:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Bionic Vision as Neuroadaptive XR: Closed-Loop Perceptual Interfaces for Neurotechnology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05963v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Visual neuroprostheses are commonly framed as technologies to restore natural sight to people who are blind. In practice, they create a novel mode of perception shaped by sparse, distorted, and unstable input. They resemble early extended reality (XR) headsets more than natural vision, streaming video from a head-mounted camera to a neural "display" with under 1000 pixels, limited field of view, low refresh rates, and nonlinear spatial mappings. No amount of resolution alone will make this experience natural. This paper proposes a reframing: bionic vision as neuroadaptive XR. Rather than replicating natural sight, the goal is to co-adapt brain and device through a bidirectional interface that responds to neural constraints, behavioral goals, and cognitive state. By comparing traditional XR, current implants, and proposed neuroadaptive systems, it introduces a new design space for inclusive, brain-aware computing. It concludes with research provocations spanning encoding, evaluation, learning, and ethics, and invites the XR community to help shape the future of sensory augmentation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05963v1</guid>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Beyeler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Between Tool and Trouble: Student Attitudes Toward AI in Programming Education</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05999</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05999v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study examines how AI code assistants shape novice programmers experiences during a two-part exam in an introductory programming course. In the first part, students completed a programming task with access to AI support; in the second, they extended their solutions without AI. We collected Likert-scale and open-ended responses from 20 students to evaluate their perceptions and challenges. Findings suggest that AI tools were perceived as helpful for understanding code and increasing confidence, particularly during initial development. However, students reported difficulties transferring knowledge to unaided tasks, revealing possible overreliance and gaps in conceptual understanding. These insights highlight the need for pedagogical strategies that integrate AI meaningfully while reinforcing foundational programming skills.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05999v1</guid>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergio Rojas-Galeano, Julian Tejada, Fernando Marmolejo-Ramos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Utilizing Composer Packages to Accelerate Laravel-Based Project Development Among Students: A Pedagogical and Practical Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05747v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Laravel has emerged as a foundational framework in university web development curricula. However, despite its scaffolding capabilities, students often struggle to complete projects within limited academic timelines. This conceptual paper introduces Composer, PHP's standard dependency manager, and categorizes a curated selection of Composer packages that significantly reduce development effort while fostering professional software practices. Grounded in practical and pedagogical considerations, the paper illustrates how educators and learners can strategically leverage these tools to build typical academic or personal Laravel-based systems. Central to this approach is maintaining code quality and reinforcing conceptual understanding. The paper also addresses potential risks such as package conflicts and over-reliance on tools, providing best-practice recommendations to mitigate them. While the goal is to accelerate development, the deeper objective is to reinforce professional workflows and industry readiness. Exposure to Composer packages enhances curriculum relevance and smooths the transition from academia to the workplace. However, effective integration requires deliberate instructional design aligned with learning objectives. Without guidance, students may treat packages as black boxes. Thus, educators must teach not only how to use these tools, but also when and why, encouraging critical evaluation of their utility and limitations. This ensures that practical convenience supports rather than supplants deep learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05747v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rohaizah Abdul Wahid, Muhamad Said Nizamuddin Nadim, Suliana Sulaiman, Syahmi Akmal Shaharudin, Muhammad Danial Jupikil, Iqqwan Jasman Su Azlan Su</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy Experience Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05869v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The material footprint of information and communications technology (ICT) systems is both significant and growing, inspiring a variety of conversations around sustainability and climate justice. In part this effort has been catalysed by past scholarship and analysis from the LIMITS community. This paper examines energy storage systems for computing, particularly batteries -- which are discarded at the rate of 15 billion a year worldwide. The International Energy Agency (IEA) is now referring to the energy transition toward low carbon systems as a critical mineral problem, and countries are speaking openly of 'mineral security' in policy documents. In this paper I 1) present a definition for energy experience and what this means for the design and making of devices, interactions and experiences. I also 2) explore a series of electronics device prototypes converted to run from batteryless sustainable energy that are extremely long lasting, and make limited use of critical minerals. As transitional energy experience device-design experiments, what do prototypes like these suggest for more mainstream, mass-manufactured systems?</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05869v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brian Sutherland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Markov Decision Process Framework for Early Maneuver Decisions in Satellite Collision Avoidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05876v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work presents a Markov decision process (MDP) framework to model decision-making for collision avoidance maneuver (CAM) and a reinforcement learning policy gradient (RL-PG) algorithm to train an autonomous guidance policy using historic CAM data. In addition to maintaining acceptable collision risks, this approach seeks to minimize the average fuel consumption of CAMs by making early maneuver decisions. We model CAM as a continuous state, discrete action and finite horizon MDP, where the critical decision is determining when to initiate the maneuver. The MDP model also incorporates analytical models for conjunction risk, propellant consumption, and transit orbit geometry. The Markov policy effectively trades-off maneuver delay-which improves the reliability of conjunction risk indicators-with propellant consumption-which increases with decreasing maneuver time. Using historical data of tracked conjunction events, we verify this framework and conduct an extensive ablation study on the hyper-parameters used within the MDP. On synthetic conjunction events, the trained policy significantly minimizes both the overall and average propellant consumption per CAM when compared to a conventional cut-off policy that initiates maneuvers 24 hours before the time of closest approach (TCA). On historical conjunction events, the trained policy consumes more propellant overall but reduces the average propellant consumption per CAM. For both historical and synthetic conjunction events, the trained policy achieves equal if not higher overall collision risk guarantees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05876v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesca Ferrara, Lander W. Schillinger Arana, Florian D\"orfler, Sarah H. Q. Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MPS-JuliQAOA: User-friendly, Scalable MPS-based Simulation for Quantum Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05883v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the MPS-JuliQAOA simulator, a user-friendly, open-source tool to simulate the Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) of any optimization problem that can be expressed as diagonal Hamiltonian. By leveraging Julia-language constructs and the ITensor package to implement a Matrix Product State (MPS) approach to simulating QAOA, MPS-Juli-QAOA effortlessly scales to 512 qubits and 20 simulation rounds on the standard de-facto benchmark 3-regular MaxCut QAOA problem. MPS-JuliQAOA also has built-in parameter finding capabilities, which is a crucial performance aspect of QAOA. We illustrate through examples that the user does not need to know MPS principles or complex automatic differentiation techniques to use MPS-JuliQAOA. We study the scalability of our tool with respect to runtime, memory usage and accuracy tradeoffs. Code available at https://github.com/lanl/JuliQAOA.jl/tree/mps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05883v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sean Feeney, Reuben Tate, John Golden, Stephan Eidenbenz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Fair Game: Auditing &amp; Debiasing AI Algorithms Over Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.06443v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: An emerging field of AI, namely Fair Machine Learning (ML), aims to quantify different types of bias (also known as unfairness) exhibited in the predictions of ML algorithms, and to design new algorithms to mitigate them. Often, the definitions of bias used in the literature are observational, i.e. they use the input and output of a pre-trained algorithm to quantify a bias under concern. In reality,these definitions are often conflicting in nature and can only be deployed if either the ground truth is known or only in retrospect after deploying the algorithm. Thus,there is a gap between what we want Fair ML to achieve and what it does in a dynamic social environment. Hence, we propose an alternative dynamic mechanism,"Fair Game",to assure fairness in the predictions of an ML algorithm and to adapt its predictions as the society interacts with the algorithm over time. "Fair Game" puts together an Auditor and a Debiasing algorithm in a loop around an ML algorithm. The "Fair Game" puts these two components in a loop by leveraging Reinforcement Learning (RL). RL algorithms interact with an environment to take decisions, which yields new observations (also known as data/feedback) from the environment and in turn, adapts future decisions. RL is already used in algorithms with pre-fixed long-term fairness goals. "Fair Game" provides a unique framework where the fairness goals can be adapted over time by only modifying the auditor and the different biases it quantifies. Thus,"Fair Game" aims to simulate the evolution of ethical and legal frameworks in the society by creating an auditor which sends feedback to a debiasing algorithm deployed around an ML system. This allows us to develop a flexible and adaptive-over-time framework to build Fair ML systems pre- and post-deployment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.06443v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/cfl.2025.8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Cambridge Forum on AI: Law and Governance , Volume 1 , 2025 , p. e27</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Debabrota Basu, Udvas Das</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Reconfigurable Time-Domain In-Memory Computing Macro using FeFET-Based CAM with Multilevel Delay Calibration in 28 nm CMOS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03925</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03925v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Time-domain nonvolatile in-memory computing (TD-nvIMC) offers a promising pathway to reduce data movement and improve energy efficiency by encoding computation in delay rather than voltage or current. This work presents a fully integrated and reconfigurable TD-nvIMC macro, fabricated in 28 nm CMOS, that combines a ferroelectric FET (FeFET)-based content-addressable memory array, a cascaded delay element chain, and a time-to-digital converter. The architecture supports binary multiply-and-accumulate (MAC) operations using XOR- and AND-based matching, as well as in-memory Boolean logic and arithmetic functions. Sub-nanosecond MAC resolution is achieved through experimentally demonstrated 550 ps delay steps, representing a 2000$\times$ improvement over prior FeFET TD-nvIMC work, enabled by multilevel-state calibration with $\leq$100 ps resolution. Write-disturb resilience is ensured via isolated triple-well bulks. The proposed macro achieves a measured throughput of 222.2 MOPS/cell and energy efficiency of 1887 TOPS/W at 0.85 V, establishing a viable path toward scalable, energy-efficient TD-nvIMC accelerators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03925v2</guid>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeries Mattar, Mor M. Dahan, Stefan Dunkel, Halid Mulaosmanovic, Gunda Beernink, Sven Beyer, Eilam Yalon, Nicol\'as Wainstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MI9 -- Agent Intelligence Protocol: Runtime Governance for Agentic AI Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03858v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Agentic AI systems capable of reasoning, planning, and executing actions present fundamentally distinct governance challenges compared to traditional AI models. Unlike conventional AI, these systems exhibit emergent and unexpected behaviors during runtime, introducing novel agent-related risks that cannot be fully anticipated through pre-deployment governance alone. To address this critical gap, we introduce MI9, the first fully integrated runtime governance framework designed specifically for safety and alignment of agentic AI systems. MI9 introduces real-time controls through six integrated components: agency-risk index, agent-semantic telemetry capture, continuous authorization monitoring, Finite-State-Machine (FSM)-based conformance engines, goal-conditioned drift detection, and graduated containment strategies. Operating transparently across heterogeneous agent architectures, MI9 enables the systematic, safe, and responsible deployment of agentic systems in production environments where conventional governance approaches fall short, providing the foundational infrastructure for safe agentic AI deployment at scale. Detailed analysis through a diverse set of scenarios demonstrates MI9's systematic coverage of governance challenges that existing approaches fail to address, establishing the technical foundation for comprehensive agentic AI oversight.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03858v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charles L. Wang, Trisha Singhal, Ameya Kelkar, Jason Tuo</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
