<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SY updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SY</link>
    <description>cs.SY updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SY" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 01:34:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Situational Awareness in Indian Power Grid using Synchrophasor Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15249v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Wide Area Measurement Systems (WAMS) can guide system operators' to increase their situational awareness by expanding observability of their supervise area and adjoining systems. Power system oscillations in the electrical grid are a matter of contention. It may transform the stable operation of the power system into an unstable system when oscillations grow and if no corrective actions are taken to mitigate them. This paper manifests the utilization of the synchrophasor technology for situational awareness by oscillation detection. An algorithm is proposed for the low-frequency oscillation-related analysis based on Prony and Fast Fourier Transform (FFT) methods. It gives better insight during the grid disturbance and other events related to power system operation. The effectiveness of this algorithm is validated by two case studies in the Western Regional Indian power grid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15249v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Makarand Sudhakar Ballal (Dept. of Electrical Engineering, VNIT, Nagpur)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gradient based reachability analysis for goal-oriented guidance. Application to Eros proximity operations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15271v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The recent growing interest in small solar system bodies such as asteroids and comets for scientific inspection, exploitation of resources, and planetary defense reasons is pushing the development of innovative engineering solutions to better investigate these celestial bodies. Current approaches for autonomous proximity operations often relies on tracking a reference trajectory previously designed and optimized on-ground. An innovative concept developed in recent years is proposing a paradigm shift towards autonomous goal-oriented strategies, providing the probe with high-level tasks and enabling replanning capability on-board. A gradient base reachability exploration scheme is introduced in this work to efficiently compute high reward paths with limited computational resource. The methodology is tested in a case study involving proximity operations to asteroid (433) Eros, comparing the proposed approach with other exploration techniques and showing promising results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15271v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Rizza, Francesco Topputo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Mobility Equity and the Promise of Emerging Transportation Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15401v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces a mobility equity metric (MEM) for evaluating fairness and accessibility in multi-modal intelligent transportation systems. The MEM simultaneously accounts for service accessibility and transportation costs across different modes of transportation and social demographics. We provide a data-driven validation of the proposed MEM to characterize the impact of various parameters in the metric across cities in the U.S. We subsequently develop a routing framework that aims to optimize MEM within a transportation network containing both public transit and private vehicles. Within this framework, a system planner provides routing suggestions to vehicles across all modes of transportation to maximize MEM. We evaluate our approach through numerical simulations, analyzing the impact of travel demands and compliance of private vehicles. This work provides insights into designing transportation systems that are not only efficient but also equitable, ensuring fair access to essential services across diverse populations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15401v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heeseung Bang, Aditya Dave, Filippos N. Tzortzoglou, Shanting Wang, Andreas A. Malikopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Plant Models Call for a Different Plant Modelling Paradigm and a New Generation of Software (Heresy in the land of moles, fractions, &amp; rigorous physical properties)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15415v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper is an invitation to the process systems engineering community to change the paradigm for process plants. The goal is to achieve much easier convergence while retaining accuracy on par with the rigorous models. Accurate plant models of existing plants can be linear or much less nonlinear if they are based on mass component flows and stream properties per unit mass properties instead of molar flows and mole fractions. Accurate stream properties per unit mass can be calculated at stream specific conditions by linear approximations which in many instances eliminates mole fraction-based flash calculations. Hybrid data-driven node models fit naturally in this paradigm, since they used measured data, which is either in mass or in volumetric units, but never in moles. Instantiation of models at all levels of abstraction (planning, scheduling, optimization, and control models) from the same plant topology representation will ensure inheritance of solutions from mass-only to mass-and-energy to mass-and-energy-and-stream-properties, thereby ensuring consistency of solutions between these models. None of the existing software provides inheritance between different levels of plant abstraction (i.e. inheritance between models for different business applications) or different levels of abstractions per plant sections or per time periods, which motivates this exposition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15415v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Mahalec</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online Event-Triggered Switching for Frequency Control in Power Grids with Variable Inertia</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15436v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The increasing integration of renewable energy resources into power grids has led to time-varying system inertia and consequent degradation in frequency dynamics. A promising solution to alleviate performance degradation is using power electronics interfaced energy resources, such as renewable generators and battery energy storage for primary frequency control, by adjusting their power output set-points in response to frequency deviations. However, designing a frequency controller under time-varying inertia is challenging. Specifically, the stability or optimality of controllers designed for time-invariant systems can be compromised once applied to a time-varying system. We model the frequency dynamics under time-varying inertia as a nonlinear switching system, where the frequency dynamics under each mode are described by the nonlinear swing equations and different modes represent different inertia levels. We identify a key controller structure, named Neural Proportional-Integral (Neural-PI) controller, that guarantees exponential input-to-state stability for each mode. To further improve performance, we present an online event-triggered switching algorithm to select the most suitable controller from a set of Neural-PI controllers, each optimized for specific inertia levels. Simulations on the IEEE 39-bus system validate the effectiveness of the proposed online switching control method with stability guarantees and optimized performance for frequency control under time-varying inertia.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15436v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jie Feng, Wenqi Cui, Jorge Cort\'es, Yuanyuan Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence Analysis of Overparametrized LQR Formulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15456</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15456v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by the growing use of Artificial Intelligence (AI) tools in control design, this paper takes the first steps towards bridging the gap between results from Direct Gradient methods for the Linear Quadratic Regulator (LQR), and neural networks. More specifically, it looks into the case where one wants to find a Linear Feed-Forward Neural Network (LFFNN) feedback that minimizes a LQR cost. This paper starts by computing the gradient formulas for the parameters of each layer, which are used to derive a key conservation law of the system. This conservation law is then leveraged to prove boundedness and global convergence of solutions to critical points, and invariance of the set of stabilizing networks under the training dynamics. This is followed by an analysis of the case where the LFFNN has a single hidden layer. For this case, the paper proves that the training converges not only to critical points but to the optimal feedback control law for all but a set of measure-zero of the initializations. These theoretical results are followed by an extensive analysis of a simple version of the problem (the ``vector case''), proving the theoretical properties of accelerated convergence and robustness for this simpler example. Finally, the paper presents numerical evidence of faster convergence of the training of general LFFNNs when compared to traditional direct gradient methods, showing that the acceleration of the solution is observable even when the gradient is not explicitly computed but estimated from evaluations of the cost function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15456v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arthur Castello B. de Oliveira, Milad Siami, Eduardo D. Sontag</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compact Multi-Service Antenna for Sensing and Communication Using Reconfigurable Complementary Spiral Resonator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15486v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, a compact multi-service antenna (MSA) is presented for sensing and communication using a reconfigurable complementary spiral resonator. A three turns complementary spiral resonator (3-CSR) is inserted in the ground plane of a modified patch antenna to create a miniaturized structure. Two Positive-Intrinsic-Negative (PIN) diodes (D1, D2) are also integrated with the 3-CSR to achieve frequency reconfiguration. The proposed structure operates in three different modes i.e., dual-band joint communication and sensing antenna (JCASA), dual-band antenna, and single-band antenna. The required mode can be selected by changing the state of the PIN diodes. In mode-1, the first band (0.95-0.97 GHz) of the antenna is dedicated to sensing by using frequency domain reflectometry (FDR), while the second band (1.53-1.56 GHz) is allocated to communication. The sensing ability of the proposed structure is utilized to measure soil moisture using FDR. Based on the frequency shift, permittivity of the soil is observed to measure soil moisture. In mode-2 and mode-3, the structure operates as a standard dual and single band antenna, respectively, with a maximum gain of 1.5 dBi at 1.55 GHz. The proposed planar structure, with its simple geometry and a high sensitivity of 1.7%, is a suitable candidate for precision farming. The proposed structure is versatile and capable of being utilized as a single or dual-band antenna and also measuring permittivity of materials within the range of 1-20. Hence, it is adaptable to a range of applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15486v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Raza, Rasool Keshavarz, Eryk Dutkiewicz, Negin Shariati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinite-Horizon Optimal Wireless Control Over Shared State-Dependent Fading Channels for IIoT Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15492v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Heterogeneous systems consisting of a multiloop wireless control system (WCS) and a mobile agent system (MAS) are ubiquitous in Industrial Internet of Things systems. Within these systems, positions of mobile agents may lead to shadow fading on the wireless channel that the WCS is controlled over and can significantly compromise its performance. This paper focuses on the infinite-horizon optimal control of MAS to ensure the performance of WCS while minimizing an average cost for the heterogeneous system subject to state and input constraints. Firstly, the state-dependent fading channel is modeled, which characterizes the interference among transmission links, and shows that the probability of a successful transmission for WCS depends on the state of MAS. A necessary and sufficient condition in terms of constrained set stabilization is then established to ensure the Lyapunov-like performance of WCS with expected decay rate. Secondly, using the semi-tensor product of matrices and constrained reachable sets, a criterion is presented to check the constrained set stabilization of MAS and to ensure the performance of WCS. In addition, a constrained optimal state transition graph is constructed to address state and input constraints, by resorting to which the feasibility analysis of the optimal control problem is presented. Finally, an algorithm is proposed for the construction of optimal input sequences by minimum-mean cycles for weighted graph. An illustrative example is provided to demonstrate effectiveness of the proposed method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15492v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuling Wang, Peizhe Li, Shanying Zhu, Cailian Chen, Xinping Guan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Existence of Linear Observed Systems on Manifolds with Connection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15497</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15497v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Linear observed systems on manifolds are a special class of nonlinear systems whose state spaces are smooth manifolds but possess properties similar to linear systems. Such properties can be characterized by the ability to conduct preintegration and exact linearization with Jacobians independent of the linearization point. IMU dynamics in navigation can be constructed into linear observed settings, leading to invariant filters with guaranteed behaviors such as local convergence and consistency. In this letter, we establish linear observed property for dynamics evolving on an arbitrary smooth manifold through the connection structure endowed upon this space. Our key findings are the existence of linear observed systems on manifolds poses strong constraints on the state space itself, apart from requiring the dynamics to be in some specific forms. The existence of such systems is equivalent to the flatness of the state space, forcing the manifold to admit a group structure under mild topological assumptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15497v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Changwu Liu, Yuan Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sufficient and Necessary Barrier-like Conditions for Safety and Reach-avoid Verification of Stochastic Discrete-time Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15572v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we examine sufficient and necessary barrier-like conditions for the safety verification and reach-avoid verification of stochastic discrete-time systems. Safety verification aims to certify the satisfaction of the safety property, which stipulates that the probability of the system, starting from a specified initial state, remaining within a safe set is greater than or equal to a specified lower bound. A sufficient and necessary barrier-like condition is formulated for safety verification. In contrast, reach-avoid verification extends beyond safety to include reachability, seeking to certify the satisfaction of the reach-avoid property. It requires that the probability of the system, starting from a specified initial state, reaching a target set eventually while remaining within a safe set until the first hit of the target, is greater than or equal to a specified lower bound. Two sufficient and necessary barrier-like conditions are formulated under certain assumptions. These conditions are derived via relaxing Bellman equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15572v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bai Xue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CBF-LLM: Safe Control for LLM Alignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15625v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper proposes a control-based framework for aligning large language models (LLMs) by leveraging a control barrier function (CBF) to ensure user-desirable text generation. The presented framework applies the safety filter, designed based on the CBF, to the output generation of the baseline LLM, i.e., the sequence of the token, with the aim of intervening in the generated text. The overall text-generation system is implemented with Llama 3 and a RoBERTa model, and the source code is available at https://github.com/Mya-Mya/CBF-LLM. The experiment demonstrates its control ability and effectiveness in reducing the number of interventions needed for user-specified alignment tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15625v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuya Miyaoka, Masaki Inoue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structural Optimization of Lightweight Bipedal Robot via SERL</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15632</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15632v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Designing a bipedal robot is a complex and challenging task, especially when dealing with a multitude of structural parameters. Traditional design methods often rely on human intuition and experience. However, such approaches are time-consuming, labor-intensive, lack theoretical guidance and hard to obtain optimal design results within vast design spaces, thus failing to full exploit the inherent performance potential of robots. In this context, this paper introduces the SERL (Structure Evolution Reinforcement Learning) algorithm, which combines reinforcement learning for locomotion tasks with evolution algorithms. The aim is to identify the optimal parameter combinations within a given multidimensional design space. Through the SERL algorithm, we successfully designed a bipedal robot named Wow Orin, where the optimal leg length are obtained through optimization based on body structure and motor torque. We have experimentally validated the effectiveness of the SERL algorithm, which is capable of optimizing the best structure within specified design space and task conditions. Additionally, to assess the performance gap between our designed robot and the current state-of-the-art robots, we compared Wow Orin with mainstream bipedal robots Cassie and Unitree H1. A series of experimental results demonstrate the Outstanding energy efficiency and performance of Wow Orin, further validating the feasibility of applying the SERL algorithm to practical design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15632v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi Cheng, Chenxi Han, Yuheng Min, Linqi Ye, Houde Liu, Hang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparison of Model Predictive Control and Proximal Policy Optimization for a 1-DOF Helicopter System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15633v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study conducts a comparative analysis of Model Predictive Control (MPC) and Proximal Policy Optimization (PPO), a Deep Reinforcement Learning (DRL) algorithm, applied to a 1-Degree of Freedom (DOF) Quanser Aero 2 system. Classical control techniques such as MPC and Linear Quadratic Regulator (LQR) are widely used due to their theoretical foundation and practical effectiveness. However, with advancements in computational techniques and machine learning, DRL approaches like PPO have gained traction in solving optimal control problems through environment interaction. This paper systematically evaluates the dynamic response characteristics of PPO and MPC, comparing their performance, computational resource consumption, and implementation complexity. Experimental results show that while LQR achieves the best steady-state accuracy, PPO excels in rise-time and adaptability, making it a promising approach for applications requiring rapid response and adaptability. Additionally, we have established a baseline for future RL-related research on this specific testbed. We also discuss the strengths and limitations of each control strategy, providing recommendations for selecting appropriate controllers for real-world scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15633v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georg Sch\"afer, Jakob Rehrl, Stefan Huber, Simon Hirlaender</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A quantitative model of takeover request time budget for conditionally automated driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15682</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15682v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In conditional automation, the automated driving system assumes full control and only issues a takeover request to a human driver to resume driving in critical situations. Previous studies have concluded that the time budget required by drivers to resume driving after a takeover request varies with situations and different takeover variables. However, no comprehensive generalized approaches for estimating in advance the time budget required by drivers to takeover have been provided. In this contribution, fixed (7 s) and variable time budgets (6 s, 5 s, and 4 s) with and without visual imagery assistance were investigated for suitability in three takeover scenarios using performance measures such as average lateral displacement. The results indicate that 7 s is suitable for two of the studied scenarios based on their characteristics. Using the obtained results and known relations between takeover variables, a mathematical formula for estimating takeover request time budget is proposed. The proposed formula integrates individual stimulus response time, driving experience, scenario specific requirements and allows increased safety for takeover maneuvers. Furthermore, the visual imagery resulted in increased takeover time which invariably increases the time budget. Thus the time demand of the visualized information if applicable (such as visual imagery) should be included in the time budget.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15682v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ACCESS.2023.0322000</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Foghor Tanshi, Dirk S\"offker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear-Quadratic Dynamic Games as Receding-Horizon Variational Inequalities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15703v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider dynamic games with linear dynamics and quadratic objective functions. We observe that the unconstrained open-loop Nash equilibrium coincides with the LQR in an augmented space, thus deriving an explicit expression of the cost-to-go. With such cost-to-go as a terminal cost, we show asymptotic stability for the receding-horizon solution of the finite-horizon, constrained game. Furthermore, we show that the problem is equivalent to a non-symmetric variational inequality, which does not correspond to any Nash equilibrium problem. For unconstrained closed-loop Nash equilibria, we derive a receding-horizon controller that is equivalent to the infinite-horizon one and ensures asymptotic stability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15703v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emilio Benenati, Sergio Grammatico</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advanced POD-Based Performance Evaluation of Classifiers Applied to Human Driver Lane Changing Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15722v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Machine learning (ML) classifiers serve as essential tools facilitating classification and prediction across various domains. The performance of these algorithms should be known to ensure their reliable application. In certain fields, receiver operating characteristic and precision-recall curves are frequently employed to assess machine learning algorithms without accounting for the impact of process parameters. However, it may be essential to evaluate the performance of these algorithms in relation to such parameters. As a performance evaluation metric capable of considering the effects of process parameters, this paper uses a modified probability of detection (POD) approach to assess the reliability of ML-based algorithms. As an example, the POD-based approach is employed to assess ML models used for predicting the lane changing behavior of a vehicle driver. The time remaining to the predicted (and therefore unknown) lane changing event is considered as process parameter. The hit/miss approach to POD is taken here and modified by considering the probability of lane changing derived from ML algorithms at each time step, and obtaining the final result of the analysis accordingly. This improves the reliability of results compared to the standard hit/miss approach, which considers the outcome of the classifiers as either 0 or 1, while also simplifying evaluation compared to the \^a versus a approach. Performance evaluation results of the proposed approach are compared with those obtained with the standard hit/miss approach and a pre-developed \^a versus a approach to validate the effectiveness of the proposed method. The comparison shows that this method provides an averaging conservative behavior with the advantage of enhancing the reliability of the hit/miss approach to POD while retaining its simplicity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15722v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ACCESS.2024.0429000</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Zahra Rastin, Dirk S\"offker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Risk-Averse Resilient Operation of Electricity Grid Under the Risk of Wildfire</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15774v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Wildfires and other extreme weather conditions due to climate change are stressing the aging electrical infrastructure. Power utilities have implemented public safety power shutoffs as a method to mitigate the risk of wildfire by proactively de-energizing some power lines, which leaves customers without power. System operators have to make a compromise between de-energizing of power lines to avoid the wildfire risk and energizing those lines to serve the demand. In this work, with a quantified wildfire ignition risk of each line, a resilient operation problem is presented in power systems with a high penetration level of renewable generation resources. A two-stage robust optimization problem is formulated and solved using column-and-constraint generation algorithm to find improved balance between the de-energization of power lines and the customers served. Different penetration levels of renewable generation to mitigate the impact of extreme fire hazard situations on the energization of customers is assessed. The validity of the presented robust optimization algorithm is demonstrated on various test cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15774v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Waseem, Arash F. Soofi, Saeed D. Manshadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Stochastic Robust Adaptive Systems Level Approach to Stabilizing Large-Scale Uncertain Markovian Jump Linear Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15789</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15789v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a unified framework for robustly and adaptively stabilizing large-scale networked uncertain Markovian jump linear systems (MJLS) under external disturbances and mode switches that can change the network's topology. Adaptation is achieved by using minimal information on the disturbance to identify modes that are consistent with observable data. Robust control is achieved by extending the system level synthesis (SLS) approach, which allows us to pose the problem of simultaneously stabilizing multiple plants as a two-step convex optimization procedure. Our control pipeline computes a likelihood distribution of the system's current mode, uses them as probabilistic weights during simultaneous stabilization, then updates the likelihood via Bayesian inference. Because of this "softer" probabilistic approach to robust stabilization, our control pipeline does not suffer from abrupt destabilization issues due to changes in the system's true mode, which were observed in a previous method. Separability of SLS also lets us compute localized robust controllers for each subsystem, allowing for network scalability; we use several information consensus methods so that mode estimation can also be done locally. We apply our algorithms to disturbance-rejection on two sample dynamic power grid networks, a small-scale system with 7 nodes and a large-scale grid of 25 nodes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15789v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>SooJean Han, Minwoo M. Kim, Ieun Choo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Practical Challenges for Reliable RIS Deployment in Heterogeneous Multi-Operator Multi-Band Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15867v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reconfigurable intelligent surfaces (RISs) have been introduced as arrays of nearly passive elements with software-tunable electromagnetic properties to dynamically manipulate the reflection/transmission of radio signals. Research works in this area are focused on two applications, namely {\it user-assist} RIS aiming at tuning the RIS to enhance the quality-of-service (QoS) of target users, and the {\it malicious} RIS aiming for an attacker to degrade the QoS at victim receivers through generating {\it intended} destructive interference. While both user-assist and malicious RIS applications have been explored extensively, the impact of RIS deployments on imposing {\it unintended} interference on various wireless user-equipments (EUs) remains underexplored. This paper investigates the challenges of integrating RISs into multi-carrier, multi-user, and multi-operator networks. We discuss how RIS deployments intended to benefit specific users can negatively impact other users served at various carrier frequencies through different network operators. While not an ideal solution, we discuss how ultra-narrowband metasurfaces can be incorporated into the manufacturing of RISs to mitigate some challenges of RIS deployment in wireless networks. We also present a simulation scenario to illuminate some practical challenges associated with the deployment of RISs in shared public environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15867v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mehdi Monemi, Mehdi Rasti, Arthur S. de Sena, Mohammad Amir Fallah, Matti Latva-Aho, Marco Di Renzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Control Theoretic Approach to Simultaneously Estimate Average Value of Time and Determine Dynamic Price for High-occupancy Toll Lanes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15990v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The dynamic pricing problem of a freeway corridor with high-occupancy toll (HOT) lanes was formulated and solved based on a point queue abstraction of the traffic system [Yin and Lou, 2009]. However, existing pricing strategies cannot guarantee that the closed-loop system converges to the optimal state, in which the HOT lanes' capacity is fully utilized but there is no queue on the HOT lanes, and a well-behaved estimation and control method is quite challenging and still elusive. This paper attempts to fill the gap by making three fundamental contributions: (i) to present a simpler formulation of the point queue model based on the new concept of residual capacity, (ii) to propose a simple feedback control theoretic approach to estimate the average value of time and calculate the dynamic price, and (iii) to analytically and numerically prove that the closed-loop system is stable and guaranteed to converge to the optimal state, in either Gaussian or exponential manners.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15990v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TITS.2020.3007160</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Trans. on ITS, 22(11):7293-7305, 2021</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xuting Wang, Wen-Long Jin, Yafeng Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pedestrian Motion Prediction Using Transformer-based Behavior Clustering and Data-Driven Reachability Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15250</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15250v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we present a transformer-based framework for predicting future pedestrian states based on clustered historical trajectory data. In previous studies, researchers propose enhancing pedestrian trajectory predictions by using manually crafted labels to categorize pedestrian behaviors and intentions. However, these approaches often only capture a limited range of pedestrian behaviors and introduce human bias into the predictions. To alleviate the dependency on manually crafted labels, we utilize a transformer encoder coupled with hierarchical density-based clustering to automatically identify diverse behavior patterns, and use these clusters in data-driven reachability analysis. By using a transformer-based approach, we seek to enhance the representation of pedestrian trajectories and uncover characteristics or features that are subsequently used to group trajectories into different "behavior" clusters. We show that these behavior clusters can be used with data-driven reachability analysis, yielding an end-to-end data-driven approach to predicting the future motion of pedestrians. We train and evaluate our approach on a real pedestrian dataset, showcasing its effectiveness in forecasting pedestrian movements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15250v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kleio Fragkedaki, Frank J. Jiang, Karl H. Johansson, Jonas M{\aa}rtensson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This is the Way: Mitigating the Roll of an Autonomous Uncrewed Surface Vessel in Wavy Conditions Using Model Predictive Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15349v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Though larger vessels may be well-equipped to deal with wavy conditions, smaller vessels are often more susceptible to disturbances. This paper explores the development of a nonlinear model predictive control (NMPC) system for Uncrewed Surface Vessels (USVs) in wavy conditions to minimize average roll. The NMPC is based on a prediction method that uses information about the vessel's dynamics and an assumed wave model. This method is able to mitigate the roll of an under-actuated USV in a variety of conditions by adjusting the weights of the cost function. The results show a reduction of 39% of average roll with a tuned controller in conditions with 1.75-metre sinusoidal waves. A general and intuitive tuning strategy is established. This preliminary work is a proof of concept which sets the stage for the leveraging of wave prediction methodologies to perform planning and control in real time for USVs in real-world scenarios and field trials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15349v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel L. Jenkins, Joshua A. Marshall</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimization Solution Functions as Deterministic Policies for Offline Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15368v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Offline reinforcement learning (RL) is a promising approach for many control applications but faces challenges such as limited data coverage and value function overestimation. In this paper, we propose an implicit actor-critic (iAC) framework that employs optimization solution functions as a deterministic policy (actor) and a monotone function over the optimal value of optimization as a critic. By encoding optimality in the actor policy, we show that the learned policies are robust to the suboptimality of the learned actor parameters via the exponentially decaying sensitivity (EDS) property. We obtain performance guarantees for the proposed iAC framework and show its benefits over general function approximation schemes. Finally, we validate the proposed framework on two real-world applications and show a significant improvement over state-of-the-art (SOTA) offline RL methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15368v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>American Control Conference 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Vanshaj Khattar, Ming Jin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Optimized Parallel Robots for Human-Robot Collaboration by Combined Structural and Dimensional Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15831v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Parallel robots (PR) offer potential for human-robot collaboration (HRC) due to their lower moving masses and higher speeds. However, the parallel leg chains increase the risks of collision and clamping. In this work, these hazards are described by kinematics and kinetostatics models to minimize them as objective functions by a combined structural and dimensional synthesis in a particle-swarm optimization. In addition to the risk of clamping within and between kinematic chains, the back-drivability is quantified to theoretically guarantee detectability via motor current. Another HRC-relevant objective function is the largest eigenvalue of the mass matrix formulated in the operational-space coordinates to consider collision effects. Multi-objective optimization leads to different Pareto-optimal PR structures. The results show that the optimization leads to significant improvement of the HRC criteria and that a Hexa structure (6-RUS) is to be favored concerning the objective functions and due to its simpler joint structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15831v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aran Mohammad, Thomas Seel, Moritz Schappler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of Primal-Dual Gradient Flow Dynamics for Multi-Block Convex Optimization Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15969v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We examine stability properties of primal-dual gradient flow dynamics for composite convex optimization problems with multiple, possibly nonsmooth, terms in the objective function under the generalized consensus constraint. The proposed dynamics are based on the proximal augmented Lagrangian and they provide a viable alternative to ADMM which faces significant challenges from both analysis and implementation viewpoints in large-scale multi-block scenarios. In contrast to customized algorithms with individualized convergence guarantees, we provide a systematic approach for solving a broad class of challenging composite optimization problems. We leverage various structural properties to establish global (exponential) convergence guarantees for the proposed dynamics. Our assumptions are much weaker than those required to prove (exponential) stability of various primal-dual dynamics as well as (linear) convergence of discrete-time methods, e.g., standard two-block and multi-block ADMM and EXTRA algorithms. Finally, we show necessity of some of our structural assumptions for exponential stability and provide computational experiments to demonstrate the convenience of the proposed dynamics for parallel and distributed computing applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15969v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ibrahim K. Ozaslan, Panagiotis Patrinos, Mihailo R. Jovanovi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Ancillary Services: From Grid Codes to Transfer Function-Based Converter Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.01552</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.01552v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Conventional grid-code specifications for dynamic ancillary services provision such as fast frequency and voltage regulation are typically defined by means of piece-wise linear step-response capability curves in the time domain. However, although the specification of such time-domain curves is straightforward, their practical implementation in a converter-based generation system is not immediate, and no customary methods have been developed yet. In this paper, we thus propose a systematic approach for the practical implementation of piece-wise linear time-domain curves to provide dynamic ancillary services by converter-based generation systems, while ensuring grid-code and device-level requirements to be reliably satisfied. Namely, we translate the piece-wise linear time-domain curves for active and reactive power provision in response to a frequency and voltage step change into a desired rational parametric transfer function in the frequency domain, which defines a dynamic response behavior to be realized by the converter. The obtained transfer function can be easily implemented e.g. via a PI-based matching control in the power loop of standard converter control architectures. We demonstrate the performance of our method in numerical grid-code compliance tests, and reveal its superiority over classical droop and virtual inertia schemes which may not satisfy the grid codes due to their structural limitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.01552v5</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Verena H\"aberle, Linbin Huang, Xiuqiang He, Eduardo Prieto-Araujo, Florian D\"orfler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>6G Fresnel Spot Beamfocusing using Large-Scale Metasurfaces: A Distributed DRL-Based Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.11109</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.11109v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce the concept of spot beamfocusing (SBF) in the Fresnel zone through extremely large-scale programmable metasurfaces (ELPMs) as a key enabling technology for 6G networks. A smart SBF scheme aims to adaptively concentrate the aperture's radiating power exactly at a desired focal point (DFP) in the 3D space utilizing some Machine Learning (ML) method. This offers numerous advantages for next-generation networks including efficient wireless power transfer (WPT), interference mitigation, reduced RF pollution, and improved information security. SBF necessitates ELPMs with precise channel state information (CSI) for all ELPM elements. However, obtaining exact CSI for ELPMs is not feasible in all environments; we alleviate this by proposing an adaptive novel CSI-independent ML scheme based on the TD3 deep-reinforcement-learning (DRL) method. While the proposed ML-based scheme is well-suited for relatively small-size arrays, the computational complexity is unaffordable for ELPMs. To overcome this limitation, we introduce a modular highly scalable structure composed of multiple sub-arrays, each equipped with a TD3-DRL optimizer. This setup enables collaborative optimization of the radiated power at the DFP, significantly reducing computational complexity while enhancing learning speed. The proposed structures benefits in terms of 3D spot-like power distribution, convergence rate, and scalability are validated through simulation results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.11109v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mehdi Monemi, Mohammad Amir Fallah, Mehdi Rasti, Matti Latva-Aho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Dynamic Ancillary Services Provision Based on Local Power Grid Perception</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.17793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.17793v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a systematic closed-loop approach to provide optimal dynamic ancillary services with converter-interfaced generation systems based on local power grid perception. In particular, we structurally encode dynamic ancillary services such as fast frequency and voltage regulation in the form of a parametric transfer function matrix, which includes several parameters to define a set of different feasible response behaviors, among which we aim to find the optimal one to be realized by the converter system. Our approach is based on a so-called "perceive-and-optimize" (P&amp;O) strategy: First, we identify a grid dynamic equivalent at the interconnection terminals of the converter system. Second, we consider the closed-loop interconnection of the identified grid equivalent and the parametric transfer function matrix, which we optimize for the set of transfer function parameters, resulting in a stable and optimal closed-loop performance for ancillary services provision. In the process, we ensure that grid-code and device-level requirements are satisfied. Finally, we demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach in different numerical case studies based on a modified Kundur two-area test system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.17793v4</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Verena H\"aberle, Xiuqiang He, Linbin Huang, Eduardo Prieto-Araujo, Florian D\"orfler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Learning based Policy Optimization for Temporal Logic Tasks by Controller Network Dropout</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15826v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces a model-based approach for training feedback controllers for an autonomous agent operating in a highly nonlinear (albeit deterministic) environment. We desire the trained policy to ensure that the agent satisfies specific task objectives and safety constraints, both expressed in Discrete-Time Signal Temporal Logic (DT-STL). One advantage for reformulation of a task via formal frameworks, like DT-STL, is that it permits quantitative satisfaction semantics. In other words, given a trajectory and a DT-STL formula, we can compute the {\em robustness}, which can be interpreted as an approximate signed distance between the trajectory and the set of trajectories satisfying the formula. We utilize feedback control, and we assume a feed forward neural network for learning the feedback controller. We show how this learning problem is similar to training recurrent neural networks (RNNs), where the number of recurrent units is proportional to the temporal horizon of the agent's task objectives. This poses a challenge: RNNs are susceptible to vanishing and exploding gradients, and na\"{i}ve gradient descent-based strategies to solve long-horizon task objectives thus suffer from the same problems. To tackle this challenge, we introduce a novel gradient approximation algorithm based on the idea of dropout or gradient sampling. One of the main contributions is the notion of {\em controller network dropout}, where we approximate the NN controller in several time-steps in the task horizon by the control input obtained using the controller in a previous training step. We show that our control synthesis methodology, can be quite helpful for stochastic gradient descent to converge with less numerical issues, enabling scalable backpropagation over long time horizons and trajectories over high dimensional state spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15826v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Navid Hashemi, Bardh Hoxha, Danil Prokhorov, Georgios Fainekos, Jyotirmoy Deshmukh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Backstepping Control of a Quadrotor Unmanned Aerial Vehicle Under Colored Noises</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.05022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.05022v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Advances in software and hardware technologies have facilitated the production of quadrotor unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs). Quadrotor UAVs are used in important missions such as search and rescue, counter terrorism, firefighting, surveillance and cargo transportation. While performing these tasks, quadrotors must operate in noisy environments. Therefore, a robust controller design that can control the altitude and attitude of the quadrotor in noisy environments is of great importance. While many researchers focus only on white Gaussian noise in their studies, all colored noises should be considered during quadrotor's operation. In this study, it is aimed to design a robust controller that is resistant to all colored noises. Firstly, a nonlinear model of the quadrotor was created with MATLAB. Then, a backstepping control design that is resistant to colored noises was realized. The designed backstepping controller was tested under Gaussian white noise, pink noise, brown noise, blue noise and purple noise. PID and Lyapunov-based controller designs were also carried out and their time responses (rise time, overshoot, settling time) were compared with those of backstepping controller. When the values obtained was examined, it was proven that the proposed backstepping controller had the least overshoot and shortest settling time under all noise types.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.05022v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mehmet Karahan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wireless Channel Aware Data Augmentation Methods for Deep Learning-Based Indoor Localization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.06452v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Indoor localization is a challenging problem that - unlike outdoor localization - lacks a universal and robust solution. Machine Learning (ML), particularly Deep Learning (DL), methods have been investigated as a promising approach. Although such methods bring remarkable localization accuracy, they heavily depend on the training data collected from the environment. The data collection is usually a laborious and time-consuming task, but Data Augmentation (DA) can be used to alleviate this issue. In this paper, different from previously used DA, we propose methods that utilize the domain knowledge about wireless propagation channels and devices. The methods exploit the typical hardware component drift in the transceivers and/or the statistical behavior of the channel, in combination with the measured Power Delay Profile (PDP). We comprehensively evaluate the proposed methods to demonstrate their effectiveness. This investigation mainly focuses on the impact of factors such as the number of measurements, augmentation proportion, and the environment of interest impact the effectiveness of the different DA methods. We show that in the low-data regime (few actual measurements available), localization accuracy increases up to 50%, matching non-augmented results in the high-data regime. In addition, the proposed methods may outperform the measurement-only high-data performance by up to 33% using only 1/4 of the amount of measured data. We also exhibit the effect of different training data distribution and quality on the effectiveness of DA. Finally, we demonstrate the power of the proposed methods when employed along with Transfer Learning (TL) to address the data scarcity in target and/or source environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.06452v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Omer Gokalp Serbetci, Daoud Burghal, Andreas F. Molisch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active Search for Low-altitude UAV Sensing and Communication for Users at Unknown Locations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14067</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14067v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper studies optimal unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV) placement to ensure line-of-sight (LOS) communication and sensing for a cluster of ground users possibly in deep shadow, while the UAV maintains backhaul connectivity with a base station (BS). The key challenges include unknown user locations, uncertain channel model parameters, and unavailable urban structure. Addressing these challenges, this paper focuses on developing an efficient online search strategy which jointly estimates channels, guides UAV positioning, and optimizes resource allocation. Analytically exploiting the geometric properties of the equipotential surface, this paper develops an LOS discovery trajectory on the equipotential surface while the closed-form search directions are determined using perturbation theory. Since the explicit expression of the equipotential surface is not available, this paper proposes to locally construct a channel model for each user in the LOS regime utilizing polynomial regression without depending on user locations or propagation distance. A class of spiral trajectories to simultaneously construct the LOS channels and search on the equipotential surface is developed. An optimal radius of the spiral and an optimal measurement pattern for channel gain estimation are derived to minimize the mean squared error (MSE) of the locally constructed channel. Numerical results on real 3D city maps demonstrate that the proposed scheme achieves over 94% of the performance of a 3D exhaustive search scheme with just a 3-kilometer search.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14067v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuanshuai Zheng, Junting Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Domain-decoupled Physics-informed Neural Networks with Closed-form Gradients for Fast Model Learning of Dynamical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14951v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Physics-informed neural networks (PINNs) are trained using physical equations and can also incorporate unmodeled effects by learning from data. PINNs for control (PINCs) of dynamical systems are gaining interest due to their prediction speed compared to classical numerical integration methods for nonlinear state-space models, making them suitable for real-time control applications. We introduce the domain-decoupled physics-informed neural network (DD-PINN) to address current limitations of PINC in handling large and complex nonlinear dynamical systems. The time domain is decoupled from the feed-forward neural network to construct an Ansatz function, allowing for calculation of gradients in closed form. This approach significantly reduces training times, especially for large dynamical systems, compared to PINC, which relies on graph-based automatic differentiation. Additionally, the DD-PINN inherently fulfills the initial condition and supports higher-order excitation inputs, simplifying the training process and enabling improved prediction accuracy. Validation on three systems - a nonlinear mass-spring-damper, a five-mass-chain, and a two-link robot - demonstrates that the DD-PINN achieves significantly shorter training times. In cases where the PINC's prediction diverges, the DD-PINN's prediction remains stable and accurate due to higher physics loss reduction or use of a higher-order excitation input. The DD-PINN allows for fast and accurate learning of large dynamical systems previously out of reach for the PINC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14951v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henrik Krauss, Tim-Lukas Habich, Max Bartholdt, Thomas Seel, Moritz Schappler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Component reusability evaluation and requirement tracing for agent-based cyber-physical-simulated systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.09565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.09565v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Evaluating early design concepts is crucial as it impacts quality and cost. This process is often hindered by vague and uncertain design information. This article introduces the SysML-based Simulated-Physical Systems Modeling Language (SPSysML). It is a Domain-Specification Language used to evaluate component reusability in cyber-physical systems, incorporating digital twins and other simulated parts. The proposed factors assess the design quantitatively. SPSysML uses a requirement-based system structuring method to couple simulated and physical parts with requirements. SPSysML enables DTs to perceive exogenous actions in the simulated world.
  SPSysML validation is survey- and application-based. First, a robotic system for an assisted living project was developed. The integrity of simulated and physical parts of the system is improved using SPSysML-based quantitative evaluation. Thus, more system components are shared between the simulated and physical setups. The system was deployed on the physical robot and two simulators based on the Robot Operating System (ROS) or ROS2. SPSysML was used by a third-party developer and was assessed by him and other practitioners in a survey.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.09565v5</guid>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wojciech Dudek, Narcis Miguel, Tomasz Winiarski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Receding-Constraint Model Predictive Control using a Learned Approximate Control-Invariant Set</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.11124</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.11124v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In recent years, advanced model-based and data-driven control methods are unlocking the potential of complex robotics systems, and we can expect this trend to continue at an exponential rate in the near future. However, ensuring safety with these advanced control methods remains a challenge. A well-known tool to make controllers (either Model Predictive Controllers or Reinforcement Learning policies) safe, is the so-called control-invariant set (a.k.a. safe set). Unfortunately, for nonlinear systems, such a set cannot be exactly computed in general. Numerical algorithms exist for computing approximate control-invariant sets, but classic theoretic control methods break down if the set is not exact. This paper presents our recent efforts to address this issue. We present a novel Model Predictive Control scheme that can guarantee recursive feasibility and/or safety under weaker assumptions than classic methods. In particular, recursive feasibility is guaranteed by making the safe-set constraint move backward over the horizon, and assuming that such set satisfies a condition that is weaker than control invariance. Safety is instead guaranteed under an even weaker assumption on the safe set, triggering a safe task-abortion strategy whenever a risk of constraint violation is detected. We evaluated our approach on a simulated robot manipulator, empirically demonstrating that it leads to less constraint violations than state-of-the-art approaches, while retaining reasonable performance in terms of tracking cost, number of completed tasks, and computation time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.11124v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ICRA57147.2024.10611467</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>"Receding-Constraint Model Predictive Control using a Learned Approximate Control-Invariant Set," 2024 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA), Yokohama, Japan, 2024, pp. 11626-11632</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gianni Lunardi, Asia La Rocca, Matteo Saveriano, Andrea Del Prete</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic-Robust Planning of Networked Hydrogen-Electrical Microgrids: A Study on Induced Refueling Demand</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00568v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Hydrogen-electrical microgrids are increasingly assuming an important role on the pathway toward decarbonization of energy and transportation systems. This paper studies networked hydrogen-electrical microgrids planning (NHEMP), considering a critical but often-overlooked issue, i.e., the demand-inducing effect (DIE) associated with infrastructure development decisions. Specifically, higher refueling capacities will attract more refueling demand of hydrogen-powered vehicles (HVs). To capture such interactions between investment decisions and induced refueling demand, we introduce a decision-dependent uncertainty (DDU) set and build a trilevel stochastic-robust formulation. The upper-level determines optimal investment strategies for hydrogen-electrical microgrids, the lower-level optimizes the risk-aware operation schedules across a series of stochastic scenarios, and, for each scenario, the middle-level identifies the "worst" situation of refueling demand within an individual DDU set to ensure economic feasibility. Then, an adaptive and exact decomposition algorithm, based on Parametric Column-and-Constraint Generation (PC&amp;CG), is customized and developed to address the computational challenge and to quantitatively analyze the impact of DIE. Case studies on an IEEE exemplary system validate the effectiveness of the proposed NHEMP model and the PC&amp;CG algorithm. It is worth highlighting that DIE can make an important contribution to the economic benefits of NHEMP, yet its significance will gradually decrease when the main bottleneck transits to other system restrictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00568v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xunhang Sun, Xiaoyu Cao, Bo Zeng, Qiaozhu Zhai, Tamer Ba\c{s}ar, Xiaohong Guan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimax problems for ensembles of control-affine systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05782</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05782v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider ensembles of control-affine systems in $\mathbb{R}^d$, and we study simultaneous optimal control problems related to the worst-case minimization. After proving that such problems admit solutions, denoting with $(\Theta^N)_N$ a sequence of compact sets that parametrize the ensembles of systems, we first show that the corresponding minimax optimal control problems are $\Gamma$-convergent whenever $(\Theta^N)_N$ has a limit with respect to the Hausdorff distance. Besides its independent interest, the previous result plays a crucial role for establishing the Pontryagin Maximum Principle (PMP) when the ensemble is parametrized by a set $\Theta$ consisting of infinitely many points. Namely, we first approximate $\Theta$ by finite and increasing-in-size sets $(\Theta^N)_N$ for which the PMP is known, and then we derive the PMP for the $\Gamma$-limiting problem. The same strategy can be pursued in applications, where we can reduce infinite ensembles to finite ones to compute the minimizers numerically. We bring as a numerical example the Schr\"odinger equation for a qubit with uncertain resonance frequency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05782v4</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Scagliotti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Submodular Maximization Approaches for Equitable Client Selection in Federated Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13683v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In a conventional Federated Learning framework, client selection for training typically involves the random sampling of a subset of clients in each iteration. However, this random selection often leads to disparate performance among clients, raising concerns regarding fairness, particularly in applications where equitable outcomes are crucial, such as in medical or financial machine learning tasks. This disparity typically becomes more pronounced with the advent of performance-centric client sampling techniques. This paper introduces two novel methods, namely SUBTRUNC and UNIONFL, designed to address the limitations of random client selection. Both approaches utilize submodular function maximization to achieve more balanced models. By modifying the facility location problem, they aim to mitigate the fairness concerns associated with random selection. SUBTRUNC leverages client loss information to diversify solutions, while UNIONFL relies on historical client selection data to ensure a more equitable performance of the final model. Moreover, these algorithms are accompanied by robust theoretical guarantees regarding convergence under reasonable assumptions. The efficacy of these methods is demonstrated through extensive evaluations across heterogeneous scenarios, revealing significant improvements in fairness as measured by a client dissimilarity metric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13683v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'es Catalino Castillo Jim\'enez, Ege C. Kaya, Lintao Ye, Abolfazl Hashemi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
