<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SY updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SY</link>
    <description>cs.SY updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SY" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2024 04:00:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dual Covariance Steering with Active Parameter Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15590v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work examines the optimal covariance steering problem for systems subject to unknown parameters that enter multiplicatively with the state and control, in addition to additive disturbances. In contrast to existing works, the unknown parameters are modeled as random variables and are estimated online. This work proposes the utilization of recursive least squares estimation for efficient parameter identification. A dual control problem is formulated in which the effect of the planned control policy on the parameter estimates is modeled and optimized for. The parameter estimates are then used to modify the pre-computed control policy online in an adaptive control fashion. Finally, the proposed approach is demonstrated in a vehicle control example with closed-loop parameter identification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15590v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacob W. Knaup, Panagiotis Tsiotras</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transactive Local Energy Markets Enable Community-Level Resource Coordination Using Individual Rewards</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15617v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: ALEX (Autonomous Local Energy eXchange) is an economy-driven, transactive local energy market where each participating building is represented by a rational agent. Relying solely on building-level information, this agent minimizes its electricity bill by automating distributed energy resource utilization and trading. This study examines ALEX's capabilities to align participant and grid-stakeholder interests and assesses ALEX's impact on short- and long-term intermittence using a set of community net-load metrics, such as ramping rate, load factor, and peak load. The policies for ALEX's rational agents are generated using dynamic programming through value iteration in conjunction with iterative best response. This facilitates comparing ALEX and a benchmark energy management system, which optimizes building-level self-consumption, ramping rate, and peak net load. Simulations are performed using the open-source CityLearn2022 dataset to provide a pathway for benchmarking by future studies. The experiments demonstrate that ALEX enables the coordination of distributed energy resources across the community. Remarkably, this community-level coordination occurs even though the system is populated by agents who only access building-level information and selfishly maximize their own relative profit. Compared to the benchmark energy management system, ALEX improves across all metrics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15617v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel C. May, Petr Musilek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncertainty Propagation in Stochastic Systems via Mixture Models with Error Quantification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15626v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Uncertainty propagation in non-linear dynamical systems has become a key problem in various fields including control theory and machine learning. In this work we focus on discrete-time non-linear stochastic dynamical systems. We present a novel approach to approximate the distribution of the system over a given finite time horizon with a mixture of distributions. The key novelty of our approach is that it not only provides tractable approximations for the distribution of a non-linear stochastic system, but also comes with formal guarantees of correctness. In particular, we consider the total variation (TV) distance to quantify the distance between two distributions and derive an upper bound on the TV between the distribution of the original system and the approximating mixture distribution derived with our framework. We show that in various cases of interest, including in the case of Gaussian noise, the resulting bound can be efficiently computed in closed form. This allows us to quantify the correctness of the approximation and to optimize the parameters of the resulting mixture distribution to minimize such distance. The effectiveness of our approach is illustrated on several benchmarks from the control community.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15626v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eduardo Figueiredo, Andrea Patane, Morteza Lahijanian, Luca Laurenti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-Time Reconfiguration and Connectivity Maintenance for AUVs Network Under External Disturbances using Distributed Nonlinear Model Predictive Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15671v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Advancements in underwater vehicle technology have significantly expanded the potential scope for deploying autonomous or remotely operated underwater vehicles in novel practical applications. However, the efficiency and maneuverability of these vehicles remain critical challenges, particularly in the dynamic aquatic environment. In this work, we propose a novel control scheme for creating multi-agent distributed formation control with limited communication between individual agents. In addition, the formation of the multi-agent can be reconfigured in real-time and the network connectivity can be maintained. The proposed use case for this scheme includes creating underwater mobile communication networks that can adapt to environmental or network conditions to maintain the quality of communication links for long-range exploration, seabed monitoring, or underwater infrastructure inspection. This work introduces a novel Distributed Nonlinear Model Predictive Control (DNMPC) strategy, integrating Control Lyapunov Functions (CLF) and Control Barrier Functions (CBF) with a relaxed decay rate, specifically tailored for 6-DOF underwater robotics. The effectiveness of our proposed DNMPC scheme was demonstrated through rigorous MATLAB simulations for trajectory tracking and formation reconfiguration in a dynamic environment. Our findings, supported by tests conducted using Software In The Loop (SITL) simulation, confirm the approach's applicability in real-time scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15671v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nhat Minh Nguyen, Stephen McIlvanna, Jack Close, Mien Van</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Safe and Stable Formation Control with Distributed Multi-Agents Using Adaptive Control and Control Barrier Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15674v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This manuscript considers the problem of ensuring stability and safety during formation control with distributed multi-agent systems in the presence of parametric uncertainty in the dynamics and limited communication. We propose an integrative approach that combines Control Barrier Functions, Adaptive Control, and connected graphs. A reference model is designed so as to ensure a safe and stable formation control strategy. This is combined with a provably correct adaptive control design that includes a use of a CBF-based safety filter that suitably generates safe reference commands, and employs error-based relaxation (EBR) of Nagumo's Invariance Theorem. Together, it is shown to lead to a guarantee of boundedness, formation control, and forward invariance. Numerical examples are provided to support the theoretical derivations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15674v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose A. Solano-Castellanos, Anuradha Annaswamy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Motion Planning for Identification of Linear Classifiers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15687</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15687v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A given region in 2-D Euclidean space is divided by a unknown linear classifier in to two sets each carrying a label. The objective of an agent with known dynamics traversing the region is to identify the true classifier while paying a control cost across its trajectory. We consider two scenarios: (i) the agent is able to measure the true label perfectly; (ii) the observed label is the true label multiplied by noise. We present the following: (i) the classifier identification problem formulated as a control problem; (ii) geometric interpretation of the control problem resulting in one step modified control problems; (iii) control algorithms that result in data sets which are used to identify the true classifier with accuracy; (iv) convergence of estimated classifier to the true classifier when the observed label is not corrupted by noise; (iv) numerical example demonstrating the utility of the control algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15687v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aneesh Raghavan, Karl Henrik Johansson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Passivity-based Attack Identification and Mitigation with Event-triggered Observer Feedback and Switching Controller</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15697v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper addresses the problem of output consensus in linear passive multi-agent systems under a False Data Injection (FDI) attack, considering the unavailability of complete state information. Our formulation relies on an event-based cryptographic authentication scheme for sensor integrity and considers FDI attacks at the actuator end, inspired by their practical nature and usages. For secure consensus, we propose (i) a passivity-based approach for detecting FDI attacks on the system and (ii) a Zeno-free event-triggered observer-based switching controller, which switches between the normal and the defense modes following an attack detection. We show that the closed-loop system achieves practical consensus under the controller's action in the defense mode. Simulation examples are provided to support the theoretical findings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15697v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pushkal Purohit, Anoop Jain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved Soft-k-Means Clustering Algorithm for Balancing Energy Consumption in Wireless Sensor Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15700v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Energy load balancing is an essential issue in designing wireless sensor networks (WSNs). Clustering techniques are utilized as energy-efficient methods to balance the network energy and prolong its lifetime. In this paper, we propose an improved soft-k-means (IS-k-means) clustering algorithm to balance the energy consumption of nodes in WSNs. First, we use the idea of ``clustering by fast search and find of density peaks'' (CFSFDP) and kernel density estimation (KDE) to improve the selection of the initial cluster centers of the soft k-means clustering algorithm. Then, we utilize the flexibility of the soft-k-means and reassign member nodes considering their membership probabilities at the boundary of clusters to balance the number of nodes per cluster. Furthermore, the concept of multi-cluster heads is employed to balance the energy consumption within clusters. {Extensive simulation results under different network scenarios demonstrate that for small-scale WSNs with single-hop transmission}, the proposed algorithm can postpone the first node death, the half of nodes death, and the last node death on average when compared to various clustering algorithms from the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15700v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/JIOT.2020.3031272</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Published in IEEE Internet of Things Journal, 2021</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Botao Zhu, Ebrahim Bedeer, Ha H. Nguyen, Robert Barton, Jerome Henry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causal Tracking of Distributions in Wasserstein Space: A Model Predictive Control Scheme</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15702v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the problem of optimal swarm tracking which can be formulated as a tracking problem for distributions in the Wasserstein metric. Optimal control solutions to this problem are non-causal and require knowing the time-trajectory of the distribution to be tracked in advance. We propose a scheme where these non-causal solutions can be used together with a predictive model for the reference to achieve causal tracking control of a priori-unknown references. We develop the resulting model-predictive control scheme in the simple case where the reference is predicted to be constant-in-time. A computational algorithm based on particle methods and discrete optimal mass transport is presented, and numerical simulations are provided for various classes of reference signals. The results demonstrate that the proposed control algorithm achieves reasonable performance even when using simple predictive models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15702v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max Emerick, Jared Jonas, Bassam Bamieh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Comparative Study of Artificial Potential Fields and Safety Filters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15743v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we have demonstrated that the controllers designed by a classical motion planning tool, namely artificial potential fields (APFs), can be derived from a recently prevalent approach: control barrier function quadratic program (CBF-QP) safety filters. By integrating APF information into the CBF-QP framework, we establish a bridge between these two methodologies. Specifically, this is achieved by employing the attractive potential field as a control Lyapunov function (CLF) to guide the design of the nominal controller, and then the repulsive potential field serves as a reciprocal CBF (RCBF) to define a CBF-QP safety filter. Building on this integration, we extend the design of the CBF-QP safety filter to accommodate a more general class of dynamical models featuring a control-affine structure. This extension yields a special CBF-QP safety filter and a general APF solution suitable for control-affine dynamical models. Through a reach-avoid navigation example, we showcase the efficacy of the developed approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15743v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ming Li, Zhiyong Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Small Noise Analysis of Non-Parametric Closed-Loop Identification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15771v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revisit the problem of non-parametric closed-loop identification in frequency domain; we give a brief survey of the literature and provide a small noise analysis of the direct, indirect, and joint input-output methods when two independent experiments with identical excitation are used. The analysis is asymptotic in the noise variance (i.e., as the standard deviation of the innovations $\sigma \to 0$), for a finite data record of length $N$. We highlight the relationship between the estimators accuracy and the loop shape via asymptotic variance expressions given in terms of the sensitivity function. The results are illustrated using a numerical simulation example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15771v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed Abdalmoaty, Roy S. Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Fairness-Oriented Reinforcement Learning Approach for the Operation and Control of Shared Micromobility Services</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15780</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15780v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As Machine Learning systems become increasingly popular across diverse application domains, including those with direct human implications, the imperative of equity and algorithmic fairness has risen to prominence in the Artificial Intelligence community. On the other hand, in the context of Shared Micromobility Systems, the exploration of fairness-oriented approaches remains limited. Addressing this gap, we introduce a pioneering investigation into the balance between performance optimization and algorithmic fairness in the operation and control of Shared Micromobility Services. Our study leverages the Q-Learning algorithm in Reinforcement Learning, benefiting from its convergence guarantees to ensure the robustness of our proposed approach. Notably, our methodology stands out for its ability to achieve equitable outcomes, as measured by the Gini index, across different station categories--central, peripheral, and remote. Through strategic rebalancing of vehicle distribution, our approach aims to maximize operator performance while simultaneously upholding fairness principles for users. In addition to theoretical insights, we substantiate our findings with a case study or simulation based on synthetic data, validating the efficacy of our approach. This paper underscores the critical importance of fairness considerations in shaping control strategies for Shared Micromobility Services, offering a pragmatic framework for enhancing equity in urban transportation systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15780v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Vittorio Piron, Matteo Cederle, Marina Ceccon, Federico Chiariotti, Alessandro Fabris, Marco Fabris, Gian Antonio Susto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semi-on-Demand Hybrid Transit Route Design with Shared Autonomous Mobility Services</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15804v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study examines the route design of a semi-on-demand hybrid route directional service in the public transit network, offering on-demand flexible route service in low-density areas and fixed route service in higher-density areas with Shared Autonomous Mobility Service (SAMS). The study develops analytically tractable cost expressions that capture access, waiting, and riding costs for users, and distance-based operating and time-based vehicle costs for operators. Two formulations are presented for strategic and tactical decisions in flexible route portion, fleet size, headway, and vehicle size optimization, enabling the determination of route types between fixed, hybrid, and flexible routes based on demand, cost, and operational parameters. The practical applications and benefits of semi-on-demand feeders are demonstrated with numerical examples and a large-scale case study in the Chicago metropolitan area. Findings reveal scenarios in which flexible route portions serving passengers located further away reduce total costs, particularly user costs. Lower operating costs in lower-demand areas favor more flexible routes, whereas higher demand densities favor more traditional line-based operations. On two studied lines, a current cost forecast favors smaller vehicles with flexible routes, but operating constraints and higher operating costs would favor bigger vehicles with hybrid routes. The study provides an analytical tool to design SAMS as directional services and transit feeders, and tractable continuous approximation formulations for future research in transit network design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15804v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max T. M. Ng, Florian Dandl, Hani S. Mahmassani, Klaus Bogenberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Learning based Policy Optimization for Temporal Tasks via Dropout</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15826v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces a model-based approach for training feedback controllers for an autonomous agent operating in a highly nonlinear environment. We desire the trained policy to ensure that the agent satisfies specific task objectives, expressed in discrete-time Signal Temporal Logic (DT-STL). One advantage for reformulation of a task via formal frameworks, like DT-STL, is that it permits quantitative satisfaction semantics. In other words, given a trajectory and a DT-STL formula, we can compute the robustness, which can be interpreted as an approximate signed distance between the trajectory and the set of trajectories satisfying the formula. We utilize feedback controllers, and we assume a feed forward neural network for learning these feedback controllers. We show how this learning problem is similar to training recurrent neural networks (RNNs), where the number of recurrent units is proportional to the temporal horizon of the agent's task objectives. This poses a challenge: RNNs are susceptible to vanishing and exploding gradients, and na\"{i}ve gradient descent-based strategies to solve long-horizon task objectives thus suffer from the same problems. To tackle this challenge, we introduce a novel gradient approximation algorithm based on the idea of dropout or gradient sampling. We show that, the existing smooth semantics for robustness are inefficient regarding gradient computation when the specification becomes complex. To address this challenge, we propose a new smooth semantics for DT-STL that under-approximates the robustness value and scales well for backpropagation over a complex specification. We show that our control synthesis methodology, can be quite helpful for stochastic gradient descent to converge with less numerical issues, enabling scalable backpropagation over long time horizons and trajectories over high dimensional state spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15826v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Navid Hashemi, Bardh Hoxha, Danil Prokhorov, Georgios Fainekos, Jyotirmoy Deshmukh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TJCCT: A Two-timescale Approach for UAV-assisted Mobile Edge Computing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15828</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15828v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV)-assisted mobile edge computing (MEC) is emerging as a promising paradigm to provide aerial-terrestrial computing services in close proximity to mobile devices (MDs). However, meeting the demands of computation-intensive and delay-sensitive tasks for MDs poses several challenges, including the demand-supply contradiction between MDs and MEC servers, the demand-supply heterogeneity between MDs and MEC servers, the trajectory control requirements on energy efficiency and timeliness, and the different time-scale dynamics of the network. To address these issues, we first present a hierarchical architecture by incorporating terrestrial-aerial computing capabilities and leveraging UAV flexibility. Furthermore, we formulate a joint computing resource allocation, computation offloading, and trajectory control problem to maximize the system utility. Since the problem is a non-convex and NP-hard mixed integer nonlinear programming (MINLP), we propose a two-timescale joint computing resource allocation, computation offloading, and trajectory control (TJCCT) approach for solving the problem. In the short timescale, we propose a price-incentive model for on-demand computing resource allocation and a matching mechanism-based method for computation offloading. In the long timescale, we propose a convex optimization-based method for UAV trajectory control. Besides, we theoretically prove the stability, optimality, and polynomial complexity of TJCCT. Extended simulation results demonstrate that the proposed TJCCT outperforms the comparative algorithms in terms of the system utility, average processing rate, average completion delay, and average completion ratio.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15828v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zemin Sun, Geng Sun, Qingqing Wu, Long He, Shuang Liang, Hongyang Pan, Dusit Niyato, Chau Yuen, Victor C. M. Leung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Modular Safety Filter for Safety-Certified Cyber-Physical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15854</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15854v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nowadays, many control systems are networked and embed communication and computation capabilities. Such control architectures are prone to cyber attacks on the cyberinfrastructure. Consequently, there is an impellent need to develop solutions to preserve the plant's safety against potential attacks. To ensure safety, this paper introduces a modular safety filter approach that is effective for a variety of cyber-attack types. This solution can be implemented in combination with existing control and detection algorithms, effectively separating safety from performance. The safety filter does not require information on the reliability of the received command or the feature of the used anomaly detector. It can be implemented in conjunction with high-performance, resilient controllers, to achieve both high performance during normal operation and safety during an attack. As an illustrative example, we have shown the effectiveness of the proposed design considering a multi-agent formation task involving 20 mobile robots. The simulation results testify that the safety filter operates effectively during false data injection and intelligent attacks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15854v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Bajelani, Walter Lucia, Klaske van Heusden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Raw Data to Safety: Reducing Conservatism by Set Expansion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15883v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In response to safety concerns associated with learning-based algorithms, safety filters have been proposed as a modular technique. Generally, these filters heavily rely on the system's model, which is contradictory if they are intended to enhance a data-driven or end-to-end learning solution. This paper extends our previous work, a purely Data-Driven Safety Filter (DDSF) based on Willems' lemma, to an extremely short-sighted and non-conservative solution. Specifically, we propose online and offline sample-based methods to expand the safe set of DDSF and reduce its conservatism. Since this method is defined in an input-output framework, it can systematically handle both unknown and time-delay LTI systems using only one single batch of data. To evaluate its performance, we apply the proposed method to a time-delay system under various settings. The simulation results validate the effectiveness of the set expansion algorithm in generating a notably large input-output safe set, resulting in safety filters that are not conservative, even with an extremely short prediction horizon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15883v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Bajelani, Klaske van Heusden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convection-Enabled Boundary Control of a 2D Channel Flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15958v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the incompressible Navier-Stokes equations in a two-dimensional channel. The tangential and normal velocities are assumed to be periodic in the streamwise (horizontal) direction. Moreover, we consider no-slip boundary conditions on the tangential velocity at the top and bottom walls of the channel, and normal velocity actuation at the top and bottom walls. For an arbitrarily large Reynolds number, we design the boundary control inputs to achieve global exponential stabilization, in the L2 sense, of a chosen parabolic Poiseuille profile. Moreover, we design the control inputs such that they have zero mean, but non-zero cubic mean. The zero-mean property is to ensure that the conservation of mass constraint is verified. The non-zero cubic mean property is the key to exploiting the stabilizing effect of nonlinear convection and achieving global stabilization independently of the size of the Reynolds number. This paper is not only the first work where a closed-form feedback law is proposed for global stabilization of parabolic Poiseuille profiles for arbitrary Reynolds number but is also the first generalization of the Cardano-Lyapunov formula, designed initially to stabilize scalar-valued convective PDEs, to a vector-valued convective PDE with a divergence-free constraint on the state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15958v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed Camil Belhadjoudja, Miroslav Krstic, Emmanuel Witrant</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fisher Information Approach for Masking the Sensing Plan: Applications in Multifunction Radars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15966</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15966v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: How to design a Markov Decision Process (MDP) based radar controller that makes small sacrifices in performance to mask its sensing plan from an adversary? The radar controller purposefully minimizes the Fisher information of its emissions so that an adversary cannot identify the controller's model parameters accurately. Unlike classical open loop statistical inference, where the Fisher information serves as a lower bound for the achievable covariance, this paper employs the Fisher information as a design constraint for a closed loop radar controller to mask its sensing plan. We analytically derive a closed-form expression for the determinant of the Fisher Information Matrix (FIM) pertaining to the parameters of the MDP-based controller. Subsequently, we constrain the MDP with respect to the determinant of the FIM. Numerical results show that the introduction of minor perturbations to the MDP's transition kernel and the total operation cost can reduce the Fisher Information of the emissions. Consequently, this reduction amplifies the variability in policy and transition kernel estimation errors, thwarting the adversary's accuracy in estimating the controller's sensing plan.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15966v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shashwat Jain, Vikram Krishnamurthy, Muralidhar Rangaswamy, Bosung Kang, Sandeep Gogineni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Force Controlled Printing for Material Extrusion Additive Manufacturing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16042</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16042v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In material extrusion additive manufacturing, the extrusion process is commonly controlled in a feed-forward fashion. The amount of material to be extruded at each printing location is pre-computed by a planning software. This approach is inherently unable to adapt the extrusion to external and unexpected disturbances, and the quality of the results strongly depends on a number of modeling and tuning parameters. To overcome these limitations, we propose the first framework for Force Controlled Printing for material extrusion additive manufacturing. We utilize a custom-built extruder to measure the extrusion force in real time, and use this quantity as feedback to continuously control the material flow in closed-loop. We demonstrate the existence of a strong correlation between extrusion force and line width, which we exploit to deposit lines of desired width in a width range of 33 % up to 233 % of the nozzle diameter. We also show how Force Controlled Printing outperforms conventional feed-forward extrusion in print quality and disturbance rejection, while requiring little tuning and automatically adapting to changes in the hardware settings. With no adaptation, Force Controlled Printing can deposit lines of desired width under severe disturbances in bed leveling, such as at layer heights ranging between 20 % and 200 % of the nominal height.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16042v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xavier Guidetti, Nathan Mingard, Raul Cruz-Oliver, Yannick Nagel, Marvin Rueppel, Alisa Rupenyan, Efe C. Balta, John Lygeros</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital control of negative imaginary systems: a discrete-time hybrid integrator-gain system approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16046</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16046v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A hybrid integrator-gain system (HIGS) is a control element that switches between an integrator and a gain, which overcomes some inherent limitations of linear controllers. In this paper, we consider using discrete-time HIGS controllers for the digital control of negative imaginary (NI) systems. We show that the discrete-time HIGS themselves are step-advanced negative imaginary systems. For a minimal linear NI system, there always exists a HIGS controller that can asymptotically stablize it. An illustrative example is provided, where we use the proposed HIGS control method to stabilize a discrete-time mass-spring system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16046v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kanghong Shi, Ian R. Petersen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a MATLAB Toolbox to compute backstepping kernels using the power series method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16070v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we extend our previous work on the power series method for computing backstepping kernels. Our first contribution is the development of initial steps towards a MATLAB toolbox dedicated to backstepping kernel computation. This toolbox would exploit MATLAB's linear algebra and sparse matrix manipulation features for enhanced efficiency; our initial findings show considerable improvements in computational speed with respect to the use of symbolical software without loss of precision at high orders. Additionally, we tackle limitations observed in our earlier work, such as slow convergence (due to oscillatory behaviors) and non-converging series (due to loss of analiticity at some singular points). To overcome these challenges, we introduce a technique that mitigates this behaviour by computing the expansion at different points, denoted as localized power series. This approach effectively navigates around singularities, and can also accelerates convergence by using more local approximations. Basic examples are provided to demonstrate these enhancements. Although this research is still ongoing, the significant potential and simplicity of the method already establish the power series approach as a viable and versatile solution for solving backstepping kernel equations, benefiting both novel and experienced practitioners in the field. We anticipate that these developments will be particularly beneficial in training the recently introduced neural operators that approximate backstepping kernels and gains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16070v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Lin, Rafael Vazquez, Miroslav Krstic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Runtime Monitoring and Fault Detection for Neural Network-Controlled Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16132v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: There is an emerging trend in applying deep learning methods to control complex nonlinear systems. This paper considers enhancing the runtime safety of nonlinear systems controlled by neural networks in the presence of disturbance and measurement noise. A robustly stable interval observer is designed to generate sound and precise lower and upper bounds for the neural network, nonlinear function, and system state. The obtained interval is utilised to monitor the real-time system safety and detect faults in the system outputs or actuators. An adaptive cruise control vehicular system is simulated to demonstrate effectiveness of the proposed design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16132v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianglin Lan, Siyuan Zhan, Ron Patton, Xianxian Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-Driven Sliding Mode Control for Partially Unknown Nonlinear Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16136v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces a new design method for data-driven control of nonlinear systems with partially unknown dynamics and unknown bounded disturbance. Since it is not possible to achieve exact nonlinearity cancellation in the presence of unknown disturbance, this paper adapts the idea of sliding mode control (SMC) to ensure system stability and robustness without assuming that the nonlinearity goes to zero faster than the state as in the existing methods. The SMC consists of a data-dependent robust controller ensuring the system state trajectory reach and remain on the sliding surface and a nominal controller solved from a data-dependent semidefinite program (SDP) ensuring robust stability of the state trajectory on the sliding surface. Numerical simulation results demonstrate effectiveness of the proposed data-driven SMC and its superior in terms of robust stability over the existing data-driven control that also uses approximate nonlinearity cancellation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16136v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianglin Lan, Xianxian Zhao, Congcong Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Voltage Regulation in Polymer Electrolyte Fuel Cell Systems Using Gaussian Process Model Predictive Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16170v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study introduces a novel approach utilizing Gaussian process model predictive control (MPC) to stabilize the output voltage of a polymer electrolyte fuel cell (PEFC) system by simultaneously regulating hydrogen and airflow rates. Two Gaussian process models are developed to capture PEFC dynamics, taking into account constraints including hydrogen pressure and input change rates, thereby aiding in mitigating errors inherent to PEFC predictive control. The dynamic performance of the physical model and Gaussian process MPC in constraint handling and system inputs is compared and analyzed. Simulation outcomes demonstrate that the proposed Gaussian process MPC effectively maintains the voltage at the target 48 V while adhering to safety constraints, even amidst workload disturbances ranging from 110-120 A. In comparison to traditional MPC using detailed system models, Gaussian process MPC exhibits a 43\% higher overshoot and 25\% slower response time. Nonetheless, it offers the advantage of not requiring the underlying true system model and needing less system information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16170v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiufei Li, Miao Zhang, Yuanxin Qi, Miao Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Reachable Sets on Lie Groups Using Lie Algebra Monotonicity and Tangent Intervals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16214v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we efficiently compute overapproximated reachable sets for control systems evolving on Lie groups, building off results from monotone systems theory and geometric integration theory. We propose to consider intervals living in the Lie algebra, which through the exponential map, describe real sets on the Lie group. A local equivalence between the original system and a system evolving on the Lie algebra allows existing interval reachability techniques to apply in the tangent space. Using interval bounds of the Baker-Campbell-Hausdorff formula, a Runge-Kutta-Munthe-Kaas reachability algorithm is proposed, providing reachable set estimates for arbitrary time horizons at little computational cost. The algorithm is demonstrated on through consensus on a torus and attitude control on $SO(3)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16214v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akash Harapanahalli, Samuel Coogan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bi-Level Control of Weaving Sections in Mixed Traffic Environments with Connected and Automated Vehicles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16225v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Connected and automated vehicles (CAVs) can be beneficial for improving the operation of highway bottlenecks such as weaving sections. This paper proposes a bi-level control approach based on an upper-level deep reinforcement learning controller and a lower-level model predictive controller to coordinate the lane-changings of a mixed fleet of CAVs and human-driven vehicles (HVs) in weaving sections. The upper level represents a roadside controller that collects vehicular information from the entire weaving section and determines the control weights used in the lower-level controller. The lower level is implemented within each CAV, which takes the control weights from the upper-level controller and generates the acceleration and steering angle for individual CAVs based on the local situation. The lower-level controller further incorporates an HV trajectory predictor, which is capable of handling the dynamic topology of vehicles in weaving scenarios with intensive mandatory lane changes. The case study inspired by a real weaving section in Basel, Switzerland, shows that our method consistently outperforms state-of-the-art benchmarks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16225v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Longhao Yan, Jinhao Liang, Kaidi Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semi-Automatic Line-System Provisioning with Integrated Physical-Parameter-Aware Methodology: Field Verification and Operational Feasibility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16281</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16281v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose methods and an architecture to conduct measurements and optimize newly installed optical fiber line systems semi-automatically using integrated physics-aware technologies in a data center interconnection (DCI) transmission scenario. We demonstrate, for the first time, digital longitudinal monitoring (DLM) and optical line system (OLS) physical parameter calibration working together in real-time to extract physical link parameters for transmission performance optimization. Our methodology has the following advantages over traditional design: a minimized footprint at user sites, accurate estimation of the necessary optical network characteristics via complementary telemetry technologies, and the capability to conduct all operation work remotely. The last feature is crucial, as it enables remote operation to implement network design settings for immediate response to quality of transmission (QoT) degradation and reversion in the case of unforeseen problems. We successfully performed semi-automatic line system provisioning over field fiber networks facilities at Duke University, Durham, NC. The tasks of parameter retrieval, equipment setting optimization, and system setup/provisioning were completed within 1 hour. The field operation was supervised by on-duty personnel who could access the system remotely from different time zones. By comparing Q-factor estimates calculated from the extracted link parameters with measured results from 400G transceivers, we confirmed that our methodology has a reduction in the QoT prediction errors (+-0.3 dB) over existing design (+-10.6 dB).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16281v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hideki Nishizawa, Giacomo Borraccini, Takeo Sasai, Yue-Kai Huang, Toru Mano, Kazuya Anazawa, Masatoshi Namiki, Soichiroh Usui, Tatsuya Matsumura, Yoshiaki Sone, Zehao Wang, Seiji Okamoto, Takeru Inoue, Ezra Ip, Andrea D'Amico, Tingjun Chen, Vittorio Curri, Ting Wang, Koji Asahi, Koichi Takasugi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Control-Coherent Koopman Modeling: A Physical Modeling Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16306</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16306v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The modeling of nonlinear dynamics based on Koopman operator theory, which is originally applicable only to autonomous systems with no control, is extended to non-autonomous control system without approximation to input matrix B. Prevailing methods using a least square estimate of the B matrix may result in an erroneous input matrix, misinforming the controller about the structure of the input matrix in a lifted space. Here, a new method for constructing a Koopman model that comprises the exact input matrix B is presented. A set of state variables are introduced so that the control inputs are linearly involved in the dynamics of actuators. With these variables, a lifted linear model with the exact control matrix, called a Control-Coherent Koopman Model, is constructed by superposing control input terms, which are linear in local actuator dynamics, to the Koopman operator of the associated autonomous nonlinear system. The proposed method is applied to multi degree-of-freedom robotic arms and multi-cable manipulation systems. Model Predictive Control is applied to the former. It is demonstrated that the prevailing Dynamic Mode Decomposition with Control (DMDc) using an approximate control matrix B does not provide a satisfactory result, while the Control-Coherent Koopman Model performs well with the correct B matrix.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16306v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Harry Asada, Jose A. Solano-Castellanos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ANN-Based Adaptive NMPC for Uranium Extraction-Scrubbing Operation in Spent Nuclear Fuel Treatment Process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16307v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper addresses the particularities in optimal control of the uranium extraction-scrubbing operation in the PUREX process. The control problem requires optimally stabilizing the system at a desired solvent saturation level, guaranteeing constraints, disturbance rejection, and adapting to set point variations. A qualified simulator named PAREX was developed by the French Alternative Energies and Atomic Energy Commission (CEA) to simulate liquid-liquid extraction operations in the PUREX process. However, since the mathematical model is complex and is described by a system of nonlinear, stiff, high-dimensional differential-algebraic equations (DAE), applying optimal control methods will lead to a large-scale nonlinear programming problem with a huge computational burden. The solution we propose in this work is to train a neural network to predict the process outputs using the measurement history. This neural network architecture, which employs the long short-term memory (LSTM), linear regression and logistic regression networks, allows reducing the number of state variables, thus reducing the complexity of the optimization problems in the control scheme. Furthermore, nonlinear model predictive control (NMPC) and moving horizon estimation (MHE) problems are developed and solved using the PSO (Particle Swarm Optimization) algorithm. Simulation results show that the proposed adaptive optimal control scheme satisfies the requirements of the control problem and provides promise for experimental testing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16307v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Duc-Tri Vo, Ionela Prodan, Laurent Lef\`evre, Vincent Vanel, Sylvain Costenoble, Binh Dinh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Datasets of Great Britain Primary Substations Integrated with Household Heating Information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16313v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The growing demand for electrified heating, electrified transportation, and power-intensive data centres challenge distribution networks. If electrification projects are carried out without considering electrical distribution infrastructure, there could be unexpected blackouts and financial losses. Datasets containing real-world distribution network information are required to address this. On the other hand, social data, such as household heating composition, are closely coupled with people's lives. Studying the coupling between the energy system and society is important in promoting social welfare. To fill these gaps, this paper introduces two datasets. The first is the main dataset for the distribution networks in Great Britain (GB), collecting information on firm capacity, peak demands, locations, and parent transmission nodes (the Grid Supply Point, namely GSP) for all primary substations (PSs). PSs are a crucial part of the UK distribution network and are at the lowest voltage level (11 kV) with publicly available data for most UK Distribution Network Operators (DNOs). Substation firm capacity and peak demand facilitate an understanding of the remaining room of the existing network. The parent GSP information helps link the dataset of distribution networks to datasets of transmission networks. The second dataset extends the main network dataset, linking each PS to information about the number of households that use different types of central heating recorded in census data. The derivation of the second dataset is based on locations of PSs collected in the main dataset with appropriate assumptions. The derivation process may also be replicated to integrate other social datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16313v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yihong Zhou, Chaimaa Essayeh, Thomas Morstyn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-informed RL for Maximal Safety Probability Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16391</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16391v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate risk quantification and reachability analysis are crucial for safe control and learning, but sampling from rare events, risky states, or long-term trajectories can be prohibitively costly. Motivated by this, we study how to estimate the long-term safety probability of maximally safe actions without sufficient coverage of samples from risky states and long-term trajectories. The use of maximal safety probability in control and learning is expected to avoid conservative behaviors due to over-approximation of risk. Here, we first show that long-term safety probability, which is multiplicative in time, can be converted into additive costs and be solved using standard reinforcement learning methods. We then derive this probability as solutions of partial differential equations (PDEs) and propose Physics-Informed Reinforcement Learning (PIRL) algorithm. The proposed method can learn using sparse rewards because the physics constraints help propagate risk information through neighbors. This suggests that, for the purpose of extracting more information for efficient learning, physics constraints can serve as an alternative to reward shaping. The proposed method can also estimate long-term risk using short-term samples and deduce the risk of unsampled states. This feature is in stark contrast with the unconstrained deep RL that demands sufficient data coverage. These merits of the proposed method are demonstrated in numerical simulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16391v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hikaru Hoshino, Yorie Nakahira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Distributionally Robust Model Predictive Control for Static and Dynamic Uncertainties in Smart Grids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16402v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The integration of various power sources, including renewables and electric vehicles, into smart grids is expanding, introducing uncertainties that can result in issues like voltage imbalances, load fluctuations, and power losses. These challenges negatively impact the reliability and stability of online scheduling in smart grids. Existing research often addresses uncertainties affecting current states but overlooks those that impact future states, such as the unpredictable charging patterns of electric vehicles. To distinguish between these, we term them static uncertainties and dynamic uncertainties, respectively. This paper introduces WDR-MPC, a novel approach that stands for two-stage Wasserstein-based Distributionally Robust (WDR) optimization within a Model Predictive Control (MPC) framework, aimed at effectively managing both types of uncertainties in smart grids. The dynamic uncertainties are first reformulated into ambiguity tubes and then the distributionally robust bounds of both dynamic and static uncertainties can be established using WDR optimization. By employing ambiguity tubes and WDR optimization, the stochastic MPC system is converted into a nominal one. Moreover, we develop a convex reformulation method to speed up WDR computation during the two-stage optimization. The distinctive contribution of this paper lies in its holistic approach to both static and dynamic uncertainties in smart grids. Comprehensive experiment results on IEEE 38-bus and 94-bus systems reveal the method's superior performance and the potential to enhance grid stability and reliability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16402v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qi Li, Ye Shi, Yuning Jiang, Yuanming Shi, Haoyu Wang, H. Vincent Poor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Geometric Perspective on Fusing Gaussian Distributions on Lie Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16411v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Stochastic inference on Lie groups plays a key role in state estimation problems, such as inertial navigation, visual inertial odometry, pose estimation in virtual reality, etc. A key problem is fusing independent concentrated Gaussian distributions defined at different reference points on the group. In this paper we approximate distributions at different points in the group in a single set of exponential coordinates and then use classical Gaussian fusion to obtain the fused posteriori in those coordinates. We consider several approximations including the exact Jacobian of the change of coordinate map, first and second order Taylor's expansions of the Jacobian, and parallel transport with and without curvature correction associated with the underlying geometry of the Lie group. Preliminary results on SO(3) demonstrate that a novel approximation using parallel transport with curvature correction achieves similar accuracy to the state-of-the-art optimisation based algorithms at a fraction of the computational cost.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16411v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yixiao Ge, Pieter van Goor, Robert Mahony</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ensuring Disturbance Rejection Performance by Synthesizing Grid-Following and Grid-Forming Inverters in Power Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16488v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To meet the dynamic requirement of power systems, it is imperative for grid-connected inverters to ensure good disturbance rejection performance (DRP) under variable grid conditions. This letter discovers and theoretically proves that for the general networks, synthesizing grid-following (GFL) inverters and grid-forming (GFM) inverters can more effectively ensure the DRP of multiple inverters, compared to homogeneous inverter-based systems that solely use either GFL or GFM inverters. The combination of GFL inverters and GFM inverters can concurrently increases the smallest eigenvalue and decreases the largest eigenvalue of the grounded network Laplacian matrix. This can be equivalent to rematching the proper short-circuit ratio (SCR) for GFL and GFM inverters, thereby ensuring the DRP of inverters both in weak and strong grids. The result reveals the necessity of synthesizing diverse inverter control schemes from the network-based perspective. Sensitivity function-based analysis and real-time simulations confirm the effectiveness of our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16488v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fuyilong Ma, Huanhai Xin, Zhiyi Li, Linbin Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid low-dimensional limiting state of charge estimator for multi-cell lithium-ion batteries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16555v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The state of charge (SOC) of lithium-ion batteries needs to be accurately estimated for safety and reliability purposes. For battery packs made of a large number of cells, it is not always feasible to design one SOC estimator per cell due to limited computational resources. Instead, only the minimum and the maximum SOC need to be estimated. The challenge is that the cells having minimum and maximum SOC typically change over time. In this context, we present a low-dimensional hybrid estimator of the minimum (maximum) SOC, whose convergence is analytically guaranteed. We consider for this purpose a battery consisting of cells interconnected in series, which we model by electric equivalent circuit models. We then present the hybrid estimator, which runs an observer designed for a single cell at any time instant, selected by a switching-like logic mechanism. We establish a practical exponential stability property for the estimation error on the minimum (maximum) SOC thereby guaranteeing the ability of the hybrid scheme to generate accurate estimates of the minimum (maximum) SOC. The analysis relies on non-smooth hybrid Lyapunov techniques. A numerical illustration is provided to showcase the relevance of the proposed approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16555v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mira Khalil, Romain Postoyan, St\'ephane Ra\"el, Dragan Ne\v{s}i\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoupling parameter variation from noise: Biquadratic Lyapunov forms in data-driven LPV control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16565v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A promising step from linear towards nonlinear data-driven control is via the design of controllers for linear parameter-varying (LPV) systems, which are linear systems whose parameters are varying along a measurable scheduling signal. However, the interplay between uncertainty arising from corrupted data and the parameter-varying nature of these systems impacts the stability analysis, and limits the generalization of well-understood data-driven methods for linear time-invariant systems. In this work, we decouple this interplay using a recently developed variant of the Fundamental Lemma for LPV systems and the viewpoint of data-informativity, in combination with biquadratic Lyapunov forms. Together, these allow us to develop novel linear matrix inequality conditions for the existence of scheduling-dependent Lyapunov functions, incorporating the intrinsic nonlinearity. Appealingly, these results are stated purely in terms of the collected data and bounds on the noise, and they are computationally favorable to check.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16565v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chris Verhoek, Jaap Eising, Florian D\"orfler, Roland T\'oth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sparsity-Constrained Linear Quadratic Regulation Problem: Greedy Approach with Performance Guarantee</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16585</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16585v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a linear quadratic regulation problem with a constraint where the control input can be nonzero only at a limited number of times. Given that this constraint leads to a combinational optimization problem, we adopt a greedy method to find a suboptimal solution. To quantify the performance of the greedy algorithm, we employ two metrics that reflect the submodularity level of the objective function: The submodularity ratio and curvature. We first present an explicit form of the optimal control input that is amenable to evaluating these metrics. Subsequently, we establish bounds on the submodularity ratio and curvature, which enable us to offer a practical performance guarantee for the greedy algorithm. The effectiveness of our guarantee is further demonstrated through numerical simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16585v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shumpei Nishida, Kunihisa Okano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guided Bayesian Optimization: Data-Efficient Controller Tuning with Digital Twin</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16619v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article presents the guided Bayesian optimization algorithm as an efficient data-driven method for iteratively tuning closed-loop controller parameters using an event-triggered digital twin of the system based on available closed-loop data. We define a controller tuning framework independent of the controller or the plant structure. Our proposed methodology is model-free, making it suitable for nonlinear and unmodelled plants with measurement noise. The objective function consists of performance metrics modeled by Gaussian processes. We utilize the available information in the closed-loop system to identify and progressively maintain a digital twin that guides the optimizer, improving the data efficiency of our method. Switching the digital twin on and off is triggered by data-driven criteria related to the digital twin's uncertainty estimations in the BO tuning framework. Effectively, it replaces much of the exploration of the real system with exploration performed on the digital twin. We analyze the properties of our method in simulation and demonstrate its performance on two real closed-loop systems with different plant and controller structures. The experimental results show that our method requires fewer experiments on the physical plant than Bayesian optimization to find the optimal controller parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16619v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahdi Nobar, J\"urg Keller, Alisa Rupenyan, Mohammad Khosravi, John Lygeros</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predictable Interval MDPs through Entropy Regularization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16711v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Regularization of control policies using entropy can be instrumental in adjusting predictability of real-world systems. Applications benefiting from such approaches range from, e.g., cybersecurity, which aims at maximal unpredictability, to human-robot interaction, where predictable behavior is highly desirable. In this paper, we consider entropy regularization for interval Markov decision processes (IMDPs). IMDPs are uncertain MDPs, where transition probabilities are only known to belong to intervals. Lately, IMDPs have gained significant popularity in the context of abstracting stochastic systems for control design. In this work, we address robust minimization of the linear combination of entropy and a standard cumulative cost in IMDPs, thereby establishing a trade-off between optimality and predictability. We show that optimal deterministic policies exist, and devise a value-iteration algorithm to compute them. The algorithm solves a number of convex programs at each step. Finally, through an illustrative example we show the benefits of penalizing entropy in IMDPs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16711v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Menno van Zutphen, Giannis Delimpaltadakis, Maurice Heemels, Duarte Antunes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SIS epidemics on open networks: A replacement-based approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16727</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16727v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we analyze continuous-time SIS epidemics subject to arrivals and departures of agents, by using an approximated process based on replacements. In defining the SIS dynamics in an open network, we consider a stochastic setting in which arrivals and departures take place according to Poisson processes with similar rates, and the new value of the infection probability of an arriving agent is drawn from a continuous distribution. Since the system size changes with time, we define an approximated process, in which replacements take place instead of arrivals and departures, and we focus on the evolution of an aggregate measure of the level of infection. So long as the reproduction number is less than one, the long-term behavior of this function measures the impact of the changes of the set of agents in the epidemic. We derive upper bounds for the expectation and variance of this function and we include a numerical example to show that the approximated process is close to the original SIS process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16727v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renato Vizuete, Paolo Frasca, Elena Panteley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A data-based comparison of methods for reducing the peak volume flow rate in a district heating system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16738v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work concerns reduction of the peak flow rate of a district heating grid, a key system property which is bounded by pipe dimensions and pumping capacity. The peak flow rate constrains the number of additional consumers that can be connected, and may be a limiting factor in reducing supply temperatures when transitioning to the 4th generation of district heating. We evaluate a full year of operational data from a subset of customer meters in a district heating system in Germany. We consider the peak flow rate reduction that could be achieved with full a posteriori knowledge of this data. Three strategies for reducing the peak flow rate are investigated: A load shifting demand response strategy, an upper limitation in substation return temperatures, and an upper limitation on each substation's volume flow rate. We show that imposing up to to 18 % load flexibility for the customers provides an equal reduction in the peak system flow rate under the load shifting strategy. The limited return temperature strategy is less efficient at curtailing the peak flow rate, but provides an overall reduction of volume flow rates. Finally, the flow rate limitation method can introduce new, higher flow rate peaks, reducing performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16738v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felix Agner, Ulrich Trabert, Anders Rantzer, Janybek Orozaliev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Branch and Bound method for the exact parameter identification of the PK/PD model for anesthetic drugs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16742</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16742v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We address the problem of parameter identification for the standard pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic (PK/PD) model for anesthetic drugs. Our main contribution is the development of a global optimization method that guarantees finding the parameters that minimize the one-step ahead prediction error. The method is based on a branch-and-bound algorithm, that can be applied to solve a more general class of nonlinear regression problems. We present some simulation results, based on a dataset of twelve patients. In these simulations, we are always able to identify the exact parameters, despite the non-convexity of the overall identification problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16742v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giulia Di Credico, Luca Consolini, Mattia Laurini, Marco Locatelli, Marco Milanesi, Michele Schiavo, Antonio Visioli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Blotto Game Approach to Ride-hailing Markets with Electric Vehicles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16755v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When a centrally operated ride-hailing company considers to enter a market already served by another company, it has to make a strategic decision about how to distribute its fleet among different regions in the area. This decision will be influenced by the market share the company can secure and the costs associated with charging the vehicles in each region, all while competing with the company already operating in the area. In this paper, we propose a Colonel Blotto-like game to model this decision-making. For the class of games that we study, we first prove the existence and uniqueness of a Nash Equilibrium. Subsequently, we provide its general characterization and present an algorithm for computing the ones in the feasible set's interior. Additionally, for a simplified scenario involving two regions, which would correspond to a city area with a downtown and a suburban region, we also provide a method to check for the equilibria on the feasible set's boundary. Finally, through a numerical case study, we illustrate the impact of charging prices on the position of the Nash equilibrium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16755v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marko Maljkovic, Gustav Nilsson, Nikolas Geroliminis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Policy Gradient-based Model Free Optimal LQG Control with a Probabilistic Risk Constraint</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16767</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16767v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate a model-free optimal control design that minimizes an infinite horizon average expected quadratic cost of states and control actions subject to a probabilistic risk or chance constraint using input-output data. In particular, we consider linear time-invariant systems and design an optimal controller within the class of linear state feedback control. Three different policy gradient (PG) based algorithms, natural policy gradient (NPG), Gauss-Newton policy gradient (GNPG), and deep deterministic policy gradient (DDPG), are developed, and compared with the optimal risk-neutral linear-quadratic regulator (LQR) and a scenario-based model predictive control (MPC) technique via numerical simulations. The convergence properties and the accuracy of all the algorithms are compared numerically. We also establish analytical convergence properties of the NPG and GNPG algorithms under the known model scenario, while the proof of convergence for the unknown model scenario is part of our ongoing work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16767v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arunava Naha, Subhrakanti Dey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Preservation by Intermittent Transmission in Cooperative LQG Control Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16797</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16797v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study a cooperative linear quadratic Gaussian (LQG) control system with a single user and a server. In this system, the user runs a process and employs the server to meet the needs of computation. However, the user regards its state trajectories as privacy. Therefore, we propose a privacy scheme, in which the user sends data to the server intermittently. By this scheme, the server's received information of the user is reduced, and consequently the user's privacy is preserved. In this paper, we consider a periodic transmission scheme. We analyze the performance of privacy preservation and LQG control of different transmission periods. Under the given threshold of the control performance loss, a trade-off optimization problem is proposed. Finally, we give the solution to the optimization problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16797v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenhao Lin, Yuqing Ni, Wen Yang, Chao Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An LLM-Based Digital Twin for Optimizing Human-in-the Loop Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16809v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The increasing prevalence of Cyber-Physical Systems and the Internet of Things (CPS-IoT) applications and Foundation Models are enabling new applications that leverage real-time control of the environment. For example, real-time control of Heating, Ventilation and Air-Conditioning (HVAC) systems can reduce its usage when not needed for the comfort of human occupants, hence reducing energy consumption. Collecting real-time feedback on human preferences in such human-in-the-loop (HITL) systems, however, is difficult in practice. We propose the use of large language models (LLMs) to deal with the challenges of dynamic environments and difficult-to-obtain data in CPS optimization. In this paper, we present a case study that employs LLM agents to mimic the behaviors and thermal preferences of various population groups (e.g. young families, the elderly) in a shopping mall. The aggregated thermal preferences are integrated into an agent-in-the-loop based reinforcement learning algorithm AitL-RL, which employs the LLM as a dynamic simulation of the physical environment to learn how to balance between energy savings and occupant comfort. Our results show that LLMs are capable of simulating complex population movements within large open spaces. Besides, AitL-RL demonstrates superior performance compared to the popular existing policy of set point control, suggesting that adaptive and personalized decision-making is critical for efficient optimization in CPS-IoT applications. Through this case study, we demonstrate the potential of integrating advanced Foundation Models like LLMs into CPS-IoT to enhance system adaptability and efficiency. The project's code can be found on our GitHub repository.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16809v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanqing Yang, Marie Siew, Carlee Joe-Wong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scheduling Power-Intensive Operations of Battery Energy Storage Systems and Application to Hybrid Hydropower Plants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16821v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Classical schedulers for Battery Energy Storage Systems (BESSs) use static power constraints, assuming that the BESS can provide the rated power at any State-Of-Charge (SOC) level and that these are representative of the underlying physical constraints of the system (BESS voltage and current). Static power constraints, however, can generate unfeasible schedules, especially in power-intensive applications, as demonstrated in this paper. This paper derives a set of alternative constraints for the BESS power that are cognizant of the physical limits of the BESS. It is shown that these constraints, developed by leveraging an equivalent circuit model of the BESS, can be formulated as linear inequalities in scheduling problems, thus leaving the properties of the original problem (i.e., linearity and convexity) unaltered. A comparative analysis against traditional schedulers from the literature shows significant reductions in current violations and the generation of feasible schedules. These findings underscore the crucial role of implementing more advanced power constraints of BESSs in power-intensive applications, thereby enhancing the reliability of BESS scheduling strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16821v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Cassano, Fabrizio Sossan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resource and Mobility Management in Hybrid LiFi and WiFi Networks: A User-Centric Learning Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16823v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hybrid light fidelity (LiFi) and wireless fidelity (WiFi) networks (HLWNets) are an emerging indoor wireless communication paradigm, which combines the advantages of the capacious optical spectra of LiFi and ubiquitous coverage of WiFi. Meanwhile, load balancing (LB) becomes a key challenge in resource management for such hybrid networks. The existing LB methods are mostly network-centric, relying on a central unit to make a solution for the users all at once. Consequently, the solution needs to be updated for all users at the same pace, regardless of their moving status. This would affect the network performance in two aspects: i) when the update frequency is low, it would compromise the connectivity of fast-moving users; ii) when the update frequency is high, it would cause unnecessary handovers as well as hefty feedback costs for slow-moving users. Motivated by this, we investigate user-centric LB which allows users to update their solutions at different paces. The research is developed upon our previous work on adaptive target-condition neural network (ATCNN), which can conduct LB for individual users in quasi-static channels. In this paper, a deep neural network (DNN) model is designed to enable an adaptive update interval for each individual user. This new model is termed as mobility-supporting neural network (MSNN). Associating MSNN with ATCNN, a user-centric LB framework named mobility-supporting ATCNN (MS-ATCNN) is proposed to handle resource management and mobility management simultaneously. Results show that at the same level of average update interval, MS-ATCNN can achieve a network throughput up to 215\% higher than conventional LB methods such as game theory, especially for a larger number of users. In addition, MS-ATCNN costs an ultra low runtime at the level of 100s $\mu$s, which is two to three orders of magnitude lower than game theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16823v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Han Ji, Xiping Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy Efficiency Optimization Method of WDM Visible Light Communication System for Indoor Broadcasting Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16836v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel approach to optimize energy efficiency in wavelength division multiplexing (WDM) Visible Light Communication (VLC) systems designed for indoor broadcasting networks. A physics-based LED model is integrated into system energy efficiency optimization, enabling quantitative analysis of the critical issue of VLC energy efficiency: the nonlinear interplay between illumination and communication performance. The optimization jointly incorporates constraints on communication quality of each channel, and illumination performance, standardized by the International Commission on Illumination (CIE). The formulated nonlinear optimization problem is solved by the Sequential Quadratic Programming (SQP) algorithm in an experiment-based simulation. An integrated Red-Green-Blue-Yellow Light Emitting Diode (RGBY-LED) is measured for model calibration and three different scenarios are simulated to evaluate the generality of the proposed method. Results demonstrate a double enhancement in performance and a high versatility in accommodating various scenarios. Furthermore, it highlights the importance of balancing communication and illumination imperatives in VLC systems, challenging conventional perceptions focused solely on minimizing power consumption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16836v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dayu Shi, Xun Zhang, Ziqi Liu, Xuanbang Chen, Jianghao Li, Xiaodong Liu, William Shieh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semantic-Aware Remote Estimation of Multiple Markov Sources Under Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16855</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16855v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper studies semantic-aware communication for remote estimation of multiple Markov sources over a lossy and rate-constrained channel. Unlike most existing studies that treat all source states equally, we exploit the semantics of information and consider that the remote actuator has different tolerances for the estimation errors of different states. We aim to find an optimal scheduling policy that minimizes the long-term state-dependent costs of estimation errors under a transmission frequency constraint. We theoretically show the structure of the optimal policy by leveraging the average-cost Constrained Markov Decision Process (CMDP) theory and the Lagrangian dynamic programming. By exploiting the optimal structural results, we develop a novel policy search algorithm, termed intersection search plus relative value iteration (Insec-RVI), that can find the optimal policy using only a few iterations. To avoid the ``curse of dimensionality'' of MDPs, we propose an online low-complexity drift-plus-penalty (DPP) scheduling algorithm based on the Lyapunov optimization theorem. We also design an efficient average-cost Q-learning algorithm to estimate the optimal policy without knowing a priori the channel and source statistics. Numerical results show that continuous transmission is inefficient, and remarkably, our semantic-aware policies can attain the optimum by strategically utilizing fewer transmissions by exploiting the timing of the important information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16855v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiping Luo, Nikolaos Pappas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>State Space Models as Foundation Models: A Control Theoretic Overview</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16899v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In recent years, there has been a growing interest in integrating linear state-space models (SSM) in deep neural network architectures of foundation models. This is exemplified by the recent success of Mamba, showing better performance than the state-of-the-art Transformer architectures in language tasks. Foundation models, like e.g. GPT-4, aim to encode sequential data into a latent space in order to learn a compressed representation of the data. The same goal has been pursued by control theorists using SSMs to efficiently model dynamical systems. Therefore, SSMs can be naturally connected to deep sequence modeling, offering the opportunity to create synergies between the corresponding research areas. This paper is intended as a gentle introduction to SSM-based architectures for control theorists and summarizes the latest research developments. It provides a systematic review of the most successful SSM proposals and highlights their main features from a control theoretic perspective. Additionally, we present a comparative analysis of these models, evaluating their performance on a standardized benchmark designed for assessing a model's efficiency at learning long sequences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16899v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carmen Amo Alonso, Jerome Sieber, Melanie N. Zeilinger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spline Trajectory Tracking and Obstacle Avoidance for Mobile Agents via Convex Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16900</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16900v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose an output feedback control-based motion planning technique for agents to enable them to converge to a specified polynomial trajectory while imposing a set of safety constraints on our controller to avoid collisions within the free configuration space (polygonal environment). To achieve this, we 1) decompose our polygonal environment into different overlapping cells 2) write out our polynomial trajectories as the output of a reference dynamical system with given initial conditions 3) formulate convergence and safety constraints as Linear Matrix Inequalities (LMIs) on our controller using Control Lyapunov Functions (CLFs) and Control Barrier Functions (CBFs) and 4) solve a semi-definite programming (SDP) problem with convergence and safety constraints imposed to synthesize a controller for each convex cell. Extensive simulations are included to test our motion planning method under different initial conditions and different reference trajectories. The synthesized controller is robust to changes in initial conditions and is always safe relative to the boundaries of the polygonal environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16900v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akua Dickson, Christos G. Cassandras, Roberto Tron</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>State-Augmented Linear Games with Antagonistic Error for High-Dimensional, Nonlinear Hamilton-Jacobi Reachability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16982</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16982v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hamilton-Jacobi Reachability (HJR) is a popular method for analyzing the liveness and safety of a dynamical system with bounded control and disturbance. The corresponding HJ value function offers a robust controller and characterizes the reachable sets, but is traditionally solved with Dynamic Programming (DP) and limited to systems of dimension less than six. Recently, the space-parallelizeable, generalized Hopf formula has been shown to also solve the HJ value with a nearly three-log increase in dimension limit, but is limited to linear systems. To extend this potential, we demonstrate how state-augmented (SA) spaces, which are well-known for their improved linearization accuracy, may be used to solve tighter, conservative approximations of the value function with any linear model in this SA space. Namely, we show that with a representation of the true dynamics in the SA space, a series of inequalities confirms that the value of a SA linear game with antagonistic error is a conservative envelope of the true value function. It follows that if the optimal controller for the HJ SA linear game with error may succeed, it will also succeed in the true system. Unlike previous methods, this result offers the ability to safely approximate reachable sets and their corresponding controllers with the Hopf formula in a non-convex manner. Finally, we demonstrate this in the slow manifold system for clarity, and in the controlled Van der Pol system with different lifting functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16982v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Will Sharpless, Yat Tin Chow, Sylvia Herbert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secure and Energy-efficient Unmanned Aerial Vehicle-enabled Visible Light Communication via A Multi-objective Optimization Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15410v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this research, a unique approach to provide communication service for terrestrial receivers via using unmanned aerial vehicle-enabled visible light communication is investigated. Specifically, we take into account a unmanned aerial vehicle-enabled visible light communication scenario with multiplex transmitters, multiplex receivers, and a single eavesdropper, each of which is equipped with a single photodetector. Then, a unmanned aerial vehicle deployment multi-objective optimization problem is formulated to simultaneously make the optical power received by receiving surface more uniform, minimize the amount of information collected by a eavesdropper, and minimize the energy consumption of unmanned aerial vehicles, while the locations and transmission power of unmanned aerial vehicles are simultaneously optimized under certain constraints. Since the formulated unmanned aerial vehicle deployment multi-objective optimization problem is complex and nonlinear, it is challenging to be tackled by using conventional methods. For the purpose of solving the problem, a multi-objective evolutionary algorithm based on decomposition with chaos initiation and crossover mutation is proposed. Simulation outcomes show that the proposed approach is superior to other approaches, and is efficient at improving the security and energy efficiency of visible light communication system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15410v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lingling Liu, Aimin Wang, Jing Wu, Jiao Lu, Jiahui Li, Geng Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Most Likely Sequence Generation for $n$-Grams, Transformers, HMMs, and Markov Chains, by Using Rollout Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15465</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15465v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we consider a transformer with an $n$-gram structure, such as the one underlying ChatGPT. The transformer provides next word probabilities, which can be used to generate word sequences. We consider methods for computing word sequences that are highly likely, based on these probabilities. Computing the optimal (i.e., most likely) word sequence starting with a given initial state is an intractable problem, so we propose methods to compute highly likely sequences of $N$ words in time that is a low order polynomial in $N$ and in the vocabulary size of the $n$-gram. These methods are based on the rollout approach from approximate dynamic programming, a form of single policy iteration, which can improve the performance of any given heuristic policy. In our case we use a greedy heuristic that generates as next word one that has the highest probability. We show with analysis, examples, and computational experimentation that our methods are capable of generating highly likely sequences with a modest increase in computation over the greedy heuristic. While our analysis and experiments are focused on Markov chains of the type arising in transformer and ChatGPT-like models, our methods apply to general finite-state Markov chains, and related inference applications of Hidden Markov Models (HMM), where Viterbi decoding is used extensively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15465v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuchao Li, Dimitri Bertsekas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Autonomous Driving With Perception Uncertainties: Deep-Ensemble Based Adaptive Cruise Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15577v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Autonomous driving depends on perception systems to understand the environment and to inform downstream decision-making. While advanced perception systems utilizing black-box Deep Neural Networks (DNNs) demonstrate human-like comprehension, their unpredictable behavior and lack of interpretability may hinder their deployment in safety critical scenarios. In this paper, we develop an Ensemble of DNN regressors (Deep Ensemble) that generates predictions with quantification of prediction uncertainties. In the scenario of Adaptive Cruise Control (ACC), we employ the Deep Ensemble to estimate distance headway to the lead vehicle from RGB images and enable the downstream controller to account for the estimation uncertainty. We develop an adaptive cruise controller that utilizes Stochastic Model Predictive Control (MPC) with chance constraints to provide a probabilistic safety guarantee. We evaluate our ACC algorithm using a high-fidelity traffic simulator and a real-world traffic dataset and demonstrate the ability of the proposed approach to effect speed tracking and car following while maintaining a safe distance headway. The out-of-distribution scenarios are also examined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15577v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao Li, H. Eric Tseng, Anouck Girard, Ilya Kolmanovsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Balancing Fairness and Efficiency in Energy Resource Allocations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15616v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Bringing fairness to energy resource allocation remains a challenge, due to the complexity of system structures and economic interdependencies among users and system operators' decision-making. The rise of distributed energy resources has introduced more diverse heterogeneous user groups, surpassing the capabilities of traditional efficiency-oriented allocation schemes. Without explicitly bringing fairness to user-system interaction, this disparity often leads to disproportionate payments for certain user groups due to their utility formats or group sizes.
  Our paper addresses this challenge by formalizing the problem of fair energy resource allocation and introducing the framework for aggregators. This framework enables optimal fairness-efficiency trade-offs by selecting appropriate objectives in a principled way. By jointly optimizing over the total resources to allocate and individual allocations, our approach reveals optimized allocation schemes that lie on the Pareto front, balancing fairness and efficiency in resource allocation strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15616v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiayi Li, Matthew Motoki, Baosen Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Variational Interpretation of Mirror Play in Monotone Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15636</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15636v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Mirror play (MP) is a well-accepted primal-dual multi-agent learning algorithm where all agents simultaneously implement mirror descent in a distributed fashion. The advantage of MP over vanilla gradient play lies in its usage of mirror maps that better exploit the geometry of decision domains. Despite extensive literature dedicated to the asymptotic convergence of MP to equilibrium, the understanding of the finite-time behavior of MP before reaching equilibrium is still rudimentary. To facilitate the study of MP's non-equilibrium performance, this work establishes an equivalence between MP's finite-time primal-dual path (mirror path) in monotone games and the closed-loop Nash equilibrium path of a finite-horizon differential game, referred to as mirror differential game (MDG). Our construction of MDG rests on the Brezis-Ekeland variational principle, and the stage cost functional for MDG is Fenchel coupling between MP's iterates and associated gradient updates. The variational interpretation of mirror path in static games as the equilibrium path in MDG holds in deterministic and stochastic cases. Such a variational interpretation translates the non-equilibrium studies of learning dynamics into a more tractable equilibrium analysis of dynamic games, as demonstrated in a case study on the Cournot game, where MP dynamics corresponds to a linear quadratic game.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15636v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunian Pan, Tao Li, Quanyan Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the role of network structure in learning to coordinate with bounded rationality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15683v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Many socioeconomic phenomena, such as technology adoption, collaborative problem-solving, and content engagement, involve a collection of agents coordinating to take a common action, aligning their decisions to maximize their individual goals. We consider a model for networked interactions where agents learn to coordinate their binary actions under a strict bound on their rationality. We first prove that our model is a potential game and that the optimal action profile is always to achieve perfect alignment at one of the two possible actions, regardless of the network structure. Using a stochastic learning algorithm known as Log Linear Learning, where agents have the same finite rationality parameter, we show that the probability of agents successfully agreeing on the correct decision is monotonically increasing in the number of network links. Therefore, more connectivity improves the accuracy of collective decision-making, as predicted by the phenomenon known as Wisdom of Crowds. Finally, we show that for a fixed number of links, a regular network maximizes the probability of success. We conclude that when using a network of irrational agents, promoting more homogeneous connectivity improves the accuracy of collective decision-making.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15683v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifei Zhang, Marcos M. Vasconcelos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Robust Learning based Formation Control of Mobile Robots based on Bioinspired Neural Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15716</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15716v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper addresses the challenges of distributed formation control in multiple mobile robots, introducing a novel approach that enhances real-world practicability. We first introduce a distributed estimator using a variable structure and cascaded design technique, eliminating the need for derivative information to improve the real time performance. Then, a kinematic tracking control method is developed utilizing a bioinspired neural dynamic-based approach aimed at providing smooth control inputs and effectively resolving the speed jump issue. Furthermore, to address the challenges for robots operating with completely unknown dynamics and disturbances, a learning-based robust dynamic controller is developed. This controller provides real time parameter estimates while maintaining its robustness against disturbances. The overall stability of the proposed method is proved with rigorous mathematical analysis. At last, multiple comprehensive simulation studies have shown the advantages and effectiveness of the proposed method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15716v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TIV.2024.3380000</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Zhe Xu, Tao Yan, Simon X. Yang, S. Andrew Gadsden, Mohammad Biglarbegian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perception and Control of Surfing in Virtual Reality using a 6-DoF Motion Platform</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15924v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The paper presents a system for simulating surfing in Virtual Reality (VR), emphasizing the recreation of aquatic motions and user-initiated propulsive forces using a 6-Degree of Freedom (DoF) motion platform. We present an algorithmic approach to accurately render surfboard kinematics and interactive paddling dynamics, validated through experimental evaluation with \(N=17\) participants. Results indicate that the system effectively reproduces various acceleration levels, the perception of which is independent of users' body posture. We additionally found that the presence of ocean ripples amplifies the perception of acceleration. This system aims to enhance the realism and interactivity of VR surfing, laying a foundation for future advancements in surf therapy and interactive aquatic VR experiences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15924v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Premankur Banerjee, Jason Cherin, Jayati Upadhyay, Jason Kutch, Heather Culbertson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Risk-Calibrated Human-Robot Interaction via Set-Valued Intent Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15959v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Tasks where robots must cooperate with humans, such as navigating around a cluttered home or sorting everyday items, are challenging because they exhibit a wide range of valid actions that lead to similar outcomes. Moreover, zero-shot cooperation between human-robot partners is an especially challenging problem because it requires the robot to infer and adapt on the fly to a latent human intent, which could vary significantly from human to human. Recently, deep learned motion prediction models have shown promising results in predicting human intent but are prone to being confidently incorrect. In this work, we present Risk-Calibrated Interactive Planning (RCIP), which is a framework for measuring and calibrating risk associated with uncertain action selection in human-robot cooperation, with the fundamental idea that the robot should ask for human clarification when the risk associated with the uncertainty in the human's intent cannot be controlled. RCIP builds on the theory of set-valued risk calibration to provide a finite-sample statistical guarantee on the cumulative loss incurred by the robot while minimizing the cost of human clarification in complex multi-step settings. Our main insight is to frame the risk control problem as a sequence-level multi-hypothesis testing problem, allowing efficient calibration using a low-dimensional parameter that controls a pre-trained risk-aware policy. Experiments across a variety of simulated and real-world environments demonstrate RCIP's ability to predict and adapt to a diverse set of dynamic human intents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15959v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Justin Lidard, Hang Pham, Ariel Bachman, Bryan Boateng, Anirudha Majumdar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Input-to-State Stability of Newton Methods for Generalized Equations in Nonlinear Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16165</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16165v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that Newton methods for generalized equations are input-to-state stable with respect to disturbances such as due to inexact computations. We then use this result to obtain convergence and robustness of a multistep Newton-type method for multivariate generalized equations. We demonstrate the usefulness of the results with other applications to nonlinear optimization. In particular, we provide a new proof for (robust) local convergence of the augmented Lagrangian method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16165v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Torbj{\o}rn Cunis, Ilya Kolmanovsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Legged Robot State Estimation within Non-inertial Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16252v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates the robot state estimation problem within a non-inertial environment. The proposed state estimation approach relaxes the common assumption of static ground in the system modeling. The process and measurement models explicitly treat the movement of the non-inertial environments without requiring knowledge of its motion in the inertial frame or relying on GPS or sensing environmental landmarks. Further, the proposed state estimator is formulated as an invariant extended Kalman filter (InEKF) with the deterministic part of its process model obeying the group-affine property, leading to log-linear error dynamics. The observability analysis of the filter confirms that the robot's pose (i.e., position and orientation) and velocity relative to the non-inertial environment are observable. Hardware experiments on a humanoid robot moving on a rotating and translating treadmill demonstrate the high convergence rate and accuracy of the proposed InEKF even under significant treadmill pitch sway, as well as large estimation errors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16252v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zijian He, Sangli Teng, Tzu-Yuan Lin, Maani Ghaffari, Yan Gu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HT-LIP Model based Robust Control of Quadrupedal Robot Locomotion under Unknown Vertical Ground Motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16262v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a hierarchical control framework that enables robust quadrupedal locomotion on a dynamic rigid surface (DRS) with general and unknown vertical motions. The key novelty of the framework lies in its higher layer, which is a discrete-time, provably stabilizing footstep controller. The basis of the footstep controller is a new hybrid, time-varying, linear inverted pendulum (HT-LIP) model that is low-dimensional and accurately captures the essential robot dynamics during DRS locomotion. A new set of sufficient stability conditions are then derived to directly guide the controller design for ensuring the asymptotic stability of the HT-LIP model under general, unknown, vertical DRS motions. Further, the footstep controller is cast as a computationally efficient quadratic program that incorporates the proposed HT-LIP model and stability conditions. The middle layer takes the desired footstep locations generated by the higher layer as input to produce kinematically feasible full-body reference trajectories, which are then accurately tracked by a lower-layer torque controller. Hardware experiments on a Unitree Go1 quadrupedal robot confirm the robustness of the proposed framework under various unknown, aperiodic, vertical DRS motions and uncertainties (e.g., slippery and uneven surfaces, solid and liquid loads, and sudden pushes).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16262v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amir Iqbal, Sushant Veer, Christopher Niezrecki, Yan Gu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-time Adaptation for Condition Monitoring Signal Prediction using Label-aware Neural Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16377v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Building a predictive model that rapidly adapts to real-time condition monitoring (CM) signals is critical for engineering systems/units. Unfortunately, many current methods suffer from a trade-off between representation power and agility in online settings. For instance, parametric methods that assume an underlying functional form for CM signals facilitate efficient online prediction updates. However, this simplification leads to vulnerability to model specifications and an inability to capture complex signals. On the other hand, approaches based on over-parameterized or non-parametric models can excel at explaining complex nonlinear signals, but real-time updates for such models pose a challenging task. In this paper, we propose a neural process-based approach that addresses this trade-off. It encodes available observations within a CM signal into a representation space and then reconstructs the signal's history and evolution for prediction. Once trained, the model can encode an arbitrary number of observations without requiring retraining, enabling on-the-spot real-time predictions along with quantified uncertainty and can be readily updated as more online data is gathered. Furthermore, our model is designed to incorporate qualitative information (i.e., labels) from individual units. This integration not only enhances individualized predictions for each unit but also enables joint inference for both signals and their associated labels. Numerical studies on both synthetic and real-world data in reliability engineering highlight the advantageous features of our model in real-time adaptation, enhanced signal prediction with uncertainty quantification, and joint prediction for labels and signals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16377v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seokhyun Chung, Raed Al Kontar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-Driven Extrusion Force Control Tuning for 3D Printing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16470</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16470v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The quality of 3D prints often varies due to different conditions inherent to each print, such as filament type, print speed, and nozzle size. Closed-loop process control methods improve the accuracy and repeatability of 3D prints. However, optimal tuning of controllers for given process parameters and design geometry is often a challenge with manually tuned controllers resulting in inconsistent and suboptimal results. This work employs Bayesian optimization to identify the optimal controller parameters. Additionally, we explore transfer learning in the context of 3D printing by leveraging prior information from past trials. By integrating optimized extrusion force control and transfer learning, we provide a novel framework for closed-loop 3D printing and propose an automated calibration routine that produces high-quality prints for a desired combination of print settings, material, and shape.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16470v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xavier Guidetti, Ankita Mukne, Marvin Rueppel, Yannick Nagel, Efe C. Balta, John Lygeros</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatially temporally distributed informative path planning for multi-robot systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16489v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates the problem of informative path planning for a mobile robotic sensor network in spatially temporally distributed mapping. The robots are able to gather noisy measurements from an area of interest during their movements to build a Gaussian Process (GP) model of a spatio-temporal field. The model is then utilized to predict the spatio-temporal phenomenon at different points of interest. To spatially and temporally navigate the group of robots so that they can optimally acquire maximal information gains while their connectivity is preserved, we propose a novel multistep prediction informative path planning optimization strategy employing our newly defined local cost functions. By using the dual decomposition method, it is feasible and practical to effectively solve the optimization problem in a distributed manner. The proposed method was validated through synthetic experiments utilizing real-world data sets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16489v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Binh Nguyen, Linh Nguyen, Truong X. Nghiem, Hung La, Jose Baca, Pablo Rangel, Miguel Cid Montoya, Thang Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Counter-example guided Imitation Learning of Feedback Controllers from Temporal Logic Specifications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16593v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a novel method for imitation learning for control requirements expressed using Signal Temporal Logic (STL). More concretely we focus on the problem of training a neural network to imitate a complex controller. The learning process is guided by efficient data aggregation based on counter-examples and a coverage measure. Moreover, we introduce a method to evaluate the performance of the learned controller via parameterization and parameter estimation of the STL requirements. We demonstrate our approach with a flying robot case study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16593v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thao Dang, Alexandre Donz\'e, Inzemamul Haque, Nikolaos Kekatos, Indranil Saha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Adaptive Workplace: Orchestrating Architectural Services around the Wellbeing of Individual Occupants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16595</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16595v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: As the academic consortia members of the EU Horizon project SONATA ("Situation-aware OrchestratioN of AdapTive Architecture"), we respond to the workshop call for "Office Wellbeing by Design: Don't Stand for Anything Less" by proposing the "Adaptive Workplace" concept. In essence, our vision aims to adapt a workplace to the ever-changing needs of individual occupants, instead of that occupants are expected to adapt to their workplace.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16595v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Vande Moere, Sara Arko, Alena Safrova Drasilova, Tom\'a\v{s} Ondr\'a\v{c}ek, Ilaria Pigliautile, Benedetta Pioppi, Anna Laura Pisello, Jakub Prochazka, Paula Acuna Roncancio, Davide Schaumann, Marcel Schweiker, Binh Vinh Duc Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symbolic and User-friendly Geometric Algebra Routines (SUGAR) for Computations in Matlab</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16634v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Geometric algebra (GA) is a mathematical tool for geometric computing, providing a framework that allows a unified and compact approach to geometric relations which in other mathematical systems are typically described using different more complicated elements. This fact has led to an increasing adoption of GA in applied mathematics and engineering problems. However, the scarcity of symbolic implementations of GA and its inherent complexity, requiring a specific mathematical background, make it challenging and less intuitive for engineers to work with. This prevents wider adoption among more applied professionals. To address this challenge, this paper introduces SUGAR (Symbolic and User-friendly Geometric Algebra Routines), an open-source toolbox designed for Matlab and licensed under the MIT License. SUGAR facilitates the translation of GA concepts into Matlab and provides a collection of user-friendly functions tailored for GA computations, including support for symbolic operations. It supports both numeric and symbolic computations in high-dimensional GAs. Specifically tailored for applied mathematics and engineering applications, SUGAR has been meticulously engineered to represent geometric elements and transformations within two and three-dimensional projective and conformal geometric algebras, aligning with established computational methodologies in the literature. Furthermore, SUGAR efficiently handles functions of multivectors, such as exponential, logarithmic, sinusoidal, and cosine functions, enhancing its applicability across various engineering domains, including robotics, control systems, and power electronics. Finally, this work includes four distinct validation examples, demonstrating SUGAR's capabilities across the above-mentioned fields and its practical utility in addressing real-world applied mathematics and engineering problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16634v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MS</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manel Velasco, Isiah Zaplana, Arnau D\'oria-Cerezo, Pau Mart\'i</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trajectory Planning of Robotic Manipulator in Dynamic Environment Exploiting DRL</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16652</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16652v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study is about the implementation of a reinforcement learning algorithm in the trajectory planning of manipulators. We have a 7-DOF robotic arm to pick and place the randomly placed block at a random target point in an unknown environment. The obstacle is randomly moving which creates a hurdle in picking the object. The objective of the robot is to avoid the obstacle and pick the block with constraints to a fixed timestamp. In this literature, we have applied a deep deterministic policy gradient (DDPG) algorithm and compared the model's efficiency with dense and sparse rewards.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16652v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Osama Ahmad, Zawar Hussain, Hammad Naeem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BatDeck: Advancing Nano-drone Navigation with Low-power Ultrasound-based Obstacle Avoidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16696v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nano-drones, distinguished by their agility, minimal weight, and cost-effectiveness, are particularly well-suited for exploration in confined, cluttered and narrow spaces. Recognizing transparent, highly reflective or absorbing materials, such as glass and metallic surfaces is challenging, as classical sensors, such as cameras or laser rangers, often do not detect them. Inspired by bats, which can fly at high speeds in complete darkness with the help of ultrasound, this paper introduces \textit{BatDeck}, a pioneering sensor-deck employing a lightweight and low-power ultrasonic sensor for nano-drone autonomous navigation. This paper first provides insights about sensor characteristics, highlighting the influence of motor noise on the ultrasound readings, then it introduces the results of extensive experimental tests for obstacle avoidance (OA) in a diverse environment. Results show that \textit{BatDeck} allows exploration for a flight time of 8 minutes while covering 136m on average before crash in a challenging environment with transparent and reflective obstacles, proving the effectiveness of ultrasonic sensors for OA on nano-drones.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16696v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanna M\"uller, Victor Kartsch, Michele Magno, Luca Benini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Looking back and forward: A retrospective and future directions on Software Engineering for systems-of-systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16740v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Modern systems are increasingly connected and more integrated with other existing systems, giving rise to systems-of-systems (SoS). An SoS consists of a set of independent, heterogeneous systems that interact to provide new functionalities and accomplish global missions through emergent behavior manifested at runtime. The distinctive characteristics of SoS, when contrasted to traditional systems, pose significant research challenges within Software Engineering. These challenges motivate the need for a paradigm shift and the exploration of novel approaches for designing, developing, deploying, and evolving these systems. The International Workshop on Software Engineering for Systems-of-Systems (SESoS) series started in 2013 to fill a gap in scientific forums addressing SoS from the Software Engineering perspective, becoming the first venue for this purpose. This article presents a study aimed at outlining the evolution and future trajectory of Software Engineering for SoS based on the examination of 57 papers spanning the 11 editions of the SESoS workshop (2013-2023). The study combined scoping review and scientometric analysis methods to categorize and analyze the research contributions concerning temporal and geographic distribution, topics of interest, research methodologies employed, application domains, and research impact. Based on such a comprehensive overview, this article discusses current and future directions in Software Engineering for SoS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16740v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Everton Cavalcante, Thais Batista, Flavio Oquendo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DBPF: A Framework for Efficient and Robust Dynamic Bin-Picking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16786v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Efficiency and reliability are critical in robotic bin-picking as they directly impact the productivity of automated industrial processes. However, traditional approaches, demanding static objects and fixed collisions, lead to deployment limitations, operational inefficiencies, and process unreliability. This paper introduces a Dynamic Bin-Picking Framework (DBPF) that challenges traditional static assumptions. The DBPF endows the robot with the reactivity to pick multiple moving arbitrary objects while avoiding dynamic obstacles, such as the moving bin. Combined with scene-level pose generation, the proposed pose selection metric leverages the Tendency-Aware Manipulability Network optimizing suction pose determination. Heuristic task-specific designs like velocity-matching, dynamic obstacle avoidance, and the resight policy, enhance the picking success rate and reliability. Empirical experiments demonstrate the importance of these components. Our method achieves an average 84% success rate, surpassing the 60% of the most comparable baseline, crucially, with zero collisions. Further evaluations under diverse dynamic scenarios showcase DBPF's robust performance in dynamic bin-picking. Results suggest that our framework offers a promising solution for efficient and reliable robotic bin-picking under dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16786v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yichuan Li, Junkai Zhao, Yixiao Li, Zheng Wu, Rui Cao, Masayoshi Tomizuka, Yunhui Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Semi-Lagrangian Approach for Time and Energy Path Planning Optimization in Static Flow Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16859</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16859v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Efficient path planning for autonomous mobile robots is a critical problem across numerous domains, where optimizing both time and energy consumption is paramount. This paper introduces a novel methodology that considers the dynamic influence of an environmental flow field and considers geometric constraints, including obstacles and forbidden zones, enriching the complexity of the planning problem. We formulate it as a multi-objective optimal control problem, propose a novel transformation called Harmonic Transformation, and apply a semi-Lagrangian scheme to solve it. The set of Pareto efficient solutions is obtained considering two distinct approaches: a deterministic method and an evolutionary-based one, both of which are designed to make use of the proposed Harmonic Transformation. Through an extensive analysis of these approaches, we demonstrate their efficacy in finding optimized paths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16859v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V\'ictor C. da S. Campos, Armando A. Neto, Douglas G. Macharet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Methods for Trust in Collaborative Multi-Agent Autonomy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16956</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16956v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multi-agent, collaborative sensor fusion is a vital component of a multi-national intelligence toolkit. In safety-critical and/or contested environments, adversaries may infiltrate and compromise a number of agents. We analyze state of the art multi-target tracking algorithms under this compromised agent threat model. We prove that the track existence probability test ("track score") is significantly vulnerable to even small numbers of adversaries. To add security awareness, we design a trust estimation framework using hierarchical Bayesian updating. Our framework builds beliefs of trust on tracks and agents by mapping sensor measurements to trust pseudomeasurements (PSMs) and incorporating prior trust beliefs in a Bayesian context. In case studies, our trust estimation algorithm accurately estimates the trustworthiness of tracks/agents, subject to observability limitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16956v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Spencer Hallyburton, Miroslav Pajic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Optimal Solution to Infinite Horizon Nonlinear Control Problems: Part II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16979v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper considers the infinite horizon optimal control problem for nonlinear systems. Under the condition of nonlinear controllability of the system to any terminal set containing the origin and forward invariance of the terminal set, we establish a regularized solution approach consisting of a ``finite free final time" optimal transfer problem to the terminal set which renders the set globally asymptotically stable. Further, we show that the approximations converge to the optimal infinite horizon cost as the size of the terminal set decreases to zero. We also perform the analysis for the discounted problem and show that the terminal set is asymptotically stable only for a subset of the state space and not globally. The theory is empirically evaluated on various nonholonomic robotic systems to show that the cost of our approximate problem converges and the transfer time into the terminal set is dependent on the initial state of the system, necessitating the free final time formulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16979v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed Naveed Gul Mohamed, Aayushman Sharma, Raman Goyal, Suman Chakravorty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint Ranging and Phase Offset Estimation for Multiple Drones using ADS-B Signatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.05370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.05370v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A new method for joint ranging and Phase Offset (PO) estimation of multiple drones/aircrafts is proposed in this paper. The proposed method employs the superimposed uncoordinated Automatic Dependent Surveillance Broadcast (ADS-B) packets broadcasted by drones/aircrafts for joint range and PO estimation. It jointly estimates range and PO prior to ADS-B packet decoding; thus, it can improve air safety when packet decoding is infeasible due to packet collision. Moreover, it enables coherent detection of ADS-B packets, which can result in more reliable multiple target tracking in aviation systems using cooperative sensors for detect and avoid (DAA). By minimizing the Kullback Leibler Divergence (KLD) statistical distance measure, we show that the received complex baseband signal coming from K uncoordinated drones corrupted by Additive White Gaussian Noise (AWGN) at a single antenna receiver can be approximated by an independent and identically distributed Gaussian Mixture (GM) with 2 power K mixture components in the two dimensional (2D) plane. While direct joint Maximum Likelihood Estimation (MLE) of range and PO from the derived GM Probability Density Function (PDF) leads to an intractable maximization, our proposed method employs the Expectation Maximization (EM) algorithm to estimate the modes of the 2D Gaussian mixture followed by a reordering estimation technique through combinatorial optimization to estimate range and PO. An extension to a multiple antenna receiver is also investigated in this paper. While the proposed estimator can estimate the range of multiple drones with a single receive antenna, a larger number of drones can be supported with higher accuracy by the use of multiple antennas at the receiver. The effectiveness of the proposed estimator is supported by simulation results. We show that the proposed estimator can jointly estimate the range of three drones accurately.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.05370v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TVT.2023.3318192</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Transactions on Vehicular Technology, vol. 73, no. 2, pp. 1667-1681, Sept. 2023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mostafa Mohammadkarimi, Geert Leus, Raj Thilak Rajan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid path-lifting algorithm and Equivalence of Stability results for MRP-based control strategies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.01983</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.01983v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The modified Rodrigues parameters (MRP) consist of two numerically different triplets that, by switching between them, yield a minimal globally non-singular attitude description with advantageous properties. The MRP space results from the Alexandroff compactification of the three-dimensional Euclidean space and is a double cover of $\mathrm{SO(3)}$. By capitalizing on instrumental properties of the covering map, this paper proposes a novel hybrid dynamic path-lifting mechanism to unambiguously and robustly extract the MRP from the attitude space. This hybrid solution allows applying an MRP-based feedback controller to the attitude dynamics in the base space while preserving its asymptotic and exponential stability properties. Furthermore, by profiting from the distinct characteristics of the MRP, the resulting interconnection is impervious to the unwinding phenomenon. The design and validation of an MRP-based controller exemplify the application of the proposed algorithm alongside the novel results for equivalence of stability between spaces. The solution renders the attitude space tracking dynamics robustly globally exponentially stable, demonstrating the potential of this novel methodology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.01983v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lu\'is Martins, Carlos Cardeira, Paulo Oliveira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the impact of regularization in data-driven predictive control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.00263</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.00263v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Model predictive control (MPC) is a control strategy widely used in industrial applications. However, its implementation typically requires a mathematical model of the system being controlled, which can be a time-consuming and expensive task. Data-driven predictive control (DDPC) methods offer an alternative approach that does not require an explicit mathematical model, but instead optimize the control policy directly from data. In this paper, we study the impact of two different regularization penalties on the closed-loop performance of a recently introduced data-driven method called $\gamma$-DDPC. Moreover, we discuss the tuning of the related coefficients in different data and noise scenarios, to provide some guidelines for the end user.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.00263v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/CDC49753.2023.10383820</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>62nd IEEE Conference on Decision and Control, Dec. 13-15, 2023, Singapore</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Valentina Breschi, Alessandro Chiuso, Marco Fabris, Simone Formentin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchical Federated Learning in Wireless Networks: Pruning Tackles Bandwidth Scarcity and System Heterogeneity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.01562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.01562v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: While a practical wireless network has many tiers where end users do not directly communicate with the central server, the users' devices have limited computation and battery powers, and the serving base station (BS) has a fixed bandwidth. Owing to these practical constraints and system models, this paper leverages model pruning and proposes a pruning-enabled hierarchical federated learning (PHFL) in heterogeneous networks (HetNets). We first derive an upper bound of the convergence rate that clearly demonstrates the impact of the model pruning and wireless communications between the clients and the associated BS. Then we jointly optimize the model pruning ratio, central processing unit (CPU) frequency and transmission power of the clients in order to minimize the controllable terms of the convergence bound under strict delay and energy constraints. However, since the original problem is not convex, we perform successive convex approximation (SCA) and jointly optimize the parameters for the relaxed convex problem. Through extensive simulation, we validate the effectiveness of our proposed PHFL algorithm in terms of test accuracy, wall clock time, energy consumption and bandwidth requirement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.01562v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Md Ferdous Pervej, Richeng Jin, Huaiyu Dai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PowerSimulationsDynamics.jl -- An Open Source Modeling Package for Modern Power Systems with Inverter-Based Resources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.02921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.02921v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we present the development of an open-source simulation toolbox, PowerSimulationsDynamics.jl, to study the dynamic response of power systems, focusing on the requirements to model systems with high penetrations of Inverter-Based Resources (IBRs). PowerSimulationsDynamics.jl is implemented in Julia and features a rich library of synchronous generator, inverter, and load models. In addition, it allows the study of quasi-static phasors and electromagnetic dq models that use a dynamic network representation. Case studies and validation exercises show that PowerSimulationsDynamics.jl results closely match other commercial and open-source simulation tools.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.02921v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose Daniel Lara, Rodrigo Henriquez-Auba, Matthew Bossart, Duncan S. Callaway, Clayton Barrows</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Recursive Data-enabled Predictive Control (Extended Version)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.13755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.13755v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the field of model predictive control, Data-enabled Predictive Control (DeePC) offers direct predictive control, bypassing traditional modeling. However, challenges emerge with increased computational demand due to recursive data updates. This paper introduces a novel recursive updating algorithm for DeePC. It emphasizes the use of Singular Value Decomposition (SVD) for efficient low-dimensional transformations of DeePC in its general form, as well as a fast SVD update scheme. Importantly, our proposed algorithm is highly flexible due to its reliance on the general form of DeePC, which is demonstrated to encompass various data-driven methods that utilize Pseudoinverse and Hankel matrices. This is exemplified through a comparison to Subspace Predictive Control, where the algorithm achieves asymptotically consistent prediction for stochastic linear time-invariant systems. Our proposed methodologies' efficacy is validated through simulation studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.13755v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jicheng Shi, Yingzhao Lian, Colin N. Jones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Integral Consensus Control of Multi-Agent Networks Perturbed by Matched and Unmatched Disturbances: The Case of Directed Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.00262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.00262v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work presents a new method to design consensus controllers for perturbed double integrator systems whose interconnection is described by a directed graph containing a rooted spanning tree. We propose new robust controllers to solve the consensus and synchronization problems when the systems are under the effects of matched and unmatched disturbances. In both problems, we present simple continuous controllers, whose integral actions allow us to handle the disturbances. A rigorous stability analysis based on Lyapunov's direct method for unperturbed networked systems is presented. To assess the performance of our result, a representative simulation study is presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.00262v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose Guadalupe Romero, David Navarro-Alarcon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forced oscillation source localization from generator measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.00458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.00458v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Malfunctioning equipment, erroneous operating conditions or periodic load variations can cause periodic disturbances that would persist over time, creating an undesirable transfer of energy across the system -- an effect referred to as forced oscillations. Wide-area oscillations may damage assets, trigger inadvertent tripping or control actions, and be the cause of equipment failure. Unfortunately, for wide-area oscillations, the location, frequency, and amplitude of these forced oscillations may be hard to determine. Recently, a data-driven maximum-likelihood-based method was proposed to perform source localization in transmission grids under wide-area response scenarios. However, this method relies on full PMU coverage and all buses having inertia and damping. Here, we extend this method to realistic scenarios which includes buses without inertia or dumping, such as passive loads and inverter-based generators. Incorporating Kron reduction directly into the maximum likelihood estimator, we are able to identify the location and frequency of forcing applied at both traditional generators and loads.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.00458v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Melvyn Tyloo, Marc Vuffray, Andrey Y. Lokhov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-Varying Soft-Maximum Control Barrier Functions for Safety in an A Priori Unknown Environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.05261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.05261v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a time-varying soft-maximum composite control barrier function (CBF) that can be used to ensure safety in an a priori unknown environment, where local perception information regarding the safe set is periodically obtained. We consider the scenario where the periodically obtained perception feedback can be used to construct a local CBF that models a local subset of the unknown safe set. Then, we use a novel smooth time-varying soft-maximum function to compose the N most recently obtained local CBFs into a single CBF. This composite CBF models an approximate union of the N most recently obtained local subsets of the safe set. Notably, this composite CBF can have arbitrary relative degree r. Next, this composite CBF is used as a rth-order CBF constraint in a real-time optimization to determine a control that minimizes a quadratic cost while guaranteeing that the state stays in a time-varying subset of the unknown safe set. We also present an application of the time-varying soft-maximum composite CBF method to a nonholonomic ground robot with nonnegligible inertia. In this application, we present a simple approach to generate the local CBFs from the periodically obtained perception data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.05261v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amirsaeid Safari, Jesse B. Hoagg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-Optimal Control for High-Order Chain-of-Integrators Systems with Full State Constraints and Arbitrary Terminal States (Part I, Extended Version)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.07039</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.07039v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Time-optimal control for high-order chain-of-integrators systems with full state constraints and arbitrary given terminal states remains a challenging problem in the optimal control theory domain, yet to be resolved. To enhance further comprehension of the problem, this paper establishes a novel notation system and theoretical framework, providing the switching manifold for high-order problems in the form of switching laws. Through deriving properties of switching laws on signs and dimension, this paper proposes a definite condition for time-optimal control. Guided by the developed theory, a trajectory planning method named the manifold-intercept method (MIM) is developed. The proposed MIM can plan time-optimal jerk-limited trajectories with full state constraints, and can also plan near-optimal non-chattering higher-order trajectories with negligible extra motion time compared to optimal profiles. Numerical results indicate that the proposed MIM outperforms all baselines in computational time, computational accuracy, and trajectory quality by a large gap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.07039v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunan Wang, Chuxiong Hu, Zeyang Li, Shize Lin, Suqin He, Ze Wang, Yu Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermally-Resilient Soft Gripper for On-Orbit Operations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.08942</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.08942v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Research in soft manipulators has significantly enhanced object grasping capabilities, thanks to their adaptability to various shapes and sizes. Applying this technology to on-orbit servicing, especially during the capture and containment stages of active space debris removal missions, might offer a secure, adaptable, and cost-effective solution compared to the trend of increasing the degrees of freedom and complexity of the manipulator (e.g. ClearSpace, Astroscale). This work aims to conduct an experimental proof of concept, for which challenges such as radiation, vacuum, and microgravity are significant, but the predominant issue is ensuring effective operation in the extreme temperature swings, where flexible materials may exhibit cryogenic crystallization or drastic shifts in their elasticity. This work addresses this challenge through an initial stage of analytical modeling of the thermal dynamics inside the manipulator in orbit; which is then used for the development of a first experimental prototype tested with liquid nitrogen and heat guns. The multi-layered design for Low Earth Orbit (LEO) leverages the properties of TPU at low infill rates for lightweight inherent flexibility, silicone rubber ensuring structural integrity, PTFE (Teflon) for unparalleled thermal stability, and aerogel for insulation. The tendon-actuated servo-driven gripper is tested in the laboratory by varying the shape and size of objects during the grasping. The results, based on servomotor force metrics to assess the flexible manipulator's adaptability and object capture efficiency across temperature changes, affirm the concept's viability. Forces increase up to 220$\%$ in cryogenic conditions and decrease by no more than 50$\%$ at high temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.08942v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Ruiz, Begona Arrue, Anibal Ollero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synthesis of Temporally-Robust Policies for Signal Temporal Logic Tasks using Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.05764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.05764v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates the problem of designing control policies that satisfy high-level specifications described by signal temporal logic (STL) in unknown, stochastic environments. While many existing works concentrate on optimizing the spatial robustness of a system, our work takes a step further by also considering temporal robustness as a critical metric to quantify the tolerance of time uncertainty in STL. To this end, we formulate two relevant control objectives to enhance the temporal robustness of the synthesized policies. The first objective is to maximize the probability of being temporally robust for a given threshold. The second objective is to maximize the worst-case spatial robustness value within a bounded time shift. We use reinforcement learning to solve both control synthesis problems for unknown systems. Specifically, we approximate both control objectives in a way that enables us to apply the standard Q-learning algorithm. Theoretical bounds in terms of the approximations are also derived. We present case studies to demonstrate the feasibility of our approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.05764v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siqi Wang, Shaoyuan Li, Li Yin, Xiang Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid physics-informed metabolic cybergenetics: process rates augmented with machine-learning surrogates informed by flux balance analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.00670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.00670v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Metabolic cybergenetics is a promising concept that interfaces gene expression and cellular metabolism with computers for real-time dynamic metabolic control. The focus is on control at the transcriptional level, serving as a means to modulate intracellular metabolic fluxes. Recent strategies in this field have employed constraint-based dynamic models for process optimization, control, and estimation. However, this results in bilevel dynamic optimization problems, which pose considerable numerical and conceptual challenges. In this study, we present an alternative hybrid physics-informed dynamic modeling framework for metabolic cybergenetics, aimed at simplifying optimization, control, and estimation tasks. By utilizing machine-learning surrogates, our approach effectively embeds the physics of metabolic networks into the process rates of structurally simpler macro-kinetic models coupled with gene expression. These surrogates, informed by flux balance analysis, link the domains of manipulatable intracellular enzymes to metabolic exchange fluxes. This ensures that critical knowledge captured by the system's metabolic network is preserved. The resulting models can be integrated into metabolic cybergenetic schemes involving single-level optimizations. Additionally, the hybrid modeling approach maintains the number of system states at a necessary minimum, easing the burden of process monitoring and estimation. Our hybrid physics-informed metabolic cybergenetic framework is demonstrated using a computational case study on the optogenetically-assisted production of itaconate by $\textit{Escherichia coli}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.00670v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebasti\'an Espinel-R\'ios, Jos\'e L. Avalos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secure Control of Connected and Automated Vehicles Using Trust-Aware Robust Event-Triggered Control Barrier Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.02306</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.02306v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We address the security of a network of Connected and Automated Vehicles (CAVs) cooperating to safely navigate through a conflict area (e.g., traffic intersections, merging roadways, roundabouts). Previous studies have shown that such a network can be targeted by adversarial attacks causing traffic jams or safety violations ending in collisions. We focus on attacks targeting the V2X communication network used to share vehicle data and consider as well uncertainties due to noise in sensor measurements and communication channels. To combat these, motivated by recent work on the safe control of CAVs, we propose a trust-aware robust event-triggered decentralized control and coordination framework that can provably guarantee safety. We maintain a trust metric for each vehicle in the network computed based on their behavior and used to balance the tradeoff between conservativeness (when deeming every vehicle as untrustworthy) and guaranteed safety and security. It is important to highlight that our framework is invariant to the specific choice of the trust framework. Based on this framework, we propose an attack detection and mitigation scheme which has twofold benefits: (i) the trust framework is immune to false positives, and (ii) it provably guarantees safety against false positive cases. We use extensive simulations (in SUMO and CARLA) to validate the theoretical guarantees and demonstrate the efficacy of our proposed scheme to detect and mitigate adversarial attacks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.02306v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H M Sabbir Ahmad, Ehsan Sabouni, Akua Dickson, Wei Xiao, Christos G. Cassandras, Wenchao Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Concurrent Learning of Policy and Unknown Safety Constraints in Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.15893</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.15893v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Reinforcement learning (RL) has revolutionized decision-making across a wide range of domains over the past few decades. Yet, deploying RL policies in real-world scenarios presents the crucial challenge of ensuring safety. Traditional safe RL approaches have predominantly focused on incorporating predefined safety constraints into the policy learning process. However, this reliance on predefined safety constraints poses limitations in dynamic and unpredictable real-world settings where such constraints may not be available or sufficiently adaptable. Bridging this gap, we propose a novel approach that concurrently learns a safe RL control policy and identifies the unknown safety constraint parameters of a given environment. Initializing with a parametric signal temporal logic (pSTL) safety specification and a small initial labeled dataset, we frame the problem as a bilevel optimization task, intricately integrating constrained policy optimization, using a Lagrangian-variant of the twin delayed deep deterministic policy gradient (TD3) algorithm, with Bayesian optimization for optimizing parameters for the given pSTL safety specification. Through experimentation in comprehensive case studies, we validate the efficacy of this approach across varying forms of environmental constraints, consistently yielding safe RL policies with high returns. Furthermore, our findings indicate successful learning of STL safety constraint parameters, exhibiting a high degree of conformity with true environmental safety constraints. The performance of our model closely mirrors that of an ideal scenario that possesses complete prior knowledge of safety constraints, demonstrating its proficiency in accurately identifying environmental safety constraints and learning safe policies that adhere to those constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.15893v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lunet Yifru, Ali Baheri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Feedback Control for Global and Optimal Safe Navigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.17038v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a hybrid feedback control strategy that safely steers a point-mass robot to a target location optimally from all initial conditions in the n-dimensional Euclidean space with a single spherical obstacle. The robot moves straight to the target when it has a clear line-of-sight to the target location. Otherwise, it engages in an optimal obstacle avoidance maneuver via the shortest path inside the cone enclosing the obstacle and having the robot's position as a vertex. The switching strategy that avoids the undesired equilibria, leading to global asymptotic stability (GAS) of the target location, relies on using two appropriately designed virtual destinations, ensuring control continuity and shortest path generation. Simulation results illustrating the effectiveness of the proposed approach are presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.17038v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ishak Cheniouni, Soulaimane Berkane, Abdelhamid Tayebi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topology Data Analysis-based Error Detection for Semantic Image Transmission with Incremental Knowledge-based HARQ</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11542</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11542v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Semantic communication (SemCom) aims to achieve high fidelity information delivery under low communication consumption by only guaranteeing semantic accuracy. Nevertheless, semantic communication still suffers from unexpected channel volatility and thus developing a re-transmission mechanism (e.g., hybrid automatic repeat request [HARQ]) is indispensable. In that regard, instead of discarding previously transmitted information, the incremental knowledge-based HARQ (IK-HARQ) is deemed as a more effective mechanism that could sufficiently utilize the information semantics. However, considering the possible existence of semantic ambiguity in image transmission, a simple bit-level cyclic redundancy check (CRC) might compromise the performance of IK-HARQ. Therefore, it emerges a strong incentive to revolutionize the CRC mechanism, so as to reap the benefits of both SemCom and HARQ. In this paper, built on top of swin transformer-based joint source-channel coding (JSCC) and IK-HARQ, we propose a semantic image transmission framework SC-TDA-HARQ. In particular, different from the conventional CRC, we introduce a topological data analysis (TDA)-based error detection method, which capably digs out the inner topological and geometric information of images, so as to capture semantic information and determine the necessity for re-transmission. Extensive numerical results validate the effectiveness and efficiency of the proposed SC-TDA-HARQ framework, especially under the limited bandwidth condition, and manifest the superiority of TDA-based error detection method in image transmission.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11542v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fei Ni, Rongpeng Li, Zhifeng Zhao, Honggang Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D Directed Formation Control with Global Shape Convergence using Bispherical Coordinates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13609</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13609v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a novel 3D formation control scheme for directed graphs in a leader-follower configuration, achieving (almost) global convergence to the desired shape. Specifically, we introduce three controlled variables representing bispherical coordinates that uniquely describe the formation in 3D. Acyclic triangulated directed graphs (a class of minimally acyclic persistent graphs) are used to model the inter-agent sensing topology, while the agents' dynamics are governed by single-integrator model. Our analysis demonstrates that the proposed decentralized formation controller ensures (almost) global asymptotic stability while avoiding potential shape ambiguities in the final formation. Furthermore, the control laws are implementable in arbitrarily oriented local coordinate frames of follower agents using only low-cost onboard vision sensors, making it suitable for practical applications. Finally, we validate our formation control approach by a simulation study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13609v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Omid Mirzaeedodangeh, Farhad Mehdifar, Dimos V. Dimarogonas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Credit vs. Discount-Based Congestion Pricing: A Comparison Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13923v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Tolling, or congestion pricing, offers a promising traffic management policy for regulating congestion, but has also attracted criticism for placing outsized financial burdens on low-income users. Credit-based congestion pricing (CBCP) and discount-based congestion pricing (DBCP) policies, which respectively provide travel credits and toll discounts to low-income users on tolled roads, have emerged as promising mechanisms for reducing traffic congestion without worsening societal inequities. However, the optimal design of CBCP and DBCP policies, as well as their relative advantages and disadvantages, remain poorly understood. To address this, we study the effects of implementing CBCP and DBCP policies to route users on a network of multi-lane highways with tolled express lanes. We formulate a non-atomic routing game framework in which a subset of eligible users is granted toll relief in the form of a fixed budget or toll discount, while the remaining ineligible users must pay out-of-pocket. We prove the existence of Nash equilibrium traffic flow patterns corresponding to any given CBCP or DBCP policy. Under the additional assumption that eligible users have time-invariant VoTs, we provide a convex program to efficiently compute these equilibria. For networks consisting of a single edge, we identify conditions under which CBCP policies outperform DBCP policies (and vice versa), in the sense of improving eligible users' access to the express lane. Finally, we present empirical results from a CBCP pilot study of the San Mateo 101 Express Lane Project in California. Our empirical results corroborate our theoretical analysis of the impact of deploying credit-based and discount-based policies, and lend insights into the sensitivity of their impact with respect to the travel demand and users' VoTs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13923v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chih-Yuan Chiu, Devansh Jalota, Marco Pavone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance-Guaranteed Solutions for Multi-Agent Optimal Coverage Problems using Submodularity, Curvature, and Greedy Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14028v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a class of multi-agent optimal coverage problems in which the goal is to determine the optimal placement of a group of agents in a given mission space so that they maximize a coverage objective that represents a blend of individual and collaborative event detection capabilities. This class of problems is extremely challenging due to the non-convex nature of the mission space and of the coverage objective. With this motivation, greedy algorithms are often used as means of getting feasible coverage solutions efficiently. Even though such greedy solutions are suboptimal, the submodularity (diminishing returns) property of the coverage objective can be exploited to provide performance bound guarantees. Moreover, we show that improved performance bound guarantees (beyond the standard (1-1/e) performance bound) can be established using various curvature measures of the coverage problem. In particular, we provide a brief review of all existing popular applicable curvature measures, including a recent curvature measure that we proposed, and discuss their effectiveness and computational complexity, in the context of optimal coverage problems. We also propose novel computationally efficient techniques to estimate some curvature measures. Finally, we provide several numerical results to support our findings and propose several potential future research directions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14028v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shirantha Welikala, Christos G. Cassandras</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decentralized Multi-Armed Bandit Can Outperform Classic Upper Confidence Bound: A Homogeneous Case over Strongly Connected Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.10933</link>
      <description>arXiv:2111.10933v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper studies a homogeneous decentralized multi-armed bandit problem, in which a network of multiple agents faces the same set of arms, and each agent aims to minimize its own regret. A fully decentralized upper confidence bound (UCB) algorithm is proposed for a multi-agent network whose neighbor relations are described by a directed graph. It is shown that the decentralized algorithm guarantees each agent to achieve a lower logarithmic asymptotic regret compared to the classic UCB algorithm, provided the neighbor graph is strongly connected. The improved asymptotic regret upper bound is reciprocally related to the maximal size of a local neighborhood within the network. The roles of graph connectivity, maximum local degree, and network size are analytically elucidated in the expression of regret.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2111.10933v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingxuan Zhu, Ji Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A cGAN Ensemble-based Uncertainty-aware Surrogate Model for Offline Model-based Optimization in Industrial Control Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.07250</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.07250v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study focuses on two important problems related to applying offline model-based optimization to real-world industrial control problems. The first problem is how to create a reliable probabilistic model that accurately captures the dynamics present in noisy industrial data. The second problem is how to reliably optimize control parameters without actively collecting feedback from industrial systems. Specifically, we introduce a novel cGAN ensemble-based uncertainty-aware surrogate model for reliable offline model-based optimization in industrial control problems. The effectiveness of the proposed method is demonstrated through extensive experiments conducted on two representative cases, namely a discrete control case and a continuous control case. The results of these experiments show that our method outperforms several competitive baselines in the field of offline model-based optimization for industrial control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.07250v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identification of Energy Management Configuration Concepts from a Set of Pareto-optimal Solutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.08318</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.08318v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Implementing resource efficient energy management systems in facilities and buildings becomes increasingly important in the transformation to a sustainable society. However, selecting a suitable configuration based on multiple, typically conflicting objectives, such as cost, robustness with respect to uncertainty of grid operation, or renewable energy utilization, is a difficult multi-criteria decision making problem. The recently developed concept identification technique can facilitate a decision maker by sorting configuration options into semantically meaningful groups (concepts). In this process, the partitioning of the objectives and design parameters into different sets (called description spaces) is a very important step. In this study we focus on utilizing the concept identification technique for finding relevant and viable energy management configurations from a very large data set of Pareto-optimal solutions. The data set consists of 20000 realistic Pareto-optimal building energy management configurations generated by a many-objective evolutionary optimization of a high quality Digital Twin energy management simulator. We analyze how the choice of description spaces, i.e., the partitioning of the objectives and parameters, impacts the type of information that can be extracted. We show that the decision maker can introduce constraints and biases into that process to meet expectations and preferences. The iterative approach presented in this work allows for the generation of valuable insights into trade-offs between specific objectives, and constitutes a powerful and flexible tool to support the decision making process when designing large and complex energy management systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.08318v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felix Lanfermann, Qiqi Liu, Yaochu Jin, Sebastian Schmitt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Complex Motion Plans using Neural ODEs with Safety and Stability Guarantees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.00186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.00186v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a Dynamical System (DS) approach to learn complex, possibly periodic motion plans from kinesthetic demonstrations using Neural Ordinary Differential Equations (NODE). To ensure reactivity and robustness to disturbances, we propose a novel approach that selects a target point at each time step for the robot to follow, by combining tools from control theory and the target trajectory generated by the learned NODE. A correction term to the NODE model is computed online by solving a quadratic program that guarantees stability and safety using control Lyapunov functions and control barrier functions, respectively. Our approach outperforms baseline DS learning techniques on the LASA handwriting dataset and complex periodic trajectories. It is also validated on the Franka Emika robot arm to produce stable motions for wiping and stirring tasks that do not have a single attractor, while being robust to perturbations and safe around humans and obstacles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.00186v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Farhad Nawaz, Tianyu Li, Nikolai Matni, Nadia Figueroa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Directionality-Aware Mixture Model Parallel Sampling for Efficient Linear Parameter Varying Dynamical System Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.02609</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.02609v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Linear Parameter Varying Dynamical System (LPV-DS) is an effective approach that learns stable, time-invariant motion policies using statistical modeling and semi-definite optimization to encode complex motions for reactive robot control. Despite its strengths, the LPV-DS learning approach faces challenges in achieving a high model accuracy without compromising the computational efficiency. To address this, we introduce the Directionality-Aware Mixture Model (DAMM), a novel statistical model that applies the Riemannian metric on the n-sphere $\mathbb{S}^n$ to efficiently blend non-Euclidean directional data with $\mathbb{R}^m$ Euclidean states. Additionally, we develop a hybrid Markov chain Monte Carlo technique that combines Gibbs Sampling with Split/Merge Proposal, allowing for parallel computation to drastically speed up inference. Our extensive empirical tests demonstrate that LPV-DS integrated with DAMM achieves higher reproduction accuracy, better model efficiency, and near real-time/online learning compared to standard estimation methods on various datasets. Lastly, we demonstrate its suitability for incrementally learning multi-behavior policies in real-world robot experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.02609v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sunan Sun, Haihui Gao, Tianyu Li, Nadia Figueroa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Traffic Management Framework for On-Demand Urban Air Mobility Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.07139</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.07139v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Urban Air Mobility (UAM) offers a solution to current traffic congestion by providing on-demand air mobility in urban areas. Effective traffic management is crucial for efficient operation of UAM systems, especially for high-demand scenarios. In this paper, we present a centralized traffic management framework for on-demand UAM systems. Specifically, we provide a scheduling policy, called VertiSync, which schedules the aircraft for either servicing trip requests or rebalancing in the system subject to aircraft safety margins and energy requirements. We characterize the system-level throughput of VertiSync, which determines the demand threshold at which passenger waiting times transition from being stabilized to being increasing over time. We show that the proposed policy is able to maximize throughput for sufficiently large fleet sizes. We demonstrate the performance of VertiSync through a case study for the city of Los Angeles, and show that it significantly reduces passenger waiting times compared to a first-come first-serve scheduling policy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.07139v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Milad Pooladsanj, Ketan Savla, Petros A. Ioannou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Peak Estimation of Rational Systems using Convex Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.08321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.08321v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper presents algorithms that upper-bound the peak value of a state function along trajectories of a continuous-time system with rational dynamics. The finite-dimensional but nonconvex peak estimation problem is cast as a convex infinite-dimensional linear program in occupation measures. This infinite-dimensional program is then truncated into finite-dimensions using the moment-Sum-of-Squares (SOS) hierarchy of semidefinite programs. Prior work on treating rational dynamics using the moment-SOS approach involves clearing dynamics to common denominators or adding lifting variables to handle reciprocal terms under new equality constraints. Our solution method uses a sum-of-rational method based on absolute continuity of measures. The Moment-SOS truncations of our program possess lower computational complexity and (empirically demonstrated) higher accuracy of upper bounds on example systems as compared to prior approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.08321v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jared Miller, Roy S. Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stable Reduced-Rank VAR Identification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00237v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The vector autoregression (VAR) has been widely used in system identification, econometrics, natural science, and many other areas. However, when the state dimension becomes large the parameter dimension explodes. So rank reduced modelling is attractive and is well developed. But a fundamental requirement in almost all applications is stability of the fitted model. And this has not been addressed in the rank reduced case. Here, we develop, for the first time, a closed-form formula for an estimator of a rank reduced transition matrix which is guaranteed to be stable. We show that our estimator is consistent and asymptotically statistically efficient and illustrate it in comparative simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00237v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinhui Rong, Victor Solo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Carbon Footprint Reduction for Sustainable Data Centers in Real-Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14092</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14092v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: As machine learning workloads significantly increase energy consumption, sustainable data centers with low carbon emissions are becoming a top priority for governments and corporations worldwide. This requires a paradigm shift in optimizing power consumption in cooling and IT loads, shifting flexible loads based on the availability of renewable energy in the power grid, and leveraging battery storage from the uninterrupted power supply in data centers, using collaborative agents. The complex association between these optimization strategies and their dependencies on variable external factors like weather and the power grid carbon intensity makes this a hard problem. Currently, a real-time controller to optimize all these goals simultaneously in a dynamic real-world setting is lacking. We propose a Data Center Carbon Footprint Reduction (DC-CFR) multi-agent Reinforcement Learning (MARL) framework that optimizes data centers for the multiple objectives of carbon footprint reduction, energy consumption, and energy cost. The results show that the DC-CFR MARL agents effectively resolved the complex interdependencies in optimizing cooling, load shifting, and energy storage in real-time for various locations under real-world dynamic weather and grid carbon intensity conditions. DC-CFR significantly outperformed the industry standard ASHRAE controller with a considerable reduction in carbon emissions (14.5%), energy usage (14.4%), and energy cost (13.7%) when evaluated over one year across multiple geographical regions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14092v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2024 Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Soumyendu Sarkar, Avisek Naug, Ricardo Luna, Antonio Guillen, Vineet Gundecha, Sahand Ghorbanpour, Sajad Mousavi, Dejan Markovikj, Ashwin Ramesh Babu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
