<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SY updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SY</link>
    <description>cs.SY updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SY" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 05:01:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Data-Driven Approach for Accelerating Selective Harmonic Elimination Algorithm in Parallel Power Converters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03626v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Current ripple minimization is one of the challenges in parallel converters to increase the capacitor lifetime in various applications. In this paper, a deep neural network-based phase-shifting (PS) technique is proposed for parallel-connected buck converters to minimize the amplitude of a selective harmonic component and facilitate a classic optimum PS at the same time. The proposed method identifies the global optimum point in real time, without the need for complicated computations. The common-link current, common-link voltage, and the duty ratios are selected as the inputs of the neural network to provide the proper phase shifts for the switching signals. To accumulate the required dataset, a Different Start-Same Step (DSSS) technique is also introduced to generate the training data and test/validation data in a separate way. The effect of the number of hidden layers on the network output error is investigated, and a proper number of hidden layers is designed based on a compromise between accuracy and computation efficiency (and execution time). Experimental results prove that the proposed artificial neural network-based PS method preserves the performance of classic optimum PS and minimizing the implementation time significantly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03626v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Karimi, S. Shahnooshi, E. Meshkati, T. Dragi\v{c}evi\'c, F. Blaabjerg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rectified Control Barrier Functions for High-Order Safety Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03708v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel approach for synthesizing control barrier functions (CBFs) from high relative degree safety constraints: Rectified CBFs (ReCBFs). We begin by discussing the limitations of existing High-Order CBF approaches and how these can be overcome by incorporating an activation function into the CBF construction. We then provide a comparative analysis of our approach with related methods, such as CBF backstepping. Our results are presented first for safety constraints with relative degree two, then for mixed-input relative degree constraints, and finally for higher relative degrees. The theoretical developments are illustrated through simple running examples and an aircraft control problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03708v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pio Ong, Max H. Cohen, Tamas G. Molnar, Aaron D. Ames</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CIKAN: Constraint Informed Kolmogorov-Arnold Networks for Autonomous Spacecraft Rendezvous using Time Shift Governor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03710v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The paper considers a Constrained-Informed Neural Network (CINN) approximation for the Time Shift Governor (TSG), which is an add-on scheme to the nominal closed-loop system used to enforce constraints by time-shifting the reference trajectory in spacecraft rendezvous applications. We incorporate Kolmogorov-Arnold Networks (KANs), an emerging architecture in the AI community, as a fundamental component of CINN and propose a Constrained-Informed Kolmogorov-Arnold Network (CIKAN)-based approximation for TSG. We demonstrate the effectiveness of the CIKAN-based TSG through simulations of constrained spacecraft rendezvous missions on highly elliptic orbits and present comparisons between CIKANs, MLP-based CINNs, and the conventional TSG.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03710v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taehyeun Kim, Anouck Girard, Ilya Kolmanovsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Spatial Resolution Transmission and Storage Expansion Planning for High Renewable Grids: A Case Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03799</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03799v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Transmission Expansion Planning (TEP) is the process of optimizing the development and upgrade of the power grid to ensure reliable, efficient, and cost-effective electricity delivery while addressing grid constraints. To support growing demand and renewable energy integration, energy storage is emerging as a pivotal asset that provides temporal flexibility and alleviates congestion. This paper presents a TEP model that incorporates the sizing and siting of short-duration storage. With a focus on high spatial resolution, the model is applied to a 2,000-bus synthetic Texas power system, offering detailed insights into geographic investment and operational patterns. To maintain computational feasibility, a simple yet effective storage candidates (SC) method is introduced, significantly reducing the search space. Results highlight that transmission investments are primarily driven by renewable energy expansion, while storage investments are shaped by renewable curtailment and load-shedding events, with their primary function being peak load shaving. The findings underscore the importance of co-optimizing transmission and storage to minimize costs and enhance grid reliability. However, limitations in the ability of the SC method to identify optimal storage locations to meet long-term needs suggest opportunities for future research, including dynamic candidate selection and hybrid optimization techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03799v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Wu, Rabab Haider, Pascal Van Hentenryck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Abstraction-based Control of Unknown Continuous-Space Models with Just Two Trajectories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03892v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Finite abstractions (a.k.a. symbolic models) offer an effective scheme for approximating the complex continuous-space systems with simpler models in the discrete-space domain. A crucial aspect, however, is to establish a formal relation between the original system and its symbolic model, ensuring that a discrete controller designed for the symbolic model can be effectively implemented as a hybrid controller (using an interface map) for the original system. This task becomes even more challenging when the exact mathematical model of the continuous-space system is unknown. To address this, the existing literature mainly employs scenario-based data-driven methods, which require collecting a large amount of data from the original system. In this work, we propose a data-driven framework that utilizes only two input-state trajectories collected from unknown nonlinear polynomial systems to synthesize a hybrid controller, enabling the desired behavior on the unknown system through the controller derived from its symbolic model. To accomplish this, we employ the concept of alternating simulation functions (ASFs) to quantify the closeness between the state trajectories of the unknown system and its data-driven symbolic model. By satisfying a specific rank condition on the collected data, which intuitively ensures that the unknown system is persistently excited, we directly design an ASF and its corresponding hybrid controller using finite-length data without explicitly identifying the unknown system, while providing correctness guarantees. This is achieved through proposing a data-based sum-of-squares (SOS) optimization program, enabling a systematic approach to the design process. We illustrate the effectiveness of our data-driven approach through a case study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03892v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Behrad Samari, Mahdieh Zaker, Abolfazl Lavaei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Certified Learning of Incremental ISS Controllers for Unknown Nonlinear Polynomial Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03901</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03901v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Incremental input-to-state stability (delta-ISS) offers a robust framework to ensure that small input variations result in proportionally minor deviations in the state of a nonlinear system. This property is essential in practical applications where input precision cannot be guaranteed. However, analyzing delta-ISS demands detailed knowledge of system dynamics to assess the state's incremental response to input changes, posing a challenge in real-world scenarios where mathematical models are unknown. In this work, we develop a data-driven approach to design delta-ISS Lyapunov functions together with their corresponding delta-ISS controllers for continuous-time input-affine nonlinear systems with polynomial dynamics, ensuring the delta-ISS property is achieved without requiring knowledge of the system dynamics. In our data-driven scheme, we collect only two sets of input-state trajectories from sufficiently excited dynamics, as introduced by Willems et al.'s fundamental lemma. By fulfilling a specific rank condition, we design delta-ISS controllers using the collected samples through formulating a sum-of-squares optimization program. The effectiveness of our data-driven approach is evidenced by its application on a physical case study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03901v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahdieh Zaker, David Angeli, Abolfazl Lavaei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Robust Safety Controllers for Uncertain Input-Affine Polynomial Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03919v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper offers a direct data-driven approach for learning robust control barrier certificates (R-CBCs) and robust safety controllers (R-SCs) for discrete-time input-affine polynomial systems with unknown dynamics under unknown-but-bounded disturbances. The proposed method relies on data from input-state observations collected over a finite-time horizon while satisfying a specific rank condition to ensure the system is persistently excited. Our data-driven scheme enables the synthesis of R-CBCs and R-SCs directly from observed data, bypassing the need for explicit modeling of the system's dynamics and thus ensuring robust system safety against disturbances within a finite time horizon. Our proposed approach is formulated as a sum-of-squares (SOS) optimization problem, providing a structured design framework. Two case studies showcase our method's capability to provide robust safety guarantees for unknown input-affine polynomial systems under bounded disturbances, demonstrating its practical effectiveness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03919v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Omid Akbarzadeh, Abolfazl Lavaei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Traffic Co-Simulation Framework Empowered by Infrastructure Camera Sensing and Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03925</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03925v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Traffic simulations are commonly used to optimize traffic flow, with reinforcement learning (RL) showing promising potential for automated traffic signal control. Multi-agent reinforcement learning (MARL) is particularly effective for learning control strategies for traffic lights in a network using iterative simulations. However, existing methods often assume perfect vehicle detection, which overlooks real-world limitations related to infrastructure availability and sensor reliability. This study proposes a co-simulation framework integrating CARLA and SUMO, which combines high-fidelity 3D modeling with large-scale traffic flow simulation. Cameras mounted on traffic light poles within the CARLA environment use a YOLO-based computer vision system to detect and count vehicles, providing real-time traffic data as input for adaptive signal control in SUMO. MARL agents, trained with four different reward structures, leverage this visual feedback to optimize signal timings and improve network-wide traffic flow. Experiments in the test-bed demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed MARL approach in enhancing traffic conditions using real-time camera-based detection. The framework also evaluates the robustness of MARL under faulty or sparse sensing and compares the performance of YOLOv5 and YOLOv8 for vehicle detection. Results show that while better accuracy improves performance, MARL agents can still achieve significant improvements with imperfect detection, demonstrating adaptability for real-world scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03925v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Talha Azfar, Ruimin Ke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Physics-Informed Scenario Approach with Data Mitigation for Safety Verification of Nonlinear Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03932</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03932v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper develops a physics-informed scenario approach for safety verification of nonlinear systems using barrier certificates (BCs) to ensure that system trajectories remain within safe regions over an infinite time horizon. Designing BCs often relies on an accurate dynamics model; however, such models are often imprecise due to the model complexity involved, particularly when dealing with highly nonlinear systems. In such cases, while scenario approaches effectively address the safety problem using collected data to construct a guaranteed BC for the dynamical system, they often require substantial amounts of data-sometimes millions of samples-due to exponential sample complexity. To address this, we propose a physics-informed scenario approach that selects data samples such that the outputs of the physics-based model and the observed data are sufficiently close (within a specified threshold). This approach guides the scenario optimization process to eliminate redundant samples and significantly reduce the required dataset size. We demonstrate the capability of our approach in mitigating the amount of data required for scenario optimizations with both deterministic (i.e., confidence 1) and probabilistic (i.e., confidence between 0 and 1) guarantees. We validate our physics-informed scenario approach through two physical case studies, showcasing its practical application in reducing the required data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03932v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Aminzadeh, MohammadHossein Ashoori, Amy Nejati, Abolfazl Lavaei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semi-automated transmission control for motorcycle gearshift: design, data-driven tuning and experimental validation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03989</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03989v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This brief addresses the gearshifting problem for Semi-Automated Manual Transmissions (S-AMT) in powered two-wheelers, a powertrain setup that allows fast and smooth gear shifts with minimal modifications to the traditional manual powertrain layout. We show that with a proper synchronization between the electronic clutch and engine torque, excellent gearshift performance can be obtained, but requires precise parameters calibration. We thus propose the use of a data-driven approach with Constrained Bayesian Optimization to optimize control parameters. The procedure's effectiveness is demonstrated on a real vehicle, assessing performance in terms of optimality, convergence rate, and repeatability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03989v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Edoardo Catenaro, Giulio Panzani, Davide Sette, Sergio M. Savaresi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal demand response policies for inertial thermal loads under stochastic renewable sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04054</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04054v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the problem of preferentially utilizing intermittent renewable power, such as wind, optimally to support thermal inertial loads in a microgrid environment. Thermal inertial loads can be programmed to preferentially consume from renewable sources. The flexibility in power consumption of inertial loads therefore can be used to absorb the fluctuations in intermittently available renewable power sources, and promote reduction of fossil fuel based costly non-renewable generation. Under a model which promotes renewable consumption by penalizing the non-renewable, but does not account for variations in the end-user requirements, the optimal solution leads to all the users' temperatures behave in a lockstep fashion, that is the power is allocated in such a fashion that all the temperatures are brought to a common value and they are kept the same after that point, resulting in synchronization among all the loads. In the first part, we showed that under a model which additionally penalizes the comfort range violation, the optimal solution is in-fact of desynchronization nature, where the temperatures are intentionally kept apart to avoid power surges resulting from simultaneous comfort violation from many loads.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04054v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaurav Sharma, P R Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Fast and Safety-Guaranteed Trajectory Planning and Tracking for Time-Varying Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04129v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When deploying autonomous systems in unknown and changing environments, it is critical that their motion planning and control algorithms are computationally efficient and can be reapplied online in real time, whilst providing theoretical safety guarantees in the presence of disturbances. The satisfaction of these objectives becomes more challenging when considering time-varying dynamics and disturbances, which arise in real-world contexts. We develop methods with the potential to address these issues by applying an offline-computed safety guaranteeing controller on a physical system, to track a virtual system that evolves through a trajectory that is replanned online, accounting for constraints updated online. The first method we propose is designed for general time-varying systems over a finite horizon. Our second method overcomes the finite horizon restriction for periodic systems. We simulate our algorithms on a case study of an autonomous underwater vehicle subject to wave disturbances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04129v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seth Siriya, Mo Chen, Ye Pu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decentralized Dynamic Event-triggered Output-feedback Control of Stochastic Non-triangular Interconnected Systems with Unknown Time-varying Sensor Sensitivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04131v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study addresses the intricate challenge of decentralized output-feedback control for stochastic non-triangular nonlinear interconnected systems with unknown time-varying sensor sensitivity in a dynamic event-triggered context. The presence of stochastic disturbances, non-triangular structural uncertainties, and evolving sensor sensitivity distinguishes this problem of global asymptotic stability from conventional event-triggered control scenarios. Existing event-triggered control approaches with static event conditions encounter difficulties in simultaneously ensuring zero tracking/stabilization error and preventing the occurrence of Zeno behavior. In this work, we develop a novel solution to address this complex issue. Firstly, we establish a linear relationship between the state vector of each interconnected subsystem and two error vectors through a unique coordinate transformation. This transformation effectively handles the complexities introduced by non-triangular structural uncertainties. Secondly, we introduce a decentralized dynamic event-triggered output-feedback control strategy, which involves a state observer and a decentralized output-feedback controller. Unlike conventional event-triggered control methods with static event conditions, this strategy formulates a modified clock-based dynamic triggering mechanism by introducing an auxiliary variable that evolves based on predicted plant state values, while utilizing a clock variable to guarantee the existence of a positive lower bound on inter-execution times. Rigorous Lyapunov analysis confirms the global asymptotic stability in probability of the closed-loop system, with the states and the output of each local subsystem converging to the equilibrium at the origin in probability. Additionally, the existence of a minimal dwell-time between triggering instants is guaranteed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04131v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TAC.2024.3508547</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Libei Sun, Yongduan Song, Maolong Lv</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Asymptotic Bounds for Closed-Loop Identification of Unstable Nonlinear Stochastic Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04157</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04157v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the problem of least squares parameter estimation from single-trajectory data for discrete-time, unstable, closed-loop nonlinear stochastic systems, with linearly parameterised uncertainty. Assuming a region of the state space produces informative data, and the system is sub-exponentially unstable, we establish non-asymptotic guarantees on the estimation error at times where the state trajectory evolves in this region. If the whole state space is informative, high probability guarantees on the error hold for all times. Examples are provided where our results are useful for analysis, but existing results are not.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04157v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seth Siriya, Jingge Zhu, Dragan Ne\v{s}i\'c, Ye Pu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Utilizing phase-type distributions for queueing-based railway junction performance determination</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04188v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To ensure the effective and objective development of transportation networks, it is crucial to identify performance limitations across various subsystems. A timetable-independent assessment of infrastructure capacity at railway junctions is a fundamental aspect of long-term rail network planning. While recent research introduced queueing-based methods to quantify route-based railway junction performance, modelling arrival and service processes has been limited to exponential distributions. This work utilizes Phase-Type Distributions to propose an extension to a previously described Continuous-Time Markov Chain model. In a comparison between assumed distribution combinations, the effect of a more detailed stochastic process modelling is described. Furthermore, an analysis of the differences to a simulation method is conducted for an exemplary railway junction. The introduced method enables infrastructure managers to accurately model stochastic processes for performance determination in the early stages of the strategic planning phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04188v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tamme Emunds, Nils Nie{\ss}en</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Behaviors of Hybrid Systems via the Voronoi Bias over Output Signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04203v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider an analysis of temporal properties of hybrid systems based on simulations, so-called falsification of requirements. We present a novel exploration-based algorithm for falsification of black-box models of hybrid systems based on the Voronoi bias in the output space. This approach is inspired by techniques used originally in motion planning: rapidly exploring random trees. Instead of commonly employed exploration that is based on coverage of inputs, the proposed algorithm aims to cover all possible outputs directly. Compared to other state-of-the-art falsification tools, it also does not require robustness or other guidance metrics tied to a specific behavior that is being falsified. This allows our algorithm to falsify specifications for which robustness is not conclusive enough to guide the falsification procedure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04203v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gidon Ernst, Ji\v{r}\'i Fejlek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model-Agnostic Meta-Learning for Fault Diagnosis of Induction Motors in Data-Scarce Environments with Varying Operating Conditions and Electric Drive Noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04255v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reliable mechanical fault detection with limited data is crucial for the effective operation of induction machines, particularly given the real-world challenges present in industrial datasets, such as significant imbalances between healthy and faulty samples and the scarcity of data representing faulty conditions. This research introduces an innovative meta-learning approach to address these issues, focusing on mechanical fault detection in induction motors across diverse operating conditions while mitigating the adverse effects of drive noise in scenarios with limited data. The process of identifying faults under varying operating conditions is framed as a few-shot classification challenge and approached through a model-agnostic meta-learning strategy. Specifically, this approach begins with training a meta-learner across multiple interconnected fault-diagnosis tasks conducted under different operating conditions. In this stage, cross-entropy is utilized to optimize parameters and develop a robust representation of the tasks. Subsequently, the parameters of the meta-learner are fine-tuned for new tasks, enabling rapid adaptation using only a small number of samples. This method achieves excellent accuracy in fault detection across various conditions, even when data availability is restricted. The findings indicate that the proposed model outperforms other sophisticated techniques, providing enhanced generalization and quicker adaptation. The accuracy of fault diagnosis reaches a minimum of 99%, underscoring the model's effectiveness for reliable fault identification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04255v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Pourghoraba, MohammadSadegh KhajueeZadeh, Ali Amini, Abolfazl Vahedi, Gholam Reza Agah, Akbar Rahideh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Spatial-Domain Coordinated Control Method for Connected and Automated Vehicles at Unsignalized Intersections Considering Motion Uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04290v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cooperative driving of connected and automated vehicles (CAVs) emerges as a promising solution to enhance traffic safety, efficiency, and sustainability. Meanwhile, mixed traffic, where CAVs coexist with conventional human-driven vehicles (HDVs), represents an upcoming and necessary stage in the development of intelligent transportation systems. Considering the motion uncertainty of HDVs, this paper proposes a coordinated control method for trajectory planning of CAVs at an unsignalized intersection in mixed traffic. By sampling in distance and using an exact change of variables, the coordinated control problem is formulated as a nonlinear program in the spatial domain, thereby allowing for unified linear collision avoidance constraints to handle crossing, following, merging, and diverging vehicle conflicts. The motion uncertainty of HDVs is decoupled and modeled as path uncertainty and speed uncertainty, whereby the robustness of collision avoidance is ensured in both spatial and temporal dimensions. The prediction deviation for HDVs is compensated by receding horizon optimization, and a real-time iteration (RTI) scheme is developed to improve computational efficiency. Simulation case studies are conducted to validate the efficacy, robustness, and potential for real-time application of the proposed method. The results show that the proposed control scheme provides collision-free and smooth trajectories with state and control constraints satisfied. Compared with the converged baseline, the RTI scheme reduces the computation time by a factor of 111 on average, and the solution deviation is less than 2.26%, demonstrating a good trade-off between computational effort and optimality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04290v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tong Zhao, Nikolce Murgovski, Wei ShangGuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stealthy Optimal Range-Sensor Placement for Target Localization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04316v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a stealthy range-sensor placement problem where a set of range sensors are to be placed with respect to targets to effectively localize them while maintaining a degree of stealthiness from the targets. This is an open and challenging problem since two competing objectives must be balanced: (a) optimally placing the sensors to maximize their ability to localize the targets and (b) minimizing the information the targets gather regarding the sensors. We provide analytical solutions in 2D for the case of any number of sensors that localize two targets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04316v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Hussein Yoosefian Nooshabadi, Rifat Sipahi, Laurent Lessard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcement Learning for Freeway Lane-Change Regulation via Connected Vehicles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04341</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04341v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Lane change decision-making is a complex task due to intricate vehicle-vehicle and vehicle-infrastructure interactions. Existing algorithms for lane-change control often depend on vehicles with a certain level of autonomy (e.g., autonomous or connected autonomous vehicles). To address the challenges posed by low penetration rates of autonomous vehicles and the high costs of precise data collection, this study proposes a dynamic lane change regulation design based on multi-agent reinforcement learning (MARL) to enhance freeway traffic efficiency. The proposed framework leverages multi-lane macroscopic traffic models that describe spatial-temporal dynamics of the density and speed for each lane. Lateral traffic flow between adjacent lanes, resulting from aggregated lane-changing behaviors, is modeled as source terms exchanged between the partial differential equations (PDEs). We propose a lane change regulation strategy using MARL, where one agent is placed at each discretized lane grid. The state of each agent is represented by aggregated vehicle attributes within its grid, generated from the SUMO microscopic simulation environment. The agent's actions are lane-change regulations for vehicles in its grid. Specifically, lane-change regulation signals are computed at a centralized traffic management center and then broadcast to connected vehicles in the corresponding lane grids. Compared to vehicle-level maneuver control, this approach achieves a higher regulation rate by leveraging vehicle connectivity while introducing no critical safety concerns, and accommodating varying levels of connectivity and autonomy within the traffic system. The proposed model is simulated and evaluated in varied traffic scenarios and demand conditions. Experimental results demonstrate that the method improves overall traffic efficiency with minimal additional energy consumption while maintaining driving safety.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04341v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ke Sun, Huan Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intersection-Aware Assessment of EMS Accessibility in NYC: A Data-Driven Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04369</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04369v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Emergency response times are critical in densely populated urban environments like New York City (NYC), where traffic congestion significantly impedes emergency vehicle (EMV) mobility. This study introduces an intersection-aware emergency medical service (EMS) accessibility model to evaluate and improve EMV travel times across NYC. Integrating intersection density metrics, road network characteristics, and demographic data, the model identifies vulnerable regions with inadequate EMS coverage. The analysis reveals that densely interconnected areas, such as parts of Staten Island, Queens, and Manhattan, experience significant accessibility deficits due to intersection delays and sparse medical infrastructure. To address these challenges, this study explores the adoption of EMVLight, a multi-agent reinforcement learning framework, which demonstrates the potential to reduce intersection delays by 50\%, increasing EMS accessibility to 95\% of NYC residents within the critical benchmark of 4 minutes. Results indicate that advanced traffic signal control (TSC) systems can alleviate congestion-induced delays while improving equity in emergency response. The findings provide actionable insights for urban planning and policy interventions to enhance EMS accessibility and ensure timely care for underserved populations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04369v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoran Su, Joseph Y. J. Chow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotics of Linear Regression with Linearly Dependent Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03702v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we study the asymptotics of linear regression in settings where the covariates exhibit a linear dependency structure, departing from the standard assumption of independence. We model the covariates using stochastic processes with spatio-temporal covariance and analyze the performance of ridge regression in the high-dimensional proportional regime, where the number of samples and feature dimensions grow proportionally. A Gaussian universality theorem is proven, demonstrating that the asymptotics are invariant under replacing the covariates with Gaussian vectors preserving mean and covariance. Next, leveraging tools from random matrix theory, we derive precise characterizations of the estimation error. The estimation error is characterized by a fixed-point equation involving the spectral properties of the spatio-temporal covariance matrices, enabling efficient computation. We then study optimal regularization, overparameterization, and the double descent phenomenon in the context of dependent data. Simulations validate our theoretical predictions, shedding light on how dependencies influence estimation error and the choice of regularization parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03702v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Behrad Moniri, Hamed Hassani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Securing RC Based P2P Networks: A Blockchain-based Access Control Framework utilizing Ethereum Smart Contracts for IoT and Web 3.0</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03709v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ensuring security for highly dynamic peer-to-peer (P2P) networks has always been a challenge, especially for services like online transactions and smart devices. These networks experience high churn rates, making it difficult to maintain appropriate access control. Traditional systems, particularly Role-Based Access Control (RBAC), often fail to meet the needs of a P2P environment. This paper presents a blockchain-based access control framework that uses Ethereum smart contracts to address these challenges. Our framework aims to close the gaps in existing access control systems by providing flexible, transparent, and decentralized security solutions. The proposed framework includes access control contracts (ACC) that manage access based on static and dynamic policies, a Judge Contract (JC) to handle misbehavior, and a Register Contract (RC) to record and manage the interactions between ACCs and JC. The security model combines impact and severity-based threat assessments using the CIA (Confidentiality, Integrity, Availability) and STRIDE principles, ensuring responses are tailored to different threat levels. This system not only stabilizes the fundamental issues of peer membership but also offers a scalable solution, particularly valuable in areas such as the Internet of Things (IoT) and Web 3.0 technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03709v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saurav Ghosh, Reshmi Mitra, Indranil Roy, Bidyut Gupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Safe Adaptive Cruise Control Under Perception Uncertainty: A Deep Ensemble and Conformal Tube Model Predictive Control Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03792v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Autonomous driving heavily relies on perception systems to interpret the environment for decision-making. To enhance robustness in these safety critical applications, this paper considers a Deep Ensemble of Deep Neural Network regressors integrated with Conformal Prediction to predict and quantify uncertainties. In the Adaptive Cruise Control setting, the proposed method performs state and uncertainty estimation from RGB images, informing the downstream controller of the DNN perception uncertainties. An adaptive cruise controller using Conformal Tube Model Predictive Control is designed to ensure probabilistic safety. Evaluations with a high-fidelity simulator demonstrate the algorithm's effectiveness in speed tracking and safe distance maintaining, including in Out-Of-Distribution scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03792v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao Li, Anouck Girard, Ilya Kolmanovsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Based MPC for Autonomous Driving Using a Low Dimensional Residual Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03874v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, a learning based Model Predictive Control (MPC) using a low dimensional residual model is proposed for autonomous driving. One of the critical challenge in autonomous driving is the complexity of vehicle dynamics, which impedes the formulation of accurate vehicle model. Inaccurate vehicle model can significantly impact the performance of MPC controller. To address this issue, this paper decomposes the nominal vehicle model into invariable and variable elements. The accuracy of invariable component is ensured by calibration, while the deviations in the variable elements are learned by a low-dimensional residual model. The features of residual model are selected as the physical variables most correlated with nominal model errors. Physical constraints among these features are formulated to explicitly define the valid region within the feature space. The formulated model and constraints are incorporated into the MPC framework and validated through both simulation and real vehicle experiments. The results indicate that the proposed method significantly enhances the model accuracy and controller performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03874v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yaoyu Li, Chaosheng Huang, Dongsheng Yang, Wenbo Liu, Jun Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is FISHER All You Need in The Multi-AUV Underwater Target Tracking Task?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03959v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It is significant to employ multiple autonomous underwater vehicles (AUVs) to execute the underwater target tracking task collaboratively. However, it's pretty challenging to meet various prerequisites utilizing traditional control methods. Therefore, we propose an effective two-stage learning from demonstrations training framework, FISHER, to highlight the adaptability of reinforcement learning (RL) methods in the multi-AUV underwater target tracking task, while addressing its limitations such as extensive requirements for environmental interactions and the challenges in designing reward functions. The first stage utilizes imitation learning (IL) to realize policy improvement and generate offline datasets. To be specific, we introduce multi-agent discriminator-actor-critic based on improvements of the generative adversarial IL algorithm and multi-agent IL optimization objective derived from the Nash equilibrium condition. Then in the second stage, we develop multi-agent independent generalized decision transformer, which analyzes the latent representation to match the future states of high-quality samples rather than reward function, attaining further enhanced policies capable of handling various scenarios. Besides, we propose a simulation to simulation demonstration generation procedure to facilitate the generation of expert demonstrations in underwater environments, which capitalizes on traditional control methods and can easily accomplish the domain transfer to obtain demonstrations. Extensive simulation experiments from multiple scenarios showcase that FISHER possesses strong stability, multi-task performance and capability of generalization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03959v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingzehua Xu, Guanwen Xie, Ziqi Zhang, Xiangwang Hou, Dongfang Ma, Shuai Zhang, Yong Ren, Dusit Niyato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Comprehensive Legislative Requirements for Cyber Physical Systems Testing in the European Union</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04132v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: While procedures prevail on the European market for the greater good of its citizens, it might be daunting when trying to introduce a product, whether innovative or not. In the current world, Cyber-Physical Systems (CPSs) are ubiquitous in our daily lives. Cars can provide intrusive assistance as they can brake or turn wheels on their own, buildings are getting smarter to optimize energy consumption, smart cities are emerging to facilitate information sharing and orchestrate the response to emergency situations, etc. As the presence of such tools will grow in the coming years and people will rely even more on CPSs, we certainly need to ensure that they are safe and reliable for users or everybody else, which is why regulations are so important. However, compliance should not act as a barrier to new actors coming to the European market. Nor should it prevent current actors from keeping systems deemed compliant when introduced while obsolete at the time they are used. While the individual elements we point out might not bring novelty in the various research areas we cover (EU policies, requirements engineering, business engineering, and software engineering), this paper identifies the challenges related to building and testing a CPS with respect to applicable laws and discusses the difficulty of automating the response to those challenges, such as finding a relevant legal text, paying for mentioned materials or identifying the level of compliance to a legal text. Our analysis of the holistic context when considering the compliance testing of CPS provides an overview enabling more effective decision-making as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04132v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillaume Nguyen, Manon Knockaert, Michael Lognoul, Xavier Devroey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Action Mapping for Reinforcement Learning in Continuous Environments with Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04327v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Deep reinforcement learning (DRL) has had success across various domains, but applying it to environments with constraints remains challenging due to poor sample efficiency and slow convergence. Recent literature explored incorporating model knowledge to mitigate these problems, particularly through the use of models that assess the feasibility of proposed actions. However, integrating feasibility models efficiently into DRL pipelines in environments with continuous action spaces is non-trivial. We propose a novel DRL training strategy utilizing action mapping that leverages feasibility models to streamline the learning process. By decoupling the learning of feasible actions from policy optimization, action mapping allows DRL agents to focus on selecting the optimal action from a reduced feasible action set. We demonstrate through experiments that action mapping significantly improves training performance in constrained environments with continuous action spaces, especially with imperfect feasibility models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04327v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mirco Theile, Lukas Dirnberger, Raphael Trumpp, Marco Caccamo, Alberto L. Sangiovanni-Vincentelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online Simultaneous State and Parameter Estimation for Second-order Nonlinear Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1703.07068</link>
      <description>arXiv:1703.07068v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, a concurrent learning based adaptive observer is developed for a class of second-order nonlinear time-invariant systems with uncertain dynamics. The developed technique results in simultaneous online state and parameter estimation. A Lyapunov-based analysis is used to show that the state and parameter estimation errors are uniformly ultimately bounded. As opposed to persistent excitation which is required for parameter estimation in traditional adaptive control methods, the developed technique only requires excitation over a finite time interval.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1703.07068v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/CDC.2017.8263965</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Rushikesh Kamalapurkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbed Decision-Focused Learning for Modeling Strategic Energy Storage</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17085v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel decision-focused framework integrating the physical energy storage model into machine learning pipelines. Motivated by the model predictive control for energy storage, our end-to-end method incorporates the prior knowledge of the storage model and infers the hidden reward that incentivizes energy storage decisions. This is achieved through a dual-layer framework, combining a prediction layer with an optimization layer. We introduce the perturbation idea into the designed decision-focused loss function to ensure the differentiability over linear storage models, supported by a theoretical analysis of the perturbed loss function. We also develop a hybrid loss function for effective model training. We provide two challenging applications for our proposed framework: energy storage arbitrage, and energy storage behavior prediction. The numerical experiments on real price data demonstrate that our arbitrage approach achieves the highest profit against existing methods. The numerical experiments on synthetic and real-world energy storage data show that our approach achieves the best behavior prediction performance against existing benchmark methods, which shows the effectiveness of our method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17085v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ming Yi, Saud Alghumayjan, Bolun Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Duality of Stochastic Observability and Constructability and Their Relation to the Fisher Information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19975v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a set of measurements, observability characterizes the distinguishability of a system's initial state, whereas constructability focuses on the final state in a trajectory. In the presence of process and/or measurement noise, the Fisher information matrices with respect to the initial and final states$\unicode{x2013}$equivalent to the stochastic observability and constructability Gramians$\unicode{x2013}$bound the performance of corresponding estimators through the Cram\'er-Rao inequality. This letter establishes a connection between stochastic observability and constructability of discrete-time linear systems and provides a more numerically stable way for calculating the stochastic observability Gramian. We define a dual system and show that the dual system's stochastic constructability is equivalent to the original system's stochastic observability, and vice versa. This duality enables the interchange of theorems and tools for observability and constructability. For example, we use this result to translate an existing recursive formula for the stochastic constructability Gramian into a formula for recursively calculating the stochastic observability Gramian for both time-varying and time-invariant systems, and we show the convergence of this sequence for the latter. Finally, we illustrate the robustness of our formula compared to existing (non-recursive) formulas through a numerical example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19975v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Burak Boyac{\i}o\u{g}lu, Floris van Breugel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PC-Gym: Benchmark Environments For Process Control Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22093v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: PC-Gym is an open-source tool for developing and evaluating reinforcement learning (RL) algorithms in chemical process control. It features environments that simulate various chemical processes, incorporating nonlinear dynamics, disturbances, and constraints. The tool includes customizable constraint handling, disturbance generation, reward function design, and enables comparison of RL algorithms against Nonlinear Model Predictive Control (NMPC) across different scenarios. Case studies demonstrate the framework's effectiveness in evaluating RL approaches for systems like continuously stirred tank reactors, multistage extraction processes, and crystallization reactors. The results reveal performance gaps between RL algorithms and NMPC oracles, highlighting areas for improvement and enabling benchmarking. By providing a standardized platform, PC-Gym aims to accelerate research at the intersection of machine learning, control, and process systems engineering. By connecting theoretical RL advances with practical industrial process control applications, offering researchers a tool for exploring data-driven control solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22093v4</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maximilian Bloor, Jos\'e Torraca, Ilya Orson Sandoval, Akhil Ahmed, Martha White, Mehmet Mercang\"oz, Calvin Tsay, Ehecatl Antonio Del Rio Chanona, Max Mowbray</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Knowledge Transfer based Evolutionary Deep Neural Network for Intelligent Fault Diagnosis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.13479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2109.13479v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A fault diagnosis with commendable accuracy is essential for the reliability of industrial machines. Two main challenges affect the design of high-performing intelligent systems: (i) the selection of a suitable model and (ii) domain adaptation if there is a continuous change in operating conditions. Therefore, we propose an evolutionary Net2Net transformation (EvoN2N) that finds the best suitable DNN architecture with limited availability of labeled data samples. Net2Net transformation-based quick learning algorithm has been used in the evolutionary framework of Non-dominated sorting genetic algorithm II to obtain the best DNN architecture. Net2Net transformation-based quick learning algorithm uses the concept of knowledge transfer from one generation to the next for faster fitness evaluation. The proposed framework can obtain the best model for intelligent fault diagnosis without a long and time-consuming search process. The proposed framework has been validated on the Case Western Reserve University dataset, the Paderborn University dataset, and the gearbox fault detection dataset under different operating conditions. The best models obtained are capable of demonstrating an excellent diagnostic performance and classification accuracy of almost up to 100\% for most of the operating conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2109.13479v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arun K. Sharma, Nishchal K. Verma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reachable Polyhedral Marching (RPM): An Exact Analysis Tool for Deep-Learned Control Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.08339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.08339v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Neural networks are increasingly used in robotics as policies, state transition models, state estimation models, or all of the above. With these components being learned from data, it is important to be able to analyze what behaviors were learned and how this affects closed-loop performance. In this paper we take steps toward this goal by developing methods for computing control invariant sets and regions of attraction (ROAs) of dynamical systems represented as neural networks. We focus our attention on feedforward neural networks with the rectified linear unit (ReLU) activation, which are known to implement continuous piecewise-affine (PWA) functions. We describe the Reachable Polyhedral Marching (RPM) algorithm for enumerating the affine pieces of a neural network through an incremental connected walk. We then use this algorithm to compute exact forward and backward reachable sets, from which we provide methods for computing control invariant sets and ROAs. Our approach is unique in that we find these sets incrementally, without Lyapunov-based tools. In our examples we demonstrate the ability of our approach to find non-convex control invariant sets and ROAs on tasks with learned van der Pol oscillator and pendulum models. Further, we provide an accelerated algorithm for computing ROAs that leverages the incremental and connected enumeration of affine regions that RPM provides. We show this acceleration to lead to a 15x speedup in our examples. Finally, we apply our methods to find a set of states that are stabilized by an image-based controller for an aircraft runway control problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.08339v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joseph A. Vincent, Mac Schwager</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algebraic solution of project scheduling problems with temporal constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.09216</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.09216v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: New solutions for problems in optimal scheduling of activities in a project under temporal constraints are developed in the framework of tropical algebra which deals with the theory and application of algebraic systems with idempotent operations. We start with a constrained tropical optimization problem that has an objective function represented as a vector form given by an arbitrary matrix, and that can be solved analytically in a closed but somewhat complicated form. We examine a special case of the problem when the objective function is given by a matrix of unit rank, and show that the solution can be sufficiently refined in this case, which results in an essentially simplified analytical form and reduced computational complexity of the solution. We exploit the obtained result to find complete solutions of project scheduling problems to minimize the project makespan and the maximum absolute deviation of start times of activities under temporal constraints. The constraints under consideration include ``start--start'', ``start--finish'' and ``finish--start'' precedence relations, release times, release deadlines and completion deadlines for activities. As an application, we consider optimal scheduling problems of a vaccination project in a medical centre.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.09216v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s12351-024-00880-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Operational Research. 2024. Vol.24, N4. P.69. URL:https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12351-024-00880-3</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>N. Krivulin, S. Gubanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Computation of Approximate Solutions to Large-Scale Backstepping Kernel Equations via Continuum Approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13612v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We provide two methods for computation of continuum backstepping kernels that arise in control of continua (ensembles) of linear hyperbolic PDEs and which can approximate backstepping kernels arising in control of a large-scale, PDE system counterpart (with computational complexity that does not grow with the number of state components of the large-scale system). In the first method, we provide explicit formulae for the solution to the continuum kernels PDEs, employing a (triple) power series representation of the continuum kernel and establishing its convergence properties. In this case, we also provide means for reducing computational complexity by properly truncating the power series (in the powers of the ensemble variable). In the second method, we identify a class of systems for which the solution to the continuum (and hence, also an approximate solution to the respective large-scale) kernel equations can be constructed in closed form. We also present numerical examples to illustrate computational efficiency/accuracy of the approaches, as well as to validate the stabilization properties of the approximate control kernels, constructed based on the continuum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13612v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Systems &amp; Control Letters 196 (2025) 105982</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jukka-Pekka Humaloja, Nikolaos Bekiaris-Liberis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kernel-Based Optimal Control: An Infinitesimal Generator Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.01591v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel approach for optimal control of nonlinear stochastic systems using infinitesimal generator learning within infinite-dimensional reproducing kernel Hilbert spaces. Our learning framework leverages data samples of system dynamics and stage cost functions, with only control penalties and constraints provided. The proposed method directly learns the diffusion operator of a controlled Fokker-Planck-Kolmogorov equation in an infinite-dimensional hypothesis space. This operator models the continuous-time evolution of the probability measure of the control system's state. We demonstrate that this approach seamlessly integrates with modern convex operator-theoretic Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman recursions, enabling a data-driven solution to the optimal control problem. Furthermore, our statistical learning framework includes nonparametric estimators for uncontrolled forward infinitesimal generators as a special case. Numerical experiments, ranging from synthetic differential equations to simulated robotic systems, showcase the advantages of our approach compared to both modern data-driven and classical nonlinear programming methods for optimal control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.01591v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Petar Bevanda, Nicolas Hoischen, Tobias Wittmann, Jan Br\"udigam, Sandra Hirche, Boris Houska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-Driven LQR with Finite-Time Experiments via Extremum-Seeking Policy Iteration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02758</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02758v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we address Linear Quadratic Regulator (LQR) problems through a novel iterative algorithm named EXtremum-seeking Policy iteration LQR (EXP-LQR). The peculiarity of EXP-LQR is that it only needs access to a truncated approximation of the infinite-horizon cost associated to a given policy. Hence, EXP-LQR does not need the direct knowledge of neither the system matrices, cost matrices, and state measurements. In particular, at each iteration, EXP-LQR refines the maintained policy using a truncated LQR cost retrieved by performing finite-time virtual or real experiments in which a perturbed version of the current policy is employed. Such a perturbation is done according to an extremum-seeking mechanism and makes the overall algorithm a time-varying nonlinear system. By using a Lyapunov-based approach exploiting averaging theory, we show that EXP-LQR exponentially converges to an arbitrarily small neighborhood of the optimal gain matrix. We corroborate the theoretical results with numerical simulations involving the control of an induction motor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02758v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guido Carnevale, Nicola Mimmo, Giuseppe Notarstefano</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
