<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SY updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SY</link>
    <description>cs.SY updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SY" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 01:21:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Planar Juggling of a Devil-Stick using Discrete VHCs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08085v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Planar juggling of a devil-stick using impulsive inputs is addressed using the concept of discrete virtual holonomic constraints (DVHC). The location of the center-of-mass of the devil-stick is specified in terms of its orientation at the discrete instants when impulsive control inputs are applied. The discrete zero dynamics (DZD) resulting from the choice of DVHC provides conditions for stable juggling. A control design that enforces the DVHC and an orbit stabilizing controller are presented. The approach is validated in simulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08085v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aakash Khandelwal, Ranjan Mukherjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Admission Control for Inelastic Traffic on a Link Shared by Deadline-Driven Elastic Traffic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08135v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Consider a (logical) link between two distributed data centers with available bandwidth designated for both deadline-driven elastic traffic, such as for scheduled synchronization services, and profitable inelastic traffic, such as for real-time streaming services. Admission control in this setting is cast as a stochastic shortest path problem, with state space derived from (discretization of) the elastic flow's size/deadline and action space corresponding to alternative subsets of admitted inelastic flows: the probabilistic model expresses uncertainty in both the link's available bandwidth and the inelastic flows' offered loads, while the objective function captures both congestion avoidance and the option to specify a desired minimum elastic rate. Its solution is shown to (i) balance the accumulation of instantaneous inelastic reward with the risk of missing the elastic deadline and (ii) exhibit a degree of robustness to link &amp; flow modeling errors that is tunable via choice of the desired minimum elastic rate. Also discussed are state augmentations that befit urgent or non-interruptible inelastic traffic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08135v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Kreidl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EnergyNet Explained: Internetification of Energy Distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08152</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08152v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In developing EnergyNet we have leveraged and are extending lessons from telecom's shift from a centralized, circuit-switched phone system to decentralized, packet-switched data networks. EnergyNet utilizes 1) an Energy Router that enforces galvanic separation and utilizes software-controlled energy flows over a DC backplane, 2) Energy Local and Wide Area Networks (ELAN/EWAN) based on DC microgrids that interconnect through an open Energy Protocol (EP), and 3) a control plane comprised of the Energy Router Operating System (EROS) and EP Server which is managed at operator scale through an Energy Network Management System (ENMS). We distinguish the architectural contribution (Tier-1 including components, interfaces, and operating model) from expected outcomes contingent on adoption (Tier-2). The latter includes local-first autonomy with global interoperability, near-real-time operation with local buffering, removal of EV-charging bottlenecks, freed grid capacity for data centers and industrial electrification, as well as a trend toward low, predictable, fixed-cost clean energy. Evidence from early municipal demonstrators illustrates feasibility and migration paths. The contribution is a coherent, open, and testable blueprint for software-defined, decentralized energy distribution, aligning power-systems engineering with networking principles and offering a practical route from legacy, synchronous grids to resilient, digitally routed energy distribution systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08152v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas Birgersson, Marc A. Weiss, Jimmy Chen, Daniel Kammen, Tomas K{\aa}berger, Franklin Carrero-Mart\'inez, Joakim Wernberg, Michael Menser, Newsha K. Ajami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Linear Pricing Mechanism for Load Management in Day-Ahead Retail Energy Markets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08166</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08166v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Regulators and utilities have been exploring hourly retail electricity pricing, with several existing programs providing day-ahead hourly pricing schedules. At the same time, customers are deploying distributed energy resources and smart energy management systems that have significant flexibility and can optimally follow price signals. In aggregate, these optimally controlled loads can create congestion management issues for distribution system operators (DSOs). In this paper, we describe a new linear pricing mechanism for day-ahead retail electricity pricing that provides a signal for customers to follow to mitigate over-consumption while still consuming energy at hours that are preferential for system performance. We show that by broadcasting a linear price designed for price-signal control of cost-optimizing loads, we can shape customer load profiles to provide congestion management without the need for bi-directional communication or customer bidding programs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08166v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Phillippe K. Phanivong, Duncan S. Callaway</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multivariable Current Controller for Enhancing Dynamic Response and Grid Synchronization Stability of IBRs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08201v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper develops a multivariable current control strategy for inverter-based resources (IBRs) based on optimal control theory to enhance their dynamic performance and grid synchronization stability. The structure of the implemented multiple-input, multiple-output (MIMO) controller closely resembles that of the commonly used conventional single-input, single-output (SISO) PI controllers for IBRs. As a result, it requires only minor adjustments to conventional vector current control schemes, thereby facilitating its straightforward adoption. Time-domain simulations and analytical analysis demonstrate the superior performance of the developed method under various conditions and use case scenarios, such as weak power systems and uncertain parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08201v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hassan Yazdani, Ali Maleki, Saeed Lotfifard, Ali Saberi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint Optimization of Computation Offloading and Resource Allocation in ISAC-assisted SAGIN-based IoT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08238</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08238v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this letters, an energy-efficient integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) for space-air-ground integrated network (SAGIN)-based Internet of Things (IoT) systems is proposed to facilitate wide coverage and real-time 6G services. For processing a sizable data collected at a IoT device, a hybrid edge computing scheme is applied with the cloudlets mounted at autonomous aerial vehicle (AAV) and low earth orbit (LEO) satellite, where the AAV with multiple antennas performs uplink sensing of the nearby target. With the aim of minimizing the total AAV's energy consumption, we optimize the duration of training and data phase and the bit allocation coupled with the offloading ratio under the constraints for offloading and sensing. Via simulations, the superiority of the proposed algorithm is verified to be pronounced with the sufficient mission time and the high sensing performance constraint.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08238v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sooyeob Jung, Seongah Jeong, Jinkyu Kang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Game-Theoretic Resilience Framework for Cyber-Physical Microgrids using Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08310</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08310v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The increasing reliance on cyber physical infrastructure in modern power systems has amplified the risk of targeted cyber attacks, necessitating robust and adaptive resilience strategies. This paper presents a mathematically rigorous game theoretic framework to evaluate and enhance microgrid resilience using a combination of quantitative resilience metrics Load Served Ratio LSR, Critical Load Resilience CLR, Topological Survivability Score TSS, and DER Resilience Score DRS. These are integrated into a unified payoff matrix using the Analytic Hierarchy Process AHP to assess attack defense interactions. The framework is formalized as a finite horizon Markov Decision Process MDP with formal convergence guarantees and computational complexity bounds. Three case studies are developed 1. static attacks analyzed via Nash equilibrium, 2. severe attacks incorporating high impact strategies, and 3. adaptive attacks using Stackelberg games, regret matching, softmax heuristics, and Multi Agent Q Learning. Rigorous theoretical analysis provides convergence proofs with explicit rates , PAC learning sample complexity bounds, and computational complexity analysis. The framework is tested on an enhanced IEEE 33bus distribution system with DERs and control switches, demonstrating the effectiveness of adaptive and strategic defenses in improving cyber physical resilience with statistically significant improvements of 18.7% 2.1% over static approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08310v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S Krishna Niketh, Sagar Babu Mitikiri, V Vignesh, Vedantham Lakshmi Srinivas, Mayukha Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resilient Global Practical Fixed-Time Cooperative Output Regulation of Uncertain Nonlinear Multi-Agent Systems Subject to Denial-of-Service Attacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08324</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08324v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the problem of resilient global practical fixed-time cooperative output regulation of uncertain nonlinear multi-agent systems subject to denial-of-service attacks. A novel distributed resilient adaptive fixed-time control strategy is proposed, which consists of a novel distributed resilient fixed-time observer with a chain of nonlinear filters and a novel distributed resilient adaptive fixed-time controller. It is shown that the problem of resilient global practical fixed-time cooperative output regulation can be solved by the proposed control strategy. More specifically, the proposed {distributed} control strategy ensures the global boundedness of all the signals in the resulting closed-loop system and the global convergence of the regulated outputs to a {tunable} residual set in a fixed time. A simulation example is finally provided to illustrate the efficacy of the proposed control strategy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08324v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TAC.2025.3602853</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Wenji Cao, Lu Liu, Zehua Ye, Dan Zhang, Gang Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AP-observation Automata for Abstraction-based Verification of Continuous-time Systems (Extended Version)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08343</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08343v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A key challenge in abstraction-based verification and control under complex specifications such as Linear Temporal Logic (LTL) is that abstract models retain significantly less information than their original systems. This issue is especially true for continuous-time systems, where the system state trajectories are split into intervals of discrete actions, and satisfaction of atomic propositions is abstracted to a whole time interval. To tackle this challenge, this work introduces a novel translation from LTL specifications to AP-observation automata, a particular type of B\"uchi automata specifically designed for abstraction-based verification. Based on this automaton, we present a game-based verification algorithm played between the system and the environment, and an illustrative example for abstraction-based system verification under several LTL specifications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08343v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sasinee Pruekprasert, Clovis Eberhart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Planning Strategy for Building a Heterogeneous Smart EM Environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08378v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a planning strategy for the deployment of smart electromagnetic entities (SEEs) to enhance the wireless coverage and the Quality-of-Service (QoS) in large urban areas. The integration of different technological solutions such as integrated access-and-backhaul nodes (IABs), smart repeaters (SRs), and electromagnetic skins (EMSs) is here addressed to enable an effective and efficient implementation of the concept of Smart Electromagnetic Environment (SEME). By combining the features of such heterogeneous SEEs and optimizing their number, positions, orientations, and configuration, the electromagnetic (EM) coverage in a set of Regions-of-Interest (RoIs) of outdoor scenarios is recovered and/or enhanced subject to installation costs and energy consumption requirements. Numerical validations from real-world scenarios are reported to assess the effectiveness of the proposed planning scheme as well as to show the potentialities of an heterogeneous deployment of SEMEs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08378v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arianna Benoni, Marco Salucci, Baozhu Li, Andrea Massa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase-Coordinated Multi-Agent Circular Formation Control with Non-Concentric Boundary Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08534</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08534v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper addresses the problem of collective circular motion control for unicycle agents, with the objective of achieving phase coordination of their velocity vectors while ensuring that their trajectories remain confined within a prescribed non-concentric circular boundary. To accommodate such nonuniform motion constraints, we build upon our earlier work and extend the use of Mobius transformation to a multi-agent framework. The Mobius transformation maps two nonconcentric circles to concentric ones, thereby converting spatially nonuniform constraints into uniform ones in the transformed plane. Leveraging this property, we introduce the notion of a phase-shifted order parameter, along with the associated concepts of Mobius phase-shift coupled synchronization and balancing, which characterize the phase-coordinated patterns studied in this paper. We establish an equivalence between the unicycle dynamics in the original and transformed planes under the Mobius transformation and its inverse, and show that synchronization is preserved across both planes, whereas balancing is generally not. Distributed control laws are then designed in the transformed plane using barrier Lyapunov functions, under the assumption of an undirected and connected communication topology among agents. These controllers are subsequently mapped back to the original plane to obtain the linear acceleration and turn-rate control inputs applied to the actual agents. Both simulations and experimental results are provided to illustrate the proposed framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08534v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shubham Singh, Anoop Jain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How can a geothermal storage system be optimally integrated into a local district? A case study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08568v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Achieving net-zero targets requires the phase-out of fossil-based heating. A major challenge is the seasonal mismatch between renewable heat supply and demand. District heating networks often dispose of excess heat in summer and rely on fossil backups in winter. Large-scale thermal energy storage offers a solution by storing surplus summer heat for use during winter, thus reducing the need for fossil fuels. This study investigates the feasibility of a large-scale thermal storage system at a power production site that supplies a large district heating network in the city of Bern, Switzerland. Specifically, the study examines the potential of a geothermal storage system to offset fossil fuel heat generation in winter by utilising heat stored during the summer months. Using a Python-based multi-energy system model, we simulate the optimal operation of the geothermal storage system with respect to cost and emissions, considering both supply and demand on an hourly basis over one year. Multi-objective optimisation is applied to generate a Pareto-optimal front. The results show that the geothermal storage system eliminates the requirement of 8 GWh of gas-powered heat supply and increases the waste heat utilisation by 20%, therefore lowering emissions. This effect is further increased when combined with an expansion of the district heating network, as individual, emission-heavy heaters are replaced by low-emission heat from the district heating network. The findings presented in this study can prove useful when evaluating similar systems across Switzerland.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08568v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ueli Schilt, Somesh Vijayananda, Sarah Schneeberger, Manuel Meyer, Santhosh Iyyakkunnel, Pascal Marc Vecsei, Philipp Schuetz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis and Control of Acoustic Emissions from Marine Energy Converters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08656v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study investigates the mitigation of acoustic emissions from tidal current converters (TCCs) through optimized control strategies to enhance power generation efficiency while minimizing environmental impacts on marine life. A MATLAB/Simulink-based model of a Tidal Current Conversion System (TCCS) was developed to simulate the effects of variable control parameters, including switching frequencies, maximum power point tracking (MPPT) coefficients, and the elimination of the gearbox, on underwater noise levels. Acoustic emissions were quantified in terms of sound pressure levels (SPLs), and their potential impacts on marine mammals and fish were evaluated against species-specific auditory thresholds for temporary and permanent hearing threshold shifts. The results indicate that adjusting control parameters can significantly reduce SPLs, with the removal of the gearbox yielding the greatest noise reduction. The study identifies operational conditions under which marine species are at risk of auditory damage and proposes control strategies to mitigate these risks without compromising energy output. These findings contribute to the understanding of how control system modifications can balance the efficiency of marine energy systems with ecological considerations, offering guidance for the design and operation of environmentally compliant TCCs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08656v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaqin He, Max Malyi, Jonathan Shek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Graph Learning for Power System Reconfigurations: Transfer Across Topology Variations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08672v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work addresses a fundamental challenge in applying deep learning to power systems: developing neural network models that transfer across significant system changes, including networks with entirely different topologies and dimensionalities, without requiring training data from unseen reconfigurations. Despite extensive research, most ML-based approaches remain system-specific, limiting real-world deployment. This limitation stems from a dual barrier. First, topology changes shift feature distributions and alter input dimensions due to power flow physics. Second, reconfigurations redefine output semantics and dimensionality, requiring models to handle configuration-specific outputs while maintaining transferable feature extraction. To overcome this challenge, we introduce a Universal Graph Convolutional Network (UGCN) that achieves transferability to any reconfiguration or variation of existing power systems without any prior knowledge of new grid topologies or retraining during implementation. Our approach applies to both transmission and distribution networks and demonstrates generalization capability to completely unseen system reconfigurations, such as network restructuring and major grid expansions. Experimental results across power system applications, including false data injection detection and state forecasting, show that UGCN significantly outperforms state-of-the-art methods in cross-system zero-shot transferability of new reconfigurations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08672v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tong Wu, Anna Scaglione, Sandy Miguel, Daniel Arnold</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CSI Compression Beyond Latents: End-to-End Hybrid Attention-CNN Networks with Entropy Regularization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08776v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Massive MIMO systems rely on accurate Channel State Information (CSI) feedback to enable high-gain beam-forming. However, the feedback overhead scales linearly with the number of antennas, presenting a major bottleneck. While recent deep learning methods have improved CSI compression, most overlook the impact of quantization and entropy coding, limiting their practical deployability. In this work, we propose an end-to-end CSI compression framework that integrates a Spatial Correlation-Guided Attention Mechanism with quantization and entropy-aware training. Our model effectively exploits the spatial correlation among the antennas, thereby learning compact, entropy-optimized latent representations for efficient coding. This reduces the required feedback bitrates without sacrificing reconstruction accuracy, thereby yielding a superior rate-distortion trade-off. Experiments show that our method surpasses existing end-to-end CSI compression schemes, exceeding benchmark performance by an average of 21.5% on indoor datasets and 18.9% on outdoor datasets. The proposed framework results in a practical and efficient CSI feedback scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08776v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maryam Ansarifard, Mostafa Rahmani, Mohit K. Sharma, Kishor C. Joshi, George Exarchakos, Alister Burr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Unknown Input Observer Design with Relaxed Conditions: Theory and Application to Vehicle Platooning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08783v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Designing observers for linear systems with both known and unknown inputs is an important problem in several research contexts, for example, fault diagnosis and fault-tolerant control, and cyber-secure control systems, and presents significant challenges in distributed state estimation due to the limited sensing capabilities of individual nodes. Existing methods typically impose an individual input-to-output rank condition on each estimator node, which severely restricts applicability in practical applications. This paper presents a novel distributed unknown-input observer design scheme based on a geometric approach under much weaker assumptions than the ones available in the literature. By leveraging the properties of the $(C, A)$-invariant (conditioned invariant) subspace at each node, our methodology aims at reconstructing portions of the system state that remain unaffected by local unknown inputs, while integrating these estimates via a network-based information exchange. A case study on vehicle platoon control shows the effectiveness of the proposed approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08783v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruixuan Zhao, Guitao Yang, Thomas Parisini, Boli Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online Learning and Coverage of Unknown Fields Using Random-Feature Gaussian Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08117v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper proposes a framework for multi-robot systems to perform simultaneous learning and coverage of the domain of interest characterized by an unknown and potentially time-varying density function. To overcome the limitations of Gaussian Process (GP) regression, we employ Random Feature GP (RFGP) and its online variant (O-RFGP) that enables online and incremental inference. By integrating these with Voronoi-based coverage control and Upper Confidence Bound (UCB) sampling strategy, a team of robots can adaptively focus on important regions while refining the learned spatial field for efficient coverage. Under mild assumptions, we provide theoretical guarantees and evaluate the framework through simulations in time-invariant scenarios. Furthermore, its effectiveness in time-varying settings is demonstrated through additional simulations and a physical experiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08117v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruijie Du, Ruoyu Lin, Yanning Shen, Magnus Egerstedt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UTM Performance Under Stressing Scenarios</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08124</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08124v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Proliferation of new classes of airspace participants, including uncrewed and advanced aerial mobility vehicles, necessitates the development and deployment of novel airspace management solutions, such as the Unmanned Traffic Management (UTM) system and the Provider of Services to UAM (PSU) Network. The efficacy of such systems has been demonstrated on multiple occasions via real-world deployments in limited test environments, however exploration of system behavior under stressing conditions requires the development of appropriate modeling and simulation (M&amp;S) environments. Autonomy Networks for Advanced Mobility at Lincoln Laboratory (ANAMLL) is a virtual Systems Integration Laboratory (SIL) designed to host federated autonomy networks, such as a UTM or PSU Network, and to enable test and validation at scales not available in real-world deployments. As an example of ANAMLL's utility, we explore the performance of a representative UTM network during a stressing demand scenario. In a close examination of the demand scenario, ANAMLL demonstrates a UTM system demand point at which in-flight replanning can no longer be accomplished within an allowable time window. In a second analysis of the same scenario, ANAMLL demonstrates the impact of network connectivity performance on end-user airspace access.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08124v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian Jessen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sample-Efficient Online Control Policy Learning with Real-Time Recursive Model Updates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08241</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08241v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Data-driven control methods need to be sample-efficient and lightweight, especially when data acquisition and computational resources are limited -- such as during learning on hardware. Most modern data-driven methods require large datasets and struggle with real-time updates of models, limiting their performance in dynamic environments. Koopman theory formally represents nonlinear systems as linear models over observables, and Koopman representations can be determined from data in an optimization-friendly setting with potentially rapid model updates. In this paper, we present a highly sample-efficient, Koopman-based learning pipeline: Recursive Koopman Learning (RKL). We identify sufficient conditions for model convergence and provide formal algorithmic analysis supporting our claim that RKL is lightweight and fast, with complexity independent of dataset size. We validate our method on a simulated planar two-link arm and a hybrid nonlinear hardware system with soft actuators, showing that real-time recursive Koopman model updates improve the sample efficiency and stability of data-driven controller synthesis -- requiring only &lt;10% of the data compared to benchmarks. The high-performance C++ codebase is open-sourced. Website: https://www.zixinatom990.com/home/robotics/corl-2025-recursive-koopman-learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08241v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zixin Zhang, James Avtges, Todd D. Murphey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Behaviorally Heterogeneous Multi-Agent Exploration Using Distributed Task Allocation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08242</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08242v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study a problem of multi-agent exploration with behaviorally heterogeneous robots. Each robot maps its surroundings using SLAM and identifies a set of areas of interest (AoIs) or frontiers that are the most informative to explore next. The robots assess the utility of going to a frontier using Behavioral Entropy (BE) and then determine which frontier to go to via a distributed task assignment scheme. We convert the task assignment problem into a non-cooperative game and use a distributed algorithm (d-PBRAG) to converge to the Nash equilibrium (which we show is the optimal task allocation solution). For unknown utility cases, we provide robust bounds using approximate rewards. We test our algorithm (which has less communication cost and fast convergence) in simulation, where we explore the effect of sensing radii, sensing accuracy, and heterogeneity among robotic teams with respect to the time taken to complete exploration and path traveled. We observe that having a team of agents with heterogeneous behaviors is beneficial.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08242v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nirabhra Mandal, Aamodh Suresh, Carlos Nieto-Granda, Sonia Mart\'inez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SKYLINK: Scalable and Resilient Link Management in LEO Satellite Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08455</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08455v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The rapid growth of space-based services has established LEO satellite networks as a promising option for global broadband connectivity. Next-generation LEO networks leverage inter-satellite links (ISLs) to provide faster and more reliable communications compared to traditional bent-pipe architectures, even in remote regions. However, the high mobility of satellites, dynamic traffic patterns, and potential link failures pose significant challenges for efficient and resilient routing. To address these challenges, we model the LEO satellite network as a time-varying graph comprising a constellation of satellites and ground stations. Our objective is to minimize a weighted sum of average delay and packet drop rate. Each satellite independently decides how to distribute its incoming traffic to neighboring nodes in real time. Given the infeasibility of finding optimal solutions at scale, due to the exponential growth of routing options and uncertainties in link capacities, we propose SKYLINK, a novel fully distributed learning strategy for link management in LEO satellite networks. SKYLINK enables each satellite to adapt to the time-varying network conditions, ensuring real-time responsiveness, scalability to millions of users, and resilience to network failures, while maintaining low communication overhead and computational complexity. To support the evaluation of SKYLINK at global scale, we develop a new simulator for large-scale LEO satellite networks. For 25.4 million users, SKYLINK reduces the weighted sum of average delay and drop rate by 29% compared to the bent-pipe approach, and by 92% compared to Dijkstra. It lowers drop rates by 95% relative to k-shortest paths, 99% relative to Dijkstra, and 74% compared to the bent-pipe baseline, while achieving up to 46% higher throughput. At the same time, SKYLINK maintains constant computational complexity with respect to constellation size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08455v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wanja de Sombre, Arash Asadi, Debopam Bhattacherjee, Deepak Vasisht, Andrea Ortiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robustness of quantum algorithms: Worst-case fidelity bounds and implications for design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08481</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08481v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Errors occurring on noisy hardware pose a key challenge to reliable quantum computing. Existing techniques such as error correction, mitigation, or suppression typically separate the error handling from the algorithm analysis and design. In this paper, we develop an alternative, algorithm-centered framework for understanding and improving the robustness against errors. For a given quantum algorithm and error model, we derive worst-case fidelity bounds which can be explicitly computed to certify the robustness. We consider general error models including coherent and (Markovian) incoherent errors and allowing for set-based error descriptions to address uncertainty or time-dependence in the errors. Our results give rise to guidelines for robust algorithm design and compilation by optimizing our theoretical robustness measure. Numerical results on algorithm analysis and robust optimization demonstrate the practicality of the framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08481v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julian Berberich, Tobias Fellner, Robert L. Kosut, Christian Holm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FMT$^{x}$: An Efficient and Asymptotically Optimal Extension of the Fast Marching Tree for Dynamic Replanning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08521v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Path planning in dynamic environments remains a core challenge in robotics, especially as autonomous systems are deployed in unpredictable spaces such as warehouses and public roads. While algorithms like Fast Marching Tree (FMT$^{*}$) offer asymptotically optimal solutions in static settings, their single-pass design prevents path revisions which are essential for real-time adaptation. On the other hand, full replanning is often too computationally expensive. This paper introduces FMT$^{x}$, an extension of the Fast Marching Tree algorithm that enables efficient and consistent replanning in dynamic environments. We revisit the neighbor selection rule of FMT$^{*}$ and demonstrate that a minimal change overcomes its single-pass limitation, enabling the algorithm to update cost-to-come values upon discovering better connections without sacrificing asymptotic optimality or computational efficiency. By maintaining a cost-ordered priority queue and applying a selective update condition that uses an expanding neighbor to identify and trigger the re-evaluation of any node with a potentially suboptimal path, FMT$^{x}$ ensures that suboptimal routes are efficiently repaired as the environment evolves. This targeted strategy preserves the inherent efficiency of FMT$^{*}$ while enabling robust adaptation to changes in obstacle configuration. FMT$^{x}$ is proven to recover an asymptotically optimal solution after environmental changes. Experimental results demonstrate that FMT$^{x}$ outperforms the influential replanner RRT$^{x}$, reacting more swiftly to dynamic events with lower computational overhead and thus offering a more effective solution for real-time robotic navigation in unpredictable worlds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08521v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soheil Espahbodini Nia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal control of stochastic networks of $M/M/\infty$ queues with linear costs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08572v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider an arbitrary network of $M/M/\infty$ queues with controlled transitions between queues. We consider optimal control problems where the costs are linear functions of the state and inputs over a finite or infinite horizon. We provide in both cases an explicit characterization of the optimal control policies. We also show that these do not involve state feedback, but they depend on the network topology and system parameters. The results are also illustrated with various examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08572v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Pugliese Carratelli, Ioannis Lestas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Architecting Resilient LLM Agents: A Guide to Secure Plan-then-Execute Implementations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08646</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08646v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: As Large Language Model (LLM) agents become increasingly capable of automating complex, multi-step tasks, the need for robust, secure, and predictable architectural patterns is paramount. This paper provides a comprehensive guide to the ``Plan-then-Execute'' (P-t-E) pattern, an agentic design that separates strategic planning from tactical execution. We explore the foundational principles of P-t-E, detailing its core components - the Planner and the Executor - and its architectural advantages in predictability, cost-efficiency, and reasoning quality over reactive patterns like ReAct (Reason + Act). A central focus is placed on the security implications of this design, particularly its inherent resilience to indirect prompt injection attacks by establishing control-flow integrity. We argue that while P-t-E provides a strong foundation, a defense-in-depth strategy is necessary, and we detail essential complementary controls such as the Principle of Least Privilege, task-scoped tool access, and sandboxed code execution. To make these principles actionable, this guide provides detailed implementation blueprints and working code references for three leading agentic frameworks: LangChain (via LangGraph), CrewAI, and AutoGen. Each framework's approach to implementing the P-t-E pattern is analyzed, highlighting unique features like LangGraph's stateful graphs for re-planning, CrewAI's declarative tool scoping for security, and AutoGen's built-in Docker sandboxing. Finally, we discuss advanced patterns, including dynamic re-planning loops, parallel execution with Directed Acyclic Graphs (DAGs), and the critical role of Human-in-the-Loop (HITL) verification, to offer a complete strategic blueprint for architects, developers, and security engineers aiming to build production-grade, resilient, and trustworthy LLM agents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08646v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ron F. Del Rosario, Klaudia Krawiecka, Christian Schroeder de Witt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TANGO: Traversability-Aware Navigation with Local Metric Control for Topological Goals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08699</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08699v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Visual navigation in robotics traditionally relies on globally-consistent 3D maps or learned controllers, which can be computationally expensive and difficult to generalize across diverse environments. In this work, we present a novel RGB-only, object-level topometric navigation pipeline that enables zero-shot, long-horizon robot navigation without requiring 3D maps or pre-trained controllers. Our approach integrates global topological path planning with local metric trajectory control, allowing the robot to navigate towards object-level sub-goals while avoiding obstacles. We address key limitations of previous methods by continuously predicting local trajectory using monocular depth and traversability estimation, and incorporating an auto-switching mechanism that falls back to a baseline controller when necessary. The system operates using foundational models, ensuring open-set applicability without the need for domain-specific fine-tuning. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our method in both simulated environments and real-world tests, highlighting its robustness and deployability. Our approach outperforms existing state-of-the-art methods, offering a more adaptable and effective solution for visual navigation in open-set environments. The source code is made publicly available: https://github.com/podgorki/TANGO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08699v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ICRA55743.2025.11127998</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Podgorski, Sourav Garg, Mehdi Hosseinzadeh, Lachlan Mares, Feras Dayoub, Ian Reid</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence Guarantees of Model-free Policy Gradient Methods for LQR with Stochastic Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19977v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Policy gradient (PG) methods are the backbone of many reinforcement learning algorithms due to their good performance in policy optimization problems. As a gradient-based approach, PG methods typically rely on knowledge of the system dynamics. If this is not available, trajectory data can be utilized to approximate first-order information. When the data are noisy, gradient estimates become inaccurate and a study that investigates uncertainty estimation and the analysis of its propagation through the algorithm is currently missing. To address this, our work focuses on the Linear Quadratic Regulator (LQR) problem for systems subject to additive stochastic noise. After briefly summarizing the state of the art for cases with a known model, we focus on scenarios where the system dynamics are unknown, and approximate gradient information is obtained using zeroth-order optimization techniques. We analyze the theoretical properties by computing the error in the estimated gradient and examining how this error affects the convergence of PG algorithms. Additionally, we provide global convergence guarantees for various versions of PG methods, including those employing adaptive step sizes and variance reduction techniques, which help increase the convergence rate and reduce sample complexity. This study contributed to characterizing robustness of the study of the robustness of model-free PG methods, aiming to identify their limitations in the presence of stochastic noise and proposing improvements to enhance their applicability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19977v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bowen Song, Andrea Iannelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Resilience-Aware Control in Multi-Robot Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03120</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03120v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Ensuring resilient consensus in multi-robot systems with misbehaving agents remains a challenge, as many existing network resilience properties are inherently combinatorial and globally defined. While previous works have proposed control laws to enhance or preserve resilience in multi-robot networks, they often assume a fixed topology with known resilience properties, or require global state knowledge. These assumptions may be impractical in physically-constrained environments, where safety and resilience requirements are conflicting, or when misbehaving agents share inaccurate state information. In this work, we propose a distributed control law that enables each robot to guarantee resilient consensus and safety during its navigation without fixed topologies using only locally available information. To this end, we establish a sufficient condition for resilient consensus in time-varying networks based on the degree of non-misbehaving or normal agents. Using this condition, we design a Control Barrier Function (CBF)-based controller that guarantees resilient consensus and collision avoidance without requiring estimates of global state and/or control actions of all other robots. Finally, we validate our method through simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03120v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haejoon Lee, Dimitra Panagou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Power-Gas Infrastructure Planning under Weather-induced Supply and Demand Uncertainties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23509</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.23509v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Implementing economy-wide decarbonization strategies based on decarbonizing the power grid via variable renewable energy (VRE) expansion and electrification of end-uses requires new approaches for energy infrastructure planning that consider, among other factors, weather-induced uncertainty in demand and VRE supply. An energy planning model that fails to account for these uncertainties can hinder the intended transition efforts to a low-carbon grid and increase the risk of supply shortage especially during extreme weather conditions. Here, we consider the generation and transmission expansion problem of joint power-gas infrastructure and operations planning under the uncertainty of both demand and renewable supply. We propose two distributionally robust optimization approaches based on moment (MDRO) and Wasserstein distance (WDRO) ambiguity sets to endogenize these uncertainties and account for the change in the underlying distribution of these parameters that is caused by the climate change, among other factors. Furthermore, our model considers the risk-aversion of the energy planners in the modeling framework via the conditional value-at-risk (CVaR) metric. An equivalent mixed-integer linear programming (MILP) reformulation of both modeling frameworks is presented, and a computationally efficient approximation scheme to obtain near-optimal solutions is proposed. We demonstrate the resulting DRO planning models and solution strategy via a New England case study under different levels of end-use electrification and decarbonization targets. Our experiments systematically explore different modeling aspects and compare the DRO models with stochastic programming (SP) results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.23509v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rahman Khorramfar, Dharik Mallapragada, Saurabh Amin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electricity Demand and Grid Impacts of AI Data Centers: Challenges and Prospects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07218</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07218v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The rapid growth of artificial intelligence (AI) is driving an unprecedented increase in the electricity demand of AI data centers, raising emerging challenges for electric power grids. Understanding the characteristics of AI data center loads and their interactions with the grid is therefore critical for ensuring both reliable power system operation and sustainable AI development. This paper provides a comprehensive review and vision of this evolving landscape. Specifically, this paper (i) presents an overview of AI data center infrastructure and its key components, (ii) examines the key characteristics and patterns of electricity demand across the stages of model preparation, training, fine-tuning, and inference, (iii) analyzes the critical challenges that AI data center loads pose to power systems across three interrelated timescales, including long-term planning and interconnection, short-term operation and electricity markets, and real-time dynamics and stability, and (iv) discusses potential solutions from the perspectives of the grid, AI data centers, and AI end-users to address these challenges. By synthesizing current knowledge and outlining future directions, this review aims to guide research and development in support of the joint advancement of AI data centers and power systems toward reliable, efficient, and sustainable operation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07218v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Chen, Xiaoyang Wang, Ana Colacelli, Matt Lee, Le Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guiding Soft Robots with Motor-Imagery Brain Signals and Impedance Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.13441</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.13441v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Integrating Brain-Machine Interfaces into non-clinical applications like robot motion control remains difficult - despite remarkable advancements in clinical settings. Specifically, EEG-based motor imagery systems are still error-prone, posing safety risks when rigid robots operate near humans. This work presents an alternative pathway towards safe and effective operation by combining wearable EEG with physically embodied safety in soft robots. We introduce and test a pipeline that allows a user to move a soft robot's end effector in real time via brain waves that are measured by as few as three EEG channels. A robust motor imagery algorithm interprets the user's intentions to move the position of a virtual attractor to which the end effector is attracted, thanks to a new Cartesian impedance controller. We specifically focus here on planar soft robot-based architected metamaterials, which require the development of a novel control architecture to deal with the peculiar nonlinearities - e.g., non-affinity in control. We preliminarily but quantitatively evaluate the approach on the task of setpoint regulation. We observe that the user reaches the proximity of the setpoint in 66% of steps and that for successful steps, the average response time is 21.5s. We also demonstrate the execution of simple real-world tasks involving interaction with the environment, which would be extremely hard to perform if it were not for the robot's softness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.13441v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/RoboSoft60065.2024.10522005</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2024 IEEE 7th International Conference on Soft Robotics (RoboSoft), San Diego, CA, USA, 2024, pp. 276-283</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Maximilian St\"olzle, Sonal Santosh Baberwal, Daniela Rus, Shirley Coyle, Cosimo Della Santina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Optimal Orders for Entanglement Swapping in Path Graphs: A Greedy Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14040</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14040v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper considers the problem of finding an optimal order for entanglement swapping in a heterogeneous path of quantum repeaters so as to maximize the path throughput defined as the delivery rate of end-to-end entanglements. The primary difficulty in addressing this problem lies in the vast array of possible swapping orders for large paths and the complexity of the expected throughput, which depends on the attributes of each node and edge along the path, as well as the order of swapping. To cope with these issues, we first propose simple approximations in estimating the swapping outcome between two entanglement distributions that can run in constant time, thereby providing an efficient approach for evaluating and comparing different swapping orders, allowing us to solve the problem exactly for small paths. Second, as the number of possible orders grows exponentially with the number of repeaters in the path, we develop an efficient heuristic based on the greedy selection of nodes to sequentially perform swaps according to their swapping scores, defined as the expected number of entanglements resulting from their swaps. The scores are local but dynamic in the sense that they depend not just on the entanglement distributions available on the path but also on prior swapping decisions. Finally, we illustrate the efficiency and effectiveness of our proposed model and approach through extensive experimentation conducted using a general quantum network simulator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14040v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Van Sy Mai, Abderrahim Amlou, Amar Abane, Abdella Battou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computational Concept of the Psyche (in Russian)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07009v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The article provides an overview of approaches to modeling the human psyche in the perspective of building an artificial one. Based on the review, a concept of cognitive architecture is proposed, where the psyche is considered as an operating system of a living or artificial subject, including a space of needs that determines its life meanings in connection with stimuli from the external world, and intelligence as a decision-making system for actions in relation to this world in order to satisfy these needs. Based on the concept, a computational formalization is proposed for creating artificial intelligence systems through learning from experience in the space of a space of needs, taking into account their biological or existential significance for an intelligent agent. Thus, the problem of building general artificial intelligence as a system for making optimal decisions in the space of agent-specific needs under conditions of uncertainty is formalized, with maximization of success in achieving goals, minimization of existential risks and maximization of energy efficiency. A minimal experimental implementation of the model is also provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07009v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Kolonin, Vladimir Kryukov</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
