<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SY updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SY</link>
    <description>cs.SY updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SY" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 05:00:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Development of a velocity form for a class of RNNs, with application to offset-free nonlinear MPC design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15889v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper addresses the offset-free tracking problem for nonlinear systems described by a class of recurrent neural networks (RNNs). To compensate for constant disturbances and guarantee offset-free tracking in the presence of model-plant mismatches, we propose a novel reformulation of the RNN model in velocity form. Conditions based on linear matrix inequalities are then derived for the design of a nonlinear state observer and a nonlinear state-feedback controller, ensuring global or regional closed-loop stability of the origin of the velocity form dynamics. Moreover, to handle input and output constraints, a theoretically sound offset-free nonlinear model predictive control algorithm is developed. The algorithm exploits the velocity form model as the prediction model and the static controller as an auxiliary law for the definition of the terminal ingredients. Simulations on a pH-neutralisation process benchmark demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15889v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniele Ravasio, Bestem Abdulaziz, Marcello Farina, Andrea Ballarino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cyber-Resilient Data-Driven Event-Triggered Secure Control for Autonomous Vehicles Under False Data Injection Attacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15925</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15925v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper proposes a cyber-resilient secure control framework for autonomous vehicles (AVs) subject to false data injection (FDI) threats as actuator attacks. The framework integrates data-driven modeling, event-triggered communication, and fractional-order sliding mode control (FSMC) to enhance the resilience against adversarial interventions. A dynamic model decomposition (DMD)-based methodology is employed to extract the lateral dynamics from real-world data, eliminating the reliance on conventional mechanistic modeling. To optimize communication efficiency, an event-triggered transmission scheme is designed to reduce the redundant transmissions while ensuring system stability. Furthermore, an extended state observer (ESO) is developed for real-time estimation and mitigation of actuator attack effects. Theoretical stability analysis, conducted using Lyapunov methods and linear matrix inequality (LMI) formulations, guarantees exponential error convergence. Extensive simulations validate the proposed event-triggered secure control framework, demonstrating substantial improvements in attack mitigation, communication efficiency, and lateral tracking performance. The results show that the framework effectively counteracts actuator attacks while optimizing communication-resource utilization, making it highly suitable for safety-critical AV applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15925v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yashar Mousavi, Mahsa Tavasoli, Ibrahim Beklan Kucukdemiral, Umit Cali, Abdolhossein Sarrafzadeh, Ali Karimoddini, Afef Fekih</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What Does It Take to Get Guarantees? Systematizing Assumptions in Cyber-Physical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15952</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15952v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Formal guarantees for cyber-physical systems (CPS) rely on diverse assumptions. If satisfied, these assumptions enable the transfer of abstract guarantees into real-world assurances about the deployed CPS. Although assumptions are central to assured CPS, there is little systematic knowledge about what assumptions are made, what guarantees they support, and what it would take to specify them precisely. To fill this gap, we present a survey of assumptions and guarantees in the control, verification, and runtime assurance areas of CPS literature. From 104 papers over a 10-year span (2014-2024), we extracted 423 assumptions and 321 guarantees using grounded-theory coding. We also annotated the assumptions with 21 tags indicating elementary language features needed for specifications. Our analysis highlighted prevalent trends and gaps in CPS assumptions, particularly related to initialization, sensing, perception, neural components, and uncertainty. Our observations culminated in a call to action on reporting and testing CPS assumptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15952v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengyu Li, Saleh Faghfoorian, Ivan Ruchkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics Informed Multi-task Joint Generative Learning for Arterial Vehicle Trajectory Reconstruction Considering Lane Changing Behavior</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16019v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reconstructing complete traffic flow time-space diagrams from vehicle trajectories offer a comprehensive view on traffic dynamics at arterial intersections. However, obtaining full trajectories across networks is costly, and accurately inferring lane-changing (LC) and car-following behaviors in multi-lane environments remains challenging. This study proposes a generative framework for arterial vehicle trajectory reconstruction that jointly models lane-changing and car-following behaviors through physics-informed multi-task joint learning. The framework consists of a Lane-Change Generative Adversarial Network (LC-GAN) and a Trajectory-GAN. The LC-GAN models stochastic LC behavior from historical trajectories while considering physical conditions of arterial intersections, such as signal control, geometric configuration, and interactions with surrounding vehicles. The Trajectory-GAN then incorporates LC information from the LC-GAN with initial trajectories generated from physics-based car-following models, refining them in a data-driven manner to adapt to dynamic traffic conditions. The proposed framework is designed to reconstruct complete trajectories from only a small subset of connected vehicle (CV) trajectories; for example, even a single observed trajectory per lane, by incorporating partial trajectory information into the generative process. A multi-task joint learning facilitates synergistic interaction between the LC-GAN and Trajectory-GAN, allowing each component to serves as both auxiliary supervision and a physical condition for the other. Validation using two real-world trajectory datasets demonstrates that the framework outperforms conventional benchmark models in reconstructing complete time-space diagrams for multi-lane arterial intersections. This research advances the integration of trajectory-based sensing from CVs with physics-informed deep learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16019v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengyun Xu, Jie Fang, Eui-Jin Kim, Tony Z. Qiu, Prateek Bansal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bellman Memory Units: A neuromorphic framework for synaptic reinforcement learning with an evolving network topology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16066</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16066v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Application of neuromorphic edge devices for control is limited by the constraints on gradient-free online learning and scalability of the hardware across control problems. This paper introduces a synaptic Q-learning algorithm for the control of the classical Cartpole, where the Bellman equations are incorporated at the synaptic level. This formulation enables the iterative evolution of the network topology, represented as a directed graph, throughout the training process. This is followed by a similar approach called neuromorphic Bellman Memory Units (BMU(s)), which are implemented with the Neural Engineering Framework on Intel's Loihi neuromorphic chip. Topology evolution, in conjunction with mixed-signal computation, leverages the optimization of the number of neurons and synapses that could be used to design spike-based reinforcement learning accelerators. The proposed architecture can potentially reduce resource utilization on board, aiding the manufacturing of compact application-specific neuromorphic ICs. Moreover, the on-chip learning introduced in this work and implemented on a neuromorphic chip can enable adaptation to unseen control scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16066v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shreyan Banerjee, Aasifa Rounak, Vikram Pakrashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parallelizable Complex Neural Dynamics Models for PMSM Temperature Estimation with Hardware Acceleration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16093v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate and efficient thermal dynamics models of permanent magnet synchronous motors are vital to efficient thermal management strategies. Physics-informed methods combine model-based and data-driven methods, offering greater flexibility than model-based methods and superior explainability compared to data-driven methods. Nonetheless, there are still challenges in balancing real-time performance, estimation accuracy, and explainability. This paper presents a hardware-efficient complex neural dynamics model achieved through the linear decoupling, diagonalization, and reparameterization of the state-space model, introducing a novel paradigm for the physics-informed method that offers high explainability and accuracy in electric motor temperature estimation tasks. We validate this physics-informed method on an NVIDIA A800 GPU using the JAX machine learning framework, parallel prefix sum algorithm, and Compute Unified Device Architecture (CUDA) platform. We demonstrate its superior estimation accuracy and parallelizable hardware acceleration capabilities through experimental evaluation on a real electric motor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16093v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinyuan Liao, Shaowei Chen, Shuai Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Describing Functions and Phase Response Curves of Excitable Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16235v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The describing function (DF) and phase response curve (PRC) are classical tools for the analysis of feedback oscillations and rhythmic behaviors, widely used across control engineering, biology, and neuroscience. These tools are known to have limitations in networks of relaxation oscillators and excitable systems. For this reason, the paper proposes a novel approach tailored to excitable systems. Our analysis focuses on the discrete-event operator mapping input trains of events to output trains of events. The methodology is illustrated on the excitability model of Hodgkin-Huxley. The proposed framework provides a basis for designing and analyzing central pattern generators in networks of excitable neurons, with direct relevance to neuromorphic control and neurophysiology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16235v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robin Wroblowski, Rodolphe Sepulchre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Self-Triggered Control Approaches Optimizing Sensors Utilization with Asynchronous Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16253v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Most control systems run on digital hardware with limited communication resources. This work develops self-triggered control for linear systems where sensors update independently (asynchronous measurements). The controller computes an optimal horizon at each sampling instant, selecting which sensor to read over the next several time steps to maximize inter-sample intervals while maintaining stability.
  Two implementations address computational complexity. The online version solves an optimization problem at each update for theoretical optimality. The offline version precomputes optimal horizons using conic partitioning, reducing online computation to a lookup. Both guarantee exponential stability for unperturbed systems and global uniform ultimate boundedness for systems with bounded disturbances. Simulations demonstrate 59-74\% reductions in sensor utilization compared to periodic sampling. The framework enables resource-efficient control in networked systems with communication constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16253v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abbas Tariverdi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatially Dependent Sampling of Component Failures for Power System Preventive Control Against Hurricane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16279v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Preventive control is a crucial strategy for power system operation against impending natural hazards, and its effectiveness fundamentally relies on the realism of scenario generation. While most existing studies employ sequential Monte Carlo simulation and assume independent sampling of component failures, this oversimplification neglects the spatial correlations induced by meteorological factors such as hurricanes. In this paper, we identify and address the gap in modeling spatial dependence among component failures under extreme weather. We analyze how the mean, variance, and correlation structure of weather intensity random variables influence the correlation of component failures. To fill this gap, we propose a spatially dependent sampling method that enables joint sampling of multiple component failures by generating correlated meteorological intensity random variables. Comparative studies show that our approach captures long-tailed scenarios and reveals more extreme events than conventional methods. Furthermore, we evaluate the impact of scenario selection on preventive control performance. Our key findings are: (1) Strong spatial correlations in uncertain weather intensity consistently lead to interdependent component failures, regardless of mean value level; (2) The proposed method uncovers more high-severity scenarios that are missed by independent sampling; (3) Preventive control requires balancing load curtailment and over-generation costs under different scenario severities; (4) Ignoring failure correlations results in underestimating risk from high-severity events, undermining the robustness of preventive control strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16279v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziyue Li, Guanglun Zhang, Grant Ruan, Haiwang Zhong, Chongqing Kang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Comprehensive Study on Cyber Attack Vectors in EV Traction Power Electronics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16399v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Electric vehicles (EVs) have drastically changed the auto industry and developed a new era of technologies where power electronics play the leading role in traction management, energy conversion and vehicle control processes. Nevertheless, this is a digital transformation, and the cyber-attack surface area has increased considerably, to the point that EV traction power electronics are becoming vulnerable to various cybersecurity risks. This paper is able to provide its expertise on possible cyber-attack vectors which can attack important parts of the traction, powertrain, including things like inverters, motor controllers, and communicated systems within the embedded bits. Using the (STRIDE) threat modeling framework, the research outlines and groups the vulnerabilities of the architecture and runs some attack simulations, such as the Denial of Service (DoS), spoofing, firmware manipulation, and data injection. The experiments prove the fact that a slight interruption in the control signal, the sensed data may lead to the severe working implications, such as unstable sensor values of the torque, abnormal voltage shifts, and entire system freezes. These results highlight the high priority on the need of injective embedded intrusion preventive mechanisms and secure design of firmware in EV powertrain electronics. In this paper, the author makes his contribution to the general body of knowledge that underpins the links existing between cyber security practices and the peculiar needs of automotive power electronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16399v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Information Systems Engineering and Management, 2023, 8(2)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Siddhesh Pimpale</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy-Efficient and Actuator-Friendly Control Under Wave Disturbances: Model Reference vs. PID for Thruster Surge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16413v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we compare a model reference control (MRC) strategy against conventional PID controllers (tuned via metaheuristic algorithms) for surge velocity control of a thruster-driven marine system, under combined wave disturbance and sensor noise. The goal is to evaluate not only tracking performance but also control energy usage and actuator stress. A high-order identified model of a Blue Robotics T200 thruster with a 2~kg vehicle is used, with an 8~N sinusoidal wave disturbance applied and white noise ( added to the speed measurement. Results show that the optimized MRC (MRC-R*) yields the lowest control energy and smoothest command among all controllers, while maintaining acceptable tracking. The IMC-based design performs closely. In contrast, PID controllers achieve comparable RMS tracking error but at the cost of excessive actuator activity and energy use, making them impractical in such scenarios. Future</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16413v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>An{\i}l Erdin\c{c} T\"uretken, Hakan Ersoy, Aslihan Kartci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Second-Order MPC-Based Distributed Q-Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16424v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The state of the art for model predictive control (MPC)-based distributed Q-learning is limited to first-order gradient updates of the MPC parameterization. In general, using secondorder information can significantly improve the speed of convergence for learning, allowing the use of higher learning rates without introducing instability. This work presents a second-order extension to MPC-based Q-learning with updates distributed across local agents, relying only on locally available information and neighbor-to-neighbor communication. In simulation the approach is demonstrated to significantly outperform first-order distributed Q-learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16424v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Mallick, Filippo Airaldi, Azita Dabiri, Bart De Schutter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tube-Based Model Predictive Control with Random Fourier Features for Nonlinear Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16425v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a computationally efficient approach for robust Model Predictive Control of nonlinear systems by combining Random Fourier Features with tube-based MPC. Tube-based Model Predictive Control provides robust constraint satisfaction under bounded model uncertainties arising from approximation errors and external disturbances. The Random Fourier Features method approximates nonlinear system dynamics by solving a numerically tractable least-squares problem, thereby reducing the approximation error. We develop the integration of RFF-based residual learning with tube MPC and demonstrate its application to an autonomous vehicle path-tracking problem using a nonlinear bicycle model. Compared to the linear baseline, the proposed method reduces the tube size by approximately 50%, leading to less conservative behavior and resulting in around 70% smaller errors in the test scenario. Furthermore, the proposed method achieves real-time performance while maintaining provable robustness guarantees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16425v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\'Akos M. Bokor, Tam\'as D\'ozsa, Felix Biert\"umpfel, \'Ad\'am Szab\'o</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observer Design for Singularly Perturbed Linear Networked Control Systems Subject to Measurement Noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16469</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16469v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper addresses the emulation-based observer design for linear networked control systems (NCS) operating at two time scales in the presence of measurement noise. The system is formulated as a hybrid singularly perturbed dynamical system, enabling the systematic use of singular perturbation techniques to derive explicit bounds on the maximum allowable transmission intervals (MATI) for both fast and slow communication channels. Under the resulting conditions, the proposed observer guarantees that the estimation error satisfies a global exponential derivative-input-to-state stability (DISS)-like property, where the ultimate bound scales proportionally with the magnitudes of the measurement noise and the time derivative of the control input. The effectiveness of the approach is illustrated through a numerical example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16469v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weixuan Wang, Alejandro I. Maass, Dragan Ne\v{s}i\'c, Ying Tan, Romain Postoyan, W. P. M. H. Heemels</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid and Accurate Changepoint Detection of Power System Forced Oscillations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15812v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper describes a new approach for using changepoint detection (CPD) to estimate the starting and stopping times of a forced oscillation (FO) in measured power system data. As with a previous application of CPD to this problem, the pruned exact linear time (PELT) algorithm is used. However, instead of allowing PELT to automatically tune its penalty parameter, a method of manually providing it is presented that dramatically reduces computation time without sacrificing accuracy. Additionally, the new algorithm requires fewer input parameters and provides a formal, data-driven approach to setting the minimum FO segment length to consider as troublesome for an electromechanical mode meter. A low-order ARMAX representation of the minniWECC model is used to test the approach, where a 98\% reduction in computation time is enjoyed with high estimation accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15812v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luke Dosiek, Akaash Karn, Frank Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-informed Gaussian Processes as Linear Model Predictive Controller with Constraint Satisfaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16195v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Model Predictive Control evolved as the state of the art paradigm for safety critical control tasks. Control-as-Inference approaches thereof model the constrained optimization problem as a probabilistic inference problem. The constraints have to be implemented into the inference model. A recently introduced physics-informed Gaussian Process method uses Control-as-Inference with a Gaussian likelihood for state constraint modeling, but lacks guarantees of open-loop constraint satisfaction. We mitigate the lack of guarantees via an additional sampling step using Hamiltonian Monte Carlo sampling in order to obtain safe rollouts of the open-loop dynamics which are then used to obtain an approximation of the truncated normal distribution which has full probability mass in the safe area. We provide formal guarantees of constraint satisfaction while maintaining the ODE structure of the Gaussian Process on a discretized grid. Moreover, we show that we are able to perform optimization of a quadratic cost function by closed form Gaussian Process computations only and introduce the Mat\'ern kernel into the inference model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16195v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\"orn Tebbe, Andreas Besginow, Markus Lange-Hegermann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Operation Recipes with Reinforcement Learning for Safe and Interpretable Control of Chemical Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16297</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16297v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Optimal operation of chemical processes is vital for energy, resource, and cost savings in chemical engineering. The problem of optimal operation can be tackled with reinforcement learning, but traditional reinforcement learning methods face challenges due to hard constraints related to quality and safety that must be strictly satisfied, and the large amount of required training data. Chemical processes often cannot provide sufficient experimental data, and while detailed dynamic models can be an alternative, their complexity makes it computationally intractable to generate the needed data. Optimal control methods, such as model predictive control, also struggle with the complexity of the underlying dynamic models. Consequently, many chemical processes rely on manually defined operation recipes combined with simple linear controllers, leading to suboptimal performance and limited flexibility.
  In this work, we propose a novel approach that leverages expert knowledge embedded in operation recipes. By using reinforcement learning to optimize the parameters of these recipes and their underlying linear controllers, we achieve an optimized operation recipe. This method requires significantly less data, handles constraints more effectively, and is more interpretable than traditional reinforcement learning methods due to the structured nature of the recipes. We demonstrate the potential of our approach through simulation results of an industrial batch polymerization reactor, showing that it can approach the performance of optimal controllers while addressing the limitations of existing methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16297v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dean Brandner, Sergio Lucia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VersaPants: A Loose-Fitting Textile Capacitive Sensing System for Lower-Body Motion Capture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16346</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16346v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present VersaPants, the first loose-fitting, textile-based capacitive sensing system for lower-body motion capture, built on the open-hardware VersaSens platform. By integrating conductive textile patches and a compact acquisition unit into a pair of pants, the system reconstructs lower-body pose without compromising comfort. Unlike IMU-based systems that require user-specific fitting or camera-based methods that compromise privacy, our approach operates without fitting adjustments and preserves user privacy. VersaPants is a custom-designed smart garment featuring 6 capacitive channels per leg. We employ a lightweight Transformer-based deep learning model that maps capacitance signals to joint angles, enabling embedded implementation on edge platforms. To test our system, we collected approximately 3.7 hours of motion data from 11 participants performing 16 daily and exercise-based movements. The model achieves a mean per-joint position error (MPJPE) of 11.96 cm and a mean per-joint angle error (MPJAE) of 12.3 degrees across the hip, knee, and ankle joints, indicating the model's ability to generalize to unseen users and movements. A comparative analysis of existing textile-based deep learning architectures reveals that our model achieves competitive reconstruction performance with up to 22 times fewer parameters and 18 times fewer FLOPs, enabling real-time inference at 42 FPS on a commercial smartwatch without quantization. These results position VersaPants as a promising step toward scalable, comfortable, and embedded motion-capture solutions for fitness, healthcare, and wellbeing applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16346v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Deniz Kasap (\'Ecole Polytechnique F\'ed\'erale de Lausanne), Taraneh Aminosharieh Najafi (\'Ecole Polytechnique F\'ed\'erale de Lausanne), J\'er\^ome Paul R\'emy Thevenot (\'Ecole Polytechnique F\'ed\'erale de Lausanne), Jonathan Dan (\'Ecole Polytechnique F\'ed\'erale de Lausanne), Stefano Albini (\'Ecole Polytechnique F\'ed\'erale de Lausanne), David Atienza (\'Ecole Polytechnique F\'ed\'erale de Lausanne)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CorrectHDL: Agentic HDL Design with LLMs Leveraging High-Level Synthesis as Reference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16395</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16395v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable potential in hardware front-end design using hardware description languages (HDLs). However, their inherent tendency toward hallucination often introduces functional errors into the generated HDL designs. To address this issue, we propose the framework CorrectHDL that leverages high-level synthesis (HLS) results as functional references to correct potential errors in LLM-generated HDL designs.The input to the proposed framework is a C/C++ program that specifies the target circuit's functionality. The program is provided to an LLM to directly generate an HDL design, whose syntax errors are repaired using a Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) mechanism. The functional correctness of the LLM-generated circuit is iteratively improved by comparing its simulated behavior with an HLS reference design produced by conventional HLS tools, which ensures the functional correctness of the result but can lead to suboptimal area and power efficiency. Experimental results demonstrate that circuits generated by the proposed framework achieve significantly better area and power efficiency than conventional HLS designs and approach the quality of human-engineered circuits. Meanwhile, the correctness of the resulting HDL implementation is maintained, highlighting the effectiveness and potential of agentic HDL design leveraging the generative capabilities of LLMs and the rigor of traditional correctness-driven IC design flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16395v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.PL</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kangwei Xu, Grace Li Zhang, Ulf Schlichtmann, Bing Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A convex approach for Markov chain estimation from aggregate data via inverse optimal transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16458v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We address the problem of identifying the dynamical law governing the evolution of a population of indistinguishable particles, when only aggregate distributions at successive times are observed. Assuming a Markovian evolution on a discrete state space, the task reduces to estimating the underlying transition probability matrix from distributional data. We formulate this inverse problem within the framework of entropic optimal transport, as a joint optimization over the transition matrix and the transport plans connecting successive distributions. This formulation results in a convex optimization problem, and we propose an efficient iterative algorithm based on the entropic proximal method. We illustrate the accuracy and convergence of the method in two numerical setups, considering estimation from independent snapshots and estimation from a time series of aggregate observations, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16458v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michele Mascherpa, Axel Ringh, Amirhossein Taghvaei, Johan Karlsson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Auditable Ledger Snapshot for Non-Repudiable Cross-Blockchain Communication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16560v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Blockchain interoperability is increasingly recognized as the centerpiece for robust interactions among decentralized services. Blockchain ledgers are generally tamper-proof and thus enforce non-repudiation for transactions recorded within the same network. However, such a guarantee does not hold for cross-blockchain transactions. When disruptions occur due to malicious activities or system failures within one blockchain network, foreign networks can take advantage by denying legitimate claims or mounting fraudulent liabilities against the defenseless network. In response, this paper introduces InterSnap, a novel blockchain snapshot archival methodology, for enabling auditability of crossblockchain transactions, enforcing non-repudiation. InterSnap introduces cross-chain transaction receipts that ensure their irrefutability. Snapshots of ledger data along with these receipts are utilized as non-repudiable proof of bilateral agreements among different networks. InterSnap enhances system resilience through a distributed snapshot generation process, need-based snapshot scheduling process, and archival storage and sharing via decentralized platforms. Through a prototype implementation based on Hyperledger Fabric, we conducted experiments using on-premise machines, AWS public cloud instances, as well as a private cloud infrastructure. We establish that InterSnap can recover from malicious attacks while preserving crosschain transaction receipts. Additionally, our proposed solution demonstrates adaptability to increasing loads while securely transferring snapshot archives with minimal overhead.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16560v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tirthankar Sengupta, Bishakh Chandra Ghosh, Sandip Chakraborty, Shamik Sural</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synthesis of Safety Specifications for Probabilistic Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16579v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ensuring that agents satisfy safety specifications can be crucial in safety-critical environments. While methods exist for controller synthesis with safe temporal specifications, most existing methods restrict safe temporal specifications to probabilistic-avoidance constraints. Formal methods typically offer more expressive ways to express safety in probabilistic systems, such as Probabilistic Computation Tree Logic (PCTL) formulas. Thus, in this paper, we develop a new approach that supports more general temporal properties expressed in PCTL. Our contribution is twofold. First, we develop a theoretical framework for the Synthesis of safe-PCTL specifications. We show how the reducing global specification satisfaction to local constraints, and define CPCTL, a fragment of safe-PCTL. We demonstrate how the expressiveness of CPCTL makes it a relevant fragment for the Synthesis Problem. Second, we leverage these results and propose a new Value Iteration-based algorithm to solve the synthesis problem for these more general temporal properties, and we prove the soundness and completeness of our method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16579v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaspard Ohlmann, Edwin Hamel-De le Court, Francesco Belardinelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stabilizing Policy Gradient Methods via Reward Profiling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16629v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Policy gradient methods, which have been extensively studied in the last decade, offer an effective and efficient framework for reinforcement learning problems. However, their performances can often be unsatisfactory, suffering from unreliable reward improvements and slow convergence, due to high variance in gradient estimations. In this paper, we propose a universal reward profiling framework that can be seamlessly integrated with any policy gradient algorithm, where we selectively update the policy based on high-confidence performance estimations. We theoretically justify that our technique will not slow down the convergence of the baseline policy gradient methods, but with high probability, will result in stable and monotonic improvements of their performance. Empirically, on eight continuous-control benchmarks (Box2D and MuJoCo/PyBullet), our profiling yields up to 1.5x faster convergence to near-optimal returns, up to 1.75x reduction in return variance on some setups. Our profiling approach offers a general, theoretically grounded path to more reliable and efficient policy learning in complex environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16629v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shihab Ahmed, El Houcine Bergou, Aritra Dutta, Yue Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OptimizedDP: An Efficient, User-friendly Library For Optimal Control and Dynamic Programming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.05520</link>
      <description>arXiv:2204.05520v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces OptimizedDP, a high-performance software library for several common grid-based dynamic programming (DP) algorithms used in control theory and robotics. Specifically, OptimizedDP provides functions to numerically solve a class of time-dependent (dynamic) Hamilton-Jacobi (HJ) partial differential equations (PDEs), time-independent (static) HJ PDEs, and additionally value iteration for continuous action-state space Markov Decision Processes (MDP). The computational complexity of grid-based DP is exponential with respect to the number of grid or state space dimensions, and thus can have bad execution runtimes and memory usage whenapplied to large state spaces. We leverage the user-friendliness of Python for different problem specifications without sacrificing the efficiency of the core computation. This is achieved by implementing the core part of the code which the user does not see in heterocl, a framework we use to abstract away details of how computation is parallelized. Compared to similar toolboxes for level set methods that are used to solve the HJ PDE, our toolbox makes solving the PDE at higher dimensions possible as well as achieving an order of magnitude improvements in execution times, while keeping the interface easy for specifying different problem descriptions. Because of that, the toolbox has been adopted to solve control and optimization problems that were considered intractable before. Our toolbox is available publicly at https://github.com/SFU-MARS/optimized_dp.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2204.05520v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minh Bui, Hanyang Hu, Chong He, Michael Lu, George Giovanis, Arrvindh Shriraman, Mo Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Differentially-Private Distributed Model Predictive Control of Linear Discrete-Time Systems with Global Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18690v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Distributed model predictive control (DMPC) has attracted extensive attention as it can explicitly handle system constraints and achieve optimal control in a decentralized manner. However, the deployment of DMPC strategies generally requires the sharing of sensitive data among subsystems, which may violate the privacy of participating systems. In this paper, we propose a differentially-private DMPC algorithm for linear discrete-time systems subject to coupled global constraints. Specifically, we first show that a conventional distributed dual gradient algorithm can be used to address the considered DMPC problem but cannot provide strong privacy preservation. Then, to protect privacy against the eavesdropper, we incorporate a differential-privacy noise injection mechanism into the DMPC framework and prove that the resulting distributed optimization algorithm can ensure both provable convergence to a global optimal solution and rigorous $\epsilon$-differential privacy. In addition, an implementation strategy of the DMPC is designed such that the recursive feasibility and stability of the closed-loop system are guaranteed. Simulation results are provided to demonstrate the effectiveness of the developed approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18690v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaixiang Zhang, Yongqiang Wang, Ziyou Song, Zhaojian Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Barrier-Riccati Synthesis for Nonlinear Safe Control with Expanded Region of Attraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.15453v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a Riccati-based framework for safety-critical nonlinear control that integrates the barrier states (BaS) methodology with the State-Dependent Riccati Equation (SDRE) approach. The BaS formulation embeds safety constraints into the system dynamics via auxiliary states, enabling safety to be treated as a control objective. To overcome the limited region of attraction in linear BaS controllers, we extend the framework to nonlinear systems using SDRE synthesis applied to the barrier-augmented dynamics and derive a matrix inequality condition that certifies forward invariance of a large region of attraction and guarantees asymptotic safe stabilization. The resulting controller is computed online via pointwise Riccati solutions. We validate the method on an unstable constrained system and cluttered quadrotor navigation tasks, demonstrating improved constraint handling, scalability, and robustness near safety boundaries. This framework offers a principled and computationally tractable solution for synthesizing nonlinear safe feedback in safety-critical environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.15453v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hassan Almubarak, Maitham F. AL-Sunni, Justin T. Dubbin, Nader Sadegh, John M. Dolan, Evangelos A. Theodorou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Renewable-Colocated Green Hydrogen Production: Optimality, Profitability, and Policy Impacts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.18368v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the optimal green hydrogen production and energy market participation of a renewable-colocated hydrogen producer (RCHP) that utilizes onsite renewable generation for both hydrogen production and grid services. Under deterministic and stochastic profit-maximization frameworks, we analyze RCHP's multiple market participation models and derive closed-form optimal scheduling policies that dynamically allocate renewable energy to hydrogen production and electricity export to the wholesale market. Analytical characterizations of the RCHP's operating profit and the optimal sizing of renewable and electrolyzer capacities are obtained. We use real-time renewable production and electricity price data from three independent system operators to assess impacts from market prices and environmental policies of renewable energy and green hydrogen subsidies on RCHP's profitability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.18368v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siying Li, Lang Tong, Timothy Mount, Kanchan Upadhyay, Harris Eisenhardt, Pradip Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear Control of a Quadrotor UAV Using Backstepping-Based Sliding Mode Technique</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14195v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents the development of a sliding mode controller using the backstepping approach. The controller is employed to synthesize tracking errors and Lyapunov functions. A novel state-space representation is formulated by incorporating the dynamics of the quadrotor and accounting for non-holonomic constraints. The proposed sliding mode controller effectively addresses system nonlinearities and improves tracking of predefined trajectories. Simulation results are presented graphically to demonstrate the controller's performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14195v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thien Nhan Vo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultra-Low Insertion Loss Stepped Impedance Resonator Topology for HTSC RF Front-End</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.14447v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the design, fabrication, and measurement of a high-temperature superconductor (HTSC) Stepped Impedance Resonator (SIR) band-pass filter for S-band applications, and its incorporation into a cryogenic receiver cascade. The 11-pole filter, implemented in YBa2Cu3O(7-x) (YBCO) thin films on sapphire, exhibits an ultra-low insertion loss (IL) of -0.1~dB, a sharp roll-off of 100~MHz, and a rejection level exceeding --80~dB. These measured results represent, to the best of our knowledge, the lowest reported IL for an S-band filter with this number of poles. When integrated with a cryogenic low-noise amplifier (LNA), system-level simulations and measurements predict a receiver noise figure (NF) of 0.34~dB at 3.39~GHz, enabling a 20% increase in radar detection range compared with conventional copper-based front ends. This work demonstrates the feasibility of practical HTSC-based RF front-ends for next-generation communication and radar systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.14447v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilan Kurtser, Yoav Koral, Eldad Holdengreber, Shmuel E. Schacham, Eliyahu Farber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete Event System Modeling of Neuromorphic Circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15594v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Excitable neuromorphic circuits are physical models of event behaviors: their continuous-time trajectories consist of sequences of discrete events. This paper explores the possibility of extracting a discrete-event model out of the physical continuous-time model. We discuss the potential of this methodology for analysis and design of neuromorphic control systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15594v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koen Scheres, Rodolphe Sepulchre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Continuous sEMG-Based Prosthetic Hand Control System Without Motion or Force Sensors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00014v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Regressively-based surface electromyography (sEMG) prosthetics are widely used for their ability to continuously convert muscle activity into finger force and motion. However, they typically require additional kinematic or dynamic sensors, which increases complexity and limits practical application. To address this, this paper proposes a method based on the simplified near-linear relationship between sEMG and finger force, using the near-linear model ResDD proposed in this work. By applying the principle that a line can be determined by two points, we eliminate the need for complex sensor calibration. Specifically, by recording the sEMG during maximum finger flexion and extension, and assigning corresponding forces of 1 and -1, the ResDD model can fit the simplified relationship between sEMG signals and force, enabling continuous prediction and control of finger force and gestures. Offline experiments were conducted to evaluate the model's classification accuracy and its ability to learn sufficient information. It uses interpolation analysis to open up the internal structure of the trained model and checks whether the fitted curve of the model conforms to the nearly linear relationship between sEMG and force. Finally, online control and sine wave tracking experiments were carried out to further verify the practicality of the proposed method. The results show that the method effectively extracts meaningful information from sEMG and accurately decodes them. The near-linear model sufficiently reflects the expected relationship between sEMG and finger force. Fitting this simplified near-linear relationship is adequate to achieve continuous and smooth control of finger force and gestures, confirming the feasibility and effectiveness of the proposed approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00014v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gang Liu, Ye Sun, Zhenxiang Wang, Chuanmei Xi, Ziyang He, Shanshan Guo, Rui Zhang, Dezhong Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>System Filter-Based Common Components Modeling for Cross-Subject EEG Decoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05268v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Brain-computer interface (BCI) technology enables direct communication between the brain and external devices through electroencephalography (EEG) signals. However, existing decoding models often mix common and personalized components, leading to interference from individual variability that limits cross-subject decoding performance. To address this issue, this paper proposes a system filter that extends the concept of signal filtering to the system level. The method expands a system into its spectral representation, selectively removes unnecessary components, and reconstructs the system from the retained target components, thereby achieving explicit system-level decomposition and filtering. We further integrate the system filter into a Cross-Subject Decoding framework based on the System Filter (CSD-SF) and evaluate it on the four-class motor imagery (MI) task of the BCIC IV 2a dataset. Personalized models are transformed into relation spectrums, and statistical testing across subjects is used to remove personalized components. The remaining stable relations, representing common components across subjects, are then used to construct a common model for cross-subject decoding. Experimental results show an average improvement of 3.28% in decoding accuracy over baseline methods, demonstrating that the proposed system filter effectively isolates stable common components and enhances model robustness and generalizability in cross-subject EEG decoding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05268v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoyuan Li, Xinru Xue, Bohan Zhang, Ye Sun, Shoushuo Xi, Gang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Binary Decision Process in Pre-Evacuation Behavior</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.08284v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In crowd evacuation the time interval before decisive movement towards a safe place is defined as the pre-evacuation phase, and it has crucial impact on the total time required for safe egress. This process mainly refers to situation awareness and response to an external stressors, e.g., fire alarms. Due to the complexity of human cognitive process, simulation is used to study this important time interval. In this paper a binary decision process is formulated to simulate pre-evacuation time of many evacuees in a given social context. The model combines the classic opinion dynamics (the French-DeGroot model) with binary phase transition to describe how group pre-evacuation time emerges from individual interaction. The model parameters are quantitatively meaningful to human factors research within socio-psychological background, e.g., whether an individual is stubborn or open-minded, or what kind of the social topology exists among the individuals and how it matters in aggregating individuals into social groups. The modeling framework also describes collective motion of many evacuee agents in a planar space, and the resulting multi-agent system is partly similar to the Vicsek flocking model, and it is meaningful to explore complex social behavior during phase transition of a non-equilibrium process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.08284v4</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peng N. Wang, Peter B. Luh, Xuesong Lu, Peter Sincak, Laura Pitukova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistically Assuring Safety of Control Systems using Ensembles of Safety Filters and Conformal Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07899v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Safety assurance is a fundamental requirement for deploying learning-enabled autonomous systems. Hamilton-Jacobi (HJ) reachability analysis is a fundamental method for formally verifying safety and generating safe controllers. However, computing the HJ value function that characterizes the backward reachable set (BRS) of a set of user-defined failure states is computationally expensive, especially for high-dimensional systems, motivating the use of reinforcement learning approaches to approximate the value function. Unfortunately, a learned value function and its corresponding safe policy are not guaranteed to be correct. The learned value function evaluated at a given state may not be equal to the actual safety return achieved by following the learned safe policy. To address this challenge, we introduce a conformal prediction-based (CP) framework that bounds such uncertainty. We leverage CP to provide probabilistic safety guarantees when using learned HJ value functions and policies to prevent control systems from reaching failure states. Specifically, we use CP to calibrate the switching between the unsafe nominal controller and the learned HJ-based safe policy and to derive safety guarantees under this switched policy. We also investigate using an ensemble of independently trained HJ value functions as a safety filter and compare this ensemble approach to using individual value functions alone.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07899v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ihab Tabbara, Yuxuan Yang, Hussein Sibai</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
