<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SY updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SY</link>
    <description>cs.SY updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SY" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 02:38:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Which Top Energy-Intensive Manufacturing Countries Can Compete in a Renewable Energy Future?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00242</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00242v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a world increasingly powered by renewables and aiming for greenhouse gas-neutral industrial production, the future competitiveness of todays top manufacturing countries is questioned. This study applies detailed energy system modeling to quantify the Renewable Pull, an incentive for industry relocation exerted by countries with favorable renewable conditions. Results reveal that the Renewable Pull is not a cross-industrial phenomenon but strongly depends on the relationship between energy costs and transport costs. The intensity of the Renewable Pull varies, with China, India, and Japan facing a significantly stronger effect than Germany and the United States. Incorporating national capital cost assumptions proves critical, reducing Germanys Renewable Pull by a factor of six and positioning it as the second least affected top manufacturing country after Saudi Arabia. Using Germany as a case study, the analysis moreover illustrates that targeted import strategies, especially within the EU, can nearly eliminate the Renewable Pull, offering policymakers clear options for risk mitigation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00242v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arne Burdack, Maximilian Stargardt, Christoph Winkler, Konrad Klein, Detlef Stolten, Jochen Linssen, Heidi Heinrichs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning a Network Digital Twin as a Hybrid System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00291v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Network digital twin (NDT) models are virtual models that replicate the behavior of physical communication networks and are considered a key technology component to enable novel features and capabilities in future 6G networks. In this work, we focus on NDTs that model the communication quality properties of a multi-cell, dynamically changing wireless network over a workspace populated with multiple moving users. We propose an NDT modeled as a hybrid system, where each mode corresponds to a different base station and comprises sub-modes that correspond to areas of the workspace with similar network characteristics. The proposed hybrid NDT is identified and continuously improved through an annealing optimization-based learning algorithm, driven by online data measurements collected by the users. The advantages of the proposed hybrid NDT are studied with respect to memory and computational efficiency, data consumption, and the ability to timely adapt to network changes. Finally, we validate the proposed methodology on real experimental data collected from a two-cell 5G testbed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00291v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christos Mavridis, Fernando S. Barbosa, Hamed Farhadi, Karl H. Johansson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing the Impact of Demand Response on Short-Circuit Current via a Unit Commitment Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00296v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In low-carbon grids, system flexibility can be enhanced through mechanisms such as Demand Response (DR), enabling the efficient utilization of renewable energy. However, as Synchronous Generators (SGs) are being replaced with renewable energy characterized by Inverter-Based Resources (IBR), system stability is severely affected. Due to the limited overload capability of IBR, their Short-Circuit Current (SCC) contribution is much smaller than that of SGs, which may result in protection devices failing to trip during faults. Consequently, the remaining SGs play a key role in offering sufficient SCC volumes. Given that the commitment of SGs is closely related to system load, DR can thus indirectly affect their SCC provision, a relationship that has not been investigated. Therefore, this paper incorporates both DR and SCC constraints into a unit commitment model and conducts studies on an IEEE 30-bus system. The results show that although DR can reduce social costs by lowering power demand, it may also lead to inadequate SCC levels. Nevertheless, the cost increases by only 0.3% when DR is combined with SCC constraints, indicating that DR can actually help achieve a stable system in a cost-effective manner.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00296v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peng Wang, Zhengmao Li, Luis Badesa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal BESS Sizing and Placement for Mitigating EV-Induced Voltage Violations: A Scalable Spatio-Temporal Adaptive Targeting Strategy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00297</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00297v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The escalating adoption of electric vehicles (EVs) and the growing demand for charging solutions are driving a surge in EV charger installations in distribution networks. However, this rising EV load strains the distribution grid, causing severe voltage drops, particularly at feeder extremities. This study proposes a proactive voltage management (PVM) framework that can integrate Monte Carlo-based simulations of varying EV charging loads to (i) identify potential voltage violations through a voltage violation analysis (VVA) model, and (ii) then mitigate those violations with optimally-invested battery energy storage systems (BESS) through an optimal expansion planning (OEP) model. A novel spatio-temporal adaptive targeting (STAT) strategy is proposed to alleviate the computational complexity of the OEP model by defining a targeted OEP (T-OEP) model, solved by applying the OEP model to (i) a reduced set of representative critical time periods and (ii) candidate BESS installation nodes. The efficacy and scalability of the proposed approach are validated on 33-bus, 69-bus, and a large-scale 240-bus system. Results demonstrate that the strategic sizing and placement of BESS not only effectively mitigate voltage violations but also yield substantial cost savings on electricity purchases under time-of-use tariffs. This research offers a cost-effective and scalable solution for integrating high penetrations of EVs, providing crucial insights for future distribution network planning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00297v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linhan Fang, Xingpeng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Language Models for Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00337v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates using large language models (LLMs) to generate control actions directly, without requiring control-engineering expertise or hand-tuned algorithms. We implement several variants: (i) prompt-only, (ii) tool-assisted with access to historical data, and (iii) prediction-assisted using learned or simple models to score candidate actions. We compare them on tracking accuracy and actuation effort, with and without a prompt that requests lower actuator usage. Results show prompt-only LLMs already produce viable control, while tool-augmented versions adapt better to changing objectives but can be more sensitive to constraints, supporting LLM-in-the-loop control for evolving cyber-physical systems today and operator and human inputs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00337v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adil Rasheed, Oscar Ravik, Omer San</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constrained computational hybrid controller for Input Affine Hybrid Dynamical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00420v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hybrid dynamical systems are viewed as the most complicated systems with continuous and event-based behaviors. Since traditional controllers cannot handle these systems, some newly-developed controllers have been published in recent decades to deal with them. This paper presents a novel implementable constrained final-state controller based on partitioning the system's state-space, computational simulations, and graph theory. Experimental results and a comparison with Model Predictive Controller on the three tank benchmark and swing-up control of a pendulum show the effectiveness of the proposed Computational Hybrid Controller(CHC).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00420v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jfranklin.2024.107142</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of the Franklin Institute, Volume 361, Issue 17, November 2024, 107142</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ali Taghavian, Ali Safi, Esmaeel Khanmirza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CT-ESKF: A General Framework of Covariance Transformation-Based Error-State Kalman Filter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00453v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Invariant extended Kalman filter (InEKF) possesses excellent trajectory-independent property and better consistency compared to conventional extended Kalman filter (EKF). However, when applied to scenarios involving both global-frame and body-frame observations, InEKF may fail to preserve its trajectory-independent property. This work introduces the concept of equivalence between error states and covariance matrices among different error-state Kalman filters, and shows that although InEKF exhibits trajectory independence, its covariance propagation is actually equivalent to EKF. A covariance transformation-based error-state Kalman filter (CT-ESKF) framework is proposed that unifies various error-state Kalman filtering algorithms. The framework gives birth to novel filtering algorithms that demonstrate improved performance in integrated navigation systems that incorporate both global and body-frame observations. Experimental results show that the EKF with covariance transformation outperforms both InEKF and original EKF in a representative INS/GNSS/Odometer integrated navigation system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00453v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiale Han, Wei Ouyang, Maoran Zhu, Yuanxin Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rotatable Antenna System Empowered Low-Altitude Economy: Opportunities and Challenges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00562v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Low-altitude economy (LAE) is an emerging technological paradigm that enables continuous airspace coverage at multiple altitudes by providing highly reliable data connectivity for numerous low-altitude applications. However, existing networks cannot sufficiently support LAE development, as current base stations (BSs) are primarily designed for terrestrial users and lack the capability to provide continuous coverage at low altitudes. To overcome these challenges, rotatable antenna system (RAS) is introduced in LAE, enabling flexible beamforming by dynamically adjusting the boresight of directional antennas to extend low-altitude coverage and enhance the stability of data transmission. In this article, we first provide an overview of RAS-empowered LAE applications, including low-altitude communication, sensing, control, and computation. Then, we present two practical RAS deployment strategies for LAE scenarios, namely RAS-aided multi-BS and multi-unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV) cooperative coverages, as well as provide detailed discussions on their system architectures and performance benefits. Additionally, key design issues of RAS in LAE are discussed, including channel modeling and estimation, cellular access and interference cancellation, as well as RAS configuration and boresight optimization. Finally, we demonstrate the performance gains of RAS in LAE networks through experimental and simulation results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00562v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Wireless Communication, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shuaijun Li, Jie Tang, Beixiong Zheng, Lipeng Zhu, Cui Yang, Nan Zhao, Xiu Yin Zhang, Kai-Kit Wong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Quantum Algorithms for the Optimization of Spanning Trees: The Power Distribution Grids Use Case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00582v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optimizing the topology of networks is an important challenge across engineering disciplines. In energy systems, network reconfiguration can substantially reduce losses and costs and thus support the energy transition. Unfortunately, many related optimization problems are NP hard, restricting practical applications. In this article, we address the problem of minimizing losses in radial networks, a problem that routinely arises in distribution grid operation. We show that even the computation of approximate solutions is computationally hard and propose quantum optimization as a promising alternative. We derive two quantum algorithmic primitives based on the Quantum Alternating Operator Ansatz (QAOA) that differ in the sampling of network topologies: a tailored sampling of radial topologies and simple sampling with penalty terms to suppress non-radial topologies. We show how to apply these algorithmic primitives to distribution grid reconfiguration and quantify the necessary quantum resources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00582v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carsten Hartmann, Nil Rodellas-Gr\`acia, Christian Wallisch, Thiemo Pesch, Frank K. Wilhelm, Dirk Witthaut, Tobias Stollenwerk, Andrea Benigni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital Twin of Aerosol Jet Printing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00593v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Aerosol Jet (AJ) printing is a versatile additive manufacturing technique capable of producing high-resolution interconnects on both 2D and 3D substrates. The AJ process is complex and dynamic with many hidden and unobservable states that influence the machine performance, including aerosol particle diameter, aerosol carrier density, vial level, and ink deposition in the tube and nozzle. Despite its promising potential, the widespread adoption of AJ printing is limited by inconsistencies in print quality that often stem from variability in these hidden states. To address these challenges, we develop a digital twin model of the AJ process that offers real-time insights into the machine's operations. The digital twin is built around a physics-based macro-model created through simulation and experimentation. The states and parameters of the digital model are continuously updated using probabilistic sequential estimation techniques to closely align with real-time measurements extracted from the AJ system's sensor and video data. The result is a digital model of the AJ process that continuously evolves over a physical machine's lifecycle. The digital twin enables accurate monitoring of unobservable physical characteristics, detects and predicts anomalous behavior, and forecasts the effect of control adjustments. This work presents a comprehensive end-to-end digital twin framework that integrates customized computer vision techniques, physics-based macro-modeling, and advanced probabilistic estimation methods to construct an evolving digital representation of the AJ equipment and process. While the methodologies are customized for aerosol jet printing, the process for constructing the digital twin can be applied for other advanced manufacturing techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00593v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aayushya Agarwal, Jace Rozsa, Matteo Pozzi, Rahul Panat, Gary K. Fedder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficiency and Optimality in Electrochemical Battery Model Parameter Identification: A Comparative Study of Estimation Techniques</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00595</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00595v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Parameter identification for electrochemical battery models has always been challenging due to the multitude of parameters involved, most of which cannot be directly measured. This paper evaluates the efficiency and optimality of three widely-used parameter identification methods for electrochemical battery models: Least Squares Method (LS), Particle Swarm Optimization (PSO), and Genetic Algorithm (GA). Therefore, a Single Particle Model (SPM) of a battery was developed and discretized. Battery parameter grouping was then performed to reduce the number of parameters required. Using a set of parameters previously identified from a real battery as a benchmark, we generated fitting and validation datasets to assess the methods' runtime and accuracy. The comparative analysis reveals that PSO outperforms the other methods in terms of accuracy and stability, making it highly effective for parameter identification when there is no prior knowledge of the battery's internal parameters. In contrast, LS is better suited for minor adjustments in parameters, particularly for aging batteries, whereas GA lags behind in both computational efficiency and optimality with respect to PSO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00595v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ICOA62581.2024.10754301</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2024 10th International Conference on Optimization and Applications (ICOA). IEEE, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Feng Guo, Luis D. Couto, Guillaume Thenaisie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Federated Learning to Optimize the MultiCast flows in Data Centers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00623</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00623v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Data centers play an increasingly critical role in societal digitalization, yet their rapidly growing energy demand poses significant challenges for sustainable operation. To enhance the energy efficiency of geographically distributed data centers, this paper formulates a multi-period optimization model that captures the interdependence of electricity, heat, and data flows. The optimization of such multicast flows inherently involves mixed-integer formulations and the access to proprietary or sensitive datasets, which correspondingly exacerbate computational complexity and raise data-privacy concerns. To address these challenges, an adaptive federated learning-to-optimization approach is proposed, accounting for the heterogeneity of datasets across distributed data centers. To safeguard privacy, cryptography techniques are leveraged in both the learning and optimization processes. A model acceptance criterion with convergence guarantee is developed to improve learning performance and filter out potentially contaminated data, while a verifiable double aggregation mechanism is further proposed to simultaneously ensure privacy and integrity of shared data during optimization. Theoretical analysis and numerical simulations demonstrate that the proposed approach preserves the privacy and integrity of shared data, achieves near-optimal performance, and exhibits high computational efficiency, making it suitable for large-scale data center optimization under privacy constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00623v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junhong Liu, Lanxin Du, Yujia Li, Rong-Peng Liu, Fei Teng, Francis Yunhe Hou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frequency Quality Assessment of GFM and GFL Converters and Synchronous Condensers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00639v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper compares the impact of different conventional and emerging technologies and control strategies on frequency quality. We study, in particular, the long-term dynamic performance of grid-forming (GFM) and grid-following (GFL) inverter-based resources (IBRs) as well as conventional synchronous machines. Extensive simulations and several realistic scenarios consider both short-term and long-term aspects of frequency quality. It is shown that, while overall GFM IBRs significantly improve frequency quality, a combination of GFL IBRs providing frequency support such as wind and batteries, and synchronous condensers, might be enough to meet similar frequency quality standards. Another result of the paper is that the need for automatic generation control (AGC) becomes less clear in GFM IBR-dominated grids from a frequency quality perspective.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00639v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taulant Kerci, Federico Milano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling Uniform Shifted Power Law in Stochastic Human and Autonomous Driving Behavior</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00659</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00659v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurately simulating rare but safety-critical driving behaviors is essential for the evaluation and certification of autonomous vehicles (AVs). However, current models often fail to reproduce realistic collision rates when calibrated on real-world data, largely due to inadequate representation of long-tailed behavioral distributions. Here, we uncover a simple yet unifying shifted power law that robustly characterizes the stochasticity of both human-driven vehicle (HV) and AV behaviors, especially in the long-tail regime. The model adopts a parsimonious analytical form with only one or two parameters, enabling efficient calibration even under data sparsity. Analyzing large-scale, micro-level trajectory data from global HV and AV datasets, the shifted power law achieves an average R2 of 0.97 and a nearly identical tail distribution, uniformly fits both frequent behaviors and rare safety-critical deviations, significantly outperforming existing Gaussian-based baselines. When integrated into an agent-based traffic simulator, it enables forward-rolling simulations that reproduce realistic crash patterns for both HVs and AVs, achieving rates consistent with real-world statistics and improving the fidelity of safety assessment without post hoc correction. This discovery offers a unified and data-efficient foundation for modeling high-risk behavior and improves the fidelity of simulation-based safety assessments for mixed AV/HV traffic. The shifted power law provides a promising path toward simulation-driven validation and global certification of AV technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00659v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wang Chen, Heye Huang, Ke Ma, Hangyu Li, Shixiao Liang, Hang Zhou, Xiaopeng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Quantum-Classical Optimization of the Resource Scheduling Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00733</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00733v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Resource scheduling is critical in many industries, especially in power systems. The Unit Commitment problem determines the on/off status and output levels of generators under many constraints. Traditional exact methods, such as mathematical programming methods or dynamic programming, remain the backbone of UC solution techniques, but they often rely on linear approximations or exhaustive search, leading to high computational burdens as system size grows. Metaheuristic approaches, such as genetic algorithms, particle swarm optimization, and other evolutionary methods, have been explored to mitigate this complexity; however, they typically lack optimality guarantees, exhibit sensitivity to initial conditions, and can become prohibitively time-consuming for large-scale systems. In this paper, we introduce a quantum-classical hybrid algorithm for UC and, by extension, other resource scheduling problems, that leverages Benders decomposition to decouple binary commitment decisions from continuous economic dispatch. The binary master problem is formulated as a quadratic unconstrained binary optimization model and solved on a quantum annealer. The continuous subproblem, which minimizes generation costs, with Lagrangian cuts feeding back to the master until convergence. We evaluate our hybrid framework on systems scaled from 10 to 1,000 generation units. Compared against a classical mixed-integer nonlinear programming baseline, the hybrid algorithm achieves a consistently lower computation-time growth rate and maintains an absolute optimality gap below 1.63%. These results demonstrate that integrating quantum annealing within a hybrid quantum-classical Benders decomposition loop can significantly accelerate large-scale resource scheduling without sacrificing solution quality, pointing toward a viable path for addressing the escalating complexity of modern power grids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00733v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tyler Christeson, Md Habib Ullah, Ali Arabnya, Amin Khodaei, Rui Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Computing for EVs to Enhance Grid Resilience and Disaster Relief: Challenges and Opportunities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00736v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The power grid is the foundation of modern society, however extreme weather events have increasingly caused widespread outages. Enhancing grid resilience is therefore critical to maintaining secure and reliable operations. In disaster relief and restoration, vehicle-to-grid (V2G) technology allows electric vehicles (EVs) to serve as mobile energy resources by discharging to support critical loads or regulating grid frequency as needed. Effective V2G operation requires coordinated charging and discharging of many EVs through optimization. Similarly, in grid restoration, EVs must be strategically routed to affected areas, forming the mobile charging station placement (CSP) problem, which presents another complex optimization challenge. This work reviews state-of-the-art optimization methods for V2G and mobile CSP applications, outlines their limitations, and explores how quantum computing (QC) could overcome current computational bottlenecks. A QC-focused perspective is presented on enhancing grid resilience and accelerating restoration as extreme weather events grow more frequent and severe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00736v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tyler Christeson, Amin Khodaei, Rui Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Power Dual-Channel Field Chamber for High-Frequency Magnetic Neuromodulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00745v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Several novel methods, including magnetogenetics and magnetoelectric stimulation, use high frequency alternating magnetic fields to precisely manipulate neural activity. To quantify the behavioral effects of such interventions in a freely moving mouse, we developed a dual-channel magnetic chamber, specifically designed for rate-sensitive magnetothermal-genetic stimulation, and adaptable for other uses of alternating magnetic fields. Through an optimized coil design, the system allows independent control of two spatially orthogonal uniform magnetic fields delivered at different frequencies within a 10 cm x 10 cm x 6 cm chamber. The two channels have nominal frequencies of 50 and 550 kHz with peak magnetic field strengths of 88 and 12.5 mT, achieved with resonant coil drives having peak voltages of 1.6 and 1.8 kV and currents of 1.0 and 0.26 kA, respectively. Additionally, a liquid cooling system enables magnetic field generation for second-level duration, and an observation port and camera allow video capture of the animal's behavior within the chamber. The system generates high-amplitude magnetic fields across two widely separated frequency channels with negligible interference (&lt; 1%). Relatively uniform magnetic field distribution (+/-10% across 94% of the chamber volume) is maintained throughout the chamber, and temperature increase of the inner side of the coil enclosure during the operation is limited to &lt; 0.35 {\deg}C/s to ensure in vivo safety. Using cobalt-doped and undoped iron oxide nanoparticles, we demonstrate channel-specific heating rates of 3.5 {\deg}C/s and 1.5 {\deg}C/s, respectively, validating frequency-selectivity. Both channels can run continuously for four seconds stably.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00745v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoyang Tian, Hui Wang, Boshuo Wang, Jinshui Zhang, Dong Yan, Jeannette Ingabire, Samantha Coffler, Guillaume Duret, Quoc-Khanh Pham, Gang Bao, Jacob T. Robinson, Stefan M. Goetz, Angel V. Peterchev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Q-Network for Optimizing NOMA-Aided Resource Allocation in Smart Factories with URLLC Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00765v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a Deep Q-Network (DQN)- based algorithm for NOMA-aided resource allocation in smart factories, addressing the stringent requirements of Ultra-Reliable Low-Latency Communication (URLLC). The proposed algorithm dynamically allocates sub-channels and optimizes power levels to maximize throughput while meeting strict latency constraints. By incorporating a tunable parameter {\lambda}, the algorithm balances the trade-off between throughput and latency, making it suitable for various devices, including robots, sensors, and controllers, each with distinct communication needs. Simulation results show that robots achieve higher throughput, while sensors and controllers meet the low-latency requirements of URLLC, ensuring reliable communication for real-time industrial applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00765v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shi Gengtian, Jiang Liu, Shigeru Shimamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimizing Maximum Latency of Task Offloading for Multi-UAV-assisted Maritime Search and Rescue</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00844v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAVs) play a crucial role in Maritime Search and Rescue (MSAR), contributing to the improvement of rescue efficiency and reduction of casualties. Typically, UAVs equipped with cameras collect data from disaster areas and transmit it to the shore-based rescue command centers. By deploying Mobile Edge Computing (MEC) servers, UAVs can pre-process video footage to reduce data transmission volume, thus reducing transmission delays. However, the limited computational capacity and energy of UAVs pose significant challenges to the efficiency of UAV-assisted MSAR systems. To address these problems, in this paper, we investigate a multi-UAV assisted MSAR system consisting of multiple Surveillance UAVs (S-UAVs) and a Relay UAV (R-UAV). Then, we formulate a joint optimization problem to minimize the maximum total latency among all S-UAVs via jointly making the computing offloading decisions, R-UAV deployment, and the association between a S-UAV and rescue targets while ensuring that all targets are monitored by S-UAVs. Since the formulated optimization problem is typically hard to solve due to its non-convexity, we propose an effective iterative algorithm by breaking it into three sub-problems. Numerical simulation results show the effectiveness of the proposed algorithm with various performance parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00844v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuang Qi, Bin Lin, Yiqin Deng, Xianhao Chen, Yuguang Fang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Traffic-Aware Grid Planning for Dynamic Wireless Electric Vehicle Charging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00941</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00941v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dynamic Wireless Electric Vehicle Charging (DWC) on electrified roadways is an emerging technology that can significantly reduce battery sizes, eliminate charging downtime, and alleviate range anxiety, specially for long-haul transportation and fleet operations of electric vehicles (EVs). However, these systems introduce new challenges for power system planning due to their short-duration and high-power demands which can strain the grid if not properly managed. As the energy demands from DWC depend on vehicle speed, density, dwell time in charging zones, and load profiles along road segments, there is a need for integrated planning of such systems, jointly considering both traffic behavior and EV energy consumption. In this paper, we propose a traffic-aware grid planning framework for DWC. We leverage a macroscopic Cell Transmission Model of traffic flow to estimate real-time, spatiotemporal EV charging demand from DWC corridors. The demand model is then integrated into an AC Optimal Power Flow based formulation to optimally size a microgrid that supports DWC under varying traffic conditions while minimizing the cost of operation. Our framework explicitly models how spatiotemporal traffic patterns affect the utilization of grid resources to obtain system designs that achieve lower costs and are easier to operationalize as compared to planning models that rely on worst-case traffic data.
  We demonstrate the framework on data from a 14-mile segment of the I-210W highway in California, USA, evaluating multiple traffic scenarios like free-flow, severe congestion, accidents of varying severity, and natural disasters like forest fires. Our results demonstrate that traffic-aware grid planning significantly reduces infrastructure costs as compared to worst-scenario based modeling, while ensuring reliability of service in terms of meeting charging demands under diverse traffic conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00941v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dipanjan Ghose, S Sivaranjani, Junjie Qin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secure Distributed Consensus Estimation under False Data Injection Attacks: A Defense Strategy Based on Partial Channel Coding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00963v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article investigates the security issue caused by false data injection attacks in distributed estimation, wherein each sensor can construct two types of residues based on local estimates and neighbor information, respectively. The resource-constrained attacker can select partial channels from the sensor network and arbitrarily manipulate the transmitted data. We derive necessary and sufficient conditions to reveal system vulnerabilities, under which the attacker is able to diverge the estimation error while preserving the stealthiness of all residues. We propose two defense strategies with mechanisms of exploiting the Euclidean distance between local estimates to detect attacks, and adopting the coding scheme to protect the transmitted data, respectively. It is proven that the former has the capability to address the majority of security loopholes, while the latter can serve as an additional enhancement to the former. By employing the time-varying coding matrix to mitigate the risk of being cracked, we demonstrate that the latter can safeguard against adversaries injecting stealthy sequences into the encoded channels. Hence, drawing upon the security analysis, we further provide a procedure to select security-critical channels that need to be encoded, thereby achieving a trade-off between security and coding costs. Finally, some numerical simulations are conducted to demonstrate the theoretical results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00963v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiahao Huang, Marios M. Polycarpou, Wen Yang, Fangfei Li, Yang Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Structural Properties of Risk-Averse Optimal Stopping Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01022v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish structural properties of optimal stopping problems under time-consistent dynamic (coherent) risk measures, focusing on value function monotonicity and the existence of control limit (threshold) optimal policies. While such results are well developed for risk-neutral (expected-value) models, they remain underexplored in risk-averse settings. Coherent risk measures typically lack the tower property and are subadditive rather than additive, complicating structural analysis. We show that value function monotonicity mirrors the risk-neutral case. Moreover, if the risk envelope associated with each coherent risk measure admits a minimal element, the risk-averse optimal stopping problem reduces to an equivalent risk-neutral formulation. We also develop a general procedure for identifying control limit optimal policies and use it to derive practical, verifiable conditions on the risk measures and MDP structure that guarantee their existence. We illustrate the theory and verify these conditions through optimal stopping problems arising in operations, marketing, and finance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01022v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xingyu Ren, Michael C. Fu, Steven I. Marcus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online Energy Storage Arbitrage under Imperfect Predictions: A Conformal Risk-Aware Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01032v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work proposes a conformal approach for energy storage arbitrage to control the downside risks arose from imperfect price forecasts. Energy storage arbitrage relies solely on predictions of future market prices, while inaccurate price predictions may lead to significant profit losses. Based on conformal decision theory, we describe a controller that dynamically adjusts decision conservativeness through prediction sets without distributional assumptions. To enable online calibration when online profit loss feedback is unobservable, we establish that a temporal difference error serves as a measurable proxy. Building on this insight, we develop two online calibration strategies: prediction error-based adaptation targeting forecast accuracy, and value error-based calibration focusing on decision quality. Analysis of the conformal controller proves bounded long-term risk with convergence guarantees in temporal difference error, which further effectively manages risk exposure in potential profit losses. Case studies demonstrate superior performance in balancing risk and opportunity compared to benchmarks under varying forecast conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01032v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiqian Wu, Ming Yi, Bolun Xu, James Anderson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GOSPA-Driven Non-Myopic Multi-Sensor Management with Multi-Bernoulli Filtering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01045</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01045v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a non-myopic sensor management algorithm for multi-target tracking, with multiple sensors operating in the same surveillance area. The algorithm is based on multi-Bernoulli filtering and selects the actions that solve a non-myopic minimisation problem, where the cost function is the mean square generalised optimal sub-pattern assignment (GOSPA) error, over a future time window. For tractability, the sensor management algorithm actually uses an upper bound of the GOSPA error and is implemented via Monte Carlo Tree Search (MCTS). The sensors have the ability to jointly optimise and select their actions with the considerations of all other sensors in the surveillance area. The benefits of the proposed algorithm are analysed via simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01045v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George Jones, Angel Garcia-Fernandez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Self-Triggered Control Approaches Optimizing Sampling Sequences with Synchronous Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01057</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01057v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Feedback control algorithms traditionally rely on periodic execution on digital platforms. While this simplifies design and analysis, it often leads to inefficient resource usage (e.g., CPU, network bandwidth) in embedded control and shared networks. This work investigates self-triggering implementations of linear controllers in sampled-data systems with synchronous measurements. Our approach precomputes the next sampling sequence over a finite horizon based on current state information. We introduce a novel optimal self-triggering scheme that guarantees exponential stability for unperturbed systems and global uniform ultimate boundedness for perturbed systems. This ensures robustness against external disturbances with explicit performance guarantees. Simulations demonstrate the benefits of our approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01057v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abbas Tariverdi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Barrier Functions for Safety and Stability of Constrained Nonlinear Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01067</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01067v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we address the problem of synthesizing safe and stabilizing controllers for nonlinear systems subject to complex safety specifications and input constraints. We introduce the Universal Barrier Function (UBF), a single continuously differentiable scalar-valued function that encodes both stability and safety criteria while accounting for input constraints. Using the UBF, we formulate a Quadratic Program (UBF-QP) to generate control inputs that are both safe and stabilizing under input constraints. We demonstrate that the UBF-QP is feasible if a UBF exists. Furthermore, under mild conditions, we prove that a UBF always exists. The proposed framework is then extended to systems with higher relative degrees. Finally, numerical simulations illustrate the effectiveness of our proposed approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01067v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vrushabh Zinage, Efstathios Bakolas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning-Accelerated Shapley Value for Fair Allocation in Power Systems: The Case of Carbon Emission Responsibility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01229</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01229v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Allocating costs, benefits, and emissions fairly among power system participant entities represents a persistent challenge. The Shapley value provides an axiomatically fair solution, yet computational barriers have limited its adoption beyond small-scale applications. This paper presents SurroShap, a scalable Shapley value approximation framework combining efficient coalition sampling with deep learning surrogate models that accelerate characteristic function evaluations. Exemplified through carbon emission responsibility allocation in power networks, SurroShap enables Shapley-based fair allocation for power systems with thousands of entities for the first time. We derive theoretical error bounds proving that time-averaged SurroShap allocations converge to be $\varepsilon$-close to exact Shapley values. Experiments on nine systems ranging from 26 to 1,951 entities demonstrate completion within the real-time operational window even at maximum scale, achieving 10^4-10^5 speedups over other sampling-based methods while maintaining tight error bounds. The resulting Shapley-based carbon allocations possess six desirable properties aligning individual interests with decarbonization goals. Year-long simulations on the Texas 2000-bus system validate real-world applicability, with regional analysis revealing how renewable-rich areas offset emission responsibility through exports while load centers bear responsibility for driving system-wide generation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01229v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuanhao Feng, Tao Sun, Yan Meng, Xuxin Yang, Donghan Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orthogonal-by-construction augmentation of physics-based input-output models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01321v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Model augmentation is a promising approach for integrating first-principles-based models with machine learning components. Augmentation can result in better model accuracy and faster convergence compared to black-box system identification methods, while maintaining interpretability of the models in terms of how the original dynamics are complemented by learning. A widely used augmentation structure in the literature is based on the parallel connection of the physics-based and learning components, for both of which the corresponding parameters are jointly optimized. However, due to overlap in representation of the system dynamics by such an additive structure, estimation often leads to physically unrealistic parameters, compromising model interpretability. To overcome this limitation, this paper introduces a novel orthogonal-by-construction model augmentation structure for input-output models, that guarantees recovery of the physically true parameters under appropriate identifiability conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01321v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bendeg\'uz M. Gy\"or\"ok, Maarten Schoukens, Tam\'as P\'eni, Roland T\'oth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Risk Aware Safe Control with Cooperative Sensing for Dynamic Obstacle Avoidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01403</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01403v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents the design, development, and on vehicle implementation and validation of a safety critical controller for autonomous driving under sensing and communication uncertainty. Cooperative sensing, fused via a Wasserstein barycenter (WB), is used to optimize the distribution of the dynamic obstacle locations. The Conditional Value at Risk (CVaR) is introduced to form a risk aware control-barrier-function (CBF) framework with the optimized distribution samplings. The proposed WB CVaR CBF safety filter improves control inputs that minimize tail risk while certifying forward invariance of the safe set. A model predictive controller (MPC) performs path tracking, and the safety filter modulates the nominal control inputs to enforce risk aware constraints. We detail the software architecture and integration with vehicle actuation and cooperative sensing. The approach is evaluated on a full-scale autonomous vehicle (AV) in scenarios with measurement noise, communication perturbations, and input disturbances, and is compared against a baseline MPC CBF design. Results demonstrate improved safety margins and robustness, highlighting the practicality of deploying the risk-aware safety filter on an actual AV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01403v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pei Yu Chang, Qizhe Xu, Vishnu Renganathan, Qadeer Ahmed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolutionary Dynamics in Continuous-time Finite-state Mean Field Games -- Part I: Equilibria</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01452v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a dynamic game with a large population of players who choose actions from a finite set in continuous time. Each player has a state in a finite state space that evolves stochastically with their actions. A player's reward depends not only on their own state and action but also on the distribution of states and actions across the population, capturing effects such as congestion in traffic networks. While prior work in evolutionary game theory has primarily focused on static games without individual player state dynamics, we present the first comprehensive evolutionary analysis of such dynamic games. We propose an evolutionary model together with a mean field approximation of the finite-population game and establish strong approximation guarantees. We show that standard solution concepts for dynamic games lack an evolutionary interpretation, and we propose a new concept - the Mixed Stationary Nash Equilibrium (MSNE) - which admits one. We analyze the relationship between MSNE and the rest points of the mean field evolutionary model and study the evolutionary stability of MSNE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01452v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonardo Pedroso, Andrea Agazzi, W. P. M. H. Heemels, Mauro Salazar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Prediction of Beam Coherence Time for Near-FieldTeraHertz Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01491v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Large multiple antenna arrays coupled with accurate beamforming are essential in terahertz (THz) communications to ensure link reliability. However, as the number of antennas increases, beam alignment (focusing) and beam tracking in mobile networks incur prohibitive overhead. Additionally, the near-field region expands both with the size of antenna arrays and the carrier frequency, calling for adjustments in the beamforming to account for spherical wavefront instead of the conventional planar wave assumption. In this letter, we introduce a novel beam coherence time for mobile THz networks, to drastically reduce the rate of beam updates. Then, we propose a deep learning model, relying on a simple feedforward neural network with a time-dependent input, to predict the beam coherence time and adjust the beamforming on the fly with minimal overhead. Our numerical results demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed approach by enabling higher data rates while reducing the overhead, especially at high (i.e., vehicular) mobility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01491v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Irched Chafaa, E. Veronica Belmega, Giacomo Bacci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On polynomial explicit partial estimator design for nonlinear systems with parametric uncertainties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01638v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the idea of designing data-driven partial estimators for nonlinear systems showing parametric uncertainties using sparse multivariate polynomial relationships. A general framework is first presented and then validated on two illustrative examples with comparison to different possible Machine/Deep-Learning based alternatives. The results suggests the superiority of the proposed sparse identification scheme, at least when the learning data is small.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01638v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mazen Alamir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital Twin based Automatic Reconfiguration of Robotic Systems in Smart Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00094</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00094v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Robotic systems have become integral to smart environments, enabling applications ranging from urban surveillance and automated agriculture to industrial automation. However, their effective operation in dynamic settings - such as smart cities and precision farming - is challenged by continuously evolving topographies and environmental conditions. Traditional control systems often struggle to adapt quickly, leading to inefficiencies or operational failures. To address this limitation, we propose a novel framework for autonomous and dynamic reconfiguration of robotic controllers using Digital Twin technology. Our approach leverages a virtual replica of the robot's operational environment to simulate and optimize movement trajectories in response to real-world changes. By recalculating paths and control parameters in the Digital Twin and deploying the updated code to the physical robot, our method ensures rapid and reliable adaptation without manual intervention. This work advances the integration of Digital Twins in robotics, offering a scalable solution for enhancing autonomy in smart, dynamic environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00094v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Angelos Alexopoulos, Agorakis Bompotas, Nikitas Rigas Kalogeropoulos, Panagiotis Kechagias, Athanasios P. Kalogeras, Christos Alexakos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A generative adversarial network optimization method for damage detection and digital twinning by deep AI fault learning: Z24 Bridge structural health monitoring benchmark validation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00099v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The optimization-based damage detection and damage state digital twinning capabilities are examined here of a novel conditional-labeled generative adversarial network methodology. The framework outperforms current approaches for fault anomaly detection as no prior information is required for the health state of the system: a topic of high significance for real-world applications. Specifically, current artificial intelligence-based digital twinning approaches suffer from the uncertainty related to obtaining poor predictions when a low number of measurements is available, physics knowledge is missing, or when the damage state is unknown. To this end, an unsupervised framework is examined and validated rigorously on the benchmark structural health monitoring measurements of Z24 Bridge: a post-tensioned concrete highway bridge in Switzerland. In implementing the approach, firstly, different same damage-level measurements are used as inputs, while the model is forced to converge conditionally to two different damage states. Secondly, the process is repeated for a different group of measurements. Finally, the convergence scores are compared to identify which one belongs to a different damage state. The process for both healthy-to-healthy and damage-to-healthy input data creates, simultaneously, measurements for digital twinning purposes at different damage states, capable of pattern recognition and machine learning data generation. Further to this process, a support vector machine classifier and a principal component analysis procedure is developed to assess the generated and real measurements of each damage category, serving as a secondary new dynamics learning indicator in damage scenarios. Importantly, the approach is shown to capture accurately damage over healthy measurements, providing a powerful tool for vibration-based system-level monitoring and scalable infrastructure resilience.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00099v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00158-025-04162-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Structural and Multidisciplinary Optimization, 68(11):1-21, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Marios Impraimakis, Evangelia Nektaria Palkanoglou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep recurrent-convolutional neural network learning and physics Kalman filtering comparison in dynamic load identification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00100v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The dynamic structural load identification capabilities of the gated recurrent unit, long short-term memory, and convolutional neural networks are examined herein. The examination is on realistic small dataset training conditions and on a comparative view to the physics-based residual Kalman filter (RKF). The dynamic load identification suffers from the uncertainty related to obtaining poor predictions when in civil engineering applications only a low number of tests are performed or are available, or when the structural model is unidentifiable. In considering the methods, first, a simulated structure is investigated under a shaker excitation at the top floor. Second, a building in California is investigated under seismic base excitation, which results in loading for all degrees of freedom. Finally, the International Association for Structural Control-American Society of Civil Engineers (IASC-ASCE) structural health monitoring benchmark problem is examined for impact and instant loading conditions. Importantly, the methods are shown to outperform each other on different loading scenarios, while the RKF is shown to outperform the networks in physically parametrized identifiable cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00100v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1177/14759217241262972</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Structural Health Monitoring 24.3 (2025): 1752-1782</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Marios Impraimakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LC-Opt: Benchmarking Reinforcement Learning and Agentic AI for End-to-End Liquid Cooling Optimization in Data Centers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00116v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Liquid cooling is critical for thermal management in high-density data centers with the rising AI workloads. However, machine learning-based controllers are essential to unlock greater energy efficiency and reliability, promoting sustainability. We present LC-Opt, a Sustainable Liquid Cooling (LC) benchmark environment, for reinforcement learning (RL) control strategies in energy-efficient liquid cooling of high-performance computing (HPC) systems. Built on the baseline of a high-fidelity digital twin of Oak Ridge National Lab's Frontier Supercomputer cooling system, LC-Opt provides detailed Modelica-based end-to-end models spanning site-level cooling towers to data center cabinets and server blade groups. RL agents optimize critical thermal controls like liquid supply temperature, flow rate, and granular valve actuation at the IT cabinet level, as well as cooling tower (CT) setpoints through a Gymnasium interface, with dynamic changes in workloads. This environment creates a multi-objective real-time optimization challenge balancing local thermal regulation and global energy efficiency, and also supports additional components like a heat recovery unit (HRU). We benchmark centralized and decentralized multi-agent RL approaches, demonstrate policy distillation into decision and regression trees for interpretable control, and explore LLM-based methods that explain control actions in natural language through an agentic mesh architecture designed to foster user trust and simplify system management. LC-Opt democratizes access to detailed, customizable liquid cooling models, enabling the ML community, operators, and vendors to develop sustainable data center liquid cooling control solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00116v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Avisek Naug, Antonio Guillen, Vineet Kumar, Scott Greenwood, Wesley Brewer, Sahand Ghorbanpour, Ashwin Ramesh Babu, Vineet Gundecha, Ricardo Luna Gutierrez, Soumyendu Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DCcluster-Opt: Benchmarking Dynamic Multi-Objective Optimization for Geo-Distributed Data Center Workloads</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00117v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The increasing energy demands and carbon footprint of large-scale AI require intelligent workload management in globally distributed data centers. Yet progress is limited by the absence of benchmarks that realistically capture the interplay of time-varying environmental factors (grid carbon intensity, electricity prices, weather), detailed data center physics (CPUs, GPUs, memory, HVAC energy), and geo-distributed network dynamics (latency and transmission costs). To bridge this gap, we present DCcluster-Opt: an open-source, high-fidelity simulation benchmark for sustainable, geo-temporal task scheduling. DCcluster-Opt combines curated real-world datasets, including AI workload traces, grid carbon intensity, electricity markets, weather across 20 global regions, cloud transmission costs, and empirical network delay parameters with physics-informed models of data center operations, enabling rigorous and reproducible research in sustainable computing. It presents a challenging scheduling problem where a top-level coordinating agent must dynamically reassign or defer tasks that arrive with resource and service-level agreement requirements across a configurable cluster of data centers to optimize multiple objectives. The environment also models advanced components such as heat recovery. A modular reward system enables an explicit study of trade-offs among carbon emissions, energy costs, service level agreements, and water use. It provides a Gymnasium API with baseline controllers, including reinforcement learning and rule-based strategies, to support reproducible ML research and a fair comparison of diverse algorithms. By offering a realistic, configurable, and accessible testbed, DCcluster-Opt accelerates the development and validation of next-generation sustainable computing solutions for geo-distributed data centers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00117v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Guillen-Perez, Avisek Naug, Vineet Gundecha, Sahand Ghorbanpour, Ricardo Luna Gutierrez, Ashwin Ramesh Babu, Munther Salim, Shubhanker Banerjee, Eoin H. Oude Essink, Damien Fay, Soumyendu Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supply Chain Exploitation of Secure ROS 2 Systems: A Proof-of-Concept on Autonomous Platform Compromise via Keystore Exfiltration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00140</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00140v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a proof-of-concept supply chain attack against the Secure ROS 2 (SROS 2) framework, demonstrated on a Quanser QCar2 autonomous vehicle platform. A Trojan-infected Debian package modifies core ROS 2 security commands to exfiltrate newly generated keystore credentials via DNS in base64-encoded chunks to an attacker-controlled nameserver. Possession of these credentials enables the attacker to rejoin the SROS 2 network as an authenticated participant and publish spoofed control or perception messages without triggering authentication failures. We evaluate this capability on a secure ROS 2 Humble testbed configured for a four-stop-sign navigation routine using an Intel RealSense camera for perception. Experimental results show that control-topic injections can cause forced braking, sustained high-speed acceleration, and continuous turning loops, while perception-topic spoofing can induce phantom stop signs or suppress real detections. The attack generalizes to any data distribution service (DDS)-based robotic system using SROS 2, highlighting the need for both supply chain integrity controls and runtime semantic validation to safeguard autonomous systems against insider and impersonation threats.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00140v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.OS</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tahmid Hasan Sakib, Yago Romano Martinez, Carter Brady, Syed Rafay Hasan, Terry N. Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multivariable Gradient-Based Extremum Seeking Control with Saturation Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00208v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper addresses the multivariable gradient-based extremum seeking control (ESC) subject to saturation. Two distinct saturation scenarios are investigated here: saturation acting on the input of the function to be optimized, which is addressed using an anti-windup compensation strategy, and saturation affecting the gradient estimate. In both cases, the unknown Hessian matrix is represented using a polytopic uncertainty description, and sufficient conditions in the form of linear matrix inequalities (LMIs) are derived to design a stabilizing control gain. The proposed conditions guarantee exponential stability of the origin for the average closed-loop system under saturation constraints. With the proposed design conditions, non-diagonal control gain matrices can be obtained, generalizing conventional ESC designs that typically rely on diagonal structures. Stability and convergence are rigorously proven using the Averaging Theory for dynamical systems with Lipschitz continuous right-hand sides. Numerical simulations illustrate the effectiveness of the proposed ESC algorithms, confirming the convergence even in the presence of saturation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00208v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enzo Ferreira Tomaz Silva, Pedro Henrique Silva Coutinho, Tiago Roux Oliveira, Miroslav Krsti\'c, Sophie Tarbouriech</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symbol Detection in a MIMO Wireless Communication System Using a FeFET-coupled CMOS Ring Oscillator Array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00479v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Symbol decoding in multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) wireless communication systems requires the deployment of fast, energy-efficient computing hardware deployable at the edge. The brute-force, exact maximum likelihood (ML) decoder, solved on conventional classical digital hardware, has exponential time complexity. Approximate classical solvers implemented on the same hardware have polynomial time complexity at the best. In this article, we design an alternative ring-oscillator-based coupled oscillator array to act as an oscillator Ising machine (OIM) and heuristically solve the ML-based MIMO detection problem. Complementary metal oxide semiconductor (CMOS) technology is used to design the ring oscillators, and ferroelectric field effect transistor (FeFET) technology is chosen as the coupling element (X) between the oscillators in this CMOS + X OIM design. For this purpose, we experimentally report high linear range of conductance variation (1 micro-S to 60 micro-S) in a FeFET device fabricated at 28 nm high-K/ metal gate (HKMG) CMOS technology node. We incorporate the conductance modulation characteristic in SPICE simulation of the ring oscillators connected in an all-to-all fashion through a crossbar array of these FeFET devices. We show that the above range of conductance variation of the FeFET device is suitable to obtain optimum OIM performance with no significant performance drop up to a MIMO size of 100 transmitting and 100 receiving antennas, thereby making FeFET a suitable device for this application. Our simulations and associated analysis using the Kuramoto model of oscillators also predict that this designed classical analog OIM, if implemented experimentally, will offer logarithmic scaling of computation time with MIMO size, thereby offering a huge improvement (in terms of computation speed) over aforementioned MIMO decoders run on conventional digital hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00479v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harsh Kumar Jadia, Abhinaba Ghosh, Md Hanif Ali, Syed Farid Uddin, Sathish N, Shirshendu Mandal, Nihal Raut, Halid Mulaosmanovic, Stefan Dunkel, Sven Beyer, Suraj Amonkar, Udayan Ganguly, Veeresh Deshpande, Debanjan Bhowmik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimization of continuous-flow over traffic networks with fundamental diagram constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00500v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Optimal transport (OT) theory provides a principled framework for modeling mass movement in applications such as mobility, logistics, and economics. Classical formulations, however, generally ignore capacity limits that are intrinsic in applications, in particular in traffic flow problems. We address this limitation by incorporating fundamental diagrams into a dynamic continuous-flow OT model on graphs, thereby including empirical relations between local density and maximal flux. We adopt an Eulerian kinetic action on graphs that preserves displacement interpolation in direct analogy with the continuous theory. Momentum lives on edges and density on nodes, mirroring road-network semantics in which segments carry speed and intersections store mass. The resulting fundamental-diagram-constrained OT problem preserves mass conservation and admits a convex variational discretization, yielding optimal congestion-aware traffic flow over road networks. We establish the existence and uniqueness of the optimal flow with sources and sinks, and develop an efficient convex optimization method. Numerical studies begin with a single-lane line network and scale to a city-level road network.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00500v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anqi Dong, Karl Henrik Johansson, Johan Karlsson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Descriptive Model-based Learning and Control for Bipedal Locomotion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00512v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Bipedal balance is challenging due to its multi-phase, hybrid nature and high-dimensional state space. Traditional balance control approaches for bipedal robots rely on low-dimensional models for locomotion planning and reactive control, constraining the full robot to behave like these simplified models. This involves tracking preset reference paths for the Center of Mass and upper body obtained through low-dimensional models, often resulting in inefficient walking patterns with bent knees. However, we observe that bipedal balance is inherently low-dimensional and can be effectively described with simple state and action descriptors in a low-dimensional state space. This allows the robot's motion to evolve freely in its high-dimensional state space, only constraining its projection in the low-dimensional state space. In this work, we propose a novel control approach that avoids prescribing a low-dimensional model to the full model. Instead, our control framework uses a descriptive model with the minimum degrees of freedom necessary to maintain balance, allowing the remaining degrees of freedom to evolve freely in the high-dimensional space. This results in an efficient human-like walking gait and improved robustness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00512v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suraj Kumar, Andy Ruina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Improvisation and Open-Endedness: Insights for Experiential AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00529v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Improvisation-the art of spontaneous creation that unfolds moment-to-moment without a scripted outcome-requires practitioners to continuously sense, adapt, and create anew. It is a fundamental mode of human creativity spanning music, dance, and everyday life. The open-ended nature of improvisation produces a stream of novel, unrepeatable moments-an aspect highly valued in artistic creativity. In parallel, open-endedness (OE)-a system's capacity for unbounded novelty and endless "interestingness"-is exemplified in natural or cultural evolution and has been considered "the last grand challenge" in artificial life (ALife). The rise of generative AI now raises the question in computational creativity (CC) research: What makes a "good" improvisation for AI? Can AI learn to improvise in a genuinely open-ended way? In this work-in-progress paper, we report insights from in-depth interviews with 6 experts in improvisation across dance, music, and contact improvisation. We draw systemic connections between human improvisational arts and the design of future experiential AI agents that could improvise alone or alongside humans-or even with other AI agents-embodying qualities of improvisation drawn from practice: active listening (umwelt and awareness), being in the time (mindfulness and ephemerality), embracing the unknown (source of randomness and serendipity), non-judgmental flow (acceptance and dynamical stability, balancing structure and surprise (unpredictable criticality at edge of chaos), imaginative metaphor (synaesthesia and planning), empathy, trust, boundary, and care (mutual theory of mind), and playfulness and intrinsic motivation (maintaining interestingness).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00529v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Botao 'Amber' Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Image-based ground distance detection for crop-residue-covered soil</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00548v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Conservation agriculture features a soil surface covered with crop residues, which brings benefits of improving soil health and saving water. However, one significant challenge in conservation agriculture lies in precisely controlling the seeding depth on the soil covered with crop residues. This is constrained by the lack of ground distance information, since current distance measurement techniques, like laser, ultrasonic, or mechanical displacement sensors, are incapable of differentiating whether the distance information comes from the residue or the soil. This paper presents an image-based method to get the ground distance information for the crop-residues-covered soil. This method is performed with 3D camera and RGB camera, obtaining depth image and color image at the same time. The color image is used to distinguish the different areas of residues and soil and finally generates a mask image. The mask image is applied to the depth image so that only the soil area depth information can be used to calculate the ground distance, and residue areas can be recognized and excluded from ground distance detection. Experimentation shows that this distance measurement method is feasible for real-time implementation, and the measurement error is within plus or minus 3mm. It can be applied in conservation agriculture machinery for precision depth seeding, as well as other depth-control-demanding applications like transplant or tillage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00548v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baochao Wang, Xingyu Zhang, Qingtao Zong, Alim Pulatov, Shuqi Shang, Dongwei Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FTT-GRU: A Hybrid Fast Temporal Transformer with GRU for Remaining Useful Life Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00564v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Accurate prediction of the remaining useful life (RUL) of industrial machinery is essential for reducing downtime and optimizing maintenance schedules. Existing approaches, such as long short-term memory (LSTM) networks and convolutional neural networks (CNNs), often struggle to model both global temporal dependencies and fine-grained degradation trends in multivariate sensor data. We propose a hybrid model, FTT-GRU, which combines a Fast Temporal Transformer (FTT) -- a lightweight Transformer variant using linearized attention via fast Fourier transform (FFT) -- with a gated recurrent unit (GRU) layer for sequential modeling. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first application of an FTT with a GRU for RUL prediction on NASA CMAPSS, enabling simultaneous capture of global and local degradation patterns in a compact architecture. On CMAPSS FD001, FTT-GRU attains RMSE 30.76, MAE 18.97, and $R^2=0.45$, with 1.12 ms CPU latency at batch=1. Relative to the best published deep baseline (TCN--Attention), it improves RMSE by 1.16\% and MAE by 4.00\%. Training curves averaged over $k=3$ runs show smooth convergence with narrow 95\% confidence bands, and ablations (GRU-only, FTT-only) support the contribution of both components. These results demonstrate that a compact Transformer-RNN hybrid delivers accurate and efficient RUL predictions on CMAPSS, making it suitable for real-time industrial prognostics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00564v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Varun Teja Chirukiri, Udaya Bhasker Cheerala, Sandeep Kanta, Abdul Karim, Praveen Damacharla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Materials for Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (TMS)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00744</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00744v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Various coils for transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) are widely available for clinical and research use. These coils are almost all designed as air coils, which require large levels of energy to achieve a given magnetic flux density and in turn electric field strength, whereas in other sectors, such as power electronics or electrical machines, magnetic materials have been used for a long time to achieve higher efficiencies. We tested the impact on the electric and magnetic properties of different soft magnetic materials, including various ferrite cores, laminated sheet materials of nonisotropic corn-oriented silicon-steel, non-oriented silicon-steel, as well as cobalt-iron, and soft magnetic compound powder cores with insulated particles. Every material led to a reduction in coil current and voltage for the same target electric field strength. For the same field energy, every material yielded lower losses. Most common materials saturated already at very low currents. More material in thicker layers could shift the saturation point but at the cost of high weight. Due to their low saturation flux density, ferrites appear unsuitable for the high amplitude requirements of TMS. Laminated sheet materials and powder cores reduce the pulse energy, but the laminated sheet material adds more weight for the same effect than powder cores. Thus, appropriate magnetic materials can reduce the required pulse energy. Saturation flux density is the most relevant parameter, whereas the permeability beyond a certain base level is practically irrelevant. Most importantly, the weight of a magnetic-core coil may always be increased compared to an air coil for the same target field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00744v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max Koehler, Akshata Sangle, Stefan M. Goetz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Semantics Connect the Swarm: LLM-Driven Fuzzy Control for Cooperative Multi-Robot Underwater Coverage</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00783v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Underwater multi-robot cooperative coverage remains challenging due to partial observability, limited communication, environmental uncertainty, and the lack of access to global localization. To address these issues, this paper presents a semantics-guided fuzzy control framework that couples Large Language Models (LLMs) with interpretable control and lightweight coordination. Raw multimodal observations are compressed by the LLM into compact, human-interpretable semantic tokens that summarize obstacles, unexplored regions, and Objects Of Interest (OOIs) under uncertain perception. A fuzzy inference system with pre-defined membership functions then maps these tokens into smooth and stable steering and gait commands, enabling reliable navigation without relying on global positioning. Then, we further coordinate multiple robots by introducing semantic communication that shares intent and local context in linguistic form, enabling agreement on who explores where while avoiding redundant revisits. Extensive simulations in unknown reef-like environments show that, under limited sensing and communication, the proposed framework achieves robust OOI-oriented navigation and cooperative coverage with improved efficiency and adaptability, narrowing the gap between semantic cognition and distributed underwater control in GPS-denied, map-free conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00783v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingzehua Xu, Weihang Zhang, Yangyang Li, Hongmiaoyi Zhang, Guanwen Xie, Jiwei Tang, Shuai Zhang, Yi Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-Time Learning of Predictive Dynamic Obstacle Models for Robotic Motion Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00814v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Autonomous systems often must predict the motions of nearby agents from partial and noisy data. This paper asks and answers the question: "can we learn, in real-time, a nonlinear predictive model of another agent's motions?" Our online framework denoises and forecasts such dynamics using a modified sliding-window Hankel Dynamic Mode Decomposition (Hankel-DMD). Partial noisy measurements are embedded into a Hankel matrix, while an associated Page matrix enables singular-value hard thresholding (SVHT) to estimate the effective rank. A Cadzow projection enforces structured low-rank consistency, yielding a denoised trajectory and local noise variance estimates. From this representation, a time-varying Hankel-DMD lifted linear predictor is constructed for multi-step forecasts. The residual analysis provides variance-tracking signals that can support downstream estimators and risk-aware planning. We validate the approach in simulation under Gaussian and heavy-tailed noise, and experimentally on a dynamic crane testbed. Results show that the method achieves stable variance-aware denoising and short-horizon prediction suitable for integration into real-time control frameworks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00814v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stella Kombo, Masih Haseli, Skylar Wei, Joel W. Burdick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-Cost Carriers in Aviation: Significance and Developments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00932</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00932v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper aims to discuss the impacts of low-cost airlines on the air transport market and, in particular, to present the most recent findings from the specialized literature in this field. To this end, several papers published on the topic since 2015 were selected and analyzed. Based on this analysis, the main subjects addressed in the studies were categorized into five groups: (i) impacts of low-cost airlines on competing carriers; (ii) impacts on airports; (iii) general effects on air transport demand; (iv) effects on passengers' choice processes; and (v) broader effects on geographical regions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00932v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.5281/zenodo.17506763</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Communications in Airline Economics Research, 1, 10671650 (2024) 1-5</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bruno Felipe de Oliveira, Alessandro V. M. Oliveira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parallel KKT Solver in PIQP for Multistage Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00946v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents an efficient parallel Cholesky factorization and triangular solve algorithm for the Karush-Kuhn-Tucker (KKT) systems arising in multistage optimization problems, with a focus on model predictive control and trajectory optimization for racing. The proposed approach directly parallelizes solving the KKT systems with block-tridiagonal-arrow KKT matrices on the linear algebra level arising in interior-point methods. The algorithm is implemented as a new backend of the PIQP solver and released as open source. Numerical experiments on the chain-of-masses benchmarks and a minimum curvature race line optimization problem demonstrate substantial performance gains compared to other state-of-the-art solvers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00946v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fenglong Song, Roland Schwan, Yuwen Chen, Colin N. Jones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental Demonstration of Software-Orchestrated Quantum Network Applications over a Campus-Scale Testbed</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01247</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01247v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: To fulfill their promise, quantum networks must transform from isolated testbeds into scalable infrastructures for distributed quantum applications. In this paper, we present a prototype orchestrator for the Argonne Quantum Network (ArQNet) testbed that leverages design principles of software-defined networking (SDN) to automate typical quantum communication experiments across buildings in the Argonne campus connected over deployed, telecom fiber. Our implementation validates a scalable architecture supporting service-level abstraction of quantum networking tasks, distributed time synchronization, and entanglement verification across remote nodes. We present a prototype service of continuous, stable entanglement distribution between remote sites that ran for 12 hours, which defines a promising path towards scalable quantum networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01247v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Md. Shariful Islam (Argonne National Laboratory), Joaquin Chung (Argonne National Laboratory), Ely Marcus Eastman (Argonne National Laboratory, Northwestern University), Robert J. Hayek (Argonne National Laboratory), Prem Kumar (Northwestern University), Rajkumar Kettimuthu (Argonne National Laboratory)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Koopman-based Prediction of Connectivity for Flying Ad Hoc Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01286v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The application of machine learning (ML) to communication systems is expected to play a pivotal role in future artificial intelligence (AI)-based next-generation wireless networks. While most existing works focus on ML techniques for static wireless environments, they often face limitations when applied to highly dynamic environments, such as flying ad hoc networks (FANETs). This paper explores the use of data-driven Koopman approaches to address these challenges. Specifically, we investigate how these approaches can model UAV trajectory dynamics within FANETs, enabling more accurate predictions and improved network performance. By leveraging Koopman operator theory, we propose two possible approaches -- centralized and distributed -- to efficiently address the challenges posed by the constantly changing topology of FANETs. To demonstrate this, we consider a FANET performing surveillance with UAVs following pre-determined trajectories and predict signal-to-interference-plus-noise ratios (SINRs) to ensure reliable communication between UAVs. Our results show that these approaches can accurately predict connectivity and isolation events that lead to modelled communication outages. This capability could help UAVs schedule their transmissions based on these predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01286v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sivaram Krishnan, Jinho Choi, Jihong Park, Gregory Sherman, Benjamin Campbell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A High-Speed Capable Spherical Robot</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01288v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper designs a new spherical robot structure capable of supporting high-speed motion at up to 10 m/s. Building upon a single-pendulum-driven spherical robot, the design incorporates a momentum wheel with an axis aligned with the secondary pendulum, creating a novel spherical robot structure. Practical experiments with the physical prototype have demonstrated that this new spherical robot can achieve stable high-speed motion through simple decoupled control, which was unattainable with the original structure. The spherical robot designed for high-speed motion not only increases speed but also significantly enhances obstacle-crossing performance and terrain robustness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01288v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bixuan Zhang, Fengqi Zhang, Haojie Chen, You Wang, Jie Hao, Zhiyuan Luo, Guang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-driven stabilization of nonlinear systems via descriptor embedding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01457</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01457v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the notion of descriptor embedding for nonlinear systems and use it for the data-driven design of stabilizing controllers. Specifically, we provide sufficient data-dependent LMI conditions which, if feasible, return a stabilizing nonlinear controller of the form $u=K(x)Z(x)$ where $K(x)$ belongs to a polytope and $Z$ is a user-defined function. The proposed method is then extended to account for the presence of uncertainties and noisy data. Furthermore, a method to estimate the resulting region of attraction is given using only data. Simulation examples are used to illustrate the results and compare them to existing methods from the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01457v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Alsalti, Claudio De Persis, Victor G. Lopez, Matthias A. M\"uller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MOBIUS: A Multi-Modal Bipedal Robot that can Walk, Crawl, Climb, and Roll</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01774v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This article presents a Multi-Modal Bipedal Intelligent Urban Scout robot (MOBIUS) capable of walking, crawling, climbing, and rolling. MOBIUS features four limbs--two 6-DoF arms with two-finger grippers for manipulation and climbing, and two 4-DoF legs for locomotion--enabling smooth transitions across diverse terrains without reconfiguration. A hybrid control architecture combines reinforcement learning-based locomotion with model-based predictive and admittance control enhanced for safety by a Reference Governor toward compliant contact interactions. A high-level MIQCP planner autonomously selects locomotion modes to balance stability and energy efficiency. Hardware experiments demonstrate robust gait transitions, dynamic climbing, and full-body load support via pinch grasp. Overall, MOBIUS demonstrates the importance of tight integration between morphology, high-level planning, and control to enable mobile loco-manipulation and grasping, substantially expanding its interaction capabilities, workspace, and traversability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01774v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Schperberg, Yusuke Tanaka, Stefano Di Cairano, Dennis Hong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Iterative Cut-Based PWA Approximation of Multi-Dimensional Nonlinear Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16960v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: PieceWise Affine (PWA) approximations for nonlinear functions have been extensively used for tractable, computationally efficient control of nonlinear systems. However, reaching a desired approximation accuracy without prior information about the behavior of the nonlinear systems remains a challenge in the function approximation and control literature. As the name suggests, PWA approximation aims at approximating a nonlinear function or system by dividing the domain into multiple subregions where the nonlinear function or dynamics is approximated locally by an affine function also called local mode. Without prior knowledge of the form of the nonlinearity, the required number of modes, the locations of the subregions, and the local approximations need to be optimized simultaneously, which becomes highly complex for large-scale systems with multi-dimensional nonlinear functions. This paper introduces a novel approach for PWA approximation of multi-dimensional nonlinear systems, utilizing a hinging hyperplane formalism for cut-based partitioning of the domain. The complexity of the PWA approximation is iteratively increased until reaching the desired accuracy level. Further, the tractable cut definitions allow for different forms of subregions, as well as the ability to impose continuity constraints on the PWA approximation. The methodology is explained via multiple examples and its performance is compared to two existing approaches through case studies, showcasing its efficacy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16960v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leila Gharavi, Bart De Schutter, Simone Baldi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aggregative games with bilevel structures: Distributed algorithms and convergence analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13776v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, the problem of distributively seeking the equilibria of aggregative games with bilevel structures is studied. Different from the traditional aggregative games, here the aggregation is determined by the minimizer of a virtual leader's objective function in the inner level, which depends on the actions of the players in the outer level. Moreover, the global objective function of the virtual leader is formed by the sum of some local functions with two arguments, each of which is strongly convex with respect to the second argument. When making decisions, each player in the outer level only has access to a local part of the virtual leader's objective function. To handle this problem, first, we propose a second order gradient-based distributed algorithm, where the Hessian matrices associated with the objective functions of the leader are involved. By the algorithm, players update their actions while cooperatively minimizing the objective function of the virtual leader to estimate the aggregation by communicating with their neighbors via a connected graph. Under mild assumptions on the graph and cost functions, we prove that the actions of players asymptotically converge to the Nash equilibrium point. Then, for the case where the Hessian matrices associated with the objective functions of the virtual leader are not available, we propose a first order gradient-based distributed algorithm, where a distributed two-point estimate strategy is developed to estimate the gradients of players' cost functions in the outer level. Under the same conditions, we prove that the convergence errors of players' actions to the Nash equilibrium point are linear with respect to the estimate parameters. Finally, simulations are provided to demonstrate the effectiveness of our theoretical results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13776v4</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaihong Lu, Huanshui Zhang, Long Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributionally Robust Control Synthesis for Stochastic Systems with Safety and Reach-Avoid Specifications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03137v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the problem of synthesizing distributionally robust control policies for stochastic systems under safety and reach-avoid specifications. Using a game-theoretical framework, we consider the setting where the probability distribution of the disturbance at each time step is selected from an ambiguity set defined by the Wasserstein distance. The goal is to synthesize a distributionally robust control policy that ensures the satisfaction probability exceeds a specified threshold under any distribution within the ambiguity set. First, for both safety and reach-avoid specifications, we establish the existence of optimal policies by leveraging the dynamic programming principles. Then we demonstrate how the associated optimization problem can be efficiently solved using the dual representation of Wasserstein distributionally robust optimization. Furthermore, for safety specifications in particular, we introduce a novel concept of distributionally robust control barrier certificates and show how these enable the efficient synthesis of controllers through sum-of-squares programming techniques. Finally, our experimental results reveal that incorporating distributional robustness during the synthesis phase significantly improves the satisfaction probability during online execution, even with limited statistical knowledge of the disturbance distribution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03137v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Chen, Yuda Li, Shaoyuan Li, Xiang Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatio-Temporal Consistent Soft Sensor Modeling and Monitoring of Thermal Power Plants based on Physical Knowledge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00858v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Data-driven soft sensors have been widely applied in complex industrial processes. However, the interpretable spatio-temporal features extraction by soft sensors remains a challenge. In this light, this work introduces a novel method termed spatio-temporal consistent and interpretable model (STCIM). First, temporal and spatial features are captured and aligned by a far topological spatio-temporal consistency extraction block. Then, the features are mapped into an interpretable latent space for further prediction by explicitly giving physical meanings to latent variables. The efficacy of the proposed STCIM is demonstrated through the modeling of two generated datasets and a real-life dataset of coal-fired power plants. The corresponding experiments show: 1) The generalization of STCIM outperforms other methods, especially in different operation situations. 2) The far topological spatio-temporal consistency is vital for feature alignment. 3) The hyper-parameters of physics-informed interpretable latent space loss decide the performance of STCIM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00858v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qianchao Wang, Peng Sha, Leena Heistrene, Yuxuan Ding, Yaping Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imperfect Competition in Markets for Short-Circuit Current Services</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09425v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: An important limitation of Inverter-Based Resources (IBR) is their reduced contribution to Short-Circuit Current (SCC), as compared to that of Synchronous Generators (SGs). With increasing penetration of IBR in most power systems, the reducing SCC poses challenges to a secure system operation, as line protections may not trip when required. In order to address this issue, the SCC ancillary service could be procured via an economic mechanism, aiming at securing adequate SCC on all buses. However, the suitability of markets for SCC services is not well understood, given that these could be prone to market-power issues: since the SCC contributions from various SGs to a certain bus are determined by the electrical topology of the grid, this is a highly local service. It is necessary to understand if SGs at advantageous electrical locations could exert market power and, if so, how it could be mitigated. In order to fill this gap, this paper adopts an SCC-constrained bilevel model to investigate strategic behaviors of SGs. To address the non-convexity due to unit commitment variables, the model is restructured through a primal-dual formulation. Based on a modified IEEE 30-bus system, cases with strategic SGs placed at different buses are analyzed. These studies demonstrate that agents exerting market power could achieve up to triple revenues from SCC provision, highlighting the need to carefully design these markets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09425v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peng Wang, Luis Badesa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introducing Coherent-Control Koopman Modeling to Reservoir Scale Porous Media Flow Studies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17857</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17857v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Accurate and robust surrogate modeling is essential for the real-time control and optimization of large-scale subsurface systems, such as geological CO2 storage and waterflood management. This study investigates the limits of classical Dynamic Mode Decomposition with control (DMDc) and introduces CCKM, as a robust alter-native, in enforcing control in pressure and water saturation reservoir dynamics under challenging prediction scenarios. We introduced a control-coherent incremental ({\Delta}) CCKM formulation, in which the field update is driven by actuator changes rather than rather than actuator levels as in the original level formulation and compared them both against DMDc and a Hybrid B-only surrogate that re-uses DMDcs bottom-B (same-step feed-through), showing that only CCKM remains stable and accurate under regime shifts. Two representative cases are considered: (i) an out-of-distribution shut-in and restart case, and (ii) an in-distribution bottomhole pressure (BHP) drawdown. Results show that only CCKM consistently maintains stability and accuracy across both scenarios, achieving sub-bar mean absolute error and sub-percent Frobenius norm percent change error (FPCE) even under regime shifts, while DMDc exhibit large unphysical errors during control transients. The findings demonstrate that strict control-coherence is critical for reliable surrogate modeling, particularly in settings with abrupt changes in control strategy. The proposed framework is broadly applicable to real-time reservoir optimization and can be integrated seamlessly into existing optimization and monitoring workflows, enabling fast and trustworthy deci-sion support in the presence of both expected and unexpected actuation regimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17857v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dimitrios Voulanas, Eduardo Gildin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Networks for AC Optimal Power Flow: Improving Worst-Case Guarantees during Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23196v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The AC Optimal Power Flow (AC-OPF) problem is central to power system operation but challenging to solve efficiently due to its nonconvex and nonlinear nature. Neural networks (NNs) offer fast surrogates, yet their black-box behavior raises concerns about constraint violations that can compromise safety. We propose a verification-informed NN framework that incorporates worst-case constraint violations directly into training, producing models that are both accurate and provably safer. Through post-hoc verification, we achieve substantial reductions in worst-case violations and, for the first time, verify all operational constraints of large-scale AC-OPF proxies. Practical feasibility is further enhanced via restoration and warm-start strategies for infeasible operating points. Experiments on systems ranging from 57 to 793 buses demonstrate scalability, speed, and reliability, bridging the gap between ML acceleration and safe, real-time deployment of AC-OPF solutions - and paving the way toward data-driven optimal control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23196v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bastien Giraud, Rahul Nellikath, Johanna Vorwerk, Maad Alowaifeer, Spyros Chatzivasileiadis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal and Heuristic Approaches for Platooning Systems with Deadlines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25564v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Efficient truck platooning is a key strategy for reducing freight costs, lowering fuel consumption, and mitigating emissions. Deadlines are critical in this context, as trucks must depart within specific time windows to meet delivery requirements and avoid penalties. In this paper, we investigate the optimal formation and dispatch of truck platoons at a highway station with finite capacity \(L\) and deadline constraints \(T\). The system operates in discrete time, with each arriving truck assigned a deadline of \(T\) slot units. The objective is to leverage the efficiency gains from forming large platoons while accounting for waiting costs and deadline violations. We formulate the problem as a Markov decision process and analyze the structure of the optimal policy \(\pi^\star\) for \(L = 3\), extending insights to arbitrary \(L\). We prove certain monotonicity properties of the optimal policy in the state space \(\mathcal{S}\) and identify classes of unreachable states. Moreover, since the size of \(\mathcal{S}\) grows exponentially with \(L\) and \(T\), we propose heuristics--including conditional and deep-learning based approaches--that exploit these structural insights while maintaining low computational complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25564v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thiago S. Gomides, Evangelos Kranakis, Ioannis Lambadaris, Yannis Viniotis, Gennady Shaikhet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ORFit: One-Pass Learning via Bridging Orthogonal Gradient Descent and Recursive Least-Squares</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.13853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.13853v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: While large machine learning models have shown remarkable performance in various domains, their training typically requires iterating for many passes over the training data. However, due to computational and memory constraints and potential privacy concerns, storing and accessing all the data is impractical in many real-world scenarios where the data arrives in a stream. In this paper, we investigate the problem of one-pass learning, in which a model is trained on sequentially arriving data without retraining on previous datapoints. Motivated by the demonstrated effectiveness of overparameterized models and the phenomenon of benign overfitting, we propose Orthogonal Recursive Fitting (ORFit), an algorithm for one-pass learning which seeks to perfectly fit each new datapoint while minimally altering the predictions on previous datapoints. ORFit updates the parameters in a direction orthogonal to past gradients, similar to orthogonal gradient descent (OGD) in continual learning. We show that, interestingly, ORFit's update leads to an operation similar to the recursive least-squares (RLS) algorithm in adaptive filtering but with significantly improved memory and computational efficiency, i.e., linear, instead of quadratic, in the number of parameters. To further reduce memory usage, we leverage the structure of the streaming data via an incremental principal component analysis (IPCA). We show that using the principal components is minimax optimal, i.e., it minimizes the worst-case forgetting of previous predictions for unknown future updates. Further, we prove that, for overparameterized linear models, the parameter vector obtained by ORFit matches what the standard multi-pass stochastic gradient descent (SGD) would converge to. Finally, we extend our results to the nonlinear setting for highly overparameterized models, relevant for deep learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.13853v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youngjae Min, Namhoon Cho, Navid Azizan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spherical Point Process with Random Heights: New Approach for Modeling and Analysis of Downlink Satellite Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.03343</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.03343v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Low Earth Orbit (LEO) satellite industry is undergoing rapid expansion, with operators competitively launching satellites due to the first-come, first-served principle governing orbital rights. This has led to the formation of increasingly large-scale, volumetric constellation where satellites operate across a diverse range of altitudes. To address the need for analyzing such complex networks, this paper establishes a new analytical framework for LEO constellations by leveraging a 3D Poisson point process (PPP). Specifically, we introduce a random height model (RHM) that can capture various altitude distributions by applying a random radial displacement to points generated by a homogeneous PPP on a nominal shell. Building on this, we derive an analytical expression for the downlink coverage probability. To motivate our model, we show that the altitude distributions of several leading satellite constellations, including Starlink, align with our model's assumptions. We then demonstrate through Monte Carlo simulations that the coverage probability of our RHM closely matches that of these real-world networks. Finally, we confirm the accuracy of our analytical expressions by showing their agreement with simulation results. Our work thereby provides a powerful tool for understanding and predict how the statistical distribution of satellite altitudes impacts network performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.03343v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seyong Kim, Jinseok Choi, Namyoon Lee, Fran\c{c}ois Baccelli, Jeonghun Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lyapunov Neural ODE State-Feedback Control Policies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.00393</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.00393v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Deep neural networks are increasingly used as an effective parameterization of control policies in various learning-based control paradigms. For continuous-time optimal control problems (OCPs), which are central to many decision-making tasks, control policy learning can be cast as a neural ordinary differential equation (NODE) problem wherein state and control constraints are naturally accommodated. This paper presents a NODE approach to solving continuous-time OCPs for the case of stabilizing a known constrained nonlinear system around a target state. The approach, termed Lyapunov-NODE control (L-NODEC), uses a novel Lyapunov loss formulation that incorporates an exponentially-stabilizing control Lyapunov function to learn a state-feedback neural control policy, bridging the gap of solving continuous-time OCPs via NODEs with stability guarantees. The proposed Lyapunov loss allows L-NODEC to guarantee exponential stability of the controlled system, as well as its adversarial robustness to perturbations to the initial state. The performance of L-NODEC is illustrated in two problems, including a dose delivery problem in plasma medicine. In both cases, L-NODEC effectively stabilizes the controlled system around the target state despite perturbations to the initial state and reduces the inference time necessary to reach the target.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.00393v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Hang Sai Ip, Georgios Makrygiorgos, Ali Mesbah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Multirobot Virtual Structure Control using Dual Quaternions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.05560v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a control strategy based on dual quaternions for the coordinated formation flying of small UAV groups. A virtual structure is employed to define the desired formation, enabling unified control of its position, orientation, and shape. This abstraction makes formation management easier by allowing a low-level controller to compute individual UAV commands efficiently. The proposed controller integrates a pose control module with a geometry-based adaptive strategy, ensuring precise and robust task execution. The effectiveness of the approach is demonstrated through both simulation and experimental results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.05560v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan I. Giribet, Alejandro S. Ghersin, Ignacio Mas, Harrison Neves Marciano, Daniel Khede Dourado Villa, Mario Sarcinelli-Filho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limits of Safe AI Deployment: Differentiating Oversight and Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03525</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03525v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Oversight and control, which we collectively call supervision, are often discussed as ways to ensure that AI systems are accountable, reliable, and able to fulfill governance and management requirements. However, the requirements for "human oversight" risk codifying vague or inconsistent interpretations of key concepts like oversight and control. This ambiguous terminology could undermine efforts to design or evaluate systems that must operate under meaningful human supervision. This matters because the term is used by regulatory texts such as the EU AI Act.
  This paper undertakes a targeted critical review of literature on supervision outside of AI, along with a brief summary of past work on the topic related to AI. We next differentiate control as ex-ante or real-time and operational rather than policy or governance, and oversight as performed ex-post, or a policy and governance function. Control aims to prevent failures, while oversight focuses on detection, remediation, or incentives for future prevention. Building on this, we make three contributions. 1) We propose a framework to align regulatory expectations with what is technically and organizationally plausible, articulating the conditions under which each mechanism is possible, where they fall short, and what is required to make them meaningful in practice. 2) We outline how supervision methods should be documented and integrated into risk management, and drawing on the Microsoft Responsible AI Maturity Model, we outline a maturity model for AI supervision. 3) We explicitly highlight boundaries of these mechanisms, including where they apply, where they fail, and where it is clear that no existing methods suffice. This foregrounds the question of whether meaningful supervision is possible in a given deployment context, and can support regulators, auditors, and practitioners in identifying both present and future limitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03525v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Manheim, Aidan Homewood</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dual-Regularized Riccati Recursions for Interior-Point Optimal Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.16370v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We derive closed-form extensions of Riccati's recursions (both sequential and parallel) for solving dual-regularized LQR problems. We show how these methods can be used to solve general constrained, non-convex, discrete-time optimal control problems via a regularized interior point method, while guaranteeing that each primal step is a descent direction of an Augmented Barrier-Lagrangian merit function. We provide MIT-licensed implementations of our methods in C++ and JAX.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.16370v4</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.MS</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jo\~ao Sousa-Pinto, Dominique Orban</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
