<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SY updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SY</link>
    <description>cs.SY updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SY" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 04:01:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>An Explainable Equity-Aware P2P Energy Trading Framework for Socio-Economically Diverse Microgrid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18738v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fair and dynamic energy allocation in community microgrids remains a critical challenge, particularly when serving socio-economically diverse participants. Static optimization and cost-sharing methods often fail to adapt to evolving inequities, leading to participant dissatisfaction and unsustainable cooperation. This paper proposes a novel framework that integrates multi-objective mixed-integer linear programming (MILP), cooperative game theory, and a dynamic equity-adjustment mechanism driven by reinforcement learning (RL). At its core, the framework utilizes a bi-level optimization model grounded in Equity-regarding Welfare Maximization (EqWM) principles, which incorporate Rawlsian fairness to prioritize the welfare of the least advantaged participants. We introduce a Proximal Policy Optimization (PPO) agent that dynamically adjusts socio-economic weights in the optimization objective based on observed inequities in cost and renewable energy access. This RL-powered feedback loop enables the system to learn and adapt, continuously striving for a more equitable state. To ensure transparency, Explainable AI (XAI) is used to interpret the benefit allocations derived from a weighted Shapley value. Validated across six realistic scenarios, the framework demonstrates peak demand reductions of up to 72.6%, and significant cooperative gains. The adaptive RL mechanism further reduces the Gini coefficient over time, showcasing a pathway to truly sustainable and fair energy communities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18738v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhijan Theja, Mayukha Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximating CCCV charging using SOC-dependent tapered charging power constraints in long-term microgrid planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18853v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Traditional long-term microgrid planning models assume constant power charging for battery energy storage systems (BESS), overlooking efficiency losses that occur toward the end of charge due to rising internal resistance. While this issue can be mitigated at the cell level using constant current-constant voltage (CCCV) charging, it is impractical at the pack level in large-scale systems. However, battery management systems and inverter controls can emulate this effect by tapering charging power at high state-of-charge (SOC) levels, trading off charging speed for improved efficiency and reduced thermal stress. Ignoring this behavior in planning models can lead to undersized batteries and potential reliability issues. This paper proposes a tractable and scalable approach to approximate CCCV behavior using SOC-dependent tapered charging power (TCP) constraints. A MATLAB-based proof of concept demonstrates the energy delivery and efficiency benefits of tapering. The method is integrated into a long-term planning framework and evaluated under a synthetic load and solar profile. Results show tapering significantly affects BESS sizing, cost, and reliability under dynamic operating conditions that demand fast charging. These findings highlight tapering as a critical modeling factor for accurately capturing BESS performance in long-term microgrid planning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18853v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hassan Zahid Butt, Xingpeng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Robustness of Control Barrier Function: A Reciprocal Resistance-based Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18888v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this note, a new reciprocal resistance-based control barrier function (RRCBF) is developed to enhance the robustness of control barrier functions for disturbed affine nonlinear systems, without requiring explicit knowledge of disturbance bounds. By integrating a reciprocal resistance-like term into the conventional zeroing barrier function framework, we formally establish the concept of the reciprocal resistance-based barrier function (RRBF), rigorously proving the forward invariance of its associated safe set and its robustness against bounded disturbances. The RRBF inherently generates a buffer zone near the boundary of the safe set, effectively dominating the influence of uncertainties and external disturbances. This foundational concept is extended to formulate RRCBFs, including their high-order variants. To alleviate conservatism in the presence of complex, time-varying disturbances, we further introduce a disturbance observer-based RRCBF (DO-RRCBF), which exploits disturbance estimates to enhance safety guarantees and recover nominal control performance. The effectiveness of the proposed framework is validated through two simulation studies: a second-order linear system illustrating forward invariance in the phase plane, and an adaptive cruise control scenario demonstrating robustness in systems with high relative degree.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18888v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinming Wang, Zongyi Guo, Jianguo Guo, Jun Yang, Yunda Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GMM-Based Time-Varying Coverage Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18938v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In coverage control problems that involve time-varying density functions, the coverage control law depends on spatial integrals of the time evolution of the density function. The latter is often neglected, replaced with an upper bound or calculated as a numerical approximation of the spatial integrals involved. In this paper, we consider a special case of time-varying density functions modeled as Gaussian Mixture Models (GMMs) that evolve with time via a set of time-varying sources (with known corresponding velocities). By imposing this structure, we obtain an efficient time-varying coverage controller that fully incorporates the time evolution of the density function. We show that the induced trajectories under our control law minimise the overall coverage cost. We elicit the structure of the proposed controller and compare it with a classical time-varying coverage controller, against which we benchmark the coverage performance in simulation. Furthermore, we highlight that the computationally efficient and distributed nature of the proposed control law makes it ideal for multi-vehicle robotic applications involving time-varying coverage control problems. We employ our method in plume monitoring using a swarm of drones. In an experimental field trial we show that drones guided by the proposed controller are able to track a simulated time-varying chemical plume in a distributed manner.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18938v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Behzad Zamani, James Kennedy, Airlie Chapman, Peter Dower, Chris Manzie, Simon Crase</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Research on Sectionalizing Switches Placement Problem of Distribution System Automation Based on Multi-Objective Optimization Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19029</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19029v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Achieving high distribution-reliability levels and concurrently minimizing operating costs can be considered as the main issues in distribution system optimization. Determination of the optimal number and location of automation devices in the distribution system network is an essential issue from the reliability and economical points of view. To address these issues, this paper develops a multi-objective model, wherein the primary objective, optimal automation devices placement is implemented aiming at minimizing the operating costs, while in the second objective the reliability indices improvement is taken into account. So, modified non dominated sorting genetic algorithm, is developed and presented to solve this multi-objective mixed-integer non-linear programming problem. The feasibility of the proposed algorithm examined by application to two distribution feeders of the Tabriz distribution network containing the third feeder of the Azar substation with a distributed generation unit and first and third feeders of ElGoli substation which form a double feed feeder.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19029v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Selma Cheshmeh Khavar, Arya Abdollahi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radio Map Assisted Routing and Predictive Resource Allocation over Dynamic Low Altitude Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19111</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19111v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dynamic low altitude networks offer significant potential for efficient and reliable data transport via unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs) relays which usually operate with predetermined trajectories. However, it is challenging to optimize the data routing and resource allocation due to the time-varying topology and the need to control interference with terrestrial systems. Traditional schemes rely on time-expanded graphs with uniform and fine time subdivisions, making them impractical for interference-aware applications. This paper develops a dynamic space-time graph model with a cross-layer optimization framework that converts a joint routing and predictive resource allocation problem into a joint bottleneck path planning and resource allocation problem. We develop explicit deterministic bounds to handle the channel uncertainty and prove a monotonicity property in the problem structure that enables us to efficiently reach the globally optimal solution to the predictive resource allocation subproblem. Then, this approach is extended to multi-commodity transmission tasks through time-frequency allocation, and a bisection search algorithm is developed to find the optimum solution by leveraging the monotonicity of the feasible set family. Simulations verify that the single-commodity algorithm approaches global optimality with more than 30 dB performance gain over the classical graph-based methods for delay-sensitive and large data transportation. At the same time, the multi-commodity method achieves 100X improvements in dense service scenarios and enables an additional 20 dB performance gain by data segmenting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19111v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bowen Li, Junting Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Truncated Gaussian Noise Estimation in State-Space Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19244</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19244v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Within Bayesian state estimation, considerable effort has been devoted to incorporating constraints into state estimation for process optimization, state monitoring, fault detection and control. Nonetheless, in the domain of state-space system identification, the prevalent practice entails constructing models under Gaussian noise assumptions, which can lead to inaccuracies when the noise follows bounded distributions. With the aim of generalizing the Gaussian noise assumption to potentially truncated densities, this paper introduces a method for estimating the noise parameters in a state-space model subject to truncated Gaussian noise. Our proposed data-driven approach is rooted in maximum likelihood principles combined with the Expectation-Maximization algorithm. The efficacy of the proposed approach is supported by a simulation example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19244v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rodrigo A. Gonz\'alez, Angel L. Cede\~no, Koen Tiels, Tom Oomen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cell-based VSC Analysis Methodology: From Graph Laplacian to Converter Degrees of Freedom</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19260v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Power-electronics-based converters are being considerably employed through the power system to interconnect multiple heterogeneous electrical layers. Furthermore, the intrinsic versatility to play with the converter network topology is widely exploited to accommodate a certain number of terminals and ports according with the specific application. On this regard, several converter arrangements can be encountered in power applications. Moreover, to properly establish both the operation and the control, the so-called degrees of freedom (DOFs) need to be assessed per each converter topology. On this matter, similarly to the well-known Clarke transformation, which clearly reveals the DOFs for the star-based topology system, further similar transformations can be achieved to depict the independent set of variables characterizing a certain converter structure. Referring to the cell-based class of Voltage Source Converter (VSC) topologies, including Modular Multilevel Converter (MMC); this article proposes a general methodology to determine the change of variable matrix transformation for several converter arrangements which are related to complete bi-partite and multi-partite graphs. The methodology lies in the graph Laplacian spectral analysis, which remarks the structural normal modes at the converter points of connections. Furthermore, for a complete characterization, the instantaneous power patterns formulations, based on the DOFs, are also introduced.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19260v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniele Falchi, Eduardo Prieto-Araujo, Oriol Gomis-Bellmunt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Year Maintenance Planning for Large-Scale Infrastructure Systems: A Novel Network Deep Q-Learning Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18732v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Infrastructure asset management is essential for sustaining the performance of public infrastructure such as road networks, bridges, and utility networks. Traditional maintenance and rehabilitation planning methods often face scalability and computational challenges, particularly for large-scale networks with thousands of assets under budget constraints. This paper presents a novel deep reinforcement learning (DRL) framework that optimizes asset management strategies for large infrastructure networks. By decomposing the network-level Markov Decision Process (MDP) into individual asset-level MDPs while using a unified neural network architecture, the proposed framework reduces computational complexity, improves learning efficiency, and enhances scalability. The framework directly incorporates annual budget constraints through a budget allocation mechanism, ensuring maintenance plans are both optimal and cost-effective. Through a case study on a large-scale pavement network of 68,800 segments, the proposed DRL framework demonstrates significant improvements over traditional methods like Progressive Linear Programming and genetic algorithms, both in efficiency and network performance. This advancement contributes to infrastructure asset management and the broader application of reinforcement learning in complex, large-scale environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18732v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amir Fard, Arnold X. -X. Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Distributed Approach for Agile Supply Chain Decision-Making Based on Network Attributes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19038v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In recent years, the frequent occurrence of disruptions has had a negative impact on global supply chains. To stay competitive, enterprises strive to remain agile through the implementation of efficient and effective decision-making strategies in reaction to disruptions. A significant effort has been made to develop these agile disruption mitigation approaches, leveraging both centralized and distributed decision-making strategies. Though trade-offs of centralized and distributed approaches have been analyzed in existing studies, no related work has been found on understanding supply chain performance based on the network attributes of the disrupted supply chain entities. In this paper, we characterize supply chains from a capability and network topological perspective and investigate the use of a distributed decision-making approach based on classical multi-agent frameworks. The performance of the distributed framework is evaluated through a comprehensive case study that investigates the performance of the supply chain as a function of the network structure and agent attributes within the network in the presence of a disruption. Comparison to a centralized decision-making approach highlights trade-offs between performance, computation time, and network communication based on the decision-making strategy and network architecture. Practitioners can use the outcomes of our studies to design response strategies based on agent capabilities, network attributes, and desired supply chain performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19038v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TASE.2023.3339171</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Transactions on Automation Science and Engineering 21 (2024) 2223-2236</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mingjie Bi, Dawn M. Tilbury, Siqian Shen, Kira Barton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic distributed decision-making for resilient resource reallocation in disrupted manufacturing systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19043</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19043v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The COVID-19 pandemic brings many unexpected disruptions, such as frequently shifting markets and limited human workforce, to manufacturers. To stay competitive, flexible and real-time manufacturing decision-making strategies are needed to deal with such highly dynamic manufacturing environments. One essential problem is dynamic resource allocation to complete production tasks, especially when a resource disruption (e.g., machine breakdown) occurs. Though multi-agent methods have been proposed to solve the problem in a flexible and agile manner, the agent internal decision-making process and resource uncertainties have rarely been studied. This work introduces a model-based resource agent (RA) architecture that enables effective agent coordination and dynamic agent decision-making. Based on the RA architecture, a rescheduling strategy that incorporates risk assessment via a clustering agent coordination strategy is also proposed. A simulation-based case study is implemented to demonstrate dynamic rescheduling using the proposed multi-agent framework. The results show that the proposed method reduces the computational efforts while losing some throughput optimality compared to the centralized method. Furthermore, the case study illustrates that incorporating risk assessment into rescheduling decision-making improves the throughput.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19043v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1080/00207543.2023.2200567</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Journal of Production Research 62 (2024) 1737-1757</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mingjie Bi, Ilya Kovalenko, Dawn M. Tilbury, Kira Barton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heterogeneous Risk Management Using a Multi-Agent Framework for Supply Chain Disruption Response</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19049</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19049v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the highly complex and stochastic global, supply chain environments, local enterprise agents seek distributed and dynamic strategies for agile responses to disruptions. Existing literature explores both centralized and distributed approaches, while most work neglects temporal dynamics and the heterogeneity of the risk management of individual agents. To address this gap, this letter presents a heterogeneous risk management mechanism to incorporate uncertainties and risk attitudes into agent communication and decision-making strategy. Hence, this approach empowers enterprises to handle disruptions in stochastic environments in a distributed way, and in particular in the context of multi-agent control and management. Through a simulated case study, we showcase the feasibility and effectiveness of the proposed approach under stochastic settings and how the decision of disruption responses changes when agents hold various risk attitudes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19049v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LRA.2024.3388838</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters 9 (2024) 5126-5133</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mingjie Bi, Juan-Alberto Estrada-Garcia, Dawn M. Tilbury, Siqian Shen, Kira Barton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monocular Vision-Based Swarm Robot Localization Using Equilateral Triangular Formations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19100v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Localization of mobile robots is crucial for deploying robots in real-world applications such as search and rescue missions. This work aims to develop an accurate localization system applicable to swarm robots equipped only with low-cost monocular vision sensors and visual markers. The system is designed to operate in fully open spaces, without landmarks or support from positioning infrastructures. To achieve this, we propose a localization method based on equilateral triangular formations. By leveraging the geometric properties of equilateral triangles, the accurate two-dimensional position of each participating robot is estimated using one-dimensional lateral distance information between robots, which can be reliably and accurately obtained with a low-cost monocular vision sensor. Experimental and simulation results demonstrate that, as travel time increases, the positioning error of the proposed method becomes significantly smaller than that of a conventional dead-reckoning system, another low-cost localization approach applicable to open environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19100v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taewon Kang, Ji-Wook Kwon, Il Bae, Jin Hyo Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Control of Hybrid Systems via Measure Relaxations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19210v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose an approach to trajectory optimization for piecewise polynomial systems based on the recently proposed graphs of convex sets framework. We instantiate the framework with a convex relaxation of optimal control based on occupation measures, resulting in a convex optimization problem resembling the discrete shortest-paths linear program that can be solved efficiently to global optimality. While this approach inherits the limitations of semidefinite programming, scalability to large numbers of discrete modes improves compared to the NP-hard mixed-integer formulation. We use this to plan trajectories under temporal logic specifications, comparing the computed cost lower bound to a nonconvex optimization approach with fixed mode sequence. In our numerical experiments, we find that this bound is typically in the vicinity of the nonconvex solution, while the runtime speedup is significant compared to the often intractable mixed-integer formulation. Our implementation is available at https://github.com/ebuehrle/hpoc.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19210v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Etienne Buehrle, \"Omer \c{S}ahin Ta\c{s}, Christoph Stiller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-time rail vehicle localisation using spatially resolved magnetic field measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19327v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work presents two complementary real-time rail vehicle localization methods based on magnetic field measurements and a pre-recorded magnetic map. The first uses a particle filter reweighted via magnetic similarity, employing a heavy-tailed non-Gaussian kernel for enhanced stability. The second is a stateless sequence alignment technique that transforms real-time magnetic signals into the spatial domain and matches them to the map using a similarity measure. Experiments with operational train data show that the particle filter achieves track-selective, sub-5-meter accuracy over 21.6 km, though its performance degrades at low speeds and during cold starts. Accuracy tests were constrained by the GNSS-based reference system. In contrast, the alignment-based method excels in cold-start scenarios, localizing within 30 m in 92 % of tests (100 % using top-3 matches). A hybrid approach combines both methods$\unicode{x2014}$alignment-based initialization followed by particle filter tracking. Runtime analysis confirms real-time capability on consumer-grade hardware. The system delivers accurate, robust localization suitable for safety-critical rail applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19327v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niklas Dieckow, Katharina Ostaszewski, Philip Heinisch, Henriette Struckmann, Hendrik Ranocha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchical Deep Reinforcement Learning Framework for Multi-Year Asset Management Under Budget Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19458v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Budget planning and maintenance optimization are crucial for infrastructure asset management, ensuring cost-effectiveness and sustainability. However, the complexity arising from combinatorial action spaces, diverse asset deterioration, stringent budget constraints, and environmental uncertainty significantly limits existing methods' scalability. This paper proposes a Hierarchical Deep Reinforcement Learning methodology specifically tailored to multi-year infrastructure planning. Our approach decomposes the problem into two hierarchical levels: a high-level Budget Planner allocating annual budgets within explicit feasibility bounds, and a low-level Maintenance Planner prioritizing assets within the allocated budget. By structurally separating macro-budget decisions from asset-level prioritization and integrating linear programming projection within a hierarchical Soft Actor-Critic framework, the method efficiently addresses exponential growth in the action space and ensures rigorous budget compliance. A case study evaluating sewer networks of varying sizes (10, 15, and 20 sewersheds) illustrates the effectiveness of the proposed approach. Compared to conventional Deep Q-Learning and enhanced genetic algorithms, our methodology converges more rapidly, scales effectively, and consistently delivers near-optimal solutions even as network size grows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19458v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amir Fard, Arnold X. -X. Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GREAT: Grassmannian REcursive Algorithm for Tracking &amp; Online System Identification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09052v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces an online approach for identifying time-varying subspaces defined by linear dynamical systems. The approach of representing linear systems by non-parametric subspace models has received significant interest in the field of data-driven control recently. This system representation enables us to provide rigorous guarantees for linear time-varying systems, which are difficult to obtain for parametric system models. The proposed method leverages optimization on the Grassmann manifold leading to the Grassmannian Recursive Algorithm for Tracking (GREAT). We view subspaces as points on the Grassmann manifold and adapt the estimate based on online data by performing optimization on the manifold. At each time step, a single measurement from the current subspace corrupted by a bounded error is available. The subspace estimate is updated online using Grassmannian gradient descent on a cost function incorporating a window of the most recent data. Under suitable assumptions on the signal-to-noise ratio of the online data and the subspace's rate of change, we establish theoretical guarantees for the resulting algorithm. More specifically, we prove an exponential convergence rate and provide an uncertainty quantification of the estimates in terms of an upper bound on their distance to the true subspace. The applicability of the proposed algorithm is demonstrated by means of numerical examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09052v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'as Sasfi, Alberto Padoan, Ivan Markovsky, Florian D\"orfler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Self-Improvement for Smarter Energy Systems using Agentic Policy Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19340</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19340v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Controlling energy systems usually involves manually designed policies for decision-making, which can be complex and time-consuming to develop. This process requires interdisciplinary collaboration among multiple domain experts, resulting in slow and inflexible adaptation to rapidly changing environments. Large Language Models (LLMs) offer a promising paradigm shift by integrating extensive contextual knowledge with the capability to generate structured, executable code.
  We present Agentic Policy Search (APS) -- a novel hierarchical optimization framework in which LLMs act as autonomous agents that propose complete control logics, translate them into executable code, and iteratively improve them through direct system feedback. We apply APS to a residential energy system with PV, battery, demand, and dynamic electricity prices. Within just seven simulated days, the method yields a net profit of up to 6.20 EUR compared to the no-battery reference scenario (-10.70 EUR), nearly matching the global optimum of a perfectly informed linear program. By combining LLM-driven policy search with the generation of human-interpretable control logic, APS effectively bridges adaptability and traceability in energy management -- while also offering a transferable framework for agentic optimization in other domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19340v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Sommer, Peter Bazan, Behnam Babaeian, Jonathan Fellerer, Warren B. Powell, Reinhard German</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modal-based prediction of power system frequency response and frequency nadir</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02735v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel approach for predicting system frequency response (SFR) and frequency nadir based on modal analysis. By decomposing the full system dynamic response, the method identifies dominant modes based on their participation in frequency behavior and derives a closed-form expression for the frequency trajectory. Unlike traditional approaches based on the Average System Frequency (ASF) model, this method captures the true system dynamics and avoids oversimplified representations. The dominant modes exhibit low sensitivity to system parameters, enabling robust and accurate estimations across diverse operating conditions. The proposed approach is tested on two benchmark systems as well as the Salvadoran transmission planning network, demonstrating its scalability, precision, and adaptability. This methodology represents a shift from observing a simplified average system frequency response to a more detailed analysis focusing on system dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02735v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francisco Zelaya-Arrazabal, Sebastian Martinez-Lizana, H\'ector Pulgar-Painemal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integration of a Graph-Based Path Planner and Mixed-Integer MPC for Robot Navigation in Cluttered Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13372v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The ability to update a path plan is a required capability for autonomous mobile robots navigating through uncertain environments. This paper proposes a re-planning strategy using a multilayer planning and control framework for cases where the robot's environment is partially known. A medial axis graph-based planner defines a global path plan based on known obstacles, where each edge in the graph corresponds to a unique corridor. A mixed-integer model predictive control (MPC) method detects if a terminal constraint derived from the global plan is infeasible, subject to a non-convex description of the local environment. Infeasibility detection is used to trigger efficient global re-planning via medial axis graph edge deletion. The proposed re-planning strategy is demonstrated experimentally.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13372v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua A. Robbins, Stephen J. Harnett, Andrew F. Thompson, Sean Brennan, Herschel C. Pangborn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A User-centric Game for Balancing V2G Benefits with Battery Degradation of Electric Vehicles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11027v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a novel user-centric vehicle-to-grid (V2G) framework that enables electric vehicle (EV) users to balance the trade-off between financial benefits from V2G and battery health degradation based on individual preference signals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11027v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arghya Mallick, Georgios Pantazis, Peyman Mohajerin Esfahani, Sergio Grammatico</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi Steady-State Frequency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21461v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Accurate frequency estimation is critical for the control, monitoring and protection of electrical power systems, in particular, of systems with a high penetration of power electronics. This paper introduces the novel concept of Quasi Steady-State (QSS) frequency as a quantity that fills the gap between stationary and instantaneous frequency. QSS frequency coincides with the fundamental frequency of an AC voltage in any stationary conditions, including unbalanced and non-sinusoidal, and is able to capture the time-varying fundamental frequency in transient conditions. The paper also proposes a metric borrowed from fluid dynamics, namely, the time derivative of the circulation, to define the scope of validity of the QSS frequency. Analytical examples as well as a case study based on a fully-fledged EMT model of the IEEE 39-bus system serve to illustrate, respectively, the properties of the QSS frequency and its behavior in transient conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21461v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joan Gutierrez-Florensa, Alvaro Ortega, Lukas Sigrist, Federico Milano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Sustainability of the Leo Orbit Capacity via Risk-Driven Active Debris Removal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16101v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The growing number of space debris in Low Earth Orbit (LEO) jeopardizes long-term orbital sustainability, requiring efficient risk assessment for active debris removal (ADR) missions. This study presents the development and validation of Filtered Modified MITRI (FMM), an enhanced risk index designed to improve the prioritization of high-criticality debris. Leveraging the MOCAT-MC simulation framework, we conducted a comprehensive performance evaluation and sensitivity analysis to probe the robustness of the FMM formulation. The results demonstrate that while the FMM provides superior identification of high-risk targets for annual removal campaigns, a nuanced performance trade-off exists between risk models depending on the operational removal cadence. The analysis also confirms that physically grounded mass terms are indispensable for practical risk assessment. By providing a validated open source tool and critical insights into the dynamics of risk, this research enhances our ability to select optimal ADR targets and ensure the long-term viability of LEO operations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16101v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yacob Medhin, Simone Servadio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Nonlinear Control Systems via Koopman Control Family: Universal Forms and Subspace Invariance Proximity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.15368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.15368v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper introduces the Koopman Control Family (KCF), a mathematical framework for modeling general (not necessarily control-affine) discrete-time nonlinear control systems with the aim of providing a solid theoretical foundation for the use of Koopman-based methods in systems with inputs. We demonstrate that the concept of KCF captures the behavior of nonlinear control systems on a (potentially infinite-dimensional) function space. By employing a generalized notion of subspace invariance under the KCF, we establish a universal form for finite-dimensional models, which encompasses the commonly used linear, bilinear, and linear switched models as specific instances. In cases where the subspace is not invariant under the KCF, we propose a method for approximating models in general form and characterize the model's accuracy using the concept of invariance proximity. We end by discussing how the proposed framework naturally lends itself to data-driven modeling of control systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.15368v4</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masih Haseli, Jorge Cort\'es</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TrafficMCTS: A Closed-Loop Traffic Flow Generation Framework with Group-Based Monte Carlo Tree Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.12797</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.12797v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Traffic flow simulation within the domain of intelligent transportation systems is garnering significant attention, and generating realistic, diverse, and human-like traffic patterns presents critical challenges that must be addressed. Current approaches often hinge on predefined driver models, objective optimization, or reliance on pre-recorded driving datasets, imposing limitations on their scalability, versatility, and adaptability. In this paper, we introduce TrafficMCTS, an innovative framework that harnesses the synergy of group-based Monte Carlo tree search (MCTS) and Social Value Orientation (SVO) to engender a multifaceted traffic flow with varying driving styles and cooperative tendencies. Anchored by a closed-loop architecture, our framework enables vehicles to dynamically adapt to their environment in real time, and ensure feasible collision-free trajectories. Through comprehensive comparisons with state-of-the-art methods, we illuminate the advantages of our approach in terms of computational efficiency, planning success rate, intention completion time, and diversity metrics. Besides, we simulate multiple scenarios to illustrate the effectiveness of the proposed framework and highlight its ability to induce diverse social behaviors within the traffic flow. Finally, we validate the scalability of TrafficMCTS by demonstrating its capability to efficiently simulate diverse traffic scenarios involving numerous interacting vehicles within a complex road network, capturing the intricate dynamics of human-like driving behaviors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.12797v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ze Fu, Licheng Wen, Pinlong Cai, Daocheng Fu, Song Mao, Botian Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational Bayesian Inference for Multiple Extended Targets or Unresolved Group Targets Tracking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15226v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we propose a method for tracking multiple extended targets or unresolvable group targets in a clutter environment. Firstly, based on the Random Matrix Model (RMM), the joint state of the target is modeled as the Gamma Gaussian Inverse Wishart (GGIW) distribution. Considering the uncertainty of measurement origin caused by the clutters, we adopt the idea of probabilistic data association and describe the joint association event as an unknown parameter in the joint prior distribution. Then the Variational Bayesian Inference (VBI) is employed to approximately solve the non-analytical posterior distribution. Furthermore, to ensure the practicability of the proposed method, we further provide two potential lightweight schemes to reduce its computational complexity. One of them is based on clustering, which effectively prunes the joint association events. The other is a simplification of the variational posterior through marginal association probabilities. Finally, the effectiveness of the proposed method is demonstrated by simulation and real data experiments, and we show that the proposed method outperforms current state-of-the-art methods in terms of accuracy and adaptability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15226v4</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuanhao Cheng, Yunhe Cao, Tat-Soon Yeo, Yulin Zhang, Fu Jie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HLSTester: Efficient Testing of Behavioral Discrepancies with LLMs for High-Level Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14641v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In high-level synthesis (HLS), C/C++ programs with synthesis directives are used to generate circuits for FPGA implementations. However, hardware-specific and platform-dependent characteristics in these implementations can introduce behavioral discrepancies between the original C/C++ programs and the circuits after high-level synthesis. Existing methods for testing behavioral discrepancies in HLS are still immature, and the testing workflow requires significant human efforts. To address this challenge, we propose HLSTester, a large language model (LLM) aided testing framework that efficiently detects behavioral discrepancies in HLS. To mitigate hallucinations in LLMs and enhance prompt quality, the testbenches for original C/C++ programs are leveraged to guide LLMs in generating HLS-compatible testbenches, effectively eliminating certain traditional C/C++ constructs that are incompatible with HLS tools. Key variables are pinpointed through a backward slicing technique in both C/C++ and HLS programs to monitor their runtime spectra, enabling an in-depth analysis of the discrepancy symptoms. To reduce test time, a testing input generation mechanism is introduced to integrate dynamic mutation with insights from an LLM-based progressive reasoning chain. In addition, repetitive hardware testing is skipped by a redundancy-aware filtering technique for the generated test inputs. Experimental results demonstrate that the proposed LLM-aided testing framework significantly accelerates the testing workflow while achieving higher testbench simulation pass rates compared with the traditional method and the direct use of LLMs on the same HLS programs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14641v3</guid>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kangwei Xu, Bing Li, Grace Li Zhang, Ulf Schlichtmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collision-free Control Barrier Functions for General Ellipsoids via Separating Hyperplane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20847</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20847v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel collision avoidance method for general ellipsoids based on control barrier functions (CBFs) and separating hyperplanes. First, collision-free conditions for general ellipsoids are analytically derived using the concept of dual cones. These conditions are incorporated into the CBF framework by extending the system dynamics of controlled objects with separating hyperplanes, enabling efficient and reliable collision avoidance. The validity of the proposed collision-free CBFs is rigorously proven, ensuring their effectiveness in enforcing safety constraints. The proposed method requires only single-level optimization, significantly reducing computational time compared to state-of-the-art methods. Numerical simulations and real-world experiments demonstrate the effectiveness and practicality of the proposed algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20847v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zeming Wu, Lu Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
