<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SY updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SY</link>
    <description>cs.SY updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SY" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 04:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Guidance and Control of Unmanned Surface Vehicles via HEOL</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00168v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work presents a new approach to the guidance and control of marine craft via HEOL, i.e., a new way of combining flatness-based and model-free controllers. Its goal is to develop a general regulator for Unmanned Surface Vehicles (USV). To do so, the well-known USV maneuvering model is simplified into a nominal Hovercraft model which is flat. A flatness-based controller is derived for the simplified USV model and the loop is closed via an intelligent proportional-derivative (iPD) regulator. We thus associate the well-documented natural robustness of flatness-based control and adaptivity of iPDs. The controller is applied in simulation to two surface vessels, one meeting the simplifying hypotheses, the other one being a generic USV of the literature. It is shown to stabilize both systems even in the presence of unmodeled environmental disturbances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00168v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lo\"ick Degorre, Emmanuel Delaleau, C\'edric Join, Michel Fliess</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Quadratic Costs in LQR: Bregman Divergence Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00317v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the past couple of decades, the use of ``non-quadratic" convex cost functions has revolutionized signal processing, machine learning, and statistics, allowing one to customize solutions to have desired structures and properties. However, the situation is not the same in control where the use of quadratic costs still dominates, ostensibly because determining the ``value function", i.e., the optimal expected cost-to-go, which is critical to the construction of the optimal controller, becomes computationally intractable as soon as one considers general convex costs. As a result, practitioners often resort to heuristics and approximations, such as model predictive control that only looks a few steps into the future. In the quadratic case, the value function is easily determined by solving Riccati equations. In this work, we consider a special class of convex cost functions constructed from Bregman divergence and show how, with appropriate choices, they can be used to fully extend the framework developed for the quadratic case. The resulting optimal controllers are infinite horizon, come with stability guarantees, and have state-feedback, or estimated state-feedback, laws. They exhibit a much wider range of behavior than their quadratic counterparts since the feedback laws are nonlinear. The approach can be applied to several cases of interest, including safety control, sparse control, and bang-bang control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00317v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Babak Hassibi, Joudi Hajar, Reza Ghane</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Quadratic Costs: A Bregman Divergence Approach to H$_\infty$ Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00319v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel extension of the H$_\infty$ control framework that generalizes the traditional quadratic cost formulation to accommodate strictly convex, nonquadratic functions for the state, control input, and disturbance. This new formulation not only captures additional noise characteristics but also supports a range of performance objectives-including sparse control, safety constraints, and other tailored behaviors-beyond what is possible with quadratic costs. We derive a closed-form solution of a central controller that minimizes the worst-case performance ratio under the proposed cost structure. Furthermore, we develop Riccati-like equations that impose necessary and sufficient conditions on the nonquadratic cost functions, thereby ensuring the existence of a robust solution. Finally, we rigorously establish Lyapunov stability for the closed-loop system. The proposed framework bridges robust control theory with modern approaches in machine learning and signal processing, offering enhanced flexibility and improved performance in complex control scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00319v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joudi Hajar, Reza Ghane, Babak Hassibi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recursive Algorithms for Sparse Parameter Identification of Multivariate Stochastic Systems with Non-stationary Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00323</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00323v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The classical sparse parameter identification methods are usually based on the iterative basis selection such as greedy algorithms, or the numerical optimization of regularized cost functions such as LASSO and Bayesian posterior probability distribution, etc., which, however, are not suitable for online sparsity inference when data arrive sequentially. This paper presents recursive algorithms for sparse parameter identification of multivariate stochastic systems with non-stationary observations. First, a new bivariate criterion function is presented by introducing an auxiliary variable matrix into a weighted $L_1$ regularization criterion. The new criterion function is subsequently decomposed into two solvable subproblems via alternating optimization of the two variable matrices, for which the optimizers can be explicitly formulated into recursive equations. Second, under the non-stationary and non-persistent excitation conditions on the systems, theoretical properties of the recursive algorithms are established. That is, the estimates are proved to be with (i) set convergence, i.e., the accurate estimation of the sparse index set of the unknown parameter matrix, and (ii) parameter convergence, i.e., the consistent estimation for values of the non-zero elements of the unknown parameter matrix. Finally, numerical examples are given to support the theoretical analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00323v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanxin Fu, Wenxiao Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stabilization by Controllers Having Integer Coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00481</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00481v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The system property of ``having integer coefficients,'' that is, a transfer function has an integer monic polynomial as its denominator, is significant in the field of encrypted control as it is required for a dynamic controller to be realized over encrypted data. This paper shows that there always exists a controller with integer coefficients stabilizing a given discrete-time linear time-invariant plant. A constructive algorithm to obtain such a controller is provided, along with numerical examples. Furthermore, the proposed method is applied to converting a pre-designed controller to have integer coefficients, while the original performance is preserved in the sense that the transfer function of the closed-loop system remains unchanged.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00481v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joowon Lee, Donggil Lee, Junsoo Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear Phase Balancing Scheme using Voltage Unbalance Sensitivities in Multi-phase Power Distribution Grids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00519v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Power distribution networks, especially in North America, are often unbalanced due to the mix of single-, two- and three-phase networks as well as due to the high penetration of single-phase devices at the distribution level such as electric vehicle (EV) chargers and single-phase solar plants. However, the network operator must adhere to the voltage unbalance levels within the limits specified by IEEE, IEC, and NEMA standards for the safety of the equipment as well as the efficiency of the network operation. Existing works have proposed active and reactive power control in the network to minimize imbalances. However, these optimization problems are highly nonlinear and nonconvex due to the inherent non-linearity of unbalanced metrics and power-flow equations. In this work, we propose a linearization approach of unbalance metrics such as voltage unbalance factors (VUF), phase voltage unbalance rate (PVUR), and line voltage unbalance rate (LVUR) using the first order Taylor's approximation. This linearization is then applied to the phase balancing control scheme; it is formulated as a feedback approach where the linearization is updated successively after the active/reactive control setpoint has been actuated and shows improvement in voltage imbalances. We demonstrate the application of the proposed scheme on a standard IEEE benchmark test case, demonstrating its effectiveness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00519v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rahul K. Gupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dimension-reduced Optimization of Multi-zone Thermostatically Controlled Loads</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00585</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00585v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study proposes a computationally efficient method for optimizing multi-zone thermostatically controlled loads (TCLs) by leveraging dimensionality reduction through an auto-encoder. We develop a multi-task learning framework to jointly represent latent variables and formulate a state-space model based on observed TCL operation data. This significantly reduces the dimensionality of TCL variables and states while preserving critical nonlinear interdependencies in TCL control. To address various application scenarios, we introduce optimization algorithms based on system identification (OptIden) and system simulation (OptSim) tailored to the latent variable representation. These approaches employ automatic differentiation and zeroth-order techniques, respectively, for efficient implementation. We evaluate the proposed method using a 90-zone apartment prototype, comparing its performance to traditional high-dimensional optimization. Results demonstrate that our approach effectively reduces control costs while achieving significantly higher computational efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00585v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xueyuan Cui, Yi Wang, Bolun Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear Parameter Varying Attitude Control For CubeSats Using Electrospray Thrusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00677v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper proposes the design of a single linear parameter-varying (LPV) controller for the attitude control of CubeSats using electro spray thrusters. CubeSat attitude control based on electro spray thrusters faces two main challenges. Firstly, the thruster can only generate a small control torque leading to easily saturating the actuation system. Secondly, CubeSats need to operate multiple different maneuvers from large to small slews to pointing tasks. LPV control is ideally suitable to address these challenges. The proposed design follows a mixed-sensitivity control scheme. The parameter-varying weights depend on the attitude error and are derived from the performance and robustness requirements of individual typical CubeSat maneuvers. The controller is synthesized by minimizing the induced L2-norm of the closed-loop interconnections between the controller and weighted plant. The performance and robustness of the controller is demonstrated on a simulation of the MIT Space Propulsion Lab's Magnetic Levitation CubeSat Testbed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00677v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felix Biert\"umpfel, Emily Burgin, Hanna-Lee Harjono, Paulo Lozano, Harald Pfifer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing gaussian mixture of motion modes for skid-steer state estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00200v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Skid-steered wheel mobile robots (SSWMRs) are characterized by the unique domination of the tire-terrain skidding for the robot to move. The lack of reliable friction models cascade into unreliable motion models, especially the reduced ordered variants used for state estimation and robot control. Ensemble modeling is an emerging research direction where the overall motion model is broken down into a family of local models to distribute the performance and resource requirement and provide a fast real-time prediction. To this end, a gaussian mixture model based modeling identification of model clusters is adopted and implemented within an interactive multiple model (IMM) based state estimation. The framework is adopted and implemented for angular velocity as the estimated state for a mid scaled skid-steered wheel mobile robot platform.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00200v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ameya Salvi, Mark Brudnak, Jonathon M. Smereka, Matthias Schmid, Venkat Krovi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative Machine Learning in Adaptive Control of Dynamic Manufacturing Processes: A Review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00210v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Dynamic manufacturing processes exhibit complex characteristics defined by time-varying parameters, nonlinear behaviors, and uncertainties. These characteristics require sophisticated in-situ monitoring techniques utilizing multimodal sensor data and adaptive control systems that can respond to real-time feedback while maintaining product quality. Recently, generative machine learning (ML) has emerged as a powerful tool for modeling complex distributions and generating synthetic data while handling these manufacturing uncertainties. However, adopting these generative technologies in dynamic manufacturing systems lacks a functional control-oriented perspective to translate their probabilistic understanding into actionable process controls while respecting constraints. This review presents a functional classification of Prediction-Based, Direct Policy, Quality Inference, and Knowledge-Integrated approaches, offering a perspective for understanding existing ML-enhanced control systems and incorporating generative ML. The analysis of generative ML architectures within this framework demonstrates control-relevant properties and potential to extend current ML-enhanced approaches where conventional methods prove insufficient. We show generative ML's potential for manufacturing control through decision-making applications, process guidance, simulation, and digital twins, while identifying critical research gaps: separation between generation and control functions, insufficient physical understanding of manufacturing phenomena, and challenges adapting models from other domains. To address these challenges, we propose future research directions aimed at developing integrated frameworks that combine generative ML and control technologies to address the dynamic complexities of modern manufacturing systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00210v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suk Ki Lee, Hyunwoong Ko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pinching-Antenna Systems (PASS): Power Radiation Model and Optimal Beamforming Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00218</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00218v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Pinching-antenna systems (PASS) improve wireless links by configuring the locations of activated pinching antennas along dielectric waveguides, namely pinching beamforming. In this paper, a novel adjustable power radiation model is proposed for PASS, where power radiation ratios of pinching antennas can be flexibly controlled by tuning the spacing between pinching antennas and waveguides. A closed-form pinching antenna spacing arrangement strategy is derived to achieve the commonly assumed equal-power radiation. Based on this, a practical PASS framework relying on discrete activation is considered, where pinching antennas can only be activated among a set of predefined locations. A transmit power minimization problem is formulated, which jointly optimizes the transmit beamforming, pinching beamforming, and the numbers of activated pinching antennas, subject to each user's minimum rate requirement. (1) To solve the resulting highly coupled mixed-integer nonlinear programming (MINLP) problem, branch-and-bound (BnB)-based algorithms are proposed for both single-user and multi-user scenarios, which is guaranteed to converge to globally optimal solutions. (2) A low-complexity many-to-many matching algorithm is further developed. Combined with the Karush-Kuhn-Tucker (KKT) theory, locally optimal and pairwise-stable solutions are obtained within polynomial-time complexity. Simulation results demonstrate that: (i) PASS significantly outperforms conventional multi-antenna architectures, particularly when the number of users and the spatial range increase; and (ii) The proposed matching-based algorithm achieves near-optimal performance, resulting in only a slight performance loss while significantly reducing computational overheads. Code is available at https://github.com/xiaoxiaxusummer/PASS_Discrete</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00218v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoxia Xu, Xidong Mu, Zhaolin Wang, Yuanwei Liu, Arumugam Nallanathan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Future-Oriented Navigation: Dynamic Obstacle Avoidance with One-Shot Energy-Based Multimodal Motion Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00237v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper proposes an integrated approach for the safe and efficient control of mobile robots in dynamic and uncertain environments. The approach consists of two key steps: one-shot multimodal motion prediction to anticipate motions of dynamic obstacles and model predictive control to incorporate these predictions into the motion planning process. Motion prediction is driven by an energy-based neural network that generates high-resolution, multi-step predictions in a single operation. The prediction outcomes are further utilized to create geometric shapes formulated as mathematical constraints. Instead of treating each dynamic obstacle individually, predicted obstacles are grouped by proximity in an unsupervised way to improve performance and efficiency. The overall collision-free navigation is handled by model predictive control with a specific design for proactive dynamic obstacle avoidance. The proposed approach allows mobile robots to navigate effectively in dynamic environments. Its performance is accessed across various scenarios that represent typical warehouse settings. The results demonstrate that the proposed approach outperforms other existing dynamic obstacle avoidance methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00237v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ze Zhang, Georg Hess, Junjie Hu, Emmanuel Dean, Lennart Svensson, Knut {\AA}kesson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological State Space Inference for Dynamical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00276</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00276v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a computational pipe aiming at recovery of the topology of the underlying phase space from observation of an output function along a sample of trajectories of a dynamical system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00276v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mishal Assif P K, Yuliy Baryshnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-segment Soft Robot Control via Deep Koopman-based Model Predictive Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00354v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Soft robots, compared to regular rigid robots, as their multiple segments with soft materials bring flexibility and compliance, have the advantages of safe interaction and dexterous operation in the environment. However, due to its characteristics of high dimensional, nonlinearity, time-varying nature, and infinite degree of freedom, it has been challenges in achieving precise and dynamic control such as trajectory tracking and position reaching. To address these challenges, we propose a framework of Deep Koopman-based Model Predictive Control (DK-MPC) for handling multi-segment soft robots. We first employ a deep learning approach with sampling data to approximate the Koopman operator, which therefore linearizes the high-dimensional nonlinear dynamics of the soft robots into a finite-dimensional linear representation. Secondly, this linearized model is utilized within a model predictive control framework to compute optimal control inputs that minimize the tracking error between the desired and actual state trajectories. The real-world experiments on the soft robot "Chordata" demonstrate that DK-MPC could achieve high-precision control, showing the potential of DK-MPC for future applications to soft robots.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00354v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Lv, Lei Liu, Lei Bao, Fuchun Sun, Jiahong Dong, Jianwei Zhang, Xuemei Shan, Kai Sun, Hao Huang, Yu Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decentralised, Self-Organising Drone Swarms using Coupled Oscillators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00442v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The problem of robotic synchronisation and coordination is a long-standing one. Combining autonomous, computerised systems with unpredictable real-world conditions can have consequences ranging from poor performance to collisions and damage. This paper proposes using coupled oscillators to create a drone swarm that is decentralised and self organising. This allows for greater flexibility and adaptiveness than a hard-coded swarm, with more resilience and scalability than a centralised system. Our method allows for a variable number of drones to spontaneously form a swarm and react to changing swarm conditions. Additionally, this method includes provisions to prevent communication interference between drones, and signal processing techniques to ensure a smooth and cohesive swarm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00442v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Quinn, Cormac Molloy, Harun \v{S}iljak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergence of Roles in Robotic Teams with Model Sharing and Limited Communication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00540</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00540v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a reinforcement learning strategy for use in multi-agent foraging systems in which the learning is centralised to a single agent and its model is periodically disseminated among the population of non-learning agents. In a domain where multi-agent reinforcement learning (MARL) is the common approach, this approach aims to significantly reduce the computational and energy demands compared to approaches such as MARL and centralised learning models. By developing high performing foraging agents, these approaches can be translated into real-world applications such as logistics, environmental monitoring, and autonomous exploration. A reward function was incorporated into this approach that promotes role development among agents, without explicit directives. This led to the differentiation of behaviours among the agents. The implicit encouragement of role differentiation allows for dynamic actions in which agents can alter roles dependent on their interactions with the environment without the need for explicit communication between agents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00540v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian O'Flynn, Harun \v{S}iljak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Network Verification for Gliding Drone Control: A Case Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00622v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: As machine learning is increasingly deployed in autonomous systems, verification of neural network controllers is becoming an active research domain. Existing tools and annual verification competitions suggest that soon this technology will become effective for real-world applications. Our application comes from the emerging field of microflyers that are passively transported by the wind, which may have various uses in weather or pollution monitoring. Specifically, we investigate centimetre-scale bio-inspired gliding drones that resemble Alsomitra macrocarpa diaspores. In this paper, we propose a new case study on verifying Alsomitra-inspired drones with neural network controllers, with the aim of adhering closely to a target trajectory. We show that our system differs substantially from existing VNN and ARCH competition benchmarks, and show that a combination of tools holds promise for verifying such systems in the future, if certain shortcomings can be overcome. We propose a novel method for robust training of regression networks, and investigate formalisations of this case study in Vehicle and CORA. Our verification results suggest that the investigated training methods do improve performance and robustness of neural network controllers in this application, but are limited in scope and usefulness. This is due to systematic limitations of both Vehicle and CORA, and the complexity of our system reducing the scale of reachability, which we investigate in detail. If these limitations can be overcome, it will enable engineers to develop safe and robust technologies that improve people's lives and reduce our impact on the environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00622v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Colin Kessler, Ekaterina Komendantskaya, Marco Casadio, Ignazio Maria Viola, Thomas Flinkow, Albaraa Ammar Othman, Alistair Malhotra, Robbie McPherson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Constraint Safe Reinforcement Learning via Closed-form Solution for Log-Sum-Exp Approximation of Control Barrier Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00671v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The safety of training task policies and their subsequent application using reinforcement learning (RL) methods has become a focal point in the field of safe RL. A central challenge in this area remains the establishment of theoretical guarantees for safety during both the learning and deployment processes. Given the successful implementation of Control Barrier Function (CBF)-based safety strategies in a range of control-affine robotic systems, CBF-based safe RL demonstrates significant promise for practical applications in real-world scenarios. However, integrating these two approaches presents several challenges. First, embedding safety optimization within the RL training pipeline requires that the optimization outputs be differentiable with respect to the input parameters, a condition commonly referred to as differentiable optimization, which is non-trivial to solve. Second, the differentiable optimization framework confronts significant efficiency issues, especially when dealing with multi-constraint problems. To address these challenges, this paper presents a CBF-based safe RL architecture that effectively mitigates the issues outlined above. The proposed approach constructs a continuous AND logic approximation for the multiple constraints using a single composite CBF. By leveraging this approximation, a close-form solution of the quadratic programming is derived for the policy network in RL, thereby circumventing the need for differentiable optimization within the end-to-end safe RL pipeline. This strategy significantly reduces computational complexity because of the closed-form solution while maintaining safety guarantees. Simulation results demonstrate that, in comparison to existing approaches relying on differentiable optimization, the proposed method significantly reduces training computational costs while ensuring provable safety throughout the training process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00671v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenggang Wang, Xinyi Wang, Yutong Dong, Lei Song, Xinping Guan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physical Limits and Optimal Synthesis of Beyond Diagonal Anomalous Scatterers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00691v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Realizing metasurfaces for anomalous scattering is fundamental to designing reflector arrays, reconfigurable intelligent surfaces, and metasurface antennas. However, the basic cost of steering scattering into non-specular directions is not fully understood. This paper derives tight physical bounds on anomalous scattering using antenna array systems equipped with non-local matching networks. The matching networks are explicitly synthesized based on the solutions of the optimization problems that define these bounds. Furthermore, we analyze fundamental limits for metasurface antennas implemented with metallic and dielectric materials exhibiting minimal loss within a finite design region. The results reveal a typical 6dB reduction in bistatic radar cross section (RCS) in anomalous directions compared to the forward direction. Numerical examples complement the theory and illustrate the inherent cost of achieving anomalous scattering relative to forward or specular scattering for canonical configurations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00691v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mats Gustafsson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Steady-State Cascade Operators and their Role in Linear Control, Estimation, and Model Reduction Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07568v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Certain linear matrix operators arise naturally in systems analysis and design problems involving cascade interconnections of linear time-invariant systems, including problems of stabilization, estimation, and model order reduction. We conduct here a comprehensive study of these operators and their relevant system-theoretic properties. The general theory is leveraged to delineate both known and new design methodologies for control and observation of cascades, and to characterize structural properties of reduced models. Several entirely new designs arise from this systematic categorization, including new recursive and low-gain design frameworks for observation of cascaded systems. The benefits of the results beyond the linear time-invariant setting are demonstrated through preliminary extensions for nonlinear systems, with an outlook towards the development of a similarly comprehensive nonlinear theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07568v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John W. Simpson-Porco, Daniele Astolfi, Giordano Scarciotti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatiotemporal Tubes for Temporal Reach-Avoid-Stay Tasks in Unknown Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13834v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The paper considers the controller synthesis problem for general MIMO systems with unknown dynamics, aiming to fulfill the temporal reach-avoid-stay task, where the unsafe regions are time-dependent, and the target must be reached within a specified time frame. The primary aim of the paper is to construct the spatiotemporal tube (STT) using a sampling-based approach and thereby devise a closed-form approximation-free control strategy to ensure that system trajectory reaches the target set while avoiding time-dependent unsafe sets. The proposed scheme utilizes a novel method involving STTs to provide controllers that guarantee both system safety and reachability. In our sampling-based framework, we translate the requirements of STTs into a Robust optimization program (ROP). To address the infeasibility of ROP caused by infinite constraints, we utilize the sampling-based Scenario optimization program (SOP). Subsequently, we solve the SOP to generate the tube and closed-form controller for an unknown system, ensuring the temporal reach-avoid-stay specification. Finally, the effectiveness of the proposed approach is demonstrated through three case studies: an omnidirectional robot, a SCARA manipulator, and a magnetic levitation system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13834v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ratnangshu Das, Ahan Basu, Pushpak Jagtap</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cooperative Deterministic Learning-Based Formation Control for a Group of Nonlinear Mechanical Systems Under Complete Uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13688</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13688v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work we address the formation control problem for a group of nonlinear mechanical systems with complete uncertain dynamics under a virtual leader-following framework. We propose a novel cooperative deterministic learning-based adaptive formation control algorithm. This algorithm is designed by utilizing artificial neural networks to simultaneously achieve formation tracking control and locally-accurate identification/learning of the nonlinear uncertain dynamics of the considered group of mechanical systems. To demonstrate the practicality and verify the effectiveness of the proposed results, numerical simulations have been conducted.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13688v5</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maryam Norouzi, Mingxi Zhou, Chengzhi Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Climate Science and Control Engineering: Insights, Parallels, and Connections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21153</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21153v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Climate science is the multidisciplinary field that studies the Earth's climate and its evolution. At the very core of climate science are indispensable climate models that predict future climate scenarios, inform policy decisions, and dictate how a country's economy should change in light of the changing climate. Climate models capture a wide range of interacting dynamic processes via extremely complex ordinary and partial differential equations. To model these large-scale complex processes, climate science leverages supercomputers, advanced simulations, and statistical methods to predict future climate. An area of engineering that is rarely studied in climate science is control engineering. Given that climate systems are inherently dynamic, it is intuitive to analyze them within the framework of dynamic system science. This perspective has been underexplored in the literature. In this manuscript, we provide a tutorial that: (i) introduces the control engineering community to climate dynamics and modeling, including spatiotemporal scales and challenges in climate modeling; (ii) offers a fresh perspective on climate models from a control systems viewpoint; and (iii) explores the relevance and applicability of various advanced graph and network control-based approaches in building a physics-informed framework for learning, control and estimation in climate systems. We also present simple and then more complex climate models, depicting fundamental ideas and processes that are instrumental in building climate change projections. This tutorial also builds parallels and observes connections between various contemporary problems at the forefront of climate science and their control theoretic counterparts. We specifically observe that an abundance of climate science problems can be linguistically reworded and mathematically framed as control theoretic ones.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21153v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Salma M. Elsherif, Ahmad F. Taha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On phase in scaled graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21448v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The scaled graph has been introduced recently as a nonlinear extension of the classical Nyquist plot for linear time-invariant systems. In this paper, we introduce a modified definition for the scaled graph, termed the signed scaled graph (SSG), in which the phase component is characterized by making use of the Hilbert transform. Whereas the original definition of the scaled graph uses unsigned phase angles, the new definition has signed phase angles which ensures the possibility to differentiate between phase-lead and phase-lag properties in a system. Making such distinction is important from both an analysis and a synthesis perspective, and helps in providing tighter stability estimates of feedback interconnections. We show how the proposed SSG leads to intuitive characterizations of positive real and negative imaginary nonlinear systems, and present various interconnection results. We showcase the effectiveness of our results through several motivating examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21448v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastiaan van den Eijnden, Chao Chen, Koen Scheres, Thomas Chaffey, Alexander Lanzon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Online Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.09619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.09619v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This text presents an introduction to an emerging paradigm in control of dynamical systems and differentiable reinforcement learning called online nonstochastic control. The new approach applies techniques from online convex optimization and convex relaxations to obtain new methods with provable guarantees for classical settings in optimal and robust control.
  The primary distinction between online nonstochastic control and other frameworks is the objective. In optimal control, robust control, and other control methodologies that assume stochastic noise, the goal is to perform comparably to an offline optimal strategy. In online nonstochastic control, both the cost functions as well as the perturbations from the assumed dynamical model are chosen by an adversary. Thus the optimal policy is not defined a priori. Rather, the target is to attain low regret against the best policy in hindsight from a benchmark class of policies.
  This objective suggests the use of the decision making framework of online convex optimization as an algorithmic methodology. The resulting methods are based on iterative mathematical optimization algorithms, and are accompanied by finite-time regret and computational complexity guarantees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.09619v5</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elad Hazan, Karan Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mitigating Covariate Shift in Imitation Learning for Autonomous Vehicles Using Latent Space Generative World Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16663</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.16663v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose the use of latent space generative world models to address the covariate shift problem in autonomous driving. A world model is a neural network capable of predicting an agent's next state given past states and actions. By leveraging a world model during training, the driving policy effectively mitigates covariate shift without requiring an excessive amount of training data. During end-to-end training, our policy learns how to recover from errors by aligning with states observed in human demonstrations, so that at runtime it can recover from perturbations outside the training distribution. Additionally, we introduce a novel transformer-based perception encoder that employs multi-view cross-attention and a learned scene query. We present qualitative and quantitative results, demonstrating significant improvements upon prior state of the art in closed-loop testing in the CARLA simulator, as well as showing the ability to handle perturbations in both CARLA and NVIDIA's DRIVE Sim.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.16663v4</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Popov, Alperen Degirmenci, David Wehr, Shashank Hegde, Ryan Oldja, Alexey Kamenev, Bertrand Douillard, David Nist\'er, Urs Muller, Ruchi Bhargava, Stan Birchfield, Nikolai Smolyanskiy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Objective Reinforcement Learning for Power Grid Topology Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00040</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00040v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Transmission grid congestion increases as the electrification of various sectors requires transmitting more power. Topology control, through substation reconfiguration, can reduce congestion but its potential remains under-exploited in operations. A challenge is modeling the topology control problem to align well with the objectives and constraints of operators. Addressing this challenge, this paper investigates the application of multi-objective reinforcement learning (MORL) to integrate multiple conflicting objectives for power grid topology control. We develop a MORL approach using deep optimistic linear support (DOL) and multi-objective proximal policy optimization (MOPPO) to generate a set of Pareto-optimal policies that balance objectives such as minimizing line loading, topological deviation, and switching frequency. Initial case studies show that the MORL approach can provide valuable insights into objective trade-offs and improve Pareto front approximation compared to a random search baseline. The generated multi-objective RL policies are 30% more successful in preventing grid failure under contingencies and 20% more effective when training budget is reduced - compared to the common single objective RL policy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00040v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Lautenbacher, Ali Rajaei, Davide Barbieri, Jan Viebahn, Jochen L. Cremer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative Predictive Control: Flow Matching Policies for Dynamic and Difficult-to-Demonstrate Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13406v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Generative control policies have recently unlocked major progress in robotics. These methods produce action sequences via diffusion or flow matching, with training data provided by demonstrations. But existing methods come with two key limitations: they require expert demonstrations, which can be difficult to obtain, and they are limited to relatively slow, quasi-static tasks. In this paper, we leverage a tight connection between sampling-based predictive control and generative modeling to address each of these issues. In particular, we introduce generative predictive control, a supervised learning framework for tasks with fast dynamics that are easy to simulate but difficult to demonstrate. We then show how trained flow-matching policies can be warm-started at inference time, maintaining temporal consistency and enabling high-frequency feedback. We believe that generative predictive control offers a complementary approach to existing behavior cloning methods, and hope that it paves the way toward generalist policies that extend beyond quasi-static demonstration-oriented tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13406v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vince Kurtz, Joel W. Burdick</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
