<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.SP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SP</link>
    <description>math.SP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2024 04:05:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On the local solvability and stability of the partial inverse problems for the non-self-adjoint Sturm-Liouville operators with a discontinuity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.13261v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we study the inverse spectral problems for the Sturm-Liouville operators on [0,1] with complex coefficients and a discontinuity at $x=a\in(0,1)$. Assume that the potential on (a,1) and some parameters in the discontinuity and boundary conditions are given. We recover the potential on (0,a) and the other parameters from the eigenvalues. This is the so-called partial inverse problem. The local solvability and stability of the partial inverse problems are obtained for $a\in(0,1)$, in which the error caused by the given partial potential is considered. As a by-product, we also obtain two new uniqueness theorems for the partial inverse problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.13261v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-Chuan Xu, Chuan-Fu Yang, Natalia Pavlovna Bondarenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the asymptotic number of low-lying states in the two-dimensional confined Stark effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14363v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the Stark operator restricted to a bounded domain $\Omega\subset\mathbb{R}^2$ with Dirichlet boundary conditions. In the semiclassical limit, a three-term asymptotic expansion for its individual eigenvalues has been established, with coefficients dependent on the curvature of $\Omega$. We analyse the accumulation of eigenvalues beneath the leading-order terms in these expansions, establishing Weyl-type asymptotics. Furthermore, we derive weak asymptotics for the density of the spectral projector onto these low-lying states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14363v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Larry Read</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holomorphic Witten instanton complexes on stratified pseudomanifolds with K\"ahler wedge metrics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13481</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.13481v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct Witten instanton complexes for K\"ahler Hamiltonian Morse functions on stratified pseudomanifolds with wedge K\"ahler metrics satisfying a local conformally totally geodesic condition. We use this to extend Witten's holomorphic Morse inequalities for the $L^2$ cohomology of Dolbeault complexes, deriving versions for Poincar\'e Hodge polynomials, the spin Dirac and signature complexes for which we prove rigidity results, in particular establishing the rigidity of $L^2$ de Rham cohomology for these circle actions. We generalize formulas studied by Witten and Gibbons-Hawking for the equivariant signature and extend formulas used to compute NUT charges of gravitational instantons. We discuss conjectural inequalities extending known Lefschetz-Riemann-Roch formulas for other cohomology theories including those of Baum-Fulton-Quart. As far as the author is aware this article contains the first extension of Witten's holomorphic Morse inequalities to singular spaces, and the first results on rigidity of $L^2$ de Rham and Dolbeault cohomology for the actions studied on stratified pseudomanifolds</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.13481v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gayana Jayasinghe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchical Representation Learning in Graph Neural Networks with Node Decimation Pooling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.11436</link>
      <description>arXiv:1910.11436v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In graph neural networks (GNNs), pooling operators compute local summaries of input graphs to capture their global properties, and they are fundamental for building deep GNNs that learn hierarchical representations. In this work, we propose the Node Decimation Pooling (NDP), a pooling operator for GNNs that generates coarser graphs while preserving the overall graph topology. During training, the GNN learns new node representations and fits them to a pyramid of coarsened graphs, which is computed offline in a pre-processing stage. NDP consists of three steps. First, a node decimation procedure selects the nodes belonging to one side of the partition identified by a spectral algorithm that approximates the \maxcut{} solution. Afterwards, the selected nodes are connected with Kron reduction to form the coarsened graph. Finally, since the resulting graph is very dense, we apply a sparsification procedure that prunes the adjacency matrix of the coarsened graph to reduce the computational cost in the GNN. Notably, we show that it is possible to remove many edges without significantly altering the graph structure. Experimental results show that NDP is more efficient compared to state-of-the-art graph pooling operators while reaching, at the same time, competitive performance on a significant variety of graph classification tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1910.11436v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TNNLS.2020.3044146</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Filippo Maria Bianchi, Daniele Grattarola, Lorenzo Livi, Cesare Alippi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved spectral projection estimates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.17266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.17266v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We obtain new improved spectral projection estimates on manifolds of non-positive curvature, including sharp ones for relatively large spectral windows for general tori. Our results are stronger than those in an earlier work of the first and third authors [6], and the arguments have been greatly simplified. We more directly make use of pointwise estimates that are implicit in the work of Berard [2] and avoid the use of weak-type spaces that were used in the previous works [6] and [22]. We also simplify and strengthen the bilinear arguments by exploiting the use of microlocal $L^2\to L^{q_c}$ Kakeya-Nikodym estimates and avoiding the of $L^2\to L^2$ ones as in earlier results. This allows us to prove new results for manifolds of negative curvature and some new sharp estimates for tori. We also have new and improved techniques in two dimensions for general manifolds of non-positive curvature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.17266v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew D. Blair, Xiaoqi Huang, Christopher D. Sogge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solutions to the discrete Pompeiu problem and to the finite Steinhaus tiling problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01279v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $K$ be a nonempty finite subset of the Euclidean space $\mathbb{R}^k$ $(k\ge 2)$. We prove that if a function $f\colon \mathbb{R}^k\to \mathbb{C}$ is such that the sum of $f$ on every congruent copy of $K$ is zero, then $f$ vanishes everywhere. In fact, a stronger, weighted version is proved. As a corollary we find that every finite subset $K$ of $\mathbb{R}^k$ having at least two elements is a Jackson set; that is, no subset of $\mathbb{R}^k$ intersects every congruent copy of $K$ in exactly one point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01279v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gergely Kiss, Mikl\'os Laczkovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
