<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.SP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SP</link>
    <description>math.SP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 02:50:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A hot spots theorem for the mixed eigenvalue problem with small Dirichet region</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.03908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.03908v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove that on convex domains, first mixed Laplace eigenfunctions have no interior critical points if the Dirichlet region is connected and sufficiently small. We use this result to construct a new family of polygonal domains for which Rauch's hot spots conjecture holds and to prove a new general theorem regarding the hot spots conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.03908v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lawford Hatcher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of moving N\'eel walls in ferromagnetic thin films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04023</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04023v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper studies moving 180-degree N\'eel walls in ferromagnetic thin films under the reduced model for the in-plane magnetization proposed by Capella, Melcher and Otto [5], in the case when a sufficiently weak external magnetic field is applied. It is shown that the linearization around the moving N\'eel wall's phase determines a spectral problem that is a relatively bounded perturbation of the linearization around the static N\'eel wall, which is the solution when the external magnetic field is set to zero and which is spectrally stable. Uniform resolvent-type estimates for the linearized operator around the static wall are established in order to prove the spectral stability of the moving wall upon application of perturbation theory for linear operators. The spectral analysis is the basis to prove, in turn, both the decaying properties of the generated semigroup and the nonlinear stability of the moving N\'eel wall under small perturbations, in the case of a sufficiently weak external magnetic field. The stability of the static N\'eel wall, which was established in a companion paper [4], plays a key role to obtain the main result.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04023v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Capella, Christof Melcher, Lauro Morales, Ram\'on G. Plaza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A geometric approach to approximating the limit set of eigenvalues for banded Toeplitz matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.00829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.00829v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This article is about finding the limit set for banded Toeplitz matrices. Our main result is a new approach to approximate the limit set $\Lambda(b)$ where $b$ is the symbol of the banded Toeplitz matrix. The new approach is geometrical and based on the formula $\Lambda(b) = \cap_{\rho \in (0, \infty)} \text{sp } T(b_\rho)$, where $\rho$ is a scaling factor, i.e. $b_\rho(t) := b(\rho t)$, and $\text{sp }(\cdot)$ denotes the spectrum. We show that the full intersection can be approximated by the intersection for a finite number of $\rho$'s, and that the intersection of polygon approximations for $\text{sp } T(b_\rho)$ yields an approximating polygon for $\Lambda(b)$ that converges to $\Lambda(b)$ in the Hausdorff metric. Further, we show that one can slightly expand the polygon approximations for $\text{sp } T(b_\rho)$ to ensure that they contain $\text{sp } T(b_\rho)$. Then, taking the intersection yields an approximating superset of $\Lambda(b)$ which converges to $\Lambda(b)$ in the Hausdorff metric, and is guaranteed to contain $\Lambda(b)$. Combining the established algebraic (root-finding) method with our approximating superset, we are able to give an explicit bound on the Hausdorff distance to the true limit set. We implement the algorithm in Python and test it. It performs on par to and better in some cases than existing algorithms. We argue, but do not prove, that the average time complexity of the algorithm is $O(n^2 + mn\log m)$, where $n$ is the number of $\rho$'s and $m$ is the number of vertices for the polygons approximating $\text{sp } T(b_\rho)$. Further, we argue that the distance from $\Lambda(b)$ to both the approximating polygon and the approximating superset decreases as $O(1/\sqrt{k})$ for most of $\Lambda(b)$, where $k$ is the number of elementary operations required by the algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.00829v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1137/23M1587804</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SIAM J. Matrix Anal. Appl., 45(3) (2024) 1573-1598</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Teodor Bucht, Jacob S. Christiansen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
