<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.SP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SP</link>
    <description>math.SP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 02:04:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral asymptotics for Robin Laplacians on Lipschitz sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22238</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22238v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove two-term spectral asymptotics for the Riesz means of the eigenvalues of the Laplacian on a Lipschitz domain with Robin boundary conditions. The second term is the same as in the case of Neumann boundary conditions. This is valid for Riesz means of arbitrary positive order. For orders at least one and under additional assumptions on the function determining the boundary conditions we derive leading order asymptotics for the difference between Riesz means of Robin and Neumann eigenvalues.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22238v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rupert L. Frank, Simon Larson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp palindromic criterion for semi-uniform dynamical localization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21700v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a sharp palindromic argument for general 1D operators, that proves absence of semi-uniform localization in the regime of exponential symmetry-based resonances. This provides the first examples of operators with dynamical localization but no SULE/SUDL, as well as with nearly uniform distribution of centers of localization in absence of SULE. For the almost Mathieu operators, this also leads to a sharp arithmetic criterion for semi-uniformity of dynamical localization in the Diophantine case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21700v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Svetlana Jitomirskaya, Wencai Liu, Lufang Mi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimization of quantum graph eigenvalues with preferred orientation vertex conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21820v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We discuss Laplacian spectrum on a finite metric graph with vertex couplings violating the time-reversal invariance. For the class of star graphs we determine, under the condition of a fixed total edge length, the configurations for which the ground state eigenvalue is maximized. Furthermore, for general finite metric graphs we provide upper bounds for all eigenvalues.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21820v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pavel Exner, Jonathan Rohleder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp spectral gap for degenerated Witten Laplacian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21899v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the Witten Laplacian associated to a non-Morse potential. We prove Eyring-Kramers formulas for the bottom of the spectrum of this operator in the semiclassical regime and quantify the spectral gap between these eigenvalues and the rest of the spectrum. The main ingredient is the construction of sharp degenerated Gaussian quasimodes through an adaptation of the WKB method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21899v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lo\"is Delande</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp spectral gap of adaptive Langevin dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00552</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00552v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a degenerated Fokker-Planck type differential operator associated to an adaptive Langevin dynamic. We prove Eyring-Kramers formulas for the bottom of the spectrum of this operator in the low temperature regime. The main ingredients are resolvent estimates obtained via hypocoercive techniques and the construction of sharp Gaussian quasimodes through an adaptation of the WKB method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00552v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lo\"is Delande</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dirichlet metric measure spaces: spectrum, irreducibility, and small deviations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07425v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that for ultracontractive irreducible Dirichlet metric measure spaces, the Dirichlet spectrum is discrete for a restriction to any connected open set without any assumption on regularity of the boundary. The main applications include small deviations for the corresponding Hunt process and large time asymptotics for the generalized heat content. Our examples include Riemannian and sub-Riemannian manifolds, as well as non-smooth and fractal spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07425v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Carfagnini, Maria Gordina, Alexander Teplyaev</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
