<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.SP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SP</link>
    <description>math.SP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 04:00:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Index theory for non-compact quantum graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09749v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop an index theory for variational problems on noncompact quantum graphs. The main results are a spectral flow formula, relating the net change of eigenvalues to the Maslov index of boundary data, and a Morse index theorem, equating the negative directions of the Lagrangian action with the total multiplicity of conjugate instants along the edges.
  These results extend classical tools in global analysis and symplectic geometry to graph based models, with applications to nonlinear wave equations such as the nonlinear Schroedinger equation. The spectral flow formula is proved by constructing a Lagrangian intersection theory in the Gelfand-Robbin quotients of the second variation of the action. This approach also recovers, in a unified way, the known formulas for heteroclinic, halfclinic, homoclinic, and bounded orbits of (non)autonomous Lagrangian systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09749v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniele Garrisi, Alessandro Portaluri, Li Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Log-Hausdorff multifractality of the absolutely continuous spectral measure of the almost Mathieu operator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09945v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper focuses on the fractal characteristics of the absolutely continuous spectral measure of the subcritical almost Mathieu operator (AMO) and Diophantine frequency. In particular, we give a complete description of the (classical) multifractal spectrum and a finer description in the logarithmic gauge. The proof combines continued$-$fraction$/$metric Diophantine techniques and refined covering arguments. These results rigorously substantiate (and quantify in a refined gauge) the physicists' intuition that the absolutely continuous component of the spectrum is dominated by energies with trivial scaling index, while also exhibiting nontrivial exceptional sets which are negligible for classical Hausdorff measure but large at the logarithmic scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09945v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jie Cao, Xianzhe Li, Baowei Wang, Qi Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Duistermaat index and eigenvalue interlacing for self-adjoint extensions of a symmetric operator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.06701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.06701v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Eigenvalue interlacing is a useful tool in linear algebra and spectral analysis. In its simplest form, the interlacing inequality states that a rank-one positive perturbation shifts each eigenvalue up, but not further than the next unperturbed eigenvalue. For different types of perturbations, this idea is known as Weyl interlacing, Cauchy interlacing, Dirichlet--Neumann bracketing and so on.
  We prove a sharp version of the interlacing inequalities for ``finite-dimensional perturbations in boundary conditions'', expressed as bounds on the spectral shift between two self-adjoint extensions of a fixed symmetric operator with finite and equal defect numbers. The bounds are given in terms of the Duistermaat index, a topological invariant describing the relative position of three Lagrangian planes in a symplectic space. Two of the Lagrangian planes describe the self-adjoint extensions being compared, while the third corresponds to the Friedrichs extension, which acts as a reference point.
  Along the way several auxiliary results are established, including one-sided continuity properties of the Duistermaat triple index, smoothness of the (abstract) Cauchy data space without unique continuation-type assumptions, and a formula for the Morse index of an extension of a non-negative symmetric operator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.06701v4</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gregory Berkolaiko, Graham Cox, Yuri Latushkin, Selim Sukhtaiev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cluster Synchronization via Graph Laplacian Eigenvectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18978v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Almost equitable partitions (AEPs) have been linked to cluster synchronization in oscillatory systems, highlighting the importance of structure in collective network dynamics. We provide a general spectral framework that formalizes this connection, showing how eigenvectors associated with AEPs span a subspace of the Laplacian spectrum that governs partition-induced synchronization behavior. This offers a principled reduction of network dynamics, allowing clustered states to be understood in terms of quotient graph projections. Our approach clarifies the conditions under which transient hierarchical clustering and multi-frequency synchronization emerge, and connects these dynamical phenomena directly to network symmetry and community structure. In doing so, we bridge a critical gap between static topology and dynamic behavior-namely, the lack of a spectral method for analyzing synchronization in networks that exhibit exact or approximate structural regularity. Perfect AEPs are rare in real-world networks since most have some degree of irregularity or noise. We define a relaxation of an AEP we call a quasi-equitable partition at level $\delta$ ($\delta-$QEP). $\delta-$QEPs can preserve many of the clustering-relevant properties of AEPs while tolerating structural imperfections and noise. This extension enables us to describe synchronization behavior in more realistic scenarios, where ideal symmetries are rarely present. Our findings have important implications for understanding synchronization patterns in real-world networks, from neural circuits to power grids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18978v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0280142</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chaos 1 September 2025; 35 (9): 093109</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Timofeyev, Alice Patania</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The fibered rotation number for ergodic symplectic cocycles and its applications: I. Gap Labelling Theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19845v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $ (\Theta,T,\mu) $ be an ergodic topological dynamical system. The fibered rotation number for cocycles in $ \Theta\times \mathrm{SL}(2,\mathbb{R}) $, acting on $ \Theta\times \mathbb{R}\mathbb{P}^1
  $ is well-defined and has wide applications in the study of the spectral theory of Schr\"odinger operators. In this paper, we will provide its natural generalization for higher dimensional cocycles in $ \Theta\times\mathrm{SP}(2m,\mathbb{R}) $ or $ \Theta\times \mathrm{HSP}(2m,\mathbb{C}) $, where $ \mathrm{SP}(2m,\mathbb{R}) $ and $ \mathrm{HSP}(2m,\mathbb{C}) $ respectively refer to the $ 2m $-dimensional symplectic or Hermitian-symplectic matrices. As a corollary, we establish the equivalence between the integrated density of states for generalized Schr\"odinger operators and the fibered rotation number; and the Gap Labelling Theorem via the Schwartzman group, as expected from the one dimensional case [AS1983, JM1982].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19845v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xianzhe Li, Li Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
