<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.SP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SP</link>
    <description>math.SP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 01:20:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral asymptotics and estimates for matrix Birman-Schwinger operators with singular measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14517v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider operators of the form $\mathbf{T}=\mathbf{A^*}(V\mu)\mathbf{A}$ in $\mathbb{R}^\mathbf{N}$, where $\mathbf{A}$ is a pseudodifferential operator of order $-l$, $\mu$ is a compactly supported singular measure, order $s&gt;0$ Ahlfors-regular, and $V$ is a weight function on the support of $\mu$. The scalar type operator $\mathbf{A}$ and the weight function $V$ are supposed to be $m\times m$ matrix valued. We establish Weyl type asymptotic formulas for singular numbers and eigenvalues of $\mathbf{T}$ for $\mu$ being the natural measure on a compact Lipschitz surface. For a general Ahlfors-regular measure $\mu$, we prove that the previously found upper spectral estimates are order sharp.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14517v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grigori Rozenblum, Grigory Tashchiyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral gap with polynomial rate for Weil-Petersson random surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14874v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that there is a constant $c&gt;0$ such that a genus $g$ closed hyperbolic surface, sampled at random from the moduli space $\mathcal{M}_{g}$ with respect to the Weil-Petersson probability measure, has Laplacian spectral gap at least $\frac{1}{4}-O\left(\frac{1}{g^{c}}\right)$ with probability tending to $1$ as $g\to\infty$. This extends and gives a new proof of a recent result of Anantharaman and Monk proved in the series of works [2,3,5,4,6].
  Our approach adapts the polynomial method for the strong convergence of random matrices, introduced by Chen, Garza-Vargas, Tropp and van Handel [19], and its generalization to the strong convergence of surface groups by Magee, Puder and van Handel [41], to the Laplacian on Weil-Petersson random hyperbolic surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14874v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Will Hide, Davide Macera, Joe Thomas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Absence of real resonances of Dirac operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14261v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The purpose of this paper is to introduce the resonances of Dirac operators by continuing meromorphically the truncated resolvent and to establish a result about their localization : a kind of Rellich Theorem. Firstly, we consider the case of the Dirac operator in an external field which is essentially bounded and compactly supported. Secondly, we consider the case of the MIT bag model outside a smooth and bounded obstacle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14261v2</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henry Dumant</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Spectral Analysis of the Superpower Graph of the Direct Product of Dihedral Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.06812v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The superpower graph of a finite group $G$, or $\mathcal{S}_G$, is an undirected simple graph whose vertices are the elements of the group $G$, and two distinct vertices $a,b\in G$ are adjacent if and only if the order of one vertex divides the order of the other vertex, which means that either $o(a)|o(b)$ or $o(b)|o(a)$. In this paper, we have investigated the $A_\alpha$-adjacency spectral properties of the superpower graph of the direct product $D_p\times D_p$, where $D_p$ is a dihedral group for $p$ being prime. Also, we have determined its Laplacian and signless Laplacian spectrum by giving different values to $\alpha$; furthermore, we delved into its superpower graph and deduced the $A_\alpha$- adjacency spectrum of the superpower graph of $D_p\times D_p$ and $D_{p^m}$ for $p$ being an odd prime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.06812v2</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Basit Auyoob Mir, Fouzul Atik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monotonicity of discrete spectra of Dirichlet Laplacian in 3-dimensional layers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12696v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate monotonicity properties of eigenvalues of the Dirichlet Laplacian in polyhedral layers of fixed width. We establish that eigenvalues below the essential spectrum threshold monotonically depend on geometric parameters defining the polyhedral layer, generalizing previous results known for planar V-shaped waveguides and conical layers. Moreover, we demonstrate non-monotone spectral behavior arising from asymmetric geometric perturbations, providing an explicit example where unfolding the polyhedral layer unexpectedly leads to the emergence of discrete eigenvalues. The limiting behavior of eigenvalues as the geometric parameters approach critical configurations is also rigorously analyzed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12696v2</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fedor Bakharev, Sergey Matveenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
