<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.SP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SP</link>
    <description>math.SP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 02:48:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral gap for Pollicott-Ruelle resonances on random coverings of Anosov surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.03726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.03726v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $(M,g)$ be a closed Riemannian surface with Anosov geodesic flow. We prove the existence of a spectral gap for Pollicott--Ruelle resonances on random finite coverings of $M$ in the limit of large degree, which is expected to be optimal. The proof combines the recent strong convergence results of Magee, Puder and van Handel for permutation representations of surface groups with an analysis of the spherical mean operator on the universal cover of $M$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.03726v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julien Moy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resonant scattering for tunable quantum walks on graphs with tails</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.03192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.03192v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the resonant scattering for discrete time quantum walks on graphs with some tails. In our arguments, we reduce the study of resonances to the perturbation of eigenvalues of a finite rank matrix associated with the internal graph. Then we can apply Kato's perturbation theory of matrices, and the reduction process of generalized eigenspaces allows us to derive an explicit asymptotic expansion of the scattering matrix. As a consequence, we obtain the resonant scattering at resonant energies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.03192v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kenta Higuchi, Ryuta Ishikawa, Hisashi Morioka, Etsuo Segawa, Eijirou Yoshimura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Steklov isospectrality of conformal metrics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15535v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Steklov spectrum of a smooth compact Riemannian manifold $(M,g)$ with boundary is the set of eigenvalues counted with multiplicities of its Dirichlet-to-Neumann map. (DN map) This article is devoted to the Steklov spectral inverse problem of recovering the metric $g$, up to natural gauge invariance, from its Steklov spectrum. Positive results are established in dimension $n\geq 3$ for conformal metrics under the assumption that the geodesic flow on the boundary is Anosov with simple length spectrum. The paper combines wave trace formula techniques with the injectivity of the geodesic X-ray transform for functions on closed Anosov manifolds. It is shown that knowledge of the Steklov spectrum determines the jet at the boundary of the underlying Riemannian metric within its conformal class. In this particular context, this parallels the well-known results of the Calder\'on problem, where we are given the entire Dirichlet-to-Neumann map instead. As a simple corollary, assuming real-analyticity of the conformal factor, Steklov isospectral metrics must coincide. Using similar arguments, we are also able to prove under the same assumption of hyperbolicity of the geodesic flow on the boundary, that generically any smooth potential $q$ can be recovered from the Steklov spectrum, in the sense that its jet at the boundary is determined by the spectrum of the DN map for the Schr\"odinger operator with potential $q$. Consequently, in this case, two analytic Steklov isospectral potentials must be equal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15535v3</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Florentin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Steklov Spectrum of Spherical Cylinders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20498v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Steklov problem on a compact Lipschitz domain is to find harmonic functions on the interior whose outward normal derivative on the boundary is some multiple (eigenvalue) of its trace on the boundary. These eigenvalues form the Steklov spectrum of the domain. This article considers the Steklov spectrum of spherical cylinders (Euclidean ball times interval). It is shown that the spectral counting function admits a two term asymptotic expansion. The coefficient of the second term consists of a contribution from the curvature of the boundary and a contribution from the edges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20498v2</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Spencer Bullent</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Morse Functions, Excision and Higher Torsions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17100v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Comparing invariants from both topological and geometric perspectives is a key focus in index theorem. This paper compares higher analytic and topological torsions and establishes a version of the higher Cheeger-M\"uller/Bismut-Zhang theorem. In fact, Bismut-Goette achieved this comparison assuming the existence of fiberwise Morse functions satisfying the fiberwise Thom-Smale transversality condition (TS condition). To fully generalize the theorem, we should remove this assumption. Notably, unlike fiberwise Morse functions, fiberwise generalized Morse functions (GMFs) always exist, we extend Bismut-Goette's setup by considering a fibration $ M \to S $ with a unitarily flat complex bundle $ F \to M $ and a fiberwise GMF $ f $, while retaining the TS condition.
  Compared to Bismut-Goette's work, handling birth-death points for a generalized Morse function poses a key difficulty. To deal with this, first, by the work of the author M.P., joint with Zhang and Zhu, we focus on a relative version of the theorem. Here, analytic and topological torsions are normalized by subtracting their corresponding torsions for trivial bundles. Next, using new techniques from by the author J.Y., we excise a small neighborhood around the locus where $f$ has birth-death points. This reduces the problem to Bismut-Goette's settings (or its version with boundaries) via a Witten-type deformation. However, new difficulties arise from very singular critical points during this deformation. To deal with these, we extend methods from Bismut-Lebeau, using Agmon estimates for noncompact manifolds developed by Dai and J.Y.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17100v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Puchol, Junrong Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
