<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.FA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA</link>
    <description>math.FA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 04:02:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral properties of the gradient operator with nonconstant coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17911v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In mathematical physics, the gradient operator with nonconstant coefficients encompasses various models, including Fourier's law for heat propagation and Fick's first law, that relates the diffusive flux to the gradient of the concentration. Specifically, consider $n\geq 3$ orthogonal unit vectors $e_1,\dots,e_n\in\mathbb{R}^n$, and let $\Omega\subseteq\mathbb{R}^n$ be some (in general unbounded) Lipschitz domain. This paper investigates the spectral properties of the gradient operator $T=\sum_{i=1}^ne_ia_i(x)\frac{\partial}{\partial x_i}$ with nonconstant positive coefficients $a_i:\overline{\Omega}\to(0,\infty)$. Under certain regularity and growth conditions on the $a_i$, we identify bisectorial or strip-type regions that belong to the $S$-resolvent set of $T$. Moreover, we obtain suitable estimates of the associated resolvent operator. Our focus lies in the spectral theory on the $S$-spectrum, designed to study the operators acting in Clifford modules $V$ over the Clifford algebra $\mathbb{R}_n$, with vector operators being a specific crucial subclass. The spectral properties related to the $S$-spectrum of $T$ are linked to the inversion of the operator $Q_s(T):=T^2-2s_0T+|s|^2$, where $s\in\mathbb{R}^{n+1}$ is a paravector, i.e., it is of the form $s=s_0+s_1e_1+\dots+s_ne_n$. This spectral problem is substantially different from the complex one, since it allows to associate general boundary conditions to $Q_s(T)$, i.e., to the squared operator $T^2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17911v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabrizio Colombo, Francesco Mantovani, Peter Schlosser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectrum of Weighted Composition Operators. Part X. The spectrum and essential spectra of weighted automorphisms of the polydisc algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17987</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17987v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the spectrum and the essential spectra of weighted automorphisms of the polydisc algebra $\mathbb{A}^n$. In the case $n=2$ we provide a detailed and, in most cases, complete description of these spectra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17987v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arkady Kitover, Mehmet Orhon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundedness of composition operators from Lorentz spaces to Orlicz spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18107</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18107v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The boundedness (continuity) of composition operators from some function space to another one is significant, though there are few results about this problem. Thus, in this study, we provide necessary and sufficient conditions on the boundedness of composition operators from Lorentz spaces to Orlicz spaces. We emphasize that the measure spaces associated with the Lorentz space may be different from those associated with the Orlicz spaces. Moreover we give some examples and counterexamples of the composed mappings in the conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18107v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naoya Hatano, Masahiro Ikeda, Ryota Kawasumi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum $U$-channels on $S$-spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18160v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: If the symmetry, (an operator $J$ satisfying $J=J^*=J^{-1}$) which defines the Krein space, is replaced by a (not necessarily self-adjoint) unitary, then we have the notion of an $S$-space which was introduced by Szafraniec. In this paper, we consider $S$-spaces and study the structure of completely $U$-positive maps between the algebras of bounded linear operators. We first give a Stinespring-type representation for a completely $U$-positive map. On the other hand, we introduce Choi $U$-matrix of a linear map and establish the equivalence of the Kraus $U$-decompositions and Choi $U$-matrices. Then we study properties of nilpotent completely $U$-positive maps. We develop the $U$-PPT criterion for separability of quantum $U$-states and discuss the entanglement breaking condition of quantum $U$-channels and explore $U$-PPT squared conjecture. Finally, we give concrete examples of completely $U$-positive maps and examples of $3 \otimes 3$ quantum $U$-states which are $U$-entangled and $U$-separable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18160v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Priyabrata Bag, Azad Rohilla, Harsh Trivedi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixed radial-angular integrabilities for Hausdorff type operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18172v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper is devoted to studying some mixed radial-angular integrabilities for various types of Hausdorff operators and commutators</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18172v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ronghui Liu, Guanghui Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Common Fixed Points of Semihypergroup Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18261v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a series of previous papers, we initiated a systematic study of semihypergroups and had a thorough discussion on certain analytic and algebraic aspects associated to this class of objects. In particular, we introduced the notion of semihypergroup actions on a general topological space and discussed different continuity, equivalence and natural fixed point properties of the same in [6]. Now in this article, we consider different kinds of representations of a semihypergroup on compact convex subsets of a locally convex space and explore equivalence relations between certain fixed-point properties of such representations and amenability of the space of almost periodic functions. Finally, we investigate how far these equivalence relations can be strengthened when in particular, we consider representations on the dual of a Banach space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18261v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Choiti Bandyopadhyay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral shift functions of all orders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18422v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $n\in\mathbb{N}$ and let $H_0,V$ be self-adjoint operators such that $V$ is bounded and $V(H_0-i)^{-p}\in\mathcal{S}^{n/p}$ for $p=1,\ldots,n$. We prove the existence, uniqueness up to polynomial summands, and regularity properties of all higher order spectral shift functions associated to the perturbation theory of $t\mapsto H_0+tV$ ($t\in[0,1]$). Such perturbations arise in situations in noncommutative geometry and mathematical physics with dimension $n-1$. Our proof is simpler than that of \cite{NuSkJST,NuSkJOT} and works at all orders regardless of $n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18422v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arup Chattopadhyay, Teun D. H. van Nuland, Chandan Pradhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Commutator estimates and Poisson bounds for Dirichlet-to-Neumann operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18272</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18272v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the Dirichlet-to-Neumann operator ${\cal N}$ associated with a general elliptic operator \[ {\cal A} u = - \sum_{k,l=1}^d \partial_k (c_{kl}\, \partial_l u) + \sum_{k=1}^d \Big( c_k\, \partial_k u - \partial_k (b_k\, u) \Big) +c_0\, u \in {\cal D}'(\Omega) \] with possibly complex coefficients. We study three problems:
  1) Boundedness on $C^\nu$ and on $L_p$ of the commutator $[{\cal N}, M_g]$, where $M_g$ denotes the multiplication operator by a smooth function $g$.
  2) H\"older and $L_p$-bounds for the harmonic lifting associated with ${\cal A}$.
  3) Poisson bounds for the heat kernel of ${\cal N}$.
  We solve these problems in the case where the coefficients are H\"older continuous and the underlying domain is bounded and of class $C^{1+\kappa}$ for some $\kappa &gt; 0$. For the Poisson bounds we assume in addition that the coefficients are real-valued. We also prove gradient estimates for the heat kernel and the Green function $G$ of the elliptic operator with Dirichlet boundary conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18272v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. F. M. ter Elst, E. M. Ouhabaz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Linear Traces on Semifinite Factors and Generalized Singular Numbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18339v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce non-linear traces of the Choquet type and Sugeno type on a semifinite factor $\mathcal{M}$ as a non-commutative analog of the Choquet integral and Sugeno integral for non-additive measures. We need weighted dimension function $p \mapsto \alpha(\tau(p))$ for projections $p \in \mathcal{M}$, which is an analog of a monotone measure. They have certain partial additivities. We show that these partial additivities characterize non-linear traces of both the Choquet type and Sugeno type respectively. Based on the notion of generalized eigenvalues and singular values, we show that non-linear traces of the Choquet type are closely related to the Lorentz function spaces and the Lorentz operator spaces if the weight functions $\alpha$ are concave. For the algebras of compact operators and factors of type ${\rm II}$, we completely determine the condition that the associated weighted $L^p$-spaces for the non-linear traces become quasi-normed spaces in terms of the weight functions $\alpha$ for any $0 &lt; p &lt; \infty$. We also show that any non-linear trace of the Sugeno type gives a certain metric on the factor. This is an attempt at non-linear and non-commutative integration theory on semifinite factors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18339v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masaru Nagisa, Yasuo Watatani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Trace of $W_{a}^{m+1,1}(\mathbb{R}_{+}^{n+1})$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18342v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we give a simple proof that any function in the Besov space $B^{m-a,1}(\mathbb{R}^{n})$ can be extended to a function in $W_{a}^{m+1,1}(\mathbb{R}_{+}^{n+1})$. In particular, utilizing the intrinsic seminorm in $B^{m-a,1}(\mathbb{R}^{n})$, we show that either a suitably scaled heat extension or the harmonic extension provides one with the desired lifting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18342v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Leoni, Daniel Spector</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bifurcations for Lagrangian systems and geodesics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18815v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we shall use the abstract bifurcation theorems developed by the author in previous papers to study bifurcations of solutions for Lagrangian systems on manifolds linearly or nonlinearly dependent on parameters under various boundary value conditions. As applications, many bifurcation results for geodesics on Finsler and Riemannian manifolds are derived.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18815v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guangcun Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpolating between Optimal Transport and KL regularized Optimal Transport using R\'enyi Divergences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18834v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Regularized optimal transport (OT) has received much attention in recent years starting from Cuturi's paper with Kullback-Leibler (KL) divergence regularized OT. In this paper, we propose to regularize the OT problem using the family of $\alpha$-R\'enyi divergences for $\alpha \in (0, 1)$. R\'enyi divergences are neither $f$-divergences nor Bregman distances, but they recover the KL divergence in the limit $\alpha \nearrow 1$. The advantage of introducing the additional parameter $\alpha$ is that for $\alpha \searrow 0$ we obtain convergence to the unregularized OT problem. For the KL regularized OT problem, this was achieved by letting the regularization parameter tend to zero, which causes numerical instabilities. We present two different ways to obtain premetrics on probability measures, namely by R\'enyi divergence constraints and penalization. The latter premetric interpolates between the unregularized and KL regularized OT problem with weak convergence of the minimizer, generalizing the interpolating property of KL regularized OT. We use a nested mirror descent algorithm for solving the primal formulation. Both on real and synthetic data sets R\'enyi regularized OT plans outperform their KL and Tsallis counterparts in terms of being closer to the unregularized transport plans and recovering the ground truth in inference tasks better.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18834v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas Bresch, Viktor Stein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizations of the projection bands and some order properties of the lattices of continuous functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.11192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.11192v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that for an ideal $H$ in an Archimedean vector lattice $F$ the following conditions are equivalent:
  $\bullet$ $H$ is a projection band;
  $\bullet$ Any collection of mutually disjoint vectors in $H$, which is order bounded in $F$, is order bounded in $H$;
  $\bullet$ $H$ is an infinite meet-distributive element of the lattice $\mathcal{I}_{F}$ of all ideals in $F$ in the sense that $\bigcap\limits_{J\in \mathcal{J}}\left(H+ J\right)=H+ \bigcap \mathcal{J}$, for any $\mathcal{J}\subset \mathcal{I}_{F}$.
  Additionally, we show that if $F$ is uniformly complete and $H$ is a uniformly closed principal ideal, then $H$ is a projection band. In the process we investigate some order properties of lattices of continuous functions on Tychonoff topological spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.11192v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eugene Bilokopytov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marcinkiewicz-Zygmund inequalities in variable Lebesgue spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.16323</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.16323v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study $\ell^r$-valued extensions of linear operators defined on Lebesgue spaces with variable exponent. Under some natural (and usual) conditions on the exponents, we characterize $1\leq r\leq \infty$ such that every bounded linear operator $T\colon L^{q(\cdot)}(\Omega_2, \mu)\to L^{p(\cdot)}(\Omega_1, \nu)$ has a bounded $\ell^r$-valued extension. We consider both non-atomic measures and measures with atoms and show the differences that can arise. We present some applications of our results to weighted norm inequalities of linear operators and vector-valued extensions of fractional operators with rough kernel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.16323v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcos Bonich, Daniel Carando, Mart\'in Mazzitelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bifurcations for Hamiltonian systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.10726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2112.10726v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: With the dual variational principle and the saddle point reduction we use the abstract bifurcation theory recently developed by author in previous work to prove many new bifurcation results for solutions of four types of Hamiltonian boundary value problems nonlinearly depending on parameters. The most interesting and important among them are those alternative results which can only be proved with our generalized versions of the famous Rabinowitz's alternative bifurcation theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2112.10726v4</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guangcun Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence results for variational-hemivariational inequality systems with nonlinear couplings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.07076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.07076v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we investigate a system of coupled inequalities consisting of a variational-hemivariational inequality and a quasi-hemivariational inequality on Banach spaces. The approach is topological, and a wide variety of existence results is established for both bounded and unbounded constraint sets in real reflexive Banach spaces. The main point of interest is that no linearity condition is imposed on the coupling functional, therefore making the system fully nonlinear. Applications to Contact Mechanics are provided in the last section of the paper. More precisely, we consider a contact model with (possibly) multivalued constitutive law whose variational formulation leads to a coupled system of inequalities. The weak solvability of the problem is proved via employing the theoretical results obtained in the previous section. The novelty of our approach comes from the fact that we consider two potential contact zones and the variational formulation allows us to determine simultaneously the displacement field and the Cauchy stress tensor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.07076v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.cnsns.2024.108026</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Communications in Nonlinear Science, Volume 134, 2024,108026</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yunru Bai, Nicusor Costea, Shengda Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved Hardy and Rellich inequalities for antisymmetric and odd functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.01677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.01677v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the Hardy and Rellich inequalities for classes of antisymmetric and odd functions and general exponent $p$. The obtained constants are better than the classical ones.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.01677v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Micha{\l} Kijaczko</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
