<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.FA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA</link>
    <description>math.FA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 04:00:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Classical harmonic analysis viewed through the prism of noncommutative geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07750</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07750v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The aim of this paper is to bridge noncommutative geometry with classical harmonic analysis on Banach spaces, focusing primarily on both classical and noncommutative $\mathrm{L}^p$ spaces. Introducing a notion of Banach Fredholm module, we define new abelian groups, $\mathrm{K}^{0}(\mathcal{A},\mathscr{B})$ and $\mathrm{K}^{1}(\mathcal{A},\mathscr{B})$, of $\mathrm{K}$-homology associated with an algebra $\mathcal{A}$ and a suitable class $\mathscr{B}$ of Banach spaces, such as the class of $\mathrm{L}^p$-spaces. We establish index pairings of these groups with the $\mathrm{K}$-theory groups of the algebra $\mathcal{A}$. Subsequently, by considering (noncommutative) Hardy spaces, we uncover the natural emergence of Hilbert transforms, leading to Banach Fredholm modules and culminating in index theorems. Moreover, by associating each reasonable sub-Markovian semigroup with a &lt;&lt;Banach noncommutative manifold&gt;&gt;, we explain how this leads to (possibly kernel-degenerate) Banach Fredholm modules, thereby revealing the role of vectorial Riesz transforms in this context. Overall, our approach significantly integrates the analysis of operators on $\mathrm{L}^p$-spaces into the expansive framework of noncommutative geometry, offering new perspectives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07750v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\'edric Arhancet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Outgoing monotone geodesics of standard subspaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08184v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a real version of the Lax-Phillips Theorem and classify outgoing reflection positive orthogonal one-parameter groups. Using these results, we provide a normal form for outgoing monotone geodesics in the set Stand(H) of standard subspaces on some complex Hilbert space H. As the modular operators of a standard subspace are closely related to positive Hankel operators, our results are obtained by constructing some explicit symbols for positive Hankel operators. We also describe which of the monotone geodesics in Stand(H) arise from the unitary one-parameter groups described in Borchers' Theorem and provide explicit examples of monotone geodesics that are not of this type.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08184v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas Schober</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpolation scattering for wave equations with singular potentials and singular data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07867v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we investigate a construction of scattering for wave-type equations with singular potentials on the whole space $\mathbb{R}^n$ in a framework of weak-$L^p$ spaces. First, we use an Yamazaki-type estimate for wave groups on Lorentz spaces and fixed point arguments to prove the global well-posedness for wave-type equations on weak-$L^p$ spaces. Then, we provide a corresponding scattering results in such singular framework. Finally, we use also the dispersive estimates to establish the polynomial stability and improve the decay of scattering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07867v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tran Thi Ngoc, Pham Truong Xuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regularity of K-finite matrix coefficients of semisimple Lie groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07944v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider $G$ a semisimple Lie group with finite center and $K$ a maximal compact subgroup of $G$. We study the regularity of $K$-finite matrix coefficients of unitary representations of $G$. More precisely, we find the optimal value $\kappa(G)$ such that all such coefficients are $\kappa(G)$-H\"older continuous. The proof relies on analysis of spherical functions of the symmetric Gelfand pair $(G,K)$, using stationary phase estimates from Duistermaat, Kolk and Varadarajan. If $U$ is a compact form of $G$, then $(U,K)$ is a compact symmetric pair. Using the same tools, we study the regularity of $K$-finite coefficients of unitary representations of $U$, improving on previous results obtained by the author.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07944v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillaume Dumas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dirichlet type spaces in the unit bidisc and Wandering Subspace Property for operator tuples</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16541v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article, we define Dirichlet-type space $\mathcal{D}^{2}(\boldsymbol{\mu})$ over the bidisc $\mathbb D^2$ for any measure $\boldsymbol{\mu}\in\mathcal{P}\mathcal{M}_{+}(\mathbb T^2).$ We show that the set of polynomials is dense in $\mathcal{D}^{2}(\boldsymbol{\mu})$ and the pair $(M_{z_1}, M_{z_2})$ of multiplication operator by co-ordinate functions on $\mathcal{D}^{2}(\boldsymbol{\mu})$ is a pair of commuting $2$-isometries. Moreover, the pair $(M_{z_1}, M_{z_2})$ is a left-inverse commuting pair in the following sense: $L_{M_{z_i}} M_{z_j}=M_{z_j}L_{M_{z_i}}$ for $1\leqslant i\neq j\leqslant n,$ where $L_{M_{z_i}}$ is the left inverse of $M_{z_i}$ with $\ker L_{M_{z_i}} =\ker M_{z_i}^*$, $1\leqslant i \leqslant n$. Furthermore, it turns out that, for the class of left-inverse commuting tuple $\boldsymbol T=(T_1, \ldots, T_n)$ acting on a Hilbert space $\mathcal{H}$, the joint wandering subspace property is equivalent to the individual wandering subspace property. As an application of this, the article shows that the class of left-inverse commuting pair with certain splitting property is modelled by the pair of multiplication by co-ordinate functions $(M_{z_1}, M_{z_2})$ on $\mathcal{D}^{2}(\boldsymbol{\mu})$ for some $\boldsymbol{\mu}\in\mathcal{P}\mathcal{M}_{+}(\mathbb T^2).$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16541v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Monojit Bhattacharjee, Rajeev Gupta, Vidhya Venugopal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>All convex bodies are in the subdifferential of some everywhere differentiable locally Lipschitz function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09206v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct a differentiable locally Lipschitz function $f$ in $\mathbb{R}^{N}$ with the property that for every convex body $K\subset \mathbb{R}^N$ there exists $\bar x \in \mathbb{R}^N$  such that $K$ coincides with the set $\partial_L f(\bar x)$ of limits of derivatives $\{Df(x_n)\}_{n\geq 1}$ of sequences $\{x_n\}_{n\geq 1}$ converging to~$\bar x$. The technique can be further refined to recover all compact connected subsets with nonempty interior, disclosing an important difference between differentiable and continuously differentiable functions. It stems out from our approach that the class of these pathological functions contains an infinite dimensional vector space and is dense in the space of all locally Lipschitz functions for the uniform convergence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09206v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aris Daniilidis (TU Wien), Robert Deville (IMB), Sebastian Tapia-Garcia (TU Wien)</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
