<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.FA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA</link>
    <description>math.FA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 01:42:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On weighted Blaschke--Santalo and strong Brascamp--Lieb inequalities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11503v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study new extensions of the functional Blaschke-Santalo inequalities, and explore applications of such new inequalities beyond the classical setting of the standard Gaussian measure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11503v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Colesanti, Alexander Kolesnikov, Galyna Livshyts, Liran Rotem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Probabilistic Approximation in Reproducing Kernel Hilbert Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11679</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11679v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper generalizes the least square method to probabilistic approximation in reproducing kernel Hilbert spaces. We show the existence and uniqueness of the optimizer. Furthermore, we generalize the celebrated representer theorem in this setting, and especially when the probability measure is finitely supported, or the Hilbert space is finite-dimensional, we show that the approximation problem turns out to be a measure quantization problem. Some discussions and examples are also given when the space is infinite-dimensional and the measure is infinitely supported.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11679v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongwei Chen, Kai-Hsiang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Application of a Fourier-Type Series Approach based on Triangles of Constant Width to Letterforms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11958v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we present a novel approach to type design by using Fourier-type series to generate letterforms. We construct a Fourier-type series for functions in $L^2(S^1,\mathbb C)$ based on triangles of constant width instead of circles to model the curves and shapes that define individual characters. In order to compute the coefficients of the series, we construct an isomorphism $\mathcal R:L^2(S^1,\mathbb C)\to L^2(S^1,\mathbb C)$ and study its application to letterforms, thus presenting an alternative to the common use of B\'ezier curves. The proposed method demonstrates potential for creative experimentation in modern type design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11958v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Micha Wasem, Florence Yerly</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An optimization problem and point-evaluation in Paley-Wiener spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11963v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the constant $\mathscr{C}_p$ defined as the smallest constant $C$ such that $|f(0)|^p \leq C\|f\|_p^p$ holds for every function $f$ in the Paley-Wiener space $PW^p$. Brevig, Chirre, Ortega-Cerd\`a, and Seip have recently shown that $\mathscr{C}_p&lt;p/2$ for all $p&gt;2$. We improve this bound for $2&lt;p \leq 5$ by solving an optimization problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11963v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sarah May Instanes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond trees: the metric geometry of subsets of weighted Hamming cubes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06684</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06684v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Associated to any finite metric space are a large number of objects and quantities which provide some degree of structural or geometric information about the space. In this paper we show that in the setting of subsets of weighted Hamming cubes there are unexpected relationships between many of these quantities. We obtain in particular formulas for the determinant of the distance matrix, the $M$-constant and the cofactor sum for such spaces. In general, these types of results offer valuable insights into the combinatorial optimization of certain constrained quadratic forms on finite metric spaces. A key focus in this context are embedding properties of negative type metrics, which play a prominent role in addressing important questions like the sparsest cut problem in graph theory. The current work extends previous results for unweighted metric trees, and more generally, for subsets of standard Hamming cubes, as well as results for weighted metric trees. Finally we consider polygonal equalities in these spaces, giving a complete description of the nontrivial $1$-polygonal equalities that can arise in weighted Hamming cubes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06684v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian Doust, Anthony Weston</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence and uniqueness of limits at infinity for bounded variation functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09489v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the existence of limits at infinity along almost every infinite curve for the upper and lower approximate limits of bounded variation functions on complete unbounded metric measure spaces. We prove that if the measure is doubling and supports a $1$-Poincar\'e inequality, then for every bounded variation function $f$ and for $1$-a.e. infinite curve $\gamma$, for both the upper approximate limit $f^\vee$ and the lower approximate limit $f^\wedge$ we have that \[ \lim_{t\to+\infty}f^\vee(\gamma(t)) {\rm \ \ and\ \ }\lim_{t\to+\infty}f^\wedge(\gamma(t)) \] exist and are equal to the same finite value. We give examples showing that the conditions of doubling and a $1$-Poincar\'e inequality are also necessary for the existence of limits. Furthermore, we establish a characterization for strictly positive $1$-modulus of the family of all infinite curves in terms of bounded variation functions. These generalize results for Sobolev functions given in \cite{KN23}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09489v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Panu Lahti, Khanh Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Around Furstenberg's times $p$, times $q$ conjecture: times $p$-invariant measures with some large Fourier coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.01089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.01089v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For each integer $n\ge 1$, denote by $T_{n}$ the map $x\mapsto nx\mod 1$ from the circle group $\mathbb{T} = \mathbb{R}/\mathbb{Z}$ into itself. Let $p,q\ge 2$ be two multiplicatively independent integers. Using Baire Category arguments, we show that generically a $T_{p}$-invariant probability measure $\mu$ on $\mathbb{T}$ with no atom has some large Fourier coefficients along the sequence $(q^n)_{n\ge 0}$. In particular, $(T_{q^{n}}\mu )_{n\ge 0}$ does not converges weak-star to the normalised Lebesgue measure on $\mathbb{T}$. This disproves a conjecture of Furstenberg and complements previous results of Johnson and Rudolph. In the spirit of previous work by Meiri and Lindenstrauss-Meiri-Peres, we study generalisations of our main result to certain classes of sequences $(c_n)_{n\ge 0}$ other than the sequences $(q^{n})_{n\ge 0}$, and also investigate the multidimensional setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.01089v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Catalin Badea, Sophie Grivaux</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement-assisted classical capacities of some channels acting as radial multipliers on fermion algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.15440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.15440v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate a new class of unital quantum channels on $\mathrm{M}_{2^k}$, acting as radial multipliers when we identify the matrix algebra $\mathrm{M}_{2^k}$ with a finite-dimensional fermion algebra. Our primary contribution lies in the precise computation of the (optimal) rate at which classical information can be transmitted through these channels from a sender to a receiver when they share an unlimited amount of entanglement. Our approach relies on new connections between fermion algebras with the $n$-dimensional discrete hypercube $\{-1,1\}^n$. Significantly, our calculations yield exact values applicable to the operators of the fermionic Ornstein-Uhlenbeck semigroup. This advancement not only provides deeper insights into the structure and behaviour of these channels but also enhances our understanding of Quantum Information Theory in a dimension-independent context.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.15440v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\'edric Arhancet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sobolev inequality and its applications to nonlinear PDE on noncommutative Euclidean spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.09100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.09100v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we study the Sobolev inequality on noncommutative Euclidean spaces. As a simple consequence, we obtain the Gagliardo-Nirenberg type inequality and as its application we show global well-posedness of nonlinear PDEs in the noncommutative Euclidean space. Moreover, we show that the logarithmic Sobolev inequality is equivalent to the Nash inequality for possibly different constants in this noncommutative setting by completing the list in noncommutative Varopoulos's theorem in [37]. Finally, we present a direct application of the Nash inequality to compute the time decay for solutions of the heat equation in the noncommutative setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.09100v4</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michale Ruzhansky, Serikbol Shaimardan, Kanat Tulenov</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
