<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.FA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA</link>
    <description>math.FA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 01:57:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-greedy Markushevich bases, duality and norming subspaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06398v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that if $\mathcal{X}$ is a quasi-greedy Markushevich basis of a Banach space $\mathbb{X}$, its dual basis $\mathcal{X}^*$ spans a norming subspace of $\mathbb{X}^*$. We also prove this result for weaker forms of quasi-greediness, and study the cases of other greedy-like properties from the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06398v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Berasategui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sequences that do frame reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06553v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Frames allow all elements of a Hilbert space to be reconstructed by inner product data in a stable manner. Recently, there is interest in relaxing the definition of frames to understand the implications for stable signal recovery. In this paper, we relax the definition of a frame by allowing the operator in the frame decomposition formula to not be invertible. We provide a complete classification of sequences that allow this decomposition via a type of frame operator. Additionally, we provide several examples of sequences that allow this reconstruction property that are not frames and illustrate in which ways they fail to be frames. Furthermore, we provide a Paley-Wiener type stability result for sequences that do this frame-like reconstruction, which is also stable under the non-frame property. Finally, we classify certain Schauder bases-such as unconditional and exponential bases-that satisfy this relaxed frame reconstruction condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06553v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chad Berner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structural properties of 2-C-normal operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06883v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce and study a new class of bounded linear operators on complex Hilbert spaces, which we call 2-C-normal operators. This class is inspired by and closely related to the notion of 2-normal operators, with additional structure imposed via conjugation. We investigate various fundamental properties of 2-C-normal operators, including algebraic characterizations, spectral properties, and examples that distinguish them from classical normal and 2-normal operators. Additionally, we explore how this class behaves under common operator transformations and examine its relation to other well-studied families of operators. The results presented contribute to a deeper understanding of conjugation-influenced operator behavior and open avenues for further study in the context of complex symmetric operator theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06883v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Messaoud Guesba, Ismail Lakehal, Sid Ahmed Ould Ahmed Mahmoud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytic Langlands correspondence from SoV</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06991v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The analytic Langlands correspondence proposed by Etingof, Frenkel and Kazhdan describes the solution to the spectral problems naturally arising in the quantisation of the Hitchin integrable systems in terms of real opers, certain second order differential operators on a Riemann surface having real monodromy. We prove this correspondence in the cases associated to the group $\mathrm{PSL}(2,\mathbb{C})$, and Riemann surfaces of genus zero with a number of punctures larger than three. A crucial ingredient is a unitary integral transformation mapping products of solutions to the ordinary differential equation associated to a real oper to eigenfunctions of the quantised Hitchin Hamiltonians. This allows us to construct joint eigenfunctions of Hecke operators and Hitchin Hamiltonians from real opers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06991v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico Ambrosino, J\"org Teschner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Klee's problem of convex bodies in Banach spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07031v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is well known that every convex body in a finite dimensional normed space can be uniformly approximated by strictly convex and smooth convex bodies. However, in the case of infinite dimensions, little progress has been made since Klee asked how it is in the case of infinite dimensions in 1959. In this paper, we show that for an infinite dimensional Banach space $X$, (1) every convex body can be uniformly approximated by strictly convex bodies if and only if $X$ admits an equivalent strictly convex norm; (2) every convex body can be uniformly approximated by G\^{a}teaux smooth convex bodies if the dual $X^*$ of $X$ admits an equivalent strictly convex dual norm; in particular, (3) if $X$ is either separable, or reflexive, then every convex body in $X$ can be uniformly approximated by strictly convex and smooth convex bodies. They are done by showing that some correspondences among the sets of all convex bodies endowed with the Hausdorff metric, all continuous coercive Minkowski functionals and Fenchel's transform defined on all quadratic homogenous continuous convex functions equipped with the metric induced by the sup-norm of all bounded continuous functions defined on the closed unit ball $B_X$ are actually locally Lipschitz isomorphisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07031v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lixin Cheng, Chunlan Jiang, Liping Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiplication operators on amalgam of $l^{q), \theta}$ and $L^{p}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07260v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We define the grand amalgam Lebesgue function space $l^{q), \theta}(L^p),$ and study the fundamental structural properties of the space, including completeness. Then we define the small Lebesgue sequence space and study its function space properties. Furthermore, we prove a version of the H\"{o}lders inequality on the frame work of these spaces. Finally, we study the multiplication operator in the setting of these spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07260v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Monika Singh, Jitendra Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Functional calculus for Safarov pseudo-differential operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06859</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06859v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given a smooth, closed Riemannian manifold $(M,g)$ equipped with a linear connection $\nabla$ (not necessarily metric), we develop the holomorphic functional calculus for operators belonging to the global pseudo-differential classes $\Psi_{\rho, \delta}^m\left(\Omega^\kappa, \nabla, \tau\right)$ introduced by Safarov. As a consequence of our main result, we establish a Szeg\"o type-theorem, derive asymptotic expansion of the heat kernel trace, and calculate some associated spectral $\zeta$-functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06859v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Santiago G\'omez Cobos, Michael Ruzhansky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local well-posedness for a class of semilinear Moore-Gibson-Thompson equations with subcritical nonlinearities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06944v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study a class of higher-order semilinear evolution equations inspired by the Moore-Gibson-Thompson model introduced by Dell'Oro, Liverani and Pata (2023), involving strongly elliptic operators of order ($2m$) with homogeneous boundary conditions. The associated unbounded linear operator is a sectorial operator with zero belonging to the resolvent set, allowing the construction of fractional powers spaces, and the analysis of their spectral properties. We prove the local well-posedness of the corresponding semilinear Cauchy problem under subcritical nonlinearities. Our framework clarifies the role of extrapolation spaces and fractional domains in handling the lack of accretivity and bounded imaginary powers of the operator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06944v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Flank D. M. Bezerra, Lu\'is M. Salge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Bubble Isoperimetric Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07078v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We survey recent advancements in the characterization of multi-bubble isoperimetric minimizers and the stability of soap bubble partitions. We conclude with some related open problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07078v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emanuel Milman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relaxation of Non-Convex Integral Functionals in the Multidimensional Scalar Case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07085v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study integral functionals defined on scalar Sobolev spaces of the form $$E[f]:u\mapsto \int_\Omega f(x,u(x),\nabla u(x)) d x,$$
  with an emphasis on the non-convex case, and the difficulties it involves to prevent the Lavrentiev phenomenon. We determine a formulation of the lower semicontinuous envelope of $E[f]$ with respect to various topologies and with fixed Lipschitz Dirichlet boundary conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07085v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tommaso Bertin, Paulin Huguet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cohomology of multipoint connections on complex curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.07747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2106.07747v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Assuming the conformal field theory correlation functions defined on complex curves satisfy the recursion formulas, we express the corresponding cohomology theory via the generalizations of holomorphic connections. The cohomology is explicitly found in terms of higher genus counterparts of elliptic functions as analytic continuations of solutions for functional equations. Explicit examples associated to correlation functions on various genera are provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2106.07747v4</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Zuevsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Funktionalanalysis Teil I</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.12981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.12981v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Roughly speaking, functional analysis is the study of vector spaces of arbitrary dimension over the field of real or complex numbers, and the continuous linear mappings between such spaces. Naturally, the notion of continuity requires a topology - or more specifically, a norm - on these vector spaces, bringing both analytic and algebraic tools into play.
  The name functional analysis originates from the early attempts to extend calculus to functionals defined on function spaces. Results from functional analysis offer powerful tools for solving problems in the theory of (partial) differential equations, in complex analysis, and for the formulation of quantum mechanics. However, the aim of these pages is not to deal with such applications.
  This first part is primarily concerned with the intrinsic properties of certain classes of spaces, namely almost metric spaces, normed vector spaces and algebras, spaces of continuous and and $p$-integrable functions (for $p \in {]}0, \infty{]}$), as well as reflexive, uniformly convex, and Hilbert spaces, rather than with the study of mappings between them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.12981v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christoph Bock</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Blaschke-Santal\'o inequality for unconditional log-concave measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21093v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Blaschke-Santal\'o inequality states that the volume product $|K| \cdot |K^{o}|$ of a symmetric convex body $K \subset \mathbb{R}^n$ is maximized by the standard Euclidean unit-ball. Cordero-Erausquin asked whether the inequality remains true for all even log-concave measures. We briefly survey the literature around this question and provide details for the known fact that the inequality holds true for all unconditional log-concave measures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21093v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emanuel Milman, Amir Yehudayoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explicit Universal and Approximate-Universal Kernels on Compact Metric Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03661v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Universal kernels, whose Reproducing Kernel Hilbert Space is dense in the space of continuous functions are of great practical and theoretical interest. In this paper, we introduce an explicit construction of universal kernels on compact metric spaces. We also introduce a notion of approximate universality, and construct tractable kernels that are approximately universal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03661v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eloi Tanguy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A refined variant of Hartley convolution: Algebraic structures and related issues</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.17529v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we propose a novel convolution product associated with the $\mathscr{H}$-transform, denoted by $\underset{\mathscr{H}}{\ast}$, and explore its fundamental properties. Here, the $\mathscr{H}$-transform may be regarded as a refined variant of the classical Fourier, Hartley transform, with kernel function depending on two parameters $a,b$. Our first contribution shows that the space of integrable functions, equipped with multiplication given by the $\underset{\mathscr{H}}{\ast}$-convolution, constitutes the commutative Banach algebra over the complex field, albeit without an identity element. Second, we prove the Wiener--L\'evy invertibility criterion for the $\mathscr H$-algebra and formulate Gelfand's spectral radius theorem. Third, we obtain a sharp form of Young's inequality for the $\underset{\mathscr{H}}{\ast}$-convolution and its direct corollary. Finally, all of these theoretical findings are applied to investigate specific classes of the Fredholm integral equations and heat source problems, yielding a priori estimates under the established assumptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.17529v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Trinh Tuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Empirical Analysis of the Laplace and Neural Tangent Kernels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.03761</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.03761v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The neural tangent kernel is a kernel function defined over the parameter distribution of an infinite width neural network. Despite the impracticality of this limit, the neural tangent kernel has allowed for a more direct study of neural networks and a gaze through the veil of their black box. More recently, it has been shown theoretically that the Laplace kernel and neural tangent kernel share the same reproducing kernel Hilbert space in the space of $\mathbb{S}^{d-1}$ alluding to their equivalence. In this work, we analyze the practical equivalence of the two kernels. We first do so by matching the kernels exactly and then by matching posteriors of a Gaussian process. Moreover, we analyze the kernels in $\mathbb{R}^d$ and experiment with them in the task of regression.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.03761v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>California State University's ScholarWorks, Summer (2022)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ronaldas Paulius Lencevi\v{c}ius</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global solvability of the Laplace equation in weighted Sobolev spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.07776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.07776v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a non-local boundary value problem for the Laplace equation in unbounded studding the weak and strong solvability of that problem in the framework of the weighted Sobolev space $W^{1,p}_\nu$, with a Muckenhoupt weight. We proved that if any weak solution belongs to the space $W_{\nu}^{2,p}$, then it is also a strong solution and satisfies the corespding boundary conditions. It should be noted that such problems do not fit into the general theory of elliptic equations and require a special technique.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.07776v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bilal T. Bilalov, Natavan P. Nasibova, Lubomira G. Softova, Salvatore Tramontano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multilinear Wavelet Compact T(1) Theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.09185</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.09185v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove a wavelet $T(1)$ theorem for compactness of multilinear Calder\'{o}n-Zygmund (CZ) operators. Our approach characterizes compactness in terms of testing conditions and yields a representation theorem for compact CZ forms in terms of wavelet and paraproduct forms that reflect the compact nature of the operator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.09185v3</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anastasios Fragkos, A. Walton Green, Brett D. Wick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regular Pairings for Non-quadratic Lyapunov Functions and Contraction Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.17350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.17350v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent studies on stability and contractivity have highlighted the importance of semi-inner products, which we refer to as pairings,
  associated with general norms. A pairing is a binary operation that relates the derivative of a curve's norm to the radius-vector of the
  curve and its tangent. This relationship, known as the curve norm derivative formula, is crucial when using the norm as a Lyapunov
  function. Another important property of the pairing, used in stability and contraction criteria, is the so-called Lumer inequality, which
  relates the pairing to the induced logarithmic norm. We prove that the curve norm derivative formula and Lumer's inequality are, in fact,
  equivalent to each other and to several simpler properties. We then introduce and characterize regular pairings that satisfy all of
  these properties. Our results unify several independent theories of pairings (semi-inner products) developed in previous work on functional
  analysis and control theory. Additionally, we introduce the polyhedral max pairing and develop computational tools for polyhedral norms,
  advancing contraction theory in non-Euclidean spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.17350v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton V. Proskurnikov, Francesco Bullo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximation of the Solutions to Quasilinear Parabolic Problems with Perturbed $VMO_x$ Coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16510v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the Cauchy-Dirichlet problem for second-order quasilinear non-divergence form operators of parabolic type. The data are Cara\-th\'e\-o\-dory functions, and the principal part is of $VMO_x$-type with respect to the variables $ (x,t).$ Assuming the existence of a strong solution $u_0,$ we apply the Implicit Function Theorem in a small domain of this solution to show that small bounded perturbations of the data, locally in time, lead to small perturbations of the solution $u_0$. Additionally, we apply the Newton Iteration Procedure to construct an approximating sequence converging to the solution $u_0$ in the corresponding Sobolev space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16510v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rosamaria Rescigno, Lubomira Softova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Particle approximation of nonlocal interaction energies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02905v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider Riesz-type nonlocal energies with general interaction kernels and their discretizations related to particle systems. We prove that the discretized energies $\Gamma$-converge in the weak-$*$ topology to the Riesz functional defined over the space of probability measures. We also address the minimization problem for the discretized energies, and prove the existence of minimal configurations of particles in a very general and natural setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02905v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.na.2025.113974</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Davide Carazzato, Aldo Pratelli, Ihsan Topaloglu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Khinchin inequalities for uniforms on spheres with a deficit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22040</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.22040v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We sharpen the moment comparison inequalities with sharp constants for sums of random vectors uniform on Euclidean spheres, providing a deficit term (optimal in high dimensions).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.22040v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacek Jakimiuk, Colin Tang, Tomasz Tkocz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relative higher index theory on quotients of Roe algebras and positive scalar curvature at infinity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23380v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we employ quotients of Roe algebras as index containers for elliptic differential operators to study the existence problem of Riemannian metrics with positive scalar curvature on non-compact complete Riemannian manifolds. The non-vanishing of such an index locates the precise direction at infinity of the obstructions to positive scalar curvature, and may be viewed as a refinement of the positive scalar curvature problem. To achieve this, we formulate the relative coarse Baum-Connes conjecture and the relative coarse Novikov conjecture, together with their maximal versions, for general metric spaces as a program to compute the $K$-theory of the quotients of the Roe algebras relative to specific ideals. We show that if the metric space admits a relative fibred coarse embedding into Hilbert space or an $\ell^p$-space, certain cases of these conjectures can be verified, which yield obstructions to the existence of uniformly positive scalar curvature metrics in specified directions at infinity. As an application, we prove that the maximal coarse Baum-Connes conjecture holds for finite products of certain expander graphs that fail to admit fibred coarse embeddings into Hilbert space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23380v2</guid>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liang Guo, Qin Wang, Chen Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
