<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.FA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA</link>
    <description>math.FA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 04:00:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>$L^p$-Theory and Noncommutative Geometry in Quantum Harmonic Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18907v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum harmonic analysis extends classical harmonic analysis by integrating quantum mechanical observables, replacing functions with operators and classical convolution structures with their noncommutative counterparts. This paper explores four interrelated developments in this field: (i) a noncommutative $L^p$-theory tailored for quantum harmonic analysis, (ii) the extension of quantum harmonic analysis beyond Euclidean spaces to include Lie groups and homogeneous spaces, (iii) its deep connections with Connes' noncommutative geometry, and (iv) the role of spectral synthesis and approximation properties in quantum settings. We establish novel results concerning the structure and spectral properties of quantum Segal algebras, analyze their functional-analytic aspects, and discuss their implications in quantum physics and operator theory. Our findings provide a unified framework for quantum harmonic analysis, laying the foundation for further advancements in noncommutative analysis and mathematical physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18907v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saeed Hashemi Sababe, Ismail Nikoufar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proof of admissible weights</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18908v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Admissable weight is an important tool for studying spectral invariance in operator algebra. Common admissable weights include polynomial weights and sub exponential weights. This article mainly provides a proof that polynomial weights are permissible weights.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18908v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multidimensional vector-valued Laplace transform and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18909v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce and analyze multidimensional vector-valued Laplace transform of functions with values in sequentially complete locally convex spaces. A great number of our results seem to be new even for the functions with values in Banach spaces. We provide several new applications of multidimensional vector-valued Laplace transform to the abstract Volterra integro-differential inclusions with multiple variables, as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18909v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marko Kostic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal inverse Radon transforms: Complexity of Radon transforms and the hybrid functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18911v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For the reconstruction problem, the universal representation of inverse Radon transforms may imply the needed complexity of the direct Radon transforms which leads to the additional contributions. Meanwhile, in the standard theory of generalized functions, if the origin function which generates the Radon image is a pure-real function, as a rule the complexity of Radon transform becomes in question. In the letter, we demonstrate that the Fourier method together with the hybrid (Wigner-like) function ensure naturally the corresponding complexity. In its turn, this complexity provides not only the additional contribution to the inverse Radon transforms, but also it makes an essential impact on the reconstruction and optimization procedures within the frame of the incorrect problems. The presented method can be effectively used for the practical tasks of reconstruction problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18911v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. V. Anikin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On wavelet-based sampling Kantorovich operators and their study in multi-resolution analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18912v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, wavelet-based filtering operators are constructed by introducing a basic function $D(t_1, t_2, t_3)$ using a general wavelet transform. The cardinal orthogonal scaling functions (COSF) provide an idea to derive the standard sampling theorem in multiresolution spaces which motivates us to study wavelet approximation analysis. With the help of modulus of continuity, we establish a fundamental theorem of approximation. Moreover, we unfold some other aspects in the form of an upper bound of the estimation taken between the operators and functions with various conditions. In that order, a rate of convergence corresponding to the wavelet-based filtering operators is derived, by which we are able to draw some important interferences regarding the error near the sharp edges and smooth areas of the function. Eventually, some examples are demonstrated and empirically proven to justify the fact about the rate of convergence. Besides that, some derivation of inequalities with justifications through examples and important remarks emphasizes the depth and significance of our work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18912v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Digvijay Singh, Rahul Shukla, Karunesh Kumar Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>p-adic Ghobber-Jaming Uncertainty Principle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18913</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18913v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $\{\tau_j\}_{j=1}^n$ and $\{\omega_k\}_{k=1}^n$ be two orthonormal bases for a finite dimensional p-adic Hilbert space $\mathcal{X}$. Let $M,N\subseteq \{1, \dots, n\}$ be such that \begin{align*} \displaystyle \max_{j \in M, k \in N}|\langle \tau_j, \omega_k \rangle|&lt;1, \end{align*} where $o(M)$ is the cardinality of $M$. Then for all $x \in \mathcal{X}$, we show that \begin{align} (1) \quad \quad \quad \quad \|x\|\leq \left(\frac{1}{1-\displaystyle \max_{j \in M, k \in N}|\langle \tau_j, \omega_k \rangle|}\right)\max\left\{\displaystyle \max_{j \in M^c}|\langle x, \tau_j\rangle |, \displaystyle \max_{k \in N^c}|\langle x, \omega_k\rangle |\right\}. \end{align}
  We call Inequality (1) as \textbf{p-adic Ghobber-Jaming Uncertainty Principle}. Inequality (1) is the p-adic version of uncertainty principle obtained by Ghobber and Jaming \textit{[Linear Algebra Appl., 2011]}. We also derive analogues of Inequality (1) for non-Archimedean Banach spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18913v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Mahesh Krishna</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizations of monotone right continuous functions which generate associative functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18944v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Associativity of a two-place function $T: [0,1]^2\rightarrow [0,1]$ defined by $T(x,y)=f^{(-1)}(T^*(f(x),f(y)))$ where $T^*:[0,1]^2\rightarrow[0,1]$ is an associative function with neutral element in $[0,1]$, $f: [0,1]\rightarrow [0,1]$ is a monotone right continuous function and $f^{(-1)}:[0,1]\rightarrow[0,1]$ is the pseudo-inverse of $f$ depends only on properties of the range of $f$. The necessary and sufficient conditions for the $T$ to be associative are presented by applying the properties of the monotone right continuous function $f$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18944v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yun-Mao Zhang, Xue-ping Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Essential Self-Adjointness of the Geometric Deformation Operator on a Compact Interval</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18914v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We define a second-order differential operator $\hat{C}$ on the Hilbert space $L^2([-v_c, v_c])$, constructed from a smooth deformation function $C(v)$. The operator is considered on the Sobolev domain $H^2([-v_c, v_c]) \cap H^1_0([-v_c, v_c])$ with Dirichlet boundary conditions. We prove that $\hat{C}$ is essentially self-adjoint by verifying its symmetry and computing von Neumann deficiency indices, which vanish. All steps are carried out explicitly. This result ensures the mathematical consistency of the operator and enables future spectral analysis on compact intervals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18914v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Alexa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast repetitivity in non-rectifiable Delone sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19114v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a construction of non-rectifiable, repetitive Delone sets in every Euclidean space $\mathbb{R}^d$ with $d \geq 2$. We further obtain a close to optimal repetitivity function for such sets. The proof is based on the process of encoding a non-realisable density in a Delone set, due to Burago and Kleiner.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19114v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashwin Bhat, Michael Dymond</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Hilbert operators acting from Hardy spaces to weighted Bergman spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19338v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $\mu$ be a positive Borel measure on the interval $[0,1)$. For $\alpha&gt;0$, the generalized Hankel matrix $\mathcal{H}_{\mu, \alpha}=(\mu_{n, k, \alpha})_{n, k \geq 0}$ with entries $\mu_{n, k, \alpha}=\int_{[0,1)} \frac{\Gamma(n+\alpha)}{n ! \Gamma(\alpha)} t^{n+k} \mathrm{d}\mu(t)$ induces formally the operator \begin{equation*} \mathcal{H}_{\mu, \alpha}(f)(z)=\sum_{n=0}^{\infty}\left(\sum_{k=0}^{\infty} \mu_{n, k, \alpha} a_k\right) z^n \end{equation*} on the space of all analytic function $f(z)=\sum_{k=0}^{\infty} a_{k} z^{k}$ in the unit disk $\mathbb{D}$. In this paper, we characterize the measures $\mu$ for which $\mathcal{H}_{\mu, \alpha}(f)$ is well defined on the Hardy spaces $H^p(0&lt;p&lt;\infty)$ and satisfies $\mathcal{H}_{\mu, \alpha}(f)(z)=\int_{[0,1)} \frac{f(t)}{(1-t z)^\alpha} \mathrm{d} \mu(t)$. Among these measures, we further describe those for which $\mathcal{H}_{\mu, \alpha}(\alpha&gt;1)$ is a bounded (resp., compact) operator from the Hardy spaces $H^p(0&lt;p&lt;\infty)$ into the weighted Bergman spaces $A_{\alpha-2}^q $.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19338v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liyi Wang, Shanli Ye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiplicity results for mixed local-nonlocal variable exponent problem involving singular and superlinear term</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19793v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study a class of quasilinear elliptic equations involving both local and nonlocal operators with variable exponents. The problem exhibits singular nonlinearities along with a subcritical superlinear growth term and a parameter $\lambda$. We study the existence of multiple solutions with the help of variational methods by restricting the associated energy functional on appropriate subsets of the Nehari manifold. Using the topological index and the structure of the fibering maps, we analyse a key splitting property of the associated Nehari manifold. This decomposition allows us to establish the existence of two distinct solutions. Additionally, we establish the $L^\infty$-bound for the solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19793v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shammi Malhotra, Ambesh Kumar Pandey, K. Sreenadh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite dimensionality of Besov spaces and potential-theoretic decomposition of metric spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.01292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.01292v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the context of a metric measure space $(X,d,\mu)$, we explore the potential-theoretic implications of having a finite-dimensional Besov space. We prove that if the dimension of the Besov space $B^\theta_{p,p}(X)$ is $k&gt;1$, then $X$ can be decomposed into $k$ number of irreducible components (Theorem 1.1). Note that $\theta$ may be bigger than $1$, as our framework includes fractals. We also provide sufficient conditions under which the dimension of the Besov space is $1$. We introduce critical exponents $\theta_p(X)$ and $\theta_p^{\ast}(X)$ for the Besov spaces. As examples illustrating Theorem 1.1, we compute these critical exponents for spaces $X$ formed by glueing copies of $n$-dimensional cubes, the Sierpi\'{n}ski gaskets, and of the Sierpi\'{n}ski carpet.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.01292v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takashi Kumagai, Nageswari Shanmugalingam, Ryosuke Shimizu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Besselian Schauder Frames and the Structure of Banach Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00777v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Schauder bases are fundamental tools for analyzing the structure of Banach spaces. In this work, we show that Besselian Schauder frames (BSF) play a similar role in certain contexts. Specifically, we extend several well-known results of Karlin and James to Banach spaces with BSF, particularly to those with unconditional Schauder frames (USF). We prove that many classical Banach spaces do not admit BSF, and in particular, do not admit USF.
  Before establishing these results, we construct an explicit Schauder frame for every Banach space with a finite dimensional decomposition. In particular, Szarek's Banach space has a Schauder frame, which famously lacks a Schauder basis. This finding provides strong motivation for extending classical Schauder basis theory to the framework of Schauder frames.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00777v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafik Karkri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Gaussian correlation inequality for centered convex sets and the case of equality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.04337v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Inspired from Milman's observation, we prove that the Gaussian correlation inequality holds for centered convex sets and characterize the case of equality. Furthermore, we confirm a nonsymmetric version of the inequality proposed by Szarek--Werner. The existing arguments due to Royen and Milman are seemingly difficult to be applied for these purposes since both of them involve certain approximation arguments that reduce the inequality to some weaker form. To overcome this difficulty, we generalize our previous work on the inverse Brascamp--Lieb inequality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.04337v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shohei Nakamura, Hiroshi Tsuji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Amenability of group actions on compact spaces and the associated Banach algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08357v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For a topological group $G$ , amenability can be characterized by the amenability of the convolution Banach algebra $L^1(G)$. Here a Banach algebra $A$ is called amenable if every bounded derivation from $A$ into any dual-type $A$-$A$-Banach bimodule are inner. We extend this classical result to discrete group actions on compact Hausdorff spaces. By introducing a Banach algebra naturally associated with the action and adopting a suitably weakened notion of amenability for Banach algebras, we obtain an analogous characterization of amenable actions. As a lemma, we also proved a fixed-point property for amenable actions that strengthens the theorem of Dong and Wang (2015).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08357v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hikaru Awazu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a Lebesgue-like integral over the Levi-Civita field $\mathcal{R}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13930</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13930v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Levi-Civita field $\mathcal{R}$ is the smallest non-Archimedean ordered field extension of the real numbers that is real closed and Cauchy complete in the topology induced by the order. In this paper we develop a new theory of integration over $\mathcal{R}$ that generalizes previous work done in the subject while circumventing the fact that not every bounded subset of $\mathcal{R}$ admits either an infimum or a supremum. We define a new family of measurable functions and a new integral over measurable subsets of $\mathcal{R}$ that satisfies some very important results analogous to those of the Lebesgue and Riemann integrals for real-valued functions. In particular, we show that the family of measurable functions forms an algebra that is closed under taking absolute values, that the integral is linear, countably additive and monotone, that the integral of a non-negative function $f:A\to\mathcal{R}$ is zero if and only if $f=0$ almost everywhere in $A$ and that the analogous versions for the uniform convergence theorem and the fundamental theorem of calculus hold true.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13930v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mateo Restrepo Borrero, Khodr Shamseddine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Layer potential operators for transmission problems on extension domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11601v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We use the well-posedness of transmission problems on classes of two-sided Sobolev extension domains to give variational definitions for (boundary) layer potential operators and Neumann-Poincar{\'e} operators. These classes of domains contain Lipschitz domains, and also domains with fractal boundaries. Although our variational formulation does not involve any measures on the boundary, we recover the classical results in smooth domains by considering the surface measure on the boundary. We discuss properties of these operators and generalize basic results in imaging beyond the Lipschitz case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11601v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel Claret (MICS), Michael Hinz (MICS), Anna Rozanova-Pierrat (MICS), Alexander Teplyaev (UCONN)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpolating between Optimal Transport and KL regularized Optimal Transport using R\'enyi Divergences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18834v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Regularized optimal transport (OT) has received much attention in recent years starting from Cuturi's introduction of Kullback-Leibler (KL) divergence regularized OT. In this paper, we propose regularizing the OT problem using the family of $\alpha$-R\'enyi divergences for $\alpha \in (0, 1)$. R\'enyi divergences are neither $f$-divergences nor Bregman distances, but they recover the KL divergence in the limit $\alpha \nearrow 1$. The advantage of introducing the additional parameter $\alpha$ is that for $\alpha \searrow 0$ we obtain convergence to the unregularized OT problem. For the KL regularized OT problem, this was achieved by letting the regularization parameter $\varepsilon$ tend to zero, which causes numerical instabilities. We present two different ways to obtain premetrics on probability measures, namely by R\'enyi divergence constraints and by penalization. The latter premetric interpolates between the unregularized and the KL regularized OT problem with weak convergence of the unique minimizer, generalizing the interpolation property of KL regularized OT. We use a nested mirror descent algorithm to solve the primal formulation. Both on real and synthetic data sets R\'enyi regularized OT plans outperform their KL and Tsallis counterparts in terms of being closer to the unregularized transport plans and recovering the ground truth in inference tasks better.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18834v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas Bresch, Viktor Stein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fundamental solutions for parabolic equations and systems: universal existence, uniqueness, representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18436v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we develop a universal, conceptually simple and systematic method to prove well-posedness to Cauchy problems for weak solutions of parabolic equations with non-smooth, time-dependent, elliptic part having a variational definition. Our classes of weak solutions are taken with minimal assumptions. We prove the existence and uniqueness of a fundamental solution which seems new in this generality: it is shown to always coincide with the associated evolution family for the initial value problem with zero source and it yields representation of all weak solutions. Our strategy is a variational approach avoiding density arguments, a priori regularity of weak solutions or regularization by smooth operators. One of our main tools are embedding results which yield time continuity of our weak solutions going beyond the celebrated Lions regularity theorem and that is addressing a variety of source terms. We illustrate our results with three concrete applications : second order uniformly elliptic part with Dirichlet boundary condition on domains, integro-differential elliptic part, and second order degenerate elliptic part.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18436v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jmaa.2025.129806</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Mathematical Analysis and Applications, 552(1):129806, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pascal Auscher, Khalid Baadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heat semigroups on quantum automorphism groups of finite dimensional C*-algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03448v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate heat semigroups on a quantum automorphism group ${\rm Aut}^+(B)$ of a finite dimensional C*-algebra $B$ and its Plancherel trace. We show ultracontractivity, hypercontractivity, and the spectral gap inequality of the heat semigroups on ${\rm Aut}^+(B)$. Furthermore, we obtain the sharpness of the Sobolev embedding property and the Hausdorff-Young inequality of ${\rm Aut}^+(B)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03448v3</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Futaba Sato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional Volterra-type operator induced by radial weight acting on Hardy space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18122v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Given a radial doubling weight $\mu$ on the unit disc $\mathbb{D}$ of the complex plane and its odd moments $\mu_{2n+1}=\int_0^1 s^{2n+1}\mu(s)\, ds$, we consider the fractional derivative
  $$
  D^\mu(f)(z)=\sum_{n=0}^{\infty} \frac{\widehat{f}(n)}{\mu_{2n+1}}z^n,
  $$
  of a function $ f(z)=\sum_{n=0}^{\infty}\widehat{f}(n)z^n$ analytic in $\mathbb{D}$. We also consider the fractional integral operator $I^\mu(f)(z)=\sum_{n=0}^{\infty} \mu_{2n+1}\widehat{f}(n)z^n$, and the fractional Volterra-type operator
  $$
  V_{\mu,g}(f)(z)= I^\mu(f\cdot D^\mu(g))(z),\quad f\in\mathcal{H}(\mathbb{D}),
  $$
  for any fixed $g\in\mathcal{H}(\mathbb{D})$. We prove that $V_{\mu,g}$ is bounded (compact) on a Hardy space $H^p$, $0&lt;p&lt;\infty$, if and only if $g$ belongs to $\text{BMOA}$ ($\text{VMOA}$). Moreover, if $\int_0^1 \frac{\left(\int_r^1 \mu(s)\, ds\right)^p}{(1-r)^2}\,dr=+\infty$, we prove that $V_{\mu,g}$ belongs to the Schatten class $S_p(H^2)$ if and only if $g=0$. On the other hand, if $\frac{\left(\int_r^1 \mu(s)\, ds\right)^p}{(1-r)^2}$ is a radial doubling weight it is proved that $V_{\mu,g} \in S_p(H^2)$ if and only if $g$ belongs to the Besov space $B_p$. En route, we obtain descriptions of $H^p$, $\text{BMOA}$, $\text{VMOA}$ and $B_p$ in terms of the fractional derivative $D^\mu$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18122v2</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlo Bellavita, \'Alvaro Miguel Moreno, Georgios Nikolaidis, Jos\'e \'Angel Pel\'aez</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
