<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.FA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA</link>
    <description>math.FA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 04:00:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Index theory for non-compact quantum graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09749v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop an index theory for variational problems on noncompact quantum graphs. The main results are a spectral flow formula, relating the net change of eigenvalues to the Maslov index of boundary data, and a Morse index theorem, equating the negative directions of the Lagrangian action with the total multiplicity of conjugate instants along the edges.
  These results extend classical tools in global analysis and symplectic geometry to graph based models, with applications to nonlinear wave equations such as the nonlinear Schroedinger equation. The spectral flow formula is proved by constructing a Lagrangian intersection theory in the Gelfand-Robbin quotients of the second variation of the action. This approach also recovers, in a unified way, the known formulas for heteroclinic, halfclinic, homoclinic, and bounded orbits of (non)autonomous Lagrangian systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09749v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniele Garrisi, Alessandro Portaluri, Li Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random Nonlinear Fusion Frames from Averaged Operator Iterations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09927v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study random iterations of averaged operators in Hilbert spaces and prove that the associated residuals converge exponentially fast, both in expectation and almost surely. Our results provide quantitative bounds in terms of a single geometric parameter, giving sharp control of convergence rates under minimal assumptions. As an application, we introduce the concept of random nonlinear fusion frames. Here the atoms are generated dynamically from the residuals of the iteration and yield exact synthesis with frame-like stability in expectation. We show that these frames achieve exponential sampling complexity and encompass important special cases such as random projections and randomized Kaczmarz methods. This reveals a link between stochastic operator theory, frame theory, and randomized algorithms, and establishes a structural tool for constructing nonlinear frame-like systems with strong stability and convergence guarantees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09927v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Tian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Approaches to the Fixed Point Property in L^1 Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10194v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents new approaches to the fixed point property for nonexpansive mappings in L^1 spaces. While it is well-known that L^1 fails the fixed point property in general, we provide a complete and self-contained proof that measure-compactness of a convex set is a sufficient condition. Our exposition makes all compactness and uniform integrability arguments explicit, offering a clear path from measure-theoretic compactness to weak compactness, normal structure, and ultimately fixed points via Kirk's theorem.
  Beyond this geometric approach, we contextualize this result within broader structural strategies for obtaining fixed points in L^1 and related spaces. We discuss the roles of ultraproducts, equivalent renormings that induce uniform convexity on l^1, and the fixed point property in non-reflexive spaces like Lorentz sequence spaces. This work unifies these perspectives, demonstrating that the obstruction to fixed points in L^1 is not the space itself but specific geometric or structural properties of its subsets. The results clarify the landscape of fixed point theory in non-reflexive Banach spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10194v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Faruk Alpay, Hamdi Alakkad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropy and Learning of Lipschitz Functions under Log-Concave Measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10355v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study regression of $1$-Lipschitz functions under a log-concave measure $\mu$ on $\mathbb{R}^d$. We focus on the high-dimensional regime where the sample size $n$ is subexponential in $d$, in which distribution-free estimators are ineffective. We analyze two polynomial-based procedures: the projection estimator, which relies on knowledge of an orthogonal polynomial basis of $\mu$, and the least-squares estimator over low-degree polynomials, which requires no knowledge of $\mu$ whatsoever. Their risk is governed by the rate of polynomial approximation of Lipschitz functions in $L^2(\mu)$. When this rate matches the Gaussian one, we show that both estimators achieve minimax bounds over a wide range of parameters. A key ingredient is sharp entropy estimates for the class of $1$-Lipschitz functions in $L^2(\mu)$, which are new even in the Gaussian setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10355v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Bizeul, Boaz Klartag</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
