<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.FA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA</link>
    <description>math.FA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 05:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Periodic Points of Diagonal and Permutation Operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12605</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12605v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We first give a condition for a normal operator on a Hilbert space to have no nonzero periodic points, then we give a characterization of normal operators with the whole space as periodic points. We proceed to study the structure of periodic points of the diagonal operators and the permutation operators with examples. Moreover, it is also shown that the set of all diagonal operators with the whole space as periodic points is dense in the set of all unitary diagonal operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12605v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Howen Chuah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A weak Hilbert space that is a twisted HIlbert space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12707</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12707v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct a weak Hilbert space that is a twisted Hilbert space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12707v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/S1474748018000221</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Inst. Math. Jussieu 19 (2020), no. 3, 855--867</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jes\'us Su\'arez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subspaces of $\ell_1$ satisfying Grothendieck's theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12715v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We characterize the subspaces $X$ of $\ell_1$ satisfying Grothendieck's theorem in terms of extension of nonnegative quadratic forms $q:X \longrightarrow \mathbb R$ to the whole $\ell_1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12715v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.bulsci.2017.10.002</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Bull. Sci. Math. 143 (2018), 73--81</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jes\'us Su\'arez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbations of embedded eigenvalues of asymptotically periodic magnetic Schr\"odinger operators on a cylinder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12817</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12817v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the persistence of embedded eigenvalues for a class of magnetic Laplacians on an infinite cylindrical domain. The magnetic potential is assumed to be $C^2$ and asymptotically periodic along the unbounded direction, with an algebraic decay rate towards a periodic background potential. Under the condition that the embedded eigenvalue of the unperturbed operator lies away from the thresholds of the continuous spectrum, we show that the set of nearby potentials for which the embedded eigenvalue persists forms a smooth manifold of finite and even codimension. The proof employs tools from Floquet theory, exponential dichotomies, and Lyapunov--Schmidt reduction. Additionally, we give an example of a potential which satisfies the assumptions of our main theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12817v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas Jansen, Sara Maad Sasane, Wilhelm Treschow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modulation spaces on the Heisenberg group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12845v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article we show how certain irreducible unitary representation $ \Pi_\lambda $ of the twisted Heisenberg group $ \He_\lambda^n(\C)$ leads to the twisted modulation spaces $ M_\lambda^{p,q}(\R^{2n}).$ These $ \Pi_\lambda $ also turn out to be irreducible unitary representations of another nilpotent Lie group $ G_n $ which contains two copies of the Heisenberg group $ \He^n.$ By lifting $ \Pi_\lambda $ we obtain another unitary representation $ \Pi $ of $ G_n $ acting on $ L^2(\He^n).$ We define our modulation spaces $ M^{p,q}(\He^n) $ in terms of the matrix coefficients associated to $ \Pi.$ These spaces are shown to be invariant under Heisenberg translations and Heisenberg modulations which are different from euclidean modulations. We also establish some of the basic properties of $ M_\lambda^{p,q}(\R^{2n})$ and $ M^{p,q}(\He^n) $ such as completeness and invariance under suitable Fourier transforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12845v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Md Hasan Ali Biswas, Sundaram Thangavelu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simpliciality of vector-valued function spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12876v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate integral representation of vector-valued function spaces, i.e., of subspaces $H\subset C(K,E)$, where $K$ is a compact space and $E$ is a (real or complex) Banach space. We point out that there are two possible ways of generalizing representation theorems known from the scalar case -- either one may represent (all) functionals from $H^*$ using $E^*$-valued vector measures on $K$ (as it is done in the literature) or one may represent (some) operators from $L(H,E)$ by scalar measures on $K$ using the Bochner integral. These two ways lead to two different notions of simpliciality which we call `vector simpliciality' and `weak simpliciality'. It turns out that these two notions are in general incomparable. Moreover, the weak simpliciality is not affected by renorming the target space $E$, while vector simpliciality may be affected. Further, if $H$ contains constants, vector simpliciality is strictly stronger and admits several characterizations (partially analogous to the characterizations known in the scalar case). We also study orderings of measures inspired by C.J.K.~Batty which may be (in special cases) used to characterize $H$-boundary measures. Finally, we give a finer version of representation theorem using positive measures on $K\times B_{E^*}$ and characterize uniqueness in this case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12876v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ond\v{r}ej F. K. Kalenda, Ji\v{r}\'i Spurn\'y</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On growth of cocycles of isometric representations on $L^p$-spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12808v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study different notions of asymptotic growth for 1-cocycles of isometric representations on Banach spaces. One can see this as a way of quantifying the absence of fixed point properties on such spaces. Inspired by the work of Lafforgue, we show the following dichotomy: for a compactly generated group $G$, either all 1-cocycles of $G$ taking values in $L^p$-spaces are bounded (this is Property $FL^p$) or there exists a 1-cocycle of $G$ taking values in an $L^p$-space with relatively fast growth. We also obtain upper and lower bounds on the average growth of harmonic 1-cocycles with values in Banach spaces with convexity properties. As a consequence, we obtain bounds on the average growth of all 1-cocycles with values in $L^p$-spaces for groups with property $(T)$. Lastly, we show that for a unimodular compactly generated group $G$, the existence of a 1-cocycle with compression larger than $\sqrt{n}$ implies the Liouville property for a large family of probability measures on $G$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12808v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio L\'opez Neumann, Juan Paucar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Upper triangular operator matrices and stability of their various spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.07387</link>
      <description>arXiv:2110.07387v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Denote by $T_n^d(A)$ an upper triangular operator matrix of dimension $n$ whose diagonal entries $D_i$ are known, where $A=(A_{ij})_{1\leq i&lt;j\leq n}$ is an unknown tuple of operators. This article is aimed at investigation of defect spectrum $\mathcal{D}^{\sigma_*}=\bigcup\limits_{i=1}^n\sigma_*(D_i)\setminus\sigma_*(T_n^d(A))$ , where $\sigma_*$ is a spectrum corresponding to various types of invertibility: (left, right) invertibility, (left, right) Fredholm invertibility, left Weyl invertibility, right Weyl invertibility. We give characterizations for each of the previous types, and provide some sufficent conditions for the stability of certain spectrum (case $\mathcal{D}^{\sigma_*}=\emptyset$). Our main results hold for an arbitrary dimension $n\geq2$ in arbitrary Hilbert or Banach spaces without assuming separability, thus generalizing results from \cite{WU}, \cite{WU2}. Hence, we complete a trilogy to previous work \cite{SARAJLIJA2}, \cite{SARAJLIJA3} of the same author, whose goal was to explore basic invertibility properties of $T_n^d(A)$ that are studied in Fredholm theory. We also retrieve a result from \cite{BAI} in the case $n=2$, and we provide a precise form of the well known 'filling in holes' result from \cite{HAN}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2110.07387v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikola Sarajlija</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Completion problem of upper triangular $3\times3$ operator matrices on arbitrary Banach spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.04960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2202.04960v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We solve the completion problem of $3\times3$ upper triangular operator matrix acting on a direct sum of Banach spaces and hence generalize the famous result of Han, Lee, Lee (Proc. Amer. Math. Soc. 128 (1) (2000), 119-123) to a greater dimension of a matrix. Our main tools are Harte's ghost of an index theorem and Banach spaces embeddings. We overcome the lack of orthogonality in Banach spaces by exploiting decomposition properties of inner regular operators, and of Fredholm regular operators when needed. Finally, we provide some necessity results related to the invertibility of $n\times n$ upper triangular operators, $n&gt;3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2202.04960v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikola Sarajlija, Dragan S. Djordjevi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On measures strongly log-concave on a subspace</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.09422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2203.09422v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work we study the concentration properties of log-concave measures that are curved only on a subspace of directions. Proofs uses an adapted version of the stochastic localization process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2203.09422v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Bizeul</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Further results on $p$-adic semigroup of contractions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.12630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.12630v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $E$ be an ultrametric Banach space over $\mathbb{C}_{p}.$ In this note, we obtain a new necessary and sufficient conditions on the resolvent of $A$ such that for each $m\in\mathbb{N},\;\|A^{m}\|\leq1.$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.12630v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jawad Ettayb</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Hille-Yoshida-Phillips theorem for discrete semigroups on complete ultrametric locally convex spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.03960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.03960v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $E$ be a complete Hausdorff locally convex space over $\mathbb{C}_{p},$ let $A\in\mathcal{L}(E)$ such that $(I-\lambda A)^{-1}$ is analytic on its domain. In this paper, we give a necessary and sufficient condition on the resolvent of $A$ such that $(A^{n})_{n\in\mathbb{N}}$ is equi-continuous.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.03960v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jawad Ettayb</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Condition pseudospectrum of operator pencils on non-archimedean Banach spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.18401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.18401v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper deals with the condition pseudospectrum and essential condition pseudospectrum of operator pencils on n.a Banach spaces. We give a characterization of the condition pseudospectrum of operator pencils on n.a Banach spaces, the relation between the condition pseudospectrum of $(A,B)$ and the usual spectrum in a n.a valued field is investigated. Finally, we give a characterization of the essential spectrum of $(A,B)$ where $A\neq B$ by means of n.a completely continuous operators and we give some examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.18401v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jawad Ettayb</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Left (right) pseudospectrum and left (right) condition pseudospectrum of bounded linear operators on ultrametric Banach spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.03998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.03998v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this note, we introduce and study the left (right) pseudospectrum and left (right) condition pseudospectrum of bounded linear operators on ultrametric Banach spaces. We prove some results about them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.03998v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jawad Ettayb</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Wigdersons' approach to the uncertainty principle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.17438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.17438v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We revisit the uncertainty principle from the point of view suggested by A. Wigderson and Y. Wigderson. This approach is based on a primary uncertainty principle from which one can derive several inequalities expressing the impossibility of a simultaneous sharp localization in time and frequency. Moreover, it requires no specific properties of the Fourier transform and can therefore be easily applied to all operators satisfying the primary uncertainty principle. A. Wigderson and Y. Wigderson also suggested many generalizations to higher dimensions and stated several conjectures which we address in the present paper. We argue that we have to consider a more general primary uncertainty principle to prove the results suggested by the authors. As a by-product we obtain some new inequalities akin to the Cowling-Price uncertainty principle, a generalization of the Heisenberg uncertainty principle, and derive the entropic uncertainty principle from the primary uncertainty principles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.17438v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nuno Costa Dias, Franz Luef, Jo\~ao Nuno Prata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributions in spaces with thick submanifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02864v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the construction of a theory of distributions (generalized functions) with a ``thick submanifold'', that is, a new theory of thick distributions on $\mathbb{R}^n$ whose domain contains a smooth submanifold on which the test functions may be singular. We define several operations, including ``thick partial derivatives'', and clarify their connection with their classical counterparts in Schwartz distribution theory. We also introduce and study a number of special thick distributions, including new thick delta functions, or more generally thick multilayer distributions along a submanifold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02864v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Electron. Res. Arch. 32 (2024), 6660-6679</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jiajia Ding, Jasson Vindas, Yunyun Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on $L^p$-$L^q$ boundedness of Fourier multipliers on noncommutative spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08643v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we study Fourier multipliers on noncommutative spaces. In particluar, we show a simple proof of $L^p$-$L^q$ estimate of Fourier multipliers on general noncommutative spaces associated with semi-finite von Neumann algebras. This includes the case of Fourier multipliers on general locally compact unimodular groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08643v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Ruzhansky, Kanat Tulenov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the harmonic generalized Cauchy-Kovalevskaya extension and its connection with the Fueter-Sce theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12265</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12265v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: One of the primary objectives of this paper is to establish a generalized Cauchy-Kovalevskaya extension for axially harmonic functions. We demonstrate that the result can be expressed as a power series involving Bessel-type functions of specific differential operators acting on two initial functions. Additionally, we analyze the decomposition of the harmonic CK extension in terms of integrals over the sphere $ \mathbb{S}^{m-1} $ involving functions of plane wave type.
  Another key goal of this paper is to explore the relationship between the harmonic Cauchy-Kovalevskaya extension and the Fueter-Sce theorem. The Fueter-Sce theorem outlines a two-step process for constructing axially monogenic functions in $ \mathbb{R}^{m+1}$ starting from holomorphic functions in one complex variable. The first step generates the class of slice monogenic functions, while the second step produces axially monogenic functions by applying the pointwise differential operator $ \Delta_{\mathbb{R}{^{m+1}}}^{\frac{m-1}{2}} $ with $m$ being odd, known as the Fueter-Sce map, to a slice monogenic function.
  By suitably factorizing the Fueter-Sce map, we introduce the set of axially harmonic functions, which serves as an intermediate class between slice monogenic and axially monogenic functions. In this paper, we establish a connection between the harmonic CK extension and the factorization of the Fueter-Sce map. This connection leads to a new notion of harmonic polynomials, which we show to form a basis for the Riesz potential. Finally, we also construct a basis for the space of axially harmonic functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12265v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonino De Martino, Ali Guzm\'an Ad\'an</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the extension and kernels of signed bimeasures and their role in stochastic integration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.10657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2009.10657v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work we provide a necessary and sufficient condition for the extension of signed bimeasures on $\delta$-rings and for the existence of relative kernels. This result generalises the construction method of regular conditional probabilities to the more general setting of extended signed measures. Building on this result, we obtain the most general theory of stochastic integrals based on random measures, thus extending and generalising the whole integration theory developed in the celebrated Rajput and Rosinski's paper (\textit{Probab.~Theory Relat.~Fields}, \textbf{82} (1989) 451-487) and the recent results by Passeggeri (\textit{Stoch.~Process.~Their Appl.}, \textbf{130}, (3), (2020), 1735-1791).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2009.10657v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riccardo Passeggeri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structured pseudospectrum and structured condition pseudospectrum of non-archimedean matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.10365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.10365v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, the structured pseudospectrum of non-archimedean matrices and structured pseudospectrum of non-archimedean matrix pencils are introduced. Many results are proved about them and we give a few examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.10365v3</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jawad Ettayb</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Score-based Diffusion Models in Function Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.07400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.07400v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Diffusion models have recently emerged as a powerful framework for generative modeling. They consist of a forward process that perturbs input data with Gaussian white noise and a reverse process that learns a score function to generate samples by denoising. Despite their tremendous success, they are mostly formulated on finite-dimensional spaces, e.g., Euclidean, limiting their applications to many domains where the data has a functional form, such as in scientific computing and 3D geometric data analysis. This work introduces a mathematically rigorous framework called Denoising Diffusion Operators (DDOs) for training diffusion models in function space. In DDOs, the forward process perturbs input functions gradually using a Gaussian process. The generative process is formulated by a function-valued annealed Langevin dynamic. Our approach requires an appropriate notion of the score for the perturbed data distribution, which we obtain by generalizing denoising score matching to function spaces that can be infinite-dimensional. We show that the corresponding discretized algorithm generates accurate samples at a fixed cost independent of the data resolution. We theoretically and numerically verify the applicability of our approach on a set of function-valued problems, including generating solutions to the Navier-Stokes equation viewed as the push-forward distribution of forcings from a Gaussian Random Field (GRF), as well as volcano InSAR and MNIST-SDF.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.07400v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jae Hyun Lim, Nikola B. Kovachki, Ricardo Baptista, Christopher Beckham, Kamyar Azizzadenesheli, Jean Kossaifi, Vikram Voleti, Jiaming Song, Karsten Kreis, Jan Kautz, Christopher Pal, Arash Vahdat, Anima Anandkumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The weak (1,1) boundedness of Fourier integral operators with complex phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.09054</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.09054v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $T$ be a Fourier integral operator of order $-(n-1)/2$ associated with a canonical relation locally parametrised by a real-phase function. A fundamental result due to Seeger, Sogge, and Stein proved in the 90's, gives the boundedness of $T$ from the Hardy space $H^1$ into $L^1.$ Additionally, it was shown by T. Tao the weak (1,1) type of $T$. In this work, we establish the weak (1,1) boundedness of a Fourier integral operator $T$ of order $-(n-1)/2$ when it has associated a canonical relation parametrised by a complex phase function. This result in the complex-valued setting, cannot be derived from its counterpart in the real-valued case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.09054v4</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Duv\'an Cardona, Michael Ruzhansky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Almost sharp variational estimates for discrete truncated operators of Carleson type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09564v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We establish $r$-variational estimates for discrete truncated Carleson-type operators on $\ell^p$ for $1&lt;p&lt;\infty$. Notably, these estimates are sharp and enhance the results obtained by Krause and Roos (J. Eur. Math. Soc. 2022, J. Funct. Anal. 2023), up to a logarithmic loss related to the scale. On the other hand, as $r$ approaches infinity, the consequences align with the estimates proved by Krause and Roos. Moreover, for the case of quadratic phases, we remove this logarithmic loss with respect to the scale, at the cost of increasing $p$ slightly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09564v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiecheng Chen, Renhui Wan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
