<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.FA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA</link>
    <description>math.FA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 05:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Ramanujan sums in signal recovery and uncertainty principle inequalities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.16190v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper explores the perfect reconstruction property of filter banks based on Ramanujan sums and their applications in signal recovery. Originally introduced by Srinivasa Ramanujan, Ramanujan sums serve as powerful tools for extracting periodic components from signals and form the foundation of Ramanujan filter banks. We investigate the perfect reconstruction property of these filter banks and analyze their robustness against erasures for discrete-time signals in a finite-dimensional space $\mathbb C^N$ . The study is further extended to non-uniform Ramanujan filter banks, showcasing their ability to address the limitations of uniform ones. Employing the reconstruction properties of uniform Ramanujan filter banks, we present an uncertainty principle associated with a tight frame of shifts of Ramanujan sums. This principle establishes representation inequalities in terms of Euler's totient function that provide sufficient conditions for the perfect recovery of signals in scenarios where signal information is lost during transmission or corrupted by noise. Finally, we illustrate that utilizing the signal's periodicity information through Ramanujan filter banks significantly improves the efficiency of signal recovery optimization algorithms, resulting in enhanced signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) gains and more precise reconstruction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.16190v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sahil Kalra, Niraj K. Shukla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on the strict sigularity of the inclusion between Nakano sequence spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.16633v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We characterize the strictly singular inclusions $\ell_{p_n}\hookrightarrow\ell_{q_n}$ between Nakano sequence spaces providing a useful criterion, namely $\varliminf_{n\rightarrow\infty}\vert p_n-q_n\vert&gt;0$ (also recently obtained by Lang and Nekvinda in [12] with a different proof). It is also noted that no inclusion operator between Nakano sequence spaces is compact, neither $L$-weakly compact nor $M$-weakly compact. An easy criterion is given for the weak compactness of the inclusion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.16633v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mauro Sanchiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropy Stability and Spectral Concentration under Convex Block Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.16192v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate entropy minimization problems for quantum states subject to convex block-diagonal constraints. Our principal result is a quantitative stability theorem: if a state has entropy within epsilon of the minimum possible value under a fixed block constraint, then it must lie within O(epsilon^{1/2}) in trace norm of the manifold of entropy minimizers. We show that this rate is optimal. The analysis is entirely finite-dimensional and relies on a precise decomposition of entropy into classical and internal components, together with sharp relative entropy inequalities. As an application, we study finite additive operators whose spectral decomposition induces natural block constraints. In this setting, the stability theorem yields quantitative non-concentration bounds for induced spectral measures. The framework is abstract and independent of arithmetic input. It provides a general stability principle for entropy minimizers under linear spectral constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.16192v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hassan Nasreddine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fields of Toeplitz algebras for the principal symbol of regular 2-step nilpotent groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16475</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.16475v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that the C*-algebra of a regular 2-step nilpotent lie group can be recovered using continuous fields of Toeplitz algebras and a crossed product. We generalize this result to polycontact manifolds in the sense of van Erp which are endowed with fields of such groups. We also investigate those manifolds with a more rigid structure, namely those modeled on H-type groups. In all those cases, there is a certain pseudodifferential calculus named filtered calculus, we show that the algebra of principal symbols can also be recovered from the field of Toeplitz algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.16475v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cl\'ement Cren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Fourier Ratio: Uncertainty, Restriction, and Approximation for Compactly Supported Measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.16751v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a continuous analog of the Fourier ratio for compactly supported Borel measures. For a measure \(\mu\) on \(\mathbb{R}^d\) and \(f\in L^2(\mu)\), the Fourier ratio compares \(L^1\) and \(L^2\) norms of a regularized Fourier transform at scale \(R\). We develop a fractal uncertainty principle giving sharp two-sided bounds in terms of covering numbers of spatial and frequency supports, with applications to exact signal recovery. We show that small Fourier ratio implies efficient approximation by low-degree trigonometric polynomials in \(L^1\), \(L^2\), and \(L^\infty\). In contrast, restriction estimates reveal a sharp gap between curved measures and random fractal measures, yielding strong lower bounds on approximation degree. Applications to convex surface measures are also obtained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.16751v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Iosevich, Z. Li, E. Palsson, A. Yavicoli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Some Transformations Associated to a Certain Cone</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16840</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.16840v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A model elliptic pseudo-differential equation in $4$-faced cone is studied in Sobolev--Slobodetskii space. The Bochner kernel for such a cone is evaluated and explicit formula for unique solution to the considered equation is presented under certain restrictions on the symbol. Boundary value problem with additional integral condition is considered and unique solvability to the boundary value problem is proved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.16840v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Vasilyev, Denis Tokarev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Free dilations of families of $\mathcal{C}_{0}$-semigroups and applications to evolution families</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16314v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Commuting families of contractions or contractive $\mathcal{C}_{0}$-semigroups on Hilbert spaces often fail to admit power dilations resp, simultaneous unitary dilations which are themselves commutative (see [45, 13, 15]). In the \emph{non-commutative} setting, Sz.-Nagy [60] and Bo\.{z}ejko [5] provided means to dilate arbitrary families of contractions. The present work extends these discrete-time results to families $\{T_{i}\}_{i \in I}$ of contractive $\mathcal{C}_{0}$-semigroups. We refer to these dilations as continuous-time \emph{free unitary dilations} and present three distinct approaches to obtain them: 1) An explicit derivation applicable to semigroups that arise as interpolations; 2) A full proof with an explicit construction, via the theory of co-generators \`{a} la S{\l}oci\'{n}ski [54, 55]; and 3) A second full proof based on the abstract structure of semigroups, which admits a natural reformulation to semigroups defined over topological free products of $\mathbb{R}_{\geq 0}$ and leads to various residuality results. In 2) a IInd free dilation theorem for topologised index sets is developed via a reformulation of the Trotter--Kato theorem for co-generators. As an application of this we demonstrate how evolution families can be reduced to continuously monitored processes subject to temporal change, \'{a} la the quantum Zeno effect [22, 23, 24, 30, 37].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16314v5</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raj Dahya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lower-Order Refinements of Greedy Approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05533</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.05533v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For two countable ordinals $\alpha$ and $\beta$, a basis of a Banach space $X$ is said to be $(\alpha, \beta)$-quasi-greedy if it is
  1) quasi-greedy,
  2) $\mathcal{S}_\alpha$-unconditional but not $\mathcal{S}_{\alpha+1}$-unconditional, and
  3) $\mathcal{S}_\beta$-democratic but not $\mathcal{S}_{\beta+1}$-democratic.
  If $\alpha$ or $\beta$ is replaced with $\infty$, then the basis is required to be unconditonal or democratic, respectively. Previous work constructed a $(0,0)$-quasi-greedy basis, an $(\alpha, \infty)$-quasi-greedy basis, and an $(\infty, \alpha)$-quasi-greedy basis. In this paper, we construct $(\alpha, \beta)$-quasi-greedy bases for $\beta\le \alpha+1$ (except the already solved case $\alpha = \beta = 0$).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.05533v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Beanland, Hung Viet Chu, Thomas Schlumprecht, Andr\'as Zs\'ak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A solution to Banach conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04628v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we begin by constructing an ellipsoid derived from the John ellipsoid of the sections. We then use this framework to present a full proof of Banach's isometric subspace problem in finite-dimensional spaces via the John ellipsoid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04628v5</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ning Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anisotropic spaces for the bilateral shift</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.15050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.15050v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Given two H\"older potentials $\phi_+$ and $\psi_-$ for the unilateral shift, we define anisotropic Banach spaces of distributions on the bilateral shift space with a finite alphabet. On these spaces, the transfer operator for the bilateral shift is quasicompact with a spectral gap, and the unique Gibbs state associated with $\phi_+$ spans its $1$-eigenspace. This result allows us to establish exponential decay of correlations for H\"older observables and a wide range of measures on the bilateral shift space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.15050v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mateus Marra, Daniel Smania</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous symmetry entails the Jordan algebra structure of finite-dimensional quantum theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19672v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Symmetry postulates play a crucial role in various approaches to reconstruct quantum theory from a few basic principles. Discrete and continuous symmetries are under consideration. The continuous case better matches the physical needs for mathematical models of dynamical processes and is studied here. Applying the representation theory of the orthomodular lattices and a generalized version of Gleason's theorem for Jordan matrix algebras, we show that the continuous symmetry, together with three further requirements, entails that the underlying mathematical structure of a finite-dimensional generalized probabilistic theory becomes a simple Euclidean Jordan algebra. The further requirements are: spectrality, a strong state space and a condition called gbit property.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19672v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gerd Niestegge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Folded optimal transport and its application to separable quantum optimal transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01722v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce folded optimal transport, as a way of extending a cost or distance defined on the extreme boundary of a convex to the whole convex, related to convex extension. This construction broadens the framework of standard optimal transport, found to be the particular case of the convex being a simplex. Relying on Choquet theory and standard optimal transport, we introduce the so-called folded Kantorovich cost and folded Wasserstein distance, and study the metric properties it provides to the convex. We then apply the construction to the quantum setting, and obtain an actual separable quantum Wasserstein distance on the set of density matrices from a distance on the set of pure states, closely related to the semi-distance of Beatty and Stilck-Franca [4], and of which we obtain a variety of properties. We also find that the semiclassical Golse-Paul [16] cost writes as a folded Kantorovich cost. Folded optimal transport therefore provides a unified framework for classical, semiclassical and separable quantum optimal transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01722v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Borsoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
