<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.FA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA</link>
    <description>math.FA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 02:19:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics for affine composition operators on weighted Bergman space of a half plane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15822</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.15822v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article, we completely characterize the positive expansive and absolutely Ces\`aro composition operators $C_{\phi}f=f\circ \phi$ induced by affine self-maps $\phi$ of the right half-plane $\mathbb{C}_+$ on the weighted Bergman space $\mathcal{A}^2_{\alpha}(\mathbb{C}_+)$. Furthermore, we characterize which of these operators have the positive shadowing property.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.15822v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Artur Blois, Osmar R. Severiano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weighted superposition operators on Fock spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16152</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16152v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We characterize
  all pairs of entire functions $(u,\psi)$ for which the induced weighted superposition operator $S_{(u,\psi)}$ transforms one Fock space into another Fock space.Further analytical structures like boundedness and Lipschitz continuity of $S_{(u,\psi)}$ are described. We, in particular, show the Fock spaces
  support no compact weighted superposition operator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16152v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s13398-022-01216-6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Rev. Real Acad. Cienc. Exactas Fis. Nat. Ser. A-Mat. (2022)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tesfa Mengestie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On exact diagrams and strict morphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16585</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16585v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Necessary and sufficient conditions for the exactness (in the algebraic sense) of certain sequences of continuous group homomorphisms are established.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16585v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dinam\'erico P. Pombo Jr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Determinant formulas for finite Toeplitz plus Hankel matrices with rational symbols</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16613</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16613v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 1975 K. Michael Day produced an exact formula for the determinants of finite Toeplitz matrices whose symbols are rational. The answer is a sum that involves powers of the roots of the numerator of the symbol and whose coefficients depend on both the roots of the numerator and denominator. In this paper we prove an analogue of Day's formula for determinants of finite Toeplitz plus Hankel matrices with rational symbols. The key to the proof is an exact formula for the finite determinants that involves a Fredholm determinant that can be explicitly computed. We apply the formula to find information about the limiting eigenvalues of the finite Toeplitz plus Hankel matrices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16613v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Estelle Basor, Kent E. Morrison</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the relation between distances and seminorms on Fr\'echet spaces, with application to isometries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16801v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A study is made of linear isometries on Fr\'echet spaces for which the metric is given in terms of a sequence of seminorms. This establishes sufficient conditions on the growth of the function that defines the metric in terms of the seminorms to ensure that a linear operator preserving the metric also preserves each of these seminorms. As an application, characterizations are given of the isometries on various spaces including those of holomorphic functions on complex domains and continuous functions on open sets, extending the Banach--Stone theorem to surjective and nonsurjective cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16801v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Isabelle Chalendar, Lucas Oger, Jonathan R. Partington</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Refined uncertainty relation for q-commutator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16850v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that Robertson uncertainty relation can be refined for q-commutator which is defined by $[A,B]_q = AB-qBA$, where $A, B$ are self-adjoint operators and real number $q\in \mathbb{R}$. The coefficient is represented by the eigenvalues of state $\rho$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16850v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kenjiro Yanagi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounded variation separates weak and strong average Lipschitz</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16930</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16930v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We closely examine a notion of average smoothness recently introduced by Ashlagi et al. (JMLR, 2024). The latter defined a {\em weak} and {\em strong} average-Lipschitz seminorm for real-valued functions on general metric spaces. Specializing to the standard metric on the real line, we compare these notions to bounded variation (BV) and discover that the weak notion is strictly weaker than BV while the strong notion strictly stronger. Along the way, we discover that the weak average smooth class is also considerably larger in a certain combinatorial sense, made precise by the fat-shattering dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16930v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ariel Elperin, Aryeh Kontorovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Concavity principles for weighted marginals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16941</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16941v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a general framework to study concavity properties of weighted marginals of $\beta$-concave functions on $\mathbb{R}^n$ via local methods. As a concrete implementation of our approach, we obtain a functional version of the dimensional Brunn-Minkowski inequality for rotationally invariant log-concave measures. Moreover, we derive a Pr\'ekopa-type concavity principle with rotationally invariant weights for even log-concave functions which encompasses the B-inequality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16941v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dario Cordero-Erausquin, Alexandros Eskenazis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Almost everywhere convergence of Bochner-Riesz means for the Hermite type Laguerre expansions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16958v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Consider the space $\mathbb{R}_+^d=(0,\infty)^d$ equipped with Euclidean distance and the Lebesgue measure. For every $\alpha=(\alpha_1,...,\alpha_d)\in[-1/2,\infty)^d$, we consider the Hermite-Laguerre operator $\mathcal{L}^\alpha=-\Delta+\arrowvert x\arrowvert^2+\sum_{i=1}^{d}(\alpha_j^2-\frac{1}{4})\frac{1}{x_i^2}$. In this paper we study almost everywhere convergence of the Bochner-Riesz means associated with $\mathcal{L}^\alpha$ which is defined as $S_R^{\lambda}(\mathcal{L}^\alpha)f(x)=\sum_{n=0}^{\infty}(1-\frac{4n+2\arrowvert\alpha\arrowvert_1+2d}{R^2})_{+}^{\lambda}\mathcal{P}_nf(x)$. Here $\mathcal{P}_nf(x)$ is the n-th Laguerre spectral projection operator and $\arrowvert\alpha\arrowvert_1$ denotes $\sum_{i=1}^{d}\alpha_i$. For $2\leq p&lt;\infty$, we prove that
  \[
  \lim_{R \to \infty} S_R^{\lambda}(\mathcal{L}^\alpha)f = f \quad \text{a.e.}
  \]
  for all $f\in L^p({\mathbb{R}_+^d})$ provided that $\lambda&gt;\lambda(p)/2$ and $\lambda(p)=\max\{d(1/2-1/p)-1/2,0\}$. Conversely, we show that the convergence generally fails if $\lambda&lt;\lambda(p)/2$ in the sense that there exists $f\in L^p({\mathbb{R}_+^d})$ for $2d/(d-1)&lt; p$ such that the convergence fails.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16958v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Longben Wei, Zhiwen Duan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mass Functions and Asymptotic Behavior of Caloric Functions on Affine Buildings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17042</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.17042v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the large-time asymptotic behavior of solutions to the discrete-time heat equation, i.e., caloric functions, on affine buildings, including those without transitive group actions. For each $p \in [1, \infty]$, we introduce a notion of a $p$-mass function and prove that caloric functions with initial data belonging to certain weighted-$\ell^1$ spaces or to the radial $\ell^1$ class, asymptotically decouple as the product of this mass function and the heat kernel. These results extend classical analogues from Euclidean spaces and symmetric spaces of non-compact type to the non-Archimedean setting, and remain valid even for exotic buildings beyond the Bruhat--Tits framework. We characterize the spatial concentration of heat kernels in $p$-norms and describe the geometry of associated critical regions. Our results highlight substantial differences in the asymptotic regimes depending on the value of $p$, and clarify the interplay between volume growth and heat diffusion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.17042v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Effie Papageorgiou, Bartosz Trojan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bjork-DEbrowere algebras topologies and comparison of regularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17054</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.17054v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we investigate properties of the family of weight functions and especiallyin the "weight function" model. We etablish in theintroduced algebra topological sharp structures analogous tothe ones introduced in Colombeau algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.17054v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anatole Khelif, Dimitris Scarpalezos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher reflections and entropy of canonical shifts for inclusions of $C^*$-algebras with finite Watatani index</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16130</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16130v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given a unital inclusion of simple $C^*$-algebras equipped with a conditional expectation of index-finite type, we study higher Fourier transforms and rotation operators and introduce the reflection operators on the relative commutants. We prove that the reflections are unital, involutive, $*$-preserving anti-homomorphisms that preserve certain Markov-type traces. As an application, we prove Fourier theoretic inequalities on the higher relative commutants and improve the existing constant in the Young's inequality found in the literature. By employing the reflection operators, we define a canonical shift on the von Neumann algebra generated by the relative commutants. We establish a connection between the Connes-St{\o}rmer entropy of the canonical shift and the minimal Watatani index.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16130v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keshab Chandra Bakshi, Satyajit Guin, Biplab Pal,  Sruthymurali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heterotopic energy for Sobolev mappings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16204</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16204v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the notion of heterotopic energy defined as the limit of Sobolev energies of Sobolev mappings in a given homotopy class approximating almost everywhere a given Sobolev mapping. We show that the heterotopic energy is finite if and only if the mappings in the corresponding homotopy classes are homotopic on a codimension one skeleton of a triangulation of the domain. When this is the case, the heterotopic energy of a mapping is the sum of its Sobolev energy and its disparity energy, defined as the minimum energy of a bubble to pass between these homotopy classes. At the more technical level, we rely on a framework that works when the target and domain manifolds are not simply connected and there is no canonical isomorphism between homotopy groups with different basepoints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16204v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antoine Detaille, Jean Van Schaftingen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Making Non-Negative Polynomials into Sums of Squares</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16321v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate linear operators $A:\mathbb{R}[x_1,\dots,x_n]\to\mathbb{R}[x_1,\dots,x_n]$. We give explicit operators $A$ such that, for fixed $d\in\mathbb{N}_0$ and closed $K\subseteq\mathbb{R}^n$, $e^A\mathrm{Pos}(K)_{\leq 2d}\subseteq\sum\mathbb{R}[x_1,\dots,x_n]_{\leq d}^2$. We give an explicit operator $A$ such that $e^A\mathrm{Pos}(\mathbb{R}^n)\subseteq\sum\mathbb{R}[x_1,\dots,x_n]^2$. For $K\subseteq\mathbb{R}^n$, we give a condition such that $A$ exists with $e^A\mathrm{Pos}(K)\subseteq\sum\mathbb{R}[x_1,\dots,x_n]^2$. In the framework of regular Fr\'echet Lie groups and Lie algebras we investigate the linear operators $A$ such that $e^{tA}:\mathbb{R}[x_1,\dots,x_n]\to\mathbb{R}[x_1,\dots,x_n]$ is well-defined for all $t\in\mathbb{R}$. We give a three-line-proof of Stochel's Theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16321v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philipp J. di Dio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Output Regulation for Impedance Passive Systems with Input Saturation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16365v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider output tracking and disturbance rejection for abstract infinite-dimensional systems with input saturation. We solve the control problem using a control law which consists of a stabilising error feedback term and a feedforward term based on the reference and disturbance signals. We use our results to design control laws for output tracking and disturbance rejection for a two-dimensional heat equation and a one-dimensional wave equation with boundary control and observation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16365v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thavamani Govindaraj, Lassi Paunonen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence Result for Singular Second Order Dynamic Equations with Mixed Boundary Conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16505</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16505v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explore singular second-order boundary value problems with mixed boundary conditions on a general time scale. Using the lower and upper solutions method combined with the Brouwer fixed point theorem we demonstrate the existence of a positive solution and obtain the desired solution by using a sequence of solutions to a sequence of nonsingular second-order equations and passing to the limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16505v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shalmali Bandyopadhyay, Curtis J Kunkel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Upper and Lower Solution Method for Regular Discrete Second-Order Single-Variable BVPs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16526v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates the existence of positive solutions for regular discrete second-order single-variable boundary value problems with mixed boundary conditions, including a nonhomogeneous Dirichlet boundary condition, of the form: \begin{equation*} u^{\Delta \Delta}(t-1)+h(t,\ u(t),\ u^{\Delta}(t-1))=0 \mbox{ for }t\in[1,\ T+1];~u^{\Delta}(0)=0;~u(T+2)=g(T+2) \end{equation*} where h is continuous on $[1, T + 1] \times \mathbb{R}^2$ and $g: [0, T + 2] \to \mathbb{R}^+$ is continuous. Using the concept of upper and lower solutions, we establish conditions under which the boundary value problem admits at least one positive solution. Our approach involves constructing an auxiliary problem with a modified nonlinearity and applying Brouwer Fixed Point Theorem to a carefully defined solution operator. We prove that any solution to this auxiliary problem that remains within the bounds of the upper and lower solutions is equivalent to a solution of the original problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16526v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shalmali Bandyopadhyay, Kyle Byassee, Curt Lynch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the rate of convergence of $\mathbb{R}^d$-ergodic averages constructed over a strictly convex set</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16740v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For $\mathbb{R}^d$-ergodic means constructed over a strictly convex set, a spectral criterion for homogeneous rates of convergence is obtained. From Hertz's result on the asymptotics of the Fourier transform of the indicator of a strictly convex set, it follows that the rate of convergence does not depend on the specific form of such a set.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16740v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ivan Podvigin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizations of Matrix Valued Asymmetric Truncated Toeplitz Operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2103.15719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2103.15719v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We characterize matrix-valued asymmetric truncated Toeplitz operators (which are compressions of multiplication operators acting between two possibly different model spaces) by using compressed shifts, modified compressed shifts and shift invariance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2103.15719v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rewayat Khan, Yagoub Ameur, Jamroz Khan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond $BV$: new pairings and Gauss-Green formulas for measure fields with divergence measure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.18730</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.18730v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A new notion of pairing between measure vector fields with divergence measure and scalar functions, which are not required to be weakly differentiable, is introduced. In particular, in the case of essentially bounded divergence-measure fields, the functions may not be of bounded variation. This naturally leads to the definition of $BV$-like function classes on which these pairings are well defined. Despite the lack of fine properties for such functions, our pairings surprisingly preserve many features of the recently introduced $\lambda$-pairings (Crasta, De Cicco, Malusa 2022, arXiv:1902.06052), as coarea formula, lower semicontinuity, Leibniz rules, and Gauss-Green formulas. Moreover, in a natural way new anisotropic "degenerate" perimeters are defined, possibly allowing for sets with fractal boundary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.18730v5</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Eugenio Comi, Virginia De Cicco, Giovanni Scilla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The polynomial cluster value problem for Banach spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.16371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.16371v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We reduce the polynomial cluster value problem for the algebra of bounded analytic functions, $H^{\infty}$, on the ball of Banach spaces $X$ to the same polynomial cluster value problem for $H^{\infty}$ but on the ball of those spaces which are $\ell_1$-sums of finite dimensional spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.16371v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sofia Ortega Castillo, Isidro Humberto Munive Lima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Second-order linear switching systems with arbitrary control sets: stability and invariant norms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07861</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07861v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that the stability problem and the problem of constructing Barabanov norms can be resolved for planar linear switching systems in an explicit form. This can be done for every compact control set of $2 \times 2$ matrices. If the control set does not contain a dominant matrix with a real spectrum, then the invariant norm is always unique (up to a multiplier) and belongs to~$C^1$. Otherwise, there may be infinitely many such norms, including non-smooth ones. All of them can be found and classified. In particular, every symmetric convex body is a unit ball of the Barabanov norm of a suitable linear switching system. Several examples of control sets such as matrix Frobenius balls and matrix polyhedra are analysed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07861v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Yu. Protasov, Asiiat Musaeva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new systems theory perspective on canonical Wiener-Hopf factorization on the unit circle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17324</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17324v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish left and right canonical factorizations of Hilbert-space operator-valued functions G(z) that are analytic on neighborhoods of the complex unit circle and the origin 0, and that have the form G(z)=I+F(z) with F(z) taking strictly contractive values on the unit circle. Such functions can be realized as transfer functions of infinite dimensional dichotomous discrete-time linear systems, and we employ the strict bounded real lemma for this class of operators, together with associated Krein space theory, to derive explicit formulas for the left and right canonical factorizations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17324v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanne ter Horst, Mikael Kurula, Andr\'e Ran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On p-summability in weighted Banach spaces of holomorphic functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15863</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15863v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given an open subset $U$ of a complex Banach space $E$, a weight $v$ on $U$, and a complex Banach space $F$, let $\mathcal{H}^\infty_v(U,F)$ denote the Banach space of all weighted holomorphic mappings $f\colon U\to F$, under the weighted supremum norm $\left\|f\right\|_v:=\sup\left\{v(x)\left\|f(x)\right\|\colon x\in U\right\}$. In this paper, we introduce and study the class $\Pi_p^{\mathcal{H}^\infty_v}(U,F)$ of $p$-summing weighted holomorphic mappings. We prove that it is an injective Banach ideal of weighted holomorphic mappings which is not generated by composition. Variants for weighted holomorphic mappings of Pietsch Domination Theorem, Pietsch Factorization Theorem and Maurey Extrapolation Theorem are presented. We also identify the spaces of $p$-summing weighted holomorphic mappings from $U$ into $F^*$ under the norm $\pi^{\mathcal{H}^\infty_v}_p$ with the duals of $F$-valued $\mathcal{H}^\infty_v$-molecules on $U$ under a suitable version $d^{\mathcal{H}^\infty_v}_{p^*}$ of the Chevet--Saphar tensor norms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15863v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. G. Cabrera-Padilla, A. Jim\'enez-Vargas, A. Keten \c{C}opur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matrix systems, algebras, and open maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01761</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01761v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Every state on the algebra $M_n$ of complex nxn matrices restricts to a state on any matrix system. Whereas the restriction to a matrix system is generally not open, we prove that the restriction to every *-subalgebra of $M_n$ is open. This simplifies topology problems in matrix theory and quantum information theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01761v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s43036-025-00448-8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Advances in Operator Theory 10:3, 62, 2025; Special issue for Ilya M. Spitkovsky on his 70th birthday</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Stephan Weis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The isoperimetric inequality for partial sums of Toeplitz eigenvalues in the Fock space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07069v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that, among all subsets $\Omega\subset \mathbb{C}$ having circular symmetry and prescribed measure, the ball is the only maximizer of the sum of the first $K$ eigenvalues ($K\geq 1$) of the corresponding Toeplitz operator $T_\Omega$ on the Fock space $\mathcal{F}$. As a byproduct, we prove that balls maximize any Schatten $p$-norm of $T_\Omega$ for $p&gt;1$ (and minimize the corresponding quasinorm for $p&lt;1$), and that the second eigenvalue is maximized by a particular annulus. Moreover, we extend some of these results to general radial symbols in $L^p(\mathbb{C})$, with $p &gt; 1$, characterizing those that maximize the sum of the first $K$ eigenvalues. We also show a symmetry breaking phenomenon for the second eigenvalue, when the assumption of circular symmetry is dropped.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07069v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabio Nicola, Federico Riccardi, Paolo Tilli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equivalence of Absolute Continuity and Apostol's Condition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14256</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14256v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Absolute continuity of polynomially bounded $n$-tuples of commuting contractions is studied. A necessary and sufficient condition is found in Constantin Apostol's "weakened $C_{0,\cdot}$ assumption", asserting the convergence to 0 of the powers of each operator in a specific topology. Kosiek with Octavio considered tuples of Hilbert space contractions satisfying the von-Neumann Inequality. We extend their results to a wider class of tuples, where there may be no unitary dilation and the bounding constant may be greater than 1. This proof also applies to Banach space contractions and uses decompositions of A-measures with respect to bands of measures related to Gleason parts of the polydisc algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14256v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Foks</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Karhunen-Lo\`eve expansion of Random Measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.14202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2203.14202v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present an orthogonal expansion for real, function-regulated, second-order random measures over $\mathbb{R}^{d}$ with measure covariance. Such a expansion, which can be seen as a Karhunen-Lo\`eve decomposition, consists in a series of deterministic real measures weighted by uncorrelated real random variables with the variances forming a convergent series. The convergence of the series is in a mean-square sense stochastically and against measurable bounded test functions (with compact support if the random measure is not finite) in the measure sense, which implies set-wise convergence. This is proven taking advantage of the extra requirement of having a covariance measure over $\mathbb{R}^{d}\times\mathbb{R}^{d}$ describing the covariance structure of the random measure, for which we also provide a series expansion. These results cover for instance the cases of Gaussian White Noise, Poisson and Cox point processes, and can be used to obtain expansions for trawl processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2203.14202v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ricardo Carrizo Vergara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of simplex slicing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11994</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11994v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We establish dimension-free stability of Webb's sharp simplex slicing (1996). Incidentally, we investigate Lipschitzness of volume of hyperplane central sections of arbitrary (not necessarily symmetric) convex bodies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11994v3</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Serhii Myroshnychenko, Colin Tang, Kateryna Tatarko, Tomasz Tkocz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stable Learning Using Spiking Neural Networks Equipped With Affine Encoders and Decoders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04549v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the learning problem associated with spiking neural networks. Specifically, we focus on spiking neural networks composed of simple spiking neurons having only positive synaptic weights, equipped with an affine encoder and decoder; we refer to these as affine spiking neural networks. These neural networks are shown to depend continuously on their parameters, which facilitates classical covering number-based generalization statements and supports stable gradient-based training. We demonstrate that the positivity of the weights enables a wide range of expressivity results, including rate-optimal approximation of smooth functions and dimension-independent approximation of Barron regular functions. In particular, we show in theory and simulations that affine spiking neural networks are capable of approximating shallow ReLU neural networks. Furthermore, we apply these affine spiking neural networks to standard machine learning benchmarks and reach competitive results. Finally, we observe that from a generalization perspective, contrary to feedforward neural networks or previous results for general spiking neural networks, the depth has little to no adverse effect on the generalization capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04549v3</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Martina Neuman, Dominik Dold, Philipp Christian Petersen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum algorithms for matrix geometric means</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00673</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00673v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Matrix geometric means between two positive definite matrices can be defined from distinct perspectives - as solutions to certain nonlinear systems of equations, as points along geodesics in Riemannian geometry, and as solutions to certain optimisation problems. We devise quantum subroutines for the matrix geometric means, and construct solutions to the algebraic Riccati equation - an important class of nonlinear systems of equations appearing in machine learning, optimal control, estimation, and filtering. Using these subroutines, we present a new class of quantum learning algorithms, for both classical and quantum data, called quantum geometric mean metric learning, for weakly supervised learning and anomaly detection. The subroutines are also useful for estimating geometric R\'enyi relative entropies and the Uhlmann fidelity, in particular achieving optimal dependence on precision for the Uhlmann and Matsumoto fidelities. Finally, we provide a BQP-complete problem based on matrix geometric means that can be solved by our subroutines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00673v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41534-025-00973-7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>npj Quantum Information, Vol. 11, No. 101, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nana Liu, Qisheng Wang, Mark M. Wilde, Zhicheng Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automorphisms of subalgebras of bounded analytic functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03245</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03245v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $H^\infty$ denote the algebra of all bounded analytic functions on the unit disk. It is well-known that every (algebra) automorphism of $H^\infty$ is a composition operator induced by disc automorphism. Maurya et al., (J. Math. Anal. Appl. 530 : Paper No: 127698, 2024) proved that every automorphism of the subalgebras $\{f\in H^\infty : f(0) = 0\}$ or $\{f\in H^\infty : f'(0) = 0\}$ is a composition operator induced by a rotation. In this article, we give very simple proof of their results. As an interesting generalization, for any $\psi\in H^\infty$, we show that every automorphism of $\psi H^\infty$ must be a composition operator and characterize all such composition operators. Using this characterization, we find all automorphism of $\psi H^\infty$ for few choices of $\psi$ with various nature depending on its zeros.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03245v2</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jmaa.2025.129804</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Published in Journal of Mathematical Analysis and Applications in 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kanha Behera, Rahul Maurya, P. Muthukumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kantorovich duality for optimal transport on completely regular Hausdorff spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03929v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a new intermediate optimization problem situated between Kantorovich's primal and dual formulations. This new problem extends Kantorovich's duality to separable Baire measures, which are strictly more general than tight (or Radon) measures in completely regular Hausdorff spaces. In the special case where the measures are Radon, our intermediate problem aligns with the classical Kantorovich's primal problem. Existence of solutions for all three formulations are also provided within this comprehensive framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03929v3</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammed Bachir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete signature tensors for persistence landscapes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02800v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Signature tensors of paths are a versatile tool for data analysis and machine learning. Recently, they have been applied to persistent homology, by embedding barcodes into spaces of paths. Among the different path embeddings, the persistence landscape embedding is injective and stable, however it loses injectivity when composed with the signature map. Here we address this by proposing a discrete alternative. The critical points of a persistence landscape form a time-series, of which we compute the discrete signature. We call this association the discrete landscape feature map (DLFM). We give results on the injectivity, stability and computability of the DLFM. We apply it to a knotted protein dataset, capturing sequence similarity and knot depth with statistical significance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02800v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincenzo Galgano, Heather A. Harrington, Daniel Tolosa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical restriction for Schr\"odinger equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.12527v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove a dynamical restriction principle, asserting that every restriction estimate satisfied by the Fourier transform in $\mathbb{R}^d$ is also valid for the propagator of certain Schr\"odinger equations. We consider smooth Hamiltonians with an at most quadratic growth, and also a class of nonsmooth Hamiltonians, encompassing potentials that are Fourier transforms of complex (finite) Borel measures. Roughly speaking, if the initial datum belongs to $L^p(\mathbb{R}^d)$, for $p$ in a suitable range of exponents, the solution $u(t,\cdot)$ (for each fixed $t$, with the exception of certain particular values) can be meaningfully restricted to compact curved submanifolds of $\mathbb{R}^d$. The underlying property responsible for this phenomenon is the boundedness of the propagator $L^p\to(\mathcal{F}L^p)_{\rm loc}$, with $1\leq p\leq2$, which is derived from almost diagonalization and dispersive estimates in function spaces defined in terms of wave packet decompositions in phase space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.12527v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabio Nicola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rust Implementation of Finite Element Exterior Calculus on Coordinate-Free Simplicial Complexes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02429v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This thesis presents the development of a novel finite element library in Rust based on the principles of Finite Element Exterior Calculus (FEEC). The library solves partial differential equations formulated using differential forms on abstract, coordinate-free simplicial complexes in arbitrary dimensions, employing an intrinsic Riemannian metric derived from edge lengths via Regge Calculus. We focus on solving elliptic Hodge-Laplace eigenvalue and source problems on the nD de Rham complex. We restrict ourselves to first-order Whitney basis functions. The implementation is partially verified through convergence studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02429v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luis Wirth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical microlocal analysis in two-dimensional X-ray CT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05113v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In many imaging applications it is important to assess how well the edges of the original object, $f$, are resolved in an image, $f^\text{rec}$, reconstructed from the measured data, $g$. In this paper we consider the case of image reconstruction in 2D X-ray Computed Tomography (CT). Let $f$ be a function describing the object being scanned, and $g=Rf + \eta$ be the Radon transform data in $\mathbb{R}^2$ corrupted by noise, $\eta$, and sampled with step size $\sim\epsilon$. Conventional microlocal analysis provides conditions for edge detectability based on the scanner geometry in the case of continuous, noiseless data (when $\eta = 0$), but does not account for noise and finite sampling step size. We develop a novel technique called Statistical Microlocal Analysis (SMA), which uses a statistical hypothesis testing framework to determine if an image edge (singularity) of $f$ is detectable from $f^\text{rec}$, and we quantify edge detectability using the statistical power of the test. Our approach is based on the theory we developed in previous work, which provides a characterization of $f^\text{rec}$ in local $O(\epsilon)$-size neighborhoods when $\eta \neq 0$. We derive a statistical test for the presence and direction of an edge microlocally given the magnitude of $\eta$ and data sampling step size. Using the properties of the null distribution of the test, we quantify the uncertainty of the edge magnitude and direction. We validate our theory using simulations, which show strong agreement between our predictions and experimental observations. Our work is not only of practical value, but of theoretical value as well. SMA is a natural extension of classical microlocal analysis theory which accounts for practical measurement imperfections, such as noise and finite step size, at the highest possible resolution compatible with the data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05113v3</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anuj Abhishek, Alexander Katsevich, James W. Webber</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
