<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.FA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA</link>
    <description>math.FA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 04:00:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Functional Donoho-Elad-Gribonval-Nielsen-Fuchs Sparsity Theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09609</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09609v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Celebrated breakthrough sparsity theorem obtained independently by Donoho and Elad \textit{[Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 2003]} and Gribonval and Nielsen \textit{[IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory, 2003]} and Fuchs \textit{[IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory, 2004]} says that unique sparse solution to NP-Hard $\ell_0$-minimization problem can be obtained using unique solution to P-Type $\ell_1$-minimization problem. In this paper, we extend their result to abstract Banach spaces using 1-approximate Schauder frames. We notice that the `normalized' condition for Hilbert spaces can be generalized to a larger extent when we consider Banach spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09609v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Mahesh Krishna</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete non-abelian X-ray transforms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09611</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09611v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We define a discrete version of the non-abelian X-ray transform, going back in particular to Manakov, Zakharov (1981) and Strichartz (1982). We extend to this transform non-overdetermined reconstruction results obtained for the abelian case in the recent article by Novikov, Sharma (2025). In addition, we establish relations with the continuous non-abelian X-ray transform. In this respect, our results include an explicit and exact non-overdetermined layer-stripping reconstruction procedure for piecewise constant matrix-valued functions from their continuous non-abelian X-ray transform. To our knowledge, this result is new even for the classical X-ray transform.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09611v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pranav Gupta, Roman Novikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Special-Affine Wavelets: Multi-Resolution Analysis and Function Approximation in L^2(R)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09612v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The multiresolution analysis (MRA) associated with the Special affine Fourier transform (SAFT) provides a structured approach for generating orthonormal bases in \( L^2(\mathbb R) \), making it a powerful tool for advanced signal analysis. This work introduces a robust sampling theory and constructs multiresolution structures within the SAFT domain to support the formation of orthonormal bases. Motivated by the need for a sampling theorem applicable to band-limited signals in the SAFT framework, we establish a corresponding theoretical foundation. Furthermore, a method for constructing orthogonal bases in $L^2(\mathbb R)$ is proposed, and the theoretical results are demonstrated through illustrative examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09612v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Waseem Z. Lone, Vikash K. Sahu, Amit K. Verma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Invertibility of Bergman Toeplitz operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09614v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we establish the invertibility of the Berezin transform of the symbol as a necessary and sufficient condition for the invertibility of the Toeplitz operator on the Bergman space $L^2_a(\mathbb{D})$. More precisely, if ${\phi} = c g + d \bar{g}$, where $c,d\in\mathbb{C}$ and $g\in H^{\infty}(\mathbb{D})$, the space of all bounded analytic functions, then $T_{\phi}$ is invertible on $L^2_a(\mathbb{D})$ if and only if $\inf\limits_{z\in \mathbb{D}}\left|\widetilde{\,{\phi}}(z)\right|=\inf\limits_{z\in \mathbb{D}}|\phi(z)|&gt;0$, where $\widetilde{\,{\phi}}$ is the Berezin transform of $\phi$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09614v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mo Javed, Amit Maji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Henstock-Kurzweil Functional Calculus on Self-Adjoint Operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09622v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This dissertation focuses on developing a new construction of a functional calculus using Henstock-Kurzweil integration methods. The assignment of a functional calculus will be applied to self-adjoint operators. We will address both the bounded and unbounded cases, examine the advantage of the underlying function space compared to larger spaces, prove the spectral mapping theorem, and explore one application of this functional calculus in abstract differential equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09622v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marin Matei-Luca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Counter Examples in Non-Archimedean Locally Convex Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09626v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we shall consider some counter examples in non-archimedean locally convex spaces with special closed subspaces and Schauder basis in non-archimedean Fr\'{e}chet spaces as well as closed subspaces \emph{without} Schauder basis in non-archimedean Fr\'{e}chet spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09626v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. E. Egwe, J. A Braimah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Class of Functionals on the Sequence Space $s$ Satisfying the Palais-Smale Condition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10146v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a class of functionals on the space of rapidly decreasing sequences $s$, called $\mathcal{F}_s$-functionals, defined as decomposable sums of quadratic and convex terms with quadratic growth. We prove that such functionals satisfy the Palais-Smale condition and admit a unique global minimum. Furthermore, we show that the Palais-Smale condition is preserved under linear homeomorphisms. This allows us to construct corresponding functionals satisfying the Palais-Smale condition on Fr\'echet spaces isomorphic to $s$. We then show how this framework provides a tool for the proof of existence and uniqueness of solutions for specific operator problems, where coupled infinite-dimensional systems are transformed into diagonalized problems in the space $s$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10146v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaveh Eftekharinasab</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral Properties of the Compact Rhaly and Compact Generalised Ces{\`a}ro Operators on Weighted $c_0$ Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10550v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article, we conduct a comprehensive study on the continuity, compactness, and spectral properties of Rhaly operators and generalized Ces\`aro operators, acting on weighted null sequence spaces. We determine the point spectrum, continuous spectrum, and residual spectrum for compact Rhaly operators and compact generalized Ces\`aro operators. Additionally, we explore Goldberg's classifications of Rhaly operators over weighted null sequence spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10550v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jyoti Rani, Arnab Patra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hardy spaces for the Lam\'e equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10798v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study, for $1 \leq p \leq \infty$, the Hardy space $\bm{h}_e^p(\B)$, the elastic analogue of the classical Hardy spaces of harmonic functions in the unit ball of $\mathbb{R}^3$. The space consists of vector-field solutions of the Lam\'e system satisfying the standard integrability condition on concentric spheres centered at the origin. Using the elastic Poisson kernel, we establish a Fatou-type theorem and show that $\bm{h}_e^p(\B)$ is isomorphic to the $\mathbb{R}^3$-valued Lebesgue space $L^p$ on the unit sphere for $1 &lt; p \leq \infty$, while $\bm{h}_e^1(\B)$ corresponds to the space of $\mathbb{R}^3$-valued Borel measures on the unit sphere.
  For $1 &lt; p &lt; \infty$, we prove that $\bm{h}_e^p(\B)$ decomposes as the direct sum of three subspaces. The main contribution of this paper is to describe each of these subspaces along with the corresponding spaces of boundary values. In particular, two of these spaces consist of solutions of the Lam\'e equation for all eligible choices of the Lam\'e constants: one of them is the space of Riesz fields (solutions of the generalized Cauchy--Riemann equations) in $\bm{h}_e^p(\B)$; the second is the space of fields given by the cross product of $x$ with such Riesz fields. The results rely on the classical decomposition of $L^2$ vector fields on the sphere into the direct sum of three spaces of vector spherical harmonics, which we extend to $L^p$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10798v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan Antonio Barcel\'o, Salvador Per\'ez-Esteva, Emilio Marmolejo-Olea, Mari Cruz Vilela</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extensions of Operator-Valued Kernels on $\mathbb{F}^{+}_{d}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10935</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10935v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the problem of extending a positive-definite operator-valued kernel, defined on words of a fixed finite length from a free semigroup, to a global kernel defined on all words. We show that if the initial kernel satisfies a natural one-step dominance inequality on its interior, a global extension that preserves this interior data and the dominance property is always possible. This extension is constructed explicitly via a Cuntz-Toeplitz model. For the problem of matching the kernel on the boundary, we introduce an intrinsic shift-consistency condition. We prove this condition is sufficient to guarantee the existence of a global extension that agrees with the original kernel on its entire domain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10935v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Tian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on remotal and uniquely remotal sets in normed linear spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10992v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Remotal and uniquely remotal sets play an important role in the area of farthest point problem as well as nearest point problem in a Banach space $X.$ In this study, we find some sufficient conditions for remotality and uniquely remotality of a bounded subset of a Banach space $X$ through $\alpha\beta$-statistical convergence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10992v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Uddalak Mukherjee, Sumit Som</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On singular points in the essential spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11025v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The paper investigates the existence of a limit in the operator norm for a family of operators $T_z(H)= F(H-z)^{-1}F^*$ for $z$ tending to the real axis. The conditions for the $H$ operator and the rigging operator $F$ are established, under which the limit exists. Special attention is paid to the separation of cases when the limit point belongs and does not belong to the point spectrum $H$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11025v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Plakhotnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Operator ranges and spaceability: An extension of the Kitson--Timoney theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11332v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we extend Theorem~3.3 from [\emph{J.~Math.~Anal.~Appl.}~\textbf{378} (2011), 680--686] concerning the spaceability of complements of operator ranges. In particular, we provide an affirmative answer to the question posed in \emph{Remark~3.4} of that paper, showing that the result remains valid when the operators act between Fr\'echet spaces. Moreover, we prove that the same conclusion holds for arbitrary (possibly uncountable) families of operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11332v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Geivison Ribeiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the boundedness of dilation operators in the context of Triebel-Lizorkin-Morrey spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11439v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we study the behavior of dilation operators $ D_\lambda \colon f \mapsto f(\lambda\,\cdot) $ with $ \lambda &gt; 1 $ in the context of Triebel-Lizorkin-Morrey spaces $\mathcal{E}^{s}_{u,p,q}(\mathbb{R}^d)$. For that purpose we prove upper and lower bounds for the operator (quasi-)norm $\| D_\lambda \,|\, \mathcal{L}\big(\mathcal{E}^s_{u,p,q}(\mathbb{R}^d)\big) \| $. We show that for $s&gt;\sigma_p $ the operator (quasi-)norm $\| D_\lambda \,|\, \mathcal{L}\big(\mathcal{E}^s_{u,p,q}(\mathbb{R}^d)\big) \| $ up to constants behaves as $\lambda^{s - \frac{d}{u}} $. For the borderline case $ s = \sigma_{p} $ we observe a behavior of the form $\lambda^{\sigma_p- \frac{d}{u}}$, multiplied with logarithmic terms of $\lambda$ that also depend on the fine index $q$. For $s &lt; \sigma_{p}$ and $p \geq 1$ we find the relation $\| D_\lambda \,|\, \mathcal{L}\big(\mathcal{E}^s_{u,p,q}(\mathbb{R}^d)\big) \| \sim \lambda^{ - \frac{d}{u}}$. The case $s &lt; \sigma_{p}$ and $p &lt; 1$ is investigated as well. Our proofs are mainly based on the Fourier analytic approach to Triebel-Lizorkin-Morrey spaces. As byproducts we show an advanced Fourier multiplier theorem for band-limited functions in the context of Morrey spaces and derive some new equivalent (quasi-)norms and characterizations of $\mathcal{E}^{s}_{u,p,q}(\mathbb{R}^d)$.
  Keywords: Dilation Operator, Morrey space, Triebel-Lizorkin-Morrey space, Fourier multiplier</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11439v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marc Hovemann, Markus Weimar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Fractional Two-Sided Quaternionic Dunkl Transform and Heisenberg-Type Inequalities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11597v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This report investigates the main definitions and fundamental properties of the fractional two-sided quaternionic Dunkl transform in two dimensions. We present key results concerning its structure and emphasize its connections to classical harmonic analysis. Special attention is given to inversion, boundedness, spectral behavior, and explicit formulas for structured functions such as radial or harmonic functions. Within this framework, we establish a generalized form of the classical Heisenberg-type uncertainty principle. Building on this foundation, we further extend the result by proving a higher-order Heisenberg-type inequality valid for arbitrary moments $p \geq 1$, with sharp constants characterized through generalized Hermite functions. Finally, by analyzing the interplay between the two-sided fractional quaternionic Dunkl transform and the two-sided fractional quaternionic Fourier transform, we derive a corresponding uncertainty principle for the latter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11597v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed Essenhajy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectrum of the wave equation with Dirac damping on a compact star graph</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09829v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the wave equation with a distributional Dirac damping and Dirichlet boundary conditions on a compact interval. It is shown that the spectrum of the corresponding wave operator is fully determined by zeroes of an entire function. Consequently, a considerable change of spectral properties is shown for certain critical values of the damping parameter. We also derive a definitive criterion for the Riesz basis property of the root vectors for an arbitrary placement of a complex-valued Dirac damping. Finally, we consider a generalisation of the problem for compact star graphs and provide insight into the essence of the critical damping constant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09829v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikul\'a\v{s} Ku\v{c}era</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local Rigidity of Quasi--Lie Brackets on Quaternionic Banach Modules and Applications to Nonlinear PDEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10124</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10124v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We establish a local rigidity theorem for quasi--Lie brackets on quaternionic Banach right modules. Under quantitative control of antisymmetry and Jacobi defects, we construct an explicit bilinear correction that preserves right $\mathbb{H}$--linearity and restores the exact Lie property. The approach combines a radial homotopy operator, a controlled Neumann-series inversion, and a finite-rank adjustment, all with explicit operator estimates. This constructive framework bridges quaternionic functional analysis with rigidity theory and yields concrete applications to nonlinear PDEs, including local well-posedness and Beale--Kato--Majda continuation criteria with explicit thresholds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10124v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nassim Athmouni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Plastic metric spaces and groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10537v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A metric space is plastic if all its non-expansive bijections are isometries. We prove three main results: (1) every countable dense subspace of a normed space is not plastic, (2) every $k$-crowded separable metric space contains a plastic dense subspace, and (3) every strictly convex separable metric group contains a plastic dense subgroup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10537v1</guid>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taras Banakh, Oles Mazurenko, Olesia Zavarzina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral and Dynamical Analysis of Fractional Discrete Laplacians on the Half-Lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10680</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10680v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate discrete fractional Laplacians defined on the half-lattice in several dimensions, allowing possibly different fractional orders along each coordinate direction. By expressing the half-lattice operator as a boundary restriction of the full-lattice one plus a bounded correction that is relatively compact with respect to it, we show that both operators share the same essential spectrum and the same interior threshold structure. For perturbations by a decaying potential, the conjugate-operator method provides a strict Mourre estimate on any compact energy window inside the continuous spectrum, excluding threshold points. As a consequence, a localized Limiting Absorption Principle holds, ensuring the absence of singular continuous spectrum, the finiteness of eigenvalues, and weighted propagation (transport) bounds. The form-theoretic construction also extends naturally to negative fractional orders. Overall, the relative compactness of the boundary correction guarantees that the interior-energy spectral and dynamical results obtained on the full lattice remain valid on the half-lattice without modification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10680v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nassim Athmouni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting the real line among one-parametric topological groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10754v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove that a topological group is isomorphic to the real line if and only if it is a one-parameteric, metrizable, and not monothetic. This result is used in the authors' other paper to prove that one-parametric groups in strictly convex metric group all are topologically isomorphic to the real line.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10754v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taras Banakh, Kateryna Makarova, Oles Mazurenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Locally compact strictly convex metric groups are abelian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10755v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that every locally compact strictly convex metric group is abelian, thus answering one problem posed by the authors in their earlir paper. To prove this theorem we first construct the isomorphic embeddings of the real line into the strictly convex metric group using its geodesic properties and charaterization of the real line as a unique not monothetic one-parametric metrizable topological group. We proceed to show that all compact subgroups in a strictly convex metric group are trivial, which combined with the classical result of Iwasawa completes the proof of the main result.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10755v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taras Banakh, Oles Mazurenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Sylvester equations in Banach subalgebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09752</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09752v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let ${\mathcal B}$ be a Banach algebra and ${\mathcal A}$ be a Banach subalgebra that admits norm-controlled inversion in ${\mathcal B}$. In this work, we take $A, B$ in the Banach subalgebra ${\mathcal A}$ with their spectra in the Banach algebra ${\mathcal B}$ being disjoint, and show that the operator Sylvester equation $ BX-XA=Q$ has a unique solution $X\in {\mathcal A}$ for every $Q\in {\mathcal A}$. Under the additional assumptions that ${\mathcal B}$ is the operator algebra ${\mathcal B}(H)$ on a Hilbert space $H$ and that $A$ and $B$ are normal in ${\mathcal B}(H)$, an explicit norm estimate for the solution $X$ of the above operator Sylvester equation is provided in this work. In addition, the above conclusion on norm control is applied to Banach subalgebras of localized infinite matrices and integral operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09752v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiquan Fang, Chang Eon Shin, Qiyu Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sign regularity preserving linear operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02428v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A matrix $A\in \mathbb{R}^{m \times n}$ is strictly sign regular/SSR (or sign regular/SR) if for each $1 \leq k \leq \min\{m,n\}$, all (non-zero) $k\times k$ minors of $A$ have the same sign. This class of matrices contains the totally positive matrices, and was first studied by Schoenberg in 1930 to characterize variation diminution, a fundamental property in total positivity theory. In this article, we classify all surjective linear mappings $\mathcal{L}:\mathbb{R}^{m\times n}\to\mathbb{R}^{m\times n}$ that preserve: (i) sign regularity and (ii) sign regularity with a given sign pattern, as well as (iii) strict versions of these.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02428v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Projesh Nath Choudhury, Shivangi Yadav</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundary values via reproducing kernels: The Julia-Carath\'eodory theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13901</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13901v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a reproducing kernel $k$ on a nonempty set $X$, we define the reproductive boundary of $X$ with respect to $k$. Furthermore, we generalize the well known nontangential and horocyclic approach regions of the unit circle to this new kind of boundary. We also introduce the concept of a composition factor of $k$, an abstract analogue of analytic selfmaps of the unit disk. Using these notions, we obtain a far reaching generalization of the Julia-Carath\'eodory theorem, stated on an arbitrary set. We also prove Julia's lemma in the abstract setting and give sufficient conditions for the convergence of iterates of some selfmaps. As an application we improve the classical theorem on the unit disk for contractive multipliers of standard weighted Dirichlet spaces, as well as Besov spaces on the unit ball. Many examples and questions are provided for these novel objects of study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13901v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Frej Dahlin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Various form closures associated with a fixed non-semibounded self-adjoint operator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09551v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: If $T$ is a semibounded self-adjoint operator in a Hilbert space $(H, \, (\cdot , \cdot))$ then the closure of the sesquilinear form $(T \cdot , \cdot)$ is a unique Hilbert space completion. In the non-semibounded case a closure is a Kre\u{\i}n space completion and generally, it is not unique. Here, all such closures are studied. A one-to-one correspondence between all closed symmetric forms (with ``gap point'' $0$) and all J-non-negative, J-self-adjoint and boundedly invertible Kre\u{\i}n space operators is observed. Their eigenspectral functions are investigated, in particular near the critical point infinity. An example for infinitely many closures of a fixed form $(T \cdot , \cdot)$ is discussed in detail using a non-semibounded self-adjoint multiplication operator $T$ in a model Hilbert space. These observations indicate that closed symmetric forms may carry more information than self-adjoint Hilbert space operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09551v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Fleige</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Note on Carlier Inequality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02285</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.02285v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, Carlier established in [3] a quantitave version of the Fitzpatrick inequality in a Hilbert space. We extend this result by Carlier to the framework of reflexive Banach spaces. In the Hilbert space setting, we obtain an improved version of the strong Fitzpatrick inequality due to Voisei and Z\u{a}linescu.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.02285v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Regina S. Burachik, J. E. Mart\'inez-Legaz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A novel approach through spherical functions in the characterization of invariant functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01043</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01043v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a compact subgroup K of the orthogonal group acting on the Euclidean space Rn, Gerald Schwarz proved that every smooth K-invariant function on Rn can be expressed as a smooth function of a generating set of $K$-invariant polynomials on n variables. The goal of this work is to provide an alternative and more straightforward proof of this result, based on Gelfand theory, with a particular focus on spherical functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01043v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roc\'io D\'iaz Mart\'in, Linda Saal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spans and convex combinations of boundary-valued continuous functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07857</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07857v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For an $(n\ge 2)$-dimensional real Banach space $E$ with unit ball $E_{\le 1}$ and a topological space $X$ arbitrary elements in $C(X,E_{\le 1})$ are always expressible as linear combinations of at most three functions valued in the unit sphere $\partial E_{\le 1}$. On the other hand, for normal $X$, $C(X,E_{\le 1})$ can only be the convex hull of $C(X,\partial E_{\le 1})$ if the covering dimension of $X$ is strictly smaller than $\dim E$. A variant of this remark is the characterization of normal $X$ with $\dim X&lt;\dim E$ as precisely those for which $C(X,E_{\le 1})$ is the convex hull of nowhere-vanishing continuous $X\to E_{\le 1}$ or, equivalently, that of continuous functions $X\to E_{[r,1]}$, $r\in (0,1)$ valued in arbitrarily thin spherical shells.
  This extends a number of results due to Peck, Cantwell, Bogachev, Mena-Jurado, Navarro-Pascual and Jim\'enez-Vargas and others revolving around the realizability of the unit ball of $C(X,E)$ as a convex hull of its extreme points for strictly convex and/or complex $E$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07857v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandru Chirvasitu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isoperimetric Inequalities on Slabs with applications to Cubes and Gaussian Slabs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06602v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study isoperimetric inequalities on "slabs", namely weighted Riemannian manifolds obtained as the product of the uniform measure on a finite length interval with a codimension-one base. As our two main applications, we consider the case when the base is the flat torus $\mathbb{R}^2 / 2 \mathbb{Z}^2$ and the standard Gaussian measure in $\mathbb{R}^{n-1}$.
  The isoperimetric conjecture on the three-dimensional cube predicts that minimizers are enclosed by spheres about a corner, cylinders about an edge and coordinate planes. This has only been established for relative volumes close to $0$, $1/2$ and $1$ by compactness arguments. Our analysis confirms the isoperimetric conjecture on the three-dimensional cube with side lengths $(\beta,1,1)$ in a new range of relatives volumes $\bar v \in [0,1/2]$. In particular, we confirm the conjecture for the standard cube ($\beta=1$) for all $\bar v \leq 0.120582$, when $\beta \leq 0.919431$ for the entire range where spheres are conjectured to be minimizing, and also for all $\bar v \in [0,1/2] \setminus (\frac{1}{\pi} - \frac{\beta}{4},\frac{1}{\pi} + \frac{\beta}{4})$. When $\beta \leq 0.919431$ we reduce the validity of the full conjecture to establishing that the half-plane $\{ x \in [0,\beta] \times [0,1]^2 \; ; \; x_3 \leq \frac{1}{\pi} \}$ is an isoperimetric minimizer. We also show that the analogous conjecture on a high-dimensional cube $[0,1]^n$ is false for $n \geq 10$.
  In the case of a slab with a Gaussian base of width $T&gt;0$, we identify a phase transition when $T = \sqrt{2 \pi}$ and when $T = \pi$. In particular, while products of half-planes with $[0,T]$ are always minimizing when $T \leq \sqrt{2 \pi}$, when $T &gt; \pi$ they are never minimizing, being beaten by Gaussian unduloids. In the range $T \in (\sqrt{2 \pi},\pi]$, a potential trichotomy occurs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06602v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emanuel Milman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Density of irreducible operators in the trace-class norm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17190v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In 1968, Paul Halmos initiated the research on density of the set of irreducible operators on a separable Hilbert space. Through the research, a long-standing unsolved problem inquires: is the set of irreducible operators dense in $B(H)$ with respect to the trace-class norm topology? Precisely, for each operator $T $ in $B(H)$ and every $\varepsilon &gt;0$, is there a trace-class operator $K$ such that $T+K$ is irreducible and $\Vert K \Vert_1 &lt; \varepsilon$?
  For $p&gt;1$, to prove the $\Vert \cdot \Vert_p$-norm density of irreducible operators in $B(H)$, a type of Weyl-von Neumann theorem effects as a key technique. But the traditional method fails for the case $p=1$, where by $\Vert \cdot \Vert_p$-norm we denote the Schatten $p$-norm.
  In the current paper, for a large family of operators in $B(H)$, we give the above long-term problem an affirmative answer. The result is derived from a combination of techniques in both operator theory and operator algebras. Moreover, we discover that there is a strong connection between the problem and another related operator-theoretical problem related to type $\mathrm{II}_1$ von Neumann algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17190v5</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junsheng Fang, Chunlan Jiang, Minghui Ma, Junhao Shen, Rui Shi, Tianze Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new characterization of (pre)liminary C*-algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20980v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Given an arbitrary countable ordinal $\alpha $, we introduce the notion of type $I_{\alpha }$ C*-algebra and $\alpha $-subhomogeneous C*-algebra. When $\alpha =0$, these recover the notions of Fell C*-algebra and of commutative C*-algebra, respectively. When $\alpha = n &lt;\omega $, these recover the notions of type $I_{n}$ C*-algebra and of $n$-subhomogeneous C*-algebra, respectively. We prove that a separable C*-algebra is liminary if and only if it is type $I_{\alpha }$ for some $\alpha &lt;\omega _{1}$, and it is preliminary (i.e., has no infinite-dimensional irreducible representation) if and only if it is $\alpha $-subhomogeneous for some $\alpha &lt;\omega _{1}$. We also prove that for any countable ordinal $\alpha $ there exists a separable C*-algebra that is type $I_{\alpha }$ and not type $I_{\beta }$ for $\beta &lt;\alpha $, and a separable C*-algebra that is $\alpha $-subhomogeneous and not $\beta $-subhomogeneous for any $\beta &lt;\alpha $.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20980v4</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martino Lupini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frictional martingale optimal transport and robust hedging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08182</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.08182v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the martingale optimal transport problem with state-dependent trading frictions and develop a geometric and duality framework extending from the one time-step to the multi-marginal setting. Building on the left-monotone structure of frictionless MOT (Beiglb\"ock and Juillet, Ann. Probab., 2016; Henry-Labord\`ere and Touzi, Finance Stoch., 2016; Beiglb\"ock et al., Ann. Probab., 2017), we introduce a convex frictional cost combining proportional bid-ask spreads and quadratic liquidity impacts. The framework extends the martingale Spence-Mirrlees condition to nonlinear frictions and establishes a frictional monotonicity principle.
  At each time step, the joint distribution between consecutive asset prices exhibits a bi-atomic, monotone geometry: conditional on the current price, the next price lies on one of two monotone branches representing upward and downward rebalancing. A no-transaction region, or trade band, arises where maintaining the position is optimal, while outside the band, transitions follow two monotone graphs whose endpoints satisfy an equal-slope condition balancing continuation value and marginal trading cost.
  The framework extends dynamically via a recursive identity, ensuring stability and convergence to the frictionless left-curtain limit, and applies to model-independent pricing and robust hedging of path-dependent derivatives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.08182v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pratik Rai</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
