<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.FA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA</link>
    <description>math.FA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>How Free-Free-Boolean Independence Arises in Bi-Free Probability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.18274v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work concerns notions of multi-algebra independence introduced by Liu and how they can be studied in the context of bi-free probability. In particular, we show how the free-free-Boolean independence for triples of algebras can be embedded intro and therefore studied from a lens of bi-free probability. It is also shown how its cumulants can be constructed from the bi-free cumulants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.18274v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Pepper</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fixed Point Theorems for TSR-Contraction Mapping in Probabilistic Metric Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.18500v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The concept of fixed point plays a crucial role in various fields of applied mathematics. The aim of this paper is to establish the existence of a unique fixed point of some type of functions which satisfy a new contraction principle, namely, TSR-contraction principle in various types of probabilistic metric spaces. The proposed contraction mapping is different from our traditional definitions of contraction mapping.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.18500v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanjay Roy, T. K. Samanta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Common Fixed Point Theorem for Six Functions on Menger Probabilistic Generalized Metric Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.18501v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The main aim of this paper is to find a unique common fixed point for six functions in a Menger probabilistic generalized metric space. For this purpose, we have defined the compatibility of three functions and established some required theorems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.18501v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanjay Roy, T. K. Samanta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bourgain-Morrey-Lorentz spaces and operators on them</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19130</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19130v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce Bourgain-Morrey-Lorentz spaces and give a description of the predual of Bourgain-Morrey-Lorentz spaces via the block spaces. As an application of duality, we obtain the boundedness of Hardy-Littlewood maximal operator, sharp maximal operator, Calder\'on-Zygmund operator, fractional integral operator, commutator on Bourgain-Morrey-Lorentz spaces. Moreover, we obtain a weak Hardy factorization terms of Calder\'on-Zygmund operator in Bourgain-Morrey-Lorentz spaces. Using this result, we obtain a characterization of functions in $\BMO$ (the functions of ``bounded mean oscillation'') via the boundedness of commutators generated by them and a homogeneous Calder\'on-Zygmund operator. In the last, we show that the commutator generated by a function $b$ and a homogeneous Calder\'on-Zygmund operator is a compact operator on Bourgain-Morrey-Lorentz spaces if and only if $b$ is the limit of compactly supported smooth functions in $\BMO$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19130v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tengfei Bai, Pengfei Guo, Jingshi Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weighted Bourgain-Morrey-Besov type and Triebel-Lizorkin type spaces associated with operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19135v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $(X,\mu)$ be a space of homogeneous type satisfying $\mu(X) =\infty$, the doubling property and the reverse doubling condition. Let $L$ be a nonnegative self-adjoint operator on $L^2(X)$ whose heat kernel enjoys a Gaussian upper bound. We introduce the weighted homogeneous Bourgain-Morrey-Besov type spaces and Triebel-Lizorkin type spaces associated with the operator $L$. We obtain their continuous characterizations in terms of Peetre maximal functions, noncompactly supported functional calculus, heat kernel. Atomic and molecular decompositions of weighted homogeneous Bourgain-Morrey-Besov type spaces and Triebel-Lizorkin type spaces are also given. As an application, we obtain the boundedness of the fractional power of $L$, the spectral multiplier of $L$ on Bourgain-Morrey-Besov type spaces and Triebel-Lizorkin type spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19135v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tengfei Bai, Pengfei Guo, Jingshi Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The preduals of Banach space valued Bourgain-Morrey spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19143v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $X$ be a Banach space such that there exists a Banach space $^\ast X$ and $ ( ^\ast X )^ \ast = X $. In this paper, we introduce $X$-valued Bourgain-Morrey spaces. We show that $^\ast X$-valued block spaces are the predual of $X$-valued Bourgain-Morrey spaces. We obtain the completeness, denseness and Fatou property of $^\ast X$-valued block spaces. We give a description of the dual of $X$-valued Bourgain-Morrey spaces and conclude the reflexivity of these spaces. The boundedness of powered Hardy-Littlewood maximal operator in vector valued block spaces is obtained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19143v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tengfei Bai, Pengfei Guo, Jingshi Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Frames and Hyperinvariant Subspaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19303v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The theory of dynamical frames evolved from practical problems in dynamical sampling where the initial state of a vector needs to be recovered from the space-time samples of evolutions of the vector. This leads to the investigation of structured frames obtained from the orbits of evolution operators. One of the basic problems in dynamical frame theory is to determine the semigroup representations, which we will call central frame representations, whose frame generators are unique (up to equivalence). Recently, Christensen, Hasannasab, and Philipp proved that all frame representations of the semigroup $\Bbb{Z}_{+}$ have this property. Their proof of this result relies on the characterization of the structure of shift-invariant subspaces in $H^2(\mathbb{D})$ due to Beurling. In this paper we settle the general uniqueness problem by presenting a characterization of central frame representations for any semigroup in terms of the co-hyperinvariant subspaces of the left regular representation of the semigroup. This result is not only consistent with the known result of Han-Larson in 2000 for group representation frames, but also proves that all the frame generators of a semigroup generated by any $k$-tuple $(A_1, ... A_k)$ of commuting bounded linear operators on a separable Hilbert space $H$ are equivalent, a case where the structure of shift-invariant subspaces, or submodules, of the Hardy Space on polydisks $H^{2}(\Bbb{D}^k)$ is still not completely characterized.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19303v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Bailey, Deguang Han, Keri Kornelson, David Larson, Rui Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C*-like modules and matrix $p$-operator norms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19471v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a generalization of H\"older duality to algebra-valued pairings via $L^p$-modules. H\"older duality states that if $p \in (1, \infty)$ and $p^{\prime}$ are conjugate exponents, then the dual space of $L^p(\mu)$ is isometrically isomorphic to $L^{p^{\prime}}(\mu)$. In this work we study certain pairs $(\mathsf{Y},\mathsf{X})$, as generalizations of the pair $(L^{p^{\prime}}(\mu), L^p(\mu))$, that have an $L^p$-operator algebra valued pairing $\mathsf{Y} \times \mathsf{X} \to A$. When the $A$-valued version of H\"older duality still holds, we say that $(\mathsf{Y},\mathsf{X})$ is C*-like. We show that finite and countable direct sums of the C*-like module $(A,A)$ are still C*-like when $A$ is any block diagonal subalgebra of $d \times d$ matrices. We provide counterexamples when $A \subset M_d^p(\mathbb{C})$ is not block diagonal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19471v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandra Calin, Ian Cartwright, Luke Coffman, Alonso Delf\'in, Charles Girard, Jack Goldrick, Anoushka Nerella, Wilson Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diversity of Lipschitz-free spaces over countable complete discrete metric spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19891v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that there are uncountably many mutually non-isomorphic Lipschitz-free spaces over countable, complete, discrete metric spaces. Also there is a countable, complete, discrete metric space whose free space does not embed into the free space of any uniformly discrete metric space. This enhanced diversity is a consequence of the fact that the dentability index $D$ presents a highly non-binary behavior when assigned to the free spaces of metric spaces outside of the oppressive confines of compact purely 1-unrectifiable spaces. Indeed, the cardinality of $\{D(\mathcal F(M)): M$ countable, complete, discrete$\}$ is uncountable while $\{D(\mathcal F(M)):M$ infinite, compact, purely 1-unrectifiable$\}=\{\omega,\omega^2\}$. Similar barrier is observed for uniformly discrete metric spaces as higher values of the dentability index are excluded for their free spaces: $\{D(\mathcal F(M)):M$ infinite, uniformly discrete$\}=\{\omega^2,\omega^3\}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19891v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Estelle Basset, Gilles Lancien, Anton\'in Proch\'azka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-strict singularity of optimal Sobolev embeddings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19981v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the operator-theoretic property of strict singularity for optimal Sobolev embeddings within the general framework of rearrangement-invariant function spaces (r.i. spaces).
  More specifically, we focus on studying the ``quality'' of non-compactness for optimal Sobolev embeddings $V^m_0X(\Omega)\to Y_X(\Omega)$, where $X$ is a given r.i. space and $Y_X$ is the corresponding optimal target r.i. space (i.e., the smallest among all r.i. spaces).
  For the class of sub-limiting norms (i.e., the norms whose fundamental function satisfies $\varphi_{Y_X}(t)\approx t^{-m/n}\varphi_X(t)$ as $t\to0^+$), we construct suitable spike-function sequences that establish a general framework for proving non-strict singularity of optimal (and thus non-compact) sublimiting Sobolev embeddings.
  As an application, we show that optimal sublimiting Sobolev embeddings are not strictly singular in a rather large subclass of r.i. spaces, namely weighted Lambda spaces $X=\Lambda^q_w$, $q\in[1, \infty)$. Except for the endpoint case $X=L^{n/m,1}$, our spike-function construction enables us to construct a subspace of $V^m_0X$ that is isomorphic to $\ell_q$, which we then leverage to prove the non-strict singularity of the corresponding optimal Sobolev embedding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19981v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Lang, Zden\v{e}k Mihula</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General solution of corona problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20220</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20220v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Our main result is a description of the spectrum of bidual algebra $A^{**}$ of a uniform algebra $A$. This allows us to obtain abstract corona theorem for certain uniform algebras, asserting density of a specific Gleason part in the spectrum of an $H^\infty$ -- type subalgebra of $A^{**}$.
  There is an isometric isomorphism of the latter subalgebra with $H^\infty(G)$ for a wide class of domains $G\subset\mathbb C^d$. Using abstract corona theorem we show the density of the canonical image of $G$ in the spectrum of $H^\infty(G)$, solving positively corona problem for this class (which in particular includes balls and polydisks).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20220v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marek Kosiek, Krzysztof Rudol</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Off-diagonal bloom weighted estimates for bilinear commutators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19007</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19007v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove the off-diagonal estimates of the bilinear iterated commutators in the two-weight setting. The upper bound is established via sparse domination, and the lower bound is proved by the median method. Our methods are so flexible so that it can be easily extended to the multilinear scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19007v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunan Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On quotients of ideals of weighted holomorphic mappings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19593v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explore the procedure given by left-hand quotients in the context of weighted holomorphic ideals. On the one hand, we show that this procedure does not generate new ideals other than the ideal of weighted holomorphic mappings when considering the left-hand quotients induced by the ideals of $p$-compact, weakly $p$-compact, unconditionally $p$-compact, approximable or right $p$-nuclear operators with their respective weighted holomorphic ideals. On the other hand, the procedure is of interest when considering other operators ideals as it provides new weighted holomorphic ideals. This is the case of the ideal of Grothendieck weighted holomorphic mappings or the ideal of Rosenthal weighted holomorphic mappings, where the applicability of this construction is shown.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19593v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Belacel Amar, Bougoutaia Amar, Rueda Pilar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical Periodic Normalization at Codim 1 Bifurcations of Limit Cycles in DDEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19786v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent work in [53, 54] by the authors on periodic center manifolds and normal forms for bifurcations of limit cycles in delay differential equations (DDEs) motivates the derivation of explicit computational formulas for the critical normal form coefficients of all codimension one bifurcations of limit cycles. In this paper, we derive such formulas via an application of the periodic normalization method in combination with the functional analytic perturbation framework for dual semigroups (sun-star calculus). The explicit formulas allow us to distinguish between nondegenerate, sub- and supercritical bifurcations. To efficiently apply these formulas, we introduce the characteristic operator as this enables us to use robust numerical boundary-value algorithms based on orthogonal collocation. Although our theoretical results are proven in a more general setting, the software implementation and examples focus on discrete DDEs. The actual implementation is described in detail and its effectiveness is demonstrated on various models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19786v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. M. Bosschaert, B. Lentjes, L. Spek, Yu. A. Kuznetsov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Minkowski symmetrizations of $\alpha$-concave functions and related applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.12619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.12619v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A Minkowski symmetral of an $\alpha$-concave function is introduced, and some of its fundamental properties are derived. It is shown that for a given $\alpha$-concave function, there exists a sequence of Minkowski symmetrizations that hypo-converges to its ``hypo-symmetrization". As an application, it is shown that the hypo-symmetrization of a log-concave function $f$ is always harder to approximate than $f$ is by ``inner log-linearizations" with a fixed number of break points. This is a functional analogue of the classical geometric result which states that among all convex bodies of a given mean width, a Euclidean ball is hardest to approximate by inscribed polytopes with a fixed number of vertices. Finally, a general extremal property of the hypo-symmetrization is deduced, which includes a Urysohn-type inequality and the aforementioned approximation result as special cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.12619v4</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steven Hoehner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large-scale behaviour of Sobolev functions in Ahlfors regular metric measure spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.11718</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.11718v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the behaviour at infinity of $p$-Sobolev functions in the setting of Ahlfors $Q$-regular metric measure spaces supporting a $p$-Poincar\'e inequality. By introducing the notions of sets which are $p$-thin at infinity, we show that functions in the homogeneous space $\dot N^{1,p}(X)$ necessarily have limits at infinity outside of $p$-thin sets, when $1\le p&lt;Q&lt;+\infty$. When $p&gt;Q$, we show by example that uniqueness of limits at infinity may fail for functions in $\dot N^{1,p}(X)$. While functions in $\dot N^{1,p}(X)$ may not have any reasonable limit at infinity when $p=Q$, we introduce the notion of a $Q$-thick set at infinity, and characterize the limits of functions in $\dot N^{1,Q}(X)$ along infinite curves in terms of limits outside $Q$-thin sets and along $Q$-thick sets. By weakening the notion of a thick set, we show that a function in $\dot N^{1,Q}(X)$ with a limit along such an almost thick set may fail to have a limit along any infinite curve. While homogeneous $p$-Sobolev functions may have infinite limits at infinity when $p\ge Q$, we provide bounds on how quickly such functions may grow: when $p=Q$, functions in $\dot N^{1,p}(X)$ have sub-logarithmic growth at infinity, whereas when $p&gt;Q$, such functions have growth at infinity controlled by $d(\cdot, O)^{1-Q/p}$, where $O$ is a fixed base point in $X$. For the inhomogeneous spaces $N^{1,p}(X)$, the phenomenon is different. We show that for $1\le p\le Q$, the limit of a function $u\in N^{1,p}(X)$ is zero outside of a $p$-thin set, whereas $\lim_{x\to+\infty}u(x)=0$ for all $u\in N^{1,p}(X)$ when $p&gt;Q$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.11718v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Josh Kline, Pekka Koskela, Khanh Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On maximal intersection position for logarithmically concave functions and measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.01033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.01033v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A new position is introduced and studied for the convolution of log-concave functions, which may be regarded as a functional analogue of the maximum intersection position of convex bodies introduced and studied by Artstein-Avidan and Katzin (2018) and Artstein-Avidan and Putterman (2022). Our main result is a John-type theorem for the maximal intersection position of a pair of log-concave functions, including the corresponding decomposition of the identity. The main result holds under very weak assumptions on the functions; in particular, the functions considered may both have unbounded supports. As an application of our results, we introduce a John-type position for even $\log$-concave measures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.01033v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steven Hoehner, Michael Roysdon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gagliardo-Nirenberg inequality with H\"older norms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00941</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00941v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The classical Gagliardo-Nirenberg inequality, known as an interpolation inequality, involves Lebesgue norms of functions and their derivatives. We established an interpolation lemma to connect Lebesgue and H\"older spaces, thus extending the Gagliardo-Nirenberg inequality. This extension involved substituting arbitrary Sobolev norms with appropriate H\"older norms, allowing for a wider range of applicable parameters in the inequality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00941v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengxia Dong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized complex symmetric composition operators with applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20875v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We characterize the weighted composition-differentiation operators $D_{\mfn,\psi,\varphi}$ acting on $\mathcal{H}_\gamma(\mathbb{D}^d)$ over the polydisk $\mathbb{D}^d$ which are complex symmetric with respect to the conjugation $\mathcal{J}$. We obtain necessary and sufficient conditions for $D_{\mfn,\psi,\varphi}$ to be self-adjoint. We also investigate complex symmetry of generalized weighted composition differentiation operators $M_{n, \psi, \varphi}=\displaystyle\sum_{j=1}^{n}a_jD_{j,\psi_j, \varphi},$ (where $a_j\in \mathbb{C}$ for $j=1, 2, \dots, n$) on the reproducing kernel Hilbert space $\mathcal{H}_\gamma(\mathbb{D})$ of analytic functions on the unit disk $\mathbb{D}$ with respect to a weighted composition conjugation $C_{\mu, \xi}$. Further, we discuss the structure of self-adjoint linear composition differentiation operators. Finally, the convexity of the Berezin range of composition operator on $\mathcal{H}_\gamma(\mathbb{D})$ are investigated. Additionally, geometrical interpretations have also been employed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20875v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vasudevarao Allu, Satyajit Sahoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topologizability and related properties of the iterates of composition operators in Gelfand-Shilov classes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23906v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We analyse the behaviour of the iterates of composition operators defined by polynomials acting on global classes of ultradifferentiable functions of Beurling type which are invariant under the Fourier transform. In particular, we determine the polynomials $\psi$ for which the sequence of iterates of the composition operator $C_\psi$ is topologizable (m-topologizable) acting on certain Gelfand-Shilov spaces defined by mean of Braun-Meise-Taylor weights. We prove that the composition operators $C_\psi$ with $\psi$ a polynomial of degree greater than one are always topologizable in certain settings involving Gelfand-Shilov spaces, just like in the Schwartz space. Unlike in the Schwartz space setting, composition operators $C_\psi$ associated with polynomials $\psi$ are not always $m-$topologizable. We also deal with the composition operators $C_\psi$ with $\psi$ being an affine function acting on $\mathcal{S}_{\omega}(\mathbb{R})$ and find a complete characterization of topologizability and m-topologizability</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23906v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Angela A. Albanese, H\'ector Ariza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of bi-parametric potentials and rate of convergence of truncated hypersingular integrals in the Dunkl setting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.15748v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we introduce the $\beta$-semigroup for $\beta &gt; 0$, which unifies and extends the classical Poisson (for $\beta=1$) and heat (for $\beta=2$) semigroups within the Dunkl analysis framework. Leveraging this semigroup, we derive an explicit representation for the inverse of the Dunkl-Riesz potential and characterize the image of the function space $L_k^p(\mathbb{R}^n)$ for $1 \leq p &lt; \frac{n + 2\gamma}{\alpha}$. We further define the bi-parametric potential of order $\alpha$ by $$\mathfrak{S}_k^{(\alpha,\beta)} = \left(I + (-\Delta_k)^{\beta/2}\right)^{-\alpha/\beta}$$ and establish its inverse along with a detailed description of the associated range space. Our approach employs a wavelet-based method that represents the inverse as the limit of truncated hypersingular integrals parameterized by $\epsilon &gt; 0$. To analyze the convergence of these approximations, we introduce the concept of $\eta$-smoothness at a point $x_0$ in the Dunkl setting. We show that if a function $f \in L_k^p(\mathbb{R}^n) \cap L_k^2(\mathbb{R}^n)$, for $1 \leq p \leq \infty$, possesses $\eta$-smoothness at $x_0$, then the truncated hypersingular approximations converge to $f(x_0)$ as $\epsilon \to 0^+$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.15748v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sandeep Kumar Verma, Athulya P</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A generic threshold phenomena in weighted $\ell^2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15937</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.15937v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider threshold phenomenons in the context of weighted $\ell^2$-spaces. Our main result is a summable Baire category version of K\"orner's topological Ivashev-Musatov Theorem, which is proved to be optimal from several aspects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.15937v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adem Limani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the equality of De Branges-Rovnyak and Dirichlet spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16572v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work is devoted to the comparison of de Branges--Rovnyak $H(b)$ spaces harmonically weighted Dirichlet spaces $\mathcal{D}_\mu$. We completely characterize which $H(b)$ spaces are also harmonically weighted Dirichlet spaces $\mathcal{D}_\mu$, when $\mu$ is a finite sum of atoms. This is a generalization of a previous result by Costara--Ransford \cite{costara2013}: we make no assumptions on the Pythagorean pair $(b,a)$, and we produce new examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16572v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eugenio Dellepiane, Marco M. Peloso, Anita Tabacco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On existence of minimizers for weighted $L^p$-Hardy inequalities on $C^{1,\gamma}$-domains with compact boundary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.03527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.03527v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $p \in (1,\infty)$, $\alpha\in \mathbb{R}$, and $\Omega\subsetneq \mathbb{R}^N$ be a $C^{1,\gamma}$-domain with a compact boundary $\partial \Omega$, where $\gamma\in (0,1]$. Denote by $\delta_{\Omega}(x)$ the distance of a point $x\in \Omega$ to $\partial \Omega$. Let $\widetilde{W}^{1,p;\alpha}_0(\Omega)$ be the closure of $C_c^{\infty}(\Omega)$ in $\widetilde{W}^{1,p;\alpha}(\Omega)$, where
  $$\widetilde{W}^{1,p;\alpha}(\Omega):= \left\{\varphi \in {W}^{1,p}_{\mathrm{loc}} (\Omega) \mid \left( \| \, |\nabla \varphi \, |\|_{L^p(\Omega;\delta_{\Omega}^{-\alpha})}^p + \|\varphi\|_{L^p(\Omega;\delta_{\Omega}^{-(\alpha+p)})}^p\right)&lt;\infty \!\right\}.$$
  We study the following two variational constants: the weighted Hardy constant \begin{align*}
  H_{\alpha,p}(\Omega): =\!\inf \left\{\int_{\Omega} |\nabla \varphi|^p \delta_{\Omega}^{-\alpha} \mathrm{d}x \biggm| \int_{\Omega} |\varphi|^p \delta_{\Omega}^{-(\alpha+p)} \mathrm{d}x\!=\!1, \varphi \in \widetilde{W}^{1,p;\alpha}_0(\Omega) \right\} , \end{align*}
  and the weighted Hardy constant at infinity \begin{align*} \lambda_{\alpha,p}^{\infty}(\Omega) :=\sup_{K\Subset \Omega}\,
  \inf_{W^{1,p}_{c}(\Omega\setminus \overline{K})} \left\{\int_{\Omega\setminus \overline{K}} |\nabla \varphi|^p \delta_{\Omega}^{-\alpha} \mathrm{d}x \biggm| \int_{\Omega\setminus \overline{K}} |\varphi|^p \delta_{\Omega}^{-(\alpha+p)} \mathrm{d}x=1 \right\}. \end{align*} We show that $H_{\alpha,p}(\Omega)$ is attained if and only if the spectral gap $\Gamma_{\alpha,p}(\Omega):= \lambda_{\alpha,p}^{\infty}(\Omega)-H_{\alpha,p}(\Omega)$ is strictly positive. Moreover, we obtain tight decay estimates for the corresponding minimizers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.03527v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ujjal Das, Yehuda Pinchover, Baptiste Devyver</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-adjointness and domain of generalized spin-boson models with mild ultraviolet divergences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.14727</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.14727v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We provide a rigorous construction of a large class of generalized spin-boson models with ultraviolet-divergent form factors. This class comprises various models of many possibly non-identical atoms with arbitrary but finite numbers of levels, interacting with a boson field. Ultraviolet divergences are assumed to be mild, such that no self-energy renormalization is necessary. Our construction is based on recent results by A. Posilicano, which also allow us to state an explicit formula for the domain of self-adjointness for our Hamiltonians.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.14727v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sascha Lill, Davide Lonigro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Landis' conjecture for positive Schr\"odinger operators on graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02149v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this note we study the Landis conjecture for positive Schr\"odin\-ger operators on graphs. More precisely, we prove a Landis-type result in the form of a decay criterion that ensures when $\mathcal{H}$-harmonic functions for a positive Schr\"odinger operator $\mathcal{H}$ with potentials bounded from above by $ 1 $ are trivial. The positivity assumption on the operator allows us to impose slow decay across the entire graph, while requiring fast decay in only one direction, rather than throughout the whole graph. We then specifically look at the special cases of $ \mathbb{Z}^{d} $ and regular trees for which we get a explicit decay criterion. Moreover, we consider the fractional analogue of the Landis conjecture on $ \mathbb{Z}^{d} $. Our approach relies on the discrete version of Liouville comparison principle which is also proved in this article.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02149v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ujjal Das, Matthias Keller, Yehuda Pinchover</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homogenisation for Maxwell and Friends</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07084</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07084v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We refine the understanding of continuous dependence on coefficients of solution operators under the nonlocal $H$-topology viz Schur topology in the setting of evolutionary equations in the sense of Picard. We show that certain components of the solution operators converge strongly. The weak convergence behaviour known from homogenisation problems for ordinary differential equations is recovered on the other solution operator components. The results are underpinned by a rich class of examples that, in turn, are also treated numerically, suggesting a certain sharpness of the theoretical findings. Analytic treatment of an example that proves this sharpness is provided too. Even though all the considered examples contain local coefficients, the main theorems and structural insights are of operator-theoretic nature and, thus, also applicable to nonlocal coefficients. The main advantage of the problem class considered is that they contain mixtures of type, potentially highly oscillating between different types of PDEs; a prototype can be found in Maxwell's equations highly oscillating between the classical equations and corresponding eddy current approximations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07084v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Buchinger, Sebastian Franz, Nathanael Skrepek, Marcus Waurick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twisted Roe algebras and their $K$-theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.16556v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce a notion of twisted Roe algebra and a twisted coarse Baum-Connes conjecture with coefficients. We will study the basic properties of twisted Roe algebras, including a coarse analogue of the imprimitivity theorem for metric spaces with a structure of coarse fibrations. We show that the twisted coarse Baum-Connes conjecture with coefficients holds for a metric space with a coarse fibration structure when the base space and the fiber satisfy the twisted coarse Baum-Connes conjecture with coefficients. As an application, the coarse Baum-Connes conjecture holds for a finitely generated group which is an extension of coarsely embeddable groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.16556v2</guid>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jintao Deng, Liang Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-variable Theory of Anisotropic Musielak-Orlicz-Lorentz Hardy Spaces with Applications to Calder\'{o}n-Zygmund Operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06611</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06611v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\varphi: \mathbb{R}^{n}\times[0,\infty)\rightarrow[0,\infty)$ be a Musielak-Orlicz function satisfying the uniformly anisotropic Muckenhoupt condition and be of uniformly lower type $p^-_{\varphi}$ and of uniformly upper type $p^+_{\varphi}$ with $0&lt;p^-_{\varphi}\leq p^+_{\varphi}&lt;\infty$, $q\in(0,\infty]$, and $A$ be a general expansive matrix on $\mathbb{R}^{n}$. In this article, the authors first introduce the anisotropic Musielak-Orlicz-Lorentz Hardy space $H^{\varphi,q}_A(\mathbb{R}^{n})$ which, when $q=\infty$, coincides with the known anisotropic weak Musielak-Orlicz Hardy space $H^{\varphi,\infty}_A(\mathbb{R}^{n})$, and then establish atomic and molecular characterizations of $H^{\varphi,q}_A(\mathbb{R}^{n})$. As applications, the authors prove the boundedness of anisotropic Calder\'{o}n-Zygmund operators on $H^{\varphi,q}_A(\mathbb{R}^{n})$ when $q\in(0,\infty)$ or from the anisotropic Musielak-Orlicz Hardy space $H^{\varphi}_A(\mathbb{R}^{n})$ to $H^{\varphi,\infty}_A(\mathbb{R}^{n})$ in the critical case. The ranges of all the exponents under consideration are the best possible admissible ones which particularly improve all the known corresponding results for $H^{\varphi,\infty}_A(\mathbb{R}^{n})$ via widening the original assumption $0&lt;p^-_{\varphi}\leq p^+_{\varphi}\leq1$ into the full range $0&lt;p^-_{\varphi}\leq p^+_{\varphi}&lt;\infty$, and all the results when $q\in(0,\infty)$ are new and generalized from isotropic setting to anisotropic setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06611v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiong Liu, Wenhua Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Invariance of intrinsic hypercontractivity under perturbation of Schr\"odinger operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20282</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20282v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A Schr\"odinger operator that is bounded below and has a unique positive ground state can be transformed into a Dirichlet form operator by the ground state transformation. If the resulting Dirichlet form operator is hypercontractive, Davies and Simon call the Schr\"odinger operator ``intrinsically hypercontractive". I will show that if one adds a suitable potential onto an intrinsically hypercontractive Schr\"odinger operator it remains intrinsically hypercontractive. The proof uses a fortuitous relation between the WKB equation and logarithmic Sobolev inequalities. All bounds are dimension independent. The main theorem will be applied to several examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20282v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonard Gross</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounded cohomology and scl of verbal wreath products</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07438v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the bounded cohomology and the stable commutator length of verbal wreath products \(\Gamma \wr^{_W}A\), where \(A\) has trivial bounded cohomology for a sufficiently large class of coefficients. We prove that the stable commutator length always vanishes, and that the bounded cohomology vanishes in positive degrees for some such verbal wreath products; including the standard restricted wreath products (extending a recent result by Monod for lamplighters groups), as well as verbal wreath products arising from n-solvable, \(n\)-nilpotent, and \(k\)-Burnside \((k = 2, 3, 4, 6)\) verbal products. As an application, we show that every group of type \(F_p\) isometrically embeds into a group of type \(F_p\) with vanishing bounded cohomology in positive degrees for a large class of coefficients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07438v3</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elena Bogliolo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The multilinear fractional sparse operator theory II: refining weighted estimates via multilinear fractional sparse forms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17300v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper refines the main results from our previous study on sparse bounds of generalized commutators of multilinear fractional singular integral operators in \cite{CenSong2412}. The key improvements are: 1. We replace pointwise domination with the $(m+1)$-linear fractional sparse form ${\mathcal A}_{\eta,\mathcal{S},\tau,{\vec{r}},s'}^\mathbf{b,k,t}$, advancing the vector-valued multilinear fractional sparse form domination principle, and relax conditions from multilinear weak type boundedness to multilinear locally weak type boundedness $W_{\vec{p}, q}(X)$. 2. We introduce a multilinear fractional $\vec{r}$-type maximal operator $\mathscr{M}_{\eta,\vec{r}}$ and develop a new class of weights $A_{(\vec{p},q),(\vec{r}, s)}(X)$ to characterize it, establishing norm equivalence with the sparse forms. 3. This norm equivalence provides sharp quantitative weighted estimates for $(m+1)$-linear fractional sparse form, removing exponent parameter limitations and achieving sharp operator norm bounds. 4. We demonstrate applications in two ways:
  (1) Providing sharp or Bloom type estimates for generalized commutators of multilinear fractional Calder\'on--Zygmund operators and multilinear fractional rough singular integral operators.
  (2) Investigating sparse form type weighted Lebesgue $L^p(\omega)$ and weighted Sobolev $W^{s,p}(\omega)$ regularity estimates for solutions of fractional Laplacian equations with higher-order commutators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17300v4</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xi Cen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
