<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.FA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA</link>
    <description>math.FA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.FA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 05:00:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Variations on two Cabrelli's works</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.05422v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we present two different problems within the framework of shift-invariant theory. First, we develop a triangular form for shift-preserving operators acting on finitely generated shift-invariant spaces. In case of the normal operators, we recover a diagonal decomposition. The results show, in particular, that any finitely generated shift-invariant space can be decomposed into an orthogonal sum of principal shift-invariant spaces, with additional invariance properties under a shift-preserving operator. Second, we provide a new characterization of the multi-tiling sets $\Omega\subset\mathbb{R}^d$ of positive measure for which $L^2(\Omega)$ admits a structured Riesz basis of exponentials that is formulated in the ambient space $\mathbb{T}^{k\times k}$. In addition, we show a simpler sufficient condition which generalizes the admissibility property, that is also necessary for 2-tiling sets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.05422v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elona Agora, Jorge Antezana, Diana Carbajal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Unified Spectral Framework for Aging, Heterogeneous, and Distributed Order Systems via Weighted Weyl-Sonine Operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05423</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.05423v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Standard fractional calculus has successfully modeled systems with power-law memory. However, complex phenomena in heterogeneous media often exhibit multi-scale memory effects and aging properties that classical operators cannot capture. In this work, we construct a unified framework by defining the \textit{Weighted Weyl-Sonine Operators}. This formalism offers a fundamental generalization of fractional calculus, freeing the theory from the constraints of power-law memory (via Sonine kernels), time-translation invariance (via scale and weight functions), and artificial history truncation (via Weyl integration).
  The main result is a Generalized Spectral Mapping Theorem, proving that the Weighted Fourier Transform acts as a universal diagonalization map for these operators. We rigorously characterize the admissible memory kernels through the class of \textit{Complete Bernstein Functions}, ensuring that the resulting operators preserve the fundamental properties of positivity and monotonicity. Furthermore, we establish a theoretical bridge between the algebraic Sonine definition and the analytical Marchaud representation involving L\'evy measures.
  Finally, we apply this theory to solve generalized relaxation equations and \textit{Weighted Distributed Order} evolution problems, demonstrating that phenomena of ultra-slow diffusion and retarded aging can be treated explicitly within this unified spectral framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.05423v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gustavo Dorrego</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundedness of the discrete Hilbert transform on discrete weighted Morrey spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05618</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.05618v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Hilbert transform is a multiplier operator and is widely used in the theory of Fourier transforms. The Hilbert transform was the motivation for the development of modern harmonic analysis. Its discrete version is also widely used in many areas of science and technology and plays an important role in digital signal processing. The essential motivation behind thinking about discrete transforms is that experimental data are most often not taken in a continuous manner but sampled at discrete time values. Since much of the data collected in both the physical sciences and engineering are discrete, the discrete Hilbert transform is a rather useful tool in these areas for the general analysis of this type of data. In this paper, we discuss the discrete Hilbert transform on discrete Weighted Morrey spaces and obtain its boundedness in these spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.05618v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rashid Aliev, Amil Jabiyev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A simpler and more efficient fixed point iterative scheme</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.05731v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Our work presents a new iterative scheme to approximate the fixed points of nonexpansive mapping. The proposed algorithm is constructed to enhance convergence efficiency while preserving theoretical robustness. Under appropriate assumptions on the underlying operator, we establish weak convergence and strong convergence results for the generated sequence. To demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed scheme, we present a numerical example and perform a detailed comparative study with several well-known iterative methods from the literature. The numerical results clearly indicate that the proposed method exhibits a faster rate of convergence than the existing schemes, thereby confirming its computational advantage. These findings suggest that the new iterative process provides an efficient and reliable alternative for solving fixed point problems arising in applied mathematics and related fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.05731v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nida Izhar Mallick, Izhar Uddin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the spectrum of non-ergodic measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.05327v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Consider a topological dynamical system where the group is abelian and the topologies are locally compact and second-countable. Given an invariant measure for this system, we show that if its dynamical spectrum is contained in some Borel subset of the dual group then the same holds almost surely for all ergodic measures arising via the Choquet theorem. In particular, if the invariant measure has pure point dynamical spectrum, so do almost all the ergodic measures. As an application, we show that given any mean almost periodic measure, in its hull there exists a Besicovitch almost periodic measure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.05327v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Francis, Christopher Ramsey, Nicolae Strungaru</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fourier restriction for the additive Brownian sheet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.05802v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Fourier restriction problem asks when it is meaningful to restrict the Fourier transform of a function to a given set. Many of the key examples are smooth co-dimension 1 manifolds, although there is increasing interest in fractal sets. Here we propose a natural intermediary problem where one considers the fractal surface generated by the graph of the additive Brownian sheet in $\mathbb{R}^k$. We obtain the first non-trivial estimates in this direction, giving both a sufficient condition on the range of $q\in[1,2]$ for the Fourier transform to be $L^{q}(\mathbb{R}^{k+1})\to L^2(G(W))$ bounded and a necessary condition for it to be $L^{q}(\mathbb{R}^{k+1})\to L^p(G(W))$ bounded. The sufficient condition is obtained via the Fourier spectrum, which is a family of dimensions that interpolate between the Fourier and Hausdorff dimensions. Our main technical result, which is of interest in its own right, gives a precise formula for the Fourier spectrum of the natural measure on the graph of the additive Brownian sheet, and we apply this result to the Fourier restriction problem. Our restriction estimate is stronger than the estimate obtained from the well-known Stein--Tomas restriction theorem for all $k\geq3$. We obtain the necessary condition in two different ways, one via the Fourier spectrum and one via an appropriate Knapp example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.05802v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan M. Fraser, Ana E. de Orellana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Manifold limit for the training of shallow graph convolutional neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.06025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.06025v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the discrete-to-continuum consistency of the training of shallow graph convolutional neural networks (GCNNs) on proximity graphs of sampled point clouds under a manifold assumption. Graph convolution is defined spectrally via the graph Laplacian, whose low-frequency spectrum approximates that of the Laplace-Beltrami operator of the underlying smooth manifold, and shallow GCNNs of possibly infinite width are linear functionals on the space of measures on the parameter space. From this functional-analytic perspective, graph signals are seen as spatial discretizations of functions on the manifold, which leads to a natural notion of training data consistent across graph resolutions. To enable convergence results, the continuum parameter space is chosen as a weakly compact product of unit balls, with Sobolev regularity imposed on the output weight and bias, but not on the convolutional parameter. The corresponding discrete parameter spaces inherit the corresponding spectral decay, and are additionally restricted by a frequency cutoff adapted to the informative spectral window of the graph Laplacians. Under these assumptions, we prove $\Gamma$-convergence of regularized empirical risk minimization functionals and corresponding convergence of their global minimizers, in the sense of weak convergence of the parameter measures and uniform convergence of the functions over compact sets. This provides a formalization of mesh and sample independence for the training of such networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.06025v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johanna Tengler, Christoph Brune, Jos\'e A. Iglesias</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generic measures with slowly decaying Fourier coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02361v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate threshold phenomena in weighted $\ell^2$-spaces and characterize the critical regimes where elements with either small support or maximally bad range can be constructed. Our results are shown to be optimal in several respects, and our proofs principally rely on techniques involving sparse Fourier spectrum. We further show that these seemingly pathological constructions are actually generic from certain categorical perspectives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02361v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adem Limani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eigenfunctionals for positive operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10646</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10646v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish an eigenfunctional theorem for positive operators, evocative of the Krein--Rutman theorem. A more general version gives a joint eigenfunctional for commuting operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10646v4</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Monod</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equilateral dimension of the planar Banach--Mazur compactum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21478v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that there are arbitrarily large equilateral sets of planar and symmetric convex bodies in the Banach--Mazur distance. The order of the size of these $d$-equilateral sets asymptotically matches the bounds of the size of maximum-size $d$-separated sets (determined by Bronstein in 1978), showing that our construction is essentially optimal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21478v2</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomasz Kobos, Konrad Swanepoel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conditional means, vector pricings, amenability and fixed points in cones</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13829v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study a generalization of conditional probability for arbitrary ordered vector spaces. A related problem is that of assigning a numerical value to one vector relative to another.
  We characterize the groups for which these generalized probabilities can be stationary, respectively invariant. Our results deviate from the setting of classical probability; this leads to a new criterion for amenability and for fixed points in cones.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13829v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Monod</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
