<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.IV updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.IV</link>
    <description>eess.IV updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.IV" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 05:00:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>SAM-I2I: Unleash the Power of Segment Anything Model for Medical Image Translation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12755v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Medical image translation is crucial for reducing the need for redundant and expensive multi-modal imaging in clinical field. However, current approaches based on Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs) and Transformers often fail to capture fine-grain semantic features, resulting in suboptimal image quality. To address this challenge, we propose SAM-I2I, a novel image-to-image translation framework based on the Segment Anything Model 2 (SAM2). SAM-I2I utilizes a pre-trained image encoder to extract multiscale semantic features from the source image and a decoder, based on the mask unit attention module, to synthesize target modality images. Our experiments on multi-contrast MRI datasets demonstrate that SAM-I2I outperforms state-of-the-art methods, offering more efficient and accurate medical image translation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12755v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiayu Huo, Sebastien Ourselin, Rachel Sparks</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FedCL-Ensemble Learning: A Framework of Federated Continual Learning with Ensemble Transfer Learning Enhanced for Alzheimer's MRI Classifications while Preserving Privacy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12756v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This research work introduces a novel approach to the classification of Alzheimer's disease by using the advanced deep learning techniques combined with secure data processing methods. This research work primary uses transfer learning models such as ResNet, ImageNet, and VNet to extract high-level features from medical image data. Thereafter, these pre-trained models were fine-tuned for Alzheimer's related subtle patterns such that the model is capable of robust feature extraction over varying data sources. Further, the federated learning approaches were incorporated to tackle a few other challenges related to classification, aimed to provide better prediction performance and protect data privacy. The proposed model was built using federated learning without sharing sensitive patient data. This way, the decentralized model benefits from the large and diversified dataset that it is trained upon while ensuring confidentiality. The cipher-based encryption mechanism is added that allows us to secure the transportation of data and further ensure the privacy and integrity of patient information throughout training and classification. The results of the experiments not only help to improve the accuracy of the classification of Alzheimer's but at the same time provides a framework for secure and collaborative analysis of health care data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12756v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rishit Kapoor (Vellore Institute of Technology), Jesher Joshua (Vellore Institute of Technology), Muralidharan Vijayarangan (Vellore Institute of Technology), Natarajan B (Vellore Institute of Technology)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cross-Layer Encrypted Semantic Communication Framework for Panoramic Video Transmission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12776v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a cross-layer encrypted semantic communication (CLESC) framework for panoramic video transmission, incorporating feature extraction, encoding, encryption, cyclic redundancy check (CRC), and retransmission processes to achieve compatibility between semantic communication and traditional communication systems. Additionally, we propose an adaptive cross-layer transmission mechanism that dynamically adjusts CRC, channel coding, and retransmission schemes based on the importance of semantic information. This ensures that important information is prioritized under poor transmission conditions. To verify the aforementioned framework, we also design an end-to-end adaptive panoramic video semantic transmission (APVST) network that leverages a deep joint source-channel coding (Deep JSCC) structure and attention mechanism, integrated with a latitude adaptive module that facilitates adaptive semantic feature extraction and variable-length encoding of panoramic videos. The proposed CLESC is also applicable to the transmission of other modal data. Simulation results demonstrate that the proposed CLESC effectively achieves compatibility and adaptation between semantic communication and traditional communication systems, improving both transmission efficiency and channel adaptability. Compared to traditional cross-layer transmission schemes, the CLESC framework can reduce bandwidth consumption by 85% while showing significant advantages under low signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12776v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haixiao Gao, Mengying Sun, Xiaodong Xu, Bingxuan Xu, Shujun Han, Bizhu Wang, Sheng Jiang, Chen Dong, Ping Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Medicinal Image Transmission and Resolution Enhancement via GAN</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12833v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: While X-ray imaging is indispensable in medical diagnostics, it inherently carries with it those noises and limitations on resolution that mask the details necessary for diagnosis. B/W X-ray images require a careful balance between noise suppression and high-detail preservation to ensure clarity in soft-tissue structures and bone edges. While traditional methods, such as CNNs and early super-resolution models like ESRGAN, have enhanced image resolution, they often perform poorly regarding high-frequency detail preservation and noise control for B/W imaging. We are going to present one efficient approach that improves the quality of an image with the optimization of network transmission in the following paper. The pre-processing of X-ray images into low-resolution files by Real-ESRGAN, a version of ESRGAN elucidated and improved, helps reduce the server load and transmission bandwidth. Lower-resolution images are upscaled at the receiving end using Real-ESRGAN, fine-tuned for real-world image degradation. The model integrates Residual-in-Residual Dense Blocks with perceptual and adversarial loss functions for high-quality upscaled images with low noise. We further fine-tune Real-ESRGAN by adapting it to the specific B/W noise and contrast characteristics. This suppresses noise artifacts without compromising detail. The comparative evaluation conducted shows that our approach achieves superior noise reduction and detail clarity compared to state-of-the-art CNN-based and ESRGAN models, apart from reducing network bandwidth requirements. These benefits are confirmed both by quantitative metrics, including Peak Signal-to-Noise Ratio and Structural Similarity Index, and by qualitative assessments, which indicate the potential of Real-ESRGAN for diagnostic-quality X-ray imaging and for efficient medical data transmission.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12833v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rishabh Kumar Sharma, Mukund Sharma, Pushkar Sharma, Jeetashree Aparjeeta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Residual Vision Transformer (ResViT) Based Self-Supervised Learning Model for Brain Tumor Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12874v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Deep learning has proven very promising for interpreting MRI in brain tumor diagnosis. However, deep learning models suffer from a scarcity of brain MRI datasets for effective training. Self-supervised learning (SSL) models provide data-efficient and remarkable solutions to limited dataset problems. Therefore, this paper introduces a generative SSL model for brain tumor classification in two stages. The first stage is designed to pre-train a Residual Vision Transformer (ResViT) model for MRI synthesis as a pretext task. The second stage includes fine-tuning a ResViT-based classifier model as a downstream task. Accordingly, we aim to leverage local features via CNN and global features via ViT, employing a hybrid CNN-transformer architecture for ResViT in pretext and downstream tasks. Moreover, synthetic MRI images are utilized to balance the training set. The proposed model performs on public BraTs 2023, Figshare, and Kaggle datasets. Furthermore, we compare the proposed model with various deep learning models, including A-UNet, ResNet-9, pix2pix, pGAN for MRI synthesis, and ConvNeXtTiny, ResNet101, DenseNet12, Residual CNN, ViT for classification. According to the results, the proposed model pretraining on the MRI dataset is superior compared to the pretraining on the ImageNet dataset. Overall, the proposed model attains the highest accuracy, achieving 90.56% on the BraTs dataset with T1 sequence, 98.53% on the Figshare, and 98.47% on the Kaggle brain tumor datasets. As a result, the proposed model demonstrates a robust, effective, and successful approach to handling insufficient dataset challenges in MRI analysis by incorporating SSL, fine-tuning, data augmentation, and combining CNN and ViT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12874v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meryem Altin Karagoz, O. Ufuk Nalbantoglu, Geoffrey C. Fox</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Deep Learning-Driven Multi-Coil MRI Reconstruction via Self-Supervised Denoising</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12919v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We examine the effect of incorporating self-supervised denoising as a pre-processing step for training deep learning (DL) based reconstruction methods on data corrupted by Gaussian noise. K-space data employed for training are typically multi-coil and inherently noisy. Although DL-based reconstruction methods trained on fully sampled data can enable high reconstruction quality, obtaining large, noise-free datasets is impractical. We leverage Generalized Stein's Unbiased Risk Estimate (GSURE) for denoising. We evaluate two DL-based reconstruction methods: Diffusion Probabilistic Models (DPMs) and Model-Based Deep Learning (MoDL). We evaluate the impact of denoising on the performance of these DL-based methods in solving accelerated multi-coil magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) reconstruction. The experiments were carried out on T2-weighted brain and fat-suppressed proton-density knee scans. We observed that self-supervised denoising enhances the quality and efficiency of MRI reconstructions across various scenarios. Specifically, employing denoised images rather than noisy counterparts when training DL networks results in lower normalized root mean squared error (NRMSE), higher structural similarity index measure (SSIM) and peak signal-to-noise ratio (PSNR) across different SNR levels, including 32dB, 22dB, and 12dB for T2-weighted brain data, and 24dB, 14dB, and 4dB for fat-suppressed knee data. Overall, we showed that denoising is an essential pre-processing technique capable of improving the efficacy of DL-based MRI reconstruction methods under diverse conditions. By refining the quality of input data, denoising can enable the training of more effective DL networks, potentially bypassing the need for noise-free reference MRI scans.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12919v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Asad Aali, Marius Arvinte, Sidharth Kumar, Yamin I. Arefeen, Jonathan I. Tamir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automating Sonologists USG Commands with AI and Voice Interface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13006</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13006v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This research presents an advanced AI-powered ultrasound imaging system that incorporates real-time image processing, organ tracking, and voice commands to enhance the efficiency and accuracy of diagnoses in clinical practice. Traditional ultrasound diagnostics often require significant time and introduce a degree of subjectivity due to user interaction. The goal of this innovative solution is to provide Sonologists with a more predictable and productive imaging procedure utilizing artificial intelligence, computer vision, and voice technology. The functionality of the system employs computer vision and deep learning algorithms, specifically adopting the Mask R-CNN model from Detectron2 for semantic segmentation of organs and key landmarks. This automation improves diagnostic accuracy by enabling the extraction of valuable information with minimal human input. Additionally, it includes a voice recognition feature that allows for hands-free operation, enabling users to control the system with commands such as freeze or liver, all while maintaining their focus on the patient. The architecture comprises video processing and real-time segmentation modules that prepare the system to perform essential imaging functions, such as freezing and zooming in on frames. The liver histopathology module, optimized for detecting fibrosis, achieved an impressive accuracy of 98.6%. Furthermore, the organ segmentation module produces output confidence levels between 50% and 95%, demonstrating its efficacy in organ detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13006v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emad Mohamed, Shruti Tiwari, Sheena Christabel Pravin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Training Physics-Driven Deep Learning Reconstruction without Raw Data Access for Equitable Fast MRI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13022v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Physics-driven deep learning (PD-DL) approaches have become popular for improved reconstruction of fast magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans. Even though PD-DL offers higher acceleration rates compared to existing clinical fast MRI techniques, their use has been limited outside specialized MRI centers. One impediment for their deployment is the difficulties with generalization to pathologies or population groups that are not well-represented in training sets. This has been noted in several studies, and fine-tuning on target populations to improve reconstruction has been suggested. However, current approaches for PD-DL training require access to raw k-space measurements, which is typically only available at specialized MRI centers that have research agreements for such data access. This is especially an issue for rural and underserved areas, where commercial MRI scanners only provide access to a final reconstructed image. To tackle these challenges, we propose Compressibility-inspired Unsupervised Learning via Parallel Imaging Fidelity (CUPID) for high-quality PD-DL training, using only routine clinical reconstructed images exported from an MRI scanner. CUPID evaluates the goodness of the output with a compressibility-based approach, while ensuring that the output stays consistent with the clinical parallel imaging reconstruction through well-designed perturbations. Our results show that CUPID achieves similar quality compared to well-established PD-DL training strategies that require raw k-space data access, while outperforming conventional compressed sensing (CS) and state-of-the-art generative methods. We also demonstrate its effectiveness in a zero-shot training setup for retrospectively and prospectively sub-sampled acquisitions, attesting to its minimal training burden.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13022v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ya\c{s}ar Utku Al\c{c}alar, Merve G\"ulle, Mehmet Ak\c{c}akaya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LMM-driven Semantic Image-Text Coding for Ultra Low-bitrate Learned Image Compression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13033v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Supported by powerful generative models, low-bitrate learned image compression (LIC) models utilizing perceptual metrics have become feasible. Some of the most advanced models achieve high compression rates and superior perceptual quality by using image captions as sub-information. This paper demonstrates that using a large multi-modal model (LMM), it is possible to generate captions and compress them within a single model. We also propose a novel semantic-perceptual-oriented fine-tuning method applicable to any LIC network, resulting in a 41.58\% improvement in LPIPS BD-rate compared to existing methods. Our implementation and pre-trained weights are available at https://github.com/tokkiwa/ImageTextCoding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13033v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shimon Murai, Heming Sun, Jiro Katto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demonstrating the Suitability of Neuromorphic, Event-Based, Dynamic Vision Sensors for In Process Monitoring of Metallic Additive Manufacturing and Welding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13108</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13108v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate the suitability of high dynamic range, high-speed, neuromorphic event-based, dynamic vision sensors for metallic additive manufacturing and welding for in-process monitoring applications. In-process monitoring to enable quality control of mission critical components produced using metallic additive manufacturing is of high interest. However, the extreme light environment and high speed dynamics of metallic melt pools have made this a difficult environment in which to make measurements. Event-based sensing is an alternative measurement paradigm where data is only transmitted/recorded when a measured quantity exceeds a threshold resolution. The result is that event-based sensors consume less power and less memory/bandwidth, and they operate across a wide range of timescales and dynamic ranges. Event-driven driven imagers stand out from conventional imager technology in that they have a very high dynamic range of approximately 120 dB. Conventional 8 bit imagers only have a dynamic range of about 48 dB. This high dynamic range makes them a good candidate for monitoring manufacturing processes that feature high intensity light sources/generation such as metallic additive manufacturing and welding. In addition event based imagers are able to capture data at timescales on the order of 100 {\mu}s, which makes them attractive to capturing fast dynamics in a metallic melt pool. In this work we demonstrate that event-driven imagers have been shown to be able to observe tungsten inert gas (TIG) and laser welding melt pools. The results of this effort suggest that with additional engineering effort, neuromorphic event imagers should be capable of 3D geometry measurements of the melt pool, and anomaly detection/classification/prediction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13108v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-031-68192-9_7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Modal Analysis Conference, Orlando, FL, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>David Mascare\~nas, Andre Green, Ashlee Liao, Michael Torrez, Alessandro Cattaneo, Amber Black, John Bernardin, Garrett Kenyon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intensity-Spatial Dual Masked Autoencoder for Multi-Scale Feature Learning in Chest CT Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13198v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the field of medical image segmentation, challenges such as indistinct lesion features, ambiguous boundaries,and multi-scale characteristics have long revailed. This paper proposes an improved method named Intensity-Spatial Dual Masked AutoEncoder (ISD-MAE). Based on the tissue-contrast semi-masked autoencoder, a Masked AutoEncoder (MAE) branch is introduced to perform intensity masking and spatial masking operations on chest CT images for multi-scale feature learning and segmentation tasks. The model utilizes a dual-branch structure and contrastive learning to enhance the ability to learn tissue features and boundary details. Experiments are conducted on multiple 2D and 3D datasets. The results show that ISD-MAE significantly outperforms other methods in 2D pneumonia and mediastinal tumor segmentation tasks. For example, the Dice score reaches 90.10% on the COVID19 LESION dataset, and the performance is relatively stable. However, there is still room for improvement on 3D datasets. In response to this, improvement directions are proposed, including optimizing the loss function, using enhanced 3D convolution blocks, and processing datasets from multiple perspectives.Our code is available at:https://github.com/prowontheus/ISD-MAE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13198v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuexing Ding, Jun Wang, Hongbing Lyu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OceanLens: An Adaptive Backscatter and Edge Correction using Deep Learning Model for Enhanced Underwater Imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13230v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Underwater environments pose significant challenges due to the selective absorption and scattering of light by water, which affects image clarity, contrast, and color fidelity. To overcome these, we introduce OceanLens, a method that models underwater image physics-encompassing both backscatter and attenuation-using neural networks. Our model incorporates adaptive backscatter and edge correction losses, specifically Sobel and LoG losses, to manage image variance and luminance, resulting in clearer and more accurate outputs. Additionally, we demonstrate the relevance of pre-trained monocular depth estimation models for generating underwater depth maps. Our evaluation compares the performance of various loss functions against state-of-the-art methods using the SeeThru dataset, revealing significant improvements. Specifically, we observe an average of 65% reduction in Grayscale Patch Mean Angular Error (GPMAE) and a 60% increase in the Underwater Image Quality Metric (UIQM) compared to the SeeThru and DeepSeeColor methods. Further, the results were improved with additional convolution layers that capture subtle image details more effectively with OceanLens. This architecture is validated on the UIEB dataset, with model performance assessed using Peak Signal-to-Noise Ratio (PSNR) and Structural Similarity Index Measure (SSIM) metrics. OceanLens with multiple convolutional layers achieves up to 12-15% improvement in the SSIM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13230v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rajini Makam, Dhatri Shankari T M, Sharanya Patil, Suresh Sundram</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RTSR: A Real-Time Super-Resolution Model for AV1 Compressed Content</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13362v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Super-resolution (SR) is a key technique for improving the visual quality of video content by increasing its spatial resolution while reconstructing fine details. SR has been employed in many applications including video streaming, where compressed low-resolution content is typically transmitted to end users and then reconstructed with a higher resolution and enhanced quality. To support real-time playback, it is important to implement fast SR models while preserving reconstruction quality; however most existing solutions, in particular those based on complex deep neural networks, fail to do so. To address this issue, this paper proposes a low-complexity SR method, RTSR, designed to enhance the visual quality of compressed video content, focusing on resolution up-scaling from a) 360p to 1080p and from b) 540p to 4K. The proposed approach utilizes a CNN-based network architecture, which was optimized for AV1 (SVT)-encoded content at various quantization levels based on a dual-teacher knowledge distillation method. This method was submitted to the AIM 2024 Video Super-Resolution Challenge, specifically targeting the Efficient/Mobile Real-Time Video Super-Resolution competition. It achieved the best trade-off between complexity and coding performance (measured in PSNR, SSIM and VMAF) among all six submissions. The code will be available soon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13362v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxuan Jiang, Jakub Nawa{\l}a, Chen Feng, Fan Zhang, Xiaoqing Zhu, Joel Sole, David Bull</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adversarial Diffusion Compression for Real-World Image Super-Resolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13383v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Real-world image super-resolution (Real-ISR) aims to reconstruct high-resolution images from low-resolution inputs degraded by complex, unknown processes. While many Stable Diffusion (SD)-based Real-ISR methods have achieved remarkable success, their slow, multi-step inference hinders practical deployment. Recent SD-based one-step networks like OSEDiff and S3Diff alleviate this issue but still incur high computational costs due to their reliance on large pretrained SD models. This paper proposes a novel Real-ISR method, AdcSR, by distilling the one-step diffusion network OSEDiff into a streamlined diffusion-GAN model under our Adversarial Diffusion Compression (ADC) framework. We meticulously examine the modules of OSEDiff, categorizing them into two types: (1) Removable (VAE encoder, prompt extractor, text encoder, etc.) and (2) Prunable (denoising UNet and VAE decoder). Since direct removal and pruning can degrade the model's generation capability, we pretrain our pruned VAE decoder to restore its ability to decode images and employ adversarial distillation to compensate for performance loss. This ADC-based diffusion-GAN hybrid design effectively reduces complexity by 73% in inference time, 78% in computation, and 74% in parameters, while preserving the model's generation capability. Experiments manifest that our proposed AdcSR achieves competitive recovery quality on both synthetic and real-world datasets, offering up to 9.3$\times$ speedup over previous one-step diffusion-based methods. Code and models will be made available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13383v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bin Chen, Gehui Li, Rongyuan Wu, Xindong Zhang, Jie Chen, Jian Zhang, Lei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Brain Imaging Analysis for Alzheimer's and Dementia Detection Using Convolution-Derivative Operations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13490v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Alzheimer's disease (AD) is characterized by progressive neurodegeneration and results in detrimental structural changes in human brains. Detecting these changes is crucial for early diagnosis and timely intervention of disease progression. Jacobian maps, derived from spatial normalization in voxel-based morphometry (VBM), have been instrumental in interpreting volume alterations associated with AD. However, the computational cost of generating Jacobian maps limits its clinical adoption. In this study, we explore alternative methods and propose Sobel kernel angle difference (SKAD) as a computationally efficient alternative. SKAD is a derivative operation that offers an optimized approach to quantifying volumetric alterations through localized analysis of the gradients. By efficiently extracting gradient amplitude changes at critical spatial regions, this derivative operation captures regional volume variations Evaluation of SKAD over various medical datasets demonstrates that it is 6.3x faster than Jacobian maps while still maintaining comparable accuracy. This makes it an efficient and competitive approach in neuroimaging research and clinical practice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13490v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yasmine Mustafa, Mohamed Elmahallawy, Tie Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparative Analysis of Machine Learning and Deep Learning Models for Classifying Squamous Epithelial Cells of the Cervix</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13535v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The cervix is the narrow end of the uterus that connects to the vagina in the female reproductive system. Abnormal cell growth in the squamous epithelial lining of the cervix leads to cervical cancer in females. A Pap smear is a diagnostic procedure used to detect cervical cancer by gently collecting cells from the surface of the cervix with a small brush and analyzing their changes under a microscope. For population-based cervical cancer screening, visual inspection with acetic acid is a cost-effective method with high sensitivity. However, Pap smears are also suitable for mass screening due to their higher specificity. The current Pap smear analysis method is manual, time-consuming, labor-intensive, and prone to human error. Therefore, an artificial intelligence (AI)-based approach for automatic cell classification is needed. In this study, we aimed to classify cells in Pap smear images into five categories: superficial-intermediate, parabasal, koilocytes, dyskeratotic, and metaplastic. Various machine learning (ML) algorithms, including Gradient Boosting, Random Forest, Support Vector Machine, and k-Nearest Neighbor, as well as deep learning (DL) approaches like ResNet-50, were employed for this classification task. The ML models demonstrated high classification accuracy; however, ResNet-50 outperformed the others, achieving a classification accuracy of 93.06%. This study highlights the efficiency of DL models for cell-level classification and their potential to aid in the early diagnosis of cervical cancer from Pap smear images.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13535v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhasish Das, Satish K Panda, Madhusmita Sethy, Prajna Paramita Giri, Ashwini K Nanda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mitigating Perception Bias: A Training-Free Approach to Enhance LMM for Image Quality Assessment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12791v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Despite the impressive performance of large multimodal models (LMMs) in high-level visual tasks, their capacity for image quality assessment (IQA) remains limited. One main reason is that LMMs are primarily trained for high-level tasks (e.g., image captioning), emphasizing unified image semantics extraction under varied quality. Such semantic-aware yet quality-insensitive perception bias inevitably leads to a heavy reliance on image semantics when those LMMs are forced for quality rating. In this paper, instead of retraining or tuning an LMM costly, we propose a training-free debiasing framework, in which the image quality prediction is rectified by mitigating the bias caused by image semantics. Specifically, we first explore several semantic-preserving distortions that can significantly degrade image quality while maintaining identifiable semantics. By applying these specific distortions to the query or test images, we ensure that the degraded images are recognized as poor quality while their semantics remain. During quality inference, both a query image and its corresponding degraded version are fed to the LMM along with a prompt indicating that the query image quality should be inferred under the condition that the degraded one is deemed poor quality.This prior condition effectively aligns the LMM's quality perception, as all degraded images are consistently rated as poor quality, regardless of their semantic difference.Finally, the quality scores of the query image inferred under different prior conditions (degraded versions) are aggregated using a conditional probability model. Extensive experiments on various IQA datasets show that our debiasing framework could consistently enhance the LMM performance and the code will be publicly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12791v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siyi Pan, Baoliang Chen, Danni Huang, Hanwei Zhu, Lingyu Zhu, Xiangjie Sui, Shiqi Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Fairness in AI for Melanoma Detection: Systemic Review and Recommendations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12846</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12846v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Early and accurate melanoma detection is crucial for improving patient outcomes. Recent advancements in artificial intelligence AI have shown promise in this area, but the technologys effectiveness across diverse skin tones remains a critical challenge. This study conducts a systematic review and preliminary analysis of AI based melanoma detection research published between 2013 and 2024, focusing on deep learning methodologies, datasets, and skin tone representation. Our findings indicate that while AI can enhance melanoma detection, there is a significant bias towards lighter skin tones. To address this, we propose including skin hue in addition to skin tone as represented by the LOreal Color Chart Map for a more comprehensive skin tone assessment technique. This research highlights the need for diverse datasets and robust evaluation metrics to develop AI models that are equitable and effective for all patients. By adopting best practices outlined in a PRISMA Equity framework tailored for healthcare and melanoma detection, we can work towards reducing disparities in melanoma outcomes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12846v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laura N Montoya, Jennafer Shae Roberts, Belen Sanchez Hidalgo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Attentive Contextual Attention for Cloud Removal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13042</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13042v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cloud cover can significantly hinder the use of remote sensing images for Earth observation, prompting urgent advancements in cloud removal technology. Recently, deep learning strategies have shown strong potential in restoring cloud-obscured areas. These methods utilize convolution to extract intricate local features and attention mechanisms to gather long-range information, improving the overall comprehension of the scene. However, a common drawback of these approaches is that the resulting images often suffer from blurriness, artifacts, and inconsistencies. This is partly because attention mechanisms apply weights to all features based on generalized similarity scores, which can inadvertently introduce noise and irrelevant details from cloud-covered areas. To overcome this limitation and better capture relevant distant context, we introduce a novel approach named Attentive Contextual Attention (AC-Attention). This method enhances conventional attention mechanisms by dynamically learning data-driven attentive selection scores, enabling it to filter out noise and irrelevant features effectively. By integrating the AC-Attention module into the DSen2-CR cloud removal framework, we significantly improve the model's ability to capture essential distant information, leading to more effective cloud removal. Our extensive evaluation of various datasets shows that our method outperforms existing ones regarding image reconstruction quality. Additionally, we conducted ablation studies by integrating AC-Attention into multiple existing methods and widely used network architectures. These studies demonstrate the effectiveness and adaptability of AC-Attention and reveal its ability to focus on relevant features, thereby improving the overall performance of the networks. The code is available at \url{https://github.com/huangwenwenlili/ACA-CRNet}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13042v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenli Huang, Ye Deng, Yang Wu, Jinjun Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Practical Compact Deep Compressed Sensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13081</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13081v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent years have witnessed the success of deep networks in compressed sensing (CS), which allows for a significant reduction in sampling cost and has gained growing attention since its inception. In this paper, we propose a new practical and compact network dubbed PCNet for general image CS. Specifically, in PCNet, a novel collaborative sampling operator is designed, which consists of a deep conditional filtering step and a dual-branch fast sampling step. The former learns an implicit representation of a linear transformation matrix into a few convolutions and first performs adaptive local filtering on the input image, while the latter then uses a discrete cosine transform and a scrambled block-diagonal Gaussian matrix to generate under-sampled measurements. Our PCNet is equipped with an enhanced proximal gradient descent algorithm-unrolled network for reconstruction. It offers flexibility, interpretability, and strong recovery performance for arbitrary sampling rates once trained. Additionally, we provide a deployment-oriented extraction scheme for single-pixel CS imaging systems, which allows for the convenient conversion of any linear sampling operator to its matrix form to be loaded onto hardware like digital micro-mirror devices. Extensive experiments on natural image CS, quantized CS, and self-supervised CS demonstrate the superior reconstruction accuracy and generalization ability of PCNet compared to existing state-of-the-art methods, particularly for high-resolution images. Code is available at https://github.com/Guaishou74851/PCNet.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13081v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bin Chen, Jian Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis and Synthesis Denoisers for Forward-Backward Plug-and-Play Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13276</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13276v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work we study the behavior of the forward-backward (FB) algorithm when the proximity operator is replaced by a sub-iterative procedure to approximate a Gaussian denoiser, in a Plug-and-Play (PnP) fashion. In particular, we consider both analysis and synthesis Gaussian denoisers within a dictionary framework, obtained by unrolling dual-FB iterations or FB iterations, respectively. We analyze the associated minimization problems as well as the asymptotic behavior of the resulting FB-PnP iterations. In particular, we show that the synthesis Gaussian denoising problem can be viewed as a proximity operator. For each case, analysis and synthesis, we show that the FB-PnP algorithms solve the same problem whether we use only one or an infinite number of sub-iteration to solve the denoising problem at each iteration. To this aim, we show that each "one sub-iteration" strategy within the FB-PnP can be interpreted as a primal-dual algorithm when a warm-restart strategy is used. We further present similar results when using a Moreau-Yosida smoothing of the global problem, for an arbitrary number of sub-iterations. Finally, we provide numerical simulations to illustrate our theoretical results. In particular we first consider a toy compressive sensing example, as well as an image restoration problem in a deep dictionary framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13276v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthieu Kowalski, Beno\^it Mal\'ezieux, Thomas Moreau, Audrey Repetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rotation Equivariant Proximal Operator for Deep Unfolding Methods in Image Restoration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.15701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.15701v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The deep unfolding approach has attracted significant attention in computer vision tasks, which well connects conventional image processing modeling manners with more recent deep learning techniques. Specifically, by establishing a direct correspondence between algorithm operators at each implementation step and network modules within each layer, one can rationally construct an almost ``white box'' network architecture with high interpretability. In this architecture, only the predefined component of the proximal operator, known as a proximal network, needs manual configuration, enabling the network to automatically extract intrinsic image priors in a data-driven manner. In current deep unfolding methods, such a proximal network is generally designed as a CNN architecture, whose necessity has been proven by a recent theory. That is, CNN structure substantially delivers the translational invariant image prior, which is the most universally possessed structural prior across various types of images. However, standard CNN-based proximal networks have essential limitations in capturing the rotation symmetry prior, another universal structural prior underlying general images. This leaves a large room for further performance improvement in deep unfolding approaches. To address this issue, this study makes efforts to suggest a high-accuracy rotation equivariant proximal network that effectively embeds rotation symmetry priors into the deep unfolding framework. Especially, we deduce, for the first time, the theoretical equivariant error for such a designed proximal network with arbitrary layers under arbitrary rotation degrees. This analysis should be the most refined theoretical conclusion for such error evaluation to date and is also indispensable for supporting the rationale behind such networks with intrinsic interpretability requirements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.15701v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TPAMI.2024.3383532</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jiahong Fu, Qi Xie, Deyu Meng, Zongben Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CPGA: Coding Priors-Guided Aggregation Network for Compressed Video Quality Enhancement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10362v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, numerous approaches have achieved notable success in compressed video quality enhancement (VQE). However, these methods usually ignore the utilization of valuable coding priors inherently embedded in compressed videos, such as motion vectors and residual frames, which carry abundant temporal and spatial information. To remedy this problem, we propose the Coding Priors-Guided Aggregation (CPGA) network to utilize temporal and spatial information from coding priors. The CPGA mainly consists of an inter-frame temporal aggregation (ITA) module and a multi-scale non-local aggregation (MNA) module. Specifically, the ITA module aggregates temporal information from consecutive frames and coding priors, while the MNA module globally captures spatial information guided by residual frames. In addition, to facilitate research in VQE task, we newly construct the Video Coding Priors (VCP) dataset, comprising 300 videos with various coding priors extracted from corresponding bitstreams. It remedies the shortage of previous datasets on the lack of coding information. Experimental results demonstrate the superiority of our method compared to existing state-of-the-art methods. The code and dataset will be released at https://github.com/VQE-CPGA/CPGA.git .</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10362v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiang Zhu, Jinhua Hao, Yukang Ding, Yu Liu, Qiao Mo, Ming Sun, Chao Zhou, Shuyuan Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demons registration for 2D empirical wavelet transforms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13075v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The empirical wavelet transform is a fully adaptive time-scale representation that has been widely used in the last decade. Inspired by the empirical mode decomposition, it consists of filter banks based on harmonic mode supports. Recently, it has been generalized to build the filter banks from any generating function using mappings. In practice, the harmonic mode supports can have low constrained shape in 2D, leading to numerical difficulties to compute the mappings and therefore the related wavelet filters. This work aims to propose an efficient numerical scheme to compute empirical wavelet coefficients using the demons registration algorithm. Results show that the proposed approach gives a numerically robust wavelet transform. An application to texture segmentation of scanning tunnelling microscope images is also presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13075v3</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charles-G\'erard Lucas, J\'er\^ome Gilles</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ONCOPILOT: A Promptable CT Foundation Model For Solid Tumor Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07908v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Carcinogenesis is a proteiform phenomenon, with tumors emerging in various locations and displaying complex, diverse shapes. At the crucial intersection of research and clinical practice, it demands precise and flexible assessment. However, current biomarkers, such as RECIST 1.1's long and short axis measurements, fall short of capturing this complexity, offering an approximate estimate of tumor burden and a simplistic representation of a more intricate process. Additionally, existing supervised AI models face challenges in addressing the variability in tumor presentations, limiting their clinical utility. These limitations arise from the scarcity of annotations and the models' focus on narrowly defined tasks.
  To address these challenges, we developed ONCOPILOT, an interactive radiological foundation model trained on approximately 7,500 CT scans covering the whole body, from both normal anatomy and a wide range of oncological cases. ONCOPILOT performs 3D tumor segmentation using visual prompts like point-click and bounding boxes, outperforming state-of-the-art models (e.g., nnUnet) and achieving radiologist-level accuracy in RECIST 1.1 measurements. The key advantage of this foundation model is its ability to surpass state-of-the-art performance while keeping the radiologist in the loop, a capability that previous models could not achieve. When radiologists interactively refine the segmentations, accuracy improves further. ONCOPILOT also accelerates measurement processes and reduces inter-reader variability, facilitating volumetric analysis and unlocking new biomarkers for deeper insights.
  This AI assistant is expected to enhance the precision of RECIST 1.1 measurements, unlock the potential of volumetric biomarkers, and improve patient stratification and clinical care, while seamlessly integrating into the radiological workflow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07908v4</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L\'eo Machado, H\'el\`ene Philippe, \'Elodie Ferreres, Julien Khlaut, Julie Dupuis, Korentin Le Floch, Denis Habip Gatenyo, Pascal Roux, Jules Gr\'egory, Maxime Ronot, Corentin Dancette, Tom Boeken, Daniel Tordjman, Pierre Manceron, Paul H\'erent</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DINO-LG: A Task-Specific DINO Model for Coronary Calcium Scoring</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07976</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07976v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Coronary artery disease (CAD), one of the most common cause of mortality in the world. Coronary artery calcium (CAC) scoring using computed tomography (CT) is key for risk assessment to prevent coronary disease. Previous studies on risk assessment and calcification detection in CT scans primarily use approaches based on UNET architecture, frequently implemented on pre-built models. However, these models are limited by the availability of annotated CT scans containing CAC and suffering from imbalanced dataset, decreasing performance of CAC segmentation and scoring. In this study, we extend this approach by incorporating the self-supervised learning (SSL) technique of DINO (self-distillation with no labels) to eliminate limitations of scarce annotated data in CT scans. The DINO model's ability to train without requiring CAC area annotations enhances its robustness in generating distinct features. The DINO model is trained on to focus specifically on calcified areas by using labels, aiming to generate features that effectively capture and highlight key characteristics. The label-guided DINO (DINO-LG) enhances classification by distinguishing CT slices that contain calcification from those that do not, performing 57% better than the standard DINO model in this task. CAC scoring and segmentation tasks are performed by a basic U-NET architecture, fed specifically with CT slices containing calcified areas as identified by the DINO-LG model. This targeted identification performed by DINO-LG model improves CAC segmentation performance by approximately 10% and significant increase in CAC scoring accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07976v4</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahmut S. Gokmen, Caner Ozcan, Cody Bumgardner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perspective-Equivariance for Unsupervised Imaging with Camera Geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09327v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Ill-posed image reconstruction problems appear in many scenarios such as remote sensing, where obtaining high quality images is crucial for environmental monitoring, disaster management and urban planning. Deep learning has seen great success in overcoming the limitations of traditional methods. However, these inverse problems rarely come with ground truth data, highlighting the importance of unsupervised learning from partial and noisy measurements alone. We propose perspective-equivariant imaging (EI), a framework that leverages classical projective camera geometry in optical imaging systems, such as satellites or handheld cameras, to recover information lost in ill-posed camera imaging problems. We show that our much richer non-linear class of group transforms, derived from camera geometry, generalises previous EI work and is an excellent prior for satellite and urban image data. Perspective-EI achieves state-of-the-art results in multispectral pansharpening, outperforming other unsupervised methods in the literature. Code at https://github.com/Andrewwango/perspective-equivariant-imaging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09327v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Wang, Mike Davies</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Occlusion-Aware Seamless Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02182</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02182v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Panoramic images can broaden the Field of View (FoV), occlusion-aware prediction can deepen the understanding of the scene, and domain adaptation can transfer across viewing domains. In this work, we introduce a novel task, Occlusion-Aware Seamless Segmentation (OASS), which simultaneously tackles all these three challenges. For benchmarking OASS, we establish a new human-annotated dataset for Blending Panoramic Amodal Seamless Segmentation, i.e., BlendPASS. Besides, we propose the first solution UnmaskFormer, aiming at unmasking the narrow FoV, occlusions, and domain gaps all at once. Specifically, UnmaskFormer includes the crucial designs of Unmasking Attention (UA) and Amodal-oriented Mix (AoMix). Our method achieves state-of-the-art performance on the BlendPASS dataset, reaching a remarkable mAPQ of 26.58% and mIoU of 43.66%. On public panoramic semantic segmentation datasets, i.e., SynPASS and DensePASS, our method outperforms previous methods and obtains 45.34% and 48.08% in mIoU, respectively. The fresh BlendPASS dataset and our source code are available at https://github.com/yihong-97/OASS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02182v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yihong Cao, Jiaming Zhang, Hao Shi, Kunyu Peng, Yuhongxuan Zhang, Hui Zhang, Rainer Stiefelhagen, Kailun Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
