<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.IV updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.IV</link>
    <description>eess.IV updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.IV" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 04:00:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>LSST: Learned Single-Shot Trajectory and Reconstruction Network for MR Imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07457</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07457v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Single-shot magnetic resonance (MR) imaging acquires the entire k-space data in a single shot and it has various applications in whole-body imaging. However, the long acquisition time for the entire k-space in single-shot fast spin echo (SSFSE) MR imaging poses a challenge, as it introduces T2-blur in the acquired images. This study aims to enhance the reconstruction quality of SSFSE MR images by (a) optimizing the trajectory for measuring the k-space, (b) acquiring fewer samples to speed up the acquisition process, and (c) reducing the impact of T2-blur. The proposed method adheres to physics constraints due to maximum gradient strength and slew-rate available while optimizing the trajectory within an end-to-end learning framework. Experiments were conducted on publicly available fastMRI multichannel dataset with 8-fold and 16-fold acceleration factors. An experienced radiologist's evaluation on a five-point Likert scale indicates improvements in the reconstruction quality as the ACL fibers are sharper than comparative methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07457v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hemant Kumar Aggarwal, Sudhanya Chatterjee, Dattesh Shanbhag, Uday Patil, K. V. S. Hari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TabMixer: Noninvasive Estimation of the Mean Pulmonary Artery Pressure via Imaging and Tabular Data Mixing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07564v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Right Heart Catheterization is a gold standard procedure for diagnosing Pulmonary Hypertension by measuring mean Pulmonary Artery Pressure (mPAP). It is invasive, costly, time-consuming and carries risks. In this paper, for the first time, we explore the estimation of mPAP from videos of noninvasive Cardiac Magnetic Resonance Imaging. To enhance the predictive capabilities of Deep Learning models used for this task, we introduce an additional modality in the form of demographic features and clinical measurements. Inspired by all-Multilayer Perceptron architectures, we present TabMixer, a novel module enabling the integration of imaging and tabular data through spatial, temporal and channel mixing. Specifically, we present the first approach that utilizes Multilayer Perceptrons to interchange tabular information with imaging features in vision models. We test TabMixer for mPAP estimation and show that it enhances the performance of Convolutional Neural Networks, 3D-MLP and Vision Transformers while being competitive with previous modules for imaging and tabular data. Our approach has the potential to improve clinical processes involving both modalities, particularly in noninvasive mPAP estimation, thus, significantly enhancing the quality of life for individuals affected by Pulmonary Hypertension. We provide a source code for using TabMixer at https://github.com/SanoScience/TabMixer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07564v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michal K. Grzeszczyk, Przemys{\l}aw Korzeniowski, Samer Alabed, Andrew J. Swift, Tomasz Trzci\'nski, Arkadiusz Sitek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DS-ViT: Dual-Stream Vision Transformer for Cross-Task Distillation in Alzheimer's Early Diagnosis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07584v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the field of Alzheimer's disease diagnosis, segmentation and classification tasks are inherently interconnected. Sharing knowledge between models for these tasks can significantly improve training efficiency, particularly when training data is scarce. However, traditional knowledge distillation techniques often struggle to bridge the gap between segmentation and classification due to the distinct nature of tasks and different model architectures. To address this challenge, we propose a dual-stream pipeline that facilitates cross-task and cross-architecture knowledge sharing. Our approach introduces a dual-stream embedding module that unifies feature representations from segmentation and classification models, enabling dimensional integration of these features to guide the classification model. We validated our method on multiple 3D datasets for Alzheimer's disease diagnosis, demonstrating significant improvements in classification performance, especially on small datasets. Furthermore, we extended our pipeline with a residual temporal attention mechanism for early diagnosis, utilizing images taken before the atrophy of patients' brain mass. This advancement shows promise in enabling diagnosis approximately six months earlier in mild and asymptomatic stages, offering critical time for intervention.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07584v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ke Chen, Yifeng Wang, Yufei Zhou, Haohan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Context-Aware Optimal Transport Learning for Retinal Fundus Image Enhancement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07862v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Retinal fundus photography offers a non-invasive way to diagnose and monitor a variety of retinal diseases, but is prone to inherent quality glitches arising from systemic imperfections or operator/patient-related factors. However, high-quality retinal images are crucial for carrying out accurate diagnoses and automated analyses. The fundus image enhancement is typically formulated as a distribution alignment problem, by finding a one-to-one mapping between a low-quality image and its high-quality counterpart. This paper proposes a context-informed optimal transport (OT) learning framework for tackling unpaired fundus image enhancement. In contrast to standard generative image enhancement methods, which struggle with handling contextual information (e.g., over-tampered local structures and unwanted artifacts), the proposed context-aware OT learning paradigm better preserves local structures and minimizes unwanted artifacts. Leveraging deep contextual features, we derive the proposed context-aware OT using the earth mover's distance and show that the proposed context-OT has a solid theoretical guarantee. Experimental results on a large-scale dataset demonstrate the superiority of the proposed method over several state-of-the-art supervised and unsupervised methods in terms of signal-to-noise ratio, structural similarity index, as well as two downstream tasks. The code is available at \url{https://github.com/Retinal-Research/Contextual-OT}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07862v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vamsi Krishna Vasa, Peijie Qiu, Wenhui Zhu, Yujian Xiong, Oana Dumitrascu, Yalin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OCTAMamba: A State-Space Model Approach for Precision OCTA Vasculature Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08000v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optical Coherence Tomography Angiography (OCTA) is a crucial imaging technique for visualizing retinal vasculature and diagnosing eye diseases such as diabetic retinopathy and glaucoma. However, precise segmentation of OCTA vasculature remains challenging due to the multi-scale vessel structures and noise from poor image quality and eye lesions. In this study, we proposed OCTAMamba, a novel U-shaped network based on the Mamba architecture, designed to segment vasculature in OCTA accurately. OCTAMamba integrates a Quad Stream Efficient Mining Embedding Module for local feature extraction, a Multi-Scale Dilated Asymmetric Convolution Module to capture multi-scale vasculature, and a Focused Feature Recalibration Module to filter noise and highlight target areas. Our method achieves efficient global modeling and local feature extraction while maintaining linear complexity, making it suitable for low-computation medical applications. Extensive experiments on the OCTA 3M, OCTA 6M, and ROSSA datasets demonstrated that OCTAMamba outperforms state-of-the-art methods, providing a new reference for efficient OCTA segmentation. Code is available at https://github.com/zs1314/OCTAMamba</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08000v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shun Zou, Zhuo Zhang, Guangwei Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AutoPET Challenge: Tumour Synthesis for Data Augmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08068</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08068v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate lesion segmentation in whole-body PET/CT scans is crucial for cancer diagnosis and treatment planning, but limited datasets often hinder the performance of automated segmentation models. In this paper, we explore the potential of leveraging the deep prior from a generative model to serve as a data augmenter for automated lesion segmentation in PET/CT scans. We adapt the DiffTumor method, originally designed for CT images, to generate synthetic PET-CT images with lesions. Our approach trains the generative model on the AutoPET dataset and uses it to expand the training data. We then compare the performance of segmentation models trained on the original and augmented datasets. Our findings show that the model trained on the augmented dataset achieves a higher Dice score, demonstrating the potential of our data augmentation approach. In a nutshell, this work presents a promising direction for improving lesion segmentation in whole-body PET/CT scans with limited datasets, potentially enhancing the accuracy and reliability of cancer diagnostics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08068v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lap Yan Lennon Chan, Chenxin Li, Yixuan Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The JPEG Pleno Learning-based Point Cloud Coding Standard: Serving Man and Machine</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08130</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08130v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Efficient point cloud coding has become increasingly critical for multiple applications such as virtual reality, autonomous driving, and digital twin systems, where rich and interactive 3D data representations may functionally make the difference. Deep learning has emerged as a powerful tool in this domain, offering advanced techniques for compressing point clouds more efficiently than conventional coding methods while also allowing effective computer vision tasks performed in the compressed domain thus, for the first time, making available a common compressed visual representation effective for both man and machine. Taking advantage of this potential, JPEG has recently finalized the JPEG Pleno Learning-based Point Cloud Coding (PCC) standard offering efficient lossy coding of static point clouds, targeting both human visualization and machine processing by leveraging deep learning models for geometry and color coding. The geometry is processed directly in its original 3D form using sparse convolutional neural networks, while the color data is projected onto 2D images and encoded using the also learning-based JPEG AI standard. The goal of this paper is to provide a complete technical description of the JPEG PCC standard, along with a thorough benchmarking of its performance against the state-of-the-art, while highlighting its main strengths and weaknesses. In terms of compression performance, JPEG PCC outperforms the conventional MPEG PCC standards, especially in geometry coding, achieving significant rate reductions. Color compression performance is less competitive but this is overcome by the power of a full learning-based coding framework for both geometry and color and the associated effective compressed domain processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08130v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'e F. R. Guarda (Instituto de Telecomunica\c{c}\~oes, Lisbon, Portugal), Nuno M. M. Rodrigues (Instituto de Telecomunica\c{c}\~oes, Lisbon, Portugal, ESTG, Polit\'ecnico de Leiria, Leiria, Portugal), Fernando Pereira (Instituto de Telecomunica\c{c}\~oes, Lisbon, Portugal, Instituto Superior T\'ecnico - Universidade de Lisboa, Lisbon, Portugal)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective Segmentation of Post-Treatment Gliomas Using Simple Approaches: Artificial Sequence Generation and Ensemble Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08143v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Segmentation is a crucial task in the medical imaging field and is often an important primary step or even a prerequisite to the analysis of medical volumes. Yet treatments such as surgery complicate the accurate delineation of regions of interest. The BraTS Post-Treatment 2024 Challenge published the first public dataset for post-surgery glioma segmentation and addresses the aforementioned issue by fostering the development of automated segmentation tools for glioma in MRI data. In this effort, we propose two straightforward approaches to enhance the segmentation performances of deep learning-based methodologies. First, we incorporate an additional input based on a simple linear combination of the available MRI sequences input, which highlights enhancing tumors. Second, we employ various ensembling methods to weigh the contribution of a battery of models. Our results demonstrate that these approaches significantly improve segmentation performance compared to baseline models, underscoring the effectiveness of these simple approaches in improving medical image segmentation tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08143v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heejong Kim, Leo Milecki, Mina C Moghadam, Fengbei Liu, Minh Nguyen, Eric Qiu, Abhishek Thanki, Mert R Sabuncu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AD-Lite Net: A Lightweight and Concatenated CNN Model for Alzheimer's Detection from MRI Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08170v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Alzheimer's Disease (AD) is a non-curable progressive neurodegenerative disorder that affects the human brain, leading to a decline in memory, cognitive abilities, and eventually, the ability to carry out daily tasks. Manual diagnosis of Alzheimer's disease from MRI images is fraught with less sensitivity and it is a very tedious process for neurologists. Therefore, there is a need for an automatic Computer Assisted Diagnosis (CAD) system, which can detect AD at early stages with higher accuracy. In this research, we have proposed a novel AD-Lite Net model (trained from scratch), that could alleviate the aforementioned problem. The novelties we bring here in this research are, (I) We have proposed a very lightweight CNN model by incorporating Depth Wise Separable Convolutional (DWSC) layers and Global Average Pooling (GAP) layers. (II) We have leveraged a ``parallel concatenation block'' (pcb), in the proposed AD-Lite Net model. This pcb consists of a Transformation layer (Tx-layer), followed by two convolutional layers, which are thereby concatenated with the original base model. This Tx-layer converts the features into very distinct kind of features, which are imperative for the Alzheimer's disease. As a consequence, the proposed AD-Lite Net model with ``parallel concatenation'' converges faster and automatically mitigates the class imbalance problem from the MRI datasets in a very generalized way. For the validity of our proposed model, we have implemented it on three different MRI datasets. Furthermore, we have combined the ADNI and AD datasets and subsequently performed a 10-fold cross-validation experiment to verify the model's generalization ability. Extensive experimental results showed that our proposed model has outperformed all the existing CNN models, and one recent trend Vision Transformer (ViT) model by a significant margin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08170v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Santanu Roy, Archit Gupta, Shubhi Tiwari, Palak Sahu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model Ensemble for Brain Tumor Segmentation in Magnetic Resonance Imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08232</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08232v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Segmenting brain tumors in multi-parametric magnetic resonance imaging enables performing quantitative analysis in support of clinical trials and personalized patient care. This analysis provides the potential to impact clinical decision-making processes, including diagnosis and prognosis. In 2023, the well-established Brain Tumor Segmentation (BraTS) challenge presented a substantial expansion with eight tasks and 4,500 brain tumor cases. In this paper, we present a deep learning-based ensemble strategy that is evaluated for newly included tumor cases in three tasks: pediatric brain tumors (PED), intracranial meningioma (MEN), and brain metastases (MET). In particular, we ensemble outputs from state-of-the-art nnU-Net and Swin UNETR models on a region-wise basis. Furthermore, we implemented a targeted post-processing strategy based on a cross-validated threshold search to improve the segmentation results for tumor sub-regions. The evaluation of our proposed method on unseen test cases for the three tasks resulted in lesion-wise Dice scores for PED: 0.653, 0.809, 0.826; MEN: 0.876, 0.867, 0.849; and MET: 0.555, 0.6, 0.58; for the enhancing tumor, tumor core, and whole tumor, respectively. Our method was ranked first for PED, third for MEN, and fourth for MET, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08232v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Capell\'an-Mart\'in, Zhifan Jiang, Abhijeet Parida, Xinyang Liu, Van Lam, Hareem Nisar, Austin Tapp, Sarah Elsharkawi, Maria J. Ledesma-Carbayo, Syed Muhammad Anwar, Marius George Linguraru</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feature Importance in Pedestrian Intention Prediction: A Context-Aware Review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07645</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07645v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent advancements in predicting pedestrian crossing intentions for Autonomous Vehicles using Computer Vision and Deep Neural Networks are promising. However, the black-box nature of DNNs poses challenges in understanding how the model works and how input features contribute to final predictions. This lack of interpretability delimits the trust in model performance and hinders informed decisions on feature selection, representation, and model optimisation; thereby affecting the efficacy of future research in the field. To address this, we introduce Context-aware Permutation Feature Importance (CAPFI), a novel approach tailored for pedestrian intention prediction. CAPFI enables more interpretability and reliable assessments of feature importance by leveraging subdivided scenario contexts, mitigating the randomness of feature values through targeted shuffling. This aims to reduce variance and prevent biased estimations in importance scores during permutations. We divide the Pedestrian Intention Estimation (PIE) dataset into 16 comparable context sets, measure the baseline performance of five distinct neural network architectures for intention prediction in each context, and assess input feature importance using CAPFI. We observed nuanced differences among models across various contextual characteristics. The research reveals the critical role of pedestrian bounding boxes and ego-vehicle speed in predicting pedestrian intentions, and potential prediction biases due to the speed feature through cross-context permutation evaluation. We propose an alternative feature representation by considering proximity change rate for rendering dynamic pedestrian-vehicle locomotion, thereby enhancing the contributions of input features to intention prediction. These findings underscore the importance of contextual features and their diversity to develop accurate and robust intent-predictive models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07645v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohsen Azarmi, Mahdi Rezaei, He Wang, Ali Arabian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DreamBeast: Distilling 3D Fantastical Animals with Part-Aware Knowledge Transfer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08271v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present DreamBeast, a novel method based on score distillation sampling (SDS) for generating fantastical 3D animal assets composed of distinct parts. Existing SDS methods often struggle with this generation task due to a limited understanding of part-level semantics in text-to-image diffusion models. While recent diffusion models, such as Stable Diffusion 3, demonstrate a better part-level understanding, they are prohibitively slow and exhibit other common problems associated with single-view diffusion models. DreamBeast overcomes this limitation through a novel part-aware knowledge transfer mechanism. For each generated asset, we efficiently extract part-level knowledge from the Stable Diffusion 3 model into a 3D Part-Affinity implicit representation. This enables us to instantly generate Part-Affinity maps from arbitrary camera views, which we then use to modulate the guidance of a multi-view diffusion model during SDS to create 3D assets of fantastical animals. DreamBeast significantly enhances the quality of generated 3D creatures with user-specified part compositions while reducing computational overhead, as demonstrated by extensive quantitative and qualitative evaluations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08271v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Runjia Li, Junlin Han, Luke Melas-Kyriazi, Chunyi Sun, Zhaochong An, Zhongrui Gui, Shuyang Sun, Philip Torr, Tomas Jakab</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Object Segmentation-Assisted Inter Prediction for Versatile Video Coding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11694</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11694v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In modern video coding standards, block-based inter prediction is widely adopted, which brings high compression efficiency. However, in natural videos, there are usually multiple moving objects of arbitrary shapes, resulting in complex motion fields that are difficult to represent compactly. This problem has been tackled by more flexible block partitioning methods in the Versatile Video Coding (VVC) standard, but the more flexible partitions require more overhead bits to signal and still cannot be made arbitrarily shaped. To address this limitation, we propose an object segmentation-assisted inter prediction method (SAIP), where objects in the reference frames are segmented by some advanced technologies. With a proper indication, the object segmentation mask is translated from the reference frame to the current frame as the arbitrary-shaped partition of different regions without any extra signal. Using the segmentation mask, motion compensation is separately performed for different regions, achieving higher prediction accuracy. The segmentation mask is further used to code the motion vectors of different regions more efficiently. Moreover, the segmentation mask is considered in the joint rate-distortion optimization for motion estimation and partition estimation to derive the motion vector of different regions and partition more accurately. The proposed method is implemented into the VVC reference software, VTM version 12.0. Experimental results show that the proposed method achieves up to 1.98%, 1.14%, 0.79%, and on average 0.82%, 0.49%, 0.37% BD-rate reduction for common test sequences, under the Low-delay P, Low-delay B, and Random Access configurations, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11694v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TBC.2024.3434520</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Zhuoyuan Li, Zikun Yuan, Li Li, Dong Liu, Xiaohu Tang, Feng Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Factual Serialization Enhancement: A Key Innovation for Chest X-ray Report Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09586v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A radiology report comprises presentation-style vocabulary, which ensures clarity and organization, and factual vocabulary, which provides accurate and objective descriptions based on observable findings. While manually writing these reports is time-consuming and labor-intensive, automatic report generation offers a promising alternative. A critical step in this process is to align radiographs with their corresponding reports. However, existing methods often rely on complete reports for alignment, overlooking the impact of presentation-style vocabulary. To address this issue, we propose FSE, a two-stage Factual Serialization Enhancement method. In Stage 1, we introduce factuality-guided contrastive learning for visual representation by maximizing the semantic correspondence between radiographs and corresponding factual descriptions. In Stage 2, we present evidence-driven report generation that enhances diagnostic accuracy by integrating insights from similar historical cases structured as factual serialization. Experiments on MIMIC-CXR and IU X-ray datasets across specific and general scenarios demonstrate that FSE outperforms state-of-the-art approaches in both natural language generation and clinical efficacy metrics. Ablation studies further emphasize the positive effects of factual serialization in Stage 1 and Stage 2. The code is available at https://github.com/mk-runner/FSE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09586v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kang Liu, Zhuoqi Ma, Mengmeng Liu, Zhicheng Jiao, Xiaolu Kang, Qiguang Miao, Kun Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zero-Shot Whole Slide Image Retrieval in Histopathology Using Embeddings of Foundation Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04631v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We have tested recently published foundation models for histopathology for image retrieval. We report macro average of F1 score for top-1 retrieval, majority of top-3 retrievals, and majority of top-5 retrievals. We perform zero-shot retrievals, i.e., we do not alter embeddings and we do not train any classifier. As test data, we used diagnostic slides of TCGA, The Cancer Genome Atlas, consisting of 23 organs and 117 cancer subtypes. As a search platform we used Yottixel that enabled us to perform WSI search using patches. Achieved F1 scores show low performance, e.g., for top-5 retrievals, 27% +/- 13% (Yottixel-DenseNet), 42% +/- 14% (Yottixel-UNI), 40%+/-13% (Yottixel-Virchow), 41%+/-13% (Yottixel-GigaPath), and 41%+/-14% (GigaPath WSI).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04631v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saghir Alfasly, Ghazal Alabtah, Sobhan Hemati, Krishna Rani Kalari, H. R. Tizhoosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detailed delineation of the fetal brain in diffusion MRI via multi-task learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.06716</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.06716v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Diffusion-weighted MRI is increasingly used to study the normal and abnormal development of fetal brain in-utero. Recent studies have shown that dMRI can offer invaluable insights into the neurodevelopmental processes in the fetal stage. However, because of the low data quality and rapid brain development, reliable analysis of fetal dMRI data requires dedicated computational methods that are currently unavailable. The lack of automated methods for fast, accurate, and reproducible data analysis has seriously limited our ability to tap the potential of fetal brain dMRI for medical and scientific applications. In this work, we developed and validated a unified computational framework to (1) segment the brain tissue into white matter, cortical/subcortical gray matter, and cerebrospinal fluid, (2) segment 31 distinct white matter tracts, and (3) parcellate the brain's cortex and delineate the deep gray nuclei and white matter structures into 96 anatomically meaningful regions. We utilized a set of manual, semi-automatic, and automatic approaches to annotate 97 fetal brains. Using these labels, we developed and validated a multi-task deep learning method to perform the three computations. Our evaluations show that the new method can accurately carry out all three tasks, achieving a mean Dice similarity coefficient of 0.865 on tissue segmentation, 0.825 on white matter tract segmentation, and 0.819 on parcellation. The proposed method can greatly advance the field of fetal neuroimaging as it can lead to substantial improvements in fetal brain tractography, tract-specific analysis, and structural connectivity assessment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.06716v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davood Karimi, Camilo Calixto, Haykel Snoussi, Maria Camila Cortes-Albornoz, Clemente Velasco-Annis, Caitlin Rollins, Camilo Jaimes, Ali Gholipour, Simon K. Warfield</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3DGCQA: A Quality Assessment Database for 3D AI-Generated Contents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07236</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07236v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Although 3D generated content (3DGC) offers advantages in reducing production costs and accelerating design timelines, its quality often falls short when compared to 3D professionally generated content. Common quality issues frequently affect 3DGC, highlighting the importance of timely and effective quality assessment. Such evaluations not only ensure a higher standard of 3DGCs for end-users but also provide critical insights for advancing generative technologies. To address existing gaps in this domain, this paper introduces a novel 3DGC quality assessment dataset, 3DGCQA, built using 7 representative Text-to-3D generation methods. During the dataset's construction, 50 fixed prompts are utilized to generate contents across all methods, resulting in the creation of 313 textured meshes that constitute the 3DGCQA dataset. The visualization intuitively reveals the presence of 6 common distortion categories in the generated 3DGCs. To further explore the quality of the 3DGCs, subjective quality assessment is conducted by evaluators, whose ratings reveal significant variation in quality across different generation methods. Additionally, several objective quality assessment algorithms are tested on the 3DGCQA dataset. The results expose limitations in the performance of existing algorithms and underscore the need for developing more specialized quality assessment methods. To provide a valuable resource for future research and development in 3D content generation and quality assessment, the dataset has been open-sourced in https://github.com/zyj-2000/3DGCQA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07236v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yingjie Zhou, Zicheng Zhang, Farong Wen, Jun Jia, Yanwei Jiang, Xiaohong Liu, Xiongkuo Min, Guangtao Zhai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Domain Adaptive Semantic Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.13254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.13254v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Unsupervised Domain Adaptive Semantic Segmentation (UDA-SS) aims to transfer the supervision from a labeled source domain to an unlabeled target domain. The majority of existing UDA-SS works typically consider images whilst recent attempts have extended further to tackle videos by modeling the temporal dimension. Although the two lines of research share the major challenges -- overcoming the underlying domain distribution shift, their studies are largely independent, resulting in fragmented insights, a lack of holistic understanding, and missed opportunities for cross-pollination of ideas. This fragmentation prevents the unification of methods, leading to redundant efforts and suboptimal knowledge transfer across image and video domains. Under this observation, we advocate unifying the study of UDA-SS across video and image scenarios, enabling a more comprehensive understanding, synergistic advancements, and efficient knowledge sharing. To that end, we explore the unified UDA-SS from a general data augmentation perspective, serving as a unifying conceptual framework, enabling improved generalization, and potential for cross-pollination of ideas, ultimately contributing to the overall progress and practical impact of this field of research. Specifically, we propose a Quad-directional Mixup (QuadMix) method, characterized by tackling distinct point attributes and feature inconsistencies through four-directional paths for intra- and inter-domain mixing in a feature space. To deal with temporal shifts with videos, we incorporate optical flow-guided feature aggregation across spatial and temporal dimensions for fine-grained domain alignment. Extensive experiments show that our method outperforms the state-of-the-art works by large margins on four challenging UDA-SS benchmarks. Our source code and models will be released at \url{https://github.com/ZHE-SAPI/UDASS}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.13254v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhe Zhang, Gaochang Wu, Jing Zhang, Xiatian Zhu, Dacheng Tao, Tianyou Chai</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
