<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.IV updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.IV</link>
    <description>eess.IV updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.IV" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 02:46:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Diff-GO$^\text{n}$: Enhancing Diffusion Models for Goal-Oriented Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06980v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The rapid expansion of edge devices and Internet-of-Things (IoT) continues to heighten the demand for data transport under limited spectrum resources. The goal-oriented communications (GO-COM), unlike traditional communication systems designed for bit-level accuracy, prioritizes more critical information for specific application goals at the receiver. To improve the efficiency of generative learning models for GO-COM, this work introduces a novel noise-restricted diffusion-based GO-COM (Diff-GO$^\text{n}$) framework for reducing bandwidth overhead while preserving the media quality at the receiver. Specifically, we propose an innovative Noise-Restricted Forward Diffusion (NR-FD) framework to accelerate model training and reduce the computation burden for diffusion-based GO-COMs by leveraging a pre-sampled pseudo-random noise bank (NB). Moreover, we design an early stopping criterion for improving computational efficiency and convergence speed, allowing high-quality generation in fewer training steps. Our experimental results demonstrate superior perceptual quality of data transmission at a reduced bandwidth usage and lower computation, making Diff-GO$^\text{n}$ well-suited for real-time communications and downstream applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06980v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suchinthaka Wanninayaka (University of California at Davis, USA), Achintha Wijesinghe (University of California at Davis, USA), Weiwei Wang (University of California at Davis, USA), Yu-Chieh Chao (University of California at Davis, USA), Songyang Zhang (University of Louisiana at Lafayette, USA), Zhi Ding (University of California at Davis, USA)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light Field Image Quality Assessment With Auxiliary Learning Based on Depthwise and Anglewise Separable Convolutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07079v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In multimedia broadcasting, no-reference image quality assessment (NR-IQA) is used to indicate the user-perceived quality of experience (QoE) and to support intelligent data transmission while optimizing user experience. This paper proposes an improved no-reference light field image quality assessment (NR-LFIQA) metric for future immersive media broadcasting services. First, we extend the concept of depthwise separable convolution (DSC) to the spatial domain of light field image (LFI) and introduce "light field depthwise separable convolution (LF-DSC)", which can extract the LFI's spatial features efficiently. Second, we further theoretically extend the LF-DSC to the angular space of LFI and introduce the novel concept of "light field anglewise separable convolution (LF-ASC)", which is capable of extracting both the spatial and angular features for comprehensive quality assessment with low complexity. Third, we define the spatial and angular feature estimations as auxiliary tasks in aiding the primary NR-LFIQA task by providing spatial and angular quality features as hints. To the best of our knowledge, this work is the first exploration of deep auxiliary learning with spatial-angular hints on NR-LFIQA. Experiments were conducted in mainstream LFI datasets such as Win5-LID and SMART with comparisons to the mainstream full reference IQA metrics as well as the state-of-the-art NR-LFIQA methods. The experimental results show that the proposed metric yields overall 42.86% and 45.95% smaller prediction errors than the second-best benchmarking metric in Win5-LID and SMART, respectively. In some challenging cases with particular distortion types, the proposed metric can reduce the errors significantly by more than 60%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07079v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TBC.2021.3099737</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Transactions on Broadcasting, vol. 67, no. 4, pp. 837-850, Dec. 2021</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Qiang Qu, Xiaoming Chen, Vera Chung, Zhibo Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>User Authentication and Vital Signs Extraction from Low-Frame-Rate and Monochrome No-contact Fingerprint Captures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07082v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present our work on leveraging low-frame-rate monochrome (blue light) videos of fingertips, captured with an off-the-shelf fingerprint capture device, to extract vital signs and identify users. These videos utilize photoplethysmography (PPG), commonly used to measure vital signs like heart rate. While prior research predominantly utilizes high-frame-rate, multi-wavelength PPG sensors (e.g., infrared, red, or RGB), our preliminary findings demonstrate that both user identification and vital sign extraction are achievable with the low-frame-rate data we collected. Preliminary results are promising, with low error rates for both heart rate estimation and user authentication. These results indicate promise for effective biometric systems. We anticipate further optimization will enhance accuracy and advance healthcare and security.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07082v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olaoluwayimika Olugbenle, Logan Drake, Naveenkumar G. Venkataswamy, Arfina Rahman, Yemi Afolayanka, Masudul Imtiaz, Mahesh K. Banavar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QCResUNet: Joint Subject-level and Voxel-level Segmentation Quality Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07156v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Deep learning has made significant strides in automated brain tumor segmentation from magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans in recent years. However, the reliability of these tools is hampered by the presence of poor-quality segmentation outliers, particularly in out-of-distribution samples, making their implementation in clinical practice difficult. Therefore, there is a need for quality control (QC) to screen the quality of the segmentation results. Although numerous automatic QC methods have been developed for segmentation quality screening, most were designed for cardiac MRI segmentation, which involves a single modality and a single tissue type. Furthermore, most prior works only provided subject-level predictions of segmentation quality and did not identify erroneous parts segmentation that may require refinement. To address these limitations, we proposed a novel multi-task deep learning architecture, termed QCResUNet, which produces subject-level segmentation-quality measures as well as voxel-level segmentation error maps for each available tissue class. To validate the effectiveness of the proposed method, we conducted experiments on assessing its performance on evaluating the quality of two distinct segmentation tasks. First, we aimed to assess the quality of brain tumor segmentation results. For this task, we performed experiments on one internal and two external datasets. Second, we aimed to evaluate the segmentation quality of cardiac Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) data from the Automated Cardiac Diagnosis Challenge. The proposed method achieved high performance in predicting subject-level segmentation-quality metrics and accurately identifying segmentation errors on a voxel basis. This has the potential to be used to guide human-in-the-loop feedback to improve segmentations in clinical settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07156v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peijie Qiu, Satrajit Chakrabarty, Phuc Nguyen, Soumyendu Sekhar Ghosh, Aristeidis Sotiras</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Dual-Exposure Quad-Bayer Patterns for Joint Denoising and Deblurring</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07256</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07256v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Image degradation caused by noise and blur remains a persistent challenge in imaging systems, stemming from limitations in both hardware and methodology. Single-image solutions face an inherent tradeoff between noise reduction and motion blur. While short exposures can capture clear motion, they suffer from noise amplification. Long exposures reduce noise but introduce blur. Learning-based single-image enhancers tend to be over-smooth due to the limited information. Multi-image solutions using burst mode avoid this tradeoff by capturing more spatial-temporal information but often struggle with misalignment from camera/scene motion. To address these limitations, we propose a physical-model-based image restoration approach leveraging a novel dual-exposure Quad-Bayer pattern sensor. By capturing pairs of short and long exposures at the same starting point but with varying durations, this method integrates complementary noise-blur information within a single image. We further introduce a Quad-Bayer synthesis method (B2QB) to simulate sensor data from Bayer patterns to facilitate training. Based on this dual-exposure sensor model, we design a hierarchical convolutional neural network called QRNet to recover high-quality RGB images. The network incorporates input enhancement blocks and multi-level feature extraction to improve restoration quality. Experiments demonstrate superior performance over state-of-the-art deblurring and denoising methods on both synthetic and real-world datasets. The code, model, and datasets are publicly available at https://github.com/zhaoyuzhi/QRNet.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07256v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TIP.2024.3515873</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yuzhi Zhao, Lai-Man Po, Xin Ye, Yongzhe Xu, Qiong Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Label up: Learning Pulmonary Embolism Segmentation from Image Level Annotation through Model Explainability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07384</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07384v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Pulmonary Embolisms (PE) are a leading cause of cardiovascular death. Computed tomographic pulmonary angiography (CTPA) stands as the gold standard for diagnosing pulmonary embolisms (PE) and there has been a lot of interest in developing AI-based models for assisting in PE diagnosis. Performance of these algorithms has been hindered by the scarcity of annotated data, especially those with fine-grained delineation of the thromboembolic burden. In this paper we attempt to address this issue by introducing a weakly supervised learning pipeline, that leverages model explainability to generate fine-grained (pixel level) masks for embolisms starting from more coarse-grained (binary, image level) PE annotations. Furthermore, we show that training models using the automatically generated pixel annotations yields good PE localization performance. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our pipeline on the large-scale, multi-center RSPECT augmented dataset for PE detection and localization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07384v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Florin Condrea, Saikiran Rapaka, Marius Leordeanu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced MRI Representation via Cross-series Masking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07387</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07387v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) is indispensable for diagnosing and planning treatment in various medical conditions due to its ability to produce multi-series images that reveal different tissue characteristics. However, integrating these diverse series to form a coherent analysis presents significant challenges, such as differing spatial resolutions and contrast patterns meanwhile requiring extensive annotated data, which is scarce in clinical practice. Due to these issues, we introduce a novel Cross-Series Masking (CSM) Strategy for effectively learning MRI representation in a self-supervised manner. Specifically, CSM commences by randomly sampling a subset of regions and series, which are then strategically masked. In the training process, the cross-series representation is learned by utilizing the unmasked data to reconstruct the masked portions. This process not only integrates information across different series but also facilitates the ability to model both intra-series and inter-series correlations and complementarities. With the learned representation, the downstream tasks like segmentation and classification are also enhanced. Taking brain tissue segmentation, breast tumor benign/malignant classification, and prostate cancer diagnosis as examples, our method achieves state-of-the-art performance on both public and in-house datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07387v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Churan Wang, Fei Gao, Lijun Yan, Siwen Wang, Yizhou Yu, Yizhou Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KneeXNeT: An Ensemble-Based Approach for Knee Radiographic Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07526v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Knee osteoarthritis (OA) is the most common joint disorder and a leading cause of disability. Diagnosing OA severity typically requires expert assessment of X-ray images and is commonly based on the Kellgren-Lawrence grading system, a time-intensive process. This study aimed to develop an automated deep learning model to classify knee OA severity, reducing the need for expert evaluation. First, we evaluated ten state-of-the-art deep learning models, achieving a top accuracy of 0.69 with individual models. To address class imbalance, we employed weighted sampling, improving accuracy to 0.70. We further applied Smooth-GradCAM++ to visualize decision-influencing regions, enhancing the explainability of the best-performing model. Finally, we developed ensemble models using majority voting and a shallow neural network. Our ensemble model, KneeXNet, achieved the highest accuracy of 0.72, demonstrating its potential as an automated tool for knee OA assessment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07526v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicharee Srikijkasemwat, Soumya Snigdha Kundu, Fuping Wu, Bartlomiej W. Papiez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Motion Artifact Removal in Pixel-Frequency Domain via Alternate Masks and Diffusion Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07590v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motion artifacts present in magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) can seriously interfere with clinical diagnosis. Removing motion artifacts is a straightforward solution and has been extensively studied. However, paired data are still heavily relied on in recent works and the perturbations in k-space (frequency domain) are not well considered, which limits their applications in the clinical field. To address these issues, we propose a novel unsupervised purification method which leverages pixel-frequency information of noisy MRI images to guide a pre-trained diffusion model to recover clean MRI images. Specifically, considering that motion artifacts are mainly concentrated in high-frequency components in k-space, we utilize the low-frequency components as the guide to ensure correct tissue textures. Additionally, given that high-frequency and pixel information are helpful for recovering shape and detail textures, we design alternate complementary masks to simultaneously destroy the artifact structure and exploit useful information. Quantitative experiments are performed on datasets from different tissues and show that our method achieves superior performance on several metrics. Qualitative evaluations with radiologists also show that our method provides better clinical feedback. Our code is available at https://github.com/medcx/PFAD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07590v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiahua Xu, Dawei Zhou, Lei Hu, Jianfeng Guo, Feng Yang, Zaiyi Liu, Nannan Wang, Xinbo Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Closed-Form Approximation of the Total Variation Proximal Operator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07718</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07718v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Total variation (TV) is a widely used function for regularizing imaging inverse problems that is particularly appropriate for images whose underlying structure is piecewise constant. TV regularized optimization problems are typically solved using proximal methods, but the way in which they are applied is constrained by the absence of a closed-form expression for the proximal operator of the TV function. A closed-form approximation of the TV proximal operator has previously been proposed, but its accuracy was not theoretically explored in detail. We address this gap by making several new theoretical contributions, proving that the approximation leads to a proximal operator of some convex function, that it always decreases the TV function, and that its error can be fully characterized and controlled with its scaling parameter. We experimentally validate our theoretical results on image denoising and sparse-view computed tomography (CT) image reconstruction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07718v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Edward P. Chandler, Shirin Shoushtari, Brendt Wohlberg, Ulugbek S. Kamilov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SKIPNet: Spatial Attention Skip Connections for Enhanced Brain Tumor Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07736v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Early detection of brain tumors through magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) is essential for timely treatment, yet access to diagnostic facilities remains limited in remote areas. Gliomas, the most common primary brain tumors, arise from the carcinogenesis of glial cells in the brain and spinal cord, with glioblastoma patients having a median survival time of less than 14 months. MRI serves as a non-invasive and effective method for tumor detection, but manual segmentation of brain MRI scans has traditionally been a labor-intensive task for neuroradiologists. Recent advancements in computer-aided design (CAD), machine learning (ML), and deep learning (DL) offer promising solutions for automating this process. This study proposes an automated deep learning model for brain tumor detection and classification using MRI data. The model, incorporating spatial attention, achieved 96.90% accuracy, enhancing the aggregation of contextual information for better pattern recognition. Experimental results demonstrate that the proposed approach outperforms baseline models, highlighting its robustness and potential for advancing automated MRI-based brain tumor analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07736v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Khush Mendiratta (Indian Institute of Technology Roorkee), Shweta Singh (Indian Institute of Technology BHU), Pratik Chattopadhyay (Indian Institute of Technology BHU)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Progressive Image Restoration Network for High-order Degradation Imaging in Remote Sensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07195v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently, deep learning methods have gained remarkable achievements in the field of image restoration for remote sensing (RS). However, most existing RS image restoration methods focus mainly on conventional first-order degradation models, which may not effectively capture the imaging mechanisms of remote sensing images. Furthermore, many RS image restoration approaches that use deep learning are often criticized for their lacks of architecture transparency and model interpretability. To address these problems, we propose a novel progressive restoration network for high-order degradation imaging (HDI-PRNet), to progressively restore different image degradation. HDI-PRNet is developed based on the theoretical framework of degradation imaging, offering the benefit of mathematical interpretability within the unfolding network. The framework is composed of three main components: a module for image denoising that relies on proximal mapping prior learning, a module for image deblurring that integrates Neumann series expansion with dual-domain degradation learning, and a module for super-resolution. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our method achieves superior performance on both synthetic and real remote sensing images.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07195v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yujie Feng, Yin Yang, Xiaohong Fan, Zhengpeng Zhang, Lijing Bu, Jianping Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MPSI: Mamba enhancement model for pixel-wise sequential interaction Image Super-Resolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07222v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Single image super-resolution (SR) has long posed a challenge in the field of computer vision. While the advent of deep learning has led to the emergence of numerous methods aimed at tackling this persistent issue, the current methodologies still encounter challenges in modeling long sequence information, leading to limitations in effectively capturing the global pixel interactions. To tackle this challenge and achieve superior SR outcomes, we propose the Mamba pixel-wise sequential interaction network (MPSI), aimed at enhancing the establishment of long-range connections of information, particularly focusing on pixel-wise sequential interaction. We propose the Channel-Mamba Block (CMB) to capture comprehensive pixel interaction information by effectively modeling long sequence information. Moreover, in the existing SR methodologies, there persists the issue of the neglect of features extracted by preceding layers, leading to the loss of valuable feature information. While certain existing models strive to preserve these features, they frequently encounter difficulty in establishing connections across all layers. To overcome this limitation, MPSI introduces the Mamba channel recursion module (MCRM), which maximizes the retention of valuable feature information from early layers, thereby facilitating the acquisition of pixel sequence interaction information from multiple-level layers. Through extensive experimentation, we demonstrate that MPSI outperforms existing super-resolution methods in terms of image reconstruction results, attaining state-of-the-art performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07222v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuchun He, Yuhan He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EchoIR: Advancing Image Restoration with Echo Upsampling and Bi-Level Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07225v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Image restoration represents a fundamental challenge in low-level vision, focusing on reconstructing high-quality images from their degraded counterparts. With the rapid advancement of deep learning technologies, transformer-based methods with pyramid structures have advanced the field by capturing long-range cross-scale spatial interaction. Despite its popularity, the degradation of essential features during the upsampling process notably compromised the restoration performance, resulting in suboptimal reconstruction outcomes. We introduce the EchoIR, an UNet-like image restoration network with a bilateral learnable upsampling mechanism to bridge this gap. Specifically, we proposed the Echo-Upsampler that optimizes the upsampling process by learning from the bilateral intermediate features of U-Net, the "Echo", aiming for a more refined restoration by minimizing the degradation during upsampling. In pursuit of modeling a hierarchical model of image restoration and upsampling tasks, we propose the Approximated Sequential Bi-level Optimization (AS-BLO), an advanced bi-level optimization model establishing a relationship between upsampling learning and image restoration tasks. Extensive experiments against the state-of-the-art (SOTA) methods demonstrate the proposed EchoIR surpasses the existing methods, achieving SOTA performance in image restoration tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07225v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuhan He, Yuchun He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Lidar-guided Image Deblurring</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07262v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The rise of portable Lidar instruments, including their adoption in smartphones, opens the door to novel computational imaging techniques. Being an active sensing instrument, Lidar can provide complementary data to passive optical sensors, particularly in situations like low-light imaging where motion blur can affect photos. In this paper, we study if the depth information provided by mobile Lidar sensors is useful for the task of image deblurring and how to integrate it with a general approach that transforms any state-of-the-art neural deblurring model into a depth-aware one. To achieve this, we developed a universal adapter structure that efficiently preprocesses the depth information to modulate image features with depth features. Additionally, we applied a continual learning strategy to pretrained encoder-decoder models, enabling them to incorporate depth information as an additional input with minimal extra data requirements. We demonstrate that utilizing true depth information can significantly boost the effectiveness of deblurring algorithms, as validated on a dataset with real-world depth data captured by a smartphone Lidar.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07262v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziyao Yi, Diego Valsesia, Tiziano Bianchi, Enrico Magli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QuantFormer: Learning to Quantize for Neural Activity Forecasting in Mouse Visual Cortex</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07264v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Understanding complex animal behaviors hinges on deciphering the neural activity patterns within brain circuits, making the ability to forecast neural activity crucial for developing predictive models of brain dynamics. This capability holds immense value for neuroscience, particularly in applications such as real-time optogenetic interventions. While traditional encoding and decoding methods have been used to map external variables to neural activity and vice versa, they focus on interpreting past data. In contrast, neural forecasting aims to predict future neural activity, presenting a unique and challenging task due to the spatiotemporal sparsity and complex dependencies of neural signals. Existing transformer-based forecasting methods, while effective in many domains, struggle to capture the distinctiveness of neural signals characterized by spatiotemporal sparsity and intricate dependencies. To address this challenge, we here introduce QuantFormer, a transformer-based model specifically designed for forecasting neural activity from two-photon calcium imaging data. Unlike conventional regression-based approaches, QuantFormerreframes the forecasting task as a classification problem via dynamic signal quantization, enabling more effective learning of sparse neural activation patterns. Additionally, QuantFormer tackles the challenge of analyzing multivariate signals from an arbitrary number of neurons by incorporating neuron-specific tokens, allowing scalability across diverse neuronal populations. Trained with unsupervised quantization on the Allen dataset, QuantFormer sets a new benchmark in forecasting mouse visual cortex activity. It demonstrates robust performance and generalization across various stimuli and individuals, paving the way for a foundational model in neural signal prediction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07264v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Salvatore Calcagno, Isaak Kavasidis, Simone Palazzo, Marco Brondi, Luca Sit\`a, Giacomo Turri, Daniela Giordano, Vladimir R. Kostic, Tommaso Fellin, Massimiliano Pontil, Concetto Spampinato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compression of Large-Scale 3D Point Clouds Based on Joint Optimization of Point Sampling and Feature Extraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07302</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07302v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Large-scale 3D point clouds (LS3DPC) obtained by LiDAR scanners require huge storage space and transmission bandwidth due to a large amount of data. The existing methods of LS3DPC compression separately perform rule-based point sampling and learnable feature extraction, and hence achieve limited compression performance. In this paper, we propose a fully end-to-end training framework for LS3DPC compression where the point sampling and the feature extraction are jointly optimized in terms of the rate and distortion losses. To this end, we first make the point sampling module to be trainable such that an optimal position of the downsampled point is estimated via aggregation with learnable weights. We also develop a reliable point reconstruction scheme that adaptively aggregates the expanded candidate points to refine the positions of upsampled points. Experimental results evaluated on the SemanticKITTI and nuScenes datasets show that the proposed method achieves significantly higher compression ratios compared with the existing state-of-the-art methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07302v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jae-Young Yim, Jae-Young Sim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leveraging Content and Context Cues for Low-Light Image Enhancement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07693v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Low-light conditions have an adverse impact on machine cognition, limiting the performance of computer vision systems in real life. Since low-light data is limited and difficult to annotate, we focus on image processing to enhance low-light images and improve the performance of any downstream task model, instead of fine-tuning each of the models which can be prohibitively expensive. We propose to improve the existing zero-reference low-light enhancement by leveraging the CLIP model to capture image prior and for semantic guidance. Specifically, we propose a data augmentation strategy to learn an image prior via prompt learning, based on image sampling, to learn the image prior without any need for paired or unpaired normal-light data. Next, we propose a semantic guidance strategy that maximally takes advantage of existing low-light annotation by introducing both content and context cues about the image training patches. We experimentally show, in a qualitative study, that the proposed prior and semantic guidance help to improve the overall image contrast and hue, as well as improve background-foreground discrimination, resulting in reduced over-saturation and noise over-amplification, common in related zero-reference methods. As we target machine cognition, rather than rely on assuming the correlation between human perception and downstream task performance, we conduct and present an ablation study and comparison with related zero-reference methods in terms of task-based performance across many low-light datasets, including image classification, object and face detection, showing the effectiveness of our proposed method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07693v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igor Morawski, Kai He, Shusil Dangi, Winston H. Hsu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Motion Blur and Deblurring in Visual Place Recognition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07751v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Visual Place Recognition (VPR) in mobile robotics enables robots to localize themselves by recognizing previously visited locations using visual data. While the reliability of VPR methods has been extensively studied under conditions such as changes in illumination, season, weather and viewpoint, the impact of motion blur is relatively unexplored despite its relevance not only in rapid motion scenarios but also in low-light conditions where longer exposure times are necessary. Similarly, the role of image deblurring in enhancing VPR performance under motion blur has received limited attention so far. This paper bridges these gaps by introducing a new benchmark designed to evaluate VPR performance under the influence of motion blur and image deblurring. The benchmark includes three datasets that encompass a wide range of motion blur intensities, providing a comprehensive platform for analysis. Experimental results with several well-established VPR and image deblurring methods provide new insights into the effects of motion blur and the potential improvements achieved through deblurring. Building on these findings, the paper proposes adaptive deblurring strategies for VPR, designed to effectively manage motion blur in dynamic, real-world scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07751v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timur Ismagilov, Bruno Ferrarini, Michael Milford, Tan Viet Tuyen Nguyen, SD Ramchurn, Shoaib Ehsan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>INFusion: Diffusion Regularized Implicit Neural Representations for 2D and 3D accelerated MRI reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13895v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Implicit Neural Representations (INRs) are a learning-based approach to accelerate Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) acquisitions, particularly in scan-specific settings when only data from the under-sampled scan itself are available. Previous work demonstrates that INRs improve rapid MRI through inherent regularization imposed by neural network architectures. Typically parameterized by fully-connected neural networks, INRs support continuous image representations by taking a physical coordinate location as input and outputting the intensity at that coordinate. Previous work has applied unlearned regularization priors during INR training and have been limited to 2D or low-resolution 3D acquisitions. Meanwhile, diffusion based generative models have received recent attention as they learn powerful image priors decoupled from the measurement model. This work proposes INFusion, a technique that regularizes the optimization of INRs from under-sampled MR measurements with pre-trained diffusion models for improved image reconstruction. In addition, we propose a hybrid 3D approach with our diffusion regularization that enables INR application on large-scale 3D MR datasets. 2D experiments demonstrate improved INR training with our proposed diffusion regularization, and 3D experiments demonstrate feasibility of INR training with diffusion regularization on 3D matrix sizes of 256 by 256 by 80.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13895v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yamin Arefeen, Brett Levac, Zach Stoebner, Jonathan Tamir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NestedMorph: Enhancing Deformable Medical Image Registration with Nested Attention Mechanisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02550v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Deformable image registration is crucial for aligning medical images in a nonlinear fashion across different modalities, allowing for precise spatial correspondence between varying anatomical structures. This paper presents NestedMorph, a novel network utilizing a Nested Attention Fusion approach to improve intra-subject deformable registration between T1-weighted (T1w) MRI and diffusion MRI (dMRI) data. NestedMorph integrates high-resolution spatial details from an encoder with semantic information from a decoder using a multi-scale framework, enhancing both local and global feature extraction. Our model notably outperforms existing methods, including CNN-based approaches like VoxelMorph, MIDIR, and CycleMorph, as well as Transformer-based models such as TransMorph and ViT-V-Net, and traditional techniques like NiftyReg and SyN. Evaluations using the HCP dataset demonstrate that NestedMorph achieves superior performance across key metrics, including SSIM, HD95, and SDlogJ, with the highest SSIM of 0.89, the lowest HD95 of 2.5 and SDlogJ of 0.22. These results highlight NestedMorph's ability to capture both local and global image features effectively, leading to superior registration performance. The promising outcomes of this study underscore NestedMorph's potential to significantly advance deformable medical image registration, providing a robust framework for future research and clinical applications. The source code and our implementation are available at: https://github.com/AS-Lab/Marthi-et-al-2024-NestedMorph-Deformable-Medical-Image-Registration</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02550v3</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gurucharan Marthi Krishna Kumar, Janine Mendola, Amir Shmuel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Ensemble for Predicting Diabetic Macular Edema Onset Using Ultra-Wide Field Color Fundus Image</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06483</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06483v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Diabetic macular edema (DME) is a severe complication of diabetes, characterized by thickening of the central portion of the retina due to accumulation of fluid. DME is a significant and common cause of visual impairment in diabetic patients. Center-involved DME (ci-DME) is the highest risk form of disease because fluid extends close to the fovea which is responsible for sharp central vision. Earlier diagnosis or prediction of ci-DME may improve treatment outcomes. Here, we propose an ensemble method to predict ci-DME onset within a year, after using synthetic ultra-wide field color fundus photography (UWF-CFP) images provided by the DIAMOND Challenge during development. We adopted a variety of baseline state-of-the-art classification networks including ResNet, DenseNet, EfficientNet, and VGG with the aim of enhancing model robustness. The best performing models were Densenet-121, Resnet-152 and EfficientNet-b7, and these were assembled into a definitive predictive model. The final ensemble model demonstrates a strong performance with an Area Under Curve (AUC) of 0.7017, an F1 score of 0.6512, and an Expected Calibration Error (ECE) of 0.2057 when deployed on the synthetic test dataset. Results from our ensemble model were superior/comparable to previous recorded results in highly curated settings using conventional fundus photography/ultra-wide field fundus photography. Optimal sensitivity in previous studies (using humans or computers to diagnose) ranges from 67.3%-98%, specificity from 47.8%-80%. Therefore, our method can be used safely and effectively in a range of settings may facilitate earlier diagnosis, better treatment decisions, and improved prognostication in ci-DME.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06483v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pengyao Qin, Arun J. Thirunavukarasu, Theodoros Arvanitis, Le Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HAAT: Hybrid Attention Aggregation Transformer for Image Super-Resolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18003</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18003v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the research area of image super-resolution, Swin-transformer-based models are favored for their global spatial modeling and shifting window attention mechanism. However, existing methods often limit self-attention to non overlapping windows to cut costs and ignore the useful information that exists across channels. To address this issue, this paper introduces a novel model, the Hybrid Attention Aggregation Transformer (HAAT), designed to better leverage feature information. HAAT is constructed by integrating Swin-Dense-Residual-Connected Blocks (SDRCB) with Hybrid Grid Attention Blocks (HGAB). SDRCB expands the receptive field while maintaining a streamlined architecture, resulting in enhanced performance. HGAB incorporates channel attention, sparse attention, and window attention to improve nonlocal feature fusion and achieve more visually compelling results. Experimental evaluations demonstrate that HAAT surpasses state-of-the-art methods on benchmark datasets. Keywords: Image super-resolution, Computer vision, Attention mechanism, Transformer</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18003v3</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Song-Jiang Lai, Tsun-Hin Cheung, Ka-Chun Fung, Kai-wen Xue, Kin-Man Lam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A No-Reference Medical Image Quality Assessment Method Based on Automated Distortion Recognition Technology: Application to Preprocessing in MRI-guided Radiotherapy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06599v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Objective:To develop a no-reference image quality assessment method using automated distortion recognition to boost MRI-guided radiotherapy precision.Methods:We analyzed 106,000 MR images from 10 patients with liver metastasis,captured with the Elekta Unity MR-LINAC.Our No-Reference Quality Assessment Model includes:1)image preprocessing to enhance visibility of key diagnostic features;2)feature extraction and directional analysis using MSCN coefficients across four directions to capture textural attributes and gradients,vital for identifying image features and potential distortions;3)integrative Quality Index(QI)calculation,which integrates features via AGGD parameter estimation and K-means clustering.The QI,based on a weighted MAD computation of directional scores,provides a comprehensive image quality measure,robust against outliers.LOO-CV assessed model generalizability and performance.Tumor tracking algorithm performance was compared with and without preprocessing to verify tracking accuracy enhancements.Results:Preprocessing significantly improved image quality,with the QI showing substantial positive changes and surpassing other metrics.After normalization,the QI's average value was 79.6 times higher than CNR,indicating improved image definition and contrast.It also showed higher sensitivity in detail recognition with average values 6.5 times and 1.7 times higher than Tenengrad gradient and entropy.The tumor tracking algorithm confirmed significant tracking accuracy improvements with preprocessed images,validating preprocessing effectiveness.Conclusions:This study introduces a novel no-reference image quality evaluation method based on automated distortion recognition,offering a new quality control tool for MRIgRT tumor tracking.It enhances clinical application accuracy and facilitates medical image quality assessment standardization, with significant clinical and research value.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06599v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zilin Wang, Shengqi Chen, Jianrong Dai, Shirui Qin, Ying Cao, Ruiao Zhao, Guohua Wu, Yuan Tang, Jiayun Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A consensus-constrained parsimonious Gaussian mixture model for clustering hyperspectral images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03349v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The use of hyperspectral imaging to investigate food samples has grown due to the improved performance and lower cost of instrumentation. Food engineers use hyperspectral images to classify the type and quality of a food sample, typically using classification methods. In order to train these methods, every pixel in each training image needs to be labelled. Typically, computationally cheap threshold-based approaches are used to label the pixels, and classification methods are trained based on those labels. However, threshold-based approaches are subjective and cannot be generalized across hyperspectral images taken in different conditions and of different foods. Here a consensus-constrained parsimonious Gaussian mixture model (ccPGMM) is proposed to label pixels in hyperspectral images using a model-based clustering approach. The ccPGMM utilizes information that is available on some pixels and specifies constraints on those pixels belonging to the same or different clusters while clustering the rest of the pixels in the image. A latent variable model is used to represent the high-dimensional data in terms of a small number of underlying latent factors. To ensure computational feasibility, a consensus clustering approach is employed, where the data are divided into multiple randomly selected subsets of variables and constrained clustering is applied to each data subset; the clustering results are then consolidated across all data subsets to provide a consensus clustering solution. The ccPGMM approach is applied to simulated datasets and real hyperspectral images of three types of puffed cereal, corn, rice, and wheat. Improved clustering performance and computational efficiency are demonstrated when compared to other current state-of-the-art approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03349v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ganesh Babu, Aoife Gowen, Michael Fop, Isobel Claire Gormley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Double-Shot 3D Shape Measurement with a Dual-Branch Network for Structured Light Projection Profilometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14198v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The structured light (SL)-based three-dimensional (3D) measurement techniques with deep learning have been widely studied to improve measurement efficiency, among which fringe projection profilometry (FPP) and speckle projection profilometry (SPP) are two popular methods. However, they generally use a single projection pattern for reconstruction, resulting in fringe order ambiguity or poor reconstruction accuracy. To alleviate these problems, we propose a parallel dual-branch Convolutional Neural Network (CNN)-Transformer network (PDCNet), to take advantage of convolutional operations and self-attention mechanisms for processing different SL modalities. Within PDCNet, a Transformer branch is used to capture global perception in the fringe images, while a CNN branch is designed to collect local details in the speckle images. To fully integrate complementary features, we design a double-stream attention aggregation module (DAAM) that consists of a parallel attention subnetwork for aggregating multi-scale spatial structure information. This module can dynamically retain local and global representations to the maximum extent. Moreover, an adaptive mixture density head with bimodal Gaussian distribution is proposed for learning a representation that is precise near discontinuities. Compared to the standard disparity regression strategy, this adaptive mixture head can effectively improve performance at object boundaries. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our method can reduce fringe order ambiguity while producing high-accuracy results on self-made datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14198v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingyang Lei, Jingfan Fan, Long Shao, Hong Song, Deqiang Xiao, Danni Ai, Tianyu Fu, Ying Gu, Jian Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local-to-Global Self-Supervised Representation Learning for Diabetic Retinopathy Grading</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00779</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00779v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Artificial intelligence algorithms have demonstrated their image classification and segmentation ability in the past decade. However, artificial intelligence algorithms perform less for actual clinical data than those used for simulations. This research aims to present a novel hybrid learning model using self-supervised learning and knowledge distillation, which can achieve sufficient generalization and robustness. The self-attention mechanism and tokens employed in ViT, besides the local-to-global learning approach used in the hybrid model, enable the proposed algorithm to extract a high-dimensional and high-quality feature space from images. To demonstrate the proposed neural network's capability in classifying and extracting feature spaces from medical images, we use it on a dataset of Diabetic Retinopathy images, specifically the EyePACS dataset. This dataset is more complex structurally and challenging regarding damaged areas than other medical images. For the first time in this study, self-supervised learning and knowledge distillation are used to classify this dataset. In our algorithm, for the first time among all self-supervised learning and knowledge distillation models, the test dataset is 50% larger than the training dataset. Unlike many studies, we have not removed any images from the dataset. Finally, our algorithm achieved an accuracy of 79.1% in the linear classifier and 74.36% in the k-NN algorithm for multiclass classification. Compared to a similar state-of-the-art model, our results achieved higher accuracy and more effective representation spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00779v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mostafa Hajighasemlou, Samad Sheikhaei, Hamid Soltanian-Zadeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrocardiogram (ECG) Based Cardiac Arrhythmia Detection and Classification using Machine Learning Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05583v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The rapid advancements in Artificial Intelligence, specifically Machine Learning (ML) and Deep Learning (DL), have opened new prospects in medical sciences for improved diagnosis, prognosis, and treatment of severe health conditions. This paper focuses on the development of an ML model with high predictive accuracy to classify arrhythmic electrocardiogram (ECG) signals. The ECG signals datasets utilized in this study were sourced from the PhysioNet and MIT-BIH databases. The research commenced with binary classification, where an optimized Bidirectional Long Short-Term Memory (Bi-LSTM) model yielded excellent results in differentiating normal and atrial fibrillation signals. A pivotal aspect of this research was a survey among medical professionals, which not only validated the practicality of AI-based ECG classifiers but also identified areas for improvement, including accuracy and the inclusion of more arrhythmia types. These insights drove the development of an advanced Convolutional Neural Network (CNN) system capable of classifying five different types of ECG signals with better accuracy and precision. The CNN model's robust performance was ensured through rigorous stratified 5-fold cross validation. A web portal was also developed to demonstrate real-world utility, offering access to the trained model for real-time classification. This study highlights the potential applications of such models in remote health monitoring, predictive healthcare, assistive diagnostic tools, and simulated environments for educational training and interdisciplinary collaboration between data scientists and medical personnel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05583v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Atit Pokharel, Shashank Dahal, Pratik Sapkota, Bhupendra Bimal Chhetri</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
