<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.IV updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.IV</link>
    <description>eess.IV updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.IV" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 04:00:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-Informed Neural Networks vs. Physics Models for Non-Invasive Glucose Monitoring: A Comparative Study Under Realistic Synthetic Conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12253v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Non-invasive glucose monitors often fail outside the lab because existing datasets ignore hardware noise, environmental drift, and person-to-person physiology. We introduce the first ultra-realistic near-infrared (NIR) simulator that injects 12-bit ADC quantisation, +/-0.1% LED ageing, photodiode dark noise, 15-45 C temperature, 30-90% relative humidity, contact-pressure variation, Fitzpatrick I-VI melanin, and diurnal glucose excursions (dawn phenomenon). Using this platform (rho glucose-NIR = 0.21), we benchmark six methods: Enhanced Beer-Lambert (physics-engineered ridge regression), three physics-informed neural networks (PINNs), a selective radiative-transfer PINN, and a shallow DNN. Beer-Lambert achieves 13.6 mg/dL RMSE, 95.8% Clarke-A and 93.8% +/-15% accuracy with only 56 parameters and 0.01 ms inference, outperforming the best PINN (14.6 mg/dL) and the SDNN baseline (35.1 mg/dL). Results overturn the assumption that deeper PINNs dominate and supply an open, end-to-end reference stack for rapid prototyping of embedded optical glucose sensors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12253v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riyaadh Gani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Radiographic Disease Detection with MetaCheX, a Context-Aware Multimodal Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12287</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12287v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Existing deep learning models for chest radiology often neglect patient metadata, limiting diagnostic accuracy and fairness. To bridge this gap, we introduce MetaCheX, a novel multimodal framework that integrates chest X-ray images with structured patient metadata to replicate clinical decision-making. Our approach combines a convolutional neural network (CNN) backbone with metadata processed by a multilayer perceptron through a shared classifier. Evaluated on the CheXpert Plus dataset, MetaCheX consistently outperformed radiograph-only baseline models across multiple CNN architectures. By integrating metadata, the overall diagnostic accuracy was significantly improved, measured by an increase in AUROC. The results of this study demonstrate that metadata reduces algorithmic bias and enhances model generalizability across diverse patient populations. MetaCheX advances clinical artificial intelligence toward robust, context-aware radiographic disease detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12287v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathan He, Cody Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DinoAtten3D: Slice-Level Attention Aggregation of DinoV2 for 3D Brain MRI Anomaly Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12512v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Anomaly detection and classification in medical imaging are critical for early diagnosis but remain challenging due to limited annotated data, class imbalance, and the high cost of expert labeling. Emerging vision foundation models such as DINOv2, pretrained on extensive, unlabeled datasets, offer generalized representations that can potentially alleviate these limitations. In this study, we propose an attention-based global aggregation framework tailored specifically for 3D medical image anomaly classification. Leveraging the self-supervised DINOv2 model as a pretrained feature extractor, our method processes individual 2D axial slices of brain MRIs, assigning adaptive slice-level importance weights through a soft attention mechanism. To further address data scarcity, we employ a composite loss function combining supervised contrastive learning with class-variance regularization, enhancing inter-class separability and intra-class consistency. We validate our framework on the ADNI dataset and an institutional multi-class headache cohort, demonstrating strong anomaly classification performance despite limited data availability and significant class imbalance. Our results highlight the efficacy of utilizing pretrained 2D foundation models combined with attention-based slice aggregation for robust volumetric anomaly detection in medical imaging. Our implementation is publicly available at https://github.com/Rafsani/DinoAtten3D.git.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12512v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fazle Rafsani, Jay Shah, Catherine D. Chong, Todd J. Schwedt, Teresa Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepEyeNet: Generating Medical Report for Retinal Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12534</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12534v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The increasing prevalence of retinal diseases poses a significant challenge to the healthcare system, as the demand for ophthalmologists surpasses the available workforce. This imbalance creates a bottleneck in diagnosis and treatment, potentially delaying critical care. Traditional methods of generating medical reports from retinal images rely on manual interpretation, which is time-consuming and prone to errors, further straining ophthalmologists' limited resources. This thesis investigates the potential of Artificial Intelligence (AI) to automate medical report generation for retinal images. AI can quickly analyze large volumes of image data, identifying subtle patterns essential for accurate diagnosis. By automating this process, AI systems can greatly enhance the efficiency of retinal disease diagnosis, reducing doctors' workloads and enabling them to focus on more complex cases. The proposed AI-based methods address key challenges in automated report generation: (1) A multi-modal deep learning approach captures interactions between textual keywords and retinal images, resulting in more comprehensive medical reports; (2) Improved methods for medical keyword representation enhance the system's ability to capture nuances in medical terminology; (3) Strategies to overcome RNN-based models' limitations, particularly in capturing long-range dependencies within medical descriptions; (4) Techniques to enhance the interpretability of the AI-based report generation system, fostering trust and acceptance in clinical practice. These methods are rigorously evaluated using various metrics and achieve state-of-the-art performance. This thesis demonstrates AI's potential to revolutionize retinal disease diagnosis by automating medical report generation, ultimately improving clinical efficiency, diagnostic accuracy, and patient care.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12534v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Hong Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Computational Pipeline for Patient-Specific Modeling of Thoracic Aortic Aneurysm: From Medical Image to Finite Element Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12596</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12596v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The aorta is the body's largest arterial vessel, serving as the primary pathway for oxygenated blood within the systemic circulation. Aortic aneurysms consistently rank among the top twenty causes of mortality in the United States. Thoracic aortic aneurysm (TAA) arises from abnormal dilation of the thoracic aorta and remains a clinically significant disease, ranking as one of the leading causes of death in adults. A thoracic aortic aneurysm ruptures when the integrity of all aortic wall layers is compromised due to elevated blood pressure. Currently, three-dimensional computed tomography (3D CT) is considered the gold standard for diagnosing TAA. The geometric characteristics of the aorta, which can be quantified from medical imaging, and stresses on the aortic wall, which can be obtained by finite element analysis (FEA), are critical in evaluating the risk of rupture and dissection. Deep learning based image segmentation has emerged as a reliable method for extracting anatomical regions of interest from medical images. Voxel based segmentation masks of anatomical structures are typically converted into structured mesh representation to enable accurate simulation. Hexahedral meshes are commonly used in finite element simulations of the aorta due to their computational efficiency and superior simulation accuracy. Due to anatomical variability, patient specific modeling enables detailed assessment of individual anatomical and biomechanics behaviors, supporting precise simulations, accurate diagnoses, and personalized treatment strategies. Finite element (FE) simulations provide valuable insights into the biomechanical behaviors of tissues and organs in clinical studies. Developing accurate FE models represents a crucial initial step in establishing a patient-specific, biomechanically based framework for predicting the risk of TAA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12596v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiasong Chen, Linchen Qian, Ruonan Gong, Christina Sun, Tongran Qin, Thuy Pham, Caitlin Martin, Mohammad Zafar, John Elefteriades, Wei Sun, Liang Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MEGAN: Mixture of Experts for Robust Uncertainty Estimation in Endoscopy Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12772v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reliable uncertainty quantification (UQ) is essential in medical AI. Evidential Deep Learning (EDL) offers a computationally efficient way to quantify model uncertainty alongside predictions, unlike traditional methods such as Monte Carlo (MC) Dropout and Deep Ensembles (DE). However, all these methods often rely on a single expert's annotations as ground truth for model training, overlooking the inter-rater variability in healthcare. To address this issue, we propose MEGAN, a Multi-Expert Gating Network that aggregates uncertainty estimates and predictions from multiple AI experts via EDL models trained with diverse ground truths and modeling strategies. MEGAN's gating network optimally combines predictions and uncertainties from each EDL model, enhancing overall prediction confidence and calibration. We extensively benchmark MEGAN on endoscopy videos for Ulcerative colitis (UC) disease severity estimation, assessed by visual labeling of Mayo Endoscopic Subscore (MES), where inter-rater variability is prevalent. In large-scale prospective UC clinical trial, MEGAN achieved a 3.5% improvement in F1-score and a 30.5% reduction in Expected Calibration Error (ECE) compared to existing methods. Furthermore, MEGAN facilitated uncertainty-guided sample stratification, reducing the annotation burden and potentially increasing efficiency and consistency in UC trials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12772v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Damola Agbelese, Krishna Chaitanya, Pushpak Pati, Chaitanya Parmar, Pooya Mobadersany, Shreyas Fadnavis, Lindsey Surace, Shadi Yarandi, Louis R. Ghanem, Molly Lucas, Tommaso Mansi, Oana Gabriela Cula, Pablo F. Damasceno, Kristopher Standish</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flexible Multimodal Neuroimaging Fusion for Alzheimer's Disease Progression Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12234v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Alzheimer's disease (AD) is a progressive neurodegenerative disease with high inter-patient variance in rate of cognitive decline. AD progression prediction aims to forecast patient cognitive decline and benefits from incorporating multiple neuroimaging modalities. However, existing multimodal models fail to make accurate predictions when many modalities are missing during inference, as is often the case in clinical settings. To increase multimodal model flexibility under high modality missingness, we introduce PerM-MoE, a novel sparse mixture-of-experts method that uses independent routers for each modality in place of the conventional, single router. Using T1-weighted MRI, FLAIR, amyloid beta PET, and tau PET neuroimaging data from the Alzheimer's Disease Neuroimaging Initiative (ADNI), we evaluate PerM-MoE, state-of-the-art Flex-MoE, and unimodal neuroimaging models on predicting two-year change in Clinical Dementia Rating-Sum of Boxes (CDR-SB) scores under varying levels of modality missingness. PerM-MoE outperforms the state of the art in most variations of modality missingness and demonstrates more effective utility of experts than Flex-MoE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12234v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Burns, Yuan Xue, Douglas W. Scharre, Xia Ning</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Diffeomorphic-Neural Operator for Residual Stress-Induced Deformation Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12237v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Accurate prediction of machining deformation in structural components is essential for ensuring dimensional precision and reliability. Such deformation often originates from residual stress fields, whose distribution and influence vary significantly with geometric complexity. Conventional numerical methods for modeling the coupling between residual stresses and deformation are computationally expensive, particularly when diverse geometries are considered. Neural operators have recently emerged as a powerful paradigm for efficiently solving partial differential equations, offering notable advantages in accelerating residual stress-deformation analysis. However, their direct application across changing geometric domains faces theoretical and practical limitations. To address this challenge, a novel framework based on diffeomorphic embedding neural operators named neural diffeomorphic-neural operator (NDNO) is introduced. Complex three-dimensional geometries are explicitly mapped to a common reference domain through a diffeomorphic neural network constrained by smoothness and invertibility. The neural operator is then trained on this reference domain, enabling efficient learning of deformation fields induced by residual stresses. Once trained, both the diffeomorphic neural network and the neural operator demonstrate efficient prediction capabilities, allowing rapid adaptation to varying geometries. The proposed method thus provides an effective and computationally efficient solution for deformation prediction in structural components subject to varying geometries. The proposed method is validated to predict both main-direction and multi-direction deformation fields, achieving high accuracy and efficiency across parts with diverse geometries including component types, dimensions and features.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12237v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Changqing Liu, Kaining Dai, Zhiwei Zhao, Tianyi Wu, Yingguang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ResidualViT for Efficient Temporally Dense Video Encoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13255v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Several video understanding tasks, such as natural language temporal video grounding, temporal activity localization, and audio description generation, require "temporally dense" reasoning over frames sampled at high temporal resolution. However, computing frame-level features for these tasks is computationally expensive given the temporal resolution requirements. In this paper, we make three contributions to reduce the cost of computing features for temporally dense tasks. First, we introduce a vision transformer (ViT) architecture, dubbed ResidualViT, that leverages the large temporal redundancy in videos to efficiently compute temporally dense frame-level features. Our architecture incorporates (i) learnable residual connections that ensure temporal consistency across consecutive frames and (ii) a token reduction module that enhances processing speed by selectively discarding temporally redundant information while reusing weights of a pretrained foundation model. Second, we propose a lightweight distillation strategy to approximate the frame-level features of the original foundation model. Finally, we evaluate our approach across four tasks and five datasets, in both zero-shot and fully supervised settings, demonstrating significant reductions in computational cost (up to 60%) and improvements in inference speed (up to 2.5x faster), all while closely approximating the accuracy of the original foundation model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13255v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mattia Soldan, Fabian Caba Heilbron, Bernard Ghanem, Josef Sivic, Bryan Russell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Image Realness Assessment and Localization with Multimodal Features</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13289</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13289v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A reliable method of quantifying the perceptual realness of AI-generated images and identifying visually inconsistent regions is crucial for practical use of AI-generated images and for improving photorealism of generative AI via realness feedback during training. This paper introduces a framework that accomplishes both overall objective realness assessment and local inconsistency identification of AI-generated images using textual descriptions of visual inconsistencies generated by vision-language models trained on large datasets that serve as reliable substitutes for human annotations. Our results demonstrate that the proposed multimodal approach improves objective realness prediction performance and produces dense realness maps that effectively distinguish between realistic and unrealistic spatial regions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13289v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lovish Kaushik, Agnij Biswas, Somdyuti Paul</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pitfalls of defacing whole-head MRI: re-identification risk with diffusion models and compromised research potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18834v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Defacing is often applied to head magnetic resonance image (MRI) datasets prior to public release to address privacy concerns. The alteration of facial and nearby voxels has provoked discussions about the true capability of these techniques to ensure privacy as well as their impact on downstream tasks. With advancements in deep generative models, the extent to which defacing can protect privacy is uncertain. Additionally, while the altered voxels are known to contain valuable anatomical information, their potential to support research beyond the anatomical regions directly affected by defacing remains uncertain. To evaluate these considerations, we develop a refacing pipeline that recovers faces in defaced head MRIs using cascaded diffusion probabilistic models (DPMs). The DPMs are trained on images from 180 subjects and tested on images from 484 unseen subjects, 469 of whom are from a different dataset. To assess whether the altered voxels in defacing contain universally useful information, we also predict computed tomography (CT)-derived skeletal muscle radiodensity from facial voxels in both defaced and original MRIs. The results show that DPMs can generate high-fidelity faces that resemble the original faces from defaced images, with surface distances to the original faces significantly smaller than those of a population average face (p &lt; 0.05). This performance also generalizes well to previously unseen datasets. For skeletal muscle radiodensity predictions, using defaced images results in significantly weaker Spearman's rank correlation coefficients compared to using original images (p &lt; 10-4). For shin muscle, the correlation is statistically significant (p &lt; 0.05) when using original images but not statistically significant (p &gt; 0.05) when any defacing method is applied, suggesting that defacing might not only fail to protect privacy but also eliminate valuable information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18834v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenyu Gao, Kaiwen Xu, Michael E. Kim, Lianrui Zuo, Zhiyuan Li, Derek B. Archer, Timothy J. Hohman, Ann Zenobia Moore, Luigi Ferrucci, Lori L. Beason-Held, Susan M. Resnick, Christos Davatzikos, Jerry L. Prince, Bennett A. Landman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WaterFlow: Learning Fast &amp; Robust Watermarks using Stable Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12354v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The ability to embed watermarks in images is a fundamental problem of interest for computer vision, and is exacerbated by the rapid rise of generated imagery in recent times. Current state-of-the-art techniques suffer from computational and statistical challenges such as the slow execution speed for practical deployments. In addition, other works trade off fast watermarking speeds but suffer greatly in their robustness or perceptual quality. In this work, we propose WaterFlow (WF), a fast and extremely robust approach for high fidelity visual watermarking based on a learned latent-dependent watermark. Our approach utilizes a pretrained latent diffusion model to encode an arbitrary image into a latent space and produces a learned watermark that is then planted into the Fourier Domain of the latent. The transformation is specified via invertible flow layers that enhance the expressivity of the latent space of the pre-trained model to better preserve image quality while permitting robust and tractable detection. Most notably, WaterFlow demonstrates state-of-the-art performance on general robustness and is the first method capable of effectively defending against difficult combination attacks. We validate our findings on three widely used real and generated datasets: MS-COCO, DiffusionDB, and WikiArt.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12354v3</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vinay Shukla, Prachee Sharma, Ryan Rossi, Sungchul Kim, Tong Yu, Aditya Grover</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diagnosis for Less-Prevalent Thyroid Carcinoma Subtype Using a Dual-Branch Attention Deep Network with Ultrasound Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02211</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02211v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Heterogeneous morphological features and data imbalance pose significant challenges in rare thyroid carcinoma classification using ultrasound imaging. To address this issue, we propose a novel multitask learning framework, Channel-Spatial Attention Synergy Network (CSASN), which integrates a dual-branch feature extractor - combining EfficientNet for local spatial encoding and ViT for global semantic modeling, with a cascaded channel-spatial attention refinement module. A residual multiscale classifier and dynamically weighted loss function further enhance classification stability and accuracy. Trained on a multicenter dataset comprising more than 2000 patients from four clinical institutions, our framework leverages a residual multiscale classifier and dynamically weighted loss function to enhance classification stability and accuracy. Extensive ablation studies demonstrate that each module contributes significantly to model performance, particularly in recognizing rare subtypes such as FTC and MTC carcinomas. Experimental results show that CSASN outperforms existing single-stream CNN or Transformer-based models, achieving a superior balance between precision and recall under class-imbalanced conditions. This framework provides a promising strategy for AI-assisted thyroid cancer diagnosis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02211v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peiqi Li, Yincheng Gao, Renxing Li, Haojie Yang, Yunyun Liu, Boji Liu, Jiahui Ni, Ying Zhang, Yulu Wu, Xiaowei Fang, Lehang Guo, Liping Sun, Jiangang Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Recursive Fusion of Multiresolution Multispectral Images with Location-Aware Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13733</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13733v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Multiresolution image fusion is a key problem for real-time satellite imaging and plays a central role in detecting and monitoring natural phenomena such as floods. It aims to solve the trade-off between temporal and spatial resolution in remote sensing instruments. Although several algorithms have been proposed for this problem, the presence of outliers such as clouds downgrades their performance. Moreover, strategies that integrate robustness, recursive operation and learned models are missing. In this paper, a robust recursive image fusion framework leveraging location-aware neural networks (NN) to model the image dynamics is proposed. Outliers are modeled by representing the probability of contamination of a given pixel and band. A NN model trained on a small dataset provides accurate predictions of the stochastic image time evolution, which improves both the accuracy and robustness of the method. A recursive solution is proposed to estimate the high-resolution images using a Bayesian variational inference framework. Experiments fusing images from the Landsat 8 and MODIS instruments show that the proposed approach is significantly more robust against cloud cover, without losing performance when no clouds are present.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13733v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoqing Li, Ricardo Borsoi, Tales Imbiriba, Pau Closas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Generalist Vision Language Models (VLMs) Rival Specialist Medical VLMs? Benchmarking and Strategic Insights</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.17337v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Vision Language Models (VLMs) have shown promise in automating image diagnosis and interpretation in clinical settings. However, developing specialist medical VLMs requires substantial computational resources and carefully curated datasets, and it remains unclear under which conditions generalist and specialist medical VLMs each perform best. This study highlights the complementary strengths of specialist medical and generalist VLMs. Specialists remain valuable in modality-aligned use cases, but we find that efficiently fine-tuned generalist VLMs can achieve comparable or even superior performance in most tasks, particularly when transferring to unseen or rare OOD medical modalities. These results suggest that generalist VLMs, rather than being constrained by their lack of specialist medical pretraining, may offer a scalable and cost-effective pathway for advancing clinical AI development.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.17337v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuan Zhong, Ruinan Jin, Qi Dou, Xiaoxiao Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy-based models for inverse imaging problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12432v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this chapter we provide a thorough overview of the use of energy-based models (EBMs) in the context of inverse imaging problems. EBMs are probability distributions modeled via Gibbs densities $p(x) \propto \exp{-E(x)}$ with an appropriate energy functional $E$. Within this chapter we present a rigorous theoretical introduction to Bayesian inverse problems that includes results on well-posedness and stability in the finite-dimensional and infinite-dimensional setting. Afterwards we discuss the use of EBMs for Bayesian inverse problems and explain the most relevant techniques for learning EBMs from data. As a crucial part of Bayesian inverse problems, we cover several popular algorithms for sampling from EBMs, namely the Metropolis-Hastings algorithm, Gibbs sampling, Langevin Monte Carlo, and Hamiltonian Monte Carlo. Moreover, we present numerical results for the resolution of several inverse imaging problems obtained by leveraging an EBM that allows for the explicit verification of those properties that are needed for valid energy-based modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12432v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Habring, Martin Holler, Thomas Pock, Martin Zach</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CryoSplat: Gaussian Splatting for Cryo-EM Homogeneous Reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.04929v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: As a critical modality for structural biology, cryogenic electron microscopy (cryo-EM) facilitates the determination of macromolecular structures at near-atomic resolution. The core computational task in single-particle cryo-EM is to reconstruct the 3D electrostatic potential of a molecule from a large collection of noisy 2D projections acquired at unknown orientations. Gaussian mixture models (GMMs) provide a continuous, compact, and physically interpretable representation for molecular density and have recently gained interest in cryo-EM reconstruction. However, existing methods rely on external consensus maps or atomic models for initialization, limiting their use in self-contained pipelines. Addressing this issue, we introduce cryoGS, a GMM-based method that integrates Gaussian splatting with the physics of cryo-EM image formation. In particular, we develop an orthogonal projection-aware Gaussian splatting, with adaptations such as a normalization term and FFT-aligned coordinate system tailored for cryo-EM imaging. All these innovations enable stable and efficient homogeneous reconstruction directly from raw cryo-EM particle images using random initialization. Experimental results on real datasets validate the effectiveness and robustness of cryoGS over representative baselines. The code will be released upon publication.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.04929v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suyi Chen, Haibin Ling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Transport Based Unsupervised Restoration Learning Exploiting Degradation Sparsity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.00273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.00273v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Optimal transport (OT) has recently been shown as a promising criterion for unsupervised restoration when no explicit prior model is available. Despite its theoretical appeal, OT still significantly falls short of supervised methods on challenging tasks such as super-resolution, deraining, and dehazing. In this paper, we propose a \emph{sparsity-aware optimal transport} (SOT) framework to bridge this gap by leveraging a key observation: the degradations in these tasks exhibit distinct sparsity in the frequency domain. Incorporating this sparsity prior into OT can significantly reduce the ambiguity of the inverse mapping for restoration and substantially boost performance. We provide analysis to show exploiting degradation sparsity benefits unsupervised restoration learning. Extensive experiments on real-world super-resolution, deraining, and dehazing demonstrate that SOT offers notable performance gains over standard OT, while achieving superior perceptual quality compared to existing supervised and unsupervised methods. In particular, SOT consistently outperforms existing unsupervised methods across all three tasks and narrows the performance gap to supervised counterparts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.00273v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fei Wen, Wei Wang, Zeyu Yan, Wenbin Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gradient-Free Adversarial Purification with Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13336</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13336v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Adversarial training and adversarial purification are two widely used defense strategies for enhancing model robustness against adversarial attacks. However, adversarial training requires costly retraining, while adversarial purification often suffers from low efficiency. More critically, existing defenses are primarily designed under the perturbation-based adversarial threat model, which is ineffective against recently introduced unrestricted adversarial attacks. In this paper, we propose an effective and efficient defense framework that counters both perturbation-based and unrestricted adversarial attacks. Our approach is motivated by the observation that adversarial examples typically lie near the decision boundary and are highly sensitive to pixel-level perturbations. To address this, we introduce adversarial anti-aliasing, a preprocessing technique that mitigates adversarial noise by reducing the magnitude of pixel-level perturbations. In addition, we propose adversarial super-resolution, which leverages prior knowledge from clean datasets to benignly restore high-quality images from adversarially degraded ones. Unlike image synthesis methods that generate entirely new images, adversarial super-resolution focuses on image restoration, making it more suitable for purification. Importantly, both techniques require no additional training and are computationally efficient since they do not rely on gradient computations. To further improve robustness across diverse datasets, we introduce a contrastive learning-based adversarial deblurring fine-tuning method. By incorporating adversarial priors during fine-tuning on the target dataset, this method enhances purification effectiveness without the need to retrain diffusion models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13336v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuelong Dai, Dong Wang, Xiuzhen Cheng, Bin Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
