<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>eess.IV updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.IV</link>
    <description>eess.IV updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/eess.IV" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 01:45:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Normalization-equivariant Diffusion Models: Learning Posterior Samplers From Noisy And Partial Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11964v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Diffusion models (DMs) have rapidly emerged as a powerful framework for image generation and restoration. However, existing DMs are primarily trained in a supervised manner by using a large corpus of clean images. This reliance on clean data poses fundamental challenges in many real-world scenarios, where acquiring noise-free data is hard or infeasible, and only noisy and potentially incomplete measurements are available. While some methods can train DMs using noisy data, they are generally effective only when the amount of noise is very mild or when some additional noise-free data is available. In addition, existing methods for training DMs from incomplete measurements require access to multiple complementary acquisition processes, an assumption that poses a significant practical limitation. Here we introduce the first approach for learning DMs for image restoration using only noisy measurement data from a single operator. As a first key contribution, we show that DMs, and more broadly minimum mean squared error denoisers, exhibit a weak form of scale equivariance linking rescaling in signal amplitude to changes in noise intensity. We then leverage this theoretical insight to develop a denoising score-matching strategy that generalizes robustly to noise levels lower than those present in the training data, thereby enabling the learning of DMs from noisy measurements. To further address the challenges of incomplete and noisy data, we integrate our method with equivariant imaging, a complementary self-supervised learning framework that exploits the inherent invariants of imaging problems, to train DMs for image restoration from single-operator measurements that are both incomplete and noisy. We validate the effectiveness of our approach through extensive experiments on image denoising, demosaicing, and inpainting, along with comparisons with the state of the art.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11964v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brett Levac, Jon Tamir, Marcelo Pereyra, Julian Tachella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LiteVPNet: A Lightweight Network for Video Encoding Control in Quality-Critical Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12379v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the last decade, video workflows in the cinema production ecosystem have presented new use cases for video streaming technology. These new workflows, e.g. in On-set Virtual Production, present the challenge of requiring precise quality control and energy efficiency. Existing approaches to transcoding often fall short of these requirements, either due to a lack of quality control or computational overhead. To fill this gap, we present a lightweight neural network (LiteVPNet) for accurately predicting Quantisation Parameters for NVENC AV1 encoders that achieve a specified VMAF score. We use low-complexity features, including bitstream characteristics, video complexity measures, and CLIP-based semantic embeddings. Our results demonstrate that LiteVPNet achieves mean VMAF errors below 1.2 points across a wide range of quality targets. Notably, LiteVPNet achieves VMAF errors within 2 points for over 87% of our test corpus, c.f. approx 61% with state-of-the-art methods. LiteVPNet's performance across various quality regions highlights its applicability for enhancing high-value content transport and streaming for more energy-efficient, high-quality media experiences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12379v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vibhoothi Vibhoothi, Fran\c{c}ois Piti\'e, Anil Kokaram</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Empirical Study of Reducing AV1 Decoder Complexity and Energy Consumption via Encoder Parameter Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12380v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The widespread adoption of advanced video codecs such as AV1 is often hindered by their high decoding complexity, posing a challenge for battery-constrained devices. While encoders can be configured to produce bitstreams that are decoder-friendly, estimating the decoding complexity and energy overhead for a given video is non-trivial. In this study, we systematically analyse the impact of disabling various coding tools and adjusting coding parameters in two AV1 encoders, libaom-av1 and SVT-AV1. Using system-level energy measurement tools like RAPL (Running Average Power Limit), Intel SoC Watch (integrated with VTune profiler), we quantify the resulting trade-offs between decoding complexity, energy consumption, and compression efficiency for decoding a bitstream. Our results demonstrate that specific encoder configurations can substantially reduce decoding complexity with minimal perceptual quality degradation. For libaom-av1, disabling CDEF, an in-loop filter gives us a mean reduction in decoding cycles by 10%. For SVT-AV1, using the in-built, fast-decode=2 preset achieves a more substantial 24% reduction in decoding cycles. These findings provide strategies for content providers to lower the energy footprint of AV1 video streaming.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12380v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vibhoothi Vibhoothi, Julien Zouein, Shanker Shreejith, Jean-Baptiste Kempf, Anil Kokaram</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MH-LVC: Multi-Hypothesis Temporal Prediction for Learned Conditional Residual Video Coding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12479v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work, termed MH-LVC, presents a multi-hypothesis temporal prediction scheme that employs long- and short-term reference frames in a conditional residual video coding framework. Recent temporal context mining approaches to conditional video coding offer superior coding performance. However, the need to store and access a large amount of implicit contextual information extracted from past decoded frames in decoding a video frame poses a challenge due to excessive memory access. Our MH-LVC overcomes this issue by storing multiple long- and short-term reference frames but limiting the number of reference frames used at a time for temporal prediction to two. Our decoded frame buffer management allows the encoder to flexibly utilize the long-term key frames to mitigate temporal cascading errors and the short-term reference frames to minimize prediction errors. Moreover, our buffering scheme enables the temporal prediction structure to be adapted to individual input videos. While this flexibility is common in traditional video codecs, it has not been fully explored for learned video codecs. Extensive experiments show that the proposed method outperforms VTM-17.0 under the low-delay B configuration in terms of PSNR-RGB across commonly used test datasets, and performs comparably to the state-of-the-art learned codecs (e.g.~DCVC-FM) while requiring less decoded frame buffer and similar decoding time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12479v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huu-Tai Phung, Zong-Lin Gao, Yi-Chen Yao, Kuan-Wei Ho, Yi-Hsin Chen, Yu-Hsiang Lin, Alessandro Gnutti, Wen-Hsiao Peng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A High-Level Feature Model to Predict the Encoding Energy of a Hardware Video Encoder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12754v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In today's society, live video streaming and user generated content streamed from battery powered devices are ubiquitous. Live streaming requires real-time video encoding, and hardware video encoders are well suited for such an encoding task. In this paper, we introduce a high-level feature model using Gaussian process regression that can predict the encoding energy of a hardware video encoder. In an evaluation setup restricted to only P-frames and a single keyframe, the model can predict the encoding energy with a mean absolute percentage error of approximately 9%. Further, we demonstrate with an ablation study that spatial resolution is a key high-level feature for encoding energy prediction of a hardware encoder. A practical application of our model is that it can be used to perform a prior estimation of the energy required to encode a video at various spatial resolutions, with different coding standards and codec presets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12754v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diwakara Reddy, Christian Herglotz, Andr\'e Kaup</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ivan-ISTD: Rethinking Cross-domain Heteroscedastic Noise Perturbations in Infrared Small Target Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12241</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12241v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the multimedia domain, Infrared Small Target Detection (ISTD) plays a important role in drone-based multi-modality sensing. To address the dual challenges of cross-domain shift and heteroscedastic noise perturbations in ISTD, we propose a doubly wavelet-guided Invariance learning framework(Ivan-ISTD). In the first stage, we generate training samples aligned with the target domain using Wavelet-guided Cross-domain Synthesis. This wavelet-guided alignment machine accurately separates the target background through multi-frequency wavelet filtering. In the second stage, we introduce Real-domain Noise Invariance Learning, which extracts real noise characteristics from the target domain to build a dynamic noise library. The model learns noise invariance through self-supervised loss, thereby overcoming the limitations of distribution bias in traditional artificial noise modeling. Finally, we create the Dynamic-ISTD Benchmark, a cross-domain dynamic degradation dataset that simulates the distribution shifts encountered in real-world applications. Additionally, we validate the versatility of our method using other real-world datasets. Experimental results demonstrate that our approach outperforms existing state-of-the-art methods in terms of many quantitative metrics. In particular, Ivan-ISTD demonstrates excellent robustness in cross-domain scenarios. The code for this work can be found at: https://github.com/nanjin1/Ivan-ISTD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12241v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuehui Li, Yahao Lu, Haoyuan Wu, Sen Zhang, Liang Lin, Yukai Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AngularFuse: A Closer Look at Angle-based Perception for Spatial-Sensitive Multi-Modality Image Fusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12260v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Visible-infrared image fusion is crucial in key applications such as autonomous driving and nighttime surveillance. Its main goal is to integrate multimodal information to produce enhanced images that are better suited for downstream tasks. Although deep learning based fusion methods have made significant progress, mainstream unsupervised approaches still face serious challenges in practical applications. Existing methods mostly rely on manually designed loss functions to guide the fusion process. However, these loss functions have obvious limitations. On one hand, the reference images constructed by existing methods often lack details and have uneven brightness. On the other hand, the widely used gradient losses focus only on gradient magnitude. To address these challenges, this paper proposes an angle-based perception framework for spatial-sensitive image fusion (AngularFuse). At first, we design a cross-modal complementary mask module to force the network to learn complementary information between modalities. Then, a fine-grained reference image synthesis strategy is introduced. By combining Laplacian edge enhancement with adaptive histogram equalization, reference images with richer details and more balanced brightness are generated. Last but not least, we introduce an angle-aware loss, which for the first time constrains both gradient magnitude and direction simultaneously in the gradient domain. AngularFuse ensures that the fused images preserve both texture intensity and correct edge orientation. Comprehensive experiments on the MSRS, RoadScene, and M3FD public datasets show that AngularFuse outperforms existing mainstream methods with clear margin. Visual comparisons further confirm that our method produces sharper and more detailed results in challenging scenes, demonstrating superior fusion capability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12260v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaopeng Liu, Yupei Lin, Sen Zhang, Xiao Wang, Yukai Shi, Liang Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Targeted Pooled Latent-Space Steganalysis Applied to Generative Steganography, with a Fix</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12414v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Steganographic schemes dedicated to generated images modify the seed vector in the latent space to embed a message, whereas most steganalysis methods attempt to detect the embedding in the image space. This paper proposes to perform steganalysis in the latent space by modeling the statistical distribution of the norm of the latent vector. Specifically, we analyze the practical security of a scheme proposed by Hu et. al. for latent diffusion models, which is both robust and practically undetectable when steganalysis is performed on generated images. We show that after embedding, the Stego (latent) vector is distributed on a hypersphere while the Cover vector is i.i.d. Gaussian. By going from the image space to the latent space, we show that it is possible to model the norm of the vector in the latent space under the Cover or Stego hypothesis as Gaussian distributions with different variances. A Likelihood Ratio Test is then derived to perform pooled steganalysis. The impact of the potential knowledge of the prompt and the number of diffusion steps, is also studied. Additionally, we also show how, by randomly sampling the norm of the latent vector before generation, the initial Stego scheme becomes undetectable in the latent space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12414v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Etienne Levecque (LIST3N), Aur\'elien Noirault (CRIStAL), Tom\'a\v{s} Pevn\'y (CTU), Jan Butora (CRIStAL), Patrick Bas (CRIStAL), R\'emi Cogranne (LIST3N)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Logarithmic Mathematical Morphology: theory and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.02007</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.02007v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In Mathematical Morphology for grey-level functions, an image is analysed by another image named the structuring function. This structuring function is translated over the image domain and summed to the image. However, in an image presenting lighting variations, the amplitude of the structuring function should vary according to the image intensity. Such a property is not verified in Mathematical Morphology for grey level functions, when the structuring function is summed to the image with the usual additive law. In order to address this issue, a new framework is defined with an additive law for which the amplitude of the structuring function varies according to the image amplitude. This additive law is chosen within the Logarithmic Image Processing framework and models the lighting variations with a physical cause such as a change of light intensity. The new framework is named Logarithmic Mathematical Morphology (LMM) and allows the definition of operators which are robust to such lighting variations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.02007v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillaume Noyel (CRESTIC)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BAAF: A benchmark attention adaptive framework for medical ultrasound image segmentation tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.00919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.00919v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The AI-based assisted diagnosis programs have been widely investigated on medical ultrasound images. Complex scenario of ultrasound image, in which the coupled interference of internal and external factors is severe, brings a unique challenge for localize the object region automatically and precisely in ultrasound images. In this study, we seek to propose a more general and robust Benchmark Attention Adaptive Framework (BAAF) to assist doctors segment or diagnose lesions and tissues in ultrasound images more quickly and accurately. Different from existing attention schemes, the BAAF consists of a parallel hybrid attention module (PHAM) and an adaptive calibration mechanism (ACM). Specifically, BAAF first coarsely calibrates the input features from the channel and spatial dimensions, and then adaptively selects more robust lesion or tissue characterizations from the coarse-calibrated feature maps. The design of BAAF further optimizes the "what" and "where" focus and selection problems in CNNs and seeks to improve the segmentation accuracy of lesions or tissues in medical ultrasound images. The method is evaluated on four medical ultrasound segmentation tasks, and the adequate experimental results demonstrate the remarkable performance improvement over existing state-of-the-art methods. In addition, the comparison with existing attention mechanisms also demonstrates the superiority of BAAF. This work provides the possibility for automated medical ultrasound assisted diagnosis and reduces reliance on human accuracy and precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.00919v3</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gongping Chen, Lei Zhao, Xiaotao Yin, Liang Cui, Jianxun Zhang, Yu Dai, Ningning Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Real-Time Endoscopic Stereo Matching under Fuzzy Tissue Boundaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00731v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Real-time acquisition of accurate scene depth is essential for automated robotic minimally invasive surgery. Stereo matching with binocular endoscopy can provide this depth information. However, existing stereo matching methods, designed primarily for natural images, often struggle with endoscopic images due to fuzzy tissue boundaries and typically fail to meet real-time requirements for high-resolution endoscopic image inputs. To address these challenges, we propose \textbf{RRESM}, a real-time stereo matching method tailored for endoscopic images. Our approach integrates a 3D Mamba Coordinate Attention module that enhances cost aggregation through position-sensitive attention maps and long-range spatial dependency modeling via the Mamba block, generating a robust cost volume without substantial computational overhead. Additionally, we introduce a High-Frequency Disparity Optimization module that refines disparity predictions near tissue boundaries by amplifying high-frequency details in the wavelet domain. Evaluations on the SCARED and SERV-CT datasets demonstrate state-of-the-art matching accuracy with a real-time inference speed of 42 FPS. The code is available at https://github.com/Sonne-Ding/RRESM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00731v3</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Ding, Can Han, Sijia Du, Yaqi Wang, Dahong Qian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anatomically and Metabolically Informed Diffusion for Unified Denoising and Segmentation in Low-Count PET Imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13257v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Positron emission tomography (PET) image denoising, along with lesion and organ segmentation, are critical steps in PET-aided diagnosis. However, existing methods typically treat these tasks independently, overlooking inherent synergies between them as correlated steps in the analysis pipeline. In this work, we present the anatomically and metabolically informed diffusion (AMDiff) model, a unified framework for denoising and lesion/organ segmentation in low-count PET imaging. By integrating multi-task functionality and exploiting the mutual benefits of these tasks, AMDiff enables direct quantification of clinical metrics, such as total lesion glycolysis (TLG), from low-count inputs. The AMDiff model incorporates a semantic-informed denoiser based on diffusion strategy and a denoising-informed segmenter utilizing nnMamba architecture. The segmenter constrains denoised outputs via a lesion-organ-specific regularizer, while the denoiser enhances the segmenter by providing enriched image information through a denoising revision module. These components are connected via a warming-up mechanism to optimize multi-task interactions. Experiments on multi-vendor, multi-center, and multi-noise-level datasets demonstrate the superior performance of AMDiff.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13257v3</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Menghua Xia, Kuan-Yin Ko, Der-Shiun Wang, Ming-Kai Chen, Qiong Liu, Huidong Xie, Liang Guo, Wei Ji, Jinsong Ouyang, Reimund Bayerlein, Benjamin A. Spencer, Quanzheng Li, Ramsey D. Badawi, Georges El Fakhri, Chi Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unsupervised patch-based dynamic MRI reconstruction using learnable tensor function with implicit neural representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21894v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dynamic MRI suffers from limited spatiotemporal resolution due to long acquisition times. Undersampling k-space accelerates imaging but makes accurate reconstruction challenging. Supervised deep learning methods achieve impressive results but rely on large fully sampled datasets, which are difficult to obtain. Recently, implicit neural representations (INR) have emerged as a powerful unsupervised paradigm that reconstructs images from a single undersampled dataset without external training data. However, existing INR-based methods still face challenges when applied to highly undersampled dynamic MRI, mainly due to their inefficient representation capacity and high computational cost. To address these issues, we propose TenF-INR, a novel unsupervised framework that integrates low-rank tensor modeling with INR, where each factor matrix in the tensor decomposition is modeled as a learnable factor function. Specifically,we employ INR to model learnable tensor functions within a low-rank decomposition, reducing the parameter space and computational burden. A patch-based nonlocal tensor modeling strategy further exploits temporal correlations and inter-patch similarities, enhancing the recovery of fine spatiotemporal details. Experiments on dynamic cardiac and abdominal datasets demonstrate that TenF-INR achieves up to 21-fold acceleration, outperforming both supervised and unsupervised state-of-the-art methods in image quality, temporal fidelity, and quantitative accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21894v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuanyuan Liu, Yuanbiao Yang, Jing Cheng, Zhuo-Xu Cui, Qingyong Zhu, Congcong Liu, Yuliang Zhu, Jingran Xu, Hairong Zheng, Dong Liang, Yanjie Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semi-Unsupervised Microscopy Segmentation with Fuzzy Logic and Spatial Statistics for Cross-Domain Analysis Using a GUI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15979v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Brightfield microscopy of unstained live cells is challenging due to low contrast, dynamic morphology, uneven illumination, and lack of labels. Deep learning achieved SOTA performance on stained, high-contrast images but needs large labeled datasets, expensive hardware, and fails under uneven illumination. This study presents a low-cost, lightweight, annotation-free segmentation method by introducing one-time calibration-assisted unsupervised framework adaptable across imaging modalities and image type. The framework determines background via spatial standard deviation from the local mean. Uncertain pixels are resolved using fuzzy logic, cumulative squared shift of nodal intensity, statistical features, followed by post-segmentation denoising calibration which is saved as a profile for reuse until noise pattern or object type substantially change. The program runs as a script or graphical interface for non-programmers. The method was rigorously evaluated using \textit{IoU}, \textit{F1-score}, and other metrics, with statistical significance confirmed via Wilcoxon signed-rank tests. On unstained brightfield myoblast (C2C12) images, it outperformed \textit{Cellpose 3.0} and \textit{StarDist}, improving IoU by up to 48\% (average IoU = 0.43, F1 = 0.60). In phase-contrast microscopy, it achieved a mean IoU of 0.69 and an F1-score of 0.81 on the \textit{LIVECell} dataset ($n = 3178$), with substantial expert agreement ($\kappa &gt; 0.75$) confirming cross-modality robustness. Successful segmentation of laser-affected polymer surfaces further confirmed cross-domain robustness. By introducing the \textit{Homogeneous Image Plane} concept, this work provides a new theoretical foundation for training-free, annotation-free segmentation. The framework operates efficiently on CPU, avoids cell staining, and is practical for live-cell imaging and biomedical applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15979v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Surajit Das, Pavel Zun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Fine-Tuning of DINOv3 Pretrained on Natural Images for Atypical Mitotic Figure Classification (MIDOG 2025 Task 2 Winner)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.21041v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Atypical mitotic figures (AMFs) represent abnormal cell division associated with poor prognosis. Yet their detection remains difficult due to low prevalence, subtle morphology, and inter-observer variability. The MIDOG 2025 challenge introduces a benchmark for AMF classification across multiple domains. In this work, we fine-tuned the recently published DINOv3-H+ vision transformer, pretrained on natural images, using low-rank adaptation (LoRA), training only ~1.3M parameters in combination with extensive augmentation and a domain-weighted Focal Loss to handle domain heterogeneity. Despite the domain gap, our fine-tuned DINOv3 transfers effectively to histopathology, reaching first place on the final test set. These results highlight the advantages of DINOv3 pretraining and underline the efficiency and robustness of our fine-tuning strategy, yielding state-of-the-art results for the atypical mitosis classification challenge in MIDOG 2025.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.21041v3</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillaume Balezo, Hana Feki, Rapha\"el Bourgade, Lily Monnier, Matthieu Blons, Alice Blondel, Etienne Decenci\`ere, Albert Pla Planas, Thomas Walter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating the Impact of Radiographic Noise on Chest X-ray Semantic Segmentation and Disease Classification Using a Scalable Noise Injection Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25265</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25265v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Deep learning models are increasingly used for radiographic analysis, but their reliability is challenged by the stochastic noise inherent in clinical imaging. A systematic, cross-task understanding of how different noise types impact these models is lacking. Here, we evaluate the robustness of state-of-the-art convolutional neural networks (CNNs) to simulated quantum (Poisson) and electronic (Gaussian) noise in two key chest X-ray tasks: semantic segmentation and pulmonary disease classification. Using a novel, scalable noise injection framework, we applied controlled, clinically-motivated noise severities to common architectures (UNet, DeepLabV3, FPN; ResNet, DenseNet, EfficientNet) on public datasets (Landmark, ChestX-ray14). Our results reveal a stark dichotomy in task robustness. Semantic segmentation models proved highly vulnerable, with lung segmentation performance collapsing under severe electronic noise (Dice Similarity Coefficient drop of 0.843), signifying a near-total model failure. In contrast, classification tasks demonstrated greater overall resilience, but this robustness was not uniform. We discovered a differential vulnerability: certain tasks, such as distinguishing Pneumothorax from Atelectasis, failed catastrophically under quantum noise (AUROC drop of 0.355), while others were more susceptible to electronic noise. These findings demonstrate that while classification models possess a degree of inherent robustness, pixel-level segmentation tasks are far more brittle. The task- and noise-specific nature of model failure underscores the critical need for targeted validation and mitigation strategies before the safe clinical deployment of diagnostic AI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25265v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Derek Jiu, Kiran Nijjer, Nishant Chinta, Ryan Bui, Kevin Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniLens: Towards Universal Lens Aberration Correction via LensLib-to-Specific Domain Adaptation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05809v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Emerging universal Computational Aberration Correction (CAC) paradigms provide an inspiring solution to light-weight and high-quality imaging with a universal model trained on a lens library (LensLib) to address arbitrary lens aberrations blindly. However, the limited coverage of existing LensLibs leads to poor generalization of the trained models to unseen lenses, whose fine-tuning pipeline is also confined to the lens-descriptions-known case. In this work, we introduce OmniLens, a flexible solution to universal CAC via (i) establishing a convincing LensLib with comprehensive coverage for pre-training a robust base model, and (ii) adapting the model to any specific lens designs with unknown lens descriptions via fast LensLib-to-specific domain adaptation. To achieve these, an Evolution-based Automatic Optical Design (EAOD) pipeline is proposed to generate a rich variety of lens samples with realistic aberration behaviors. Then, we design an unsupervised regularization term for efficient domain adaptation on a few easily accessible real-captured images based on the statistical observation of dark channel priors in degradation induced by lens aberrations. Extensive experiments demonstrate that the LensLib generated by EAOD effectively develops a universal CAC model with strong generalization capabilities, which can also improve the non-blind lens-specific methods by 0.35-1.81dB in PSNR. Additionally, the proposed domain adaptation method significantly improves the base model, especially in severe aberration cases (at most 2.59dB in PSNR). The code and data will be available at https://github.com/zju-jiangqi/OmniLens.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05809v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qi Jiang, Yao Gao, Shaohua Gao, Zhonghua Yi, Xiaolong Qian, Hao Shi, Kailun Yang, Lei Sun, Kaiwei Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DarkIR: Robust Low-Light Image Restoration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13443v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Photography during night or in dark conditions typically suffers from noise, low light and blurring issues due to the dim environment and the common use of long exposure. Although Deblurring and Low-light Image Enhancement (LLIE) are related under these conditions, most approaches in image restoration solve these tasks separately. In this paper, we present an efficient and robust neural network for multi-task low-light image restoration. Instead of following the current tendency of Transformer-based models, we propose new attention mechanisms to enhance the receptive field of efficient CNNs. Our method reduces the computational costs in terms of parameters and MAC operations compared to previous methods. Our model, DarkIR, achieves new state-of-the-art results on the popular LOLBlur, LOLv2 and Real-LOLBlur datasets, being able to generalize on real-world night and dark images. Code and models at https://github.com/cidautai/DarkIR</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13443v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Feijoo, Juan C. Benito, Alvaro Garcia, Marcos V. Conde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Software System for Low-Cost, GUI-Based Microscopy Segmentation: Algorithmic Implementation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11354v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This article presents a novel microscopy image analysis framework designed for low-budget labs equipped with a standard CPU desktop. The Python-based program enables cytometric analysis of live, unstained cells in culture through an advanced computer vision and machine learning pipeline. Crucially, the framework operates on label-free data, requiring no manually annotated training data or training phase. It is accessible via a user-friendly, cross-platform GUI that requires no programming skills, while also providing a scripting interface for programmatic control and integration by developers. The end-to-end workflow performs semantic and instance segmentation, feature extraction, analysis, evaluation, and automated report generation. Its modular architecture supports easy maintenance and flexible integration while supporting both single-image and batch processing. Validated on several unstained cell types from the public dataset of livecells, the framework demonstrates superior accuracy and reproducibility compared to contemporary tools like Cellpose and StarDist. Its competitive segmentation speed on a CPU-based platform highlights its significant potential for basic research and clinical application-particularly in cell transplantation for personalised medicine and muscle regeneration therapies. The access to the application is available for reproducibility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11354v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Surajit Das, Pavel Zun</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
