<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.supr-con updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con</link>
    <description>cond-mat.supr-con updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2024 04:00:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Electrical control of superconducting spin valves using ferromagnetic helices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05798v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The geometrical properties of a helical ferromagnet are shown theoretically to control the critical temperature of a proximity-coupled superconductor. Using the Usadel equation for diffusive spin transport, we provide self-consistent analysis of how curvature and torsion modulate the proximity effect. When the helix is attached to a piezoelectric actuator, the pitch of the helix -- and hence the superconducting transition -- can be controlled electrically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05798v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tancredi Salamone, Henning G. Hugdal, Morten Amundsen, Sol H. Jacobsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Current dependence of the low bias resistance of small capacitance Josephson junctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05890v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The dc current-voltage characteristics of small Josephson junctions reveal features that are not observed in larger junctions, in particular, a switch to the finite voltage state at current values much less than the expected critical current of the junction and a finite resistance in the nominally superconducting regime. Both phenomena are due to the increased sensitivity to noise associated with the small capacitance of the Josephson junction and have been extensively studied a few decades ago. Here I focus on the current bias dependence of the differential resistance of the junction at low current bias in the nominally superconducting regime, using a quantum Langevin equation approach that enables a physically transparent incorporation of the noise environment of the junction. A similar approach might be useful in modeling the sensitivity of superconducting qubits to noise in the microwave regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05890v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Venkat Chandrasekhar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Copper doping effects on the superconducting properties of Sm-based oxypnictides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06146v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A systematic investigation has been performed by synthesis and comprehensive characterization of a series of SmFe1-xCuxAsO0.8F0.2 bulks (x = 0 to 0.2). These samples are well characterized by structural, Raman spectroscopy, microstructural, transport, magnetic measurements, and supplementary calculations within density functional theory (DFT). The parent compound, SmFeAsO0.8F0.2 (Sm1111), exhibits a superconducting transition temperature (Tc) of approximately 54 K. The lattice volume (V) is increased with Cu substitution (x) without observing any impurity phase related to copper, which confirms the successful incorporation of Cu at Fe sites in the superconducting FeAs layers. These analyses are also well in agreement with Raman spectroscopy measurements and relevant DFT results. The superconducting transition is decreased systematically with copper doping and completely suppressed for 7% Cu-doped Sm1111 (x = 0.07). A large amount of Cu substitution (x greater than 0.07) has demonstrated the metal to insulate transition in the low-temperature range, and no impurity phase was observed even at high Cu doping levels (x = 0.2). The calculated critical current density of the parent sample is suppressed with copper substitution, suggesting the reduced pinning centers, sample density, and grain connections, as confirmed by the microstructural analysis. Our studies suggest that the substitution of Cu in the superconducting FeAs layer, resulting the enlargement of the lattice volume, is a source of strong disorder scattering, leading to the suppression of Tc and the emergence of metal-to-insulator, unlike the more successful carrier doping by nickel (Ni) or cobalt (Co), as previously reported.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06146v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Azam, Manasa Manasa, Tatiana Zajarniuk, Taras Palasyuk, Ryszard Diduszko, Tomasz Cetner, Andrzej Morawski, Cezariusz Jastrzebski, Micha{\l} Wierzbicki, Andrzej Wi\'sniewski, Shiv J. Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless vortex unbinding transition in two-dimensional superconductors using local noise magnetometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06147</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06147v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The melting of quasi-long-range superconductivity in two spatial dimensions occurs through the proliferation and unbinding of vortex-antivortex pairs -- a phenomenon known as the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless (BKT) transition. Although signatures of this transition have been observed in bulk measurements, these experiments are often complicated, ambiguous, and unable to resolve the rich physics of the vortex unbinding transition. Here we show that local noise magnetometry is a sensitive, noninvasive probe that can provide direct information about the scale-dependent vortex dynamics. In particular, by resolving the distance and temperature dependence of the magnetic noise, it may be possible to experimentally study the renormalization group flow equations of the vortex gas and track the onset of vortex unbinding in situ. Specifically, we predict i) a nonmonotonic dependence of the noise on temperature and ii) the local noise is almost independent of the sample-probe distance at the BKT transition. We also show that noise magnetometry can distinguish Gaussian superconducting order-parameter fluctuations from topological vortex fluctuations and can detect the emergence of unbound vortices. The weak distance dependence at the BKT transition can also be used to distinguish it from quasiparticle background noise. Our predictions may be within experimental reach for a number of unconventional superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06147v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan B. Curtis, Nikola Maksimovic, Nicholas R. Poniatowski, Amir Yacoby, Bertrand Halperin, Prineha Narang, Eugene Demler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Constant self-consistent scattering lifetime in superconducting Strontium Ruthenate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06262v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this numerical work, we find a self-consistent constant scattering superconducting lifetime for two different values of the disorder parameters, the inverse atomic strength, and the stoichiometric impurity in the triplet paired unconventional super-conductor strontium ruthenate. This finding is relevant for experimentalists given that the expressions for the ultrasound attenuation and the electronic thermal conductivity depend on the superconducting scattering lifetime, and a constant lifetime fits well nonequilibrium experimental data. Henceforth, this work helps experimentalists in their interpretation of the acquired data. Additionally, we encountered tiny imaginary parts of the self-energy that resembles the Miyake-Narikiyo tiny gap out-side the unitary elastic scattering limit, and below the threshold zero gap value of 1.0 meV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06262v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro L. Contreras E</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced weak superconductivity in trigonal $\gamma$-PtBi$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.00105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.00105v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Electrical resistivity experiments show superconductivity at $T_c = 1.1\,$K in a high-quality single crystal of trigonal $\gamma$-PtBi$_2$, with an enhanced critical magnetic field $\mu_0H_{c2}(0) \gtrsim 1.5\,$Tesla and a low critical current-density $J_c(0)\approx 40\,\mathrm{A}/\mathrm{cm}^2$ at $H=0$. Both $T_c$ and $H_{c2}(0)$ are the highest reported values for stoichiometric bulk samples at ambient pressure. We found a weak $H_{c2}$ anisotropy with $\Gamma=H_{c2}^{ab}/H_{c2}^{c} &lt; 1$, which is unusual among superconductors. Under a magnetic field, the superconducting transition becomes broader and asymmetric. Along with the low critical currents, this observation suggests an inhomogeneous superconducting state. In fact, no trace of superconductivity is observed through field-cooling--zero-field-cooling magnetization experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.00105v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-648X/ad3878</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>J. Zabala, P. Pedrazzini, F. J. Castro, V. F. Correa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>"Quantum bipolaron'' superconductivity from quadratic electron-phonon coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.03844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.03844v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: When the electron-phonon coupling is quadratic in the phonon coordinates, electrons can pair to form bipolarons due to phonon zero-point fluctuations, a purely quantum effect. We study superconductivity originating from this pairing mechanism in a minimal model and reveal that, in the strong coupling regime, the critical temperature ($T_c$) is only mildly suppressed by the coupling strength, in stark contrast to the exponential suppression in linearly coupled systems, thus implying higher optimal $T_c$ values. We demonstrate that large coupling constants of this flavor are achieved in known materials such as perovskites, and discuss strategies to realize such superconductivity using superlattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.03844v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhaoyu Han, Steven A. Kivelson, Pavel A. Volkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Andreev bound states in Josephson junctions of semi-Dirac semimetals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.00506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.00506v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a Josephson junction built with the two-dimensional semi-Dirac semimetal, which features a hybrid of linear and quadratic dispersion around a nodal point. We model the weak link between the two superconducting regions by a Dirac delta potential because it mimics the thin-barrier-limit of a superconductor-barrier-superconductor configuration. Assuming a homogeneous pairing in each region, we set up the BdG formalism for electronlike and holelike quasiparticles propagating along the quadratic-in-momentum dispersion direction. This allows us to compute the discrete bound-state energy spectrum $\varepsilon $ of the subgap Andreev states localized at the junction. In contrast with the Josephson effect investigated for propagation along linearly dispersing directions, we find a pair of doubly degenerate Andreev bound states. Using the dependence of $\varepsilon $ on the superconducting phase difference $\phi$, we compute the variation of Josephson current as a function of $\phi$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.00506v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physb.2024.415918</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physica B: Condensed Matter 683, 415918 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ipsita Mandal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasiclassical theory of superconducting spin-splitter effects and spin-filtering via altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04851v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Conducting altermagnets have recently emerged as intriguing materials supporting strongly spin-polarized currents without magnetic stray fields. We demonstrate that altermagnets enable three key functionalities, merging superconductivity and spintronics. The first prediction is a controllable supercurrent-induced edge magnetization, which acts like a dissipationless spin-splitter effect. The second and third predictions are a Cooper pair spin-splitter and a filtering effect, respectively. These effects allow for spatial separation of triplet pairs with opposite spin-polarizations and spin-selective tunneling of Cooper pairs. We derive a quasiclassical theory with associated boundary conditions that describe these phenomena and explain how they can be experimentally verified. Our results open a new path for spatial control of spin signals via triplet Cooper pairs using hybrid superconductor-altermagnet devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04851v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hans Gl{\o}ckner Giil, Bj{\o}rnulf Brekke, Jacob Linder, Arne Brataas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Local Spin Nematicity to Altermagnets: Footprints of Band Topology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14620v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Altermagnets are crystallographic rotational symmetry breaking spin-ordered states, possessing a net zero magnetization despite manifesting Kramers non-degenerate bands. Here, we show that momentum-independent local spin nematic orders in monolayer, Bernal bilayer and rhombohedral trilayer graphene give rise to $p$-wave, $d$-wave and $f$-wave altermagnets, respectively, thereby inheriting topology of linear, quadratic and cubic free fermion band dispersions that are also described in terms of angular momentum $\ell=1,\; 2$ and $3$ harmonics in the reciprocal space. The same conclusions also hold inside a spin-triplet nematic superconductor, featuring Majorana altermagnets. Altogether, these findings highlight the importance of electronic band structure in identifying such exotic magnetic orders in quantum materials. We depict the effects of in-plane magnetic fields on altermagnets, and propose novel spin-disordered alter-valleymagnets in these systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14620v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanjib Kumar Das, Bitan Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
