<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.supr-con updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con</link>
    <description>cond-mat.supr-con updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 04:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Solvable models of two-level systems coupled to itinerant electrons: Robust non-Fermi liquid and quantum critical pairing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06532v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Strange metal behavior is traditionally associated with an underlying putative quantum critical point at zero temperature. However, in many correlated metals, e.g., high-Tc cuprate superconductors, strange metallicity persists at low temperatures over an extended range of microscopic parameters, suggesting the existence of an underlying quantum critical phase, whose possible physical origins remain poorly understood. Systematic investigations of physical scenarios giving rise to such a critical, non-Fermi liquid (NFL) phase are therefore crucial to better understand this puzzling behavior. In a previous work [Bashan et al. arXiv:2310.07768], we considered a solvable large-N model consisting of itinerant electrons coupled to local two-level systems (TLSs) via spatially random interactions, inspired by the possibility of emergent metallic glassiness due to frustrated competing orders, and found that the system hosts an NFL phase with tunable exponents at intermediate couplings. In this work, we expand our investigation to the following: (i) We study the extent to which this NFL phase is generic by considering various deformations of our theory, including coupling of electrons to multiple operators of the TLSs and arbitrarily directed TLS-fields. We find that the physical picture obtained in Bashan et al. qualitatively persist in a wide region of parameter space, showcasing the robustness of the NFL phase; (ii) We analyze the superconducting instability due to coupling of TLSs to electrons, and find a rich structure, including quantum critical pairing associated with the NFL phase and conventional BCS pairing in the weak and strong coupling limits; (iii) We elaborate on the analysis of Bashan et al., including single-particle, transport and thermodynamic properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06532v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evyatar Tulipman, Noga Bashan, J\"org Schmalian, Erez Berg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subgap states in semiconductor-superconductor devices for quantum technologies: Andreev qubits and minimal Majorana chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06592v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In recent years, experimental advances have made it possible to achieve an unprecedented degree of control over the properties of subgap bound states in hybrid nanoscale superconducting structures. This research has been driven by the promise of engineering subgap states for quantum applications, which includes Majorana zero modes predicted to appear at the interface of superconductor and other materials, like topological insulators or semiconductors. In this chapter, we revise the status of the field towards the engineering of quantum devices in controllable semiconductor-superconductor heterostructures. We begin the chapter with a brief introduction about subgap states, focusing on their mathematical formulation. After introducing topological superconductivity using the Kitaev model, we discuss the advances in the search for Majorana states over the last few years, highlighting the difficulties of unambiguously distinguish these states from nontopological subgap states. In recent years, the precise engineering of bound states by a bottom-up approach using quantum dots has led to unprecedented experimental advances, including experimental demonstrations of an Andreev qubits based on a quantum dot Josephson junction and a minimal Kitaev chain based on two quantum dots coherently coupled by the bound states of an intermediate superconducting segment. These experimental advances have revitalized the field and helped to understand that, far from being a disadvantage, the presence of subgap bound states can be exploited for new qubit designs and quantum coherence experiments, including Majorana-based qubits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06592v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rub\'en Seoane Souto, Ram\'on Aguado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noise-Tolerance of Majorana Teleportation in Mesoscopic Topological Superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06677v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate teleportation interference associated with the non-local character of Majorana zero modes (MZMs) as a probe of MZMs focusing on the tolerance of teleportation against disturbances, such as inhomogeneous potentials at junctions and disorder. We develop a method for calculating non-local conductance in mesoscopic topological superconductors with fixed parity. In the trivial phase, the non-local conductance exhibits the $h/2e$-periodicity, while in the topological phase with fixed parity, it exhibits the $h/e$-periodicity, indicative of Majorana teleportation. We find that the $h/e$-periodicity is stable against changes in inhomogeneous potential structures and disorder. These results imply that MZMs can cause teleportation interference even in the presence of disturbances, leading to a clear distinction between the trivial and topological phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06677v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tsukasa Goto, Masayuki Sugeta, Takeshi Mizushima, Satoshi Fujimoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SQUID oscillations in PbTe nanowire networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06899v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Network structures by semiconductor nanowires hold great promise for advanced quantum devices, especially for applications in topological quantum computing. In this study, we created networks of PbTe nanowires arranged in loop configurations. Using shadow-wall epitaxy, we defined superconducting quantum interference devices (SQUIDs) using the superconductor Pb. These SQUIDs exhibit oscillations in supercurrent upon the scanning of a magnetic field. Most of the oscillations can be fitted assuming a sinusoidal current-phase relation for each Josephson junction. Under certain conditions, the oscillations are found to be skewed, suggesting possible deviation from a sinusoidal behavior. Our results highlight the potential of PbTe nanowires for building complex quantum devices in the form of networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06899v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yichun Gao, Wenyu Song, Zehao Yu, Shuai Yang, Yuhao Wang, Ruidong Li, Fangting Chen, Zuhan Geng, Lining Yang, Jiaye Xu, Zhaoyu Wang, Zonglin Li, Shan Zhang, Xiao Feng, Tiantian Wang, Yunyi Zang, Lin Li, Runan Shang, Qi-Kun Xue, Ke He, Hao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ubiquitous light real-space pairing from long-range hopping and interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.06498v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We systematically examine how long-range hopping and its synergy with extended interactions leads to light bound pairs. Pair properties are determined for a dilute extended Hubbard model with large on-site repulsion ($U$) and both near- and next-nearest neighbour hopping ($t$ and $t'$) and attraction ($V$ and $V'$), for cubic and tetragonal lattices. The presence of $t'$ and $V'$ promotes light pairs. For tetragonal lattices, $t'&lt;0$ pairs can be lighter than non-interacting particles, and $d$-symmetric pairs form. Close packing transition temperatures, $T^{\ast}$ are estimated for the Bose-Einstein condensation (BEC) of pairs to be $k_{B}T^{\ast}\sim\overline{t} 0.1$, where $\overline{t}$ is the geometric mean of the hoppings on the Cartesian axes. When pairs have $d$-symmetry, the condensate has $d$-wave character. Thus, the presence of both $t'$ and $V'$ leads ubiquitously to small strongly bound pairs with an inverse mass that is linear in hopping, which could lead to high temperature BECs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.06498v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physleta.2024.129474</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>G. D. Adebanjo, J. P. Hague, P. E. Kornilovitch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-constant geometric curvature for tailored spin-orbit coupling and chirality in superconductor-magnet heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.06774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.06774v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that tailoring the geometric curvature profile of magnets can be used for bespoke design of an effective non-relativistic spin-orbit coupling, which may be used to control proximity effects if the magnet is coupled to a superconductor. We consider proximity-coupled one-dimensional magnetic wires with variable curvatures, specifically three distinct shapes classified as J-, C-, and S-type. We demonstrate a chirality-dependent spin polarization of the superconducting correlations, and show the role of curvature in determining the ground state of mixed-chirality junctions. We speculate on how this may be implemented in novel device design, and include analysis of its usage in a spin-triplet SQUID</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.06774v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-648X/ad2e23</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 36 235302 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alv Johan Skarpeid, Henning G. Hugdal, Tancredi Salamone, Morten Amundsen, Sol H. Jacobsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence of Ginzburg-Landau expansions: superconductivity in the Bardeen-Cooper-Schrieffer theory and chiral symmetry breaking in the Nambu-Jona-Lasinio model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.16372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.16372v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the convergence of the Ginzburg-Landau (GL) expansion in the context of the Bardeen-Cooper-Schrieffer (BCS) theory for superconductivity and the Nambu-Jona-Lasinio (NJL) model for chiral symmetry breaking at finite temperature $T$ and chemical potential $\mu$. We present derivations of the all-order formulas for the coefficients of the GL expansions in both systems under the mean-field approximation. We show that the convergence radii for the BCS gap $\Delta$ and dynamical quark mass $M$ are given by $\Delta_\text{conv} = \pi T$ and $M_\text{conv} = \sqrt{\mu^2 + (\pi T)^2}$, respectively. We also discuss the implications of these results and the quantitative reliability of the GL expansion near the first-order chiral phase transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.16372v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/ptep/ptae032</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PTEP 2024 (2024) 4, 043D01</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>William Gyory, Naoki Yamamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
