<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.supr-con updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con</link>
    <description>cond-mat.supr-con updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2024 04:00:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Superconducting transition temperatures of pure vanadium and vanadium-titanium alloys in the presence of dynamical electronic correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13202v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ordinary superconductors are widely assumed insensitive to small concentrations of random nonmagnetic impurities, whereas strong disorder suppresses superconductivity, ultimately leading to a superconductor-insulator transition. In between these limiting cases, a most fascinating regime may emerge where disorder enhances superconductivity. This effect is discussed here for the $\beta$-phase of vanadium-titanium alloys. Disorder is modeled using the coherent potential approximation while local electronic interactions are treated using dynamical mean-field theory. The McMillan formula is employed to estimate the superconducting transition temperature, showing a maximum at a Ti concentration of around $0.33$ for a local Coulomb interaction $U$ in the range of $2$ to $3$ eV. Our calculations quantitatively agree with the experimentally observed concentration dependent increase of $T_c$, and its maximal value of about $20\%$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13202v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Jones, A. \"Ostlin, A. Weh, F. Beiuseanu, U. Eckern, L. Vitos, L. Chioncel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching Materials Space for Hydride Superconductors at Ambient Pressure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13496v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We employed a machine-learning assisted approach to search for superconducting hydrides under ambient pressure within an extensive dataset comprising over 150 000 compounds. Our investigation yielded around 50 systems with transition temperatures surpassing 20 K, and some even reaching above 70 K. These compounds have very different crystal structures, with different dimensionality, chemical composition, stoichiometry, and arrangement of the hydrogens. Interestingly, most of these systems displayed slight thermodynamic instability, implying that their synthesis would require conditions beyond ambient equilibrium. Moreover, we found a consistent chemical composition in the majority of these systems, which combines alkali or alkali-earth elements with noble metals. This observation suggests a promising avenue for future experimental investigations into high-temperature superconductivity within hydrides at ambient pressure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13496v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tiago F. T. Cerqueira, Yue-Wen Fang, Ion Errea, Antonio Sanna, Miguel A. L. Marques</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal transport across a Josephson junction in a dissipative environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13552</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13552v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: At zero temperature, a Josephson junction coupled to an ohmic environment displays a quantum phase transition between superconducting and insulating phases, depending whether the resistance of the environment is below or above the resistance quantum. At finite temperature, this so-called Schmid transition turns into a crossover. We determine the conditions under which the temperature dependence of the thermal conductance, which characterizes heat flow from a hot to cold resistor across the Josephson junction, displays universal scaling characteristic of the Schmid transition. We also discuss conditions for heat rectification to happen in the circuit. Our work can serve as a guide for identifying signatures of the Schmid transition in heat transport experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13552v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tsuyoshi Yamamoto, Leonid I. Glazman, Manuel Houzet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient exploration of high-Tc superconductors by a gradient-based composition design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13627v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a material design method via gradient-based optimization on compositions, overcoming the limitations of traditional methods: exhaustive database searches and conditional generation models. It optimizes inputs via backpropagation, aligning the model's output closely with the target property and facilitating the discovery of unlisted materials and precise property determination. Our method is also capable of adaptive optimization under new conditions without retraining. Applying to exploring high-Tc superconductors, we identified potential compositions beyond existing databases and discovered new hydrogen superconductors via conditional optimization. This method is versatile and significantly advances material design by enabling efficient, extensive searches and adaptability to new constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13627v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akihiro Fujii, Koji Shimizu, Satoshi Watanabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photonic heat transport through a Josephson junction in a resistive environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13526v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Motivated by recent experiments (Subero et. al. Nature Comm. $\bf{14}$, 7924 (2023)) we analyze photonic heat transport through a Josephson junction in a dissipative environment. For this purpose we derive the general expressions for the heat current in terms of non-equilibrium Green functions for the junction coupled in series or in parallel with two environmental impedances at different temperatures. We show that even on the insulating side of the Schmid transition the heat current is sensitive to the Josephson coupling exhibiting an opposite behavior for the series and parallel connection and in qualitative agreement with experiments. We also predict that this device should exhibit heat rectification properties and provide simple expressions to account for them in terms of the system parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13526v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Levy Yeyati, D. Subero, J. Pekola, R. S\'anchez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultraclean Andreev interferometers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13669</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13669v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Coupling a two-terminal Josephson junction to the stationary modes of the electromagnetic field produces the so-called Fiske resonances. Here, we propose another mechanism based on the exchange between the static Andreev bound states (ABS) and a nonequilibrium Fermi surface in an ultraclean multiterminal device. As a simple model, we consider an effective $S_a$-$N_{eff}$-$S_b$ double junction connecting the superconductors $S_a$ and $S_b$ to the infinite central normal metal $N_{eff}$. We find that the underlying microscopic process of phase-sensitive Andreev reflection (phase-AR) produces the possibility of an inversion, that is, the conductance can be larger at half-flux quantum than in zero field. The inversion-noninversion alternate as the bias voltage is increased. In addition, if the central region $N_{eff}$ is an integrable billiard connected to an infinite normal reservoir, we find that the standard ABS are replaced by one- and two-particle Andreev resonances that can be probed by the bias voltage. Finally, we find that, in the corresponding all-superconducting Andreev interferometer, the superconducting gap produces protection against the short relaxation time of the quasiparticle continua if the time periodic dynamics is treated as a perturbation. The spectrum of the two-particle resonances is then sparse inside the spectrum of the pairs of one-particle resonances. Our work supports the nonFloquet intrinsic resonances in two-dimensional metal-based Andreev interferometers, and challenges the Floquet theory of multiterminal Josephson junctions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13669v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R\'egis M\'elin, Asmaul Smitha Rashid, Morteza Kayyalha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Amperean superconductivity cannot be induced by deep subwavelength cavities in a two-dimensional material</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.10371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.10371v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Amperean superconductivity is an exotic phenomenon stemming from attractive effective electron-electron interactions (EEEIs) mediated by a transverse gauge field. Originally introduced in the context of quantum spin liquids and high-Tc superconductors, Amperean superconductivity has been recently proposed to occur at temperatures on the order of 1-20 K in two-dimensional, parabolic-band, electron gases embedded inside deep sub-wavelength optical cavities. In this work, we first generalize the microscopic theory of cavity-induced Amperean superconductivity to the case of graphene and then argue that this superconducting state cannot be achieved in the deep sub-wavelength regime. In the latter regime, indeed, a cavity induces only EEEIs between density fluctuations rather than the current-current interactions which are responsible for Amperean pairing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.10371v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.104513</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, 104513 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gian Marcello Andolina, Antonella De Pasquale, Francesco Maria Dimitri Pellegrino, Iacopo Torre, Frank H. L. Koppens, Marco Polini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlocality of Majorana bound states revealed by electron waiting times in a topological Andreev interferometer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.14964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.14964v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The analysis of waiting times of electron transfers has recently become experimentally accessible owing to advances in noninvasive probes working in the short-time regime. We study electron waiting times in a topological Andreev interferometer: a superconducting loop with controllable phase difference connected to a quantum spin Hall edge, where the edge state helicity enables the transfer of electrons and holes into separate leads, with transmission controlled by the loop's phase difference $\phi$. This setup features gapless Majorana bound states at $\phi=\pi$. The waiting times for electron transfers across the junction are sensitive to the presence of the gapless states, but are uncorrelated for all $\phi$. By contrast, at $\phi=\pi$ the waiting times of Andreev-scattered holes show a strong correlation and the crossed (hole-electron) distributions feature a unique behavior. Both effects exclusively result from the nonlocal properties of Majorana bound states. Consequently, electron waiting times and their correlations could circumvent some of the challenges for detecting topological superconductivity and Majorana states beyond conductance signatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.14964v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.6.L012062</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review Research (Letter) 6, L012062 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Paramita Dutta, Jorge Cayao, Annica M. Black-Schaffer, Pablo Burset</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interlayer Coupling Driven High-Temperature Superconductivity in La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ Under Pressure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.14965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.14965v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The newly discovered high-temperature superconductivity in La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ under pressure has attracted a great deal of attentions. The essential ingredient characterizing the electronic properties is the bilayer NiO$_2$ planes coupled by the interlayer bonding of $3d_{z^2}$ orbitals through the intermediate oxygen-atoms. In the strong coupling limit, the low energy physics is described by an intralayer antiferromagnetic spin-exchange interaction $J_{\parallel}$ between $3d_{x^2-y^2}$ orbitals and an interlayer one $J_{\perp}$ between $3d_{z^2}$ orbitals. Taking into account Hund's rule on each site and integrating out the $3d_{z^2}$ spin degree of freedom, the system reduces to a single-orbital bilayer $t$-$J$ model based on the $3d_{x^2-y^2}$ orbital. By employing the slave-boson approach, the self-consistent equations for the bonding and pairing order parameters are solved. Near the physically relevant $\frac{1}{4}$-filling regime (doping $\delta=0.3\sim 0.5$), the interlayer coupling $J_{\perp}$ tunes the conventional single-layer $d$-wave superconducting state to the $s$-wave one. A strong $J_{\perp}$ could enhance the inter-layer superconducting order, leading to a dramatically increased $T_c$. Interestingly, there could exist a finite regime in which an $s+id$ state emerges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.14965v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Lu, Zhiming Pan, Fan Yang, Congjun Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetointerferometry of multiterminal Josephson junctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.12964v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report a theoretical study of multiterminal Josephson junctions under the influence of a magnetic field $B$. We consider a ballistic rectangular two-dimensional metal $N_0$ connected by the edges to the left, right, top and bottom superconductors $S_L$, $S_R$, $S_T$ and $S_B$, respectively. We numerically calculate in the large-gap approximation the critical current $I_c$ versus $B$ between the left and right $S_L$ and $S_R$ for various aspect ratios, with the top and bottom $S_T$ and $S_B$ playing the role of superconducting mirrors. We find the critical current $I_c$ to be enhanced by orders of magnitude, especially at long distance, due to the phase rigidity provided by the mirrors. We obtain superconducting quantum interference device-like magnetic oscillations. With symmetric couplings, the self-consistent superconducting phase variables of the top and bottom mirrors take the values $0$ or $\pi$, as for emerging Ising degrees of freedom. We propose a simple effective Josephson junction circuit model that is compatible with these microscopic numerical calculations. From the $I_c(B)$ patterns we infer where the supercurrent flows in various device geometries. In particular in the elongated geometry, we show that the supercurrent flows between all pairs of contacts, which allows exploring the full phase space of the relevant phase differences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.12964v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.125406</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, 125406 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>R\'egis M\'elin, Clemens B. Winkelmann, Romain Danneau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scattering theory of mesons in doped antiferromagnetic Mott insulators: Multichannel perspective and Feshbach resonance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.02978v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Modeling the underlying pairing mechanism of charge carriers in strongly correlated electrons, starting from a microscopic theory, is among the central challenges of condensed-matter physics. Hereby, the key task is to understand what causes the appearance of superconductivity at comparatively high temperatures upon hole doping an antiferromagnetic (AFM) Mott insulator. Recently, it has been proposed that at strong coupling and low doping, the fundamental one- and two-hole meson-type constituents -- magnetic polarons and bipolaronic pairs -- likely realize an emergent Feshbach resonance producing near-resonant $d_{x^2-y^2}$ interactions between charge carriers. Here, we provide detailed calculations of the proposed scenario by describing the open and closed meson scattering channels in the $t$-$t'$-$J$ model using a truncated basis method. After integrating out the closed channel constituted by bipolaronic pairs, we find $d_{x^2-y^2}$ attractive interactions between open channel magnetic polarons. The closed form of the derived interactions allows us analyze the resonant pairing interactions and we find enhanced (suppressed) attraction for hole (electron) doping in our model. The formalism we introduce provides a framework to analyze the implications of a possible Feshbach scenario, e.g. in the context of BEC-BCS crossover, and establishes a foundation to test quantitative aspects of the proposed Feshbach pairing mechanisms in doped antiferromagnets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.02978v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.125135</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, 125135 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Homeier, Pit Bermes, Fabian Grusdt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinetic inductance traveling wave amplifier designs for practical microwave readout applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11354v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A Kinetic Inductance Traveling Wave amplifier (KIT) utilizes the nonlinear kinetic inductance of superconducting films, particularly Niobium Titanium Nitride (NbTiN), for parametric amplification. These amplifiers achieve remarkable performance in terms of gain, bandwidth, compression power, and frequently approach the quantum limit for noise. However, most KIT demonstrations have been isolated from practical device readout systems. Using a KIT as the first amplifier in the readout chain of an unoptimized microwave SQUID multiplexer coupled to a transition-edge sensor microcalorimeter we see an initial improvement in the flux noise. One challenge in KIT integration is the considerable microwave pump power required to drive the non-linearity. To address this, we have initiated efforts to reduce the pump power by using thinner NbTiN films and an inverted microstrip transmission line design. In this article, we present the new transmission line design, fabrication procedure, and initial device characterization -- including gain and added noise. These devices exhibit over 10 dB of gain with a 3 dB bandwidth of approximately 5.5-7.25 GHz, a maximum practical gain of 12 dB and typical gain ripple under 4 dB peak-to-peak. We observe an appreciable impedance mismatch in the NbTiN transmission line, which is likely the source of the majority of the gain ripple. Finally we perform an initial noise characterization and demonstrate system-added noise of three quanta or less over nearly the entire 3 dB bandwidth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11354v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Giachero, M. Visser, J. Wheeler, L. Howe, J. Gao, J. Austermann, J. Hubmayr, A. Nucciotti, J. Ullom</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
