<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.supr-con updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con</link>
    <description>cond-mat.supr-con updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 01:35:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Topological in-gap chiral edge states in superconducting Haldane model with spin-orbit coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09418v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Topological superconductivity is currently one of the prime interests, given the properties of its exotic nature of chiral edge states. A broken time-reversal symmetry (TRS) is an essential ingredient in the recipe of a chiral edge state. The Haldane model is one of the many factors that can break TRS in a system. Thus, we explore the possibility of topological superconductivity in the Haldane model under the influence of a conventional superconductor. The edge states originating from such recipes mostly remain outside the superconducting gap. Contrary to this, in the presence of spin-orbit coupling, the edge modes lie within the superconducting gap, and can lead to a gapless state for some range of parameters. Moreover, we use band inversion and projection on the real-space lattice to confirm the topological and chiral nature of the obtained edge states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09418v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sajid Sekh, Andrzej Ptok</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perfect Superconducting Diode and Supercurrent Range Controller</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09478v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Diodes have a nonreciprocal voltage versus current relationship, produced by breaking the space and time reversal symmetry. However, developing high-end superconducting computers requires a superconducting analogue of the traditional semiconductor diode. Such a superconducting diode exhibits non-reciprocity, or a high asymmetry in its critical currents. We present a model of a perfect superconducting diode based on a superconducting quantum interference device made with multiple superconducting nanowires (MW-SQUID). The superconducting condensate in the nanowires is assumed to obey a linear current-phase relationship (CPR). The diode predicted by our model has a large positive critical current, while the negative critical current can be made exactly zero. Thus achieved 100\% diode efficiency ($\eta = 1$) remains stable against small changes of the magnetic field. Another important result is that under certain and quite broad conditions such devices can act as supercurrent range controllers. In such device a supercurrent can flow with zero voltage applied, but only if the supercurrent is contained in some narrow, adjustable range, which excludes zero current.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09478v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cliff Sun, Alexey Bezryadin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnon-induced transparency of a disordered antiferromagnetic Josephson junction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09516</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09516v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We considered a planar Josephson junction which is composed of two s-wave superconducting contacts deposited on the top of a thin antiferromagnetic (AFM) disordered metal film. In such a system noticeable Josephson currents may be observed, if contacts are just nanometers away from each other. It is shown that the excitation of AFM by magnons results in a strong enhancement of the stationary current through much longer junctions, whose length may be comparable to the coherence length of superconducting correlations in a nonmagnetic metal. Such a current is calculated at the weak tunneling amplitude of electrons between superconducting contacts and AFM. The problem is considered for nonequilibrium Green functions in the second-order perturbation theory with respect to the electron-magnon interaction. A spin-orbit torque oscillator was taken as a possible source of long-wavelength classic magnetic waves. This work predicts a strong effect of magnons on superconducting proximity effect in AFM, with promising applications in superconducting spintronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09516v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. G. Mal'shukov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum interference among vortex bound states in superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09519v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a recent experiment (Hou et al Phys. Rev. X 15, 011027), a new type of necklace-like vortex bound state (VBS) was observed and attributed to disorder induced interference among different Caroli-de Gennes-Matricon (CdGM) states within one single vortex. In this work, we further investigate the possibilities of quantum interference among the CdGM states from different vortices in clean superconductors, which may become significant near the upper critical field. We find a series of interference patterns in the local density of states (LDOS) due to the overlap between spatially separated individual CdGM states. On a vortex lattice, the interference can also lead to a necklace-like LDOS, hence, providing an alternative and intrinsic mechanism to observe the novel necklace-like, or other spatially modulated VBS more generally, in experiments. These results can be understood quite well within an effective tight-binding model constructed from the individual CdGM states, and can be checked in future experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09519v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1367-2630/adea18</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>New J. Phys. 27 073502 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yi-Ming Fu, Da Wang, Qiang-Hua Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinct Uniaxial Stress and Pressure Fingerprint of Superconductivity in the 3D Kagome Lattice Compound CeRu2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09779</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09779v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The exploration of tunable superconductivity in strongly correlated electron systems is a central pursuit in condensed matter physics, with implications for both fundamental understanding and potential applications. The Laves phase CeRu$_{2}$, a pyrochlore compound, exhibits a three-dimensional (3D) Kagome lattice type geometry giving rise to flat bands and degenerate Dirac points, where band structure features intertwine with strong multi-orbital interaction effects deriving from its correlated electronic structure. Here, we combine muon spin rotation ($\mu$SR), uniaxial in-plane stress, and hydrostatic pressure to probe the superconducting state of CeRu$_{2}$. Uniaxial stress up to 0.22 GPa induces a dome-shaped evolution of the critical temperature $T_{\rm c}$, with an initial plateau, successively followed by enhancement and suppression without any structural phase transition. Stress is further found to drive a crossover from anisotropic to isotropic $s$-wave pairing. In contrast, hydrostatic pressure up to 2.2 GPa leaves $T_{\rm c}$ largely unchanged but alters the superfluid density from exponential to linear behavior at low temperatures, indicative of nodal superconductivity under hydrostatic pressure. Taken together, these results indicate that CeRu$_{2}$ occupies an ideal position in parameter space, enabling highly responsive and multifold tunability of superconductivity in this three-dimensional correlated electronic system. This warrants further quantitative analysis of the interplay between lattice geometry, electronic correlations, and pairing symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09779v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>O. Gerguri, D. Das, V. Sazgari, H. X. Liu, C. Mielke III, P. Kr\`al, S. S. Islam, J. N. Graham, V. Grinenko, R. Sarkar, T. Shiroka, J. -X. Yin, J. Chang, R. Thomale, H. H. Klauss, R. Khasanov, Y. Shi, H. Luetkens, Z. Guguchia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancement of superconductivity outside Abrikosov vortex core in a tightly bound Cooper pair superconductor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09849</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09849v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Abrikosov vortices play a central role in the disruption of superconductivity in type-II superconductors. It is commonly accepted that as one moves away from the vortex's axis, the density of superconductive electrons gradually increases from zero to its bulk value. However, we demonstrate that this behavior is qualitatively altered in the zero-temperature limit provided that the Cooper pairs comprising the superconductive liquid are sufficiently tightly bound. Specifically, outside the vortex core, the density of superconductive electrons reaches a maximum surpassing its bulk value. This phenomenon has electrostatic origins: since normal electrons are absent and there exists a charged ionic background, the spatial variation of the charge density of superconductive electrons violates local neutrality, leading to the generation of an electric field. This electric field shrinks the vortex core and turns the density profile into that with a maximum, ensuring global neutrality. The effect is most pronounced in the limit of strong electrostatic screening, where the field configurations describing the vortex attain a universal form, with the electric field screened over a length scale determined by the London penetration depth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09849v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eugene B. Kolomeisky, Mia Kyler, Ishaan U. Patel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamic adsorption potential of superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09869v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Based on the general thermodynamic analysis of Polanyi adsorption potential, the adsorption potential condition for superconductors is obtained exactly by using the quantum state equation we presented. Because this adsorption potential results in changes of electron concentration, temperature and pressure in a certain volume (adsorption space) adjacent to the surface of the lattice, the composition and structure of superconductors are of course decisive for the adsorption potential. Then we calculate the molar adsorption potentials for those typical superconductors, and find that it is positively correlated to the superconductivity temperature , which reveals that those high-superconductors are mainly determined by the higher molar adsorption potentials. In addition, the adsorption potential at still works despite the disappearance of the energy gap of the BCS theory. This shows that beyond the electron-phonon interaction mechanism, the Cooper-paired electrons are mainly formed by this physical adsorption potential for high-superconductors. This adsorption potential theory could explain almost all common facts about high-temperature superconductors, including many anomalies of the normal and superconducting states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09869v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiu Hui Wu, Jiamin Niu, Kejiang Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eight-fold classification of superconducting orders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10079v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a thorough symmetry-based classification of superconducting order parameters that is independent of their microscopic origins. Our approach involves classifying pairing states through the pairwise permutation of spatial, temporal, spin, and orbital indices, focusing on the parities of the relative coordinates and times of the paired fields. This framework leads to the emergence of new classes of superconducting states, which we visualize as a multidimensional cube representing the relative parities in space and time, referred to as the Berezinskii-Abrahams hypercube. While some predicted states, such as odd-frequency superconductors, have been previously discussed, our symmetry analysis also reveals states that have yet to be explored, including odd-frequency Fulde-Ferrell-Larkin-Ovchinnikov (FFLO) states. Furthermore, we draw parallels to the classification of particle-hole states, and reiterate the possibility of new states, such as odd-frequency density waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10079v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander V. Balatsky, Saikat Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature dependence of surface superconductivity in t-PtBi$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10187</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10187v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Weyl semimetal trigonal PtBi$_2$ has recently been identified as a promising candidate material for intrinsic topological surface superconductivity emerging from the Fermi arc states of the material with a sizeable superconducting gap. We report the temperature evolution of the superconducting excitation spectrum using scanning tunneling spectroscopy in the range of $8-45\,$K. A large low-temperature gap in the order of $\Delta \approx 9\,$meV and a closing of the gap around $T_c \approx 45\,$K is observed. Thus, our results confirm the previously indicated high $T_c$-like superconductivity in t-PtBi$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10187v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julia Besproswanny, Sebastian Schimmel, Yanina Fasano, Grigory Shipunov, Saicharan Aswartham, Danny Baumann, Bernd B\"uchner, Christian Hess</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Effect of Pearl Vortices on the Shape and Position of N\'eel-Type Skyrmions in Superconductor-Chiral Ferromagnet Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10199</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10199v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This review presents recent work carried out at the Landau Institute for Theoretical Physics of the Russian Academy of Sciences on the study of the effect of superconducting vortices on the shape and position of N\'eel-type skyrmions in superconductor--chiral ferromagnet heterostructures. Based on analytical and numerical approaches, a number of effects caused by the inhomogeneous magnetic field of the vortex have been predicted: a significant increase in the skyrmion radius, a change in its chirality in the case of a coaxial configuration of the vortex and skyrmion, and modification of the skyrmion shape in the case of an eccentric configuration. Recent experiments studying these effects are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10199v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3367/UFNe.2025.05.039936</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>S. S. Apostoloff, E. S. Andriyakhina, I. S. Burmistrov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced superconductivity in the compressively strained bilayer nickelate thin films by pressure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10399v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The discovery of high temperature superconductivity in the nickelate system has stimulated enormous interest in the community of condensed matter physics. Recently, superconductivity with an onset transition temperature (Tc^onset) over 40 K was achieved in La3Ni2O7 and (La,Pr)3Ni2O7 thin films at ambient pressure due to in-plane compressive strain. This observation has sparked enormous attention because measurements on superconducting properties can be accessible with many commonly used experimental tools. On the other hand, the Tc in these thin films is much lower than that of the bulk bilayer nickelates under pressure. Here we report the enhancement of Tc^onset to over 60 K by applying hydrostatic pressure on the compressively strained superconducting bilayer nickelate thin films. The Tc^onset firstly ramps up with pressure, then it slightly drops down after reaching the maximum Tc^onset at about 61.5 K under a pressure of 9 GPa, showing a dome-like phase diagram. Hall effect measurements reveal that the dominant charge carriers are hole-like with a slight enhancement of charge carrier density with pressure in accompanying with the increase of Tc. Our theoretical results demonstrate that the enhancement of Tc arises from a cooperative amplification of magnetic fluctuations within and between the layers and increased metallicity under pressure. However, this enhancement exhibits saturation at higher pressures. These findings highlight the critical role of the interplay between interlayer and intralayer electronic correlations in bilayer nickelate superconductors and point to the potential of tuning Tc through controlled manipulation of the electronic structure and interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10399v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qing Li, Jianping Sun, Steffen Boetzel, Mengjun Ou, Zhe-Ning Xiang, Frank Lechermann, Bosen Wang, Yi Wang, Ying-Jie Zhang, Jinguang Cheng, Ilya M. Eremin, Hai-Hu Wen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal scaling of microwave dissipation in superconducting circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08953</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08953v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Improving the coherence of superconducting qubits is essential for advancing quantum technologies. While superconductors are theoretically perfect conductors, they consistently exhibit residual energy dissipation when driven by microwave currents, limiting coherence times. Here, we report a universal scaling between microwave dissipation and the superfluid density, a bulk property of superconductors related to charge carrier density and disorder. Our analysis spans a wide range of superconducting materials and device geometries, from highly disordered amorphous films to ultra-clean systems with record-high quality factors, including resonators, 3D cavities, and transmon qubits. This scaling reveals an intrinsic bulk dissipation channel, independent of surface dielectric losses, that originates from a universal density of nonequilibrium quasiparticles trapped within disorder-induced spatial variations of the superconducting gap. Our findings define a fundamental limit to coherence set by intrinsic material properties and provide a predictive framework for selecting materials and the design of next-generation superconducting quantum circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08953v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thibault Charpentier, Anton Khvalyuk, Lev Ioffe, Mikhail Feigel'man, Nicolas Roch, Benjamin Sac\'ep\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipation induced Majarona $0$- and $\pi$-modes in a driven Rashba nanowire</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10271v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Periodic drive is an intriguing way of creating topological phases in a non-topological setup. However, most systems are often studied as a closed system, despite being always in contact with the environment, which induces dissipation. Here, we investigate a periodically driven Rashba nanowire in proximity to an $s$-wave superconductor in a dissipative background. The system's dynamics is governed by a periodic Liouvillian operator, from which we construct the Liouvillian time-evolution operator and use the third-quantization method to obtain the `Floquet damping matrix', which captures the spectral and topological properties of the system. We show that the system exhibits edge-localized topological Majorana $0$-modes (MZMs) and $\pi$-modes (MPMs). Additionally, the system also supports a trivial $0$-modes (TZMs) and $\pi$-modes (TPMs), which are also localized at the edges of the system. The MZMs and the MPMs are connected to the bulk topology and carry a bulk topological invariant, while the emergence of TZMs and TPMs is primarily tied to exceptional points and is topologically trivial. We study the topological phase diagrams in terms of the topological invariants and show that the dissipation can modify the topological phase diagram substantially and even induce topological phases in the system. Our work extends the understanding of a driven-dissipative topological superconductor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10271v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koustabh Gogoi, Tanay Nag, Arnob Kumar Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quark model of nucleon based on an analogy with polaron</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10350v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate that the polaron theory from solid state physics can serve as an interesting analogue model for non-perturbative QCD, at least in the description of nucleons and related low-energy physics of strong interactions. By drawing explicit analogies between polaron physics, arising for an electron moving in an ionic crystal, and physics of pion-nucleon interactions, certain rules for the "polaron/QCD correspondence" are proposed. In polaron theory, the effective fermion mass as a function of the coupling constant is known both in the weak and strong coupling limits. The conjectured "polaron/QCD correspondence" translates these results into strong interactions. It is then shown how application of these rules leads to unexpectedly good quantitative predictions for the nucleon mass and the pion-nucleon sigma term. The polaron approach also predicts that the quark degrees of freedom in the form of the constituent quark account for one-third of the nucleon mass, consistent with lattice predictions. We discuss possible physical reasons underlying the observed quantitative similarity between polaron physics and non-perturbative QCD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10350v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. S. Afonin, A. V. Tulub</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hole distribution and self-doping enhanced electronic correlation in hole-doped infinite-layer nickelates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10364v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The minimal model for infinite-layer nickelates remains under debate, particularly regarding the hybridization between itinerant interstitial-$s$ and the correlated Ni-3$d_{x^2-y^2}$ orbitals, as well as the interaction between $d_{x^2-y^2}$ and other $3d$ orbitals. Additionally, how the doped holes in La$_{1-x}$Sr$_x$NiO$_2$ are distributed among different orbitals remain unresolved. Motivated by recent angle resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) experiments, we theoretically study the electronic structure of infinite-layer La$_{1-x}$Sr$_x$NiO$_2$ at various doping levels. We find that, unlike the expectation from a rigid band shift, holes are equally distributed to Ni-3$d_{x^2-y^2}$ and interstitial-$s$ orbitals. The role of interstitial-$s$ orbital is further confirmed from the renormalization of Ni-3$d_{x^2-y^2}$ band, for which the coupling between interstitial-$s$ and Ni-3$d_{x^2-y^2}$ exerts a non-negligible impact on the orbital-selective renormalization observed in ARPES. We also discuss the implication of our results to the single-band model, where the interstitial-$s$ orbital in the normal state of La$_{1-x}$Sr$_x$NiO$_2$ acts as charge donator enhancing the correlation of Ni-3$d_{x^2-y^2}$ by increasing its concentration close to half-filling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10364v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongbin Qu, Guang-Ming Zhang, Gang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Short range intervortex forces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10438v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: An explicit formula for the interaction energy of $n$ vortices in the abelian Higgs (or Ginzburg-Landau) model is derived, valid in the regime where all vortices are close to one another. An immediate consequence of this formula is that the interaction energy of a vortex pair with separation $d$ varies as $d^4$, not $d^2$. The formula contains $n-1$ real coefficients which are fixed by certain spectral data of the Jacobi operator of the cocentred $n$-vortex. The coefficients are computed numerically for $n=2$ and $n=3$ for couplings $0.1\leq \lambda\leq 2.5$. The resulting short range interaction potentials are compared with the results of full field theory simulations for $\lambda=0.5$ and $\lambda=2$, with excellent agreement at small to moderate vortex separation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10438v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Speight, Thomas Winyard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resonant Valance Bond and Bethe Ansatz on Quasi-1D Lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10471v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Hubbard model at $U\to\infty$ has recently been shown to have resonant valence bond (RVB) ground states on the corner-sharing sawtooth and pyrochlore lattices in the dilute doping limit of a single vacancy. In an effort to further generalize those results, I study how the ground state is modified when not all corners are shared between two tetrahedra as in the quasi-1D lattices of a pyrochlore stripe, and how to approach the problem in the case of finite doping. Using a non-Abelian version of the flux inequality, the tetrahedron chain is shown to have degenerate RVB-like ground states. The Bethe ansatz (BA) is adapted to solve the sawtooth chain with spinless or spin-polarized fermions and multiple holons, which is the first example of applying BA to a quasi-1D lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10471v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kondo $s$-$d$ exchange in the CuO$_2$ plane as the long sought interaction determining $T_c$ in cuprates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.18235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.18235v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The well-known Pavarini et al. [Phys. Rev. Lett. 87, 047003 (2001)] correlation between the critical temperature $T_{c,\,\mathrm{max}}$ and the shape of the Fermi contour of the optimally hole-doped cuprates is explained within the framework of the BCS theory with Kondo exchange interaction incorporated as a pairing mechanism. The strong influence of the relative position of the Cu4$s$ level with respect to the Cu3$d_{x^2-y^2}$ level on the critical temperature $T_c$ reveals the importance of the $s$-$d$ hybridization of the conduction band. This hybridization is proportional to the $s$-$d$ exchange scattering amplitude between the conduction electrons -- the mechanism of $d$-wave pairing in the CuO$_2$ plane. In other words the Kondo interaction considered as a pairing mechanism in the CuO$_2$ plane gives a natural explanation of the correlation between the critical temperature and the shape of the Fermi contour. This result suggests that the long-sought pairing mechanism in high-$T_c$ superconducting cuprates has possibly been found and that the Kondo exchange interaction as a property of strongly correlated quantum matter deserves further attention in the physics of layered cuprates. To test the developed theoretical scheme, we explored in detail the recent results of the scanned Josephson modulation microscopy experiment of the modulation of the order parameter due to apex distance super-modulation. Our analysis shows a satisfactory agreement between our theory and the named experiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.18235v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physb.2025.417509</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physica B: Cond. Matt. Vol. 715, 15 Oct 2025, 417509</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Todor M. Mishonov, Nedeltcho I. Zahariev, Hassan Chamati, Albert M. Varonov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anisotropic, multiband, and strong-coupling superconductivity of the Pb0.64Bi0.36 alloy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18315v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents theoretical and experimental studies on the superconductivity of Pb${_{0.64}}$Bi$_{0.36}$ alloy, which is a prototype of strongly coupled superconductors and exhibits one of the strongest coupling under ambient pressure among the materials studied so far. The critical temperature, the specific heat in the superconducting state, and the magnetic critical fields are experimentally determined. Deviations from the single-gap s-wave BCS-like behavior are observed. The electronic structure, phonons and electron-phonon interactions are analyzed in relation to the metallic Pb, explaining why the Pb-Bi alloy exhibits such a large value of the electron-phonon coupling parameter $\lambda \simeq 2$. Superconductivity is studied using the isotropic Eliashberg formalism as well as the anisotropic density functional theory for superconductors. We find that while Pb is a two-gap superconductor with well-defined separate superconducting gaps, in the Pb-Bi alloy an overlapped three-gap-like structure is formed with a strong anisotropy. Furthermore, the chemical disorder, inherent to this alloy, leads to strong electron scattering, which is found to reduce the critical temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18315v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.214510</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 214510 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sylwia Gutowska, Karolina G\'ornicka, Pawe{\l} W\'ojcik, Tomasz Klimczuk, Bartlomiej Wiendlocha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Volume dependence of microwave induced excess quasiparticles in superconducting resonators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07443v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The presence of quasiparticles typically degrades the performance of superconducting microwave circuits. The readout signal can generate non-equilibrium quasiparticles, which lead to excess microwave loss and decoherence. To understand this effect quantitatively, we measure quasiparticle fluctuations and extract the quasiparticle density across different temperatures, readout powers, and resonator volumes. We find that microwave power generates a higher quasiparticle density as the active resonator volume is reduced and show that this effect sets a sensitivity limit on kinetic inductance detectors. We compare our results with theoretical models of direct microwave photon absorption by quasiparticles and conclude that an unknown, indirect mechanism plays a dominant role in quasiparticle generation. These results provide a route to mitigate quasiparticle generation due to readout power in superconducting devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07443v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steven A. H. de Rooij, Jochem J. A. Baselmans, Juan Bueno, Vignesh Murugesan, David J. Thoen, Pieter J. de Visser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Dipole Trapping Potential between Infinite Superconducting Plates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.18852v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We derive the exact analytic form of the potential experienced by a magnetic dipole trapped between two infinite parallel superconducting plates using the method of image dipoles, providing a benchmark for numerical methods and a foundation for studying the stability and dynamics of magnetically levitated systems in precision measurements and fundamental physics experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.18852v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francis J. Headley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced superconductivity via layer differentiation in trilayer Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.06614v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Motivated by the highest superconducting transition temperature ($T_c$) in multilayer cuprates,we investigated the trilayer Hubbard model by adopting the large-scale dynamical cluster quantum Monte Carlo simulations. Focusing on the systems with hole dopings within the two outer layers (OL) higher than the inner layer (IL), which is believed to be relevant to the realistic multilayer cuprates, our exploration discovered that the IL and OL manifest strong differentiation in a wide range of hole doping combinations. Specifically, the OLs remain metallic while the IL shows a distinct transition from the pseudogap to superconducting state. More importantly, the highest $T_c$ of the composite trilayer system can be largely enhanced compared to the single layer model and the imbalanced hole dopings between IL and OL are generically beneficial for global SC. We further provide strong numerical evidence on the possibility of $d$-wave superconductivity solely hosted in the IL. Our investigation provides new insight into the origin of highest $T_c$ in multilayer cuprates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.06614v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xun Liu, Mi Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounds on $T_c$ in the Eliashberg theory of Superconductivity. II: Dispersive phonons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.00532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.00532v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The standard Eliashberg theory of superconductivity is studied, in which the effective electron-electron interactions are mediated by generally dispersive phonons, with Eliashberg spectral function $\alpha^2 F(\omega)\geq 0$ that is $\propto\omega^2$ for small $\omega&gt;0$ and vanishes for large $\omega$. The Eliashberg function also defines the electron-phonon coupling strength $\lambda:= 2 \int_0^\infty\frac{\alpha^2 F(\omega)}{\omega}d\omega$. Setting $\frac{2\alpha^2 F(\omega)}{\omega}d\omega =: \lambda P(d\omega)$, formally defining a probability measure $P(d\omega)$ with compact support, and assuming as usual that the phase transition between normal and superconductivity coincides with the linear stability boundary $\mathscr{S}_{\!c}$ of the normal region against perturbations toward the superconducting region, it is shown that $\mathscr{S}_{\!c}$ is a graph of a function $\Lambda(P,T)$ that is determined by a variational principle: if $(\lambda,P,T)\in\mathscr{S}_{\!c}$, then $\lambda = 1/\mathfrak{k}(P,T)$, where $\mathfrak{k}(P,T)&gt;0$ is the largest eigenvalue of a compact self-adjoint operator $\mathfrak{K}(P,T)$ on $\ell^2$ sequences constructed in the paper. Given $P$, sufficient conditions on $T$ are stated under which the map $T\mapsto \lambda = \Lambda(P,T)$ is invertible. For sufficiently large $\lambda$ this yields: (i) the existence of a critical temperature $T_c$ as function of $\lambda$ and $P$; (ii) a sequence of lower bounds on $T_c(\lambda,P)$ that converges to $T_c(\lambda,P)$. Also obtained is an upper bound on $T_c(\lambda,P)$. It agrees with the asymptotic form $T_c(\lambda,P) \sim C \sqrt{\langle \omega^2\rangle} \sqrt{\lambda}$ valid for $\lambda\sim\infty$, given $P$, though with a constant $C$ that is a factor $\approx 2.034$ larger than the sharp constant. Here, $\langle\omega^2\rangle := \int_0^\infty \omega^2 P(d\omega)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.00532v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10955-025-03468-z</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Statist. Phys. vol.92, art.94, 32.pp (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Michael K. -H. Kiessling, Boris L. Altshuler, Emil A. Yuzbashyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-dimensional spectroscopy of bosonic collective excitations in disordered many-body systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16856v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a novel theoretical approach for computing and analyzing two-dimensional spectroscopy of bosonic collective excitations in disordered many-body systems. Specifically, we employ the Keldysh formalism to derive, within a non-pertubative treatment of disorder effects, the third-order nonlinear response and obtain two-dimensional spectroscopy maps. In the weak nonlinear regime of our formalism, we demonstrate the ability of the echo peak to distinguish between elastic and inelastic scattering processes, in perfect agreement with the intuition developed in isolated two-level systems. Furthermore, we discuss unique many-body effects on the echo peak signature arising from interaction induced quantum fluctuations. In particular, we show that these quantum fluctuations induce a finite nonrephasable broadening and examine how the echo peak is influenced by the attractive or repulsive nature of the collective excitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16856v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex G\'omez Salvador, Ivan Morera, Marios H. Michael, Pavel E. Dolgirev, Danica Pavicevic, Albert Liu, Andrea Cavalleri, Eugene Demler</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
