<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.supr-con updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con</link>
    <description>cond-mat.supr-con updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 04:04:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Raman fingerprint of high-temperature superconductivity in compressed hydrides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10784v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The discovery of high-temperature superconductivity in hydrogen-rich compounds under extreme pressures has prompted great excitement, intense research, but also debate over the past decade. Electrical transport has been the primary diagnostic tool for identifying superconductivity in these systems, whereas complementary probes, including magnetic, spectroscopic, tunnelling and ultrafast methods, remain mostly qualitative due to experimental constraints and sample heterogeneity. Recent concerns over their reliability have fuelled controversy, leading to scepticism and pointing out the need for alternative, quantitative approaches. In this study, we acquired unprecedented high-quality Raman spectra of hexagonal LaH10 at approximately 145 GPa and low temperatures, in conjunction with electrical transport measurements. Upon cooling, we observe a drop of resistivity and simultaneous remarkable variations of phonon frequencies and linewidths. These effects are interpreted and perfectly reproduced by the Migdal-Eliashberg theory, providing a definitive proof of phonon-mediated superconductivity and enabling a quantitative determination of the superconducting energy gap. Our results establish Raman spectroscopy as a robust, contact-free probe with micrometric resolution for studying high temperature superconductivity, opening a powerful route to its discovery and characterization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10784v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philip Dalladay-Simpson, Guglielmo Marchese, Zi-Yu Cao, Paolo Barone, Lara Benfatto, Gaston Garbarino, Francesco Mauri, Federico Aiace Gorelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical Properties of Superconducting K$_{0.8}$Fe$_{1.7}$(Se$_{0.73}$S$_{0.27}$)$_2$ Single Crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11123</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11123v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The optical properties of the superconducting K$_{0.8}$Fe$_{1.7}$(Se$_{0.73}$S$_{0.27}$)$_2$ single crystals with a critical temperature $T_c\approx 26$ K have been measured in the {\it ab} plane in a wide frequency range using both infrared Fourier-transform spectroscopy and spectroscopic ellipsometry at temperatures of 4--300 K. The normal-state reflectance of K$_{0.8}$Fe$_{1.7}$(Se$_{0.73}$S$_{0.27}$)$_2$ is analyzed using a Drude-Lorentz model with one Drude component. The temperature dependences of the plasma frequency, optical conductivity, scattering rate, and dc resistivity of the Drude contribution in the normal state are presented. In the superconducting state, we observe a signature of the superconducting gap opening at $2\Delta $(5~K) = 11.8~meV. An abrupt decrease in the low-frequency dielectric permittivity $\varepsilon _1(\omega )$ at $T &lt; T_c$ also evidences the formation of the superconducting condensate. The superconducting plasma frequency $\omega _{pl,s} = (213\pm 5)$~cm$^{-1}$ and the magnetic penetration depth $\lambda =(7.5\pm 0.2)$~$\mu $m at $T=5$~K are determined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11123v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10948-025-07078-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Superconductivity and Novel Magnetism 38, 236 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Muratov (P.N. Lebedev Physical Institute of RAS, Moscow, Russia), Yevgeny Rakhmanov (P.N. Lebedev Physical Institute of RAS, Moscow, Russia, Lomonosov Moscow State University, Department of Chemistry, Moscow, Russia), Andrei Shilov (P.N. Lebedev Physical Institute of RAS, Moscow, Russia), Igor Morozov (Lomonosov Moscow State University, Department of Chemistry, Moscow, Russia), Yurii Aleshchenko (P.N. Lebedev Physical Institute of RAS, Moscow, Russia)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Theory of Helium 4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11200v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we attempt to construct the topological theory of superfluid helium $4$ in the framework of the (rigid) $U(1)$ model in which the initial $U(1)$ group is destroyed with appearance of (topologically nontrivial) domains separated by domain walls treated as step voltages between domains (e.g. with neighboring topological numbers). This can explain the superfluid properties in a helium $4$ specimen as well as the appearance of topologically nontrivial vortices therein.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11200v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonid Lantsman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple correlation lengths and type-1.5 superconductivity in $U(1)$ superconductors due to hidden competition between irreducible representations of nonlocal pairing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11263</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11263v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A fundamental characteristic of a superconducting state is the coherence length $\xi$. Multicomponent superconductors, particularly ones breaking multiple symmetries, are characterized by multiple coherence lengths. Here we show that even, nominally $single$-component superconductors under certain conditions are characterized by multiple coherence lengths. We consider nearest-neighbor pairing interactions on a square lattice that leads to $s$-wave and $d$-wave representations of link superconducting order parameter. We show that even if the subdominant order parameter is completely suppressed in the ground state, it results in multiple correlation lengths with nontrivial hierarchy, resulting in important physical consequences in inhomogeneous solutions. Under certain conditions, this leads to type-1.5 superconductivity, where magnetic field penetration length falls between two coherence lengths, leading to vortex clustering in an external magnetic field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11263v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Talkachov, Paul Leask, Egor Babaev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpretable descriptors enable prediction of hydrogen-based superconductors at moderate pressures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11284v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Room temperature superconductivity remains elusive, and hydrogen-base compounds despite remarkable transition temperatures(Tc) typically require extreme pressures that hinder application. To accelerate discovery under moderate pressures, an interpretable framework based on symbolic regression is developed to predict Tc in hydrogen-based superconductors. A key descriptor is an integrated density of states (IDOS) within 1 eV of the Fermi level (EF), which exhibits greater robustness than conventional single-point DOS features. The resulting analytic model links electronic-structure characteristics to superconducting performance, achieves high accuracy (RMSEtrain = 20.15 K), and generalizes well to external datasets. By relying solely on electronic structure calculations, the approach greatly accelerates materials screening. Guided by this model, four hydrogen-based candidates are identified and validated via calculation: Na2GaCuH6 with Tc =42.04 K at ambient pressure (exceeding MgB2), and NaCaH12, NaSrH12, and KSrH12 with Tc up to 162.35 K, 86.32 K, and 55.13 K at 100 GPa, 25 GPa, and 25 GPa, respectively. Beyond rapid screening, the interpretable form clarifies how hydrogen-projected electronic weight near EF and related features govern Tc in hydrides, offering a mechanism-aware route to stabilize high-Tc phases at reduced pressures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11284v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiawei Chen, Junhao Peng, Yanwei Liang, Renhai Wang, Huafeng Dong, Wei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kapitza-Dirac interference of Higgs waves in superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10954v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a novel framework for controlling Higgs mode and vortex dynamics in superconductors using structured light. We propose a phenomenon analog of the Kapitza-Dirac effect in superconductors, where Higgs waves scatter off light-induced vortex lattices, generating interference patterns akin to matter wave diffraction. We also find that the vortices enable the linear coupling of Higgs mode to the electromagnetic field. This interplay between light-engineered Higgs excitations and emergent vortex textures opens a pathway to probe nonequilibrium superconductivity with unprecedented spatial and temporal resolution. Our results bridge quantum optics and condensed matter physics, offering new examples of quantum printing where one uses structured light to manipulate the collective modes in correlated quantum fluids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10954v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daemo Kang, Tien-Tien Yeh, Takahiro Morimoto, Alexander V. Balatsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of spin-orbit coupling and Zeeman interaction on the subharmonic gap structure due to multiple Andreev reflections in nanoscopic Josephson junctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11277v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multiple Andreev reflections in voltage-biased Josephson junctions give rise to the subharmonic gap structure in the conductance, which is widely used to characterize transport properties and estimate the induced gap in the junctions. Here we theoretically investigate the evolution of the subharmonic gap structure in spinful Josephson junctions. Spin mixing introduced by the spin-orbit coupling opens avoided crossings in the dispersion relation of the leads, which, as we demonstrate, subsequently results in pronounced multiple Andreev reflection features in the conductance traces. We analyze how these features evolve under an external magnetic field and explain that their visibility in conductance is governed by the spin polarization of the bands.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11277v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Kuiri, J. H. Correa, A. Biborski, M. P. Nowak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherent-state path integrals in quantum thermodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11547v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In these notes, we elucidate some subtle aspects of coherent-state path integrals, focusing on their application to the equilibrium thermodynamics of quantum many-particle systems. These subtleties emerge when evaluating path integrals in the continuum, either in imaginary time or in Matsubara-frequency space. Our central message is that, when handled with due care, the path integral yields results identical to those obtained from the canonical Hamiltonian approach. We illustrate this through a pedagogical treatment of several paradigmatic systems: the bosonic and fermionic harmonic oscillators, the single-site Bose-Hubbard and Hubbard models, the weakly-interacting Bose gas with contact and finite-range interactions, and the BCS superconductor with contact and finite-range interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11547v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Salasnich, Cesare Vianello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ubiquitous missing first Shapiro step in Al-InSb nanosheet Josephson junctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07370v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The absence of odd-order Shapiro steps is a predicted signature of topological superconductors. Experimentally, the missing first-order Shapiro step has been reported in both putative topological superconducting systems and topologically trivial superconductor-semiconductor Josephson junctions. Here, we revisit this phenomenon in topologically trivial Al-InSb nanosheet Josephson junctions under microwave irradiation. The missing first Shapiro step coincides with a sharp voltage jump during superconducting switching, yet reappears when the jump is lowered and softened by increasing microwave power, temperature, or magnetic field. It also reappears at higher microwave frequencies, consistent with qualitative results from an RSJ model incorporating the sharp jump. These observations indicate that the absence of the first Shapiro step, associated with the sharp switching jump, simply results from their location within the measurement blind region. This work identifies a common but overlooked mechanism underlying the missing first Shapiro step, offering new insights into fractional Josephson effect experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07370v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/3tvf-5v29</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Xingjun Wu, Haitian Su, Chuanchang Zeng, Ji-Yin Wang, Shili Yan, Dong Pan, Jianhua Zhao, Po Zhang, H. Q. Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inherent momentum-dependent gap structure of altermagnetic superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03247</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03247v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Altermagnetic metals break time-reversal symmetry and feature spin-split Fermi surfaces generated by compensated N\'eel-ordered collinear magnetic moments. Being metallic, such altermagnets may undergo a further instability at low temperatures to a superconducting state, and it is an interesting open question what are the salient features of such altermagnetic superconductors? We address this question on the basis of realistic microscopic models that capture the altermagnetic sublattice degrees of freedom. We find that the sublattice structure can strongly affect the superconducting gap structure in altermagnetic superconductors. In particular, it imposes nodes in the gap on the Brillouin zone edges for superconductors stabilized by momentum-independent bare attraction channels. We contrast this to the case of superconductivity generated by extended range interactions where pairing is allowed on the Brillouin zone edges and both spin-singlet and equal-spin-pairing triplet states can be stabilized. Equal-spin-pairing triplet superconductivity is generically favored in the limit of large altermagnetic spin-splitting of the bands compared to the superconducting gap scale, and features characteristic non-unitary properties due to the altermagnetic order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03247v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian L. H. Rasmussen, Jannik Gondolf, Mats Barkman, Merc\`e Roig, Daniel F. Agterberg, Andreas Kreisel, Brian M. Andersen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital-Selective Band Structure Evolution in BaFe$_{2-x}$M$_x$As$_2$ (M = Cr, Co, Cu, Ru and Mn) Probed by Polarization-Dependent ARPES</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19190v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a systematic study of the evolution of the band structure in the Fe-based superconductor family BaFe$_{2-x}$M$_x$As$_2$ (M = Cr, Co, Cu, Ru and Mn) using polarization-dependent angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES). Low-substituted samples, with comparable spin-density wave transition temperatures ($T_\text{SDW}$), were chosen to facilitate controlled comparisons. The sizes of the central hole pockets ($\alpha$, $\beta$, and $\gamma$) remain largely unchanged across different substitutions, showing no clear correlation with either $T_\text{SDW}$ or the As height relative to the Fe planes. However, subtle trends are observed: a modest increase in the size of the $\eta_\text{X}$ electron pocket correlates with the suppression of $T_\text{SDW}$. Furthermore, the contraction of the $\eta_\text{X}$ pocket appears to be linked to an increase in the As height relative to the Fe planes. Our results suggest that the suppression of $T_\text{SDW}$ is primarily driven by changes in the Fe-As bond length, with the effect being more pronounced in electronic states with planar character. These findings provide insight into the electronic structure of BaFe$_{2-x}$M$_x$As$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19190v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. R. Pakuszewski, M. R. Cantarino, I. Romanenko, A. P. Machado, M. M. Piva, G. S. Freitas, H. B. Pizzi, F. A. Garcia, P. G. Pagliuso, C. Adriano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase Separation in Kitaev Chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20312</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20312v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Kitaev chain is a one-dimensional spinless fermion model that has $p$-wave superconducting (SC) states and Majorana zero modes at the edge. Usually this model is analyzed by taking only SC order parameter (OP) into account, but the situation significantly changes when OPs other than the SCOP are included. It turns out that the SC state in the latter case is prone to phase separation for moderate to strong attractiive interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20312v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuhiro Kuboki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-resolution magnetostriction measurements of the Pauli-limited superconductor Sr2RuO4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06938v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We performed high-resolution magnetostriction measurements on the Pauli-limited superconductor Sr$_2$RuO$_4$ using high-quality single crystals. A first-order superconducting transition, accompanied by pronounced hysteresis, was observed under in-plane magnetic fields, where the relative length change of the sample, $\Delta L/L$, was on the order of $10^{-8}$. To ensure the reliability of the measurements, particular attention was paid to minimizing the influence of magnetic torque, which can significantly affect data under in-plane field configurations, via field-angle-resolved magnetostriction. Within the hysteresis regime, slightly below the Pauli-limited upper critical field, a hump-like anomaly in the magnetostriction coefficient was identified. Furthermore, a characteristic double-peak structure in the field-angle derivative of the magnetostriction provides additional support for this anomaly. Although these findings may reflect a lattice response associated with the emergence of the Fulde-Ferrell-Larkin-Ovchinnikov (FFLO) phase in Sr$_2$RuO$_4$, the possibility of a broadened first-order transition cannot be excluded. Notably, this magnetostriction anomaly qualitatively deviates from the FFLO phase boundary suggested by previous NMR measurements, highlighting the necessity for further experimental and theoretical investigations to elucidate the nature of the FFLO state in this material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06938v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunichiro Kittaka, Yohei Kono, Toshiro Sakakibara, Naoki Kikugawa, Shinya Uji, Dmitry A. Sokolov, Kazushige Machida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The True Parent Phase of K1.9Fe4.2Se5: A Stripe-type Orthorhombic Phase Requiring a Superconducting Distortion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10443v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The origin of the four-fold Tc amplification in A_xFe_{2-y}Se_2 (&gt;30 K) compared to FeSe (8 K) remains a central puzzle, complicated by a debate over the true superconducting (SC) parent phase--the I4/m (245) insulating matrix or a supposed I4/mmm metallic phase. Here, we resolve this ambiguity by identifying a novel "stripe-type orthorhombic phase" as the true parent phase of the high-Tc state, whose diffraction signature is the d2 peaks. Through decisive experiments, we demonstrate that this d2 parent phase is not intrinsically superconducting. Instead, superconductivity emerges only after this stripe phase undergoes a subsequent structural distortion, the definitive signature of which is the asymmetric broadening of the d1 main peaks. Our findings establish that the d2 peaks signal the formation of the parent phase, while the broadening of d1 peaks signals the transition into the superconducting state. This discovery of a two-step transition--formation of a stripe parent phase, followed by a superconducting distortion--provides a new mechanism for Tc amplification via controlled heterogeneity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10443v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chih-Han Wang, Jie-Yu Yang, Wu Phillip M, Gwo-Tzong Huang, Ming-Jye Wang, Maw-Kuen Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chirality-selective proximity effect between chiral $p$-wave superconductors and quantum Hall insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00994</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00994v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Heterostructures of superconductors and quantum-Hall insulators are promising platforms of topological quantum computation. However, these two systems are incompatible in some aspects such as a strong magnetic field, the Meissner effect, and chirality. In this work, we address the condition that the superconducting proximity effect works in the bulk of quantum Hall states, and identify an essential role played by the vortex lattice regardless of pairing symmetry. We extend this finding to a heterostructure of a chiral $p$-wave superconductor in the mixed state and an integer quantum Hall insulator. The proximity effect works selectively in the lowest Landau level depending on relative chiralities. If the chiralities align, a topological phase transition to a topological superconductor occurs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00994v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/qxt1-ncfn</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 094520 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ryota Nakai, Koji Kudo, Hiroki Isobe, Kentaro Nomura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A superinductor in a deep sub-micron integrated circuit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13202v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Superinductors are circuit elements characterised by an intrinsic impedance in excess of the superconducting resistance quantum ($R_\text{Q}\approx6.45~$k$\Omega$), with applications from metrology and sensing to quantum computing. However, they are typically obtained using exotic materials with high density inductance such as Josephson junctions, superconducting nanowires or twisted two-dimensional materials. Here, we present a superinductor realised within a silicon integrated circuit (IC), exploiting the high kinetic inductance ($\sim 1$~nH/$\square$) of TiN thin films native to the manufacturing process (22-nm FDSOI). By interfacing the superinductor to a silicon quantum dot formed within the same IC, we demonstrate a radio-frequency single-electron transistor (rfSET), the most widely used sensor in semiconductor-based quantum computers. The integrated nature of the rfSET reduces its parasitics which, together with the high impedance, yields a sensitivity improvement of more than two orders of magnitude over the state-of-the-art, combined with a 10,000-fold area reduction. Beyond providing the basis for dense arrays of integrated and high-performance qubit sensors, the realization of high-kinetic-inductance superconducting devices integrated within modern silicon ICs opens many opportunities, including kinetic-inductance detector arrays for astronomy and the study of metamaterials and quantum simulators based on 1D and 2D resonator arrays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13202v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. H. Swift, F. Olivieri, G. Aizpurua-Iraola, J. Kirkman, G. M. Noah, M. de Kruijf, F. E. von Horstig, A. Gomez-Saiz, J. J. L. Morton, M. F. Gonzalez-Zalba</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
