<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.supr-con updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con</link>
    <description>cond-mat.supr-con updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 01:47:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Development of microwave surface elastoresistivity measurement technique under tunable strain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10626v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: By integrating a dielectric microwave resonator with a piezoelectric-based strain device, we develop an in situ strain-tunable microwave spectroscopy technique that enables contactless measurements of superconducting properties under strain. In the slightly overdoped iron-based superconductor BaFe$_2$(As$_{1-x}$P$_x$)$_2$, we successfully observe a systematic strain dependence of the superconducting transition, manifested as changes in the quality factor and resonance frequency shifts. Both compressive and tensile anisotropic lattice distortions along the [110]${_{\rm T}}$ direction suppress superconductivity, consistent with standard transport measurements, highlighting the pivotal role of nematic fluctuations in the superconducting mechanism. Our strain-tunable cavity therefore serves as a powerful, contactless probe of fundamental superconducting material properties under strain and may also potentially facilitate the design of hybrid quantum systems with strain-controlled quantum degrees of freedom.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10626v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suguru Hosoi, Kohei Matsuura, Masaaki Shimozawa, Koichi Izawa, Shigeru Kasahara, Takasada Shibauchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconducting quantum oscillations and anomalous negative magnetoresistance in a honeycomb nanopatterned oxide interface superconductor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10912v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The extremely low superfluid density and unprecedented tunability of oxide interface superconductors provide an ideal platform for studying fluctuations in two-dimensional superconductors. In this work, we have fabricated a LaAlO3/KTaO3 interface superconductor patterned with a nanohoneycomb array of insulating islands. Little-Parks-like magnetoresistance oscillations have been observed, which are dictated by the superconducting flux quantum h/2e. Moreover, an anomalous negative magnetoresistance (ANMR) appears under a weak magnetic field, suggesting magnetic-field-enhanced superconductivity. By examining their dependences on temperature, measurement current, and electrical gating, we conclude that both phenomena are associated with superconducting order parameter: The h/2e oscillations provide direct evidence of Cooper pair transport; the ANMR is interpreted as a consequence of multiple connected narrow superconducting paths with strong fluctuations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10912v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevX.15.011006</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review X 15, 011006 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yishuai Wang, Siyuan Hong, Wenze Pan, Yi Zhou, Yanwu Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic transport properties of titanium nitride grown by molecular beam epitaxy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11065</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11065v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study investigates the molecular beam epitaxial (MBE) growth of titanium nitride (TiN) thin films, achieving a high residual resistivity ratio (RRR) of 15.8. We observed a strong correlation between growth temperature and crystalline quality, as reflected in both RRR values and lattice parameter variations. Characterization of superconductivity yielded a Ginzburg-Landau coherence length of 60.4 $\pm$ 0.6 nm, significantly higher than typical sputtered films, suggesting improved superconducting coherence. First-principles calculations, in conjunction with experimental data, provided detailed insights into the electronic structure and transport properties of the TiN films. Temperature-dependent Hall coefficient measurements further revealed the influence of anisotropic scattering mechanisms. These findings establish a promising route for the development of nitride-based superconducting materials for advanced quantum computing technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11065v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kosuke Takiguchi, Yoshiharu Krockenberger, Tom Ichibha, Kenta Hongo, Ryo Maezono, Yoshitaka Taniyasu, Hideki Yamamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intertwined fluctuations and isotope effects in the Hubbard-Holstein model on the square lattice from functional renormalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10863</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10863v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Electron-electron and electron-phonon interactions are responsible for the formation of spin, charge, and superconducting correlations in layered quantum materials. A paradigmatic model for such materials that captures both kinds of interactions is the two-dimensional Hubbard-Holstein model with a dispersionless Einstein phonon. In this work, we provide a detailed analysis of the magnetic, density, and superconducting fluctuations at and away from half-filling. To that end, we employ the functional renormalization group using the recently introduced extension of the single-boson exchange formulation. More precisely, we go beyond previous approaches to the model by resolving the full frequency dependence of the two-particle vertex and taking into account the feedback from the electronic self-energy. We perform broad parameter scans in the space of Hubbard repulsion, electron-phonon coupling strength, and phonon frequency to explore the leading magnetic, density, and superconducting susceptibilities from the adiabatic to the anti-adiabatic regime. Our numerical data reveal that self-energy effects lead to an enhancement of the $d$-wave superconducting susceptibility towards larger phonon frequencies, in contrast to earlier isotope-effect studies. At small phonon frequencies, large density contributions to the $s$-wave superconducting susceptibility change sign and eventually lead to a reduction of $s$-wave superconductivity with increasing electron-phonon coupling, signaling the breakdown of Migdal-Eliashberg theory. We analyze our findings systematically, employing detailed diagnostics of the intertwined fluctuations and pinning down the various positive and negative isotope effects of the physical susceptibilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10863v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aiman Al-Eryani, Sabine Andergassen, Michael M. Scherer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring coherent dynamics of a superconducting qubit in an open waveguide</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11028v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We measured the relaxation and decoherence rates of a superconducting transmon qubit in a resonator-free setting. In our experiments, the qubit is coupled to an open coplanar waveguide such that the transmission of microwaves through this line depends on the qubit's state. To determine the occupation of the first excited qubit energy level, we introduced a two-pulse technique. The first applied pulse, at a frequency close to the eigenfrequency of the qubit, serves to excite the qubit. A second pulse is then used for probing the transition between the first and second excited energy levels. Utilizing this measurement technique allowed for the reconstruction of the relaxation dynamics and Rabi oscillations. Furthermore, we demonstrate the consistency between the extracted parameters and the corresponding estimations from frequency-domain measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11028v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aidar Sultanov, Evgeniya Mutsenik, Matthias Schmelz, Leonie Kaczmarek, Gregor Oelsner, Uwe H\"ubner, Ronny Stolz, Evgeni Il'ichev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reciprocal and nonreciprocal paraconductivity in bilayer multiphase superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14350v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Thin-film multiphase superconductors are attracting much attention, and it is important to propose how to detect them in experiments. In this work, we study the reciprocal and nonreciprocal paraconductivity of a bilayer model with staggered Rashba-type spin-orbit coupling with and without the potential gradient and Zeeman field. This model shows the Bardeen-Cooper-Schrieffer phase, the pair-density-wave phase, and the Fulde-Ferrell-Larkin-Ovchinnikov (FFLO) phase, and we focus on how their properties are encoded to the charge transport. We show that the reciprocal paraconductivity has a peak associated with the phase transitions between different superconducting states due to the degeneracy of the transition temperatures as well as the paramagnetic depairing effect. We also show that the FFLO superconducting state shows a sizable nonreciprocal paraconductivity once the degeneracy of Cooper pairs is lifted by applying the potential gradient. Observation of the peaked reciprocal and nonreciprocal paraconductivity can be used as a probe of multiphase superconductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14350v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.064501</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 064501 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tsugumi Matsumoto, Youichi Yanase, Akito Daido</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Berry Phase Enforced Spinor Pairing Order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09579v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a class of topological pairing orders characterized by a half-integer pair monopole charge, leading to Berry phase enforced half-integer partial wave symmetry. This exotic spinor order emerges from pairing between Fermi surfaces with Chern numbers differing by an odd integer. Using tight-binding models, we demonstrate spinor superconducting orders with monopole charges $\pm 1/2$, featuring a single gap node and nontrivial surface states. Additionally, the superfluid velocity follows a fractionalized Mermin-Ho relation in spatially inhomogeneous pairing orders. The concept extends to spinor density waves and excitons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09579v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi Li, Grayson R. Frazier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chemical enhancement of superconductivity in LaRu3Si2 with mode-selective coupling between kagome phonons and flat bands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22477</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.22477v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In kagome metals, flat electronic bands induced by frustrated hopping are a platform for strong electron correlations. In particular, a selective coupling of flat band states to certain kagome phonon modes is proposed as a universal origin of superconductivity in this material class. Here, we investigate the superconductivity in the kagome system LaRu$_3$(Si$_{1-x}$Ge$_x$)$_2$ by chemical pressure tuning while preserving the Ru-$4d$ states that constitute the kagome flat bands. We observe a sizable enhancement in the density of states up to $x = 0.07$, as determined by the specific heat, with a concomitant increase in the superconducting transition temperature $T_\mathrm{c}$. Ge-dopants induce a uniaxial lattice expansion along the $c$-axis. Our first-principles calculations suggest that this mitigates the detrimental effect of hybridization between kagome layers and reduces the dispersion of the Ru-$4d_{x^2-y^2}$ flat band. The calculated chemical potential moves closer to the maximum in the energy-dependent density of states. Our result is consistent with a theoretical prediction of tunable flat band superconductivity in LaRu$_3$Si$_2$ by mode-selective coupling between specific kagome phonons and the Ru-$d_{x^2-y^2}$ orbitals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.22477v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryo Misawa, Markus Kriener, Rinsuke Yamada, Ryota Nakano, Milena Jovanovic, Leslie M. Schoop, Max Hirschberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Superconductivity at a Corner for the Linear BCS Equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.07115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.07115v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the critical temperature for superconductivity, defined via the linear BCS equation. We prove that at weak coupling the critical temperature for a sample confined to a quadrant in two dimensions is strictly larger than the one for a half-space, which in turn is strictly larger than the one for $\mathbb{R}^2$. Furthermore, we prove that the relative difference of the critical temperatures vanishes in the weak coupling limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.07115v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/fms.2024.145</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Barbara Roos, Robert Seiringer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivity and quantized anomalous Hall in rhombohedral graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12584v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Inducing superconducting correlations in chiral edge states is predicted to generate topologically protected zero energy modes with exotic quantum statistics. Experimental efforts to date have focused on engineering interfaces between superconducting materials typically amorphous metals and semiconducting quantum Hall or quantum anomalous Hall (QAH) systems. However, the interfacial disorder inherent in this approach can prevent the formation of isolated topological modes. An appealing alternative is to use low-density flat band materials where the ground state can be tuned between intrinsic superconducting and quantum anomalous Hall states using only the electric field effect. However, quantized transport and superconductivity have not been simultaneously achieved. Here, we show that rhombohedral tetralayer graphene aligned to a hexagonal boron nitride substrate hosts a quantized anomalous Hall state at superlattice filling $\nu=-1$ as well as a superconducting state at $\nu-3.5$ at zero magnetic field. Remarkably, gate voltage can also be used to actuate nonvolatile switching of the chirality in the quantum anomalous Hall state, allowing, in principle, arbitrarily reconfigurable networks of topological edge modes in locally gated devices. Thermodynamic compressibility measurements further reveal a topologically ordered fractional Chern insulator at $\nu=2/3$-also stable at zero magnetic field-enabling proximity coupling between superconductivity and fractionally charged edge modes. Finally, we show that, as in rhombohedral bi- and trilayers, integrating a transition metal dichalcogenide layer to the heterostructure nucleates a new superconducting pocket, while leaving the topology of the $\nu=-1$ quantum anomalous Hall state intact. Our results pave the way for a new generation of hybrid interfaces between superconductors and topological edge states in the low-disorder limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12584v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41586-025-08621-y</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature 639, 342 347 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Youngjoon Choi, Ysun Choi, Marco Valentini, Caitlin L. Patterson, Ludwig F. W. Holleis, Owen I. Sheekey, Hari Stoyanov, Xiang Cheng, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Andrea F. Young</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced nonlinear Hall effect by Cooper pairs near superconductor criticality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06710v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Unlike the linear Hall effect that requires broken time-reversal symmetry, the nonlinear Hall effect may occur in time-reversal symmetric systems as long as there exists a non-zero Berry curvature dipole in the absence of inversion symmetry. Interestingly, the presence of time-reversal symmetry is consistent with and thus allows a direct transition into a superconducting phase. Indeed, superconductivity has been established in various nonlinear Hall materials, such as WTe$_2$ and MoTe$_2$, at sufficiently low temperatures. We find that the nonlinear Hall response should be significantly enhanced near the superconducting criticality, dominated by the Aslamazov-Larkin (AL) contributions augmented by superconducting fluctuations, which we attribute to the Berry curvature dipole and a divergent lifetime $\tau\sim (T-T_c)^{-1}$ of the Cooper pairs, instead of the single electrons. Such a controlled enhancement brings the nonlinear Hall effect into various simple experimental observations and practical applicational potentials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06710v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.155120</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 155120 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zi-Hao Dong, Hui Yang, Yi Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
