<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.supr-con updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con</link>
    <description>cond-mat.supr-con updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 01:37:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Protected Symmetrical Superconducting Qubit Based on Quantum Flux Parametron</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06593v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Conventional Quantum Flux Parametrons (QFPs) have historically been used for storing classical bits in Josephson junction-based computers. In this work, we propose a novel QFP-based topology dubbed "Degenerium" qubit, to process and compute quantum information. Degenerium combines principles from the 0-$\pi$ qubit and flux qubit to create ideally degenerate quantum ground states, while significantly simplifying the 0-$\pi$ qubit structure. The symmetrical design of Degenerium enables easier qubit control and fabrication. We demonstrate that due to the inherent symmetry of Degenerium, our designed qubit is insensitive to fabrication-induced variations in critical current ($I_c$) of the Josephson junctions. Our calculations of depolarization and dephasing rates due to charge, flux, and critical current noise sources result in depolarization and dephasing times of 1.25 s and 90 $\mu$s, respectively. Further parameter tuning and optimization is possible to meet specific application demands.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06593v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kian Rafati Sajedi, Mojtaba Hosseinpour Choubi, Mehdi Fardmanesh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fluxon cotunneling in coupled Josephson junctions: Perturbation theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06720v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the effects of fluxon cotunneling and quantum Coulomb drag in a system of two small Josephson junctions coupled by means of mutual capacitance $C_m$. Depending on the value of $C_m$ we identify three different regimes of strong, intermediate and weak coupling. Focusing our attention on the last two regimes we develop a perturbation theory in the interaction and explicitly derive fluxon cotunneling amplitudes at sufficiently small mutual capacitance values. We demonstrate that the Coulomb drag effect survives at any non-zero $C_m$ and evaluate the non-local voltage response that is in general determined by a trade off between two different cotunneling processes. Our predictions can be straightforwardly generalized to bilinear Josephson chains and directly verified in future experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06720v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew G. Semenov, Alex Latyshev, Andrei D. Zaikin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconducting Dome and Quantum Criticality in Two-Dimensional NbO2 Triangular Lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07241</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07241v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The emergence of superconductivity with strong correlation is one of the most attracted issues in condensed-matter physics, as seen in various unconventional superconductors. Here we show a new strongly correlated superconductor Li1-xNbO2 with rich characteristics such as two-dimensional, geometrically frustrated, and triangular NbO2 lattice and correlated flat-band-like electronic states. We revealed the electronic phase diagram by implementing Li-ion electrochemical cells with LiNbO2 epitaxial films. The Li-ion deintercalation increased the hole-doping level in NbO2 layer, along which a band insulator LiNbO2 underwent to a Fermi-liquid (FL) metal and superconductor associated with non-Fermi liquid (NFL) characters. The evolution of the NFL state coincided with the suppression of the Kondo-singlet formation near the superconducting dome, which linked superconductivity with quantum criticality. The obtained phase diagram involves general aspects of strongly correlated superconductors and bridges the gap between various systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07241v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takuto Soma, Kohei Yoshimatsu, Akira Ohtomo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational Quantum Monte Carlo investigations of the superconducting pairing in La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07341</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07341v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the pairing symmetry in the novel superconductor La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ under pressure by the non-perturbative variational quantum Monte Carlo. Within the bilayer Hubbard model and extended $t-J$ model with two orbitals in the $E_g$ doublet, we find the local strong correlation triggers $s_\pm$-wave Cooper pairing, with sign change of the gap function among the various Fermi pockets, while the $d_{x^2-y^2}$-wave pairing is generically disfavored. This is in agreement with the results from functional renormalization group applied in the weak up to moderate correlation limit. We find the 3d$_{3z^2-r^2}$ orbital plays a leading role in the superconducting pairing. We also demonstrate the finite intra-orbital double occupancy even in the strong correlation limit, shedding light on the itinerant versus local moment picture of the electrons in this material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07341v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi-Qun Liu, Da Wang, Qiang-Hua Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-step phase transitions in Fe(Se,Te)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07807v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the studied crystals of FeSe0.7 Te0.3 , a structural phase transition occurs in two stages. At higher temperatures, the electronic subsystem undergoes a reconstruction, leading to a significant increase in elastoresistance. 77 Se NMR data show an abrupt change in the relaxation rate during this transition. The final transition occurs at a temperature several degrees below and is also accompanied by anomalies in the electronic properties. Thus, in the Fe(Se,Te) series, similarly to the behavior of pure FeSe under pressure, the type of transition changes and intermediate state appear before the structural transition is suppressed. This similarity between the corresponding phase diagrams is explained by the same deformation of the iron coordination environment in Fe(Se,Te) compounds and in FeSe under pressure. Our findings provide new and significant information on the phase diagram of Fe(Se,Te) compounds and in particular suggest the possible existence of a triple point near the quantum critical point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07807v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. A. Chareev, A. A. Gippius, Y. A. Ovchenkov, D. E. Presnov, I. G. Puzanova, A. V. Tkachev, O. S. Volkova, S. V. Zhurenko, A. N. Vasiliev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Manipulating the topological spin of Majoranas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06334</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06334v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The non-Abelian exchange statistics of Majorana zero modes make them interesting for both technological applications and fundamental research. Unlike their non-Abelian counterpart, the Abelian contribution $e^{i \theta}$, where $\theta$ is directly related to the Majorana's topological spin, is often neglected. However, the Abelian exchange phase and hence the topological spin can differ from system to system. For vortices in topological superconductors, the Abelian exchange phase is interpreted as an Aharonov-Casher phase arising from a vortex encircling an $e/4$ charge. In this work, we show how this fractional charge and hence the topological spin can be manipulated, introducing an additional knob for braiding operations in topological quantum computing. To probe this effect, we propose a vortex interference experiment that reveals the effect of this fractional charge through measurable shifts in the critical current.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06334v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stijn R. de Wit, Emre Duman, A. Mert Bozkurt, Alexander Brinkman, Inanc Adagideli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing quantum phase transition in a staggered Bosonic Kitaev chain via layer-resolved localization-delocalization transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07017</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07017v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The bosonic statistics, which allow for macroscopic multi-occupancy of single-particle states, pose significant challenges for analyzing quantum phase transitions in interacting bosonic systems, both analytically and numerically. In this work, we systematically investigate the non-Hermitian Bloch core matrix of a Hermitian staggered bosonic Kitaev chain, formulated within the Nambu framework. We derive explicit analytic conditions for the emergence of exceptional points (EPs) in the $4\times 4$ Bloch core matrix, with each EP marking the onset of complex-conjugate eigenvalue pairs. By mapping the full many-body Hamiltonian onto an effective tight-binding network in Fock-space and introducing layer-resolved inverse participation ratio, we demonstrate that these EPs coincide precisely with sharp localization--delocalization transitions of collective eigenstates. Comprehensive numerical analyses across hopping amplitudes, pairing strengths, and on-site potentials confirm that the EP of effective Hamiltonian universally capture the global many-body phase boundaries. Our results establish an analytically tractable, EP-based criterion for detecting critical behavior in interacting bosonic lattices, with direct relevance to photonic and cold-atom experimental platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07017v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Wang, X. Z. Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermoelectric processes of quantum normal-superconductor interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07426v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Superconducting interfaces have recently been demonstrated to contain a rich variety of effects that give rise to sizable thermoelectric responses and unexpected thermal properties, despite traditionally being considered poor thermoelectrics due to their intrinsic electron-hole symmetry. We review different mechanisms driving this response in hybrid normal-superconducting junctions, depending on the dimensionality of the mesoscopic interface. In addition to discussing heat to power conversion, cooling and heat transport, special emphasis is put on physical properties of hybrid devices that can be revealed by the thermoelectric effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07426v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Arrachea, A. Braggio, P. Burset, E. J. H. Lee, A. Levy Yeyati, R. S\'anchez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New experimental evidence for Podkletnov effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.03332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.03332v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the works of E. Podkletnov et al. (for example [Physica C: Superconductivity, 1992, Vol. 203, p. 441]), a unique experiment is described in which a significant reduction in the weight of various test bodies was observed when placed above a rotating disk made of the superconductor YBa2Cu3O6+delta (YBCO); the disk was in the superconducting state (at 20-70 K) and was subjected to an alternating (50 Hz-100 MHz) magnetic field. Numerous attempts to replicate this experiment in other laboratories have been unsuccessful; however, a broad discussion has been initiated regarding the possible nature of the "Podkletnov effect" - the weight loss of objects located above the superconductor. In the present experimental work, results similar to the Podkletnov effect have been obtained, which, however, occur at room temperature. During our experiments, gas-tight containers with the crystal hydrate K2CO3X1.5H2O and dispersed YBCO exhibited a sharp loss of part of their weight during and after 0.5 hours of exposure to a magnetic field with a frequency of 50 MHz. Changes in the weight of various test bodies located in close proximity to the containers were recorded. It was found that these weight changes correlate with the external surface area of the bodies and do not depend on their chemical nature. A dependence of the magnitude of weight changes on the oxygen content in YBCO was obtained, which shows a significant dip in the region where superstructural orderings of the oxygen sublattice exist in the basal plane. This dip coincides in shape with the well-known dip in the dependence of Tc on delta (the "60-K plateau"). The possible connection between these two extraordinary phenomena coexisting in YBCO compounds - inexplicable weight changes and high-temperature superconductivity - is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.03332v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. V. Fetisov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theoretical study on the possibility of high $T_c$ s$\pm$-wave superconductivity in the heavily hole-doped infinite layer nickelates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21461v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We theoretically propose a possibility of realizing high $T_c$ superconductivity having $s\pm$-wave symmetry in the heavily hole-doped infinite layer nickelates La$_{1-x}$Sr$_x$NiO$_2$. We consider situations where the original $P4/mmm$ symmetry of LaNiO$_2$ is maintained even for a significant amount of Sr substitution by growing thin films on substrates having tetragonal symmetry. Considering such cases is indeed justified by our phonon calculations. For electron configurations somewhat close to $d^8$, the interaction between the $d_{x^2-y^2}$ band and the other $3d$ bands that lie just below the Fermi level results in an enhancement of superconductivity where the sign of the gap function is reversed between the former and the latter bands. The strong enhancement of superconductivity can be attributed to the large energy level offset between $d_{x^2-y^2}$ and other orbitals due to the absence of the apical oxygens, as has been pointed out in previous studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21461v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hirofumi Sakakibara, Ryota Mizuno, Masayuki Ochi, Hidetomo Usui, Kazuhiko Kuroki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Out-of-plane bond-order phase, superconductivity, and their competition in the $t$-$J_\parallel$-$J_\perp$ model: Possible implications for bilayer nickelates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00269v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Almost four decades of intense research have been invested to study the physics of high-T$_c$ cuprate superconductors. The recent discovery of high-T$_c$ superconductivity in pressurized bilayer nickelates and its potential similarities with cuprate superconductors may open a new window to understand this long-standing problem. We have studied the proposed bilayer $t$-$J_\parallel$-$J_\perp$ model [where $J_\parallel$ ($J_\perp$) is the in-plane (out-of-plane) magnetic exchange] in a large-$N$ approach on the basis of the path integral representation for Hubbard operators, which allows to obtain results at mean-field and beyond mean-field level. We find that $J_\perp$ is a candidate for triggering high superconducting $T_c$ values at quarter filling (hole doping $\delta=0.5$) of the $d_{x^2-y^2}$ orbitals. Beyond mean-field level, we find a new phase, an out-of-plane bond-order phase (z-BOP), triggered also by $J_\perp$. z-BOP develops below a critical temperature which decreases with increasing doping and vanishes at a quantum critical point below quarter filling. The occurrence of this phase and its competition with superconductivity leads to a superconducting dome-shaped behavior as a function of doping and as a function of $J_\perp$. Qualitative comparisons with the physics of cuprates and the recent literature on the new pressurized nickelates are given along the paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00269v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.144514</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 144514 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mat\'ias Bejas, Xianxin Wu, Debmalya Chakraborty, Andreas P. Schnyder, Andr\'es Greco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Josephson Field Effect Transistors with InAs on Insulator and High Permittivity Gate Dielectrics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16221</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16221v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: InAs on Insulator (InAsOI) has been recently demonstrated as a promising platform to develop hybrid semiconducting-superconducting Josephson Junctions (JJs) and Josephson Field Effect Transistors (JoFETs). The InAsOI consists of an InAs epilayer grown onto a cryogenic-electrically-insulating InAlAs metamorphic buffer, which allows the electrical decoupling of surface-exposed adjacent devices together with a high critical current density integration. The miniaturization of Si microchips has progressed significantly due to the integration of high permittivity (high-k) gate insulators, allowing an increased gate coupling with the transistor channel with consequent reduced gate operating voltages and leakages. As well as for Si-based FETs, integrating high-k gate insulators with JoFETs promises similar advantages in superconducting electronics. Here, we investigate the gate-tunable electrical properties of InAsOI-based JoFETs featuring different high-k gate insulators, namely, HfO2 and Al2O3. We found that both the ungated and gate-tunable electrical properties of the JoFETs are strongly dependent on the insulator chosen. With both dielectrics, the JoFETs can entirely suppress the switching current and increase the normal state resistance by 10-20 times using negative gate voltages. The HfO2-JoFETs exhibit improved gate-tunable electrical performance compared to those achieved with Al2O3-JoFETs, which is related to the higher permittivity of the insulator. Gate-dependent electrical properties of InAsOI-based JoFETs were evaluated in the temperature range from 50 mK to 1 K. Moreover, under the influence of an out-of-plane magnetic field, JoFETs exhibited an unconventional Fraunhofer diffraction pattern, from which an edge-peaked supercurrent density distribution was calculated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16221v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acsaelm.5c00038?urlappend=%3Fref%3DPDF&amp;jav=VoR&amp;rel=cite-as</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Paghi, Laura Borgongino, Sebastiano Battisti, Simone Tortorella, Giacomo Trupiano, Giorgio De Simoni, Elia Strambini, Lucia Sorba, Francesco Giazotto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phonon-mediated electron attraction in SrTiO$_3$ via the generalized Fr\"ohlich and deformation potential mechanisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17230v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Superconductivity in doped SrTiO$_3$ was discovered in 1964, the first superconducting transition observed in a doped semiconductor. However, the mechanism of electron pairing in SrTiO$_3$ remains a subject of debate. By developing a theoretical framework to incorporate dynamical lattice screening in the electronic Coulomb interactions of semiconductors and insulators, we demonstrate analytically that linear long-range coupling of electrons to multiple longitudinal optical phonons, described by a generalized Fr\"ohlich mechanism, can result in superconductivity in SrTiO$_3$. Moreover, by combining our theory with first-principles calculations, we reveal an additional attractive interaction between electrons in SrTiO$_3$ due to the deformation potential mechanism, arising from the mixed ionic-covalent character of the Ti-O bond. Our results may have implications for the emergence of phonon-mediated electron attraction and superconductivity in a broad range of materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17230v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher J. N. Coveney, Norm M. Tubman, Chih-En Hsu, Andres Montoya-Castillo, Marina R. Filip, Jeffrey B. Neaton, Zhenglu Li, Vojtech Vlcek, Antonios M. Alvertis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complete suppression of flux instabilities in ramped superconducting magnets with synchronous temperature-modulated Jc</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.04159v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Nonlinear multi-field coupling as an intrinsic property of complex physical systems often leads to abrupt and undesired instabilities. For current-ramped high-field Nb3Sn magnets, frequent flux jumps are observed, which easily causes premature quenches and requires prolonged and resource-intensive magnet training process. In this study, we propose a paradigm-shifting methodology framework that achieves complete suppression of thermomagnetic instabilities through synchronized temperature-modulated critical current density (Jc). Through numerical simulations of flux jumps in multifilamentary Nb3Sn wires at various temperatures, we construct thermomagnetic stability diagram in the Ha-T plane. The simulated results are in good agreement with experiments, confirming that the synchronized temperature ramp-down can fully eliminate flux jumps. We reveal the underlying mechanism of enhancing the thermomagnetic stability arises from that synchronized temperature ramp-down can continuously tune both Jc and its slope. Furthermore, we explore the thermomagnetic instabilities of current-ramped superconducting magnets through large-scale GPU-optimized algorithm. The flux jump and quench diagram in the Ia-T plane are obtained. It indicates that the temperature ramp-down can completely suppress flux jumps without compromising Jc at high magnetic fields. Importantly, this method does not require modifications to the superconducting microstructures or fabrication process, offering a practical and broadly applicable solution. The findings not only provide a robust method for stabilizing various superconducting magnet systems, including high-temperature superconducting magnets wound with second-generated (2G) coated tapes, but also suggest a generalizable strategy for controlling instability in other nonlinear non-equilibrium physical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.04159v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cun Xue, Han-Xi Ren, Kai-Wei Cao, Wei Liu, Wen-Tao Zhang, Fang Yang, Guo Yan, You-He Zhou, Pingxiang Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engineering inter-band coupling in a two-band superconductor by topological defects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06072v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The vast majority of superconductors have more than one Fermi surface, on which the electrons pair below the critical temperature TC, yet their superconducting behavior can be well described by a single-band Bardeen-Cooper-Schrieffer theory. This is mostly due to inter-band scattering, especially in superconductors in the dirty limit, rigidly linking the pairing amplitude of the different bands. This effect has severely limited experimental studies of the complex physics of multi-band superconductivity. In this study, we utilize the fact that elementary Pb - as a clean limit system - has two Fermi surfaces that are only weakly coupled by inter-band scattering, allowing the formation of two separate condensates. By studying elementary crystal defects in the form of stacking faults with our millikelvin scanning tunneling microscope, we show how to locally tune inter-band coupling ranging from weak to strong coupling and modify the superconducting order parameters around defects. The experiments critically test the theory of multi-band superconductors and give a route to access a wide range of predicted quantum effects in these systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06072v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Gozlinski, Qili Li, Rolf Heid, Oleg Kurnosikov, Alexander Haas, Ryohei Nemoto, Toyo Kazu Yamada, Joerg Schmalian, Wulf Wulfhekel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscopic theory for electron-phonon coupling in twisted bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03293</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03293v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The origin of superconductivity in twisted bilayer graphene -- whether phonon-driven or electron-driven -- remains unresolved, in part due to the absence of a quantitative and efficient model for electron-phonon coupling (EPC). In this work, we develop a first-principles-based microscopic theory to calculate EPC in twisted bilayer graphene for arbitrary twist angles without requiring a periodic moir\'e supercell. Our approach combines a momentum-space continuum model for both electronic and phononic structures with a generalized Eliashberg-McMillan theory beyond the adiabatic approximation. Using this framework, we find that the EPC is strongly enhanced near the magic angle. The superconducting transition temperature induced by low-energy phonons peaks at $1.1^\circ$ around 1 K, and remains finite for a range of angles both below and above the magic angles. We predict that superconductivity persists up to $\sim 1.4^\circ$, where superconductivity has been recently observed despite the dispersive electronic bands. Beyond a large density of states, we identify a key condition for strong EPC: resonance between the electronic bandwidth and the dominant phonon frequencies. We also show that the EPC strength of a specific phonon corresponds to the modification of the moir\'e potential. In particular, we identify several $\Gamma$-phonon branches that contribute most significantly to the EPC, which are experimentally detectable via Raman spectroscopy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03293v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziyan Zhu, Thomas P. Devereaux</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A method to treat strongly correlated topological superconductors in one and two dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07022v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the strong electron-electron (e-e) interaction limit each atomic site is constrained to be either empty or singly occupied. One can treat this scenario by fractionalizing the electrons into spin and charge degrees of freedom. We use the coherent state symbols associated with the lowest irreducible representation of the $su(2|1)$ superalgebra spanned by the Hubbard operators to solve the proposed models, as they implicitly take into account both the single particle occupation constraint and the fractionalization of the electrons. As an example, using the proposed method we solve the one dimensional Kitaev chain and two-dimensional BCS-Hubbard model to show the emergence of topological properties. The proposed procedure is quite general and can be used to analyze different lattice Hamiltonian, provided strong e-e correlation excludes doubly occupied states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07022v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaushal Kumar Kesharpu, Evgenii A. Kochetov, Alvaro Ferraz</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
