<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.supr-con updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con</link>
    <description>cond-mat.supr-con updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 04:00:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Critical spin fluctuations across the superconducting dome in La$_{2-x}$Sr$_{x}$CuO$_4$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13600v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Overdoped cuprate superconductors are strange metals above their superconducting transition temperature. In such materials, the electrical resistivity has a strong linear dependence on temperature ($T$) and electrical current is not carried by electron quasiparticles as in conventional metals. Here we demonstrate that the strange metal behavior co-exists with strongly temperature-dependent critical spin fluctuations showing dynamical scaling across the cuprate phase diagram. Our neutron scattering observations and the strange metal behavior are consistent with a spin density wave quantum phase transition in a metal with spatial disorder in the tuning parameter. Numerical computations on a Yukawa-Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model yield an extended `Griffiths phase' with scaling properties in agreement with observations, establishing that low-energy spin excitations and spatial disorder are central to the strange metal behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13600v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacopo Radaelli, Oliver J. Lipscombe, Mengze Zhu, J. Ross Stewart, Aavishkar A. Patel, Subir Sachdev, Stephen M. Hayden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Competing Quantum Orders in 6R-TaS$_2$: Unconventional Superconductivity, Charge Order, and an Anomalous Hall Effect phase</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13944v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The transition metal dichalcogenide 6R-TaS$_{2}$ offers a natural platform for studying the interplay among charge density wave (CDW) order, superconductivity, and transport anomalies. Recent findings reveal that, in the intermediate temperature range between charge order and superconductivity, a hidden order emerges around $T^{*}$ ${\simeq}$ 35 K-as evidenced by strong magnetoresistance and an anomalous Hall effect (AHE). However, the nature of the superconducting pairing, the hidden order, and their relationship with the CDW remain unclear. Using ${\mu}$SR, magnetotransport, susceptibility, and hydrostatic pressure techniques, we identify a nodal superconducting state with low superfluid density at ambient pressure, with no spontaneous magnetic order detected below $T^{*}$. This indicates that the AHE originates from the band structure rather than magnetism. Under pressures up to 2 GPa, the superfluid density rises markedly in correlation with the superconducting transition temperature, the nodal pairing shifts to a nodeless state, and the CDW onset is reduced by half. Notably, AHE is fully suppressed and magnetoresistance drops by 50${\%}$ within just 0.2 GPa, highlighting the fragility of the hidden order. These results reveal an unconventional superconducting pairing in 6R-TaS$_{2}$, competing with both CDW and hidden orders through weakened interlayer coupling and competition for the same electronic states. With a multifaceted approach, we establish a comprehensive phase diagram that reveals the intricate interplay and competition between the intertwined quantum orders in 6R-TaS$_{2}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13944v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Sazgari, J. N. Graham, S. S. Islam, 1 P. Kr\'al, O. Gerguri, A. Achari, J. N. Tangermann, H. Gopakumar, G. Simutis, M. Janoschek, M. Bartkowiak, R. Khasanov, H. Luetkens, F. O. von Rohr, R. R. Nair, Z. Guguchia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complex spin-density-wave ordering in La$_4$Ni$_{3}$O$_{10}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14128v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The discovery of high-temperature superconductivity in layered nickelates under pressure has recently triggered enormous interest. Studies of these compounds have revealed a density-wave-like transition at ambient pressure, though its connection with superconductivity is still not well understood. Here, we report a detailed \msr\ study on single crystals of trilayer nickelate \LNO\ at ambient pressure. We have identified a spin-density-wave (SDW) transition at the temperature of $T_\mathrm{N} \sim$130 K, as well as a broad crossover around 70 - 100 K. Based on the temperature dependence of the muon precession amplitudes, we attribute this additional crossover either to a spin reorientation, or to an inhomogeneous SDW ordering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14128v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yantao Cao, Andi Liu, Bin Wang, Mingxin Zhang, Yanpeng Qi, Thomas J. Hicken, Hubertus Luetkens, Zhendong Fu, Jason S. Gardner, Jinkui Zhao, Hanjie Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frustrated Frustration of Arrays with Four-Terminal Nb-Pt-Nb Josephson Junctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14423</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14423v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the frustration pattern of a square lattice with in-situ fabricated Nb-Pt-Nb four-terminal Josephson junctions. The four-terminal geometry gives rise to a checker board pattern of alternating fluxes f, f' piercing the plaquettes, which stabilizes the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless transition even at irrational flux quanta per unit cell, due to an unequal repartition of integer flux sum f+f' into alternating plaquettes. This type of frustrated frustration manifests as a beating pattern of the dc resistance, with state configurations at the resistance dips gradually changing between the conventional zero-flux and half-flux states. Hence, the four-terminal Josephson junctions array offers a promising platform to study previously unexplored flux and vortex configurations, and provides an estimate on the spatial expansion of the four-terminal Josephson junctions central weak link area.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14423v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Justus Teller, Christian Sch\"afer, Kristof Moors, Benjamin Bennemann, Matvey Lyatti, Florian Lentz, Detlev Gr\"utzmacher, Roman-Pascal Riwar, Thomas Sch\"apers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flux trapping in NbTiN strips and structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14457</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14457v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We use scanning superconducting quantum interference device (SQUID) microscopy to image vortices in superconducting strips fabricated from NbTiN thin films. We repeatedly cool superconducting strips with different width in an applied magnetic field and image the individual vortices. From these images we determine the threshold field at which the first vortex enters a strip, as well as the number and spatial configuration of vortices beyond this threshold field. We model vortex behavior with and without considering the effect of pinning by numercially minimizing the Gibbs free energy of vortices in the strips. Our measurements provide a first benchmark to understand the flux trapping properties of NbTiN thin films directly relevant to NbTiN-based superconducting circuits and devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14457v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruiheng Bai, Aliakbar Sepehri, Yen-Lee Loh, Anne-Marie Valente-Feliciano, Anna Herr, Quentin Herr, Katja C. Nowack</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sn-InAs nanowire shadow-defined Josephson junctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13725v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Interest in hybrid electronic devices for quantum science is driving the research into superconductor-semiconductor materials combinations. Here we study InAs nanowires coated with shells of $\beta$-Sn. The wires grow via the vapor-liquid-solid mechanism out from (001) InAs substrates along two orientations, forming a criss-crossing landscape. This allows us to define nanowire-shadow junctions during the low temperature Sn shell deposition by carefully choosing the deposition angle. We find that the Sn shells are uniform in thickness and the grains have a preferential in-plane epitaxial relationship with InAs. The interface between Sn and InAs is abrupt and we do not observe interdiffusion. In our nanowire devices, Sn induces a superconducting gap of order 600 $\mu$eV, switching currents reaching values up to 500 nA, and critical magnetic fields along the nanowire of up to 1.3 T. These characteristics can be leveraged in the design of superconducting transmon qubits, parametric microwave amplifiers as well as for the investigation of triplet and topological superconductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13725v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amritesh Sharma, An-Hsi Chen, Connor P. Dempsey, Amrita Purkayastha, Mihir Pendharkar, Susheng Tan, Christopher J. Palmstr{\o}m, Sergey M. Frolov, Mo\"ira Hocevar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comment on Unusual violation of the Wiedemann-Franz law at ultralow temperatures in topological compensated semimetals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13968v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently, Wang et al. [1] reported on an unusual violation of Wiedemann-Franz law in three semimetals. We compare their observations to our observations in a variety of systems, where the apparent WF law violations in the same temperature range arise as a consequence of electron-phonon decoupling. Given the empirical similarity of their data with these cases, the most plausible explanation for the reported violation is an experimental artefact.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13968v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kamran Behnia, Shiyan Li, Johnpierre Paglione, Louis Taillefer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Materials-Level Sources of Performance Variation in Superconducting Transmon Qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14424v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Superconducting Materials and Systems (SQMS) Center, a DOE National Quantum Information Science Research Center, has conducted a comprehensive and coordinated study using superconducting transmon qubit chips with known performance metrics to identify the underlying materials-level sources of device-to-device performance variation. Following qubit coherence measurements, these qubits of varying base superconducting metals and substrates have been examined with various nondestructive and invasive material characterization techniques at Northwestern University, Ames National Laboratory, and Fermilab as part of a blind study. We find trends in variations of the depth of the etched substrate trench, the thickness of the surface oxide, and the geometry of the sidewall, which when combined, lead to correlations with the T$_1$ lifetime across different devices. In addition, we provide a list of features that varied from device to device, for which the impact on performance requires further studies. Finally, we identify two low-temperature characterization techniques that may potentially serve as proxy tools for qubit measurements. These insights provide materials-oriented solutions to not only reduce performance variations across neighboring devices, but also to engineer and fabricate devices with optimal geometries to achieve performance metrics beyond the state-of-the-art values.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14424v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akshay A. Murthy, Mustafa Bal, Michael J. Bedzyk, Hilal Cansizoglu, Randall K. Chan, Venkat Chandrasekhar, Francesco Crisa, Amlan Datta, Yanpei Deng, Celeo D. Matute Diaz, Vinayak P. Dravid, David A. Garcia-Wetten, Sabrina Garattoni, Sunil Ghimire, Dominic P. Goronzy, Sebastian de Graaf, Sam Haeuser, Mark C. Hersam, Dieter Isheim, Kamal Joshi, Richard Kim, Saagar Kolachina, Cameron J. Kopas, Matthew J. Kramer, Ella O. Lachman, Jaeyel Lee, Peter G. Lim, Andrei Lunin, William Mah, Jayss Marshall, Josh Y. Mutus, Jin-Su Oh, David Olaya, David P. Pappas, Joong-mok Park, Ruslan Prozorov, Roberto dos Reis, David N. Seidman, Zuhawn Sung, Makariy Tanatar, Mitchell J. Walker, Jigang Wang, Haotian Wu, Lin Zhou, Shaojiang Zhu, Anna Grassellino, Alexander Romanenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pressure-enhanced splitting of density wave transitions in La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_{7-\delta}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.10485</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.10485v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The observation of superconductivity in La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_{7-\delta}$ under pressure, following the suppression of a high-temperature density wave state, has attracted considerable attention. The nature of this density wave order was not clearly identified. Here, we probe the magnetic response of the zero-pressure phase of La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_{7-\delta}$ as hydrostatic pressure is applied and find that the apparent single density wave transition at zero applied pressure splits into two. The comparison of our muon-spin rotation and relaxation experiments with dipole-field numerical analysis reveals the magnetic structure's compatibility with a stripe-type arrangement of Ni moments, characterized by alternating lines of magnetic moments and nonmagnetic stripes at ambient pressure. When pressure is applied, the magnetic ordering temperature increases, while the unidentified density wave transition temperature falls. Our findings reveal that the ground state of the La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_{7-\delta}$ system is characterized by the coexistence of two distinct orders -- a magnetically ordered spin density wave and a lower-temperature ordering that is most likely a charge density wave -- with a notable pressure-enhanced separation between them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.10485v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41567-024-02754-z</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Physics, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Rustem Khasanov, Thomas J. Hicken, Dariusz J. Gawryluk, Vahid Sazgari, Igor Plokhikh, Lo\"ic Pierre Sorel, Marek Bartkowiak, Steffen B\"otzel, Frank Lechermann, Ilya M. Eremin, Hubertus Luetkens, Zurab Guguchia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disorder Induced Superconductivity in TiSe_1.2S_0.8</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.06319v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Disorder can be utilized as an effective parameter to probe the interplay between two long range orders such as superconductivity and charge density wave. In the present work, we report on the experimental evidence for filamentary superconductivity in polycrystalline TiSe1.2S0.8 with superconducting transition Tc ~ 7K. This is validated from magnetization and magneto-transport measurements. Strain induced dislocations, substitutional defects, and randomly distributed Ti ions (with local moments) are considered as possible sources of disorder. A detailed analysis of the temperature dependent resistivity evaluates the degree of disorder and the consequent localization effects. The findings are in striking contrast to the fact that superconductivity has not been reported in single crystals of TiSe2-xSx system. It is established that disorder serves as a stabilizing factor for the superconducting phase due to in-commensuration of the charge density wave.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.06319v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Singh, P. Saha, A. Chahar, B. Birajdar, D. K. Shukla, S. Patnaik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spontaneous magnetic field and disorder effects in BaPtAs_1-x_Sb_x_ with honeycomb network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05266v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Chiral superconductivity exhibits the formation of novel electron pairs that breaks the time-reversal symmetry and has been actively studied in various quantum materials in recent years. However, despite its potential to provide definitive information, effects of disorder in the crystal structure on the chiral superconductivity has not yet been clarified, and therefore the investigation using a solid-solution system is desirable. We report muon-spin-relaxation (muSR) results of layered pnictide BaPtAs_1-x_Sb_x_ with a honeycomb network composed of Pt and (As, Sb). We observed an increase of the zero-field muon-spin relaxation rate in the superconducting (SC) state at the Sb end of x=1.0, suggesting the occurrence of spontaneous magnetic field due to the time-reversal symmetry breaking in the SC state. On the other hand, spontaneous magnetic field was almost and completely suppressed for the As-Sb mixed samples of x=0.9 and 0.2, respectively, suggesting that the time-reversal symmetry breaking SC state in x=1.0 is sensitive to disorder. The magnetic penetration depth estimated from transverse-field muSR measurements at x=1.0 and 0.2 behaved like weak-coupling s-wave superconductivity. These seemingly incompatible zero-field and transverse-field muSR results of BaPtAs_1-x_Sb_x_ with x=1.0 could be understood in terms of chiral d-wave superconductivity with point nodes on the three-dimensional Fermi surface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05266v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Adachi, T. Ogawa, Y. Komiyama, T. Sumura, Y. Saito-Tsuboi, T. Takeuchi, K. Mano, K. Manabe, K. Kawabata, T. Imazu, A. Koda, W. Higemoto, H. Okabe, J. G. Nakamura, T. U. Ito, R. Kadono, C. Baines, I. Watanabe, T. Kida, M. Hagiwara, Y. Imai, J. Goryo, M. Nohara, K. Kudo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital-analog quantum computing of fermion-boson models in superconducting circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.12040</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.12040v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a digital-analog quantum algorithm for simulating the Hubbard-Holstein model, describing strongly-correlated fermion-boson interactions, in a suitable architecture with superconducting circuits. It comprises a linear chain of qubits connected by resonators, emulating electron-electron (e-e) and electron-phonon (e-p) interactions, as well as fermion tunneling. Our approach is adequate for a digital-analog quantum computing (DAQC) of fermion-boson models including those described by the Hubbard-Holstein model. We show the reduction in the circuit depth of the DAQC algorithm, a sequence of digital steps and analog blocks, outperforming the purely digital approach. We exemplify the quantum simulation of a half-filling two-site Hubbard-Holstein model. In such example we obtain fidelities larger than 0.98, showing that our proposal is suitable to study the dynamical behavior of solid-state systems. Our proposal opens the door to computing complex systems for chemistry, materials, and high-energy physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.12040v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41534-025-01001-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>npj Quantum Inf 11, 43 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shubham Kumar, Narendra N. Hegade, Enrique Solano, Francisco Albarr\'an-Arriagada, Gabriel Alvarado Barrios</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Influence of oxygen orbitals and boundary conditions on the pairing behavior in the Emery model for doped ladders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14280v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the Emery model on several ladder-like lattices including two legs of copper d-orbitals and various numbers of oxygen p-orbitals. Pair binding energy, pair spatial structure, density distribution, and pairing correlation functions are calculated using the density matrix renormalization group (DMRG). We show that a Luther-Emery phase with enhanced pairing correlations can be found for hole doping as well as for electron doping with realistic model parameters. Ladder properties depend sensitively on model parameters, the oxygen p-orbitals taken into account, and boundary conditions. The pair binding energy is a more reliable quantity than correlation functions for studying pairing in ladders. Overall, our results for two-leg Emery ladders support the possibility of superconductivity in the hole-doped 2D model. The issue is rather to determine which of the various ladder structures and model parameters are appropriate to approximate the two-dimensional cuprates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14280v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.125137</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 125137 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>G\"okmen Polat (Institute of Theoretical Physics, Leibniz Universit\"at Hannover), Eric Jeckelmann (Institute of Theoretical Physics, Leibniz Universit\"at Hannover)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zero energy modes with Gaussian, exponential, or polynomial decay: Exact solutions in hermitian and nonhermitian regimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14255v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Topological zero modes in topological insulators or superconductors are exponentially localized at the phase transition between a topologically trivial and nontrivial phase. These modes are solutions of a Jackiw-Rebbi equation modified with an additional term which is quadratic in the momentum. Moreover, localized fermionic modes can also be induced by harmonic potentials in superfluids and superconductors or in atomic nuclei. Here, by using inverse methods, we consider in the same framework exponentially-localized zero modes, as well as Gaussian modes induced by harmonic potentials (with superexponential decay) and polynomially decaying modes (with subexponential decay), and derive the explicit and analytical form of the modified Jackiw-Rebbi equation (and of the Schr\"odinger equation) which admits these modes as solutions. We find that the asymptotic behavior of the mass term is crucial in determining the decay properties of the modes. Furthermore, these considerations naturally extend to the nonhermitian regime. These findings allow us to classify and understand topological and nontopological boundary modes in topological insulators and superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14255v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/ptep/ptaf025</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Pasquale Marra, Angela Nigro</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
