<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.supr-con updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con</link>
    <description>cond-mat.supr-con updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 05:02:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Phase Control of a Thick SNS Weak Link: Proposed experimental scheme</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07862v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In contrast to the extensive literature on thin tunnel junctions and traditional SQUID geometries, there is almost no quantitative experimental data on magnetic control of the Josephson phase in thick SNS weak links. The standard view is that in such compact structures without macroscopic loops the local magnetic coupling to the phase is negligibly small, which in practice forces one to use bulky SQUID devices for phase control. We show that this view is overly restrictive. We consider a thick SNS bridge with an on-chip microcoil placed directly above it, which controls the Josephson phase via strong phase-flux coupling enhanced near the Josephson plasma resonance. In the proposed configuration realistic thick SNS weak links, with normal-layer thickness d of order xi, can achieve phase-flux efficiencies of order 30-60 percent of an ideal dc SQUID. Within a standard RSJ/RCSJ model and linear circuit theory we show that this unexpectedly strong coupling arises from the combination of a large kinetic inductance of the thick SNS bridge and resonant amplification of about 15-35 dB, rather than from any exotic microphysics. The proposed experiment, a comparative analysis of Shapiro steps driven by a direct RF signal and by the magnetic field of the same microcoil, provides a direct and quantitative method to measure the phase-flux response of a thick SNS junction. If confirmed experimentally, such structures may become compact phase elements capable of locally controlling the Josephson phase without a macroscopic loop and enabling dense, locally addressable phase control in superconducting quantum circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07862v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.5281/zenodo.17703630 10.5281/zenodo.17703630 10.5281/zenodo.17703630 10.5281/zenodo.17703630</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Aleksey Turchanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A unified model for lunderdoped and overdoped cuprate superconductors based on a spinodal transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08070v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many years of intense research on cuprate superconductors have led to several discoveries, such as the pseudogap and charge density waves (CDW), yet a complete theory is still lacking. By analyzing some experiments and performing calculations, we provide a full interpretation of their properties; from the undoped insulator to the overdoped metallic compounds. The variation of the anomalous Hall coefficient ($R_{\rm H}(T)$) with temperature at half-filling ($n = 1$) and, combinations of undoped ($p = 0$) insulators and metallic films, which, among other things, are indicative of a thermodynamic transition. On the overdoped side, recent experiments near the superconducting-to-metal transition detecting superconducting puddles and a considerable degree of charge disorder, suggest that a similar thermodynamic transition operates at all doping levels. We propose a spinodal or charge-separation transition starting near the pseudogap temperature $T^*(p)$, which among other things generates the CDW domains with a typical double-well Landau free-energy functional. Thus, from the half-filled to the overdoped region, the free energy forms an array of wells with $n = 1$ {\it static} holes. With doping, {\it mobile} holes tend to occupy these wells with alternating high and low densities, generating the CDW pattern. The confined holes in small regions develop local superconducting amplitudes, giving rise to a mesoscopic granular superconductor. Similar to the XY model, the grains develop correlation effects mediated by Josephson coupling, which is proportional to the local superfluid density. This approach yields a unified theory of cuprate superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08070v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hercules H. Santana, E. V. L. de Mello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Control of the effective value of the critical current of the RF SQUID by the high-frequency electromagnetic field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08072v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An analysis of the influence of the high-frequency electromagnetic field on the amplitude-frequency and signal characteristics of RF SQUID and experimental verification are carried out. At low parameter , the RF SQUID behavior is well described analytically by the theoretical model. In experiment, basic operation scheme is used in which the interferometer is inductively connected to a resonant tank circuit driven by RF current at a frequency close to the resonance frequency of the tank. It is shown that parameter , which distinguishes between hysteretic and non-hysteretic regimes, can be effectively adjusted to a desired value by applying the high-frequency field of a certain amplitude and frequency much higher than tank resonant frequency. A significant increase in the conversion factor and sensitivity of the RF SQUID during this adjustment is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08072v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/10.0026089</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Low Temp. Phys. 50, 497-501 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>V. I. Shnyrkov, V. Yu. Lyakhno, O. A. Kalenyuk, D. G. Mindich, O. O. Leha, A. P. Shapovalov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-consistent solution of Eliashberg equations for metal hydride superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08126</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08126v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In recent years, the quest for high critical-temperature superconductors has increasingly focused on metal and molecular hydrides, which have demonstrated potential for superconductivity at or near room temperature under extremely high pressures. Such hydrides were first proposed by N. W. Ashcroft in 1968, because hydrogen-rich materials possess elevated vibrational frequencies due to the low atomic mass of hydrogen. This article presents a self-consistent solution to the Eliashberg equations for analysing superconductivity in hydrides, contrasting with the commonly used McMillan-Allen-Dynes parameterized formula. We also analyse effects of the electron-phonon spectral function and the broadening parameters arising from phonon lifetime and sample imperfections on the superconducting critical temperature. Finally, both theoretical approaches are applied to a typical metal hydride superconductor, and the reliability of self-consistent solutions is validated against the experimentally measured critical temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08126v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomas J. Escamilla, Chumin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite-Temperature $\textit{ab initio}$ Structural Optimization of the Bilayer Nickelate Superconductor La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08251v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a first-principles framework for finite-temperature structural optimization that incorporates vibrational contributions to the free energy through anharmonic phonon theory. We extend and further improve the efficiency of the recent approach, enabling its application to systems in which the size of the primitive cell changes across structural phase transitions. Applying this framework to La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$, we establish its pressure-temperature phase diagram and find that the slope of the phase boundary between the high-symmetry and low-symmetry phases is negative, with a magnitude of approximately -60 K / GPa. The present results provide a theoretical foundation for discussing how changes in crystal symmetry influence the emergence of superconductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08251v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryoma Asai, Ryotaro Arita, Takumi Chida, Ryota Masuki, Kazuhiko Kuroki, Terumasa Tadano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>YRu$_3$B$_2$ - a kagome lattice superconductor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08514</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08514v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report the synthesis and physical properties of a polycrystalline, hexagonal boride YRu$_3$B$_2$. Our resistivity and heat capacity measurements indicate that YRu$_3$B$_2$ is a weakly coupled superconductor, with critical temperature $T_c$ = 0.63 K and upper critical field $\mu_0 H_{c2}$ (0)=0.11 T. Density functional theory calculations, together with chemical-bonding analysis, reveal that the electronic states at and near the Fermi energy level are dominated by the Ru kagome sublattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08514v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Micha{\l} J. Winiarski, Dominik Walczak, Szymon Kr\'olak, Duygu Yazici, Robert J. Cava, Tomasz Klimczuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of thermal fluctuations on topological crossover in the chiral d+id superconducting phase</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08527v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The effect of thermal fluctuations on the temperature dependence of the topological index C1 of the chiral d+id superconducting phase of a two-dimensional single-band model on a triangular lattice is investigated. Thermal fluctuations are taken into account within the framework of the self-consistent functional-integral theory. It is established that when the nodal points are located far inside (outside) the Fermi contour of the normal phase, thermal fluctuations expand the relative temperature ranges in which the values of the topological index are close to integer values C1=4(-2). This expansion depends both on the value of the topological index and on the magnitude of the effective attraction between the electrons. However, as the nodal points approach the Fermi contour, topological crossovers to new C1 values are observed, which can persist over a wide temperature range. The nature and degree of influence of thermal fluctuations on these crossovers are established. It is assumed that the observed effects may also manifest in the edge state behavior of a similar system with open boundaries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08527v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. G. Groshev, A. K. Arzhnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microwave Signature of the Emerging Abrikosov Lattice Above $H_{c2}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08586v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The emergence of the Abrikosov lattice in the normal phase of type-II superconducting films when the magnetic field approaches the critical field $H_{c2}$ from above was predicted in Ref.~\cite{GVV2011}. In the quantum fluctuation regime \cite{GL2001} it is characterized by the formation of relatively large (with sizes of order $\xi_{\mathrm{QF}} \sim \xi_{\mathrm{BCS}}\sqrt{H_{c2}/(H-H_{c2})}$) ``long lived'' (lifetime of order $\tau_{\mathrm{QF}} \sim \hbar \Delta^{-1} H_{c2}/(H-H_{c2})$) clusters of rotating fluctuation Cooper pairs - signatures of developing Abrikosov vortices. We demonstrate that these fluctuation-induced vortex clusters, previously considered unobservable due to their ultrafast dynamics and weak (only logarithmically singular) contribution to the dc-conductivity, can in fact be detected through their distinct electromagnetic signature. By analyzing the high-frequency electromagnetic response of these rotating fluctuation Cooper pairs above the second critical field in superconducting film, we predict a pronounced and measurable enhancement in the imaginary part of the ac-conductivity arising directly from quantum fluctuations. This enhancement is expected to occur at characteristic frequencies $\omega_{QF} \sim \hbar^{-1}\Delta(H-H_{c2})/H_{c2}$, which are well below the superconducting threshold at $2\hbar^{-1}\Delta $, where a similar increase in imaginary conductivity occurs in the superconducting phase. For niobium, a prototypical type II superconductor, $\omega_{QF}$ lies in the experimentally accessible microwave range, making the effect directly testable with modern microwave spectroscopy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08586v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hang Zhou, Zhanghai Chen, A. A. Varlamov, Andreas Glatz, Yuriy Yerin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dominant Excitonic Superconductivity in a Three-component Hubbard Chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08784v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding superconductivity emerging from repulsive fermions remains a major challenge in condensed matter physics. In this paper, we investigate the pairing tendencies in a one-dimensional, three component repulsive Hubbard model, using the density matrix renormalization group method. At half-filling, the system exhibits density wave ground state due to strong Hubbard repulsions. Upon doping, we find that Cooper pairs can emerge, whose fluctuations predominate the long-range physics in the system across a wide parameter range. The effective attractions between Cooper pairs are mediated by the particle-hole fluctuations in the third non-pairing component, resembling an excitonic mechanism of superconductivity. The coexistence of multiple density waves and superconductivity at different fermion fillings is explored. We also present an analytical study of the pairing mechanism in both weak and strong coupling limits. Our results provide a new perspective for understanding and exploring unconventional superconductivities in strongly correlated fermionic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08784v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sheng Chen, Qiao Yang, W\'ei W\'u, Fadi Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherence-limited digital control of a superconducting qubit using a Josephson pulse generator at 3 K</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07962v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Compared to traditional semiconductor control electronics (TSCE) located at room temperature, cryogenic single flux quantum (SFQ) electronics can provide qubit measurement and control alternatives that address critical issues related to scalability of cryogenic quantum processors. Single-qubit control and readout have been demonstrated recently using SFQ circuits coupled to superconducting qubits. Experiments where the SFQ electronics are co-located with the qubit have suffered from excess decoherence and loss due to quasiparticle poisoning of the qubit. A previous experiment by our group showed that moving the control electronics to the 3 K stage of the dilution refrigerator avoided this source of decoherence in a high-coherence 3D transmon geometry. In this paper, we also generate the pulses at the 3 K stage but have optimized the qubit design and control lines for scalable 2D transmon devices. We directly compare the qubit lifetime $T_1$, coherence time $T_2^*$ and gate fidelity when the qubit is controlled by the Josephson pulse generator (JPG) circuit versus the TSCE setup. We find agreement to within the daily fluctuations for $T_1$ and $T_2^*$, and agreement to within 10% for randomized benchmarking. We also performed interleaved randomized benchmarking on individual JPG gates demonstrating an average error per gate of $0.46$% showing good agreement with what is expected based on the qubit coherence and higher-state leakage. These results are an order of magnitude improvement in gate fidelity over our previous work and demonstrate that a Josephson microwave source operated at 3 K is a promising component for scalable qubit control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07962v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0147692</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Appl. Phys. Lett. 122, 192602 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M. A. Castellanos-Beltran, A. J. Sirois, L. Howe, D. I. Olaya, J. Biesecker, S. P. Benz, P. F. Hopkins</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherent and compact van der Waals transmon qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08059v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: State-of-the-art superconducting qubits rely on a limited set of thin-film materials. Expanding their materials palette can improve performance, extend operating regimes, and introduce new functionalities, but conventional thin-film fabrication hinders systematic exploration of new material combinations. Van der Waals (vdW) materials offer a highly modular crystalline platform that facilitates such exploration while enabling gate-tunability, higher-temperature operation, and compact qubit geometries. Yet it remains unknown whether a fully vdW superconducting qubit can support quantum coherence and what mechanisms dominate loss at both low and elevated temperatures in such a device. Here we demonstrate quantum-coherent merged-element transmons made entirely from vdW Josephson junctions. These first-generation, fully crystalline qubits achieve microsecond lifetimes in an ultra-compact footprint without external shunt capacitors. Energy relaxation measurements, together with microwave characterization of vdW capacitors, point to dielectric loss as the dominant relaxation channel up to hundreds of millikelvin. These results establish vdW materials as a viable platform for compact superconducting quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08059v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jesse Balgley, Jinho Park, Xuanjing Chu, Jiru Liu, Madisen Holbrook, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Archana Kamal, Leonardo Ranzani, Martin V. Gustafsson, James Hone, Kin Chung Fong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinetic Inductance of Few-Layer NbSe$_2$ in the Two-Dimensional Limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08466v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Van der Waals (vdW) superconductors remain superconducting down to the monolayer limit, enabling the exploration of emergent physical phenomena and functionality driven by reduced dimensionality. Here, we report the characterization of the kinetic inductance of atomically thin NbSe$_2$, a two-dimensional van der Waals superconductor, using superconducting coplanar waveguides and microwave measurement techniques familiar to circuit quantum electrodynamics (cQED). The kinetic inductance scales inversely with the number of NbSe$_2$ layers, reaching 1.2 nH/$\Box$ in the monolayer limit. Furthermore, the measured kinetic inductance exhibits a thickness-dependent crossover from clean- to dirty-limit behavior, with enhanced dirty-limit contributions emerging in the ultra-thin regime. These effects are likely driven by increased surface scattering, multi-band superconductivity, and geometric confinement. Additionally, the self-Kerr nonlinearity of the NbSe$_2$ films ranges from $K/2\pi$ = -0.008 to -14.7 Hz/photon, indicating its strong potential in applications requiring compact, nearly linear, high-inductance superconducting quantum devices and detectors. The fabrication and characterization techniques demonstrated here are extensible to the investigation of other two-dimensional superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08466v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sameia Zaman, Joel \^I-j. Wang, Thomas Werkmeister, Miuko Tanaka, Thao Dinh, Max Hays, Daniel Rodan-Legrain, Aranya Goswami, R\'eouven Assouly, Ahmet Kemal Demir, David K. Kim, Bethany M. Niedzielski, Kyle Serniak, Mollie E. Schwartz, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Philip Kim, Riccardo Comin, Jeffrey A. Grover, Terry P. Orlando, Pablo Jarillo-Herrero, William D. Oliver</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay between Superconductivity and Altermagnetism in Disordered Materials and Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04819v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the interplay between superconductivity and altermagnetism in disordered systems using recently derived quantum kinetic transport equations. Starting from this framework, we derive the Ginzburg-Landau free energy and identify, in addition to the conventional pair-breaking term, a coupling between the spin and the spatial variation of the superconducting order parameter. Two distinct effects emerge from this coupling. The first is a magnetoelectric effect, in which a supercurrent (i.e., a phase gradient) induces a spin texture; this contribution is quadratic in the phase gradient. The second effect arises when the magnitude, rather than the phase, of the superconducting order parameter varies in space, likewise leading to a finite magnetization. We show that these two contributions compete in the case of an Abrikosov vortex, where both the amplitude and phase of the order parameter vary spatially. The effect associated with amplitude variations also gives rise to a proximity-induced magnetization (PIM) in hybrid structures composed of a superconductor (S) and an altermagnet (AM). Using quasiclassical theory, we analyze the PIM in diffusive S/AM bilayers and S/AM/S Josephson junctions, and determine the induced magnetization profiles. In Josephson junctions, where both the PIM and the magnetoelectric effect coexist, we further predict the occurrence of $0$-$\pi$ transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04819v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rodrigo de las Heras, Tim Kokkeler, Stefan Ili\'c, Ilya V. Tokatly, F. Sebastian Bergeret</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Massive Dirac states bound to vortices by a boson-fermion interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00950</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00950v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Results are presented from numerical simulations of the flat-space nonlinear Maxwell-Klein-Gordon-Dirac equations. The introduction of a boson-fermion interaction allows a scalar vortex to act as a harmonic trap that can confine massive Dirac bound states. A parametric analysis is performed to understand the range of boson-fermion coupling strengths, Ginzburg-Landau parameters, and fermion effective masses that support the existence of bound state solutions; results are shown to be comparable to quasiparticle bound states in gapped Dirac materials. Solutions are time-evolved and are observed to be stable until the fermion field {\psi} becomes large enough to collapse the spontaneously broken vacuum of the condensate. Head-on scattering simulations are performed, and traditional vortex right-angle scattering is shown to break down with increased fermion field strength. For sufficiently large {\psi} and low velocity, the collision of two m = 1 vortices results in a pseudostable m= 2 bound state that eventually becomes unstable and decays back into two m= 1 vortices. For large {\psi} and collision velocity, vortex scattering is observed to produce nontopological (zero winding number) scalar bound states that are ejected from the collision. The scalar bubbles contain coherent fermion bound states in their interiors and interpolate between the spontaneously broken vacuum of the bulk and the modified vacuum induced by the boson-fermion interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00950v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/wfm6-2kfv</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ethan P. Honda</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
