<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.supr-con updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con</link>
    <description>cond-mat.supr-con updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 04:03:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Origin of insulating-like behavior of Bi$_2$Sr$_2$CaCu$_2$O$_{8+x}$ under pressure: A first-principles study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07336</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07336v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent experimental study on Bi$_2$Sr$_2$CaCu$_2$O$_{8+x}$ superconductors has revealed an unexpected quantum phase transition from superconducting state to insulatinglike state under pressure [Zhou et al., Nat. Phys. 18, 406 (2022)]. To better understand the physical origin of this pressure-induced phenomenon, here we have studied the structural, electronic, and magnetic properties of undoped and O-doped Bi$_2$Sr$_2$CaCu$_2$O$_{8+x}$ (Bi2212) under pressures based on density-functional theory calculations. We first identified the crystal structure of undoped Bi2212 with the armchair distortions in the BiO layers and reproduced the insulating feature of the parent compound. Then we added an extra O atom to the parent compound to simulate the hole-doping effect and found that the structure with O dopant located in the van der Waals (vdW) gap is energetically the most stable. Further calculations on O-doped (0.125 holes/Cu) Bi2212 revealed that the pressure can induce charge redistributions between CuO$_2$ planes and BiO layers; specifically, Cu-$d_{x^2-y^2}$ orbitals gain electrons and Cu atoms rather than O atoms dominate around the Fermi level under high pressure. Along with the increasing pressure, the density of states at the Fermi level first reaches the maximum at $\sim$ 10 GPa and then shows a valley near the Fermi level above 20 GPa, which may be responsible for the insulatinglike state observed in recent experiments. We suggest that the competition among several factors, such as the increase of electrons in the CuO$_2$ plane, the variation of in-plane hopping due to the shortened Cu-O distance, and the enhanced Coulomb repulsion among the Cu-3$d$ electrons, could lead to the exotic transition under pressure. Our work provides an explanation of the high-pressure behaviors of Bi2212, which may facilitate a comprehensive understanding of cuprate superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07336v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/6btw-jk8n</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 045113 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xin Du, Jian-Feng Zhang, Zhong-Yi Lu, Kai Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of superconductivity-induced leading-edge gap in Sr-doped $\mathrm{La}_{3}\mathrm{Ni}_{2}\mathrm{O}_{7}$ thin films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07409v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The discovery of high-temperature superconductivity in pressurized bulk $\mathrm{La}_{3}\mathrm{Ni}_{2}\mathrm{O}_{7}$ has ignited significant interest in nickelate superconductors. Unlike cuprates, where superconductivity predominantly originates from the $\mathrm{3}d_{x^2-y^2}$ orbital, nickelates exhibit additional complexities involving contributions from the $\mathrm{3}d_{z^2}$ orbital, prompting fundamental questions about their pairing mechanisms. Despite recent progress in stabilizing superconductivity in $\mathrm{La}_{3}\mathrm{Ni}_{2}\mathrm{O}_{7}$ thin films at ambient pressure, direct spectroscopic evidence of the superconducting gap opening remains elusive. Here, we present an in-situ angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy study of Sr-doped superconducting $\mathrm{La}_{3}\mathrm{Ni}_{2}\mathrm{O}_{7}$ thin films. Fermi surface mapping reveals Ni-$\mathrm{3}d_{x^2-y^2}$-derived $\alpha$ and $\beta$ pockets, with orbital fillings of 0.11$\pm$0.02 electrons and 0.66$\pm$0.03 holes per Ni, respectively, resulting in a total of 0.45$\pm$0.04 electrons for each Ni. These bands exhibit moderate electron correlations, characterized by a band renormalization factor of 3-4. Notably, both $\alpha$ and $\beta$ bands exhibit leading-edge shifts across the superconducting transition, with gap magnitude of ~1-2 meV at Fermi momenta along the Brillouin zone diagonal and slightly away from the zone diagonal, deviating from the conventional $d_{x^2-y^2}$-wave gap structure. Additionally, the Ni-$\mathrm{3}d_{z^2}$-derived $\gamma$ band lies ~75 meV below the Fermi level, indicating a $\mathrm{3}d_{x^2-y^2}$-dominated fermiology in this compound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07409v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenjie Sun, Zhicheng Jiang, Bo Hao, Shengjun Yan, Hongyi Zhang, Maosen Wang, Yang Yang, Haoying Sun, Zhengtai Liu, Dianxiang Ji, Zhengbin Gu, Jian Zhou, Dawei Shen, Donglai Feng, Yuefeng Nie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark states of electrons in a quantum system with two pairs of sublattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07533</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07533v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A quantum state of matter that is forbidden to interact with photons and is therefore undetectable by spectroscopic means is called a dark state. This basic concept can be applied to condensed matter where it suggests that a whole band of quantum states could be undetectable across a full Brillouin zone. Here we report the discovery of such condensed matter dark states in palladium diselenide as a model system that has two pairs of sublattices in the primitive cell. By using angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy, we find valence bands that are practically unobservable over the whole Brillouin zone at any photon energy, polarisation, and scattering plane. Our model shows that two pairs of sublattices located at half-translation positions and related by multiple glide-mirror symmetries make their relative quantum phases polarised into only four kinds, three of which become dark due to double destructive interference. This mechanism is generic to other systems with two pairs of sublattices, and we show how the phenomena observed in cuprates, lead-halide perovskites, and density wave systems can be resolved by the mechanism of dark states. Our results suggest that the sublattice degree of freedom, which has been overlooked so far, should be considered in the study of correlated phenomena and optoelectronic characteristics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07533v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41567-024-02586-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Physics 20, 1582-1588 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yoonah Chung, Minsu Kim, Yeryn Kim, Seyeong Cha, Joon Woo Park, Jeehong Park, Yeonjin Yi, Dongjoon Song, Jung Hyun Ryu, Kimoon Lee, Timur K. Kim, Cephise Cacho, Jonathan Denlinger, Chris Jozwiak, Eli Rotenberg, Aaron Bostwick, Keun Su Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase transitions and spontaneous symmetry breaking in the renormalized Ginzburg-Landau theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07534</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07534v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we present theoretical investigations of phase transitions and critical phenomena in materials through the lens of second-order Ginzburg-Landau theory, in conjunction with considerations of symmetry groups and thermal fluctuations. By addressing the residual effects after a renormalization process, a small number of macroscopic degrees of freedom can effectively replace the infinite number of microscopic degrees of freedom, emphasizing the significant role of dimensionality and the intrinsic characteristics of the system in understanding and analyzing transitions. We highlight several non-universal characteristics of continuous phase transitions near the transition temperature, including the non-monotonic relationship between the critical temperature and dimensionality, as well as the enhancement or disappearance of the specific heat jump in complex superconductors. While the resulting expressions for thermodynamic quantities are complex for one-dimensional systems, obeying Mermin-Wagner's theorem, they are considerably simplified for two-dimensional and three-dimensional systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07534v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Feulefack Ornela Claire, Tsague Fotio Carlos, Keumo Tsiaze Roger Magloire</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nodeless superconductivity in 4H$_{b}$-TaS$_{2}$ with broken time reversal symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07584v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The transition metal dichalcogenide 4H$_{b}$-TaS$_{2}$ exhibits characteristics of topological edge modes and two-component superconductivity with time-reversal symmetry breaking (TRSB). The nature of the superconducting order parameter is a crucial issue that requires experimental investigation. Here, we report measurements of the magnetic penetration depth using a tunnel-diode-oscillator based technique, as well as the specific heat. Both the specific heat and the change in magnetic penetration depth ($\Delta$$\lambda$(T)) display an exponentially-activated temperature dependence, providing evidence for nodeless superconductivity in 4H$_{b}$-TaS$_{2}$. Moreover, the deduced superfluid density can be well described by a two-gap $s$-wave model, and such multigap superconductivity is consistent with there being multiple bands crossing the Fermi energy. These results constrain the possible pairing symmetries of 4H$_{b}$-TaS$_{2}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07584v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.195132</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 014507 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yuwei Zhou, Fanyu Meng, Yanen Huang, Jiawen Zhang, Jin Zhan, Ye Chen, Yu Liu, Hechang Lei, Michael Smidman, Huiqiu Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A comprehensive study of bond bipolaron superconductivity in triangular lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07662</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07662v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We employ the diagrammatic Monte Carlo method with a lattice path-integral formulation for both electron and phonon degrees of freedom to investigate the formation and properties of bond polarons and bipolarons on a two-dimensional triangular lattice. In the adiabatic regime ($\omega/t &lt; 1.0$), single polarons remain light with a small effective mass, while bipolarons remain compact and lightweight, resulting in a high superfluid transition temperature $T_c$. We systematically study the dependence of $T_c$ on electron-phonon coupling strength and on-site interaction in the bond bipolaron model. Our results show that a moderate on-site repulsion enhances $T_c$ by stabilizing compact yet lightweight bipolarons, leading to high-$T_c$ superconductivity in the dilute limit. Notably, the triangular lattice sustains relatively high $T_c$ across a wide range of phonon frequencies, outperforming square lattice geometry. This enhancement arises from the higher coordination number and the bond-centered nature of the electron-phonon coupling. These findings suggest that triangular lattice geometry offers a promising platform for realizing high-$T_c$ bipolaronic superconductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07662v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crossing over from flat band superconductivity to conventional superconductivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07701v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Over the past ten years, flat band (FB) or geometric superconductivity has become a major issue in condensed matter physics due to the significant technological benefits it could offer. Observations of this unconventional form of superconductivity are unfortunately still very limited, and significant efforts are being made to search for candidate materials. Most existing theoretical studies focus on systems with strictly non-dispersive bands, which, from an experimental point of view, represents an extremely difficult technological constraint to achieve. It is therefore crucial to understand to what extent this constraint can be relaxed. In other words, to what extent can superconductivity in flat bands survive weak perturbations? The main objective of the present study is precisely to answer this essential question in detail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07701v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Thumin, G. Bouzerar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature Dependent Optical Response Of High- Tc Yba2cu3o7-{\delta} (Ybco) Thin Films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07866v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report on the temperature-dependent optical response of thin films of YBa2Cu3O7-{\delta} (YBCO) in the visible spectral range under cryogenic conditions. Specifically, we observe an increase in transmittance near the superconducting transition temperature (Tc), which saturates within a few kelvins below Tc. The increase in transmittance is accompanied by a corresponding decrease in reflectance as the temperature drops below Tc, and both quantities track the superconducting phase transition. Changes in transmittance are found to be wavelength dependent, with the maximum variation occurring at 633 nm and minimal at 450 nm. These observations establish a correlation between the variation in optical response and the superconducting phase transition, even in the visible regime. The results of our experiment highlight the potential for using non-contact optical measurements to determine Tc. The effect can be explained using the two-fluid model, which can account for the observed temperature and wavelength dependence of the transmittance of the superconducting thin films.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07866v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vivek Khichar, V. A. Chirayath, Jonathan Asaadi, Nader Hozhabri, Benjamin J. P. Jones, Ali R. Koymen, Iakovos Tzoka, Pratyanik Sau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pressure Induced Altermagnetism in Layered Ternary Iron-Selenides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11228</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11228v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Employing first-principles based calculations, we reexamined the high-pressure phases of the vacancy-ordered iron-selenides, i.e. A2Fe4Se5 phase. A magnetic transition from the block-spin antiferromagnetic phase to Neel-AM phase is observed under high pressure when the iron-vacancy order is preserved. The transition is first-order, driven by the collapse of c-axis and accompanied by an insulator-metal transition. In addition, the Neel-AM phase is a rare example of intrinsic altermagnetism that does not require ligand atoms nor supercell construction to break the spatial inversion or translational symmetry between the two spin sublattices, with a spin-splitting of the band structure as large as 300 meV. If the re-entrant superconducting phase of KyFe2-xSe2 under high pressure emerges from the Neel-AM normal state, an equal-spin triplet pairing would be naturally favored.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11228v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zilong Li, Xin Ma, Siqi Wu, H. -Q. Yuan, Jianhui Dai, Chao Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudogap in a crystalline insulator doped by disordered metals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07500v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A key to understand how electrons behave in crystalline solids is the band structure that connects the energy of electron waves to their wavenumber (k). Even in the phase of matter with only short-range order (liquid or amorphous solid), the coherent part of electron waves still possesses a band structure. Theoretical models for the band structure of liquid metals were formulated more than 5 decades ago, but thus far, bandstructure renormalization and pseudogap induced by resonance scattering have remained unobserved. Here, we report the observation of this unusual band structure at the interface of a crystalline insulator (black phosphorus) and disordered dopants (alkali metals). We find that a conventional parabolic band structure of free electrons bends back towards zero k with the pseudogap of 30-240 meV from the Fermi level. This is k renormalization caused by resonance scattering that leads to the formation of quasi-bound states in the scattering potential of alkali-metal ions. The depth of this potential tuned by different kinds of alkali metal (Na, K, Rb, and Cs) allows to classify the pseudogap of p-wave and d-wave resonance. Our results may provide a clue to the puzzling spectrum of various crystalline insulators doped by disordered dopants, such as the waterfall dispersion in cuprates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07500v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41586-021-03683-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature 596, 68-73 (2021)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sae Hee Ryu, Minjae Huh, Do Yun Park, Chris Jozwiak, Eli Rotenberg, Aaron Bostwick, Keun Su Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic rotons and Wigner crystallites in a two-dimensional dipole liquid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07506v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A key concept proposed by Landau to explain superfluid liquid helium is the elementary excitation of quantum particles called rotons. The irregular arrangement of atoms in a liquid forms the aperiodic dispersion of rotons that played a pivotal role in understanding fractional quantum Hall liquid (magneto-rotons) and the supersolidity of Bose-Einstein condensates. Even for a two-dimensional electron or dipole liquid in the absence of a magnetic field, their repulsive interactions were predicted to form a roton minimum that can be used to trace the transition to Wigner crystals and superconductivity, but it has not been observed. Here, we report the observation of such electronic rotons in a two-dimensional dipole liquid of alkali-metal ions doping charges to surface layers of black phosphorus. Our data reveal a striking aperiodic dispersion of rotons characterized by a local minimum of energy at a finite momentum. As the density of dipoles decreases, where interactions dominate over kinetic energy, the roton gap reduces to 0 as in crystals, signalling Wigner crystallisation. Our model shows the importance of short-range order arising from repulsion between dipoles, which can be viewed as the formation of Wigner crystallites (bubbles or stripes) floating in the sea of Fermi liquids. Our results reveal that the primary origin of electronic rotons (and the pseudogap) is strong correlations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07506v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41586-024-08045-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature 634, 813-817 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Soobin Park, Minjae Huh, Chris Jozwiak, Eli Rotenberg, Aaron Bostwick, Keun Su Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral superconductivity near a fractional Chern insulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07921v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Superconductivity arising from fully spin-polarized, repulsively interacting electrons can host intrinsically chiral Cooper pairs and Majorana zero modes, yet no concrete microscopic route to such a state has been established. Motivated by recent observations in twisted MoTe$_2$ and rhombohedral pentalayer graphene, where fractional Chern insulators (FCIs) appear adjacent to spin-valley-polarized superconductors, we investigate a minimal model: spinless electrons in the lowest Landau level subject to a tunable moire potential. Large-scale density-matrix renormalization group (DMRG) calculations show that, as the FCI gap closes, two nearly degenerate phases emerge before a metallic state forms. A chiral $f+if$ superconductor and a commensurate $\sqrt{3} \times \sqrt{3}$ charge-density wave (CDW) differ in energy by less than $1\%$, reproducing the distinct superconducting and re-entrant integer quantum Hall (RIQH) phases experimentally observed near the FCI regime. The superconducting dome remains robust against realistic Coulomb screening, light doping, and variations in lattice geometry. Melting the FCI therefore provides a new mechanism for realizing spin-polarized chiral superconductivity and RIQH order. We predict that twisted MoTe$_2$ at larger twist angles will develop a superconducting dome even at filling $\nu = 2/3$, and suppressing this superconductivity with a magnetic field should drive the system into an RIQH state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07921v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taige Wang, Michael P. Zaletel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermi-surface diagnosis for topological superconductivity with $s$-wave-like pairing symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20231</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20231v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Theoretical prediction of topological superconductivity is key to their discovery. Recently, it is proved that in 199 out of 230 space groups, topological superconductivity coexists with an $s$-wave-like pairing symmetry, raising the hope of finding more candidates for this exotic phase. However, a comprehensive and efficient method for diagnosing topological superconductivity in realistic materials remains elusive. Here, we derive Fermi-surface formulas for gapped and gapless topological phases of time-reversal symmetric superconductors with $s$-wave-like pairing symmetries in all layer and space groups, applicable to thin-film and bulk materials. Our diagnosis uses only the sign of the pairing and the Fermi velocity at several Fermi points, and yields complete (partial) diagnosis for gapped topological superconductivity in 159 (40) out of the 199 space groups. This provides a fundamental basis for the first-principles prediction of new topological superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20231v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhongyi Zhang, Ken Shiozaki, Chen Fang, Seishiro Ono</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optically active Higgs and Leggett modes in multiband pair-density-wave superconductors with Lifshitz invariant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18438v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Lifshitz invariant is a symmetry invariant composed of multiple order parameters that contain a single spatial derivative in a Ginzburg-Landau (GL) free energy, which may induce a nonuniform configuration of the order parameters. In multiband superconductors, we find phase transitions from a uniform superconducting state to qualitatively distinct two pair-density-wave (PDW) states with small and large momenta $\boldsymbol{q}$ based on the GL theory. The former is induced by the Lifshitz invariant, while the latter originates from the drag effect. In the PDW states, the Higgs and Leggett modes (i.e., collective amplitude and relative phase oscillations of the order parameters) are shown to couple to electromagnetic fields linearly. We construct microscopic models of multiband superconductors with Lifshitz invariant that exhibit PDW states, and calculate the linear optical conductivity using the diagrammatic approach. We find optically active Higgs and Leggett modes in the small $\boldsymbol{q}$ PDW state, indicating that the PDW state is a suitable platform to explore collective modes of multiband superconductors in the linear response regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18438v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/cgyd-2g11</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 024503 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Raigo Nagashima, Titouan Mouilleron, Naoto Tsuji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ab initio screening for BCS-type superconductivity in ThCr$_2$Si$_2$-type compounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04297</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.04297v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study, we applied ab initio $T_\mathrm{c}$ calculations to compounds with the ThCr$_2$Si$_2$-type structure to search for BCS superconductor candidates. From the 1883 compounds registered in the Inorganic Crystal Structure Database, we excluded those whose chemical compositions would inhibit the emergence of BCS-type superconductivity by giving rise to magnetism or heavy-fermionic behavior. We then focused on 66 compounds confirmed to be dynamically stable through phonon calculations. Among these, for the 24 systems with experimentally reported $T_\mathrm{c}$ values, we verified that the ab initio $T_\mathrm{c}$ calculations exhibit excellent predictive reliability. For the remaining 42 compounds lacking experimental $T_\mathrm{c}$ values, our predictions identified several new BCS-type superconductor candidates, including SrPb$_2$Al$_2$ $\left(T_c^\mathrm{calc}=2.2\,\mathrm{K}\right)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.04297v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom Ichibha, Ryo Maezono, Kenta Hongo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivity via paramagnon and magnon exchange in a 2D near-ferromagnetic full metal and ferromagnetic half-metal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.00158v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study superconductivity in paramagnetic and ferromagnetically-ordered phases in a two-dimensional electron system with parabolic fermionic dispersion and short-range repulsive interaction. In the paramagnetic phase, we find that a weak momentum dependence of a paramagnon propagator parametrically reduces the onset temperature for the pairing compared to that in phenomenological theories which assume a strong dispersion of a paramagnon and also changes the topology of the gap function. In the ferromagnetic phase, we show that the order instantly polarizes low-energy fermionic excitations. We derive the fully renormalized pairing interaction between low-energy fermions, mediated by two transverse Goldstone modes and show that it is attractive in a spatially-odd channel. The pairing temperature in the ferromagnetic phase is found to be a fraction of the Fermi energy, significantly larger than in the paramagnetic phase near the transition. Our results are relevant for understanding superconductivity in proximity to itinerant ferromagnetism in multi-valley graphene systems, particularly the ones with full valley and spin polarization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.00158v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zachary M Raines, Andrey V Chubukov</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
