<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.supr-con updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con</link>
    <description>cond-mat.supr-con updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.supr-con" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 05:00:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Oxygen sublattice disorder and valence state modulation in infinite-layer nickelate superlattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.03873v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The family of infinite-layer nickelates promises important insights into the mechanism of unconventional superconductivity. Since superconductivity has so far only been observed in epitaxial thin films, heteroepitaxy with the substrate or a capping layer possibly plays an important role. Here, we use soft x-ray spectroscopy to investigate superlattices as a potential approach for a targeted material design of high-temperature superconductors. We observe modulations in valence state and oxygen coordination in topotactically reduced artificial superlattices with repeating interfaces between nickelate layers and layers of materials commonly used as substrates and capping layers. Our results show that depending on the interlayer material metallic conductivity akin to the parent infinite-layer compounds is achieved. Depth-resolved electronic structure measured by resonant x-ray reflectivity reveals a reconstructed ligand field and valence state at the interface, which is confined to one or two unit cells. The central layers show characteristics of monovalent nickel, but linear dichroism analysis reveals considerable disorder in the oxygen removal sites. We observe a quantitative correlation of this disorder with the interlayer material that is important for future modeling and design strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.03873v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. A. Ortiz, N. Enderlein, K. F\"ursich, R. Pons, P. Radhakrishnan, E. Schierle, P. Wochner, G. Logvenov, G. Cristiani, P. Hansmann, B. Keimer, E. Benckiser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boosting superconductivity: how nanofaceted surfaces transform the ground state of ultrathin YBa$_2$Cu$_3$O$_{7-\delta}$ thin films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03986</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.03986v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the cuprate high-temperature superconductors doping is fixed during synthesis and the charge carrier density per CuO$_2$ plane cannot be easily tuned by conventional gating, unlike 2D materials. Strain engineering has recently emerged as a powerful tuning knob for manipulating the properties of cuprates, in particular charge and spin orders, and their delicate interplay with superconductivity. In thin films, additional tunability can be introduced by the substrate surface morphology, particularly nanofacets formed by substrate surface reconstruction. Here we show a remarkable enhancement of the superconducting onset temperature $T_{\mathrm{c}}^{\mathrm{on}}$ and the upper critical magnetic field $H_{c,2}$ in nanometer-thin YBa$_2$Cu$_3$O$_{7-\delta}$ films grown on a substrate with a nanofaceted surface. We theoretically show that the enhancement is driven by electronic nematicity and unidirectional charge density waves, where both elements are captured by an additional effective potential at the interface between the film and the uniquely textured substrate. Our findings show a new paradigm in which substrate engineering can effectively enhance the superconducting properties of cuprates. This approach opens an exciting frontier in the design and optimization of high-performance superconducting materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.03986v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Wahlberg, R. Arpaia, D. Chakraborty, A. Kalaboukhov, D. Vignolles, C. Proust, A. M. Black-Shaffer, G. Seibold, T. Bauch, F. Lombardi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature dependent energy gap for Yu-Shiba-Rusinov states at the quantum phase transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04196v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by recent experiments, which allow for fine tuning of the effective magnetic interaction between the impurity and the superconductor, we investigate the regime around the quantum phase transition where the system's ground state changes from a weakly coupled free spin to a screened spin regime. At this transition we find that the YSR states remain at finite energies at low temperatures, thereby generating a gap in the spectrum, which is inconsistent with predictions of the original YSR theory. We investigate various gap-generating scenarios and determine that the local suppression of the order parameter, only captured by self-consistent calculations, generates the gap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04196v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Theiler, Christian R. Ast, Annica M. Black-Schaffer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Josephson coupling in Lanthanum-based cuprates superlattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04231</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04231v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In most anisotropic compounds such as bismuth-based layered cuprate perovskites, the supercurrent across the blocking layer is of Josephson type, and a single crystal forms a natural stack of Josephson junctions. Here, we report on the evidence of Josephson-like transport in an artificial cuprate superlattice composed of 10 LaSrCuO-LaCuO repeats, creating a superlattice of junctions, where LCO is a superconducting Mott insulator and LSCO an overdoped metal, respectively. The superlattice has been designed with a long period d = L+W = 5.28 nm, with L and W the thickness of LCO and LSCO units, respectively, and is in the underdoped regime with an average doping level &lt; {\delta} &gt;= 0.11. Quantum-size effects and Rashba spin-orbit coupling are controlled by L/d = 0.75, with a quasi-2D superconducting transition temperature of 41 K and a c-axis coherence length of about 1.5 nm. Measurements at very low temperatures show evidence of Josephson phase dynamics consistent with very low Josephson coupling and a phase diffusion regime, thus explaining why Josephson coupling in LSCO superlattices has been so elusive. The tuning of LSCO superlattices in the Josephson regime enriches the phase diagram of HTS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04231v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0251121</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>APL Quantum 1 March 2025; 2 (1): 016113</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Halima Giovanna Ahmad, Davide Massarotti, Francesco Tafuri, Gennady Logvenov, Antonio Bianconi, Gaetano Campi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The effect of Carrier Doping and Thickness on the Electronic Structures of La$3$Ni$2$O$7$ Thin Films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04255v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, the superconductivity of bilayer nickelate La3Ni2O7 has been observed in the thin film at ambient pressure, facilitated by epitaxial strain. Here, we investigate the effects of film thickness and carrier doping on the electronic structure of La3Ni2O7 thin films with thickness of 0.5-3 unit cells (UC) using first-principles calculations. At an optimal doping concentration of 0.4 holes per formula unit for 2UC film, the Ni-"d" _("z" ^"2" ) interlayer bonding state metallizes, leading to the formation of {\gamma} pockets at the Fermi surface, which quantitatively matches the experimental results of angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES). These findings provide theoretical support for recent experimental observations of ambient-pressure superconductivity in La3Ni2O7 thin films and highlight the crucial role of film thickness and carrier doping in modulating electronic properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04255v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoliang Shi, Zihao Huo, Guanlin Li, Hao Ma, Tian Cui, Dao-Xin Yao, Defang Duan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge density waves and pinning by lattice anisotropy in 214 cuprates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23468v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The detection of static charge density waves (CDWs) in La$_{2-x}$Sr$_x$CuO$_4$ (LSCO) with x $\sim$ 0.12 at relatively high temperatures has raised the question of what lattice feature pins the CDWs. Some recent structural studies have concluded that some form of monoclinic distortion, indicated by the appearance of certain weak Bragg peaks (type M peaks) at otherwise forbidden positions, are responsible for CDW pinning. As a test of this idea, we present neutron diffraction results for a single crystal of La$_{2-x}$Ba$_x$CuO$_4$ (LBCO) with x = 1/8, which is known to undergo two structural transitions on cooling, from high-temperature tetragonal (HTT) to low-temperature orthorhombic (LTO) near 240 K, involving a collective tilt pattern of the corner-sharing CuO$_6$ octahedra, and from LTO to low temperature tetragonal (LTT) near 56 K, involving a new tilt pattern and the appearance of intensity at peaks of type T. We observe both type M and type T peaks in the LTT phase, while the type M peaks (but not type T) are still present in the LTO phase. Given that CDW order is observed only in the LTT phase of LBCO, it is apparent that the in-plane Cu-O bond anisotropy associated with the octahedral tilt pattern is responsible for charge pinning. We point out that evidence for a similar, but weaker, bond anisotropy has been observed previously in LSCO and should be responsible for CDW pinning there. In the case of LBCO, the monoclinic distortion may help to explain previously-reported magneto-optical evidence for gyrotropic order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23468v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao Hu, Pedro M. Lozano, Feng Ye, Qiang Li, Jennifer Sears, Igor. A. Zaliznyak, Genda Gu, John M. Tranquada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivity and magnetic ordering in chalcogen-intercalated graphene bilayers with charge compensation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02931v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This work introduces a new class of two-dimensional crystals with the structure AC$_8$XC$_8$, consisting of two layers of graphene, a chalcogen (X = O, S, Se, Te) intercalation layer, and an alkaline earth (A = Be, Ca, Mg, Sr, Ba) adlayer. The electronic band structure for the 20 compounds was studied using density functional theory. The chalcogen $p$ orbitals interact with the carbon $\pi$ orbitals to form weakly dispersing bands that intersect the Fermi level and give rise to complex Fermi surfaces featuring electron and hole pockets whose densities exactly compensate each other, and van Hove singularities that are very close to, or coincident with, the Fermi level in the majority of compounds studied. The resulting electron-electron interaction effects are studied using both the temperature-flow renormalisation group approach and a spin fluctuation model, which show a ferromagnetic phase with critical temperatures as high as $\sim 10^3$ K that coexists with $p$- or $f$-wave spin triplet superconductivity over a range of temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02931v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tommy Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
