<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.LO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.LO</link>
    <description>cs.LO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.LO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 04:00:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A Note on the Practice of Logical Inferentialism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10546v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A short essay presenting the State-Effect Interpretation of natural deduction rules as an explanatory framework for recent developments in proof-theoretic semantics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10546v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander V. Gheorghiu, Tao Gu, David J. Pym</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The interpolant existence problem for weak K4 and difference logic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11255v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As well known, weak K4 and the difference logic DL do not enjoy the Craig inter- polation property. Our concern here is the problem of deciding whether any given implication does have an interpolant in these logics. We show that the nonexistence of an interpolant can always be witnessed by a pair of bisimilar models of polynomial size for DL and of triple-exponential size for weak K4, and so the interpolant existence problems for these logics are decidable in coNP and coN3ExpTime, respectively. We also establish coNExpTime-hardness of this problem for weak K4, which is higher than the PSpace-completeness of its decision problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11255v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Agi Kurucz, Frank Wolter, Michael Zakharyaschev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Safe Planning through Incremental Decomposition of Signal Temporal Logic Specifications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10554v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Trajectory planning is a critical process that enables autonomous systems to safely navigate complex environments. Signal temporal logic (STL) specifications are an effective way to encode complex temporally extended objectives for trajectory planning in cyber-physical systems (CPS). However, planning from these specifications using existing techniques scale exponentially with the number of nested operators and the horizon of specification. Additionally, performance is exacerbated at runtime due to limited computational budgets and compounding modeling errors. Decomposing a complex specification into smaller subtasks and incrementally planning for them can remedy these issues. In this work, we present a way to decompose STL requirements temporally to improve planning efficiency and performance. The key insight in our work is to encode all specifications as a set of reachability and invariance constraints and scheduling these constraints sequentially at runtime. Our proposed technique outperforms the state-of-the-art trajectory synthesis techniques for both linear and non linear dynamical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10554v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Parv Kapoor, Eunsuk Kang, Romulo Meira-Goes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EXPLORER: Exploration-guided Reasoning for Textual Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10692v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Text-based games (TBGs) have emerged as an important collection of NLP tasks, requiring reinforcement learning (RL) agents to combine natural language understanding with reasoning. A key challenge for agents attempting to solve such tasks is to generalize across multiple games and demonstrate good performance on both seen and unseen objects. Purely deep-RL-based approaches may perform well on seen objects; however, they fail to showcase the same performance on unseen objects. Commonsense-infused deep-RL agents may work better on unseen data; unfortunately, their policies are often not interpretable or easily transferable. To tackle these issues, in this paper, we present EXPLORER which is an exploration-guided reasoning agent for textual reinforcement learning. EXPLORER is neurosymbolic in nature, as it relies on a neural module for exploration and a symbolic module for exploitation. It can also learn generalized symbolic policies and perform well over unseen data. Our experiments show that EXPLORER outperforms the baseline agents on Text-World cooking (TW-Cooking) and Text-World Commonsense (TWC) games.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10692v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kinjal Basu, Keerthiram Murugesan, Subhajit Chaudhury, Murray Campbell, Kartik Talamadupula, Tim Klinger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Logic for Veracity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.06164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.06164v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper shows the initial stages of development, from first principles, of a formal logic to characterise and then explore issues in a broadly defined idea of Veracity, which includes properties of demonstrability, truth, trust and authenticity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.06164v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steve Reeves</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributional Probabilistic Model Checking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.05584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.05584v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Probabilistic model checking can provide formal guarantees on the behavior of stochastic models relating to a wide range of quantitative properties, such as runtime, energy consumption or cost. But decision making is typically with respect to the expected value of these quantities, which can mask important aspects of the full probability distribution such as the possibility of high-risk, low-probability events or multimodalities. We propose a distributional extension of probabilistic model checking, applicable to discrete-time Markov chains (DTMCs) and Markov decision processes (MDPs). We formulate distributional queries, which can reason about a variety of distributional measures, such as variance, value-at-risk or conditional value-at-risk, for the accumulation of reward until a co-safe linear temporal logic formula is satisfied. For DTMCs, we propose a method to compute the full distribution to an arbitrary level of precision, based on a graph analysis and forward analysis of the model. For MDPs, we approximate the optimal policy with respect to expected value or conditional value-at-risk using distributional value iteration. We implement our techniques and investigate their performance and scalability across a range of benchmark models. Experimental results demonstrate that our techniques can be successfully applied to check various distributional properties of large probabilistic models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.05584v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ingy Elsayed-Aly, David Parker, Lu Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Infinite Needle in a Finite Haystack: Finding Infinite Counter-Models in Deductive Verification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.16762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.16762v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: First-order logic, and quantifiers in particular, are widely used in deductive verification. Quantifiers are essential for describing systems with unbounded domains, but prove difficult for automated solvers. Significant effort has been dedicated to finding quantifier instantiations that establish unsatisfiability, thus ensuring validity of a system's verification conditions. However, in many cases the formulas are satisfiable: this is often the case in intermediate steps of the verification process. For such cases, existing tools are limited to finding finite models as counterexamples. Yet, some quantified formulas are satisfiable but only have infinite models. Such infinite counter-models are especially typical when first-order logic is used to approximate inductive definitions such as linked lists or the natural numbers. The inability of solvers to find infinite models makes them diverge in these cases. In this paper, we tackle the problem of finding such infinite models. These models allow the user to identify and fix bugs in the modeling of the system and its properties. Our approach consists of three parts. First, we introduce symbolic structures as a way to represent certain infinite models. Second, we describe an effective model finding procedure that symbolically explores a given family of symbolic structures. Finally, we identify a new decidable fragment of first-order logic that extends and subsumes the many-sorted variant of EPR, where satisfiable formulas always have a model representable by a symbolic structure within a known family. We evaluate our approach on examples from the domains of distributed consensus protocols and of heap-manipulating programs. Our implementation quickly finds infinite counter-models that demonstrate the source of verification failures in a simple way, while SMT solvers and theorem provers such as Z3, cvc5, and Vampire diverge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.16762v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.PL</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3632875</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proceedings of the ACM on Programming Languages 8, no. POPL (2024): 970-1000</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Neta Elad, Oded Padon, Sharon Shoham</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graphical Symplectic Algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.07914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.07914v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We give complete presentations for the dagger-compact props of affine Lagrangian and coisotropic relations over an arbitrary field. This provides a unified family of graphical languages for both affinely constrained classical mechanical systems, as well as odd-prime-dimensional stabiliser quantum circuits. To this end, we present affine Lagrangian relations by a particular class of undirected coloured graphs. In order to reason about composite systems, we introduce a powerful scalable notation where the vertices of these graphs are themselves coloured by graphs. In the setting of stabiliser quantum mechanics, this scalable notation gives an extremely concise description of graph states, which can be composed via ``phased spider fusion.'' Likewise, in the classical mechanical setting of electrical circuits, we show that impedance matrices for reciprocal networks are presented in essentially the same way.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.07914v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert I. Booth, Titouan Carette, Cole Comfort</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complete equational theories for classical and quantum Gaussian relations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10479v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We give generators and relations for the hypergraph props of Gaussian relations and positive affine Lagrangian relations. The former extends Gaussian probabilistic processes by completely-uninformative priors, and the latter extends Gaussian quantum mechanics with infinitely-squeezed states. These presentations are given by adding a generator to the presentation of real affine relations and of real affine Lagrangian relations which freely codiscards effects, as well as certain rotations.
  The presentation of positive affine Lagrangian relations provides a rigorous justification for many common yet informal calculations in the quantum physics literature involving infinite-squeezing. Our presentation naturally extends Menicucci et al.'s graph-theoretic representation of Gaussian quantum states with a representation for Gaussian transformations. Using this graphical calculus, we also give a graphical proof of Braunstein and Kimble's continuous-variable quantum teleportation protocol. We also interpret the LOv-calculus, a diagrammatic calculus for reasoning about passive linear-optical quantum circuits in our graphical calculus. Moreover, we show how our presentation allows for additional optical operations such as active squeezing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10479v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert I. Booth, Titouan Carette, Cole Comfort</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skill Machines: Temporal Logic Skill Composition in Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.12532v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It is desirable for an agent to be able to solve a rich variety of problems that can be specified through language in the same environment. A popular approach towards obtaining such agents is to reuse skills learned in prior tasks to generalise compositionally to new ones. However, this is a challenging problem due to the curse of dimensionality induced by the combinatorially large number of ways high-level goals can be combined both logically and temporally in language. To address this problem, we propose a framework where an agent first learns a sufficient set of skill primitives to achieve all high-level goals in its environment. The agent can then flexibly compose them both logically and temporally to provably achieve temporal logic specifications in any regular language, such as regular fragments of linear temporal logic. This provides the agent with the ability to map from complex temporal logic task specifications to near-optimal behaviours zero-shot. We demonstrate this experimentally in a tabular setting, as well as in a high-dimensional video game and continuous control environment. Finally, we also demonstrate that the performance of skill machines can be improved with regular off-policy reinforcement learning algorithms when optimal behaviours are desired.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.12532v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Geraud Nangue Tasse, Devon Jarvis, Steven James, Benjamin Rosman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnushammer: A Transformer-Based Approach to Premise Selection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.04488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.04488v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel approach to premise selection, a crucial reasoning task in automated theorem proving. Traditionally, symbolic methods that rely on extensive domain knowledge and engineering effort are applied to this task. In contrast, this work demonstrates that contrastive training with the transformer architecture can achieve higher-quality retrieval of relevant premises, without the engineering overhead. Our method, Magnushammer, outperforms the most advanced and widely used automation tool in interactive theorem proving called Sledgehammer. On the PISA and miniF2F benchmarks Magnushammer achieves $59.5\%$ (against $38.3\%$) and $34.0\%$ (against $20.9\%$) success rates, respectively. By combining \method with a language-model-based automated theorem prover, we further improve the state-of-the-art proof success rate from $57.0\%$ to $71.0\%$ on the PISA benchmark using $4$x fewer parameters. Moreover, we develop and open source a novel dataset for premise selection, containing textual representations of (proof state, relevant premise) pairs. To the best of our knowledge, this is the largest available premise selection dataset, and the first one for the Isabelle proof assistant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.04488v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maciej Miku{\l}a, Szymon Tworkowski, Szymon Antoniak, Bartosz Piotrowski, Albert Qiaochu Jiang, Jin Peng Zhou, Christian Szegedy, {\L}ukasz Kuci\'nski, Piotr Mi{\l}o\'s, Yuhuai Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Llemma: An Open Language Model For Mathematics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.10631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.10631v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present Llemma, a large language model for mathematics. We continue pretraining Code Llama on the Proof-Pile-2, a mixture of scientific papers, web data containing mathematics, and mathematical code, yielding Llemma. On the MATH benchmark Llemma outperforms all known open base models, as well as the unreleased Minerva model suite on an equi-parameter basis. Moreover, Llemma is capable of tool use and formal theorem proving without any further finetuning. We openly release all artifacts, including 7 billion and 34 billion parameter models, the Proof-Pile-2, and code to replicate our experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.10631v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhangir Azerbayev, Hailey Schoelkopf, Keiran Paster, Marco Dos Santos, Stephen McAleer, Albert Q. Jiang, Jia Deng, Stella Biderman, Sean Welleck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Opposites of weak $\omega$-categories and the suspension and hom adjunction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.01611</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.01611v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We define inductively the opposites of a weak globular $\omega$\-category with respect to a set of dimensions, and we show that the properties of being free on a globular set or a computad are preserved under forming opposites. We then provide a new description of the hom functor on $\omega$\-categories, and we show that it admits a left adjoint that we construct explicitly and call the suspension functor. We also show that the hom functor preserves the property of being free on computad, and that the opposites of a hom $\omega$\-category are hom $\omega$\-categories of opposites of the original $\omega$\-category.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.01611v2</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thibaut Benjamin, Ioannis Markakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
