<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.LO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.LO</link>
    <description>cs.LO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.LO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 05:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Stable Andrews-Curtis trivialization of AK(3) revisited. A case study using automated deduction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18601v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent work by Shehper et al. (2024) demonstrated that the well-known Akbulut-Kirby AK(3) balanced presentation of the trivial group is stably AC-equivalent to the trivial presentation. This result eliminates AK(3) as a potential counterexample to the stable Andrews-Curtis conjecture. In this paper, we present an alternative proof of this result using an automated deduction approach. We provide several transformation sequences, derived from two different proofs generated by the automated theorem prover Prover9, that certify the stable AC-equivalence of AK(3) and the trivial presentation. We conclude by proposing a challenge to develop computational methods for searching stable AC-transformations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18601v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexei Lisitsa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RTAMT -- Runtime Robustness Monitors with Application to CPS and Robotics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18608</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18608v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we present Real-Time Analog Monitoring Tool (RTAMT), a tool for quantitative monitoring of Signal Temporal Logic (STL) specifications. The library implements a flexible architecture that supports: (1) various environments connected by an Application Programming Interface (API) in Python, (2) various flavors of temporal logic specification and robustness notion such as STL, including an interface-aware variant that distinguishes between input and output variables, and (3) discrete-time and dense-time interpretation of STL with generation of online and offline monitors. We specifically focus on robotics and Cyber-Physical Systems (CPSs) applications, showing how to integrate RTAMT with (1) the Robot Operating System (ROS) and (2) MATLAB/Simulink environments. We evaluate the tool by demonstrating several use scenarios involving service robotic and avionic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18608v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/S10009-023-00720-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Int. J. Softw. Tools Technol. Transf. 26(1): 79-99 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tomoya Yamaguchi, Bardh Hoxha, Dejan Nickovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deeply Optimizing the SAT Solver for the IC3 Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18612v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The IC3 algorithm, also known as PDR, is a SAT-based model checking algorithm that has significantly influenced the field in recent years due to its efficiency, scalability, and completeness. It utilizes SAT solvers to solve a series of SAT queries associated with relative induction. Based on our observations of the unique characteristics of SAT queries in IC3, this paper introduces GipSAT, a lightweight SAT solver specifically optimized for IC3. By observing that SAT queries do not necessarily require decisions on all variables, GipSAT calculates a subset of variables that need to be decided before each solving, while ensuring that the result remains unaffected. By observing that the overhead of binary heap operations in VSIDS is not negligible, GipSAT utilizes buckets instead of binary heap to achieve constant-time operations. GipSAT supports temporary clauses without the need to allocate a new activation variable before each solving, thus eliminating the need to reset solvers. The comprehensive evaluation demonstrates a significant performance improvement achieved by GipSAT. When compared to Minisat, GipSAT achieves an average speedup of 3.61 times in solving time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18612v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuheng Su, Qiusong Yang, Yiwei Ci, Yingcheng Li, Tianjun Bu, Ziyu Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Comprehensive Survey of the Lean 4 Theorem Prover: Architecture, Applications, and Advances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18639v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This comprehensive survey examines Lean 4, a state-of-the-art interactive theorem prover and functional programming language. We analyze its architectural design, type system, metaprogramming capabilities, and practical applications in formal verification and mathematics. Through detailed comparisons with other proof assistants and extensive case studies, we demonstrate Lean 4's unique advantages in proof automation, performance, and usability. The paper also explores recent developments in its ecosystem, including libraries, tools, and educational applications, providing insights into its growing impact on formal methods and mathematical formalization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18639v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.PL</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xichen Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Complexity of Fragments of Second-Order HyperLTL</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19046</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19046v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We settle the complexity of satisfiability, finite-state satisfiability, and model-checking for several fragments of second-order HyperLTL, which extends HyperLTL with quantification over sets of traces: they are all in the analytical hierarchy and beyond</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19046v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ga\"etan Regaud, Martin Zimmermann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Projective Presentations of Lex Modalities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19187</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19187v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Modalities in homotopy type theory are used to create and access subuniverses of a given type universe. These have significant applications throughout mathematics and computer science, and in particular can be used to create universes in which certain logical principles are true. We define presentations of topological modalities, which act as an internalisation of the notion of a Grothendieck topology. A specific presentation of a modality gives access to a surprising amount of computational information, such as explicit methods of determining membership of the subuniverse via internal sheaf conditions. Furthermore, assuming all terms of the presentation satisfy the axiom of choice, we are able to describe generic and powerful computational tools for modalities. This assumption is validated for presentations given by representables in presheaf categories. We deduce a local choice principle, and an internal reconstruction of Kripke-Joyal style reasoning. We use the local choice principle to show how to relate cohomology between universes, showing that a certain class of abelian groups has cohomolgoy stable between universes. We apply the methods to a prominent example, a type theory axiomatising the classifying topos of an algebraic theory, which specialises to give type theories for synthetic algebraic geometry and synthetic higher category theory.We apply the sheaf conditions to show that several presentations of interest are subcanonical, and apply the cohomology methods to show that quasi-coherent modules have cohomology stable between the Zariski, \'etale and fppf toposes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19187v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark Damuni Williams</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Logical Modalities within the European AI Act: An Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19112v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The paper presents a comprehensive analysis of the European AI Act in terms of its logical modalities, with the aim of preparing its formal representation, for example, within the logic-pluralistic Knowledge Engineering Framework and Methodology (LogiKEy). LogiKEy develops computational tools for normative reasoning based on formal methods, employing Higher-Order Logic (HOL) as a unifying meta-logic to integrate diverse logics through shallow semantic embeddings. This integration is facilitated by Isabelle/HOL, a proof assistant tool equipped with several automated theorem provers. The modalities within the AI Act and the logics suitable for their representation are discussed. For a selection of these logics, embeddings in HOL are created, which are then used to encode sample paragraphs. Initial experiments evaluate the suitability of these embeddings for automated reasoning, and highlight key challenges on the way to more robust reasoning capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19112v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lara Lawniczak, Christoph Benzm\"uller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the horizontal compression of dag-derivations in minimal purely implicational logic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.02300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.02300v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This report defines (plain) Dag-like derivations in the purely implicational fragment of minimal logic $M_{\supset}$. Introduce the horizontal collapsing set of rules and the algorithm {\bf HC}. Explain why {\bf HC} can transform any polynomial height-bounded tree-like proof of a $M_{\supset}$ tautology into a smaller dag-like proof. Sketch a proof that {\bf HC} preserves the soundness of any tree-like ND in $M_{\supset}$ in its dag-like version after the horizontal collapsing application. We show some experimental results about applying the compression method to a class of (huge) propositional proofs and an example, with non-hamiltonian graphs, for qualitative analysis. The contributions include the comprehensive presentation of the set of horizontal compression (HC), the (sketch) of the proof that HC rules preserve soundness and the demonstration that the compressed dag-like proofs are polynomially upper-bounded when the submitted tree-like proof is height and foundation poly-bounded. Finally, in the appendix, we outline an algorithm that verifies in polynomial time on the size of the dag-like proofs whether they are valid proofs of their conclusions.In the conclusion we discuss what part of the formal results on the HC-compressed dag-like proofs have been proved with the use of Interactive Theorem Prover assistance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.02300v5</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Part of a previous version of this compression algorithm was published in Studia Logica 107(1), pp.55-83, 2019. Part of the paper was published in pre-proceedings of LSFA2022</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Edward Hermann Haeusler, Jos\'e Fl\'avio Cavalcante Barros Junior,  Robinson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synthesis of Temporal Causality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10912v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present an automata-based algorithm to synthesize omega-regular causes for omega-regular effects on executions of a reactive system, such as counterexamples uncovered by a model checker. Our theory is a generalization of temporal causality, which has recently been proposed as a framework for drawing causal relationships between trace properties on a given trace. So far, algorithms exist only for verifying a single causal relationship and, as an extension, cause synthesis through enumeration, which is complete only for a small fragment of effect properties. This work presents the first complete cause-synthesis algorithm for the class of omega-regular effects. We show that in this case, causes are guaranteed to be omega-regular themselves and can be computed as, e.g., nondeterministic B\"uchi automata. We demonstrate the practical feasibility of this algorithm with a prototype tool and evaluate its performance for cause synthesis and cause checking.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10912v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-031-65633-0_5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Computer Aided Verification: 36th International Conference, CAV 2024, Proceedings, Part III, Lecture Notes in Computer Science, vol 14683, Springer</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bernd Finkbeiner, Hadar Frenkel, Niklas Metzger, Julian Siber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pantograph: A Machine-to-Machine Interaction Interface for Advanced Theorem Proving, High Level Reasoning, and Data Extraction in Lean 4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16429v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Machine-assisted theorem proving refers to the process of conducting structured reasoning to automatically generate proofs for mathematical theorems. Recently, there has been a surge of interest in using machine learning models in conjunction with proof assistants to perform this task. In this paper, we introduce Pantograph, a tool that provides a versatile interface to the Lean 4 proof assistant and enables efficient proof search via powerful search algorithms such as Monte Carlo Tree Search. In addition, Pantograph enables high-level reasoning by enabling a more robust handling of Lean 4's inference steps. We provide an overview of Pantograph's architecture and features. We also report on an illustrative use case: using machine learning models and proof sketches to prove Lean 4 theorems. Pantograph's innovative features pave the way for more advanced machine learning models to perform complex proof searches and high-level reasoning, equipping future researchers to design more versatile and powerful theorem provers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16429v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leni Aniva, Chuyue Sun, Brando Miranda, Clark Barrett, Sanmi Koyejo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Alternation Hierarchy of First-Order Logic on Words is Decidable</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14899v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that for any $i &gt; 0$, it is decidable, given a regular language, whether it is expressible in the $\Sigma_i[&lt;]$ fragment of first-order logic FO[&lt;]. This settles a question open since 1971.
  Our main technical result relies on the notion of polynomial closure of a class of languages $\mathcal{V}$, that is, finite unions of languages of the form $L_0a_1L_1\cdots a_nL_n$ where each $a_i$ is a letter and each $L_i$ a language of $\mathcal{V}$. We show that if a class $\mathcal{V}$ of regular languages with some closure properties (namely, a positive variety) has a decidable separation problem, then so does its polynomial closure Pol($\mathcal{V}$). The resulting algorithm for Pol($\mathcal{V}$) has time complexity that is exponential in the time complexity for $\mathcal{V}$ and we propose a natural conjecture that would lead to a polynomial time blowup instead.
  Corollaries include the decidability of half levels of the dot-depth hierarchy and the group-based concatenation hierarchy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14899v2</guid>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Corentin Barloy, Micha\"el Cadilhac, Charles Paperman, Howard Straubing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>String Diagrams for Graded Monoidal Theories with an Application to Imprecise Probability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18404</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18404v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this technical report we introduce string diagrams for graded symmetric monoidal categories. Our approach includes a definition of graded monoidal theory and the corresponding freely generated syntactic category. Also, we show how an axiomatic presentation for the graded theory may be modularly obtained from one for the grading theory and one for the base category. The Para construction on monoidal actegories is a motivating example for our framework. As a case study, we show how to axiomatize a variant of the graded category ImP, recently introduced by Liell-Cock and Staton to model imprecise probability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18404v2</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ralph Sarkis, Fabio Zanasi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
