<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.LO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.LO</link>
    <description>cs.LO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.LO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 04:00:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Anonymous Public Announcements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12546v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We formalise the notion of an \emph{anonymous public announcement} in the tradition of public announcement logic. Such announcements can be seen as in-between a public announcement from ``the outside" (an announcement of $\phi$) and a public announcement by one of the agents (an announcement of $K_a\phi$): we get more information than just $\phi$, but not (necessarily) about exactly who made it. Even if such an announcement is prima facie anonymous, depending on the background knowledge of the agents it might reveal the identity of the announcer: if I post something on a message board, the information might reveal who I am even if I don't sign my name. Furthermore, like in the Russian Cards puzzle, if we assume that the announcer's intention was to stay anonymous, that in fact might reveal more information. In this paper we first look at the case when no assumption about intentions are made, in which case the logic with an anonymous public announcement operator is reducible to epistemic logic. We then look at the case when we assume common knowledge of the intention to stay anonymous, which is both more complex and more interesting: in several ways it boils down to the notion of a ``safe" announcement (again, similarly to Russian Cards). Main results include formal expressivity results and axiomatic completeness for key logical languages.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12546v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas {\AA}gotnes, Rustam Galimullin, Ken Satoh, Satoshi Tojo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reachability in Geometrically $d$-Dimensional VASS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12302</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12302v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Reachability of vector addition systems with states (VASS) is Ackermann complete~\cite{leroux2021reachability,czerwinski2021reachability}. For $d$-dimensional VASS reachability it is known that the problem is NP-complete~\cite{HaaseKreutzerOuaknineWorrell2009} when $d=1$, PSPACE-complete~\cite{BlondinFinkelGoellerHaaseMcKenzie2015} when $d=2$, and in $\mathbf{F}_d$~\cite{FuYangZheng2024} when $d&gt;2$. A geometrically $d$-dimensional VASS is a $D$-dimensional VASS for some $D\ge d$ such that the space spanned by the displacements of the circular paths admitted in the $D$-dimensional VASS is $d$-dimensional. It is proved that the $\mathbf{F}_d$ upper bounds remain valid for the reachability problem in the geometrically $d$-dimensional VASSes with $d&gt;2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12302v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxi Fu, Yangluo Zheng, Qizhe Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Canonicity for Cost-Aware Logical Framework via Synthetic Tait Computability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12464v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the original work on the cost-aware logical framework by Niu et al., a dependent variant of the call-by-push-value language for cost analysis, the authors conjectured that the canonicity property of the type theory can be succinctly proved via Sterling's synthetic Tait computability. This work resolves the conjecture affirmatively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12464v1</guid>
      <category>cs.PL</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Runming Li, Robert Harper</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Timing via Pinwheel Double Categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12846</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12846v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We discuss string diagrams for timed process theories -- represented by duoidally-graded symmetric strict monoidal categories -- built upon the string diagrams of pinwheel double categories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12846v1</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elena Di Lavore, Mario Rom\'an</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Saturation-Based Unification Algorithm for Higher-Order Rational Patterns</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.07263</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.07263v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Higher-order unification has been shown to be undecidable. Miller discovered the pattern fragment and subsequently showed that higher-order pattern unification is decidable and has most general unifiers. We extend the algorithm to higher-order rational terms (a.k.a. regular B\"{o}hm trees, a form of cyclic $\lambda$-terms) and show that pattern unification on higher-order rational terms is decidable and has most general unifiers. We prove the soundness and completeness of the algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.07263v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.PL</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhibo Chen, Frank Pfenning</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Step Deductive Reasoning Over Natural Language: An Empirical Study on Out-of-Distribution Generalisation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.14000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.14000v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Combining deep learning with symbolic logic reasoning aims to capitalize on the success of both fields and is drawing increasing attention. Inspired by DeepLogic, an end-to-end model trained to perform inference on logic programs, we introduce IMA-GloVe-GA, an iterative neural inference network for multi-step reasoning expressed in natural language. In our model, reasoning is performed using an iterative memory neural network based on RNN with a gated attention mechanism. We evaluate IMA-GloVe-GA on three datasets: PARARULES, CONCEPTRULES V1 and CONCEPTRULES V2. Experimental results show DeepLogic with gated attention can achieve higher test accuracy than DeepLogic and other RNN baseline models. Our model achieves better out-of-distribution generalisation than RoBERTa-Large when the rules have been shuffled. Furthermore, to address the issue of unbalanced distribution of reasoning depths in the current multi-step reasoning datasets, we develop PARARULE-Plus, a large dataset with more examples that require deeper reasoning steps. Experimental results show that the addition of PARARULE-Plus can increase the model's performance on examples requiring deeper reasoning depths. The source code and data are available at https://github.com/Strong-AI-Lab/Multi-Step-Deductive-Reasoning-Over-Natural-Language.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.14000v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiming Bao, Alex Yuxuan Peng, Tim Hartill, Neset Tan, Zhenyun Deng, Michael Witbrock, Jiamou Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The weakness of finding descending sequences in ill-founded linear orders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.11807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.11807v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We explore the Weihrauch degree of the problems ``find a bad sequence in a non-well quasi order'' ($\mathsf{BS}$) and ``find a descending sequence in an ill-founded linear order'' ($\mathsf{DS}$). We prove that $\mathsf{DS}$ is strictly Weihrauch reducible to $\mathsf{BS}$, correcting our mistaken claim in [arXiv:2010.03840]. This is done by separating their respective first-order parts. On the other hand, we show that $\mathsf{BS}$ and $\mathsf{DS}$ have the same finitary and deterministic parts, confirming that $\mathsf{BS}$ and $\mathsf{DS}$ have very similar uniform computational strength. We prove that K\"onig's lemma $\mathsf{KL}$ and the problem $\mathsf{wList}_{2^{\mathbb{N}},\leq\omega}$ of enumerating a given non-empty countable closed subset of $2^{\mathbb{N}}$ are not Weihrauch reducible to $\mathsf{DS}$ or $\mathsf{BS}$, resolving two main open questions raised in [arXiv:2010.03840]. We also answer the question, raised in [arXiv:1804.10968], on the existence of a ``parallel quotient'' operator, and study the behavior of $\mathsf{BS}$ and $\mathsf{DS}$ under the quotient with some known problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.11807v4</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun Le Goh, Arno Pauly, Manlio Valenti</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
