<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.LO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.LO</link>
    <description>cs.LO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.LO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 05:01:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Fast Ramsey Quantifier Elimination in LIRA (with applications to liveness checking)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05323</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05323v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ramsey quantifiers have recently been proposed as a unified framework for handling properties of interests in program verification involving proofs in the form of infinite cliques, which are not expressible in first-order logic. Among others, these include liveness verification and monadic decomposability. We present the tool REAL, which implements an efficient elimination of Ramsey quantifiers in existential linear arithmetic theories over integers (LIA), reals (LRA), and the mixed case (LIRA). The tool supports a convenient input format, which is an extension of SMT-LIB over the aforementioned theories with Ramsey quantifiers. We also demonstrate a substantial speedup from the original prototype. As an application, we provide an automatic translation from FASTer (a tool for verifying reachability over infinite-state systems) output format to our extension of SMT-LIB and show how our tool extends FASTer to liveness checking.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05323v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kilian Lichtner, Pascal Bergstr\"a{\ss}er, Moses Ganardi, Anthony W. Lin, Georg Zetzsche</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\text{C}^2\text{P}$: Featuring Large Language Models with Causal Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18069v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Causal reasoning is one of the primary bottlenecks that Large Language Models (LLMs) must overcome to attain human-level intelligence. Recent studies indicate that LLMs display near-random performance on reasoning tasks. To address this, we introduce the Causal Chain of Prompting ($\text{C}^2\text{P}$), a reasoning framework that aims to equip current LLMs with causal reasoning capabilities as the first framework of its kind operating autonomously without relying on external tools or modules during both the causal learning and reasoning phases. To evaluate the performance of $\text{C}^2\text{P}$, we first demonstrate that reasoning accuracy improved by over $30.7\%$ and $25.9\%$ for GPT-4 Turbo and LLaMA 3.1, respectively, when using our framework, compared to the same models without $\text{C}^2\text{P}$ on a synthetic benchmark dataset. Then, using few-shot learning of the same LLMs with $\text{C}^2\text{P}$, the reasoning accuracy increased by more than $20.05\%$ and $20.89\%$, respectively, with as few as ten examples, compared to the corresponding LLMs without $\text{C}^2\text{P}$ on the same dataset. To evaluate $\text{C}^2\text{P}$ in realistic scenarios, we utilized another benchmark dataset containing natural stories across various fields, including healthcare, medicine, economics, education, social sciences, environmental science, and marketing. The results show improved reasoning when $\text{C}^2\text{P}$ is applied, compared to cases where our framework is not used, which often leads to random and hallucinated responses. By showing the improved performance of few-shot learned GPT-4 Turbo and LLaMA 3.1 with $\text{C}^2\text{P}$, we demonstrate the generalizability of our framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18069v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdolmahdi Bagheri, Matin Alinejad, Mahdi Dehshiri, Kevin Bello, Alireza Akhondi-Asl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Proof-Theoretic Approach to the Semantics of Classical Linear Logic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08349v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Linear logic (LL) is a resource-aware, abstract logic programming language that refines both classical and intuitionistic logic. Linear logic semantics is typically presented in one of two ways: by associating each formula with the set of all contexts that can be used to prove it (e.g. phase semantics) or by assigning meaning directly to proofs (e.g. coherence spaces).
  This work proposes a different perspective on assigning meaning to proofs by adopting a proof-theoretic perspective. More specifically, we employ base-extension semantics (BeS) to characterise proofs through the notion of base support.
  Recent developments have shown that BeS is powerful enough to capture proof-theoretic notions in structurally rich logics such as intuitionistic linear logic. In this paper, we extend this framework to the classical case, presenting a proof-theoretic approach to the semantics of the multiplicative-additive fragment of linear logic (MALL).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08349v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Barroso-Nascimento, Ekaterina Piotrovskaya, Elaine Pimentel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computation by infinite descent made explicit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.22206v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a non-wellfounded proof system for intuitionistic logic extended with inductive and co-inductive definitions, based on a syntax in which fixpoint formulas are annotated with explicit variables for ordinals. We explore the computational content of this system, in particular we introduce a notion of computability and show that every valid proof is computable. As a consequence, we obtain a normalization result for proofs of what we call finitary formulas. A special case of this result is that every proof of a sequent of the appropriate form represents a unique function on natural numbers. Finally, we derive a categorical model from the proof system and show that least and greatest fixpoint formulas correspond to initial algebras and final coalgebras respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.22206v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Enqvist</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher-order Kripke models for intuitionistic and non-classical modal logics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18798v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces higher-order Kripke models, a generalization of standard Kripke models that is remarkably close to Kripke's original idea - both mathematically and conceptually. Standard Kripke models are now considered $0$-ary models, whereas an $n$-ary model for $n &gt; 0$ is a model whose set of objects (''possible worlds'') contains only $(n-1)$-ary Kripke models. Models with infinitely many layers are also considered. This framework is obtained by promoting a radical change of perspective in how modal semantics for non-classical logics are defined: just like classical modalities are obtained through use of an accessibility relation between classical propositional models, non-classical modalities are now obtained through use of an accessibility relation between non-classical propositional models (even when they are Kripke models already). The paper introduces the new models after dealing specifically with the case of intuitionistic modal logic. It is shown that, depending on which intuitionistic $0$-ary propositional models are allowed, we may obtain $1$-ary models equivalent to either birelational models for $IK$ or for a new logic called $MK$. Those $1$-ary models have an intuitive reading that adds to the interpretation of intuitionistic models in terms of ''timelines'' the concept of ''alternative timelines''. More generally, $n$-ary models (for $n &gt; 0$) can be read as defining a concept of ''alternative'' for any interpretation of the $(n-1)$-ary models. The semantic clauses for necessity and possibility of $MK$ are modular and can be used to obtain similar modal semantics for every non-classical logic, each of which can be provided with a similar intuitive reading. After intuitionistic modal logic is dealt with, the general structure of higher-order Kripke Models and some of its variants are defined, and a series of conjectures about their properties are stated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18798v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Barroso-Nascimento</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Formalizing the notions of non-interactive and interactive algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19037</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19037v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: An earlier paper gives an account of a quest for a satisfactory formalization of the classical informal notion of an algorithm. That notion only covers algorithms that are deterministic and non-interactive. In this paper, an attempt is made to generalize the results of that quest first to a notion of an algorithm that covers both deterministic and non-deterministic algorithms that are non-interactive and then further to a notion of an algorithm that covers both deterministic and non-deterministic algorithms that are interactive. The notions of an non-interactive proto-algorithm and an interactive proto-algorithm are introduced. Non-interactive algorithms and interactive algorithms are expected to be equivalence classes of non-interactive proto-algorithms and interactive proto-algorithms, respectively, under an appropriate equivalence relation. On both non-interactive proto-algorithms and interactive proto-algorithms, three equivalence relations are defined. Two of them are deemed to be bounds for an appropriate equivalence relation and the third is likely an appropriate one.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19037v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. A. Middelburg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparing and Contrasting Arrow's Impossibility Theorem and G\"odel's Incompleteness Theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.06589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.06589v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Incomputability results in formal logic and the Theory of Computation (i.e., incompleteness and undecidability) have deep implications for the foundations of mathematics and computer science. Likewise, Social Choice Theory, a branch of Welfare Economics, contains various impossibility results that place limits on the potential fairness, rationality and consistency of social decision-making processes. However, a relationship between the fields' most seminal results: G\"odel's First Incompleteness Theorem of Formal Logic, and Arrow's Impossibility Theorem in Social Choice Theory is lacking. In this paper, we address this gap by introducing a general mathematical object called a Self-Reference System. Correspondences between the two theorems are formalised by abstracting well-known diagonalisation and fixed-point arguments, and consistency and completeness properties of provability predicates in the language of Self-Reference Systems. Nevertheless, we show that the mechanisms generating Arrovian impossibility and G\"odelian incompleteness have subtle differences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.06589v3</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ori Livson, Mikhail Prokopenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
