<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.LO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.LO</link>
    <description>cs.LO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.LO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 01:43:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Synthesiz3 This: an SMT-Based Approach for Synthesis with Uncomputable Symbols</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16536v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Program synthesis is the task of automatically constructing a program conforming to a given specification. In this paper we focus on synthesis of single-invocation recursion-free functions conforming to a specification given as a logical formula in the presence of uncomputable symbols (i.e., symbols used in the specification but not allowed in the resulting function). We approach the problem via SMT-solving methods: we present a quantifier elimination algorithm using model-based projections for both total and partial function synthesis, working with theories of uninterpreted functions and linear arithmetic and their combination. For this purpose we also extend model-based projection to produce witnesses for these theories. Further, we present procedures tailored for the case of uniquely determined solutions. We implemented a prototype of the algorithms using the SMT-solver Z3, demonstrating their practicality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16536v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Petra Hozzov\'a, Nikolaj Bj{\o}rner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Query Algorithms for Relational Structures Based on Homomorphism Counts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16567v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A query algorithm based on homomorphism counts is a procedure to decide membership for a class of finite relational structures using only homomorphism count queries. A left query algorithm can ask the number of homomorphisms from any structure to the input structure and a right query algorithm can ask the number of homomorphisms from the input structure to any other structure. We systematically compare the expressive power of different types of left or right query algorithms, including non-adaptive query algorithms, adaptive query algorithms that can ask a bounded number of queries, and adaptive query algorithms that can ask an unbounded number of queries. We also consider query algorithms where the homomorphism counting is done over the Boolean semiring $\mathbb{B}$, meaning that only the existence of a homomorphism is recorded, not the precise number of them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16567v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Balder ten Cate, Phokion G. Kolaitis, Arnar \'A. Kristj\'ansson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decidability Problems for Micro-Stipula</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16703v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Micro-Stipula is a stateful calculus in which clauses can be activated either through interactions with the external environment or by the evaluation of time expressions. Despite the apparent simplicity of its syntax and operational model, the combination of state evolution, time reasoning, and nondeterminism gives rise to significant analytical challenges. In particular, we show that determining whether a clause is never executed is undecidable. We formally prove that this undecidability result holds even for syntactically restricted fragments: namely, the time-ahead fragment, where all time expressions are strictly positive, and the instantaneous fragment, where all time expressions evaluate to zero. On the other hand, we identify a decidable subfragment: within the instantaneous fragment, reachability becomes decidable when the initial states of functions and events are disjoint.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16703v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giorgio Delzanno, Cosimo Laneve, Arnaud Sangnier, Gianluigi Zavattaro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Expressive Coalgebraic Modal Logic for Cellular Automata</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16735v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cellular automata provide models of parallel computation based on cells, whose connectivity is given by an action of a monoid on the cells. At each step in the computation, every cell is decorated with a state that evolves in discrete steps according to a local update rule, which determines the next state of a cell based on its neighbour's states. In this paper, we consider a coalgebraic view on cellular automata, which does not require typical restrictions, such as uniform neighbourhood connectivity and uniform local rules. Using the coalgebraic view, we devise a behavioural equivalence for cellular automata and a modal logic to reason about their behaviour. We then prove a Hennessy-Milner style theorem, which states that pairs of cells satisfy the same modal formulas exactly if they are identified under cellular behavioural equivalence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16735v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henning Basold, Chase Ford, Lulof Pir\'ee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetric Proofs in the Ideal Proof System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16820v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the Ideal Proof System (IPS) introduced by Grochow and Pitassi and pose the question of which tautologies admit symmetric proofs, and of what complexity. The symmetry requirement in proofs is inspired by recent work establishing lower bounds in other symmetric models of computation. We link the existence of symmetric IPS proofs to the expressive power of logics such as fixed-point logic with counting and Choiceless Polynomial Time, specifically regarding the graph isomorphism problem. We identify relationships and tradeoffs between the symmetry of proofs and other parameters of IPS proofs such as size, degree and linearity. We study these on a number of standard families of tautologies from proof complexity and finite model theory such as the pigeonhole principle, the subset sum problem and the Cai-F\"urer-Immerman graphs, exhibiting non-trivial upper bounds on the size of symmetric IPS proofs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16820v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anuj Dawar, Erich Gr\"adel, Leon Kullmann, Benedikt Pago</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Formal Verification of Blockchain Nonforking in DAG-Based BFT Consensus with Dynamic Stake</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16853v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Blockchain consensus protocols enable participants to agree on consistent views of the blockchain that may be ahead or behind relative to each other but do not fork into different chains. A number of recently popular Byzantine-fault-tolerant (BFT) protocols first construct a directed acyclic graph (DAG) that partially orders transactions, then linearize the DAG into a blockchain that totally orders transactions. The definitions and correctness proofs of these DAG-based protocols typically assume that the set of participants is fixed, which is impractical in long-lived blockchains. Additionally, only a few of those proofs have been machine-checked, uncovering errors in some published proofs. We developed a formal model of a DAG-based BFT protocol with dynamic stake, where participants can join and leave at every block, with stake used to weigh decisions in the protocol. We formally proved that blockchains never fork in the model, also clarifying how BFT bounds on faulty participants generalize to these highly dynamic sets of participants. Our model and proofs are formalized in the ACL2 theorem prover, apply to arbitrarily long executions and arbitrarily large system states, and are verified in 1 minute by ACL2.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16853v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Coglio, Eric McCarthy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Logic and Concepts in the 2-category of Topoi</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16690v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We use Kan injectivity to axiomatise concepts in the 2-category of topoi. We showcase the expressivity of this language through many examples, and we establish some aspects of the formal theory of Kan extension in this 2-category (pointwise Kan extensions, fully faithful morphisms, etc.). We use this technology to introduce fragments of geometric logic, and we accommodate essentially algebraic, disjunctive, regular, and coherent logic in our framework, together with some more exotic examples. We show that each fragment $\mathcal{H}$ in our sense identifies a lax-idempotent (relative) pseudomonad $\mathsf{T}^{\mathcal{H}}$ on $\mathsf{lex}$, the $2$-category of finitely complete categories. We show that the algebras for $\mathsf{T}^{\mathcal{H}}$ admit a notion of classifying topos, for which we deliver several Diaconescu-type results. The construction of classifying topoi allows us to define conceptually complete fragments of geometric logic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16690v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ivan Di Liberti, Lingyuan Ye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Categorical Treatment of Open Linear Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03934</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03934v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: An open stochastic system \`a la Jan Willems is a system affected by two qualitatively different kinds of uncertainty: one is probabilistic fluctuation, and the other one is nondeterminism caused by a fundamental lack of information. We present a formalization of open stochastic systems in the language of category theory. Central to this is the notion of copartiality which models how the lack of information propagates through a system (corresponding to the coarseness of sigma-algebras in Willems' work). As a concrete example, we study extended Gaussian distributions, which combine Gaussian probability with nondeterminism and correspond precisely to Willems' notion of Gaussian linear systems. We describe them both as measure-theoretic and abstract categorical entities, which enables us to rigorously describe a variety of phenomena like noisy physical laws and uninformative priors in Bayesian statistics. The category of extended Gaussian maps can be seen as a mutual generalization of Gaussian probability and linear relations, which connects the literature on categorical probability with ideas from control theory like signal-flow diagrams.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03934v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dario Stein, Richard Samuelson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Formalizing equivalences without tears</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11501v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This expository note describes two convenient techniques in the context of homotopy type theory for proving and formalizing that a given map is an equivalence. The first technique decomposes the map as a series of basic equivalences, while the second refines this approach using the 3-for-2 property of equivalences. The techniques are illustrated by proving a basic result in synthetic homotopy theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11501v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom de Jong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence Laws for Extensions of First-Order Logic with Averaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14270v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For many standard models of random structure, first-order logic sentences exhibit a convergence phenomenon on random inputs. The most well-known example is for random graphs with constant edge probability, where the probabilities of first-order sentences converge to 0 or 1. In other cases, such as certain ``sparse random graph'' models, the probabilities of sentences converge, although not necessarily to 0 or 1. In this work we deal with extensions of first-order logic with aggregate operators, variations of averaging. These logics will consist of real-valued terms, and we allow arbitrary Lipschitz functions to be used as ``connectives''. We show that some of the well-known convergence laws extend to this setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14270v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sam Adam-Day, Michael Benedikt, Alberto Larrauri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sound and Complete Invariant-Based Heap Encodings (Technical Report)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.15844v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Verification of programs operating on mutable, heap-allocated data structures poses significant challenges due to potentially unbounded structures like linked lists and trees. In this paper, we present a novel relational heap encoding leveraging uninterpreted predicates and prophecy variables, reducing heap verification tasks to satisfiability checks over integers in constrained Horn clauses (CHCs). To the best of our knowledge, our approach is the first invariant-based method that achieves both soundness and completeness for heap-manipulating programs. We provide formal proofs establishing the correctness of our encodings. Through an experimental evaluation we demonstrate that our method significantly extends the capability of existing CHC-based verification tools, allowing automatic verification of programs with heap previously unreachable by state-of-the-art tools.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.15844v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zafer Esen, Philipp R\"ummer, Tjark Weber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Practicable Algorithms for Rewriting Graph Queries beyond DL-Lite</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18181v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Despite the many advantages that ontology-based data access (OBDA) has brought to a range of application domains, state-of-the-art OBDA systems still do not support popular graph database management systems such as Neo4j. Algorithms for query rewriting focus on languages like conjunctive queries and their unions, which are fragments of first-order logic and were developed for relational data. Such query languages are poorly suited for querying graph data. Moreover, they also limit the expressiveness of the ontology languages that admit rewritings, restricting them to those where the data complexity of reasoning is not higher than it is in first-order logic. In this paper, we propose a technique for rewriting a family of navigational queries for a suitably restricted fragment of ELHI that extends DL-Lite and that is NL-complete in data complexity. We implemented a proof-of-concept prototype that rewrites into Cypher queries, and tested it on a real-world cognitive neuroscience use case with promising results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18181v3</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bianca L\"ohnert, Nikolaus Augsten, Cem Okulmus, Magdalena Ortiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error Detection and Constraint Recovery in Hierarchical Multi-Label Classification without Prior Knowledge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15192v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent advances in Hierarchical Multi-label Classification (HMC), particularly neurosymbolic-based approaches, have demonstrated improved consistency and accuracy by enforcing constraints on a neural model during training. However, such work assumes the existence of such constraints a-priori. In this paper, we relax this strong assumption and present an approach based on Error Detection Rules (EDR) that allow for learning explainable rules about the failure modes of machine learning models. We show that these rules are not only effective in detecting when a machine learning classifier has made an error but also can be leveraged as constraints for HMC, thereby allowing the recovery of explainable constraints even if they are not provided. We show that our approach is effective in detecting machine learning errors and recovering constraints, is noise tolerant, and can function as a source of knowledge for neurosymbolic models on multiple datasets, including a newly introduced military vehicle recognition dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15192v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Shay Kricheli, Khoa Vo, Aniruddha Datta, Spencer Ozgur, Paulo Shakarian</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
