<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.LO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.LO</link>
    <description>cs.LO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.LO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 05:00:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Computing Supported Models via Transformation to Stable Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05437</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05437v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Answer Set Programming (ASP) with stable model semantics has proven highly effective for knowledge representation and reasoning. However, the minimality requirement of stable models can be restrictive for applications requiring exploration of non-minimal but logically consistent solution spaces. Supported models, introduced by Apt, Blair, and Walker in 1988, relax this minimality constraint while maintaining a support condition ensuring every true atom is justified by some rule.
  Despite their theoretical significance, supported models lack practical computational tools integrated with modern ASP solvers. We present a novel transformation-based method enabling computation of supported models using standard ASP infrastructure. Our approach transforms any ground logic program into an equivalent program whose stable models correspond exactly to the supported models of the original program. We implement this transformation for Clingo, providing the first practical tool for computing supported models with state-of-the-art ASP solvers.
  We demonstrate applications in software verification, medical diagnosis, and planning where supported models enable valuable exploratory reasoning capabilities beyond those provided by stable models. We also provide an empirical evaluation to justify the practical utility of our approach compared to established methods. Our implementation is publicly available and compatible with standard ASP syntax.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05437v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fang Li, Gopal Gupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Formalizing Polynomial Laws and the Universal Divided Power Algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05750</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05750v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The goal of this paper is to present an ongoing formalization, in the framework provided by the Lean/Mathlib mathematical library, of the construction by Roby (1965) of the universal divided power algebra. This is an analogue, in the theory of divided powers, of the classical algebra of polynomials. It is a crucial tool in the development of crystalline cohomology; it is also used in $p$-adic Hodge theory to define the crystalline period ring. As an algebra, this universal divided power algebra has a fairly simple definition that shows that it is a graded algebra. The main difficulty in Roby's theorem lies in constructing a divided power structure on its augmentation ideal. To that aim, Roby identified the graded pieces with another universal structure: homogeneous polynomial laws.We formalize the first steps of the theory of polynomial laws and show how future work will allow to complete the formalization of the above-mentioned divided power structure. We report on various difficulties that appeared in this formalization: taking care of universes, extending to semirings some aspects of the Mathlib library, and coping with several instances of "invisible mathematics".</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05750v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3779031.3779108</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Antoine Chambert-Loir, Mar\'ia In\'es de Frutos-Fern\'andez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skolemization and Decidability of the Bernays-Schoenfinkel Class in Goedel Logics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05772v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 1928, Bernays and Schoenfinkel proved the decidability of prenex sentences whose matrices contain no function symbols, now known as the Bernays-Schoenfinkel (BS) class. We investigate the decidability of the BS class for all Goedel logics. Our validity argument relies on the fact that Skolemization works for prenex Goedel logics, while 1-satisfiability follows from structural properties of prenex formulas. We show that validity and 1-satisfiability for the BS class are decidable in every Goedel logic, and that these properties persist across all infinite Goedel logics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05772v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mariami Gamsakhurdia, Matthias Baaz, Anela Lolic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complex Bounded Operators in Isabelle/HOL</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05878v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Functional analysis, especially the theory of Hilbert spaces and of operators on these, form an important area in mathematics. We formalized the Isabelle/HOL library Complex_Bounded_Operators containing a large amount of theorems about complex Hilbert spaces and (bounded) operators on these.
  Specifically, we formalize the properties complex vector spaces, inner product (and Hilbert) spaces, one-dimensional spaces, bounded operators, adjoints, unitaries, projections, extensions of bounded operators (BLT-theorem), positive operators, square-summable sequences and much more.
  Additionally, we provide support for code generation in the finite-dimensional case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05878v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dominique Unruh, Jos\'e Manuel Rodr\'iguez Caballero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete Homotopy and Promise Constraint Satisfaction Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05120</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05120v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Promise Constraint Satisfaction Problem (PCSP for short) is a generalization of the well-studied Constraint Satisfaction Problem (CSP). The PCSP has its roots in such classic problems as the Approximate Graph Coloring and the $(1+\varepsilon)$-Satisfiability problems. The area received much attention recently with multiple approaches developed to design efficient algorithms for restricted versions of the PCSP, and to prove its hardness.
  One such approach uses methods from Algebraic Topology to relate the complexity of the PCSP to the structure of the fundamental group of certain topological spaces. In this paper, we attempt to develop a discrete analog of this approach by replacing topological structures with combinatorial constructions and some basic group-theoretic concepts. We consider the `one-dimensional' case of the approach. We introduce and prove the basics of the framework, show how it is related to the complexity of the PCSP, and obtain several hardness results, including the existing ones, as applications of our approach. The main hope, however, is that this discrete variant of the topological approach can be generalized to the `multi-dimensional' case needed for further progress.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05120v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arash Beikmohammadi, Andrei A. Bulatov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Verified VCG and Verified Compiler for Dafny</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05262v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Dafny is a verification-aware programming language that comes with a compiler and static program verifier. However, neither the compiler nor the verifier is proved correct; in fact, soundness bugs have been found in both tools. This paper shows that the aforementioned Dafny tools can be developed with foundational correctness guarantees. We present a functional big-step semantics for an imperative subset of Dafny and, based on this semantics, a verified verification condition generator (VCG) and a verified compiler for Dafny. The subset of Dafny we have formalized includes mutually recursive method calls, while loops, and arrays -- these language features are significant enough to cover challenging examples such as McCarthy's 91 function and array-based programs that are used when teaching Dafny. The verified VCG allows one to prove functional correctness of annotated Dafny programs, while the verified compiler can be used to compile verified Dafny programs to CakeML programs. From there, one can obtain executable machine code via the (already verified) CakeML compiler, all while provably maintaining the functional correctness guarantees that were proved for the source-level Dafny programs. Our work has been mechanized in the HOL4 theorem prover.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05262v1</guid>
      <category>cs.PL</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3779031.3779092</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Nezamabadi, Magnus O. Myreen, Yong Kiam Tan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parajudica: An RDF-Based Reasoner and Metamodel for Multi-Framework Context-Dependent Data Compliance Assessments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05453v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Motivated by the challenges of implementing policy-based data access control (PBAC) under multiple simultaneously applicable compliance frameworks, we present Parajudica, an open, modular, and extensible RDF/SPARQL-based rule system for evaluating context-dependent data compliance status. We demonstrate the utility of this resource and accompanying metamodel through application to existing legal frameworks and industry standards, offering insights for comparative framework analysis. Applications include compliance policy enforcement, compliance monitoring, data discovery, and risk assessment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05453v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luc Moreau (University of Sussex, Brighton, United Kingdom), Alfred Rossi (Immuta Research, Boston, Massachusetts, USA), Sophie Stalla-Bourdillon (Brussels Privacy Hub, Vrije Universiteit Brussel, Brussels, Belgium)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Impact of the Communication Model on Realisability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05609</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05609v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multiparty Session Types (MPST) provide a type-theoretic foundation for specifying and verifying communication protocols in distributed systems. MPST rely on the notion of global type which specifies the global behaviour and local types, which are the projections of the global behaviour onto each local participant. A central notion in MPST is realisability - whether local implementations derived from a global specification correctly realise the intended protocol under a given communication model. While realisability has been extensively studied under peer-to-peer semantics, it remains poorly understood in alternative communication models such as bag-based, causally ordered, or synchronous communications. In this paper, we develop a unified framework for reasoning about realisability and subtyping across a spectrum of communication models. We show that the communication model does not impact the notion of subtyping, but that it impacts the notion of realisability. We introduce several decision procedures for subtyping checking and realisability checking with complexities ranging from NLOGSPACE to EXPSPACE depending on the assumptions made on the global types, in particular depending on their complementability and the size of a given complement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05609v1</guid>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cinzia Di Giusto (Laboratoire I3S - COMRED, I3S), Etienne Lozes (I3S, Laboratoire I3S - COMRED, SCALE), Pascal Urso (I3S)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Executing Discrete/Continuous Declarative Process Specifications via Complex Event Processing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05653</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05653v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Traditional Business Process Management (BPM) focuses on discrete events and fails to incorporate critical continuous sensor data in cyber-physical environments. Hybrid declarative specifications, utilizing Signal Temporal Logic (STL), address this limitation by allowing constraints over both discrete events and real-valued signals. However, existing work has been limited to monitoring and post-hoc conformance checking. This paper introduces a novel Complex Event Processing (CEP)-based execution architecture that enables the real-time execution and enforcement of hybrid declarative models. Our three-layer approach integrates STL-inspired predicates into the execution flow, allowing the system to actively trigger activities and enforce process boundaries based on continuous sensor behavior. This approach bridges the gap between hybrid specification and operational control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05653v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Sch\"onig, Leo Poss, Fabrizio Maria Maggi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extended Resolution Clause Learning via Dual Implication Points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14190v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a new extended resolution clause learning (ERCL) algorithm, implemented as part of a conflict-driven clause-learning (CDCL) SAT solver, wherein new variables are dynamically introduced as definitions for {\it Dual Implication Points} (DIPs) in the implication graph constructed by the solver at runtime. DIPs are generalizations of unique implication points and can be informally viewed as a pair of dominator nodes, from the decision variable at the highest decision level to the conflict node, in an implication graph. We perform extensive experimental evaluation to establish the efficacy of our ERCL method, implemented as part of the MapleLCM SAT solver and dubbed xMapleLCM, against several leading solvers including the baseline MapleLCM, as well as CDCL solvers such as Kissat 3.1.1, CryptoMiniSat 5.11, and SBVA+CaDiCaL, the winner of SAT Competition 2023. We show that xMapleLCM outperforms these solvers on Tseitin and XORified formulas. We further compare xMapleLCM with GlucoseER, a system that implements extended resolution in a different way, and provide a detailed comparative analysis of their performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14190v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sam Buss, Jonathan Chung, Vijay Ganesh, Albert Oliveras</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Derivatives on Graphs for the Positive Calculus of Relations with Transitive Closure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08236</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08236v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that the equational theory of the positive calculus of relations with transitive closure (PCoR*) is EXPSPACE-complete. Here, PCoR* terms consist of the following standard operators on binary relations: identity, empty, universality, union, intersection, composition, converse, and reflexive transitive closure (so, PCoR* terms subsume Kleene algebra and allegory terms as fragments). Additionally, we show that the equational theory of PCoR* extended with tests and nominals (in hybrid logic) is still EXPSPACE-complete; moreover, it is PSPACE-complete for its intersection-free fragment.
  To this end, we design derivatives on graphs by extending derivatives on words for regular expressions. The derivatives give a finite automata construction on path decompositions, like those on words. Because the equational theory has a linearly bounded pathwidth model property, we can decide the equational theory of PCoR* using these automata.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08236v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoshiki Nakamura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Cut-Free Sequent Calculus for the Analysis of Finite-Trace Properties in Concurrent Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.03164v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We address the problem of identifying a proof-theoretic framework that enables a compositional analysis of finite-trace properties in concurrent systems, with a particular focus on those specified via prefix-closure. To this end, we investigate the interaction of a prefix-closure operator and its residual (with respect to set-theoretic inclusion) with language intersection, union, and concatenation, and introduce the variety of closure $\ell$-monoids as a minimal algebraic abstraction of finite-trace properties to be conveniently described within an analytic proof system. Closure $\ell$-monoids are division-free reducts of distributive residuated lattices equipped with a forward diamond/backward box residuated pair of unary modal operators, where the diamond is a topological closure operator satisfying $\Diamond(x \cdot y) \leq \Diamond x \cdot \Diamond y$. As a logical counterpart to these structures, we present $\mathsf{LMC}$, a Gentzen-style system based on the division-free fragment of the Distributive Full Lambek Calculus. In $\mathsf{LMC}$, structural terms are built from formulas using Belnap-style structural operators for monoid multiplication, meet, and diamond. The rules for the modalities and the structural diamond are taken from Moortgat's system $\mathsf{NL}(\Diamond)$. We show that the calculus is sound and complete with respect to the variety of closure $\ell$-monoids and that it admits cut elimination.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.03164v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ludovico Fusco, Alessandro Aldini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Eckmann-Hilton: Commutativity in Higher Categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16465</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16465v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that in a weak globular $\omega$-category, all composition operations are equivalent and commutative for cells with sufficiently degenerate boundary, which can be considered a higher-dimensional generalisation of the Eckmann-Hilton argument. Our results are formulated constructively in a type-theoretic presentation of $\omega$-categories. The heart of our construction is a family of padding and repadding techniques, which gives an equivalence relation between cells which are not necessarily parallel. Our work has been implemented, allowing us to explicitly compute suitable witnesses, which grow rapidly in complexity as the dimension increases. These witnesses can be exported as inhabitants of identity types in Homotopy Type Theory, and hence are of relevance in synthetic homotopy theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16465v2</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thibaut Benjamin, Ioannis Markakis, Wilfred Offord, Chiara Sarti, Jamie Vicary</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
