<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.atm-clus updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atm-clus</link>
    <description>physics.atm-clus updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.atm-clus" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 04:05:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Relaxation dynamics in excited helium nanodroplets probed with high resolution, time-resolved photoelectron spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10258</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10258v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Superfluid helium nanodroplets are often considered as transparent and chemically inert nanometer-sized cryo-matrices for high-resolution or time-resolved spectroscopy of embedded molecules and clusters. On the other hand, when the helium nanodroplets are resonantly excited with XUV radiation, a multitude of ultrafast processes are initiated, such as relaxation into metastable states, formation of nanoscopic bubbles or excimers, and autoionization channels generating low-energy free electrons. Here, we discuss the full spectrum of ultrafast relaxation processes observed when helium nanodroplets are electronically excited. In particular, we perform an in-depth study of the relaxation dynamics occurring in the lowest 1s2s and 1s2p droplet bands using high resolution, time-resolved photoelectron spectroscopy. The simplified excitation scheme and improved resolution allow us to identify the relaxation into metastable triplet and excimer states even when exciting below the droplets' autoionization threshold, unobserved in previous studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10258v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. C. LaForge, J. D. Asmussen, B. Bastian, M. Bonanomi, C. Callegari S. De, M. Di Fraia, L. Gorman, S. Hartweg, S. R. Krishnan, M. F. Kling, D. Mishra, S. Mandal, A. Ngai, N. Pal, O. Plekan, K. C. Prince, P. Rosenberger, E. Aguirre Serrata, F. Stienkemeier, N. Berrah, M. Mudrich</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
