<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG</link>
    <description>math.AG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 May 2024 04:00:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Colocalizing subcategories on schemes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10383v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A full triangulated subcategory $\mathsf{C} \subset \mathsf{T}$ of triangulated category $\mathsf{T}$ is colocalizing if it is stable for products. If, further, $\mathsf{T}$ is monoidal and closed, i.e. $(\mathsf{T}, \otimes)$ is tensor-triangulated with internal homs (denoted $[-,-]$), we say that $\mathsf{C}$ is an $\mathcal{H}$-coideal if $[F, G] \in \mathsf{C}$ for all $G \in \mathsf{C}$ and all $F \in \mathsf{T}$. We prove, for a noetherian scheme $X$, that all $\mathcal{H}$-coideal colocalizing subcategories of $\mathsf{D}_{\mathrm{qc}}(X)$ are classified by subsets of $X$. Every such colocalizing subcategory $\mathsf{C}$ is of the form $\mathsf{C} = \mathsf{L}^\perp$, where $\mathsf{L}$ is a $\otimes$-ideal localizing subcategory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10383v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leovigildo Alonso, Ana Jerem\'ias, Eduardo Loureiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grothendieck's use of equality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10387</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10387v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss how the concept of equality is used by mathematicians (including Grothendieck), and what effect this has when trying to formalise mathematics. We challenge various reasonable-sounding slogans about equality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10387v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Buzzard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anticanonical minimal models and Zariski decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10533</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10533v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Birkar and Hu showed that if a pair $(X,\Delta)$ is lc and $K_{X}+\Delta$ admits a birational Zariski decomposition, then $(X,\Delta)$ has a minimal model. Analogously, we prove that if a pair $(X,\Delta)$ is pklt and $-(K_{X}+\Delta)$ admits a birational Zariski decomposition, then $(X,\Delta)$ has an anticanonical minimal</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10533v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sungwook Jang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isomorphism classes and stably isomorphisms of double Danielewski varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10602v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The interest in Danielewski varieties arose from the study of the Cancellation Problem. In this paper, we study the isomorphism classes and stably isomorphisms of double Danielewski varieties, and show that they are counterexamples of the Cancellation Problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10602v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaosong Sun, Shuai Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>La structure des courbes analytiques</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10619v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This is a work in progress, far from being in its final form whose purpose is to investigate thoroughly the structure of Berkovich analytic curves and its relation with the semi-stable reduction theorem (of which a new proof is given here, starting from the local study of Berkovich curves) through the formalism of "triangulations". It has been already on the author's webpage for years, but it seems better to make it available on a public preprint server.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10619v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antoine Ducros</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diagonal del Pezzo of degree 2 with a Brauer-Manin obstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10693v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we give an asymptotic formula for the quantity of diagonal del Pezzo surfaces of degree 2 which have a Brauer-Manin obstruction to the Hasse principle when ordered by height.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10693v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harry C. Shaw</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>K-stability of special Gushel-Mukai manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10797</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10797v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Gushel-Mukai manifolds are specific families of $n$-dimensional Fano manifolds of Picard rank $1$ and index $n-2$ where $3\leq n \leq 6$. A Gushel-Mukai $n$-fold is either ordinary, i.e. a hyperquadric section of a quintic Del Pezzo $(n+1)$-fold, or special, i.e. it admits a double cover over the quintic Del Pezzo $n$-fold branched along an ordinary Gushel-Mukai $(n-1)$-fold. In this paper, we prove that a general special Gushel-Mukai $n$-fold is K-stable for every $3\leq n\leq 6$. Furthermore, we give a description of the first and last walls of the K-moduli of the pair $(M,cQ)$, where $M$ is the quintic Del Pezzo fourfold (or fivefold) and $Q$ is an ordinary Gushel-Mukai threefold (or fourfold). Besides, we compute $\delta$-invariants of quintic Del Pezzo fourfolds and fivefolds which were shown to be K-unstable by K. Fujita, and show that they admit K\"ahler-Ricci solitons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10797v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuchen Liu, Linsheng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A flat perspective on moduli spaces of hyperbolic surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10869v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Volumes of moduli spaces of hyperbolic cone surfaces were previously defined and computed when the angles of the cone singularities are at most 2pi. We propose a general definition of these volumes without restriction on the angles. This construction is based on flat geometry as our proposed volume is a limit of Masur-Veech volumes of moduli spaces of multi-differentials. This idea generalizes the observation in quantum gravity that the Jackiw-Teitelboim partition function is a limit of minimal string partition functions from Liouville gravity. Finally, we use the properties of these volumes to recover Mirzakhani's recursion formula for Weil-Petersson polynomials. This provides a new proof of Witten-Kontsevich's theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10869v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrien Sauvaget</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Filtrations associated with singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10898v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We fix a complex analytic normal singularity germ $(X,o)$ of dimension $\geq 2$ and a (not necessarily irreducible) reduced Weil divisor $(S,o)\subset (X,o)$. The embedded resolution of the pair determines a multi-index filtration of the local ring $\mathcal{O}_{X,o}$, which measures the embedded geometry of the pair. Furthermore, from the (induced) resolution of $(S,o)$ we also consider a multi-index filtration associated with $(S,o)$. This latter one can be lifted to a filtration of $\mathcal{O}_{X,o}$ too. The main result proves that the second filtration of $\mathcal{O}_{X,o}$ can be realized as a `limit' filtration of the first one (if we blow up certain centers sufficiently many times).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10898v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'as N\'emethi, Willem Veys</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Webs and squabs of conics over finite fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10710v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper is a contribution towards a solution for the longstanding open problem of classifying linear systems of conics over finite fields initiated by L. E. Dickson in 1908, through his study of the projective equivalence classes of pencils of conics in $\mathrm{PG}(2,q)$, for $q$ odd. In this paper a set of complete invariants is determined for the projective equivalence classes of webs and of squabs of conics in $\mathrm{PG}(2,q)$, both for $q$ odd and even. Our approach is mainly geometric, and involves a comprehensive study of the geometric and combinatorial properties of the Veronese surface in $\mathrm{PG}(5,q)$. The main contribution is the determination of the distribution of the different types of hyperplanes incident with the $K$-orbit representatives of points and lines of $\mathrm{PG}(5,q)$, where $K\cong\mathrm{PGL}(3,q)$, is the subgroup of $\mathrm{PGL}(6,q)$ stabilizing the Veronese surface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10710v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nour Alnajjarine, Michel Lavrauw</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symplectic duality via log topological recursion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10720v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We review the notion of symplectic duality earlier introduced in the context of topological recursion. We show that the transformation of symplectic duality can be expressed as a composition of $x-y$ dualities in a broader context of log topological recursion. As a corollary, we establish nice properties of symplectic duality: various convenient explicit formulas, invertibility, group property, compatibility with topological recursion and KP integrability. As an application of these properties, we get a new and uniform proof of topological recursion for large families of weighted double Hurwitz numbers; this encompasses and significantly extends all previously known results on this matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10720v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Alexandrov, Boris Bychkov, Petr Dunin-Barkowski, Maxim Kazarian, Sergey Shadrin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the local negativity of surfaces with numerically trivial canonical class</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1512.06022</link>
      <description>arXiv:1512.06022v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this note we study the local negativity for certain configurations of smooth rational curves in smooth surfaces with numerically trivial canonical class. We show that for such rational curves there is a bound for the so-called local Harbourne constants, which measure the local negativity phenomenon. Moreover, we provide explicit examples of interesting configurations of rational curves in some K3 and Enriques surfaces and compute their local Harbourne constants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1512.06022v4</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.4171/RLM/803</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Rend. Lincei Mat. Appl. 29: 237 - 253 (2018)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Roberto Laface, Piotr Pokora</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Models of Jacobians of curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2007.10792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2007.10792v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that the Jacobians of prestable curves over toroidal varieties always admit N\'eron models. These models are rarely quasi-compact or separated, but we also give a complete classification of quasi-compact separated group-models of such Jacobians. In particular we show the existence of a maximal quasi-compact separated group model, which we call the saturated model, which has the extension property for all torsion sections. The N\'eron model and the saturated model coincide over a Dedekind base, so the saturated model gives an alternative generalisation of the classical notion of N\'eron models to higher-dimensional bases; in the general case we give necessary and sufficient conditions for the N\'eron model and saturated model to coincide. The key result, from which most others descend, is that the logarithmic Jacobian of \cite{Molcho2018The-logarithmic} is a log Neron model of the Jacobian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2007.10792v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Holmes, Samouil Molcho, Giulio Orecchia, Thibault Poiret</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $P=W$ conjecture for $\mathrm{GL}_n$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.02568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.02568v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove the $P=W$ conjecture for $\mathrm{GL}_n$ for all ranks $n$ and curves of arbitrary genus $g\geq 2$. The proof combines a strong perversity result on tautological classes with the curious Hard Lefschetz theorem of Mellit. For the perversity statement, we apply the vanishing cycles constructions in our earlier work to global Springer theory in the sense of Yun, and prove a parabolic support theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.02568v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davesh Maulik, Junliang Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Degree of the 3-secant variety</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.00913</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.00913v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a formula for the degree of the 3-secant variety of a nonsingular projective variety embedded by a 5-very ample line bundle. The formula is provided in terms of Segre classes of the tangent bundle of a given variety. We use the generalized version of double point formula to reduce the calculation into the case of the 2-secant variety. Due to the singularity of the 2-secant variety, we use secant bundle as a nonsingular birational model and compute multiplications of desired algebraic cycles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.00913v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Pure Appl. Algebra, 228(9)(2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Doyoung Choi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverting log blow-ups in log geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.10407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.10407v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the category of log schemes, it is unclear how to define the blow-ups for non-strict closed immersions. In this article, we introduce the notion of divided log spaces. We obtain the category of divided log spaces by locally inverting log blow-ups in the category of log schemes. We show that blow-ups exist for closed immersions of log smooth divided log spaces. This is an ingredient of the motivic six-functor formalism for log schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.10407v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Doosung Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on generation and descent for derived categories of noncommutative schemes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02840</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.02840v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work demonstrates classical generation is preserved by the derived pushforward along the canonical morphism of a noncommutative scheme to its underlying scheme. There are intriguing examples illustrating this phenomenon, particularly from noncommutative resolutions, categorical resolutions, and homological projective duality. Additionally, we establish that the Krull dimension of a variety over a field is a lower bound for the Rouquier dimension of the bounded derived category associated with a noncommutative scheme on it. This is an extension of a classical result of Rouquier to the noncommutative context.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.02840v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anirban Bhaduri, Souvik Dey, Pat Lank</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Virasoro constraints for K3 surfaces and monodromy operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12723</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12723v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Virasoro constraints for moduli spaces of stable torsion free sheaves on a surface with only $(p,p)$-cohomology were recently proved by Bojko-Moreira-Lim. The rank 1 case, which is not restricted to surfaces with only $(p,p)$-cohomology, was established by Moreira. We prove Virasoro constraints for K3 surfaces using Markman monodromy operators, which allow us to reduce to the rank 1 case. We also prove new Virasoro constraints in rank 0. Finally, for K3 surfaces, we introduce new Virasoro operators in negative degree which, together with the previous Virasoro operators, give a representation of Virasoro algebra with central charge $24$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12723v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weisheng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An algebraic-geometric construction of "lump" solutions of the KP1 equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15200v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this note, we show how certain everywhere-regular real rational function solutions of the KP1 equation ("multi-lumps") can be constructed via the polynomial analogs of theta functions from singular rational curves with cusps. We use two methods, one direct and the other producing a degeneration of the well-understood soliton solutions from nodal singular curves. The second approach can be seen as a variation on the long-wave limit technique of Ablowitz and Satsuma, as developed by Zhang, Yang, Li, Guo, and Stepanyants. We present an explicit example of a three-lump solution constructed via the polynomial analog of the theta function from a rational curve with two cuspidal singular points, each with semigroup $\langle 2,5\rangle$. (In the theory of curve singularities, these are known as $A_4$ double points.) We conjecture that these ideas will generalize to give similar $M$-lump solutions with $M = \frac{N(N+1)}{2}$ for $N &gt; 2$ starting from rational curves with two singular points with semigroup $\langle 2,2N+1\rangle$ ($A_{2N}$ double points). We also show a five-lump solution obtained from a curve with two cusps with semigroup $\langle 3,4\rangle$. Similar solutions have been constructed by other methods previously; our contribution is to show how they arise from the algebraic-geometric setting by considering singular curves with several cusps, as in previous work of Agostini, Celik, and Little.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15200v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John B. Little</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A refined Weyl character formula for comodules on $\operatorname{GL}(2,A)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09210v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $A$ be any commutative unital ring and let $\operatorname{GL}(2,A)$ be the general linear group scheme on $A$ of rank $2$. We study the representation theory of $\operatorname{GL}(2,A)$ and the symmetric powers $\operatorname{Sym}^d(V)$, where $(V, \Delta)$ is the standard right comodule on $\operatorname{GL}(2,A)$. We prove a refined Weyl character formula for $\operatorname{Sym}^d(V)$. There is for any integer $d \geq 1$ a (canonical) refined weight space decomposition $\operatorname{Sym}^d(V) \cong \oplus_i \operatorname{Sym}^d(V)^i$ where each direct summand $\operatorname{Sym}^d(V)^i$ is a comodule on $N \subseteq \operatorname{GL}(2,A)$. Here $N$ is the schematic normalizer of the diagonal torus $T \subseteq \operatorname{GL}(2,A)$. We prove a character formula for the direct summands of $\operatorname{Sym}^d(V)$ for any integer $d \geq 1$. This refined Weyl character formula implies the classical Weyl character formula. As a Corollary we get a refined Weyl character formula for the pull back $\operatorname{Sym}^d(V \otimes K)$ as a comodule on $\operatorname{GL}(2,K)$ where $K$ is any field. We also calculate explicit examples involving the symmetric powers, symmetric tensors and their duals. The refined weight space decomposition exists in general for group schemes such as $\operatorname{GL}(n,A)$ and $\operatorname{SL}(n,A)$. The methods introduced in the paper may have applications to the study of finite rank torsion free comodules on $\operatorname{SL}(n,Z)$ and $\operatorname{GL}(n,Z)$. There is no "highest weight theory" or "complete reducibility property" for such comodules, and we want to give a definition of the notion "good filtration". The study may have applications to the study of groups $G$ such as $\operatorname{SL}(n,k)$ and $\operatorname{GL}(n,k)$ and quotients $G/H$ where $k$ is an arbitrary field and $H \subseteq G$ is a closed subgroup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09210v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Helge {\O}ystein Maakestad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological recursion for Kadomtsev-Petviashvili tau functions of hypergeometric type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.14723</link>
      <description>arXiv:2012.14723v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the $n$-point differentials corresponding to Kadomtsev-Petviashvili tau functions of hypergeometric type (also known as Orlov-Scherbin partition functions), with an emphasis on their $\hbar^2$-deformations and expansions. Under the naturally required analytic assumptions, we prove certain higher loop equations that, in particular, contain the standard linear and quadratic loop equations, and thus imply the blobbed topological recursion. We also distinguish two large families of the Orlov-Scherbin partition functions that do satisfy the natural analytic assumptions, and for these families we prove in addition the so-called projection property and thus the full statement of the Chekhov-Eynard-Orantin topological recursion. A particular feature of our argument is that it clarifies completely the role of $\hbar^2$-deformations of the Orlov-Scherbin parameters for the partition functions, whose necessity was known from a variety of earlier obtained results in this direction but never properly understood in the context of topological recursion. As special cases of the results of this paper one recovers new and uniform proofs of the topological recursion to all previously studied cases of enumerative problems related to weighted double Hurwitz numbers. By virtue of topological recursion and the Grothendieck-Riemann-Roch formula this, in turn, gives new and uniform proofs of almost all ELSV-type formulas discussed in the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2012.14723v4</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boris Bychkov, Petr Dunin-Barkowski, Maxim Kazarian, Sergey Shadrin</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
