<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG</link>
    <description>math.AG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2024 01:39:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Distributions and Legendrian foliations in dimension 3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17913</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17913v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the field of rational first integrals of distributions. We show that for a distribution on 3 dimensional manifolds there exists a tangent vector field with the same field of first integrals. We also show a similar result for integrable distributions in any dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17913v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maycol Falla Luza, Rudy Rosas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytic torsion for irreducible holomorphic symplectic fourfolds with involution, I: Construction of an invariant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18023</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18023v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we construct an invariant for irreducible holomorphic symplectic manifolds of $K3^{[2]}$-type with antisymplectic involution by using the equivariant analytic torsion. Moreover, we give a formula for the complex Hessian of the logarithm of the invariant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18023v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dai Imaike</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarized endomorphisms of log Calabi-Yau pairs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18092</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18092v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $(X,\Delta)$ be a dlt log Calabi-Yau pair admitting a polarized endomorphism. We show that $(X,\Delta)$ is a finite quotient of a toric log Calabi-Yau fibration over an abelian variety. We provide an example which shows that the previous statement does not hold if we drop the dlt condition of $(X,\Delta)$ even if $X$ is a smooth variety. Given a klt type variety $X$ and a log Calabi-Yau pair $(X,\Delta)$ admitting a polarized endomorphism, we show that a suitable birational modification of $(X,\Delta)$ is a finite quotient of a toric log Calabi-Yau fibration over an abelian variety.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18092v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joaqu\'in Moraga, Jos\'e Ignacio Y\'a\~nez, Wern Yeong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unstability problem of real analytic maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18106v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As well-known, the $C^\infty$ stability of proper $C^\infty$ maps is characterized by the infinitesimal $C^\infty$ stability. In the present paper we study the counterpart in real analytic context. In particular, we show that the infinitesimal $C^\omega$ stability does not imply $C^\omega$ stability; for instance, a Whitney umbrella $\mathbb{R}^2 \to \mathbb{R}^3$ is not $C^\omega$ stable. A main tool for the proof is a relative version of Whitney's Analytic Approximation Theorem which is shown by using H. Cartan's Theorems A and B.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18106v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karim Bekka, Satoshi Koike, Toru Ohmoto, Masahiro Shiota, Masato Tanabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metrics with minimal singularities and the Abundance conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18233v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Abundance conjecture predicts that on a minimal projective klt pair $(X,\Delta)$, the adjoint divisor $K_X+\Delta$ is semiample. When $\chi(X,\mathcal O_X)\neq0$, we give a necessary and sufficient condition for the conjecture to hold in terms of the asymptotic behaviour of multiplier ideals of currents with minimal singularities of small twists of $K_X+\Delta$. Furthermore, we prove fundamental structural properties as well as regularity and weak convergence behaviour of an important class of currents with minimal singularities: the supercanonical currents. The results of the paper indicate strongly that supercanonical currents are central to the completion of the proof of the Abundance conjecture for minimal klt pairs $(X,\Delta)$ with $\chi(X,\mathcal O_X)\neq0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18233v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Lazi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enriques surfaces of zero entropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18407v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We classify Enriques surfaces of zero entropy, or, equivalently, Enriques surfaces with a virtually abelian automorphism group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18407v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gebhard Martin, Giacomo Mezzedimi, Davide Cesare Veniani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometrical finiteness for automorphism groups via cone conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18438v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper aims to establish the geometrical finiteness for the natural isometric actions of (birational) automorphism groups on the hyperbolic spaces for K3 surfaces, Enriques surfaces, Coble surfaces, and irreducible symplectic varieties.
  As an application, it can be seen that such groups are non-positively curved: ${\rm CAT(0)}$ and relatively hyperbolic. In the case of K3 surfaces, we additionally provide a dynamical characterization of the relative hyperbolicity, and the first counterexample to Mukai's conjecture concerning the virtual cohomological dimension of automorphism groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18438v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kohei Kikuta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-perturbative topological strings from resurgence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17852v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The partition function of topological string theory on any family of Calabi-Yau threefolds is defined perturbatively as an asymptotic series in the topological string coupling and encodes, in a holomorphic limit, higher genus Gromov-Witten as well as Gopakumar-Vafa invariants. We prove that the partition function of topological strings of any CY in this limit can be written as a product, where each factor is given by the partition function of the resolved conifold with shifted arguments, raised to the power of certain sheaf invariants. We use this result to put forward an expression for the non-perturbative topological string partition function in this limit, as a product over analytic functions in the topological string coupling which correspond to the Borel sums for the resolved conifold found previously. The non-perturbative corrections to the partition function are identified with Stokes jumps of a Borel summation. They depend only on genus zero GV invariants and can be expressed entirely in terms of a single function which is introduced as a deformation of the prepotential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17852v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Murad Alim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Hilton-Milner theorem for exterior algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17857</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17857v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent work of Scott and Wilmer and of Woodroofe extends the Erd\H{o}s-Ko-Rado theorem from set systems to subspaces of k-forms in an exterior algebra. We prove an extension of the Hilton-Milner theorem to the exterior algebra setting, answering in a strong way a question asked by these authors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17857v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denys Bulavka, Francesca Gandini, Russ Woodroofe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The weak Lefschetz property for artinian Gorenstein algebras of small Sperner number</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17943v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For artinian Gorenstein algebras in codimension four and higher, it is well known that the Weak Lefschetz Property (WLP) does not need to hold. For Gorenstein algebras in codimension three, it is still open whether all artinian Gorenstein algebras satisfy the WLP when the socle degree and the Sperner number are both higher than six. We here show that all artinian Gorenstein algebras with socle degree $d$ and Sperner number at most $d+1$ satisfy the WLP, independent of the codimension. This is a sharp bound in general since there are examples of artinian Gorenstein algebras with socle degree $d$ and Sperner number $d+2$ that do not satisfy the WLP for all $d\ge 3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17943v1</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mats Boij, Juan C. Migliore, Rosa Maria Mir\'o-Roig, Uwe Nagel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two improvements in Birch's theorem on forms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18498v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $K$ be a Birch field, that is, a field for which every diagonal form of odd degree in sufficiently many variables admits a non-zero solution; for example, $K$ could be the field of rational numbers. Let $f_1, \ldots, f_r$ be homogeneous forms of odd degree over $K$ in $n$ variables, and let $Z$ be the variety they cut out. Birch proved if $n$ is sufficiently large then $Z(K)$ contains a non-zero point. We prove two results which show that $Z(K)$ is actually quite large. First, the Zariski closure of $Z(K)$ has bounded codimension in $\mathbf{A}^n$. And second, if the $f_i$'s have sufficiently high strength then $Z(K)$ is in fact Zariski dense in $Z$. The proofs use recent results on strength, and our methods build on recent work of Bik, Draisma, and Snowden, which established similar improvements to Brauer's theorem on forms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18498v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amichai Lampert, Andrew Snowden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Notes characterising higher and derived stacks concretely</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1105.4853</link>
      <description>arXiv:1105.4853v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This is an informal summary of the main concepts in arXiv:0905.4044, based on notes of various seminars. It gives constructions of higher and derived stacks without recourse to the extensive theory developed by Toen, Vezzosi and Lurie. Explicitly, higher stacks are described in terms of simplicial diagrams of affine schemes, which are analogous to atlases for manifolds. We also describe quasi-coherent sheaves and complexes on such objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1105.4853v4</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. P. Pridham</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on \'etale atlases for Artin stacks and Lie groupoids, Poisson structures and quantisation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.09255</link>
      <description>arXiv:1905.09255v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explain how any Artin stack $\mathfrak{X}$ over $\mathbb{Q}$ extends to a functor on non-negatively graded commutative cochain algebras, which we think of as functions on Lie algebroids or stacky affine schemes. There is a notion of \'etale morphisms for these CDGAs, and Artin stacks admit \'etale atlases by stacky affines, giving rise to a small \'etale site of stacky affines over $\mathfrak{X}$. This site has the same quasi-coherent sheaves as $\mathfrak{X}$ and leads to efficient formulations of shifted Poisson structures, differential operators and quantisations for Artin stacks. There are generalisations to higher and derived stacks.
  We also describe analogues for differentiable and analytic stacks; in particular, a Lie groupoid naturally gives a functor on NQ-manifolds which we can use to transfer structures. In those settings, local diffeomorphisms and biholomorphisms are the analogues of \'etale morphisms.
  This note mostly elaborates constructions scattered across several of the author's papers, but with an emphasis on the functor of points perspective. New results include consistency checks showing that the induced notions of structures such as vector bundles or torsors on a stacky affine scheme coincide with familiar definitions in terms of flat connections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1905.09255v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. P. Pridham</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Birational geometry of sextic double solids with a compound $A_n$ singularity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2101.00501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2101.00501v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Sextic double solids, double covers of $\mathbb P^3$ branched along a sextic surface, are the lowest degree Gorenstein Fano 3-folds, hence are expected to behave very rigidly in terms of birational geometry. Smooth sextic double solids, and those which are $\mathbb Q$-factorial with ordinary double points, are known to be birationally rigid. In this article, we study sextic double solids with an isolated compound $A_n$ singularity. We prove a sharp bound $n \leq 8$, describe models for each $n$ explicitly and prove that sextic double solids with $n &gt; 3$ are birationally non-rigid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2101.00501v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erik Paemurru</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the embedded Nash problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.08546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.08546v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The embedded Nash problem for a hypersurface in a smooth algebraic variety, is to characterize geometrically the maximal irreducible families of arcs with fixed order of contact along the hypersurface. We show that divisors on minimal models of the pair contribute with such families. We solve the problem for unibranch plane curve germs, in terms of the resolution graph. These are embedded analogs of known results for the classical Nash problem on singular varieties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.08546v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nero Budur, Javier de la Bodega, Eduardo de Lorenzo Poza, Javier Fern\'andez de Bobadilla, Tomasz Pe{\l}ka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orphan Calabi-Yau threefold with arithmetic monodromy group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.02367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.02367v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study monodromy groups of Picard-Fuchs operators of one-parameter families of Calabi-Yau threefolds without a point of Maximal Unipotent Monodromy (\emph{orphan operators}). We construct rational symplectic bases for the monodromy action for all orphan double octic Picard-Fuchs operators of order $4$. As a consequence we show that monodromy groups of all double octic orphan operators are dense in $\mathrm{Sp(4,\mathbb{Z})}$ and identify maximally unipotent elements in all of them, except one. Finally, we prove that the monodromy group of one of these orphan operators is arithmetic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.02367v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tymoteusz Chmiel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic base loci on hyper-K\"ahler manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.01773v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a projective hyper-K\"ahler manifold $X$, we study the asymptotic base loci of big divisors on $X$. We provide a numerical characterization of these loci and study how they vary while moving a big divisor class in the big cone, using the divisorial Zariski decomposition, and the Beauville-Bogomolov-Fujiki form. We determine the dual of the cones of $k$-ample divisors $\mathrm{Amp}_k(X)$, for any $1\leq k \leq \mathrm{dim}(X)$, answering affirmatively (in the case of projective hyper-K\"ahler manifolds) a question asked by Sam Payne. We provide a decomposition for the effective cone $\mathrm{Eff}(X)$ into chambers of Mori-type, analogous to that for Mori dream spaces into Mori chambers. To conclude, we illustrate our results with several examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.01773v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Antonio Denisi, \'Angel David R\'ios Ortiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Goppa code and quantum stabilizer codes from plane curves given by separated polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.07833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.07833v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we examine algebraic geometric (AG) codes associated with curves generated by separated polynomials, and we create AG codes and quantum stabilizer codes from these curves by varying their parameters. Our research involves a thorough examination of the curves' algebraic features as well as the creation of Goppa codes over them. Extending these findings, we create quantum stabilizer codes, revealing that quantum codes built from Hermitian self-orthogonal AG codes have acceptable parameters, improving the reliability and performance of communication networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.07833v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vahid Nourozi, Farzaneh Ghanbari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Minimal Model Program for K\"ahler 3-folds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.11708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.11708v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article we prove the existence of pl-flipping and divisorial contractions and pl flips in dimension $n$ for compact K\"ahler varieties, assuming results of the minimal model program in dimension $n-1$. We also give a self contained proof of the cone theorem, the existence of flipping and divisorial contractions, of flips and minimal models in dimension 3.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.11708v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Omprokash Das, Christopher Hacon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Counterexample to N\'eron-Ogg-Shafarevich criterion for Calabi-Yau threefolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.04008</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.04008v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For any prime $p&gt;5$ we construct a Calabi-Yau threefold $X$ defined over a finite extension $K$ of $\mathbb{Q}_p$ such that every model of $X$ over $\operatorname{Spec}\mathcal{O}_K$ has singular special fiber, yet the Galois action on the $\ell$-adic cohomology group $H^3_{\acute{e}t}(X,\mathbb{Q}_\ell)$ is unramified for $\ell\neq p$ and crystalline for $\ell=p$. This provides a counterexample to the analogue of the N\'eron-Ogg-Shafarevich criterion for three-dimensional Calabi-Yau manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.04008v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tymoteusz Chmiel, Marcin Oczko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Endomorphisms of a variety of Ueno type and Kawaguchi-Silverman Conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.04386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.04386v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We first show that the moniod of separable surjective self morphisms of a variety of Ueno type coincides with the group of automorphisms. We also give an explicit description of the automorphism group. As applications, we confirm Kawaguchi Silverman Conjecture for automorphisms of a variety of Ueno type and some Calabi-Yau threefolds, defined over $\overline{\Q}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.04386v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keiji Oguiso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Listing superspecial curves of genus three by using Richelot isogeny graph</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.10500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.10500v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In algebraic geometry, superspecial curves are important research objects. While the number of superspecial genus-3 curves in characteristic $p$ is known, the number of hyperelliptic ones among them has not been determined even for small $p$. In this paper, in order to compute the latter number, we give an algorithm for computing the Richelot isogeny graph of superspecial abelian threefolds by using theta functions. Our algorithm enables us to efficiently list superspecial genus-3 curves, and we succeeded in counting hyperelliptic curves among them when $11 \leq p &lt; 100$ by executing our algorithm in Magma.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.10500v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryo Ohashi, Hiroshi Onuki, Momonari Kudo, Ryo Yoshizumi, Koji Nuida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Game theory of undirected graphical models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.13246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.13246v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: An $n$-player game $X$ in normal form can be modeled via undirected discrete graphical models where the discrete random variables represent the players and their state spaces are the set of pure strategies. There exists an edge between the vertices of the graphical model whenever there is a dependency between the associated players. We study the Spohn conditional independence (CI) variety $\mathcal{V}_{X,\mathcal{C}}$, which is the intersection of the independence model $\mathcal{M}_{\mathcal{C}}$ with the Spohn variety of the game $X$. We prove a conjecture by the first author and Sturmfels that $\mathcal{V}_{X,\mathcal{C}}$ is of codimension $n$ in $\mathcal{M}_{\mathcal{C}}$ for a generic game $X$ with binary choices. We show that the set of totally mixed CI equilibria i.e., the restriction of the Spohn CI variety to the open probability simplex is a smooth semialgebraic manifold for a generic game $X$ with binary choices. If the undirected graph is a disjoint union of cliques, we analyze certain algebro-geometric features of Spohn CI varieties and prove affine universality theorems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.13246v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Irem Portakal, Javier Sendra-Arranz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Uniform Mordell-Lang Conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2105.15085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2105.15085v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Mordell--Lang conjecture for abelian varieties states that the intersection of an algebraic subvariety $X$ with a subgroup of finite rank is contained in a finite union of cosets contained in $X$. In this article, we prove a uniform version of this conjecture, meaning that that the number of cosets necessary does not depend on the ambient abelian variety. To achieve this, we prove a general gap principle on algebraic points that extends the gap principle for curves embedded into their Jacobians, previously obtained by Dimitrov--Gao--Habegger and K\"{u}hne. Our new gap principle also implies the full uniform Bogomolov conjecture in abelian varieties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2105.15085v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziyang Gao, Tangli Ge, Lars K\"uhne</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graded $p$-polar rings and the homology of $\Omega^n\Sigma^nX$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.05286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2203.05286v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: As an extension of previous ungraded work, we define a graded $p$-polar ring to be an analog of a graded commutative ring where multiplication is only allowed on $p$-tuples (instead of pairs) of elements of equal degree. We show that the free affine $p$-adic group scheme functor, as well as the free formal group functor, defined on $k$-algebras for a perfect field $k$ of characteristic $p$, factors through $p$-polar $k$-algebras. It follows that the same is true for any affine $p$-adic or formal group functor, in particular for the functor of $p$-typical Witt vectors. As an application, we show that the homology of the free $E_n$-algebra $H^*(\Omega^n\Sigma^n X;\mathbf F_p)$, as a Hopf algebra, only depends on the $p$-polar structure of $H^*(X;\mathbf F_p)$ in a functorial way.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2203.05286v3</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tilman Bauer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algorithm to find new identifiable reparametrizations of parametric rational ODE models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.03057</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.03057v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Structural identifiability concerns the question of which unknown parameters of a model can be recovered from (perfect) input-output data. If all of the parameters of a model can be recovered from data, the model is said to be identifiable. However, in many models, there are parameters that can take on an infinite number of values but yield the same input-output data. In this case, those parameters and the model are called unidentifiable. The question is then what to do with an unidentifiable model. One can either adjust the model, if experimentally feasible, or try to find a reparametrization to make the model identifiable. In this paper, we take the latter approach. While existing approaches to find identifiable reparametrizations were limited to scaling reparametrizations or were not guaranteed to find a globally identifiable reparametrization even if it exists, we significantly broaden the class of models for which we can find a globally identifiable model with the same input-output behavior as the original one. We also prove that, for linear models, a globally identifiable reparametrization always exists and show that, for a certain class of linear compartmental models, an explicit reparametrization formula exists. We illustrate our method on several examples and provide detailed analysis in supplementary material on github.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.03057v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolette Meshkat, Alexey Ovchinnikov, Thomas Scanlon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convex Geometry of Building Sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05514</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05514v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Building sets were introduced in the study of wonderful compactifications of hyperplane arrangement complements and were later generalized to finite meet-semilattices. Convex geometries, the duals of antimatroids, offer a robust combinatorial abstraction of convexity. Supersolvable convex geometries and antimatroids appear in the study of poset closure operators, Coxeter groups, and matroid activities. We prove that the building sets on a finite meet-semilattice form a supersolvable convex geometry. As an application, we demonstrate that building sets and nested set complexes respect certain restrictions of finite meet-semilattices unifying and extending results of several authors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05514v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Spencer Backman, Rick Danner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Odd and Even Elliptic Curves with Complex Multiplication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07240</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.07240v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We call an order $O$ in a quadratic field $K$ odd (resp. even) if its discriminant is an odd (resp. even) integer. We call an elliptic curve $E$ over the field $C$ of complex numbers with CM odd (resp. even) if its endomorphism ring $End(E)$ is an odd (resp. even) order in the corresponding imaginary quadratic field.
  Suppose that $j(E)$ is a real number and let us consider the set $J(R,E)$ of all $j(E')$ where $E'$ is any elliptic curve that enjoys the following properties.
  1) $E'$ is isogenous to $E$;
  2) $j(E')$ is a real number;
  3) $E'$ has the same parity as $E$.
  We prove that the closure of $J(R,E)$ in the set $R$ of real numbers is the closed semi-infinite interval $(-\infty,1728]$ (resp. the whole $R$) if $E$ is odd (resp. even).
  This paper was inspired by a question of Jean-Louis Colliot-Th\'el\`ene and Alena Pirutka about the distribution of $j$-invariants of certain elliptic curves of CM type.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.07240v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuri G. Zarhin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Weak Lefschetz Property for certain ideals generated by powers of linear forms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09571</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09571v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Ideals $I\subseteq R=k[\mathbb P^n]$ generated by powers of linear forms arise, via Macaulay duality, from sets of fat points $X\subseteq \mathbb P^n$. Properties of $R/I$ are connected to the geometry of the corresponding fat points. When the linear forms are general, many authors have studied the question of whether or not $R/I$ has the Weak Lefschetz Property (WLP). We study this question instead for ideals coming from a family of sets of points called grids. We give a complete answer in the case of uniform powers of linear forms coming from square grids, and we give a conjecture and approach for the case of nonsquare grids. In the cases where WLP holds, we also describe the non-Lefschetz locus.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09571v2</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Favacchio, Juan Migliore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deformation Families of Quasi-Projective Varieties and Symmetric Projective K3 Surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16208v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The main aim of this paper is to construct a deformation family of symmetric projective K3 surfaces through a deformation family of quasi-projective varieties together with construction of symmetric Kahler metrics on symmetric projective K3 surfaces. Firstly, if the normal bundle satisfies the Diophantine condition, the tubular neighborhood of an elliptic curve embedded in $\text{CP}^2 \text{$\#$9} \overline{\text{CP}}^2$ can be identified through the toroidal group. Secondly, with ample line bundles fixed on $\text{CP}^2 \text{$\#$9} \overline{\text{CP}}^2$, complete Kahler metrics are constructed on the quasi-projective variety from $\text{CP}^2 \text{$\#$9} \overline{\text{CP}}^2$. Finally, a deformation family of symmetric projective K3 surfaces over a 10-dimensional complex manifold is constructed through a smooth compactifiable deformation of complete quasi-projective varieties from $\text{CP}^2 \text{$\#$9} \overline{\text{CP}}^2$ over a 9-dimensional complex manifold and an analogue deformation family.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16208v3</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fan Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
