<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG</link>
    <description>math.AG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 05:00:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Cubic fourfolds of discriminant 24 and rationality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04222v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cubic fourfolds of discriminant 24 contain special codimension-two algebraic cycles of degree 6 and self-intersection 20. Such cycles may be represented by singular scrolls or del Pezzo surfaces. A discriminant 24 cubic fourfold gives rise to a twisted surface, consisting of a degree-six K3 surface and a two-torsion element of its Brauer group. We show that the cubic fourfold is rational if the Brauer class vanishes. This yields a countably-infinite collection of new examples of rational cubic fourfolds, each of codimension two in moduli.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04222v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brendan Hassett</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Plc pairs with good asymptotic base loci</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04628v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we give a characterization of Fano type varieties of plc pairs. This extends a result due to Choi and Park for pklt pairs. Moreover, we show that for a plc pair $(X,\Delta)$, if no plc centers are contained in the augmented base locus $\mathbf{B}_{+}(-(K_X+\Delta))$, then $(X,\Delta)$ admits a good $-(K_X+\Delta)$-minimal model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04628v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sung Rak Choi, Sungwook Jang, Dae-Won Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automorphisms of Nikulin-type orbifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04668v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the monodromoy group of Nikulin-type orbifolds is maximal and classify finite order symplectic automorphisms up to deformation in terms of their action on the second integral cohomology group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04668v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Brandhorst, Gr\'egoire Menet, Stevell Muller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Birational geometry of hypersurfaces in products of weighted projective spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04673</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04673v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the birational geometry of hypersurfaces in products of weighted projective spaces, extending results previously established by J. C. Ottem. For most cases where these hypersurfaces are Mori dream spaces, we determine all relevant cones and characterise their birational models, along with the small $\mathbf{Q}$-factorial modifications to them. We also provide a presentation of their Cox ring. Finally, we establish the birational form of the Kawamata-Morrison cone conjecture for terminal Calabi-Yau hypersurfaces in Gorenstein products of weighted projective spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04673v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Antonio Denisi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is... Random Algebraic Geometry?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04705v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We survey some ideas from the subject of Random Algebraic Geometry, a field that introduces a probabilistic perspective on classical topics in real algebraic geometry. This offers a modern approach to classical problems, such as Hilbert's Sixteenth Problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04705v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Lerario</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Group Cohomology of Peroidized Hypertoric Variety</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04853v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To a graph $\Gamma$, one can associate a hypertoric variety $\mathcal{M}(\Gamma)$ and its multiplicative version $\mathcal{M}^{\mathrm{mul}}(\Gamma)$. It was shown in [DMS24] that the cohomology of $\mathcal{M}^{\mathrm{mul}}(\Gamma)$ is computed by the CKS complex, which is a finite dimensional complex attached to $\Gamma$. The multiplicative hypertoric variety can be realized as the quotient of a periodized hypertoric variety by a lattice action. In this paper, we show that the group cohomology of the lattice with coefficients in the cohomology of the prequotient is isomorphic to the cohomology of the CKS complex using a spectral sequence argument. Therefore, the group cohomology can serve as an alternative way to compute the cohomology of multiplicative hypertoric varieties.
  We also found graph-theoretic descriptions for the Euler characteristics of the graded pieces in a certain decomposition of $\mathrm{H}^\bullet(\mathcal{M}^{\mathrm{mul}}(\Gamma))$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04853v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sum Kiu Law, Nok To Omega Tong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complexity theory of orbit closure intersection for tensors: reductions, completeness, and graph isomorphism hardness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04639v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Many natural computational problems in computer science, mathematics, physics, and other sciences amount to deciding if two objects are equivalent. Often this equivalence is defined in terms of group actions. A natural question is to ask when two objects can be distinguished by polynomial functions that are invariant under the group action. For finite groups, this is the usual notion of equivalence, but for continuous groups like the general linear groups it gives rise to a new notion, called orbit closure intersection. It captures, among others, the graph isomorphism problem, noncommutative PIT, null cone problems in invariant theory, equivalence problems for tensor networks, and the classification of multiparty quantum states. Despite recent algorithmic progress in celebrated special cases, the computational complexity of general orbit closure intersection problems is currently quite unclear. In particular, tensors seem to give rise to the most difficult problems.
  In this work we start a systematic study of orbit closure intersection from the complexity-theoretic viewpoint. To this end, we define a complexity class TOCI that captures the power of orbit closure intersection problems for general tensor actions, give an appropriate notion of algebraic reductions that imply polynomial-time reductions in the usual sense, but are amenable to invariant-theoretic techniques, identify natural tensor problems that are complete for TOCI, including the equivalence of 2D tensor networks with constant physical dimension, and show that the graph isomorphism problem can be reduced to these complete problems, hence GI$\subseteq$TOCI. As such, our work establishes the first lower bound on the computational complexity of orbit closure intersection problems, and it explains the difficulty of finding unconditional polynomial-time algorithms beyond special cases, as has been observed in the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04639v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Lysikov, Michael Walter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An exploration of connections and curvature in the presence of singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04829v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop the notions of connections and curvature for general Lie-Rinehart algebras without using smoothness assumptions on the base space. We present situations when a connection exists. E.g., this is the case when the underlying module is finitely generated. We show how the group of module automorphism acts as gauge transformations on the space of connections. When the underlying module is projective we define a version of the Chern character reproducing results of Hideki Ozeki. We discuss various examples of flat connections and the associated Maurer-Cartan equations. We provide examples of Levi-Civita connections on singular varieties and singular differential spaces with non-zero Riemannian curvature. The main observation is that for quotient singularities, even though the metric degenerates along strata, the poles of the Christoffel symbols are removable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04829v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hans-Christian Herbig, William Osnayder Clavijo Esquivel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mirror symmetric Gamma conjecture for Fano and Calabi-Yau manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.15940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.15940v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The mirror symmetric Gamma conjecture roughly speaking says that the Gamma class of a manifold determines the asymptotics of (exponential) periods of the mirror. We recast the method in [Iri11] in a more general context and show that the mirror symmetric Gamma conjecture for a Fano manifold F implies, via Laplace transformation, that for the total space K_F of the canonical bundle or for anticanonical sections in F. More generally, we discuss the mirror symmetric Gamma conjecture for the total space of a sum of anti-nef line bundles over F or for nef complete intersections in F.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.15940v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroshi Iritani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A multiplicity formula for the Milnor number of smoothable curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.16558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.16558v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For a reduced complex analytic curve germ we introduce an algebraic invariant we call the complete intersection discrepancy. We determine some of its basic properties. As an application we derive a multiplicity formula for the Milnor number of a reduced smoothable curve singularity generalizing a well-known formula due to L\^e, Greuel and Teissier for complete intersection curves. We obtain a multiplicity characterization of Whitney equisingularity for families of locally smoothable curves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.16558v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Bengu\c{s}-Lasnier, Terence Gaffney, Antoni Rangachev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Gizatullin's Problem for quartic surfaces of Picard rank $2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08415v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we determine which automorphisms of general smooth quartic surfaces $S\subset \mathbb{P}^3$ of Picard rank $2$ are restrictions of Cremona transformations of $\mathbb{P}^3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08415v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carolina Araujo, Daniela Paiva, Sokratis Zikas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Jouanolou duality, weakly Gorenstein rings, and applications to blowup algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.03837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.03837v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We provide a generalization of Jouanolou duality that is applicable to a plethora of situations. The environment where this generalized duality takes place is a new class of rings, that we introduce and call weakly Gorenstein. As a main consequence, we obtain a new general framework to investigate blowup algebras. We use our results to study and determine the defining equations of the Rees algebra of certain families of ideals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.03837v2</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yairon Cid-Ruiz, Claudia Polini, Bernd Ulrich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faster Lattice Basis Computation via a Natural Generalization of the Euclidean Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.06685v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Euclidean algorithm is the oldest algorithms known to mankind. Given two integral numbers $a_1$ and $a_2$, it computes the greatest common divisor (gcd) of $a_1$ and $a_2$ in a very elegant way. From a lattice perspective, it computes a basis of the sum of two one-dimensional lattices $a_1 \mathbb{Z}$ and $a_2 \mathbb{Z}$ as $\gcd(a_1,a_2) \mathbb{Z} = a_1 \mathbb{Z} + a_2 \mathbb{Z}$. In this paper, we show that the classical Euclidean algorithm can be adapted in a very natural way to compute a basis of a general lattice $L(A_1, \ldots , A_n)$ given vectors $A_1, \ldots , A_n \in \mathbb{Z}^d$ with $n&gt; \mathrm{rank}(a_1, \ldots ,a_d)$. Similar to the Euclidean algorithm, our algorithm is very easy to describe and implement and can be written within 12 lines of pseudocode.
  As our main result, we obtain an algorithm to compute a lattice basis for given vectors $A_1, \ldots , A_n \in \mathbb{Z}^d$ in time (counting bit operations) $LS + \tilde{O}((n-d)d^2 \cdot \log(||A||)$, where $LS$ is the time required to obtain the exact fractional solution of a certain system of linear equalities. The analysis of the running time of our algorithms relies on fundamental statements on the fractionality of solutions of linear systems of equations.
  So far, the fastest algorithm for lattice basis computation was due to Storjohann and Labhan [SL96] having a running time of $\tilde{O}(nd^\omega\log ||A||)$. For current upper bounds of $LS$, our algorithm has a running time improvement of a factor of at least $d^{0.12}$ over [SL96]. Our algorithm is therefore the first general algorithmic improvement to this classical problem in nearly 30 years. At last, we present a postprocessing procedure which yields an improved size bound of $\sqrt{d} ||A||$ for vectors of the resulting basis matrix.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.06685v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kim-Manuel Klein, Janina Reuter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological obstruction to the training of shallow ReLU neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14837v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Studying the interplay between the geometry of the loss landscape and the optimization trajectories of simple neural networks is a fundamental step for understanding their behavior in more complex settings. This paper reveals the presence of topological obstruction in the loss landscape of shallow ReLU neural networks trained using gradient flow. We discuss how the homogeneous nature of the ReLU activation function constrains the training trajectories to lie on a product of quadric hypersurfaces whose shape depends on the particular initialization of the network's parameters. When the neural network's output is a single scalar, we prove that these quadrics can have multiple connected components, limiting the set of reachable parameters during training. We analytically compute the number of these components and discuss the possibility of mapping one to the other through neuron rescaling and permutation. In this simple setting, we find that the non-connectedness results in a topological obstruction, which, depending on the initialization, can make the global optimum unreachable. We validate this result with numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14837v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Nurisso, Pierrick Leroy, Francesco Vaccarino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$q$-Witt vectors and $q$-Hodge complexes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23078v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this article, we'll introduce a $q$-variant of Witt vectors and de Rham-Witt complexes. This variant is closely related to the Habiro ring of a number field constructed by Garoufalidis, Scholze, Wheeler, and Zagier, to $q$-Hodge cohomology, and to $\operatorname{THH}(-/\mathrm{ku})$. While most of these connections will only be explored in forthcoming work, the goal of this article is to provide the necessary technical foundation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23078v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ferdinand Wagner</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
