<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG</link>
    <description>math.AG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2024 04:00:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Terminal 3-folds that are not Cohen-Macaulay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02608</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02608v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An important local vanishing theorem for the minimal model program is the fact that klt singularities in characteristic zero are Cohen-Macaulay. In contrast, even in the narrow setting of terminal singularities of dimension 3, we show that Cohen-Macaulayness can fail in characteristic $p$ or mixed characteristic $(0,p)$ for $p$ equal to 2, 3, or 5. This is optimal, by work of Arvidsson-Bernasconi-Lacini.
  The examples are quotients of regular schemes by the cyclic group $G$ of order $p$. In characteristic $p$ or mixed characteristic, such quotients can exhibit a wide range of behavior. Our key technical tool is a sufficient condition for quotients by $G$ to have only toric singularities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02608v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Burt Totaro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Signed Goldman-Iwahori Space and Real Tropical Linear Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02619v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Goldman-Iwahori space of seminorms on a finite-dimensional vector space over a non-Archimedean field is a non-Archimedean analogue of a symmetric space. If, in addition, $K$ is real closed, we define a signed analogue of the Goldman-Iwahori space consisting of signed seminorms. This new space can be seen as the linear algebraic version of the real analytification of projective space over $K$. We study this space with methods from real tropical geometry by constructing natural real tropicalization maps from the signed Goldman-Iwahori space to all real tropicalized linear spaces. We prove that this space is the limit of all real tropicalized linear embeddings. We give a combinatorial interpretation of this result by showing that the signed Goldman-Iwahori space is the real tropical linear space associated to the universal realizable oriented matroid. In the constant coefficient case for $K = \mathbb{R}$, we describe this space explicitly and relate it to real Bergman fans.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02619v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Kuehn, Arne Kuhrs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A dual basis for the equivariant quantum $K$-theory of cominuscule varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02703v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The equivariant quantum $K$-theory ring of a flag variety is a Frobenius algebra equipped with a perfect pairing called the quantum $K$-metric. It is known that in the classical $K$-theory ring for a given flag variety the ideal sheaf basis is dual to the Schubert basis with regard to the sheaf Euler characteristic. We define a quantization of the ideal sheaf basis for the equivariant quantum $K$-theory of cominuscule flag varieties. These quantized ideal sheaves are then dual to the Schubert basis with regard to the quantum $K$-metric. We prove explicit type-uniform combinatorial formulae for the quantized ideal sheaves in terms of the Schubert basis for any cominuscule flag variety. We also provide an application ultilizing the quantized ideal sheaves to calculate the Schubert structure constants associated to multiplication by the top exterior power of the tautological quotient bundle in $QK_T(Gr(k,n))$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02703v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Summers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algorithm to Compute Orbit Zariski Closure in Affine Plane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02739</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02739v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The article demonstrates the procedure how to compute the Zariski closure of an orbit by an algebraic action of finitely generated group on the affine plane. First half of the algorithm is about deciding whether given finitely generated group is contained in an algebraic group. For the next half, we compute the totality of the invariant subvarieties for a single triangular automorphism. Then, the computation for the individual generators is applied to compute the orbit Zariski closure for a finitely generated group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02739v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Young Joon Ley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modules of derivations, logarithmic ideals and singularities of maps on analytic varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02947v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the module of derivations $\Theta_{h,M}$ attached to a given analytic map $h:(\mathbb C^n,0)\to (\mathbb C^p,0)$ and a submodule $M\subseteq \mathcal O_n^p$ and analyse several exact sequences related to $\Theta_{h,M}$. Moreover, we obtain formulas for several numerical invariants associated to the pair $(h,M)$ and a given analytic map germ $f:(\mathbb C^n,0)\to (\mathbb C^q,0)$. In particular, if $X$ is an analytic subvariety of $\mathbb C^n$, we derive expressions for analytic invariants defined in terms of the module $\Theta_X$ of logarithmic vector fields of $X$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02947v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carles Bivi\`a-Ausina, Konstantinos Kourliouros, Maria Aparecida Soares Ruas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Campana points and adelic approximation on toric varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03048</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03048v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a general framework for studying special subsets of rational points on an algebraic variety, termed $\mathcal{M}$-points. The notion of $\mathcal{M}$-points generalizes the concepts of integral points, Campana points and Darmon points. We introduce and study $M$-approximation over number fields and function fields, which is a notion that generalizes weak and strong approximation. We show that this property implies that the set of $\mathcal{M}$-points is not thin. We then give a simple characterisation of when a split toric varieties satisfy $M$-approximation, generalizing work of Nakahara and Streeter. Further, we determine when the set of $\mathcal{M}$-points on a split toric variety is thin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03048v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boaz Moerman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence of arithmetic degrees for generic orbits and dynamical Lang-Siegel problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03097v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove the existence of the arithmetic degree for dominant rational self-maps at any point whose orbit is generic. As a corollary, we prove the same existence for \'etale morphisms on quasi-projective varieties and any points on it. We apply the proof of this fact to dynamical Lang-Siegel problem. Namely, we prove that local height function associated with zero-dimensional subscheme grows slowly along orbits of a rational map under reasonable assumption. Also if local height function associated with any proper closed subscheme grows fast on a subset of an orbit of a self-morphism, we prove that such subset has Banach density zero under some assumptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03097v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yohsuke Matsuzawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Section conjectures over $\mathbb{C}$ and Kodaira fibrations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03248</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03248v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we propose and study topological and Hodge theoretic analogues of Grothendieck's section conjecture over the complex numbers. We study these questions in the context of family of curves, in particular Kodaira fibrations, and in the context of the family of Jacobians associated to a Kodaira fibration. We showed that in the case of family of curves, both the topological and Hodge-theoretic analogues of the injectivity part of the section conjecture holds, and that in the case of family of Jacobians, the topological analogue of the surjectivity part of the section conjecture does not hold in general. For family of curves, we also reduce the topological analogue of the surjectivity part of the section conjecture to the case where the families have no algebraic sections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03248v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Shuofeng Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Derivative of the Riemann-Hilbert map</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03296v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given a pair $(X,\nabla)$, consisting of a closed Riemann surface $X$ and a holomorphic connection $\nabla$ on the trivial principal bundle $X\times\mathrm{SL}_2(\mathbb{C})\to X$, the Riemann-Hilbert map sends $(X,\nabla)$ to its monodromy representation. We compute the derivative of this map, and provide a simple description of the locus where it is injective, recovering in the process several previously obtained results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03296v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Markovi\'c, Ognjen To\v{s}i\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relative Polar Multiplicities, the Real Link, and Morse Inequalities for Hypersurfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03313v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For a hypersurface defined by a complex analytic function, we derive Morse-type inequalities between the Betti numbers of the real link of the hypersurface and the relative polar multiplicities of the function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03313v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David B. Massey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a classification of planar functions in characteristic three</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03170v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Planar functions are functions over a finite field that have optimal combinatorial properties and they have applications in several branches of mathematics, including algebra, projective geometry and cryptography. There are two relevant equivalence relations for planar functions, that are isotopic equivalence and CCZ-equivalence. Classification of planar functions is performed via CCZ-equivalence which arises from cryptographic applications. In the case of quadratic planar functions, isotopic equivalence, coming from connections to commutative semifields, is more general than CCZ-equivalence and isotopic transformations can be considered as a construction method providing up to two CCZ-inequivalent mappings. In this paper, we first survey known infinite classes and sporadic cases of planar functions up to CCZ-equivalence, aiming to exclude equivalent cases and to identify those with the potential to provide additional functions via isotopic equivalence. In particular, for fields of order $3^n$ with $n\le 11$, we completely resolve if and when isotopic equivalence provides different CCZ-classes for all currently known planar functions. Further, we perform an extensive computational investigation on some of these fields and find seven new sporadic planar functions over $\mathbb{F}_{3^6}$ and two over $\mathbb{F}_{3^9}$. Finally, we give new simple quadrinomial representatives for the Dickson family of planar functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03170v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuele Andreoli, Lilya Budaghyan, Robert Coulter, Alise Haukenes, Nikolay Kaleyski, Enrico Piccione</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lattices, Gates, and Curves: GKP codes as a Rosetta stone</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03270v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill (GKP) codes are a promising candidate for implementing fault tolerant quantum computation in quantum harmonic oscillator systems such as superconducting resonators, optical photons and trapped ions, and in recent years theoretical and experimental evidence for their utility has steadily grown. It is known that logical Clifford operations on GKP codes can be implemented fault tolerantly using only Gaussian operations, and several theoretical investigations have illuminated their general structure. In this work, we explain how GKP Clifford gates arise as symplectic automorphisms of the corresponding GKP lattice and show how they are identified with the mapping class group of suitable genus $n$ surfaces. This correspondence introduces a topological interpretation of fault tolerance for GKP codes and motivates the connection between GKP codes (lattices), their Clifford gates, and algebraic curves, which we explore in depth. For a single-mode GKP code, we identify the space of all GKP codes with the moduli space of elliptic curves, given by the three sphere with a trefoil knot removed, and explain how logical degrees of freedom arise from the choice of a level structure on the corresponding curves. We discuss how the implementation of Clifford gates corresponds to homotopically nontrivial loops on the space of all GKP codes and show that the modular Rademacher function describes a topological invariant for certain Clifford gates implemented by such loops. Finally, we construct a universal family of GKP codes and show how it gives rise to an explicit construction of fiber bundle fault tolerance as proposed by Gottesman and Zhang for the GKP code. On our path towards understanding this correspondence, we introduce a general algebraic geometric perspective on GKP codes and their moduli spaces, which uncovers a map towards many possible routes of future research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03270v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Conrad, Ansgar G. Burchards, Steven T. Flammia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some remarks on Spin-orbits of unit vectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.11120</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.11120v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For $n \in \mathbb{N}$ and a commutative ring $R$ with $2 \in R^{\times}$, the group $SL_n (R)$ acts on the set $Um_n (R)$ of unimodular vectors of length $n$ and $Spin_{2n}(R)$ acts on the set of unit vectors $U_{2n-1}(R)$. We give an example of a ring for which the comparison map $Um_n (R)/SL_n (R) \rightarrow U_{2n-1}(R)/Spin_{2n}(R)$ fails to be bijective.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.11120v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tariq Syed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The symplectic form associated to a singular Poisson algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14921v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given an affine Poisson algebra, that is singular one may ask whether there is an associated symplectic form. In the smooth case the answer is obvious: for the symplectic form to exist the Poisson tensor has to be invertible. In the singular case, however, derivations do not form a projective module and the nondegeneracy condition is more subtle. For a symplectic singularity one may naively ask if there is indeed an analogue of a symplectic form. We examine an example of a symplectic singularity, namely the double cone, and show that here such a symplectic form exists. We use the naive de Rham complex of a Lie-Rinehart algebra. Our analysis of the double cone uses Gr\"obner bases calculations. We also give an alternative construction of the symplectic form that generalizes to categorical quotients of cotangent lifted representations of finite groups. We use the same formulas to construct a symplectic form on the simple cone, seen as a Poisson differential space and generalize the construction to linear symplectic orbifolds. We present useful auxiliary results that enable to explicitly determine generators for the module of derivations an affine variety. The latter may be understood as a differential space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14921v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hans-Christian Herbig, William Osnayder Clavijo Esquivel, Christopher Seaton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real plane separating (M-2)-curves of degree d and totally real pencils of degree (d-3)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09671v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is well known that a non-singular real plane projective curve of degree five with five connected components is separating if and only if its ovals are in non-convex position. In this article, this property is set into a different context and generalised to all real plane separating (M-2)-curves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09671v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matilde Manzaroli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the exponential algebraic geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17203v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The set of roots of any finite system of exponential sums in the space $\mathbb{C}^n$ is called an exponential variety. We define the intersection index of varieties of complementary dimensions, and the ring of classes of numerical equivalence of exponential varieties with operations "addition-union" and "multiplication-intersection". This ring is analogous to the ring of conditions of the torus $(\mathbb{C}\setminus 0)^n$ and is called the ring of conditions of $\mathbb{C}^n$. We provide its description in terms of convex geometry. Namely we associate an exponential variety with an element of a certain ring generated by convex polyhedra in $\mathbb{C}^n$. We call this element the Newtonization of the exponential variety. For example, the Newtonization of an exponential hypersurface is its Newton polyhedron. The Newtonization map defines an isomorphism of the ring of conditions to the ring generated by convex polyhedra in $\mathbb{C}^n$. It follows, in particular, that the intersection index of $n$ exponential hypersurfaces is equal to the mixed pseudo-volume of their Newton polyhedra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17203v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Kazarnovskii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounds on cohomological support varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.15574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.15574v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Over a local ring $R$, the theory of cohomological support varieties attaches to any bounded complex $M$ of finitely generated $R$-modules an algebraic variety $V_R(M)$ that encodes homological properties of $M$. We give lower bounds for the dimension of $V_R(M)$ in terms of classical invariants of $R$. In particular, when $R$ is Cohen-Macaulay and not complete intersection we find that there are always varieties that cannot be realized as the cohomological support of any complex. When $M$ has finite projective dimension, we also give an upper bound for $ \dim V_R(M)$ in terms of the dimension of the radical of the homotopy Lie algebra of $R$. This leads to an improvement of a bound due to Avramov, Buchweitz, Iyengar, and Miller on the Loewy lengths of finite free complexes. Finally, we completely classify the varieties that can occur as the cohomological support of a complex over a Golod ring.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.15574v2</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1090/btran/182</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Trans. Amer. Math. Soc. Ser. B 11 (2024), 703-726</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Briggs, Elo\'isa Grifo, Josh Pollitz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Valuative Section Conjecture, \'Etale Homotopy, and Berkovich Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.03970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.03970v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We reinterpret a result of Pop and Stix on the $p$-adic section conjecture in terms of Berkovich spaces and fixed points. In doing this, we see a version of the result extends to larger classes of fields, which in turn allows us to prove a valuative section conjecture type result for a larger class of varieties. This adds to the programme to reinterpret anabelian geometry results in terms of \'etale homotopy types.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.03970v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jesse Pajwani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chern Characteristics and Todd-Hirzebruch Identities for Transpolar Pairs of Toric Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07139</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07139v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Standard toric geometry methods used to construct Calabi-Yau varieties may be extended to complete intersections in non-Fano varieties encoded by star triangulating non-convex polytopes. Similarly, mirror symmetry is conjectured to hold in terms of a transpolar duality generalizing the original construction of Batyrev and Borisov. The associated mirror pairs naturally include certain flip-folded, multi-layered multihedral objects, inclusively named VEX multitopes, and a correspondingly generalized transpolar duality. These self-overlaying VEX multitopes, long since known in pre-symplectic geometry, are found to correspond to certain non-algebraic but smooth toric spaces with Chern classes that satisfy the standard Todd-Hirzebruch identities. The computation of diffeomorphism invariants, including characteristic submanifold intersection numbers, corroborates their recent inclusion in the connected web of Calabi-Yau spaces and associated string compactifications: They arise together with the standard (Fano/reflexive polytope) constructions, within deformation families of generalized complete intersections in products of projective spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07139v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Per Berglund, Tristan H\"ubsch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The solving degrees for computing Gr\"{o}bner bases of affine semi-regular polynomial sequences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03530</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03530v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Determining the complexity of computing Gr\"{o}bner bases is an important problem both in theory and in practice, and for that the solving degree plays a key role. In this paper, we study the solving degrees of affine semi-regular sequences and their homogenized sequences. Some of our results are considered to give mathematically rigorous proofs of the correctness of methods for computing Gr\"{o}bner bases of the ideal generated by an affine semi-regular sequence. This paper is a sequel of the authors' previous work and gives additional results on the solving degrees and important behaviors of Gr\"obner basis computation.
  We also define the generalized degree of regularity for a sequence of homogeneous polynomials. For the homogenization of an affine semi-regular sequence, we relate its generalized degree of regularity with its maximal Gr\"{o}bner basis degree (i.e., the solving degree of the homogenized sequence). The definition of a generalized (cryptographic) semi-regular sequence is also given, and it derives a new cryptographic assumption to estimate the security of cryptosystems and signature schemes. From our experimental observation, we raise a conjecture and some questions related to this generalized semi-regularity. These new definitions and our results provide a theoretical formulation of (somehow heuristic) discussions done so far in the cryptographic community.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03530v2</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Momonari Kudo, Kazuhiro Yokoyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
