<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG</link>
    <description>math.AG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 01:41:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Motivic versions of mass formulas by Krasner, Serre and Bhargava</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13481</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13481v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove motivic versions of mass formulas by Krasner, Serre and Bhargava concerning (weighted) counts of extensions of local fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13481v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takehiko Yasuda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quotient singularities by permutation actions are canonical</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13504</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13504v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The quotient variety associated to a permutation representation of a finite group has only canonical singularities in arbitrary characteristic. Moreover, the log pair associated to such a representation is Kawamata log terminal except in characteristic two, and log canonical in arbitrary characteristic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13504v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takehiko Yasuda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bernstein-Sato ideals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13560v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we review several results on the zero loci of Bernstein-Sato ideals related to singularities of hypersurfaces. This is an exposition for the Frontiers of Science Awards in Mathematics presenting results from one of our articles, with history, motivation, and further developments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13560v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nero Budur, Robin van der Veer, Lei Wu, Peng Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spaces of maps between real algebraic varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13757v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given two real algebraic varieties X and Y, we denote by R(X,Y) the set of all regular maps from X to Y. The set R(X,Y) is regarded as a topological subspace of the space C(X,Y) of all continuous maps from X to Y endowed with the compact-open topology. We prove, in a much more general setting than previously considered, that each path component of C(X,Y) contains at most one path component of R(X,Y), and for every positive integer k the inclusion map R(X,Y)--&gt;C(X,Y) induces an isomorphism between the kth homotopy groups of the corresponding path components. We also identify several cases where this inclusion map is a weak homotopy equivalence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13757v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wojciech Kucharz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meromorphic differentials, twisted DR cycles and quantum integrable hierarchies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13806v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We define twisted versions of the classical and quantum double ramification hierarchy construction based on intersection theory of the strata of meromorphic differentials in the moduli space of stable curves and $k$-twisted double ramification cycles for $k=1$, respectively, we prove their integrability and tau symmetry and study their connection. We apply the construction to the case of the trivial cohomological field theory to find it produces the KdV hierarchy, although its relation to the untwisted case is nontrivial. The key role of the KdV hierarchy in controlling the intersection theory of several natural tautological classes translates this relation into a series of remarkable identities between intersection numbers involving psi-classes, Hodge classes, Norbury's theta class and the strata of meromorphic differentials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13806v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xavier Blot, Paolo Rossi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A non-abelian version of Deligne's Fixed Part Theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13910</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13910v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We formulate and prove a non-abelian analog of Deligne's Fixed Part theorem on Hodge classes, revisiting previous work of Jost--Zuo, Katzarkov--Pantev and Landesman--Litt. To this aim we study algebraically isomonodromic extensions of local systems and we relate them to variations of Hodge structures, for example we show that the Mumford-Tate group at a generic point stays constant in an algebraically isomonodromic extension of a variation of Hodge structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13910v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H\'el\`ene Esnault, Moritz Kerz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Periods of Real Biextensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13997</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13997v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A real biextension is a real mixed Hodge structure that is an extension of R(0) by a mixed Hodge structure with weights $-1$ and $-2$. A unipotent real biextension over an algebraic manifold is a variation of mixed Hodge structure over it, each of whose fibers is a real biextension and whose weight graded quotients are do not vary. We show that if a unipotent real biextension has non abelian monodromy, then its ``general fiber'' does not split. This result is a tool for investigating the boundary behaviour of normal functions and is applied in arXiv:2408.07809 to study the boundary behaviour of the normal function of the Ceresa cycle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13997v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Richard Hain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Degeneracy Loci for Smooth Moduli of Sheaves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14021</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14021v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let S be a smooth projective surface over $\mathbb{C}$. We prove that, under certain technical assumptions, the degeneracy locus of the universal sheaf over the moduli space of stable sheaves is either empty or an irreducible Cohen-Macaulay variety of the expected dimension. We also provide a criterion for when the degeneracy locus is non-empty. This result generalizes the work of Bayer, Chen, and Jiang for the Hilbert scheme of points on surfaces.
  The above result is a special case of a general phenomenon: for a perfect complex of Tor-amplitude [0,1], the geometry of the degeneracy locus is closely related to the geometry of the derived Grassmannian. We analyze their birational geometry and relate it to the incidence varieties of derived Grassmannians. As a corollary, we prove a statement previously claimed by the author in arXiv:2408.06860.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14021v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimal model program for algebraically integrable adjoint foliated structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14258</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14258v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For $\mathbb Q$-factorial klt algebraically integrable adjoint foliated structures, we prove the cone theorem, the contraction theorem, and the existence of flips. Therefore, we deduce the existence of the minimal model program for such structures.
  We also prove the base-point-freeness theorem for such structures of general type and establish an adjunction formula and the existence of $\mathbb Q$-factorial quasi-dlt modifications for algebraically integrable adjoint foliated structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14258v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Cascini, Jingjun Han, Jihao Liu, Fanjun Meng, Calum Spicer, Roberto Svaldi, Lingyao Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Picard-Fuchs system for family of Kummer surfaces as subsystem of GKZ hypregeometric system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14271v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We determine a simple expression of the Picard-Fuchs system for a family of Kummer surfaces for all principally polarized Abelian surfaces. It is given by a system of linear partial differential equations in three variables of rank five. Our results are based on a Jacobian elliptic fibration on Kummer surfaces and a GKZ hypergeometric system suited to the elliptic fibration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14271v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Atsuhira Nagano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Positivity of the tangent bundle of rational surfaces with nef anticanonical divisor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14411v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the property of bigness of the tangent bundle of a smooth projective rational surface with nef anticanonical divisor. We first show that the tangent bundle $T_S$ of $S$ is not big if $S$ is a rational elliptic surface. We then study the property of bigness of the tangent bundle $T_S$ of a weak del Pezzo surface $S$. When the degree of $S$ is $4$, we completely determine the bigness of the tangent bundle through the configuration of $(-2)$-curves. When the degree $d$ of $S$ is less than or equal to $3$, we get a partial answer. In particular, we show that $T_S$ is not big when the number of $(-2)$-curves is less than or equal to $7-d$, and $T_S$ is big when $d=3$ and $S$ has the maximum number of $(-2)$-curves. The main ingredient of the proof is to produce irreducible effective divisors on $\mathbb{P}(T_S)$, using Serrano's work on the relative tangent bundle when $S$ has a fibration, or the total dual VMRT associated to a conic fibration on $S$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14411v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hosung Kim, Jeong-Seop Kim, Yongnam Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transition matrices and Pieri-type rules for polysymmetric functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13404</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13404v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Asvin G and Andrew O'Desky recently introduced the graded algebra P$\Lambda$ of polysymmetric functions as a generalization of the algebra $\Lambda$ of symmetric functions. This article develops combinatorial formulas for some multiplication rules and transition matrix entries for P$\Lambda$ that are analogous to well-known classical formulas for $\Lambda$. In more detail, we consider pure tensor bases $\{s^{\otimes}_{\tau}\}$, $\{p^{\otimes}_{\tau}\}$, and $\{m^{\otimes}_{\tau}\}$ for P$\Lambda$ that arise as tensor products of the classical Schur basis, power-sum basis, and monomial basis for $\Lambda$. We find expansions in these bases of the non-pure bases $\{P_{\delta}\}$, $\{H_{\delta}\}$, $\{E^+_{\delta}\}$, and $\{E_{\delta}\}$ studied by Asvin G and O'Desky. The answers involve tableau-like structures generalizing semistandard tableaux, rim-hook tableaux, and the brick tabloids of E\u{g}ecio\u{g}lu and Remmel. These objects arise by iteration of new Pieri-type rules that give expansions of products such as $s^{\otimes}_{\sigma}H_{\delta}$, $p^{\otimes}_{\sigma}E_{\delta}$, etc.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13404v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aditya Khanna, Nicholas A. Loehr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Torsion graded pieces of Nyggard filtration for crystalline representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13422v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $K$ be a unramified $p$-adic field with the absolute Galois group $G_K$ and $T$ a crystalline $\mathbb Z_p$-representation of $G_K$. We study the graded pieces of integral filtration on $D_{\rm dR}(T)$ given by Nyggard filtration of the attached Breuil-Kisin module of $T$. We show that the $i$-graded piece has nontrivial $p$-torsion only if $ i = r_j +m p$ for a Hodge-Tate weight $ r_j$ of $T$ and $m$ a positive integer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13422v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tong Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On fields of meromorphic functions on neighborhoods of rational curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14061v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Suppose that $F$ is a smooth and connected complex surface (not necessarily compact) containing a smooth rational curve with positive self-intersection. We prove that if there exists a non-constant meromorphic function on $F$, then the field of meromorphic functions on $F$ is isomorphic to the field of rational functions in one or two variables over $\mathbb C$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14061v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Serge Lvovski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Betti numbers and linear covers of points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14064v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove that for a finite set of points $X$ in the projective $n$-space over any field, the Betti number $\beta_{n,n+1}$ of the coordinate ring of $X$ is non-zero if and only if $X$ lies on the union of two planes whose sum of dimension is less than $n$. Our proof is direct and short, and the inductive step rests on a combinatorial statement that works over matroids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14064v1</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hailong Dao, Ben Lund, Sreehari Suresh-Babu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lauricella hypergeometric functions, unipotent fundamental groups of the punctured Riemann sphere, and their motivic coactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.06603</link>
      <description>arXiv:1907.06603v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The goal of this paper is to raise the possibility that there exists a meaningful theory of `motives' associated to certain hypergeometric integrals, viewed as functions of their parameters. It goes beyond the classical theory of motives, but should be compatible with it. Such a theory would explain a recent and surprising conjecture arising in the context of scattering amplitudes for a motivic Galois group action on Gauss' ${}_2F_1$ hypergeometric function, which we prove in this paper by direct means. More generally, we consider Lauricella hypergeometric functions and show on the one hand how the coefficients in their Taylor expansions can be promoted, via the theory of motivic fundamental groups, to motivic multiple polylogarithms. The latter are periods of ordinary motives and admit an action of the usual motivic Galois group, which we call the `local' action. On the other hand, we define lifts of the full Lauricella functions as matrix coefficients in a Tannakian category of twisted cohomology, which inherit an action of the corresponding Tannaka group. We call this the `global' action. We prove that these two actions, local and global, are compatible with each other, even though they are defined in completely different ways. The main technical tool is to prove that metabelian quotients of generalised Drinfeld associators on the punctured Riemann sphere are hypergeometric functions. We also study single-valued versions of these hypergeometric functions, which may be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1907.06603v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/nmj.2022.27</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nagoya Math. J. 249 (2023), 148-220</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Francis Brown, Cl\'ement Dupont</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The localization spectral sequence in the motivic setting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04217</link>
      <description>arXiv:2003.04217v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct and study a motivic lift of a spectral sequence associated to a stratified scheme, recently discovered by Petersen in the context of mixed Hodge theory and $\ell$-adic Galois representations. The original spectral sequence expresses the compactly supported cohomology of an open stratum in terms of the compactly supported cohomology of the closures of strata and the combinatorics of the poset underlying the stratification. Some of its special cases are classical tools in the study of arrangements of subvarieties and configuration spaces. Our motivic lift lives in the triangulated category of \'{e}tale motives and takes the shape of a Postnikov system. We describe its connecting morphisms and study some of its functoriality properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2003.04217v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.2140/agt.2024.24.1431</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Algebr. Geom. Topol. 24 (2024) 1431-1466</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Cl\'ement Dupont, Daniel Juteau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arnold's monotonicity problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.11795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2006.11795v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: According to the Kouchnirenko formula, the Milnor number of a generic isolated singularity with given Newton polyhedron is equal to the alternating sum of certain volumes associated to the Newton polyhedron. In this paper we obtain a non-negative analogue (i.e. without negative summands) of the Kouchnirenko formula. The analogue relies on the non-negative formula for the monodromy operator from arXiv:1405.5355 and formulas for the Milnor number from arXiv:math/9901107 . As an application we give a criterion for the Arnold's monotonicity problem (1982-16) in arbitrary dimension, which leads to complete solution in dimension up to $4$ and partial solution in dimension $5$. The latter relies on the classification of thin triangulations (or vanishing local h-polynomial) in dimension $2$ and $3$ from arXiv:1909.10843 (and from the book by Gelfand, Kapranov and Zelevinsky) and contains examples which differ dramatically from the ones which arise in dimension up to $3$ in arXiv:1705.00323 (see also arXiv:2001.10316 ). Some of the $4$-dimensional examples were first described in arXiv:1309.0630 in the context of the local monodromy conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2006.11795v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fedor Selyanin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extending torsors under quasi-finite flat group schemes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.16067</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.16067v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $R$ be a discrete valuation ring of field of fractions $K$ and of residue field $k$ of characteristic $p &gt; 0$.
  In an earlier work, we studied the question of extending torsors on $K$-curves into torsors over $R$-regular models of the curves in the case when the structural $K$-group scheme of the torsor admits a finite flat model over $R$. In this paper, we first give a simpler description of the problem in the case where the curve is semistable. Secondly, if $R$ is assumed to be Henselian and Japanese, we solve the problem of extending torsors even if the structural group does not admit a finite flat $R$-model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.16067v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sara Mehidi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>D-Algebraic Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.02512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.02512v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Differentially-algebraic (D-algebraic) functions are solutions of polynomial equations in the function, its derivatives, and the independent variables. We revisit closure properties of these functions by providing constructive proofs. We present algorithms to compute algebraic differential equations for compositions and arithmetic manipulations of univariate D-algebraic functions and derive bounds for the order of the resulting differential equations. We apply our methods to examples in the sciences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.02512v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rida Ait El Manssour, Anna-Laura Sattelberger, Bertrand Teguia Tabuguia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Affine Deligne-Lusztig varieties via the double Bruhat graph I: Semi-infinite orbits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.05933</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.05933v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a new language to describe the geometry of affine Deligne-Lusztig varieties in affine flag varieties. This first part of a two paper series develops the definition and fundamental properties of the double Bruhat graph by studying semi-infinite orbits. This double Bruhat graph was originally introduced by Naito-Watanabe to study periodic $R$-polynomials. We use it to describe the geometry of many affine Deligne-Lusztig varieties, overcoming a previously ubiquitous regularity condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.05933v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felix Schremmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local structure of the Teichm\"uller and the Riemann moduli stacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.15244</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.15244v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The goal of this note is to introduce an interesting question proposed by D. Rydh on an analytic version of the local structure of Artin stacks saying that near points with linearly reductive stabilizers, Artin stacks are \'etale-locally quotient stacks. We give some supporting evidence by verifying it on two fundamental classes of classical analytic moduli spaces: the Teichm\"uller moduli space and the Riemann moduli space of integrable complex structures whose analytic stack versions have been constructed by a recent work of L. Meersseman.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.15244v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s13348-024-00450-y</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Collectanea Mathematica (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>An Khuong Doan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$q$-de Rham complexes of higher level</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.02057</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.02057v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article, we construct two kinds of de Rham-like complexes which compute the cohomology of complete crystals on the higher-level $q$-crystalline site, which was introduced in a previous article of the author. One complex is the $q$-analog of the higher de Rham complex constructed by Miyatani, and another complex is the $q$-analog of the jet complex constructed by Le Stum-Quir\'os. The complexes we construct can also be regarded as the higher-level analogs of the $q$-de Rham complex.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.02057v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kimihiko Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A counterexample to the PIA conjecture for minimal log discrepancies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06164v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We give a counterexample to the PIA (precise inversion of adjunction) conjecture for minimal log discrepancies. We also give a counterexample to the LSC conjecture for families.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06164v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yusuke Nakamura, Kohsuke Shibata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the irregular Riemann-Hilbert correspondence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04260v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The original Riemann-Hilbert problem asks to find a Fuchsian ordinary differential equation with prescribed singularities and monodromy in the complex line. In the early 1980's Kashiwara solved a generalized version of the problem, valid on complex manifolds of any dimension. He presented it as a correspondence between regular holonomic D-modules and perverse sheaves. The analogous problem where one drops the regularity condition remained open for about thirty years. We solved it in the paper that received a 2024 Frontiers of Science Award. Our construction requires in particular an enhancement of the category of perverse sheaves. Here, using some examples in dimension one, we wish to convey the gist of the main ingredients used in our work.
  This is a written account of a talk given by the first named author at the International Congress of Basic Sciences on July 2024 in Beijing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04260v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea D'Agnolo, Masaki Kashiwara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Rank of the Normal Functions of the Ceresa and Gross--Schoen Cycles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07809v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The main result is that when the genus is at least 3, the rank of the normal function function of the Ceresa cycle over the moduli space of curves has maximal rank. This result was proved independently by Z. Gao and S.-W. Zhang (arXiv:2407.01304) by different methods. In genus 3 we show that the Green--Griffiths invariant of this normal function is a Teichmuller modular form of weight (4,0,-1) and use this to show that the rank of the Ceresa normal function is exactly 1 along the hyperelliptic locus.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07809v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Richard Hain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local-global principle for leaf schemes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11188v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study Hodge loci as leaf schemes of foliations. The main ingredient is the Gauss-Manin connection matrix of families of projective varieties. We also aim to investigate a conjecture on the ring of definition of leaf schemes and its consequences such as the algebraicity of leaf schemes (Cattani-Deligne-Kaplan theorem in the case of Hodge loci). This conjecture is a consequence of a local-global principle for leaf schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11188v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hossein Movasati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Structures of Large Scale Interacting Systems via Uniform Functions and Forms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.04699</link>
      <description>arXiv:2009.04699v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this article, we investigate the topological structure of large scale interacting systems on infinite graphs, by constructing a suitable cohomology which we call the uniform cohomology. The central idea for the construction is the introduction of a class of functions called uniform functions. Uniform cohomology provides a new perspective for the identification of macroscopic observables from the microscopic system. As a straightforward application of our theory when the underlying graph has a free action of a group, we prove a certain decomposition theorem for shift-invariant closed uniform forms. This result is a uniform version in a very general setting of the decomposition result for shift-invariant closed $L^2$-forms originally proposed by Varadhan, which has repeatedly played a key role in the proof of the hydrodynamic limits of nongradient large scale interacting systems. In a subsequent article, we use this result as a key to prove Varadhan's decomposition theorem for a general class of large scale interacting systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2009.04699v5</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kenichi Bannai, Yukio Kametani, Makiko Sasada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Affine Deligne-Lusztig varieties via the double Bruhat graph II: Iwahori-Hecke algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.06873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.06873v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a new language to describe the geometry of affine Deligne-Lusztig varieties in affine flag varieties. This second part of a two paper series uses this new language, i.e. the double Bruhat graph, to describe certain structure constants of the Iwahori-Hecke algebra. As an application, we describe nonemptiness and dimension of affine Deligne-Lusztig varieties for most elements of the affine Weyl group and arbitrary $\sigma$-conjugacy classes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.06873v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felix Schremmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The quantum connection, Fourier-Laplace transform, and families of A-infinity-categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.13567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.13567v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Take a closed monotone symplectic manifold containing a smooth anticanonical divisor. The quantum connection on its cohomology has singularities at zero and infinity (in the quantum parameter). At zero it has a regular singular point, by definition. We show that the singularity at infinity is of unramified exponential type. The argument involves: realizing cohomology as a deformation of the symplectic cohomology of the divisor complement; the corresponding deformation of the wrapped Fukaya category; a new categorical interpretation of the Fourier-Laplace transform of D-modules; and the regularity theorem of Petrov-Vaintrob-Vologodsky in noncommutative geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.13567v3</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Pomerleano, Paul Seidel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric Langlands duality for periods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.00180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.00180v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study conjectures of Ben-Zvi--Sakellaridis--Venkatesh that categorify the relationship between automorphic periods and $L$-functions in the context of the Geometric Langlands equivalence. We provide evidence for these conjectures in some low-rank examples, by using derived Fourier analysis and the theory of chiral algebras to categorify the Rankin-Selberg unfolding method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.00180v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tony Feng, Jonathan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equivariant $K$-theory of cellular toric varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14201v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this article we describe the $T_{comp}$-equivariant topological $K$-ring of a $T$-{\it cellular} complete toric variety. We further show that $K_{T_{comp}}^0(X)$ is isomorphic as an $R(T_{comp})$-algebra to the ring of piecewise Laurent polynomial functions on the associated fan denoted $PLP(\Delta)$. Furthermore, we compute a basis for $K_{T_{comp}}^0(X)$ as a $R(T_{comp})$-module and multiplicative structure constants with respect to this basis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14201v4</guid>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Uma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deformation Families of Quasi-Projective Varieties and Symmetric Projective K3 Surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16208v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The main aim of this paper is to construct a complex analytic family of symmetric projective K3 surfaces through a compactifiable deformation family of complete quasi-projective varieties from $\text{CP}^2 \text{$\#$9} \overline{\text{CP}}^2$. Firstly, for an elliptic curve $C_0$ embedded in $\text{CP}^2$, let $S \cong \text{CP}^2 \text{$\#$9} \overline{\text{CP}}^2$ be the blow up of $\text{CP}^2$ at nine points on the image of $C_0$ and $C$ be the strict transform of the image. Then if the normal bundle satisfies the Diophantine condition, a tubular neighborhood of the elliptic curve $C$ can be identified through a toroidal group. Fixing the Diophantine condition, a smooth compactifiable deformation of $S\backslash C$ over a 9-dimensional complex manifold is constructed. What's more, with an ample line bundle fixed on $S$, complete K\"ahler metrics can be constructed on the quasi-projective variety $S\backslash C$. So complete K\"ahler metrics are constructed on each quasi-projective variety fiber of the smooth compactifiable deformation family. Then a complex analytic family of symmetric projective K3 surfaces over a 10-dimensional complex manifold is constructed through the smooth compactifiable deformation family of complete quasi-projective varieties and an analogue deformation family.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16208v4</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fan Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
