<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG</link>
    <description>math.AG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 04:00:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The integral chow ring of $M_2^{ct}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04912v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper computes the integral Chow ring of the moduli space $M_2^{ct}$ of stable genus 2 curves of compact type. This is done by excising boundary strata from $\bar M_2$ one-by-one. During this process, we determine the Chow rings of all other open strata in $\bar M_2$ with $Z[1/2]$-coefficients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04912v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joseph Helfer, Eric Jovinelly, Eric Larson, Anda Tenie, Chengxi Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Splicing skew shaped positroids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04923v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Skew shaped positroids (or skew shaped positroid varieties) are certain Richardson varieties in the flag variety that admit a realization as explicit subvarieties of the Grassmannian $\mathrm{Gr}(k,n)$. They are parametrized by a pair of Young diagrams $\mu \subseteq \lambda$ fitting inside a $k \times (n-k)$-rectangle. For every $a = 1, \dots, n-k$, we define an explicit open set $U_a$ inside the skew shaped positroid $S^{\circ}_{\lambda/\mu}$, and show that $U_a$ is isomorphic to the product of two smaller skew shaped positroids. Moreover, $U_a$ admits a natural cluster structure and the aforementioned isomorphism is quasi-cluster in the sense of Fraser. Our methods depend on realizing the skew shaped positroid as an explicit braid variety, and generalize the work of the first and third authors for open positroid cells in the Grassmannian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04923v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eugene Gorsky, Soyeon Kim, Tonie Scroggin, Jos\'e Simental</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homotopy Wave Function in Algebraic Geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05099v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose the homotopy shape of the Segal topos of derived stacks over simplicial k-algebras as the higher homotopical generalization of the concept of wave function in Quantum Mechanics</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05099v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renaud Gauthier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Derived deformation functors, Koszul duality, and Maurer-Cartan spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05307v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We summarise the chain of comparisons showing Hinich's derived Maurer-Cartan functor gives an equivalence between differential graded Lie algebras and derived Schlessinger functors on Artinian differential graded-commutative algebras. We include some motivating deformation problems and analogues for more general Koszul dual pairs of operads.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05307v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. P. Pridham</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Derived derivations govern contraderived deformations of dg algebras over dg (pr)operads</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05317v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that Hinich's simplicial nerve of the differential graded Lie algebra (DGLA) of derived derivations of a dg algebra $A$ over a dg properad $\mathcal{P}$ is equivalent to the space of deformations of $A$ as a $\mathcal{P}_{\infty}$-algebra in Positselski's contraderived dg category. This resolves Hinich's counterexamples to the general existence of derived deformations. It also generalises his results when $A$ is homologically bounded below, since contraderived deformations are then precisely derived deformations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05317v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. P. Pridham</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On semipositive piecewise linear functions in non-archimedean analytic geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05513v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we generalize results on Zhang's semipositive model metrics from the algebraic setting to strictly analytic spaces over a non-trivially valued non-Archimedean field. We prove stability under pointwise limits and under forming the maximum. We also prove the maximum principle. As tools, we use a local lifting theorem from the special fiber to the generic fiber of a model and an affinoid Bieri--Groves theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05513v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Walter Gubler, Joseph Rabinoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supersingular curves via the Shimura--Taniyama method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04878v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For a curve which admits an abelian cover of the projective line branched at three points, we study when its reduction to positive characteristic is supersingular. Using the method of Shimura and Taniyama, we give a complete classification when the genus of the curve is at most 10. The natural density of the set of primes for which this construction yields a supersingular curve is larger than expected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04878v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeremy Booher, Rachel Pries</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spherical representation spaces of quivers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05407v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider representation spaces of quivers, together with their base change action, and classify the spherical varieties among them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05407v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jennifer M\"uller, Markus Reineke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Derived Adelic Cohomology Conjecture for Elliptic Curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05614v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a novel derived cohomological framework for the Birch and Swinnerton-Dyer (BSD) conjecture for elliptic curves. In our approach, local arithmetic data are encoded in derived sheaves which, when glued via a mapping cone construction, yield an adelic complex. A natural Postnikov filtration on this complex gives rise to a spectral sequence whose first nonzero differential detects the analytic and algebraic rank of the curve. Moreover, the determinant of this differential equals the combination of classical invariants appearing in the BSD formula. We present rigorous constructions of the derived sheaves involved and establish their key properties, including explicit connections to L-functions through cohomological interpretations. Extensive numerical evidence across curves of various ranks, including those with non-trivial Tate-Shafarevich groups, supports these structural predictions. Our framework unifies several existing approaches to the BSD conjecture, providing a cohomological interpretation that explains both the rank equality and the precise formula where previous methods addressed only partial aspects of the conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05614v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dane Wachs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homological mirror symmetry for projective K3 surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05680</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05680v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove the homological mirror symmetry conjecture of Kontsevich for K3 surfaces in the following form: The Fukaya category of a projective K3 surface is equivalent to the derived category of coherent sheaves on the mirror, which is a K3 surface of Picard rank $19$ over the field $\mathbb{C}((q))$ of formal Laurent series. This builds on prior work of Seidel, who proved the theorem in the case of the quartic surface, Sheridan, Lekili--Ueda, and Ganatra--Pardon--Shende.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05680v1</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Hacking, Ailsa Keating</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundary stratifications of Hurwitz spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05688</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05688v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $\mathcal{H}$ be a Hurwitz space that parametrises holomorphic maps to $\mathbb{P}^1$. Abramovich, Corti and Vistoli, building on work of Harris and Mumford, describe a compactification $\overline{\mathcal{H}}$ with a natural boundary stratification. We show that the irreducible strata of $\overline{\mathcal{H}}$ are in bijection with combinatorial objects called decorated trees (up to a suitable equivalence), and that containment of irreducible strata is given by edge contraction of decorated trees. This combinatorial description allows us to define a tropical Hurwitz space, refining a definition given by Cavalieri, Markwig and Ranganathan. We also discuss applications to complex dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05688v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Darragh Glynn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forms on Berkovich spaces based on harmonic tropicalizations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.05741</link>
      <description>arXiv:2111.05741v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce tropical skeletons for Berkovich spaces based on results of Ducros. Then we study harmonic functions on good strictly analytic spaces over a non-trivially valued non-Archimedean field. Chambert-Loir and Ducros introduced bigraded sheaves of smooth real-valued differential forms on Berkovich spaces by pulling back Lagerberg forms with respect to tropicalization maps. We give a new approach in which we allow pullback by more general harmonic tropicalizations to get a larger sheaf of differential forms with essentially the same properties, but with a better cohomological behavior. A crucial ingredient is that tropical varieties arising from harmonic tropicalization maps are balanced.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2111.05741v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Walter Gubler, Philipp Jell, Joseph Rabinoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification of Unimodal Parametric Plane Curve Singularities in Positive Characteristic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.09409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.09409v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In 2011, Hefez and Hernandes completed Zariski's analytic classification of plane branches belonging to a certain equisingularity class by creating "very short" parameterizations over the complex numbers. Their results were used by Mehmood and Pfister to classify unimodal plane branches in characteristic 0 by constructing lists of normal forms. The goal of this paper is to give a complete classification of unimodal plane branches over an algebraically closed field of positive characteristic. Since the methods of Hefez and Hernandes are not applicable in positive characteristic, we use a different approach and, for some sporadic singularities in small characteristic, computations with SINGULAR. Our methods are characteristic-independent and provide a different proof for the classification in characteristic 0, showing at the same time that this classification holds also in large characteristic. The main theoretical ingredients are the semicontinuity of the semigroup and the modality, which we prove.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.09409v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jalgebra.2024.07.018</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Algebra 660 (2024) 451-512</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Ahsan Binyamin, Gert-Martin Greuel, Khawar Mehmood, Gerhard Pfister</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sections of Lagrangian fibrations on holomorphic symplectic manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07877v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $M$ be a holomorphically symplectic manifold, equipped with a Lagrangian fibration $\pi:\; M \to X$. A degenerate twistor deformation (sometimes also called ``a Tate-Shafarevich twist'') is a family of holomorphically symplectic structures on $M$ parametrized by $H^{1,1}(X)$. All members of this family are equipped with a holomorphic Lagrangian projection to $X$, and their fibers are isomorphic to the fibers of $\pi$. Assume that $M$ is a compact hyperkahler manifold of maximal holonomy, and the general fiber of the Lagrangian projection $\pi$ is primitive (that is, not divisible) in integer homology. We also assume that $\pi$ has reduced fibers in codimension 1. Then $M$ has a degenerate twistor deformation $M'$ such that the Lagrangian projection $\pi:\; M' \to X$ admits a meromorphic section.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07877v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fedor Bogomolov, Ljudmila Kamenova, Misha Verbitsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Derived characterizations for rational pairs \`{a} la Schwede-Takagi and Koll\'{a}r-Kov\'{a}cs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02783v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Our work establishes derived characterizations for notions of rational pairs \`{a} la Schwede--Takagi and Koll\'{a}r--Kov\'{a}cs. We use a concept of generation in triangulated categories, introduced by Bondal and Van den Bergh, to study these classes of singularities for pairs. One component of our work introduces rational pairs \`{a} la Koll\'{a}r--Kov\'{a}cs for quasi-excellent schemes of characteristic zero, which gives a Kov\'{a}cs style splitting criterion and a Kov\'{a}cs-Schwede style cohomological vanishing result.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02783v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pat Lank, Peter McDonald, Sridhar Venkatesh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the canonical bundle formula and effective birationality for Fano varieties in char $p&gt;0$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12041v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we give some results on the birational geometry of varieties of Fano type and boundedness problems in positive characteristic, including a result ensuring that boundedness is invariant under normalizations, a canonical bundle formula for fibrations of Fano type which is easier to use, and the effective birationality of certain weak Fano varieties with good singularities, which is predicted by the BAB conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12041v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xintong Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A counterexample to the Jordan-H\"older property for polarizable semiorthogonal decompositions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12075v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that the Jordan-H\"older property fails for polarizable semiorthogonal decompositions -- those where every factor admits a Bridgeland stability condition. Counterexamples exist among Fukaya categories of surfaces and bounded derived categories of smooth projective varieties. Furthermore, we give an example of a smooth and proper pre-triangulated dg category with positive rank Grothendieck group which does not admit a stability condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12075v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabian Haiden, Dongjian Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
