<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG</link>
    <description>math.AG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 02:49:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Isocrystals and de Rham-Witt connections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01902v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the notion of integrable connections for a sheaf of differential graded algebras on a topological space. We then describe them in the finite locally projective setting, when the sheaf is either the de Rham complex of a formal or a weakly formal scheme, or for the convergent or the overconvergent de Rham-Witt complex on a smooth scheme over a perfect field of positive characteristic. This enables us to give a new description of convergent and overconvergent isocrystals with a Frobenius structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01902v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rub\'en Mu\~noz--Bertrand</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperflex loci of hypersurfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02075v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The $k$-flex locus of a projective hypersurface $V\subset \mathbb P^n$ is the locus of points $p\in V$ such that there is a line with order of contact at least $k$ with $V$ at $p$. Unexpected contact orders occur when $k\ge n+1$. The case $k=n+1$ is known as the classical flex locus, which has been studied in details in the literature. This paper is dedicated to compute the dimension and the degree of the $k$-flex locus of a general degree $d$ hypersurface for any value of $k$. As a corollary, we compute the dimension and the degree of the biggest ruled subvariety of a general hypersurface. We show moreover that through a generic $k$-flex point passes a unique $k$-flex line and that this line has contact order exactly $k$ if $k\le d$. The proof is based on the computation of the top Chern class of a certain vector bundle of relative principal parts, inspired by and generalizing a work of Eisenbud and Harris.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02075v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cristina Bertone, Martin Weimann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spinor modifications of conic bundles and derived categories of 1-nodal Fano threefolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02082v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given a flat conic bundle $X/S$ and an abstract spinor bundle $\mathcal{F}$ on $X$ we define a new conic bundle $X_{\mathcal{F}}/S$, called a spinor modification of $X$, such that the even Clifford algebras of $X/S$ and $X_{\mathcal{F}}/S$ are Morita equivalent and the orthogonal complements of $\mathrm{D}^{\mathrm{b}}(S)$ in $\mathrm{D}^{\mathrm{b}}(X)$ and $\mathrm{D}^{\mathrm{b}}(X_{\mathcal{F}})$ are equivalent as well. We demonstrate how the technique of spinor modifications works in the example of conic bundles associated with some nonfactorial 1-nodal prime Fano threefolds. In particular, we construct a categorical absorption of singularities for these Fano threefolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02082v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Kuznetsov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A twisted derived category of hyper-K\"ahler varieties of $K3^{[n]}$-type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02143v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We conjecture that a natural twisted derived category of any hyper-K\"ahler variety of $K3^{[n]}$-type is controlled by its Markman-Mukai lattice. We prove the conjecture under numerical constraints, and our proof relies heavily on Markman's projectively hyperholomorphic bundle and a recently proven twisted version of the D-equivalence conjecture.
  In particular, we prove that any two fine moduli spaces of stable sheaves on a $K3$ surface are derived equivalent if they have the same dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02143v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruxuan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faber's socle intersection numbers via Gromov--Witten theory of elliptic curve</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02297</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02297v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The goal of this very short note is to give a new proof of Faber's formula for the socle intersection numbers in the tautological ring of $\mathcal{M}_g$. This new proof exhibits a new beautiful tautological relation that stems from the recent work of Oberdieck--Pixton on the Gromov--Witten theory of the elliptic curve via a refinement of their argument, and some straightforward computation with the double ramification cycles that enters the recursion relations for the Hamiltonians of the KdV hierarchy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02297v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xavier Blot, Sergey Shadrin, Ishan Jaztar Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quadratically Enriched Plane Curve Counting via Tropical Geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02569</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02569v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that the quadratically enriched count of rational curves in a smooth toric del Pezzo surface passing through $k$-rational points and pairs of conjugate points in quadratic field extensions $k\subset k(\sqrt{d_i})$ can be determined by counting certain tropical stable maps through vertically stretched point conditions with a suitable multiplicity. Building on the floor diagram technique in tropical geometry, we provide an algorithm to compute these numbers.
  Our tropical algorithm computes not only these new quadratically enriched enumerative invariants, but simultaneously also the complex Gromov-Witten invariant, the real Welschinger invariant counting curves satisfying real point conditions only, the real Welschinger invariant of curves satisfying pairs of complex conjugate and real point conditions, and the quadratically enriched count of curves satisfying $k$-rational point conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02569v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'es Jaramillo Puentes, Hannah Markwig, Sabrina Pauli, Felix R\"ohrle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dirichlet Species and Arithmetic Zeta Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01833v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Though Joyal's species are known to categorify generating functions in enumerative combinatorics, they also categorify zeta functions in algebraic geometry. The reason is that any scheme $X$ of finite type over the integers gives a "zeta species" $Z_X$, and any species $F$ gives a Dirichlet series $\widehat{F}$, in such a way that $\widehat{Z}_X$ is the arithmetic zeta function of $X$, a well-known Dirichlet series that encodes the number of points of $X$ over each finite field. Specifically, a $Z_X$-structure on a finite set is a way of making that set into a semisimple commutative ring, say $k$, and then choosing a $k$-point of the scheme $X$. This is joint work with James Dolan.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01833v1</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John C. Baez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Siegel's problem and Dwork's conjecture for $G$-functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02147</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02147v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We answer in the negative Siegel's problem for $G$-functions, as formulated by Fischler and Rivoal. Roughly, we prove that there are $G$-functions that cannot be written as polynomial expressions in algebraic pullbacks of hypergeometric functions; our examples satisfy differential equations of order two, which is the smallest possible. In fact, we construct infinitely many non-equivalent rank-two local systems of geometric origin which are not algebraic pullbacks of hypergeometric local systems, thereby providing further counterexamples to Dwork's conjecture and answering a question by Krammer. The main ingredients of the proof are a Lie algebra version of Goursat's lemma, the monodromy computations of hypergeometric local systems due to Beukers and Heckman, as well as results on invariant trace fields of Fuchsian groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02147v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Javier Fres\'an, Yeuk Hay Joshua Lam, Yichen Qin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ovoids of $Q^+(7,q)$ of low-degree</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02219</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02219v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ovoids of the hyperbolic quadric $Q^+(7,q)$ of $\mathrm{PG}(7,q)$ have been extensively studied over the past 40 years, partly due to their connections with other combinatorial objects. It is well known that the points of an ovoid of $Q^+(7,q)$ can be parametrized by three polynomials $f_1(X,Y,Z)$, $f_2(X,Y,Z)$, $f_3(X,Y,Z)$. In this paper, we classify ovoids of $Q^+(7,q)$ of low degree, specifically under the assumption that $f_1(X,Y,Z)$, $f_2(X,Y,Z)$, $f_3(X,Y,Z)$ have degree at most 3. Our approach relies on the analysis of an algebraic hypersurface associated with the ovoid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02219v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniele Bartoli, Nicola Durante, Giovanni Giuseppe Grimaldi, Marco Timpanella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Motives of nullcones of quiver representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02353v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We derive two formulas for motives of nullcones of quiver representations, one being explicit, the other being of wall-crossing type.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02353v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lydia G\"osmann, Markus Reineke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On singular Hilbert schemes of points: local structures and tautological sheaves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2101.05236</link>
      <description>arXiv:2101.05236v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show an intrinsic version of Thomason's fixed point theorem. Then we determine the local structure of the Hilbert scheme of $\leq 7$ points in $\mathbb{A}^3$. In particular, we show that in these cases the points with the same extra dimension have the same singularity type. Using these results we compute the equivariant Hilbert functions at the singularities and verify a conjecture of Zhou on the Euler characteristics of tautological sheaves on Hilbert schemes of points on $\mathbb{P}^3$ for $\leq 6$ points.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2101.05236v5</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaowen Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum cohomology of blowups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.13555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.13555v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove a decomposition theorem of the quantum cohomology D-module of the blowup of a smooth projective variety X along a smooth subvariety Z. The main tools we use are shift operators and Fourier analysis for equivariant quantum cohomology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.13555v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroshi Iritani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orlov's Theorem for dg-algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.17422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.17422v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A landmark theorem of Orlov relates the singularity category of a graded Gorenstein algebra to the derived category of the associated noncommutative projective scheme. We generalize this theorem to the setting of differential graded algebras. As an application, we obtain new cases of the Lattice Conjecture in noncommutative Hodge theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.17422v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Advances in Mathematics 460 (2025), 110035</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Michael K. Brown, Prashanth Sridhar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Wall Crossing Formula for Motivic Enumerative Invariants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17681v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove an analog of the wall crossing formula for Welschinger invariants relating the difference of signed curve counting of real curves passing through configurations that differ by a pair of complex conjugated points, and a correspondence Welschinger invariant of the blow up.
  We prove this analogue for the motivic count of rational curves of fixed degree passing through a generic configuration of points, counted with a motivic multiplicity in the Grothendieck-Witt ring of a base field, extending the notions in the correspondence theorem between motivic invariants for $k$-rational point conditions and tropical curves.
  We use this formula to compute the degree 4 motivic enumerative invariants of the projective plane counting curves passing through configurations of points defined over quadratic extensions of a base field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17681v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'es Jaramillo Puentes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compactifications of C^n and the complex projective space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07207v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that the complex projective space is the only projective manifold compactifying $\mathbb{C}^n$ by a smooth connected hypersurface, provided $n$ is even. In the odd dimensional case we give some partial results. The case when $n \equiv 1 $ mod $4$ has now been settled by Ping Li.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07207v4</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Peternell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The number of smooth varieties in an MMP on a 3-fold of Fano type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01370v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove that for a threefold of Fano type $X$ and a movable $\mathbb{Q}$-Cartier Weil divisor $D$ on $X$, the number of smooth varieties that arise during the running of a $D$-MMP is bounded by $1 + h^1(X, 2D)$. Additionally, we prove a partial converse to the Kodaira vanishing theorem for a movable divisor on a threefold of Fano type.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01370v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Donghyeon Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cherkis bow varieties and Coulomb branches of quiver gauge theories of affine type $A$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1606.02002</link>
      <description>arXiv:1606.02002v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that Coulomb branches of quiver gauge theories of affine type $A$ are Cherkis bow varieties, which have been introduced as ADHM type description of moduli space of instantons on the Taub-NUT space equivariant under a cyclic group action.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1606.02002v4</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiraku Nakajima, Yuuya Takayama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimal reduction type and the Kazhdan-Lusztig map</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.13642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2010.13642v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce the notion of minimal reduction type of an affine Springer fiber, and use it to define a map from the set of conjugacy classes in the Weyl group to the set of nilpotent orbits. We show that this map is the same as the one defined by Lusztig, and that the Kazhdan-Lusztig map is a section of our map. This settles several conjectures in the literature. For classical groups, we prove more refined results by introducing and studying the "skeleta" of affine Springer fibers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2010.13642v3</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Indag. Math. (N.S.) 32 (2021), no. 6, 1240--1274</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zhiwei Yun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One-form symmetries and the 3d $\mathcal{N}=2$ $A$-model: Topologically twisted indices and CS theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18141v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study three-dimensional $\mathcal{N}=2$ supersymmetric Chern-Simons-matter gauge theories with a one-form symmetry in the $A$-model formalism on $\Sigma_g\times S^1$. We explicitly compute expectation values of topological line operators that implement the one-form symmetry. This allows us to compute the topologically twisted index on the closed Riemann surface $\Sigma_g$ for any real compact gauge group $G$ as long as the ground states are all bosonic. All computations are carried out in the effective $A$-model on $\Sigma_g$, whose $S^1$ ground states are the so-called Bethe vacua. We discuss how the 3d one-form symmetry acts on the Bethe vacua, and also how its 't Hooft anomaly constrains the vacuum structure. In the special case of the $\text{SU}(N)_K$ $\mathcal{N}=2$ Chern-Simons theory, we obtain results for the $(\text{SU}(N)/\mathbb Z_r)^{\theta}_K$ $\mathcal{N}=2$ Chern-Simons theories, for all non-anomalous $\mathbb Z_r \subseteq \mathbb Z_N$ subgroups of the centre of the gauge group, and with a $\mathbb Z_r$ $\theta$-angle turned on. In the special cases with $N$ even, $\frac{N}{r}$ odd and $\frac{K}{r}$ even, we find a mixed 't Hooft anomaly between gravity and the $\mathbb Z_r^{(1)}$ one-form symmetry of the $\text{SU}(N)_K$ theory, and the infrared 3d TQFT after gauging is spin. In all cases, we count the Bethe states and the higher-genus states in terms of refinements of Jordan's totient function. This counting gives us the twisted indices if and only if the infrared 3d TQFT is bosonic. Our results lead to precise conjectures about integrality of indices, which appear to have a strong number-theoretic flavour. Note: this paper directly builds upon unpublished notes by Brian Willett from 2020.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18141v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cyril Closset, Elias Furrer, Osama Khlaif</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The generic geometry of steady state varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17798v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We answer several fundamental geometric questions about reaction networks with power-law kinetics, on topics such as generic finiteness of the number of steady states, robustness, and nondegenerate multistationarity. In particular, we give an ideal-theoretic characterization of generic absolute concentration robustness, as well as conditions under which a network that admits multiple steady states also has the capacity for nondegenerate multistationarity. The key tools underlying our results come from the theory of vertically parametrized systems, and include a linear algebra condition that characterizes when the steady state system has positive nondegenerate zeros.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17798v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.MN</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elisenda Feliu, Oskar Henriksson, Beatriz Pascual-Escudero</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
