<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG</link>
    <description>math.AG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 08:06:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Abel maps for integral curves via a derived perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11786v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a general framework for Abel maps associated with a family $X/S$ of integral curves using derived algebraic geometry. For compactified Picard schemes, our approach yields relative quasi-smooth derived enhancements of the Quot schemes $\mathrm{Quot}_{\omega/X/S}^d$ and, in the Gorenstein case, of the Hilbert schemes of points $\mathrm{Hilb}_{X/S}^d$ on $X/S$. These constructions naturally generalize to higher rank torsion-free sheaves and their coherent systems.
  We obtain unified semiorthogonal decompositions for the derived categories of these derived moduli spaces, broadly extending previous results for symmetric powers, varieties of linear series, and Thaddeus pairs to torsion-free sheaves on integral curves.
  Central to our approach are two novel tools of independent interest: the $\mathcal{Q}$-complex, a derived generalization of Grothendieck's $Q$-module and the Altman--Kleiman $H$-module, and a derived theory of moduli of extensions that extends Lange's classical framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11786v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qingyuan Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Curve semistable Higgs bundles and smooth projective varieties whose canonical bundle is ample</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12062v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Considering the so-called Simpson system on smooth projective varieties, defined over an algebraically closed field of characteristic $0$, whose canonical bundle is ample, I prove the stability of this Higgs bundle. From this I obtain another proof of the Guggenheimer-Yau inequality. Where the equality holds, I prove that the discriminant class of the Simpson system vanishes. This follows from the study of the relations between ampleness and numerically nefness for Higgs bundles which "feel" the Higgs field and (semi)stability. Moreover, I obtain another proof of algebraic hyperbolicity of these varieties which furnishes a lower bound on a real positive constant related to this property; to best of my knowledge, this is the first and unique result of this type.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12062v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Armando Capasso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The quasisymmetric flag variety: a toric complex on noncrossing partitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12171</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12171v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop the geometric theory of equivariant quasisymmetry via a new ``quasisymmetric flag variety''. This is a toric complex in the flag variety whose fixed point set is the set of noncrossing partitions, and whose cohomology ring is the ring of quasisymmetric coinvariants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12171v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nantel Bergeron, Lucas Gagnon, Philippe Nadeau, Hunter Spink, Vasu Tewari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On surfaces satisfying $q=0,p_g=0,c_1^2=9$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12339v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: I consider the class of surfaces $X$ over algebraically closed fields with numerical invariants given in the title. In characteristic zero, this class contains fake projective planes which were introduced by David Mumford. I prove that in characteristic $p&gt;0$ such surfaces are Hodge-Witt and also ordinary under additional assumptions. In particular, fake projective planes are Hodge-Witt (Theorem 3.1). I show that if $X$ is Frobenius split then $X\simeq \mathbb{P}^2$ (Theorem 4.1). I also establish a characteristic free characterization of the projective plane using the Nori fundamental group scheme (Theorem 5.1). Finally, I show that any fake projective plane over a number field has good ordinary reduction at all but finitely many primes and in particular fake projective planes exist in positive characteristics (Theorem 6.1).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12339v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kirti Joshi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A motivic discrepancy function on arc spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12420v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: At the heart of motivic integration is a change-of-variables formula which relates motivic integrals along proper birational maps of varieties. The formula was first proved by Kontsevich for smooth blow-ups of smooth varieties, and extended to arbitrary resolutions of singularities by Denef and Loeser. The purpose of this paper is to establish a general change-of-variables formula for a proper birational morphism of arbitrary varieties in arbitrary characteristics that does not rely on resolutions of singularities. As an application, we prove that birationally equivalent Calabi-Yau manifolds of positive characteristics define the same class in the motivic ring, extending the well-known result from characteristic zero.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12420v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tommaso de Fernex, Zach Mere</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arcs on rational double points in arbitrary characteristic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12423</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12423v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that the Nash problem holds for two-dimensional rational double points in all characteristics. The proof is based on a direct computation of the families of arcs through these singularities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12423v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tommaso de Fernex, Shih-Hsin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetric power of higher dimensional varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12654v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study several properties of the symmetric power $S^mX$ of a smooth variety $X$. We describe the Picard and divisor class groups of $S^mX$ when $X$ is projective. We give a complete description of the stratification of $S^mX$ by iterated singular locus in terms of some combinatorial data regarding partitions of the integer $m.$ This gives a new viewpoint of a natural stratification of $S^mX$ by multiplicities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12654v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashima Bansal, Supravat Sarkar, Shivam Vats</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BRIDGES Lectures: G2 in action, and a mathematical theory of exceptions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12757v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The BRIDGES meeting in gauge theory, extremal structures, and stability was held in June 2024 at l'Institut d'\'Etudes Scientifiques de Carg\`ese in Corsica, organized by Daniele Faenzi, Eveline Legendre, Eric Loubeau, and Henrique S\'a Earp. The first week was a summer school consisting of four independent but related lecture series by Oscar Garc\'ia-Prada, Spiro Karigiannis, Laurent Manivel, and Ruxandra Moraru. The present document consists of notes for the lecture series by Laurent Manivel on the geometry of G2 and the other exceptional complex Lie groups. Some assistance in the preparation of these notes by the author was provided by several participants of the summer school. See the Comments field for more information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12757v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laurent Manivel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniqueness of Skabelund Maximal Curves via Genus and Automorphism Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12959v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a genus-automorphism characterization of maximal Skabelund curves, showing that they are uniquely determined up to $\mathbb{F}_{q}$-isomorphism by their genus and automorphism group structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12959v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saeed Tafazolian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Motivic Mirror Symmetry for Character Stacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12995</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12995v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a motivic version of T. Hausel and M. Thaddeus' Topological Mirror Symmetry for character stacks associated with arbitrary semisimple groups, which is an analogue of F. Loeser and D. Wyss' result for Chow motives of moduli spaces of Higgs bundles. As first steps towards it, we generalize A. Mellit's cell decomposition to arbitrary connected and reductive groups. We use it to describe all automorphisms on the associated character stacks. Then we show that the Weyl pairing induces a duality between cells that interchanges automorphisms by connected components. As a toy example, we show that these results imply our conjecture for the special linear group of rank two.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12995v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas de Amorin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A survey on birational Rigidity of threefold Weighted Complete Intersections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13025v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We survey what is known about Fano threefold weighted complete intersections from the point of view of birational rigidity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13025v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tiago Duarte Guerreiro, Takuzo Okada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Report on $\mathbb{E}_\infty$-descendability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13089v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the notion of $\mathbb{E}_\infty$-descendability as well as a derived variant. We prove that several classes of descendable maps of commutative rings are $\mathbb{E}_\infty$-descendable. As an application, we prove a variant of Tannaka duality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13089v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Antieau, Germ\'an Stefanich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complementary bodies in sphere packing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11633v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Symbolic and graphical tools, such as Mathematica, enable precise visualization and analysis of void spaces in sphere packings. In the cubic close packing (CCP, or face-centred cubic packing; FCC) arrangement these voids can be partitioned into repeating geometric units we term spherically truncated polyhedra - bodies analogous to plane-truncated polyhedra but bounded by both planar and spherical surfaces. These structures are relevant in geometric studies and applications such as modelling diffusion in porous media and biological tissues. This work examines the properties of these complementary bodies, deriving their surface area-to-volume ratios, which are significant in physical contexts; and we establish a result concerning the packing density of truncated tetrahedra and octahedra, demonstrating how they tile the interstitial space surrounding packed spheres. These findings contribute to a deeper understanding of classical packing problems and their geometrical complements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11633v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philip W. Kuchel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Quantum Analogue of the Pfaffian-Determinant Identity, An Algebraic and Geometric Study in the q-Skew-Symmetric Case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11634v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper explores a quantum deformation of the classical identity Pf(A)^2 = det(A) for 2n by 2n skew-symmetric matrices A, which classically relates the square of the Pfaffian to the determinant. In the quantum setting, we study matrices whose entries lie in a noncommutative algebra and satisfy the q-skew-symmetry relations a_ji = -q times a_ij and a_ii = 0, where q is a nonzero complex parameter. This deformation introduces new algebraic structures and challenges in defining quantum analogues of classical invariants.
  We construct the quantum Pfaffian Pf_q(A) and quantum determinant det_q(A) using two main approaches: the Faddeev-Reshetikhin-Takhtajan (FRT) construction and quantum exterior algebras. We provide precise definitions, derive algebraic identities, and analyze properties of these quantum objects. Special attention is given to verifying the quantum analogue of the Pfaffian-determinant identity, q to the power c times Pf_q(A)^2 = det_q(A), in low-dimensional cases such as 2n = 4, using explicit symbolic computations.
  We also explore geometric interpretations within the context of braided vector spaces, quantum symplectic geometry, and deformations of volume forms. The paper includes examples and diagrams highlighting connections between combinatorics, representation theory, and noncommutative geometry. Potential applications are discussed in quantum invariant theory, low-dimensional topology, and categorified geometry. These results contribute to the broader understanding of quantum analogues of classical linear algebra and their role in quantum group theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11634v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hani Safadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Vojta's proof of the Mordell conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11888v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper re-organizes Vojta's proof of the Mordell conjecture (i.e. Faltings' theorem) in terms of Arakelov geometry. A new ingredient is to replace an application of Gillet--Soule's arithmetic Riemannn--Roch theorem by that of Yuan's arithmetic Siu inequality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11888v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinyi Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jacobian Ideals of Hyperplane Arrangements and their Graded Betti Numbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12113v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A hyperplane arrangement $\cA$ is said to be free if the corresponding Jacobian ideal $J_\cA$ is Cohen-Macaulay. If $\cA$ is free then $J_\cA$ is unmixed (i.e. equidimensional). Freeness is an important property, yet its presence is not well understood. A conjecture of Terao says that freeness of $\cA$ depends only on the intersection lattice of $\cA$. Given an arrangement $\cA$, we define the ideal $J_\cA^{top}$ to be the intersection of the codimension 2 primary components of $J_\cA$. This ideal is unmixed, but not necessarily Cohen-Macaulay; if $\cA$ is free then $J_\cA = J_\cA^{top}$. We develop a new method for studying the ideals $J_\cA$ and $J_\cA^{top}$ and establish results in the spirit of Terao's conjecture, focusing on $J_\cA^{top}$ rather than $J_\cA$. It is based on a new application of liaison theory, the general residual of $\cA$. This residual ideal defines a scheme with surprisingly simple properties. These allow us to track back to $J_\cA^{top}$. Extending earlier results with Schenck, we identify mild conditions on a hyperplane arrangement which imply that the Hilbert function of $\Jac( f_\cA)^{top}$ or even its graded Betti numbers, are determined by the intersection lattice of $\cA$. We establish new bounds on the global Tjurina number of a hyperplane arrangement. For line arrangements, we show that the graded Betti numbers of $\Jac( f_\cA)^{sat}$ determine the graded Betti numbers of $\Jac( f_\cA)$, and of the corresponding Milnor module $J_\cA^{sat}/J_\cA$. We obtain a new freeness criterion for line arrangements -- it highlights the fact that free line arrangements are special by proving that a related codimension two ideal has the least possible number of generators, namely two, if and only if $\cA$ is free. We illustrate our results by computing the graded Betti numbers for a number of basic arrangements that were not accessible with previous methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12113v1</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan Migliore, Uwe Nagel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 4-fold Pandharipande--Thomas vertex and Jeffrey--Kirwan residue</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12128v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a contour integral formalism for computing the K-theoretic equivariant Pandharipande--Thomas (PT) 4-vertex. Within the Jeffrey--Kirwan (JK) residue framework, we show that the PT 4-vertex can be obtained from the same integrand as the Donaldson--Thomas (DT) 4-vertex by choosing a different reference vector. We illustrate the formalism through examples involving curves and surfaces on the 4-fold. Furthermore, we investigate the DT/PT correspondence for the 4-fold setting together with its higher rank and supergroup-like generalizations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12128v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taro Kimura, Go Noshita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local constancy of reduction type and related invariants for curves in $p$-adic families</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12329v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the behaviour of the reduction type and related invariants of curves in families of curves over a discretely valued field. By a family, we will mean a set of curves obtained by perturbing the coefficients of the defining equations. We will show that the reduction type in these families is locally constant in the topology induced by the valuation. We also derive local constancy results for some related invariants, such as the Tamagawa number, the Birch and Swinnerton-Dyer 'fudge factor' and the Galois representation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12329v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jakab Schrettner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the analytic rank of the twin prime elliptic curve $y^2=x(x-2)(x-p)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12340</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12340v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $p\geq 7$ and suppose $(p,p-2)$ are twin prime numbers, in [Hatley, 2009], the elliptic curve $E_p:y^2=x(x-2)(x-p)$ was considered in the context of a conjecture by Jason Beers about the Mordell-Weil ranks of $E_p/\mathbb{Q}$. I show that for $p\equiv 3,5\bmod 8$, the analytic rank of $E_p$ is at least one (Theorem 1.1.2) in line with Beers' predictions. This is done by finding a formula (Theorem 4.1.1) for the global root number of $E_p$ for all twin prime pairs. I also show that Beers' conjecture, that for $p\equiv 1\bmod 8$ the rank of $E_p$ is two, is false as stated because $E_{73}$ has rank zero. In the light of Theorem 4.1.1, Beers' conjecture needs to be modified: if $p\equiv 1\bmod 8$ then the rank of $E_p$ is zero or two (Conjecture 5.3.1).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12340v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kirti Joshi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tilting theory for hypersurface singularities of dimension one</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12581v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It was shown by Buchweitz, the first author, and Yamaura that any $\mathbb{N}$-graded commutative Gorenstein ring $R$ of Krull dimension one with $R_0$ a field admits a standard silting object $V$ in the stable category $\underline{\mathrm{CM}\, \!}_0^{\mathbb{Z}}R$. Moreover, they proved that the object $V$ is tilting if and only if the $a$-invariant $a$ is non-negative. In this article, under the additional assumption that $R$ is a hypersurface singularity, we give an explicit description of the endomorphism algebra of $V$ and prove that it is Iwanaga-Gorenstein of self-injective dimension at most $2$. In the case of where $a$ is negative, we give an explicit description of the endomorphism dg algebra of $V$ and prove that it is Gorenstein. Moreover, we give a characterization of Gorensteinness of homologically finite dg algebras in terms of Serre functors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12581v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Osamu Iyama, Junyang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symplectic Eichler criterion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12624</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12624v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove an Eichler-type criterion for symplectic lattices which determines in a simple way when two primitive vectors are equivalent under a canonical congruence subgroup of the symplectic group. This is supplemented by another, related criterion which determines when a given primitive vector is splitting. Both criteria use the discriminant groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12624v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shouhei Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Upper Bounds on the Sizes of Finite Orbits for Unramified Morphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12639v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove that for a dynamical system on an algebraic variety over $\overline{\mathbb{Q}}$ generated by finitely many unramified endomorphisms, it is decidable whether a given point has a finite orbit. This is achieved by establishing an effective upper bound for the size of finite orbits in integral algebraic dynamical systems with unramified morphisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12639v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Young Kyun Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>K3 surfaces and cubic fourfolds with Abelian motive</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.05969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2012.05969v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that cubic fourfolds with lattice of algebraic 2-cycles of rank greater than 19 have abelian and finite dimensional (in the sense of Kimura) Chow motive. This also implies Abelianity and finite dimensionality of the motive of related hyperKahler varieties, such as the Fano variety of lines and the LLSvS 8fold. A similar remark allows us to show the Abelianity of the motive of an infinity of LSV 10folds, and of other hyperKahler 10folds associated to the twisted intermediate Jacobian fibration of cubic fourfolds with an associated K3 surface. After that, starting from certain 4-dimensional families of K3 surfaces, we construct two families of Fano varieties whose Chow motive is finite dimensional. Varieties from the first family are some quadric surface fibrations, and contain the finite dimensional transcendental motive of a K3 surface. Varieties from the second family are singular cubic fourfolds, and their motives are Schur-finite and Abelian in Voevodsky's triangulated category of motives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2012.05969v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanine Awada, Michele Bolognesi, Robert Laterveer, Claudio Pedrini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Birational induction of nilpotent orbit covers in exceptional types</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.01838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.01838v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a semisimple simply connected algebraic group over ${\mathbb C}$ of exceptional type. For each $G$-equivariant nilpotent cover of a nilpotent coadjoint $G$-orbit ${\mathbb O}$, we determine the unique birationally rigid induction datum from which it is birationally induced.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.01838v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Westaway</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundedness of klt good minimal models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.03313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.03313v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For good minimal models with klt singularities, polarized by Weil divisors that are relatively nef and big over the bases of the Iitaka fibration, we show that, after fixing appropriate numerical invariants, they form a bounded family. As an application, we construct separated coarse moduli spaces for klt good minimal models polarized by line bundles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.03313v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaowei Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relative Gromov-Witten and maximal contact conics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.08487</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.08487v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We discuss some properties of the relative Gromov--Witten invariants counting rational curves with maximal contact order at one point. We compute the number of Cayley's sextactic conics to any smooth plane curve $Y$. In particular, we compute the contribution, from double covers of inflectional lines, to a certain degree $2$ relative Gromov--Witten invariant relative to $Y$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.08487v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00013-025-02169-z</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Giosu\`e Muratore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unirationality of the universal moduli space of semistable bundles over smooth curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.01041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.01041v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct explicit dominant, rational morphisms from projective bundles over rational varieties to relevant moduli spaces, showing their unirationality. These constructions work for $U_{r,d,g}$; for all ranks, degrees and genus $2\leq g \leq 9$. Furthermore, the arguments presented also show that a similar conclusion can be made for $U_{r, \mathcal{L}, g}$ for all $r,d$ and unirational $M_g$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.01041v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shubham Saha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Hodge structure on the singularity category of a complex hypersurface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09988</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09988v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a complex affine hypersurface with isolated singularity determined by a homogeneous polynomial, we identify the noncommutative Hodge structure on the periodic cyclic homology of its singularity category with the classical Hodge structure on the primitive cohomology of the associated projective hypersurface. As a consequence, we show that the Hodge conjecture for the projective hypersurface is equivalent to a dg-categorical analogue of the Hodge conjecture for the singularity category.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09988v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Annals of K-theory 10(2) (2025), 237-277</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Michael K. Brown, Mark E. Walker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ranks of matrix factorizations and sheaf cohomology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.01060v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Buchweitz-Greuel-Schreyer conjectured in 1987 a lower bound on the ranks of matrix factorizations over certain local hypersurface rings. We study a graded version of this conjecture, and we show that it implies a novel conjecture concerning the cohomology of sheaves over non-Fano projective hypersurfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.01060v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proceedings of the AMS 153(8) (2025), 3291-3301</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Michael K. Brown, Mark E. Walker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimal model program for normal pairs along log canonical locus in complex analytic setting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04057</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04057v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish the minimal model theory for normal pairs along log canonical locus in the complex analytic setting. This is the complex analytic analog of the previous result by the author.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04057v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kenta Hashizume</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A polynomial formula for the perspective four points problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13058</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13058v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a fast and accurate solution to the perspective $n$-points problem, by way of a new approach to the n=4 case. Our solution hinges on a novel separation of variables: given four 3D points and four corresponding 2D points on the camera canvas, we start by finding another set of 3D points, sitting on the rays connecting the camera to the 2D canvas points, so that the six pair-wise distances between these 3D points are as close as possible to the six distances between the original 3D points. This step reduces the perspective problem to an absolute orientation problem, which has a solution via explicit formula. To solve the first problem we set coordinates which are as orientation-free as possible: on the 3D points side our coordinates are the squared distances between the points. On the 2D canvas-points side our coordinates are the dot products of the points after rotating one of them to sit on the optical axis. We then derive the solution with the help of a computer algebra system. Our solution is an order of magnitude faster than state of the art algorithms, while offering similar accuracy under realistic noise. Moreover, our reduction to the absolute orientation problem runs two orders of magnitude faster than other perspective problem solvers, allowing extremely efficient seed rejection when implementing RANSAC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13058v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Lehavi, Brian Osserman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extending one-forms on $F$-regular singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17148</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17148v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove the logarithmic extension theorem for one-forms on strongly $F$-regular singularities. Additionally, we establish the logarithmic extension theorem for one-forms on three-dimensional klt singularities in characteristic $p&gt;41$. To this end, we reduce the problem to the logarithmic extension theorem for two-dimensional klt singularities with imperfect residue fields using a technique based on Cartier operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17148v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tatsuro Kawakami, Kenta Sato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On The Geometry and Topology of Cayley Condition in Poncelet Porism for Triangles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19349v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates the differential-geometric and topological properties of the Cayley condition in Poncelet porism for triangles, defined as the locus of pairs of non-degenerate conics that admit a Poncelet triangle. While the algebraic condition for this porism, established by Cayley, is classical, the geometric nature of the set of solutions has remained largely unexplored. We demonstrate that this Cayley set is a smooth, connected, 9-dimensional complex manifold. This is proven by showing it is an open subset of a smooth algebraic variety endowed with a trivial fiber bundle structure over the space of non-degenerate conics.
  To further analyze its structure, we construct the moduli space of transversely intersecting conic pairs under the action of $\mathbb{P}GL_3(\mathbb{C})$ and identify it with an open subset of $\mathbb{CP}^2/S_3$. We compute the fundamental group of a generic orbit.
  The elliptic j-invariant is then introduced as a holomorphic map on this space of conics, which factors through this moduli space. We analyze the subset of the Cayley set where this map is a submersion - its regular part - which corresponds to excluding points whose j-invariant is one of the critical values $0$ or $1728$. We prove that this regular part is the total space of a fiber bundle over $\C \setminus \{0,1728\}$. This structure allows for the computation of the fundamental group via the long exact sequence of homotopy.
  Finally, we provide a principal bundle formulation for the Poncelet correspondence itself over orbits of conic pairs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19349v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yirmeyahu Kaminski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Delta-matroids and toric degenerations in OG(n,2n+1)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16133v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct an explicit, embedded degeneration of the general torus orbit closure in the maximal orthogonal Grassmannian OG(n,2n+1) into a union of Richardson varieties. In particular, we deduce a formula for the cohomology class of the torus orbit closure, as a sum of products of Schubert classes. The moment map images of the degenerate pieces are the base polytopes of their underlying delta-matroids, and give a polyhedral decomposition of the unit hypercube, which had previously been studied by Chen-Sanchez-Veliz-Ying.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16133v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Chen, Carl Lian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometry of Supermanifolds through Sheaf and Ringed Space Methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01726v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces the concept of supermanifolds, viewed as the super-analogues of classical manifolds. Instead of treating supermanifolds as sets of points, we adopt an algebraic-geometric perspective, emphasizing the algebra of functions and utilizing the framework of ringed spaces and sheaf theory. We begin by constructing presheaves and sheaves to define locally ringed spaces, which model the local structure of supermanifolds. Superfunctions, a key element, are shown to differ significantly from ordinary functions, leading to a richer structure. We also prove a key characterization theorem for morphisms between supermanifolds and demonstrate that the category of supermanifolds admits finite products. This approach provides a solid foundation for further studies in mathematics and theoretical physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01726v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mousa Rahseed, Michel Egeileh, Abdallah Assi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear syzygies of curves in weighted projective space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.09150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.09150v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop analogues of Green's $N_p$-conditions for subvarieties of weighted projective space, and we prove that such $N_p$-conditions are satisfied for high degree embeddings of curves in weighted projective space. A key technical result links positivity with low degree (virtual) syzygies in wide generality, including cases where normal generation fails.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.09150v2</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Compositio Mathematica, 161 (2025), 916-944</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Michael K. Brown, Daniel Erman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noncommutative crepant resolutions of $cA_n$ singularities via Fukaya categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.06592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.06592v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We compute the wrapped Fukaya category $\mathcal{W}(T^*S^1, D)$ of a cylinder relative to a divisor $D= \{p_1,\ldots, p_n\}$ of $n$ points, proving a mirror equivalence with the category of perfect complexes on a crepant resolution (over $k[t_0,\ldots, t_n]$) of the singularity $uv=t_0t_1\ldots t_n$. Upon making the base-change $t_i= f_i(x,y)$, we obtain the derived category of any crepant resolution of the $cA_{n}$ singularity given by the equation $uv= f_0\ldots f_n$. These categories inherit braid group actions via the action on $\mathcal{W}(T^*S^1,D)$ of the mapping class group of $T^*S^1$ fixing $D$. We also give a geometric model of the derived contraction algebra of a $cA_n$ singularity in terms of the relative Fukaya category of the disc.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.06592v3</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan David Evans, Yanki Lekili</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calabi-Yau metrics on rank two symmetric spaces with horospherical tangent cone at infinity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.05122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.05122v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that on every non-$G_2$ complex symmetric space of rank two, there are complete Calabi-Yau metrics of Euclidean volume growth with prescribed horospherical singular tangent cone at infinity, providing the first examples of affine Calabi-Yau smoothings of singular and irregular tangent cone. As a corollary, we obtain infinitely many examples of Calabi-Yau manifolds degenerating to the tangent cone in a single step, supporting a recent conjecture by Sun-Zhang, which was only proved when the tangent cone at infinity has only an isolated singularity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.05122v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tran-Trung Nghiem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A transversality theorem for semi-algebraic sets with application to signal recovery from the second moment and cryo-EM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04354v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Semi-algebraic priors are ubiquitous in signal processing and machine learning. Prevalent examples include a) linear models where the signal lies in a low-dimensional subspace; b) sparse models where the signal can be represented by only a few coefficients under a suitable basis; and c) a large family of neural network generative models. In this paper, we prove a transversality theorem for semi-algebraic sets in orthogonal or unitary representations of groups: with a suitable dimension bound, a generic translate of any semi-algebraic set is transverse to the orbits of the group action. This, in turn, implies that if a signal lies in a low-dimensional semi-algebraic set, then it can be recovered uniquely from measurements that separate orbits.
  As an application, we consider the implications of the transversality theorem to the problem of recovering signals that are translated by random group actions from their second moment. As a special case, we discuss cryo-EM: a leading technology to constitute the spatial structure of biological molecules, which serves as our prime motivation. In particular, we derive explicit bounds for recovering a molecular structure from the second moment under a semi-algebraic prior and deduce information-theoretic implications. We also obtain information-theoretic bounds for three additional applications: factoring Gram matrices, multi-reference alignment, and phase retrieval. Finally, we deduce bounds for designing permutation invariant separators in machine learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04354v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tamir Bendory, Nadav Dym, Dan Edidin, Arun Suresh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some coefficients of rank 2 cluster scattering diagrams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.21916v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The purpose of this paper is to translate the expression of rank 2 cluster scattering diagrams via dilogarithm elements into via formal power series. As a corollary, we prove some conjectures introduced by Thomas Elgin, Nathan Reading, and Salvatore Stella.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.21916v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryota Akagi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-valued periods of meromorphic modular forms and a motivic interpretation of the Gross-Zagier conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.04844v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A well-known conjecture of Gross and Zagier states that the values of the higher automorphic Green's function at pairs of points with complex multiplication in the upper half-plane are proportional to the logarithm of an algebraic number. It was recently settled in the case of congruence subgroups of the form $\Gamma_0(N)$ by analytic methods. In this paper we provide a geometric and motivic interpretation of the general conjecture, and show that it is a consequence of a standard conjecture in the theory of motives. In addition, we define a new class of matrix-valued higher Green's functions for both odd and even weight modular forms, and show that they are single-valued periods of a motive constructed from a suitable moduli stack of elliptic curves with marked points. The motive has the structure of a biextension involving symmetric powers of the motives of elliptic curves. This suggests a very general extension of the Gross-Zagier conjecture relating values of matrix-valued higher Green's functions at points which do not necessarily have complex multiplication to special values of $L$-functions. In particular, our motivic interpretation of the Gross-Zagier log-algebraicity conjecture enables us to give a completely geometric proof in level 1 and weight 4 by showing that the motive of the moduli stack $\mathcal{M}_{1,3}$ of elliptic curves with 3 marked points is mixed Tate.
  In the course of this paper we develop many new foundational results on: the theory of weak harmonic lifts, meromorphic modular forms, biextensions of modular motives, and their corresponding algebraic de Rham cohomology and single-valued periods, which may all be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.04844v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francis Brown, Tiago J. Fonseca</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
