<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG</link>
    <description>math.AG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 04:01:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A refinement on the local cactus rank algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15062v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an algorithm to recover a minimal local apolar scheme to a homogeneous polynomial $F$. The socle degree of the scheme determines whether it is evinced by a Generalized Additive Decomposition (GAD) of $F$ or of an extension. We give constructive procedures for both cases and compute the Hilbert function efficiently via Hankel operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15062v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandra Bernardi, Oriol Reig Fit\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singularities of symmetric powers and irrationality of motivic zeta functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15065</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15065v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $K_0(\mathcal{V}_{K})$ be the Grothendieck ring of varieties over a field $K$ of characteristic zero, and let $\mathbb{L} = [\mathbb{A}^1_{K}]$ denote the Lefschetz class. We prove that if a $K$-variety has $\mathbb{L}$-rational singularities, then all its symmetric powers also have $\mathbb{L}$-rational singularities. We then use this result to show that, for a smooth complex projective variety $X$ of dimension greater than one, the rationality of its Kapranov motivic zeta function $Z(X, t)$ (viewed as a formal power series over $K_0(\mathcal{V}_{K})$) implies that the Kodaira dimension of $X$ is negative and that $X$ does not admit global nonzero differential forms of even degree. This extends the irrationality part of the Larsen-Lunts rationality criterion from the surface case to arbitrary dimension. We also discuss some applications of these results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15065v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Shein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Milnor fibrations and oriented matroids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15331v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a combinatorial model for the Milnor fibration of a complexified real arrangement using oriented matroids. It is a poset quasi-fibration, a notion recently introduced by the first author, whose domain is a subdivision of the Salvetti complex stemming from a natural subdivision of the dual oriented matroid complex. This yields a concrete finite regular CW complex which is homotopy equivalent to the Milnor fiber of the complexified real arrangement and implies that the homotopy type of the Milnor fiber of a complexified real arrangement only depends on the underlying combinatorial structure given by its oriented matroid. Moreover, our construction works for any oriented matroid, disregarding realizability, so we obtain a notion of a combinatorial Milnor fibration for any oriented matroid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15331v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul M\"ucksch, Masahiko Yoshinaga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of distinguished matrices of isolated hypersurface singularities through their spectral numbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15497</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15497v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Isolated hypersurface singularities come equipped with distinguished bases of their Milnor lattices and with upper triangular integral matrices, which are called here distinguished matrices. These matrices form an orbit of a braid group and a sign change group. This paper proposes to characterize the distinguished matrices of singularities within all upper triangular integral matrices in terms of the variance of certain spectral numbers. It succeeds in the positive definite and the positive semidefinite cases. The ADE root lattices are crucial. In the semidefinite cases, results on non-reduced presentations of Weyl group elements are used.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15497v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sven Balnojan, Claus Hertling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On relative vertical compactification of weakly square complete adic spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15707</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15707v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove for a morphism $f \colon X \rightarrow S$ locally of $^+$weakly finite type, separated and taut, where $X$ is a weakly square complete adic space and $S$ a square complete and stable adic space, there exists a universal vertical compactification $f' \colon X' \rightarrow S$. This provides a generalized version of Huber's proof of universal compactification of morphisms between analytic adic spaces. Notably, we will see that for the compactification, it is not necessary to assume that the adic spaces are locally Noetherian. In the fourth section we give an explicit and simple construction of $X'$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15707v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ronald Solodov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the generic fibers and true base of parabolic $\mathrm{SO}_{2n}$-Hitchin systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15714</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15714v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we confirm a physical conjecture regarding the parabolic $\mathrm{SO}_{2n}$-Hitchin system, showing that Hitchin map factors through a finite cover of the Hitchin base that is isomorphic to an affine space. We first show that the generic Hitchin fiber is disconnected, with the number of components determined by the degree of the generalized Springer map, and then construct the cover explicitly. To this end, we introduce and study a new class of moduli spaces, termed \emph{residually nilpotent Hitchin systems}, and analyze their generic Hitchin fibers. Furthermore, we uncover an interesting connection between self-duality of the generic Hitchin fiber and special nilpotent orbits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15714v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bin Wang, Xueqing Wen, Yaoxiong Wen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Vanishing of Gromov--Witten Invariants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15715v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the decision problem of whether a particular Gromov--Witten invariant on a partial flag variety is zero. We prove that for the $3$-pointed, genus zero invariants, this problem is in the complexity class ${\sf AM}$ assuming the Generalized Riemann Hypothesis (GRH), and therefore lies in the second level of polynomial hierarchy ${\sf PH}$.
  For the proof, we construct an explicit system of polynomial equations through a translation of the defining equations. We also need to prove an extension of the Parametric Hilbert's Nullstellensatz to obtain our central reduction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15715v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igor Pak, Colleen Robichaux, Weihong Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum cohomology of variations of GIT quotients and flips</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15770</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15770v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a decomposition theorem for the quantum cohomology of variations of GIT quotients. More precisely, for any reductive group $G$ and a simple $G$-VGIT wall-crossing $X_- \dashrightarrow X_+$ with a wall $S$, we show that the quantum $D$-module of $X_-$ can be decomposed into a direct sum of that of $X_+$ and copies of that of $S$. As an application, we obtain a decomposition theorem for the quantum cohomology of local models of standard flips in birational geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15770v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhaoxing Gu, Song Yu, Tony Yue YU</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computational Resolution of Hadamard Product Factorization for $4 \times 4$ Matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14901</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14901v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We computationally resolve an open problem concerning the expressibility of $4 \times 4$ full-rank matrices as Hadamard products of two rank-2 matrices. Through exhaustive search over $\mathbb{F}_2$, we identify 5,304 counterexamples among the 20,160 full-rank binary matrices (26.3\%). We verify that these counterexamples remain valid over $\mathbb{Z}$ through sign enumeration and provide strong numerical evidence for their validity over $\mathbb{R}$.
  Remarkably, our analysis reveals that matrix density (number of ones) is highly predictive of expressibility, achieving 95.7\% classification accuracy. Using modern machine learning techniques, we discover that expressible matrices lie on an approximately 10-dimensional variety within the 16-dimensional ambient space, despite the naive parameter count of 24 (12 parameters each for two $4 \times 4$ rank-2 matrices). This emergent low-dimensional structure suggests deep algebraic constraints governing Hadamard factorizability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14901v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igor Rivin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hypergeometric decomposition of Delsarte K3 pencils</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15049</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15049v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study five pencils of projective quartic Delsarte K3 surfaces. Over finite fields, we give explicit formulas for the point counts of each family, written in terms of hypergeometric sums. Over the complex numbers, we match the periods of the corresponding family with hypergeometric differential operators and series. We also obtain a decomposition of the $L$-function of each pencil in terms of hypergeometric $L$-series and Dedekind zeta functions. This gives an explicit description of the hypergeometric motives geometrically realised by each pencil.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15049v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rachel Davis, Jessamyn Dukes, Eli Orvis, Thais Ribeiro, Adriana Salerno, Leah Sturman, Ursula Whitcher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GW/DT invariants and 5D BPS indices for strips from topological recursion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15459v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Topological string theory partition function gives rise to Gromov-Witten invariants, Donaldson-Thomas invariants and 5D BPS indices. Via the remodeling conjecture connecting Topological Recursion and topological string theory for toric Calabi-Yau 3-folds, a more direct connection is studied for the subclass of strip geometries. In doing so, new developments in the theory of topological recursion are applied as its extension to Logarithmic Topological Recursion (Log-TR) and the universal $x$--$y$ duality. Through these techniques, our main result in this paper is a direct derivation of all free energies from topological recursion for general strip geometries. In analyzing the expression of free energy, we shed some light on the meaning and the influence of the $x$--$y$ duality in topological string theory and its interconnection to GW and DT invariants as well as the 5D BPS index.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15459v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sibasish Banerjee, Alexander Hock, Olivier Marchal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Point Counting on Igusa Varieties for function fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.01069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.01069v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Igusa varieties over the special fibre of Shimura varieties have demonstrated many applications to the Langlands program via Mantovan's formula and Shin's point counting method. In this paper we study Igusa varieties over the moduli stack of global $\Gscr$-shtukas and (under certain conditions) calculate the Hecke action on its cohomology. As part of their construction we prove novel results about local $G$-shtukas in both equal and unequal characteristic and also discuss application of these results to Barsotti-Tate groups and Shimura varieties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.01069v5</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Hamacher, Wansu Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nakayama-Zariski decomposition and the termination of flips</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.01752</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.01752v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that for pseudoeffective projective pairs the termination of one sequence of flips implies the termination of all flips, assuming a natural conjecture on the behaviour of the Nakayama-Zariski decomposition under the operations of a Minimal Model Program.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.01752v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Lazi\'c, Zhixin Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-BPS categories for symmetric quivers with potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.08425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.08425v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study certain categories associated to symmetric quivers with potential, called quasi-BPS categories. We construct semiorthogonal decompositions of the categories of matrix factorizations for moduli stacks of representations of (framed or unframed) symmetric quivers with potential, where the summands are categorical Hall products of quasi-BPS categories. These results generalize our previous results about the three loop quiver.
  We prove several properties of quasi-BPS categories: wall-crossing equivalence, strong generation, and categorical support lemma in the case of tripled quivers with potential. We also introduce reduced quasi-BPS categories for preprojective algebras, which have trivial relative Serre functor and are indecomposable when the weight is coprime with the total dimension. In this case, we regard the reduced quasi-BPS categories as noncommutative local hyperk\"ahler varieties, and as (twisted) categorical versions of crepant resolutions of singularities of good moduli spaces of representations of preprojective algebras.
  The studied categories include the local models of quasi-BPS categories of K3 surfaces. In a follow-up paper, we establish analogous properties for quasi-BPS categories of K3 surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.08425v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tudor P\u{a}durariu, Yukinobu Toda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Springer correspondence and mirror symmetries for parabolic Hitchin systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07552</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07552v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove the Strominger--Yau--Zaslow and topological mirror symmetries for parabolic Hitchin systems of types B and C. In contrast to type A, a geometric reinterpretation of Springer duality is necessary. Furthermore, unlike Hitchin's construction in the non-parabolic case, the map between generic fibers in type B and C needs more analysis due to the change of partitions of Springer dual nilpotent orbits, which is the main difficulty in this article. To tackle this challenge, we first construct and study the geometry of the generic Hitchin fibers of moduli spaces of Higgs bundles associated to the nilpotent orbit closures. Then we study their relation with the generic Hitchin fibers of parabolic Hitchin systems. Along this way, we establish intriguing connections between Springer duality, Kazhdan--Lusztig maps, and singularities of spectral curves, and uncover a new geometric interpretation of Lusztig's canonical quotient.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07552v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bin Wang, Xueqing Wen, Yaoxiong Wen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal piecewise polynomiality for counting curves in toric surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03761</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03761v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Inspired by piecewise polynomiality results of double Hurwitz numbers, Ardila and Brugall\'e introduced an enumerative problem which they call double Gromov--Witten invariants of Hirzebruch surfaces. These invariants serve as a two-dimensional analogue and satisfy a similar piecewise polynomial structure. More precisely, they introduced the enumeration of curves in Hirzebruch surfaces satisfying point conditions and tangency conditions on the two parallel toric boundaries. These conditions are stored in four partitions and the resulting invariants are piecewise polynomial in their entries. Moreover, they found that these expressions also behave polynomially with respect to the parameter determining the underlying Hirzebruch surfaces. Based on work of Ardila and Block, they proposed that such a polynomiality could also hold while changing between more general toric surfaces corresponding to $h$-transverse polygons. In this work, we answer this question affirmatively. Moreover, we express the resulting invariants for $h$-transverse polygons as matrix elements in the two-dimensional bosonic Fock space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03761v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marvin Anas Hahn, Vincenzo Reda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toric invariance of vertically parametrized systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.15134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.15134v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the problem of deciding whether the complex, real or positive solution sets of a parametrized polynomial system are toric (in the sense that they admit a monomial parametrization) for either all parameter values or generically in parameter space. We focus on vertically parametrized systems, which are sparse systems where we allow linear dependencies between coefficients in front of the same monomial. We give a matroid-theoretic characterization of the maximal-dimensional torus for which all solution sets are invariant under componentwise multiplication. Building on this, we provide necessary conditions and sufficient conditions for when the solution sets are unions of finitely many or a unique coset. Our results are applied to steady state systems of reaction networks, where toricity substantially simplifies the determination of multistationarity, and we illustrate our criteria by scanning for toricity in a database of biological models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.15134v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elisenda Feliu, Oskar Henriksson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On polynomial automorphisms commuting with a simple derivation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09519v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $D$ be a simple derivation of the polynomial ring $\mathbb{k}[x_1,\dots,x_n]$, where $\mathbb{k}$ is an algebraically closed field of characteristic zero, and denote by $\operatorname{Aut}(D)\subset\operatorname{Aut}(\mathbb{k}[x_1,\dots,x_n])$ the subgroup of $\mathbb{k}$-automorphisms commuting with $D$. We show that the connected component of $\operatorname{Aut}(D)$ passing through the identity is a unipotent algebraic group of dimension at most $n-2$, this bound being sharp. Moreover, $\operatorname{Aut}(D)$ is an algebraic group if and only if it is a connected ind-group. Given a simple derivation $D$, we characterize when $\operatorname{Aut}(D)$ contains a normal subgroup of translations. As an application of our techniques we show that if $n=3$, then either $\operatorname{Aut}(D)$ is a discrete group or it is isomorphic to the additive group acting by translations, and give some insight on the case $n=4$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09519v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre-Louis Montagard, Iv\'an Pan, Alvaro Rittatore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tight approximation for rationally simply connected varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10564v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove that holomorphic maps from an open subset of a complex smooth projective curve to a complex smooth projective rationally simply connected variety can be approximated by algebraic maps for the compact-open topology. This theorem can be applied in particular when the target is a smooth hypersurface of degree d in P^n with n greater than or equal to d^2-1. We deduce it from a more general result: the tight approximation property holds for rationally simply connected varieties over function fields of complex curves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10564v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olivier Benoist, Olivier Wittenberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the generalized toroidal completion of period mappings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10109</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.10109v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a period map defined over a quasi-projective variety, we construct a completion with rich geometric and Hodge-theoretic meaning. This result may be regarded as an analog of Mumford's toroidal compactification for locally symmetric Hodge varieties as well as a realizable alternative of Kato--Nakayama--Usui's construction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.10109v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haohua Deng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stress-linked pairs of vertices and the generic stress matroid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.16851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.16851v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Given a graph $G$ and a mapping $p : V(G) \to \mathbb{R}^d$, we say that the pair $(G,p)$ is a ($d$-dimensional) realization of $G$. Two realizations $(G,p)$ and $(G,q)$ are equivalent if each of the point pairs corresponding to the edges of $G$ have the same distance under the embeddings $p$ and $q$. A pair of vertices $\{u,v\}$ is globally linked in $G$ in $\mathbb{R}^d$ if for every generic realization $(G,p)$ and every equivalent realization $(G,q)$, $(G+uv,p)$ and $(G+uv,q)$ are also equivalent.
  In this paper, we introduce and investigate the notion of $d$-stress-linked vertex pairs. Roughly speaking, a pair of vertices $\{u,v\}$ is $d$-stress-linked in $G$ if the edge $uv$ is generically stressed in $G+uv$ and for every generic $d$-dimensional realization $(G,p)$, every configuration $q$ that satisfies the equilibrium stresses of $(G,p)$ also satisfies the equilibrium stresses of $(G+uv,p)$. Among other results, we show that $d$-stress-linked vertex pairs are globally linked in $\mathbb{R}^d$, and we give a combinatorial characterization of $2$-stress-linked vertex pairs that matches the conjectural characterization of globally linked pairs in $\mathbb{R}^2$ due to Jackson et al.
  As a key tool, we introduce and study the ``algebraic dual'' of the $d$-dimensional generic rigidity matroid of a graph $G$, which we call the $d$-dimensional generic stress matroid of $G$. Our results about this matroid, which describes the global behavior of equilibrium stresses of generic realizations of $G$, may be of independent interest.
  We use our results to give positive answers to a conjecture of Jord\'an on minimally globally rigid graphs, a conjecture of Jord\'an and the author on globally linked vertex pairs, and to conjectures of Connelly and Grasegger et al. on rigidity properties of graphs with small separators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.16851v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D\'aniel Garamv\"olgyi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Derivative of a Constructible Function is Constructible</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02517v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The notion of constructible functions in the setting of tame real geometry has been introduced by Cluckers and Dan Miller in their work on parametric integration of globally subanalytic functions. A function on a globally subanalytic set is called constructible if it is a finite sum of finite products of globally subanalytic functions and the logarithm of positive globally subanalytic functions. We show that the class of constructible functions is stable under taking derivatives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02517v2</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Kaiser</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
