<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG</link>
    <description>math.AG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 04:11:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Arrangements of circles, the regions surrounded by them and labeled Poincar\'e-Reeb graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15195v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We are interested in arrangements of circles and the regions surrounded by them. {\it Poincar\'e-Reeb graphs} have been fundamental and strong tools in studying shapes of regions surrounded by real algebraic curves, since around 2020. They are natural graphs the regions naturally collapse to and were first formulated by Sorea with several researchers. Studying shapes of such regions is one of fundamental studies in real algebraic geometry and combinatorics for example. This is surprisingly new and recently developing.
  Our study introduces labels on vertices and edges of such graphs encoding information of the circles where we concentrate on regions surrounded by circles. The author studied local changes of Poincar\'e-Reeb graphs by addition of circles under certain rules before and we discuss changes of new types. The author has started related studies motivated by singularity theory of real algebraic maps and found first that our regions are the images of natural real algebraic maps, generalizing natural projections of spheres.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15195v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naoki Kitazawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maximal Representation Dimensions of Algebraic Tori of Fixed Dimension Over Arbitrary Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15513v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We define the representation dimension of an algebraic torus $T$ to be the minimal positive integer $r$ such that there exists a faithful embedding $T \hookrightarrow \operatorname{GL}_r$. Given a positive integer $n$, there exists a maximal representation dimension of all $n$-dimensional algebraic tori over all fields. In this paper, we use the theory of group actions on lattices to find lower bounds on this maximum for all $n$. Further, we find the exact maximum value for irreducible tori for all $n \in \left\lbrace 1, 2, \dots, 10, 11, 13, 17, 19, 23\right\rbrace$ and conjecturally infinitely many primes $n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15513v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bailey Heath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CoHAs of Torsion Sheaves on Weighted Projective Curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15517v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We describe the cohomological Hall algebra of torsion sheaves on a weighted projective line with weights $(2, \dots, 2)$ in terms of generators and relations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15517v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timm Peerenboom</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the quantum parameter in the quantum cohomology of a family of odd symplectic partial flag varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15550v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We will consider a particular family of odd symplectic partial flag varieties denoted by $\mbox{IF}$. In the quantum cohomology ring $\mbox{QH}^*(\mbox{IF})$, we will show that $q_1q_2\cdots q_m$ appears $m$ times in the quantum product $\tau_{Div_i} \star \tau_{id}$ when expressed as a sum in terms of the Schubert basis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15550v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Connor Bean, Caleb Shank, Ryan M. Shifler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarizations on a triangulated category</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15621v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a recent collaboration, Hiroki Matsui and the author introduced a new proof of the reconstruction theorem of Bondal-Orlov and Ballard, using Matsui's construction of a ringed space associated to a triangulated category. This paper first shows that these ideas can be applied to reconstructions of more general varieties from their perfect derived categories. For further applications of these ideas, we introduce the framework of a polarized triangulated category, a pair $(\mathcal T,\tau)$ consisting of a triangulated category $\mathcal T$ and an autoequivalence $\tau$ (called a polarization), to which we can associate a ringed space called the pt-spectrum. As concrete applications, we observe that several reconstruction results of Favero naturally fit within this framework, leading to both generalizations and new proofs of these results. Furthermore, we explore broader implications of polarizations and pt-spectra in tensor triangular geometry, noncommutative projective geometry, birational geometry and homological mirror symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15621v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daigo Ito</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explicit modularity of K3 surfaces with complex multiplication of large degree</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15052v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the transcendental motive of three K3 surfaces $X$ conjectured to have complex multiplication (CM). Under this assumption, we match these to explicit algebraic Hecke quasi-characters $\psi_X$, and CM abelian threefolds $A$. This provides substantial evidence that a power of $A$ corresponds to $X$ under the Kuga-Satake correspondence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15052v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Edgar Costa, Andreas-Stephan Elsenhans, J\"org Jahnel, John Voight</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holomorphic automorphisms of Markov-type surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15101v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Every complex surface of Markov-type, i.e.\ the variety given by $x^2 + y^2 + z^2 + Exyz - Ax - By - Cz - D = 0$, has the symplectic density property and the Hamiltonian density property. We prove a singular symplectic/Hamiltonian version of the Anders{\'e}n--Lempert theorem for normal reduced affine complex varieties and apply it to describe the holomorphic symplectic automorphisms of a complex surface of Markov-type. To this end, we also investigate the germs of vector fields in isolated singularities of type $A_k$ and $D_k$. Moreover, we show that any injective self-map of the set of ordered Markov triples can be realized by a holomorphic symplectic automorphism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15101v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael B. Andrist</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Littlewood--Richardson rules from quivers for two-step flag varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15126</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15126v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $\bigwedge_1$ and $\bigwedge_2$ be two symmetric function algebras in independent sets of variables. We define vector space bases of $\bigwedge_1 \otimes_\mathbb{Z} \bigwedge_2$ coming from certain quivers, with vertex sets indexed by pairs of partitions. We use these vector space bases to give a positive tableau formula for Littlewood--Richardson coefficients for the product of Schubert polynomials with certain Schur polynomials in two-step flag varieties, in the spirit of the Remmel-Whitney rule for the product of two Schur polynomials in Grassmannians. This in particular covers the cases considered by the Pieri rule.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15126v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linda Chen, Elana Kalashnikov, Appendix by Ellis Buckminster, Linda Chen, Elana Kalashnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complements of the point schemes of noncommutative projective lines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15175v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently, Chan and Nyman constructed noncommutative projective lines via a noncommutative symmetric algebra for a bimodule $V$ over a pair of fields. These noncommutative projective lines of contain a canonical closed subscheme (the point scheme) determined by a normal family of elements in the noncommutative symmetric algebra. We study the complement of this subscheme when $V$ is simple, the coordinate ring of which is obtained by inverting said normal family. We show that this localised ring is a noncommutative Dedekind domain of Gelfand-Kirillov dimension 1. Furthermore, the question of simplicity of these Dedekind domains is answered by a similar dichotomy to an analogous open subscheme of the noncommutative quadrics of Artin, Tate and Van den Bergh.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15175v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jackson Ryder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modular forms for three-loop banana integrals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15325v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study periods of multi-parameter families of K3 surfaces, which are relevant to compute the maximal cuts of certain classes of Feynman integrals. We focus on their automorphic properties, and we show that generically the periods define orthogonal modular forms. Using exceptional isomorphisms between Lie groups of small rank, we show how one can use the intersection product on the periods to identify K3 surfaces whose periods can be expressed in terms of other classes of modular forms that have been studied in the mathematics literature. We apply our results to maximal cuts of three-loop banana integrals, and we show that depending on the mass configuration, the maximal cuts define ordinary modular forms or Hilbert, Siegel or hermitian modular forms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15325v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Claude Duhr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feynman integrals, elliptic integrals and two-parameter K3 surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15326v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The three-loop banana integral with three equal masses and the conformal two-loop five-point traintrack integral in two dimensions are related to a two-parameter family of K3 surfaces. We compute the corresponding periods and the mirror map, and we show that they can be expressed in terms of ordinary modular forms and functions. In particular, we find that the maximal cuts of the three-loop banana integral with three equal masses can be written as a product of two copies of the maximal cuts of the two-loop equal-mass sunrise integral. Our computation reveals a hidden symmetry of the banana integral not manifest from the Feynman integral representation, which corresponds to exchanging the two copies of the sunrise elliptic curve.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15326v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Claude Duhr, Sara Maggio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On rational connectedness and parametrization of finite Galois extensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15674v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given two $G$-Galois extensions of $\mathbb Q$, is there an extension of $\mathbb Q(t)$ that specializes to both? The equivalence relation on $G$-Galois extension of $\mathbb Q$, induced by the above question, is called $R$-equivalence. The number of $R$-equivlance classes indicates how many rational spaces are required in order to parametrize all $G$-Galois extensions of $\mathbb Q$. We determine the $R$-equivalence classes for basic families of groups $G$, and consequently obtain parametrizations of the $G$-Galois extensions of $\mathbb Q$ in the absence of a generic extension for $G$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15674v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Krashen, Danny Neftin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Virtual Classes of Character Stacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2201.08699</link>
      <description>arXiv:2201.08699v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we extend the Topological Quantum Field Theory developed by Gonz\'alez-Prieto, Logares, and Mu\~noz for computing virtual classes of $G$-representation varieties of closed orientable surfaces in the Grothendieck ring of varieties to the setting of the character stacks. To this aim, we define a suitable Grothendieck ring of representable stacks, over which this Topological Quantum Field Theory is defined. In this way, we compute the virtual class of the character stack over $BG$, that is, a motivic decomposition of the representation variety with respect to the natural adjoint action.
  We apply this framework in two cases providing explicit expressions for the virtual classes of the character stacks of closed orientable surfaces of arbitrary genus. First, in the case of the affine linear group of rank $1$, the virtual class of the character stack fully remembers the natural adjoint action, in particular, the virtual class of the character variety can be straightforwardly derived. Second, we consider the non-connected group $\mathbb{G}_m \rtimes \mathbb{Z}/2\mathbb{Z}$, and we show how our theory allows us to compute motivic information of the character stacks where the classical na\"ive point-counting method fails.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2201.08699v4</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.geomphys.2025.105450</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Geometry and Physics, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>\'Angel Gonz\'alez-Prieto, M\'arton Hablicsek, Jesse Vogel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An arithmetic Yau-Zaslow formula</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.15788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.15788v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove an arithmetic refinement of the Yau-Zaslow formula by replacing the classical Euler characteristic in Beauville's argument by a "motivic Euler characteristic", related to the work of Levine. Our result implies similar formulas for other related invariants, including a generalisation of a formula of Kharlamov and Rasdeaconu on counting real rational curves on real K3 surfaces, and Saito's determinant of cohomology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.15788v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jesse Pajwani, Ambrus P\'al</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Degree bounds for Putinar's Positivstellensatz on the hypercube</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.12558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.12558v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Positivstellens\"atze of Putinar and Schm\"udgen show that any polynomial $f$ positive on a compact semialgebraic set can be represented using sums of squares. Recently, there has been large interest in proving effective versions of these results, namely to show bounds on the required degree of the sums of squares in such representations. These effective Positivstellens\"atze have direct implications for the convergence rate of the celebrated moment-SOS hierarchy in polynomial optimization. In this paper, we restrict to the fundamental case of the hypercube $\mathrm{B}^{n} = [-1, 1]^n$. We show an upper degree bound for Putinar-type representations on $\mathrm{B}^{n}$ of the order $O(f_{\max}/f_{\min})$, where $f_{\max}$, $f_{\min}$ are the maximum and minimum of $f$ on $\mathrm{B}^{n}$, respectively. Previously, specialized results of this kind were available only for Schm\"udgen-type representations and not for Putinar-type ones. Complementing this upper degree bound, we show a lower degree bound in $\Omega(\sqrt[8]{f_{\max}/f_{\min}})$. This is the first lower bound for Putinar-type representations on a semialgebraic set with nonempty interior described by a standard set of inequalities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.12558v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1137/23M1555430</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Baldi, Lucas Slot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Duality and polyhedrality of cones for Mori dream spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.18536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.18536v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Our goal is twofold. On one hand we show that the cones of divisors ample in codimension $k$ on a Mori dream space are rational polyhedral. On the other hand we study the duality between such cones and the cones of $k$-moving curves by means of the Mori chamber decomposition of the former. We give a new proof of the weak duality property (already proved by Payne and Choi) and we exhibit an interesting family of examples for which strong duality holds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.18536v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maria Chiara Brambilla, Olivia Dumitrescu, Elisa Postinghel, Luis Jos\'e Santana S\'anchez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fixed loci of symplectic automorphisms of $K3^{[n]}$ and $n$-Kummer type manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.14692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.14692v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The aim of this paper is to give an explicit description of the fixed loci of symplectic automorphisms for certain hyperkahler manifolds, namely for Hilbert schemes on K3 surfaces and for generalized Kummer varieties. Here we extend our previous results from the case of involutions to more general groups. In particular, under some conditions on the dimension, we give the full answer for finite group actions of symplectic automorphisms coming from K3 surfaces. We prove that the all irreducible components of the fixed loci are of $K3^{[k]}$ type of lower dimensions or isolated points.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.14692v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ljudmila Kamenova, Giovanni Mongardi, Alexei Oblomkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective membership problem and systems of polynomial equations with multiple roots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10884v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For a tuple of $k+1$ convex bodies $(A, B,\ldots, B)$ we solve the so called effective membership problem, i.e. for generic $f_1,\ldots, f_k\in\mathbb{C}^{B}$ we provide a method to compute $\mathbb{C}^A\cap I$, where $I=(f_1,\ldots, f_k)$ is an ideal in the ring of Laurent polynomials. We connect this topic to the study of mixed discriminants and multiple solutions of sparse systems of equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10884v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ivan Nikitin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variation of Archimedean Zeta Function and $n/d$-Conjecture for Generic Multiplicities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00757v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For $f_1,...,f_r\in \mathbb C[z_1,...,z_n]\setminus \mathbb C$, we introduce the variation of archimedean zeta function. As an application, we show that the $n/d$-conjecture, proposed by Budur, Musta\c{t}\u{a}, and Teitler, holds for generic multiplicities. Consequently, strong monodromy conjecture holds for hyperplane arrangements with generic multiplicities as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00757v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quan Shi, Huaiqing Zuo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noncommutative Gelfand Duality: the algebraic case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.11816v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The goal of this paper is to define a notion of non-commutative Gelfand duality. Using techniques from derived algebraic geometry, we show that the category of rings is anti-equivalent to a subcategory of pre-ringed sites, inspired by Grothendieck's work on commutative rings. Our notion of spectrum, although formally reminiscent of the Grothendieck spectrum, is new. Remarkably, an appropriately refined relative version of our spectrum agrees with the Grothendieck spectrum for finitely generated commutative algebras over the complex numbers, among others. This work aims to represent the starting point for a rigorous study of geometric properties of quantum spacetimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.11816v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico Bambozzi, Matteo Capoferri, Simone Murro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isotropic motivic fundamental groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16540</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16540v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The main goal of this paper is to study relative versions of the category of modules over the isotropic motivic Brown-Peterson spectrum, with a particular emphasis on their cellular subcategories. Using techniques developed by Levine, we equip these categories with motivic $t$-structures, whose hearts are Tannakian categories over ${\mathbb F}_2$. This allows to define isotropic motivic fundamental groups, and to interpret relative isotropic Tate motives in the heart as their representations. Moreover, we compute these groups in the cases of the punctured projective line and split tori. Finally, we also apply Spitzweck's derived approach to establish an identification between relative isotropic Tate motives and representations of certain affine derived group schemes, whose 0-truncations coincide with the aforementioned isotropic motivic fundamental groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16540v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabio Tanania</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Counting points on superelliptic curves in average polynomial time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.10189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2004.10189v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We describe the practical implementation of an average polynomial-time algorithm for counting points on superelliptic curves defined over $\mathbb Q$ that is substantially faster than previous approaches. Our algorithm takes as input a superelliptic curves $y^m=f(x)$ with $m\ge 2$ and $f\in \mathbb Z[x]$ any squarefree polynomial of degree $d\ge 3$, along with a positive integer $N$. It can compute $\#X(\mathbb F_p)$ for all $p\le N$ not dividing $m\mathrm{lc}(f)\mathrm{disc}(f)$ in time $O(md^3 N\log^3 N\log\log N)$. It achieves this by computing the trace of the Cartier--Manin matrix of reductions of $X$. We can also compute the Cartier--Manin matrix itself, which determines the $p$-rank of the Jacobian of $X$ and the numerator of its zeta function modulo~$p$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2004.10189v5</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.2140/obs.2020.4.403</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Fourteenth Algorithmic Number Theory Symposium (ANTS XIV), The Open Book Series 4 (2020), 403-422</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andrew V. Sutherland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When is a polarised abelian variety determined by its $\boldsymbol{p}$-divisible group?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.13180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.13180v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the Siegel modular variety $\mathcal{A}_g \otimes \overline{\mathbb{F}}_p$ of genus $g$ and its supersingular locus $\mathcal{S}_g$. As our main result we determine precisely when $\mathcal{S}_g$ is irreducible, and we list all $x$ in $\mathcal{A}_g \otimes \overline{\mathbb{F}}_p$ for which the corresponding central leaf $\mathcal{C}(x)$ consists of one point, that is, for which $x$ corresponds to a polarised abelian variety which is uniquely determined by its associated polarised $p$-divisible group. The first problem translates to a class number one problem for quaternion Hermitian lattices. The second problem also translates to a class number one problem, whose solution involves mass formulae, automorphism groups, and a careful analysis of Ekedahl-Oort strata in genus $g=4$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.13180v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomoyoshi Ibukiyama, Valentijn Karemaker, Chia-Fu Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Mumford conjecture (after Bianchi)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.06232</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.06232v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We give a self-contained and streamlined rendition of Andrea Bianchi's recent proof of the Mumford conjecture using moduli spaces of branched covers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.06232v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ronno Das, Dan Petersen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supersingular Ekedahl-Oort strata and Oort's conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19748v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\mathcal{A}_g$ be the moduli space over $\overline{\mathbb{F}}_p$ of $g$-dimensional principally polarised abelian varieties, where $p$ is a prime. We show that if $g$ is even and $p\geq 5$, then every geometric generic member in the maximal supersingular Ekedahl-Oort stratum in $\mathcal{A}_g$ has automorphism group $\{ \pm 1\}$. This confirms Oort's conjecture in the case of $p\geq 5$ and even $g$. We also separately prove Oort's conjecture for $g=4$ and any prime $p$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19748v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valentijn Karemaker, Chia-Fu Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
