<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG</link>
    <description>math.AG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 02:48:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A note on varieties of non-negative Kodaira dimension with polarized self maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17242</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17242v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this note we prove that a smooth projective variety (defined over a field $k$) of non-negative Kodaira dimension that has a $k$-rational point and a polarized self map must be a finite free quotient of an abelian variety.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17242v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ankit Rai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On one-leg orbifold topological vertex in refined Gromov-Witten theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17321v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We define the one-leg orbifold topological vertex in refined Gromov-Witten theory \cite{BS24}. There are two cases where the leg is effective or gerby. The main result of this paper is the computation of the effective case. In the smooth case, this result matches the one-leg refined vertex in \cite{IKV09}. As an application, we compute the refined Gromov-Witten invariants of the local football.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17321v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinghao Yu, Zhengyu Zong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Odd magical triples and maximal Higgs bundles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17415v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the notion of extended magical $\mathfrak{sl}_2$-triples, a generalization of the magical $\mathfrak{sl}_2$-triples in Bradlow--Collier--Garc\'ia-Prada--Gothen--Oliveira's work and show that, apart from the known even magical triples, there are precisely three odd triples of nontube type Hermitian Lie algebras that are extended magical.
  We then show that the Slodowy slice of an odd extended magical triple of $G^\textbf{R}$ in the $G^\textbf{R}$-Higgs bundle moduli space are precisely the maximal components. Finally, assuming that the underlying curve has sufficiently large genus, we give a geometric characterization of extended magical triples and prove a Cayley correspondence for the maximal components of $G^\textbf{R}$-Higgs bundles for nontube type Hermitian Lie groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17415v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enya Hsiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Proper Descent of Smooth Affine Surfaces with Finite Homotopy Rank-Sum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17479v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the descent behaviour of homotopy-theoretic properties of smooth complex affine surfaces under finite surjective morphisms. We first examine the Eilenberg-MacLane property and show, by means of an explicit counterexample, that it does not descend under proper morphisms in general. This negative result motivates the introduction of a weaker notion, the finite homotopy rank-sum property. Our main theorem establishes that this property does descend under proper morphisms between smooth affine surfaces of logarithmic Kodaira dimension at most zero. The proof relies essentially on the recent classification of smooth complex affine surfaces of log non-general type characterized by these two properties. As a further application, we classify smooth affine surfaces properly dominated by the complex algebraic 2-torus, thereby clarifying an earlier remark of M. Furushima.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17479v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Buddhadev Hajra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher order double point formulas via SSM-Thom polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17651</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17651v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the geometry of double point loci of maps $F:M\to N$ of complex manifolds through the lens of Segre-Schwartz-MacPherson (SSM) classes. Classical double point formulas express the fundamental class of the closure of the double point locus of $F$ in terms of global invariants of source and target spaces, as well as $F$. In this paper we extend these results by computing a one-parameter cohomological deformation of the double point formula given by the SSM class. We compute the SSM class of the double point locus in a large cohomological degree range. The leading term in our new formulas recovers the classical double point formula of Fulton and Laksov, while higher-degree terms provide explicit universal corrections. Our approach uses interpolation techniques for SSM-Thom polynomials of multisingularities, recently developed by Koncki, Nekarda, Ohmoto and Rim\'anyi. We also compute SSM-Thom polynomials for the singularities $A_0$ and $A_1$ in the same range. As an application, we show how the deformed formulas yield refined geometric information about those singularity loci through a theorem of Aluffi and Ohmoto, including constraints on when such loci can arise as complete intersections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17651v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reese Lance</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hitchin maps and parabolic Hitchin maps on the moduli spaces of Hitchin sheaves on nodal curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17672v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the Hitchin maps on the moduli spaces of Hitchin sheaves and parabolic Hitchin sheaves on a nodal integral curve $Y$. We study their fibres, the BNR correspondences and the relation of the restriction of the Hitchin map with very stable bundles. As an application, in the "coprime" case we prove that the parabolic Poincar\'e sheaf on $U_{par}(n, \xi)\times Y$ is parabolic stable where $U_{par}(n, \xi)$ is a fixed determinant moduli space of parabolic sheaves on $Y$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17672v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Usha N. Bhosle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jacobian rings and the infinitesimal Torelli Theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17765v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article we deal with jacobian rings and identify a mixed Hodge component of a nondegenerate hypersurface in the torus with a lattice geometric quotient vector space. We introduce a period map, study its differential and compute the kernel of the differential much explicitly via certain Laurent polynomials. As an application we deal with the infinitesimal Torelli theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17765v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julius Giesler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the genus of a curve in a projective $3$-fold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17852v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $X\subset \mathbb P^r$ be a projective factorial variety of dimension $3$, degree $n$, with at worst isolated singularities. Assume that the Picard group of $X$ is generated by the hyperplane section class. Let $C\subset X$ be a projective subscheme of dimension $1$, degree $d\gg n$, and arithmetic genus $p_a(C)$. Improving a recent result by Liu, we exhibit a Castelnuovo's bound for $p_a(C)$. In the case $X$ is Calabi-Yau, our bound gives a step forward for a certain conjecture concerning the vanishing of Gopakumar-Vafa invariants of $X$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17852v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincenzo Di Gennaro, Antonio Rapagnetta, Pietro Sabatino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rigidity Criterion for Certain Calabi-Yau families</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17894v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a new rigidity criterion for families of polarized Calabi-Yau manifolds. Motivated by known non-rigid examples, we conjecture that a family over a quasi-projective curve is rigid if it admits a smooth compactification whose singular fiber has only isolated singularities. We verify this conjecture for singularities with a concentrated mixed Hodge spectrum class including ordinary double points and cusps. The proof combines an analysis of the vanishing cycle exact sequence and limiting mixed Hodge structure with a tensor-product decomposition of the associated variation of Hodge structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17894v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruiran Sun, Chenglong Yu, Kang Zuo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equivalent computational problems for superspecial abelian surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18050v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show reductions and equivalences between various problems related to the computation of the endomorphism ring of principally polarised superspecial abelian surfaces. Problems considered are the computation of the Ibukiyama-Katsura-Oort matrix and computation of unpolarised isomoprhisms between superspecial abelian surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18050v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Micka\"el Montessinos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dimers for degenerating families of M-curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18093v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study dimer models on infinite minimal graphs with Fock's weights for degenerating families of M-curves of any genus based on works of Boutillier-Cimasoni-de Tili\`{e}re and Bobenko A.I.- Bobenko N.-Suris for a fixed M-curve. We show that these dimer models for families of M-curves behave consistently under their degeneration shrinking real circles to points, and that they can be calculated as power series in the associated deformation parameters which are regarded as the perturbation of Kenyon's critical dimer models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18093v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takashi Ichikawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pullback and Direct Image of Parabolic Ample and Parabolic Nef Vector Bundles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18166</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18166v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that under a finite surjective map of irreducible smooth complex projective curves, the pullback and direct image of a parabolic ample (respectively, parabolic nef) vector bundle is again parabolic ample (respectively, parabolic nef) if and only if the original parabolic vector bundle is parabolic ample (respectively, parabolic nef).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18166v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashima Bansal, Indranil Biswas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lie algebroid connection and Harder-Narasimhan reduction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18169v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Take a holomorphic Lie algebroid $(V,\, \phi)$ on a compact connected Riemann surface $X$ such that the anchor map $\phi$ is not surjective. Let $P$ be a parabolic subgroup of a complex reductive affine algebraic group $G$ and $E_P\, \subset\, E_G$ a holomorphic reduction of structure group, to $P$, of a holomorphic principal $G$--bundle $E_G$ on $X$. We prove that $E_P$ admits a holomorphic Lie algebroid connection for $(V,\,\phi)$ if the reduction $E_P$ is infinitesimally rigid. If $E_P$ is the Harder--Narasimhan reduction of $E_G$, then it is shown that $E_P$ admits a holomorphic Lie algebroid connection for $(V,\,\phi)$. In particular, for any point $x_0\,\in\, X$, the Harder--Narasimhan reduction $E_P$ admits a logarithmic connection that is nonsingular on the complement $X\setminus\{x_0\}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18169v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashima Bansal, Indranil Biswas, Pradip Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General tropical convergence of harmonic amoebas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18180v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: By using Schottky uniformization theory of degenerating algebraic curves, we describe the tropical convergence of harmonic amoebas of pointed Riemann surfaces to tropical curves which are not necessarily simple. We extend Lang's results on the simple tropical convergence based on the Frenchel-Nielsen coordinates to the nonsimple case. Our results are hoped to give contributions in compactifying the moduli space of pointed Riemann surfaces with tropical curves, and in studying crystallization of general dimer models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18180v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takashi Ichikawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On positivity of CM line bundles on the moduli space of klt good minimal models with $\kappa=1$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18208v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the positivity of CM line bundles on the coarse moduli space of Kawamata log terminal (klt) good minimal models with Kodaira dimension one. We prove that the seminormalization of the moduli space is quasi-projective under a mild assumption on the general fibers of good minimal models. Moreover, we show that the CM line bundle becomes ample after normalization. A key new ingredient is the construction of a moduli space of numerical equivalence classes, which is an extension of the work of Viehweg and allows us to bypass the failure of quasi-finiteness in the approach of the previous work by Hashizume and the author.
  We also establish the projectivity of the moduli space of $\epsilon$-stable quotients, which is introduced by Toda, to a projective space, which plays a central role in our method. This particular situation is encompassed by our general framework of K-moduli of quasimaps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18208v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masafumi Hattori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relative Dixmier property for Poisson algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18249v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dixmier property concerns the bijectivity of endomorphisms for algebras. We introduce a relative Dixmier property, which is a generalization of the Dixmier property. This new concept has applications in proving that several classes of Poisson algebras possess the Dixmier property, as well as in other topics such as the cancellation problem and the non-existence of Hopf coactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18249v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongdi Huang, Zahra Nazemian, Xin Tang, Xingting Wang, Yanhua Wang, James J. Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cohomologically or numerically trivial automorphisms of surfaces of general type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18389</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18389v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Our main result is the determination of the respective groups $ Aut_\mathbb{Z}(S) $ of cohomologically trivial automorphisms and $ Aut_\mathbb{Q}(S) $ of numerically trivial automorphisms for the reducible fake quadrics, that is, the surfaces $S$ isogenous to a product with $q=p_g=0$.
  In this way we produce new record winning examples: a surface $S$ with $|Aut_\mathbb{Q}(S)| =192$, and a surface whose cohomology has torsion with nontrivial $ Aut_\mathbb{Z}(S) \cong \mathbb{Z}/2.$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18389v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabrizio Catanese (University\"at Bayreuth), Davide Frapporti (Politecnico di Milano)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Applications of the Nash double of a Nash manifold with corners</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18515v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work we study some properties and applications of Nash manifolds with corners. Our first main result shows how to `build' a Nash manifold with corners ${\mathcal Q}\subset{\mathbb R}^n$ from a suitable Nash manifold $M\subset{\mathbb R}^n$ (of its same dimension), that contains ${\mathcal Q}$ as a closed subset, by folding $M$ along the irreducible components of a normal-crossings divisor of $M$ (the smallest Nash subset of $M$ that contains the boundary $\partial{\mathcal Q}$ of ${\mathcal Q}$). Our second main results shows that we can choose as the Nash manifold $M$ the Nash `double' $D({\mathcal Q})$ of ${\mathcal Q}$, which is the analogous to the Nash double of a Nash manifold with (smooth) boundary, but $D({\mathcal Q})$ takes into account the peculiarities of the boundary of a Nash manifold with corners.
  We propose several applications of the previous results: (1) Nash ramified coverings of closed semialgebraic sets, (2) Weak Nash uniformization of closed semialgebraic sets using Nash manifolds with (smooth) boundary, (3) Representation of compact semialgebraic sets connected by analytic paths as images under Nash maps of closed unit balls, (4) Explicit construction of Nash models for compact orientable smooth surfaces of genus $g\geq0$, and (5) Nash approximation of continuous semialgebraic maps whose target spaces are Nash manifolds with corners.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18515v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Carbone, Jos\'e F. Fernando</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fibers of phase tropicalizations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18519v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The subject of the present paper is phase tropicalization, which was used crucially in the context of Mikhalkin's correspondence theorem for curve counting in the complex coefficient case. The subject can be traced back to Viro's patchworking for constructing topological types of real algebraic curves. These two instances correspond to complex and real phases. Both fall into the category of what can be called "abelian" or classical tropicalization, referring to degenerations of varieties within an algebraic torus (or its compactification). In contrast, in "non-abelian" tropicalizations the ambient torus is replaced by a non-commutative group such as the special linear group. This is the beginning of a general theory valid for a wide array of coefficient systems and dimensions. As an application, the paper settles the question of phase tropicalization for the special linear group $\mathrm{SL}_2$. It also gives an algebraic explanation and phase extension of the case of curves, previously studied in the purely geometric framework. To accomplish these tasks we introduce valuative tools that allow us to prove an affine version of Kapranov's theorem on tropical hypersurfaces and its generalization to arbitrary tropical varieties. Most notably, we show the functorial properties of the graded ring of a valuation and exhibit the polynomial structure of the graded ring of monomial valuations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18519v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Bengus-Lasnier, Mikhail Shkolnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On slope unstable Fano varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18526v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For Fano varieties, significant progress has been made recently in the study of $K$-stability, while the understanding of the weaker but more algebraic concept of $(-K)$-slope stability remains intricate. For instance, a conjecture attributed to Iskovskikh states that the tangent bundle of a Picard rank one Fano manifold is slope stable. Peternell-Wi\'sniewski and Hwang proved this conjecture up to dimension five in 1998, but Kanemitsu later disproved it in 2021. To address this gap in understanding, we present a method that aims to characterize the geometry associated with the maximal destabilizing sheaf of the tangent sheaf of a Fano variety. This approach utilizes modern advancements in the foliated minimal model program. In dimension two, our approach leads to a complete classification of $(-K)$-slope unstable weak del Pezzo surfaces with canonical singularities. As by-products, we provide the first conceptual proof that $\mathbb{P}^1 \times \mathbb{P}^1$ and $\mathbb{F}_1$ are the only $(-K)$-slope unstable nonsingular del Pezzo surfaces, recovering a classical result of Fahlaoui in 1989. We also uncover a phenomenon that does not occur for Fano manifolds: there exists a del Pezzo surface with type A singularities admitting a weak K\"ahler-Einstein metric, yet whose tangent sheaf is slope unstable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18526v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yen-An Chen, Ching-Jui Lai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>There is no Definable Grauert Direct Image Theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18711v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove the claim in the title by showing that a definable Grauert Direct Image
  Theorem in o-minimal geometry would imply a weak
  representability-like property of the definable Picard functor. However, this weak representability cannot hold because of the Definable Chow Theorem of Peterzil and Starchenko.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18711v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H\'el\`ene Esnault, Moritz Kerz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Representations of the Flat Space Wavefunction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17619v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: From any graph $G$ arises a flat space wavefunction, obtained by integrating a product of propagators associated to the vertices and edges of $G$. This function is a key ingredient in the computation of cosmological correlators, and several representations for it have been proposed. We formulate three such representations and prove their correctness. In particular, we show that the flat space wavefunction can be read off from the canonical form of the cosmological polytope, and we settle a conjecture of Fevola, Pimentel, Sattelberger, and Westerdijk regarding a partial fraction decomposition for the flat space wavefunction. The terms of the decomposition correspond to certain collections of connected subgraphs associated to $G$ and its spanning subgraphs, reflecting the fact that the flat space wavefunction contains information about how $G$ is connected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17619v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tyler Dunaisky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Tate cohomology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17677v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We formulate a definition of Tate cohomology in the context of three functor formalisms, and we establish basic monoidality and functoriality properties of it in this context. Our approach to these properties is based on the treatment of Nikolaus-Scholze in the setting of local systems of spectra on spaces. We discuss a couple of other specific settings of interest that are accommodated by our generalization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17677v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arpon Raksit</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A relative Langlands dual realization of $T^*(G/K)$ and derived Satake</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18022v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that the cotangent bundle $T^*(G/K)$ of a quasi-split symmetric space $G/K$ is isomorphic to the dual variety of the loop symmetric space for the Langlands dual group, providing instances of the relative Langlands duality for non-split groups. Then we establish a Langlands dual description of equivariant coherent sheaves on $T^*(G/K)$ in terms of constructible sheaves on the loop symmetric spaces, generalizing the derived Satake equivalence for reductive groups to quasi-split symmetric spaces. To this end, we prove the derived Satake equivalence for the twisted affine Grassmannians, study ring objects arising from loop symmetric spaces, and explore the formality and fully-faithfulness properties of $!$-pure objects. We deduce a version of Bezrukavnikov equivalence for quasi-split symmetric spaces and make connections to the geometric Langlands on the twistor $\mathbb P^1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18022v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tsao-Hsien Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arithmetic volumes of moduli stacks of Shtukas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18557</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18557v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We define and study "tautological classes" in the cohomology of moduli stacks of shtukas, pursuing two directions of applications. First, we prove a formula relating the "arithmetic volume" of tautological classes to higher derivatives of Artin $L$-functions, which can be viewed as an arithmetic analog of Hirzebruch's Proportionality principle. Second, we define and analyze the structure of the "phantom tautological ring", using a general relation between Hecke correspondences and Vinberg's degeneration, and give applications to a function field analog of Colmez's Conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18557v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tony Feng, Zhiwei Yun, Wei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arithmetic Fujita approximation over adelic curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.15271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.15271v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we will prove an analogue of Fujita's approximation theorem under the framework of Arakelov theory over adelic curves, which proves a conjecture of Huayi Chen and Atsushi Moriwaki.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.15271v4</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chunhui Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cohomological Hall algebras for 3-Calabi-Yau categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12838v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The aim of this paper is to construct the cohomological Hall algebras for $3$-Calabi--Yau categories admitting a strong orientation data. This can be regarded as a mathematical definition of the algebra of BPS states, whose existence was first mathematically conjectured by Kontsevich and Soibelman. Along the way, we prove Joyce's conjecture on the functorial behaviour of the Donaldson--Thomas perverse sheaves for the attractor Lagrangian correspondence of $(-1)$-shifted symplectic stacks. This result allows us to construct a parabolic induction map for cohomological Donaldson--Thomas invariants of $G$-local systems on $3$-manifolds for a reductive group $G$, which can be regarded as a $3$-manifold analogue of the Eisenstein series functor in the geometric Langlands program.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12838v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tasuki Kinjo, Hyeonjun Park, Pavel Safronov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relative Fundamental Lemmas for Spherical Hecke Algebras and Multiplicative Hitchin Fibrations: the Jacquet--Rallis Case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15155v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove the Jacquet--Rallis fundamental lemma for spherical Hecke algebras over local function fields using multiplicative Hitchin fibrations. Our work is inspired by the proof of [Yun11] in the Lie algebra case and builds upon the general framework of multiplicative Hitchin fibrations in [Wang26].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15155v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>X. Griffin Wang, Zhiyu Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variation of cones of divisors in a family of varieties -- Fano type case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04109</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.04109v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the relationship between the Fano type property on fibers over a Zariski dense subset and the global Fano type property. We establish the invariance of N\'eron-Severi spaces, nef cones, effective cones, movable cones, and Mori chamber decompositions for a family of Fano type varieties after a generically finite base change. Additionally, we show the uniform behavior of the minimal model program for this family. These results are applied to the boundedness problem of Fano type varieties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.04109v4</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sung Rak Choi, Zhan Li, Chuyu Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brauer group of moduli of parabolic symplectic bundles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03260v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $X$ be a smooth connected complex projective curve of genus $g$, with $g\,\geq\, 3$. Fix an integer $r\geq 2$, a finite subset $D\, \subset\, X$, and a line bundle $L$ on $X$. We compute the Brauer group of the smooth locus of the moduli space of parabolic symplectic stable bundles of rank $r$ on $X$ equipped with a symplectic form taking values in $L(D)$, where $L(D)$ is given the trivial parabolic structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03260v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Indranil Biswas, Sujoy Chakraborty, Arijit Dey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The spaces of rational curves on del Pezzo surfaces via conic bundles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18239v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Using the homological sieve method developed by Das--Lehmann--Tosteson and the author, we prove Peyre's all height approach to Manin's conjecture for split quintic del Pezzo surfaces defined over $\mathbb F_q(t)$ assuming $q$ is sufficiently large. We also establish lower bounds of correct magnitude for the counting function of rational curves on split low degree del Pezzo surfaces defined over $\mathbb F_q$ assuming $q$ is large.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18239v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sho Tanimoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spherical and Semibrick Classifications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02009v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article provides an overview of the techniques related to classification of spherical and more general objects within triangulated categories, and its relationship with algebraic geometry, representation theory and symplectic geometry. The primary focus are the techniques of the authors within the 'finite' algebraic geometry setting in dimensions two and three, and within silting discrete algebras, but other approaches including to more general settings by Bapat-Deopurkar-Licata, Smith-Wemyss, Ishii-Uehara, Keating-Smith and Shimpi are also surveyed, in varying levels of detail. Various explicit examples are provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02009v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wahei Hara, Michael Wemyss</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extensions Of Unirational Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00391</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00391v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We undertake a study of extensions of unirational algebraic groups. We prove that extensions of unirational groups are also unirational over fields of degree of imperfection $1$, but that this fails over every field of higher degree of imperfection, answering a question of Achet. We also initiate a study of those groups which admit filtrations with unirational graded pieces, and show that one may deduce unirationality of unipotent groups from unirationality of certain quotients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00391v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zev Rosengarten</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relative Gieseker's problem on $F$-divided bundles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10583v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $f: X\to Y$ be a proper surjective morphism of varieties defined over an algebraically closed field of positive characteristic. We prove that if $f$ has geometrically connected fibers then the induced homomorphism of $F$-divided fundamental groups is faithfully flat. An important new ingredient in our proof is an analogue of B. Bhatt's and P. Scholze's descent theorem \cite[Theorem 1.3]{Bhatt-Scholze2017} for $F$-divided bundles.
  As a corollary, we prove that in general if $X$ is normal, $Y$ is smooth, both $X$ and $Y$ are projective, and the induced map on \'etale fundamental groups is surjective, then the corresponding homomorphism on $F$-divided fundamental groups is faithfully flat. We also establish an analogous result for isomorphisms. This generalizes and strengthens a recent result of X. Sun and L. Zhang \cite{Sun-Zhang2025}, which in turn generalized earlier results of H. Esnault and V. Mehta \cite{Esnault-Mehta2010} and I. Biswas, M. Kumar, and A. J. Parameswaran \cite{Biswas-Parameswaran-Kumar2025}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10583v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrian Langer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intersection of curves in projective 4 space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15801v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given two distinct reduced, irreducible curves of given degrees, contained in projective space but whose union is not contained in a hyperplane, what is the largest number of points of intersection they can have? When the projective space is the plane, this is trivial. For projective 3 space this problem was solved independently by Diaz and by Giuffrida in 1986. They showed that two curves achieving the maximum number of intersection points have to be rational curves on a smooth surface of minimal degree, i.e., a quadric surface. Note that these curves are far from being arithmetically Cohen-Macaulay. In contrast, Hartshorne and Mir\'o-Roig addressed this problem in 2015 for space curves under the assumption that the curves are arithmetically Cohen-Macaulay (ACM), introducing very deep techniques and obtaining very different results from Diaz and Giuffrida. Diaz and Giuffrida also gave initial results in dimensions greater than 3. Here we continue this study for dimension 4. We introduce a number B defined in terms of the degrees of the curves and prove that when both curves lie on a surface of minimal degree (thus a cubic surface) then the number of points of intersection is at most B. Moreover, we conjecture that B is always an upper bound and we prove this conjecture in many cases, including when at least one of the curves is ACM. Our approach focuses on the genera of the curves and their union. In addition we define a second number B' in terms of the degrees and the genus of the union which we can show bounds the number of points of intersection above, and we use a variety of methods to study how B and B' compare.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15801v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Chiantini, {\L}ucja Farnik, Giuseppe Favacchio, Brian Harbourne, Juan Migliore, Tomasz Szemberg, Justyna Szpond</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moduli of vector bundles on $\mu_n$-gerbes over genus 2 curves and the period-index problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03417</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.03417v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a framework for describing vector bundles on $\mu_n$-gerbes over curves and illustrate the construction through two detailed examples. Using the interpretation of Brauer classes as obstructions to descending determinantal line bundles from the algebraic closure, together with a geometric analysis of the moduli space of twisted sheaves, we prove that for genus $2$ curves there exist Brauer classes over the base field whose period equals their index. Over $C_1$-fields, we further show that every $2$-torsion class in the Brauer group of a genus $2$ curve satisfies the period-index problem. As an application, we construct higher-dimensional varieties obtained as fibre products of genus $2$ curves over $C_1$-fields whose $2$-torsion algebraic Brauer classes also satisfy the period-index problem, providing new evidence toward the period-index conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.03417v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ting Gong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Virtual Hodge numbers of $\mathcal{M}_{g, n}(\mathbb{P}^r, d)$: stability and calculations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.07981v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study $\mathbb{S}_n$-equivariant motivic invariants of the moduli space $\mathcal{M}_{g, n}(\mathbb{P}^r, d)$ of degree-$d$ maps from $n$-pointed curves of genus $g$ to $\mathbb{P}^r$. In particular, we obtain formulas for the Serre characteristic, which specializes to the Hodge--Deligne polynomial. Fixing $g, r \geq 1$, we prove that an explicit invertible transform of the generating function for the Serre characteristics is rational. We use our formula to prove a stability result for the weight-graded compactly-supported Euler characteristics of $\mathcal{M}_{g, n}(\mathbb{P}^r, d)$ as $d \to \infty$. In genus one and two, we reduce the calculation of the Serre characteristic of $\mathcal{M}_{g, n}(\mathbb{P}^r, d)$ to those of the moduli spaces $\mathcal{M}_{g, n}$ of $n$-pointed curves. Formulas for the latter follow from work of Getzler and Petersen, so our formula in particular determines the Serre characteristic of $\mathcal{M}_{g, n}(\mathbb{P}^r, d)$ for arbitrary $n$, $r$, and $d$ when $g = 1$ and $g = 2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07981v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siddarth Kannan, Terry Dekun Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Factoriality of normal projective varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13151v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For a normal projective variety $X$, the $\bf Q$-factoriality defect $\sigma(X)$ is defined to be the rank of the quotient of the group of Weil divisors by the subgroup of Cartier ones. We prove a slight improvement of a topological formula of S.G. Park and M. Popa asserting that $\sigma(X)=h^{2n-2}(X)-h^2(X)$ by assuming only 2-semi-rationality, that is, $R^k\pi_*{\mathcal O}_{\widetilde{X}}=0$ for $k=1,2$, instead of rational singularities for $X$, where $\pi:\widetilde{X}\to X$ is a desingularization with $h^k(X):=\dim H^k(X,{\bf Q})$ and $n:=\dim X&gt;2$. Our proof generalizes the one by Y. Namikawa and J.H.M. Steenbrink for the case $n=3$ with isolated hypersurface singularities. We also give a proof of (a slight generalization of) the assertion that $\bf Q$-factoriality implies factoriality if $X$ is a local complete intersection whose singular locus has at least codimension three. (This follows rather easily from SGA2, X.3.4, and seems to be known to specialists in the case $X$ has only isolated hypersurface singularities with $n=3$ using Milnor's Bouquet theorem.) These imply a slight improvement of Grothendieck's theorem in the projective case asserting that $X$ is factorial if it is a local complete intersection whose singular locus has at least codimension three and at general points of its components of codimension three, $X$ has rational singularities and is a $\bf Q$-homology manifold. In the hypersurface singularity case, the last condition means that any spectral number of a transversal slice to the singular locus is greater than 1 (hence less than 3), and is not an integer (more precisely, not 2), that is, 1 is not an eigenvalue of the Milnor monodromy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13151v4</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seung-Jo Jung, Morihiko Saito</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Entanglement Geometry on Severi-Brauer Schemes: Subsystem Reductions of Azumaya Algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.13764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.13764v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum entanglement is a defining signature and resource of quantum theory, but its standard definition presupposes a globally fixed decomposition into subsystems. We develop a geometric framework that detects when such a decomposition cannot be globalized for twisted families of pure-state spaces. Using Severi--Brauer schemes associated to Azumaya algebras over a base scheme, we study pure-state entanglement in families of projective state spaces that are locally trivial but globally twisted. For a given factorization type, we show that the existence of a global locus of product states is equivalent to a reduction of the underlying projective linear torsor to the stabilizer of the corresponding Segre variety, so entanglement in families becomes a geometric obstruction to globalizing subsystem structure.
  We construct the moduli space of subsystem structures, identify it with a natural torsor quotient, and realize it as a locally closed locus in the relative Hilbert scheme, yielding a canonical compactification by degenerations of product-state loci. In the bipartite case, once a subsystem structure is chosen, the Schmidt-rank stratification globalizes to a flat filtration with base-change compatible incidence resolutions and fiberwise constant numerical invariants. We complement this with Brauer-theoretic constraints and explicit examples showing that reducibility can depend on the underlying torsor rather than only on the Brauer class, with an interpretation via entangling monodromy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.13764v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuki Ikeda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$L^2$-property for algebraic stacks over local non-archimedean fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14557</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.14557v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce an $L^2$-norm on the space of Schwartz half-densities over algebraic stacks over local non-archimedean fields. We show that these $L^2$-norms are finite for the stacks of $PGL_2$-bundles on $\mathbb{P}^1$ with parabolic structures at $\ge 3$ points. The latter property was conjectured in the context of the analytic Langlands correspondence of arXiv:2103.01509.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.14557v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Kazhdan, Alexander Polishchuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Seshadri constants of adjoint divisors on surfaces and threefolds in arbitrary characteristic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.16094</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.16094v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a new approach towards obtaining lower bounds of the Seshadri constants of ample adjoint divisors on smooth projective varieties $X$ in arbitrary characteristic. Let $x\in X$ be a closed point and $A$ an ample divisor on $X$. If $X$ is a surface, we recover some known lower bounds by proving, e.g., that $\varepsilon(K_X+4A;x)\geq 3/4$. If $X$ is a threefold, we prove that for all $\delta&gt;0$ and all but finitely many curves $C$ through $x$, we have $\frac{(K_X+6A).C}{\operatorname{mult}_x C}\geq\frac{1}{2\sqrt{2}}-\delta$. In particular, if $\varepsilon(K_X+6A;x)&lt;1/(2\sqrt{2})$, then $\varepsilon(K_X+6A;x)$ is a rational number, attained by a Seshadri curve $C$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.16094v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linus R\"osler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A uniform quantitative Manin-Mumford theorem for curves over function fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2101.11593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2101.11593v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that any smooth projective geometrically connected non-isotrivial curve of genus $g\ge 2$ over a one-dimensional function field of any characteristic has at most $16g^2+32g+124$ torsion points for any Abel-Jacobi embedding of the curve into its Jacobian. The proof uses Zhang's admissible pairing on curves, the arithmetic Hodge index theorem over function fields, and the metrized graph analogue of Elkies' lower bound for the Green function. More generally, we prove an explicit Bogomolov-type result bounding the number of geometric points of small N\'eron-Tate height on the curve embedded into its Jacobian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2101.11593v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1515/crelle-2025-0055</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Reine Angew. Math. 828 (2025), pp. 127-147</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nicole Looper, Joseph Silverman, Robert Wilms</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extension of Lipschitz maps definable in Hensel minimal structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.05900</link>
      <description>arXiv:2204.05900v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we establish a theorem on extension of Lipschitz maps $f$ definable in Hensel minimal, non-trivially valued fields $K$ of equicharacteristic zero. This may be regarded as a definable, non-Archimedean, non-locally compact version of Kirszbraun's extension theorem. We proceed with double induction with respect to the dimensions of the ambient space and of the domain of $f$. To this end, we introduce the concept of a definable open cell package with a skeleton which, along with the concept of a risometry, plays a key role in our induction procedure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2204.05900v5</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Krzysztof Jan Nowak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The coarse quotient for affine Weyl groups and pseudo-reflection groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.00175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.00175v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the coarse quotient $\mathfrak{t}^*//W^{\text{aff}}$ of the affine Weyl group $W^{\text{aff}}$ acting on a dual Cartan $\mathfrak{t}^*$ for some semisimple Lie algebra. Specifically, we classify sheaves on this space via a "pointwise" criterion for descent, which says that a $W^{\text{aff}}$-equivariant sheaf on $\mathfrak{t}^*$ descends to the coarse quotient if and only if the fiber at each field-valued point descends to the associated GIT quotient. We also prove the analogous pointwise criterion for descent for an arbitrary finite group acting on a vector space. Using this, we show that an equivariant sheaf for the action of a finite pseudo-reflection group descends to the GIT quotient if and only if it descends to the associated GIT quotient for every pseudo-reflection, generalizing a recent result of Lonergan.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.00175v3</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00031-025-09941-z</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Tom Gannon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contrastive independent component analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02357v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In recent years, there has been growing interest in jointly analyzing a foreground dataset, representing an experimental group, and a background dataset, representing a control group. The goal of such contrastive investigations is to identify salient features in the experimental group relative to the control. Independent component analysis (ICA) is a powerful tool for learning independent patterns in a dataset. We generalize it to contrastive ICA (cICA). For this purpose, we devise a new linear algebra based tensor decomposition algorithm, which is more expressive but just as efficient and identifiable as other linear algebra based algorithms. We establish the identifiability of cICA and demonstrate its performance in finding patterns and visualizing data, using synthetic, semi-synthetic, and real-world datasets, comparing the approach to existing methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02357v3</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kexin Wang, Aida Maraj, Anna Seigal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First-order definability of Darmon points in number fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.03033v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For a given number field $K$, we give a $\forall\exists\forall$-first order description of affine Darmon points over $\mathbb{P}^1_K$, and show that this can be improved to a $\forall\exists$-definition in a remarkable particular case. Darmon points, which are a geometric generalization of perfect powers, constitute a non-linear set-theoretical filtration between $K$ and its ring of $S$-integers, the latter of which can be defined with universal formulas, as has been progressively proven by Koenigsmann, Park, and Eisentr\"ager &amp; Morrison. We also show that our formulas are uniform with respect to all possible $S$, with a parameter-free uniformity, and we compute the number of quantifiers and a bound for the degree of the defining polynomial.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.03033v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan Pablo De Rasis, Hunter Handley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Likelihood Correspondence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02536v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: An arrangement of hypersurfaces in projective space is strict normal crossing (SNC) if and only if its Euler discriminant is nonzero. We study the critical loci of arbitrary Laurent monomials in the equations of the smooth hypersurfaces. The family of these loci forms an irreducible variety in the product of two projective spaces, known in algebraic statistics as the likelihood correspondence and in particle physics as the scattering correspondence. We establish an explicit determinantal representation for the minimal generators of the bihomogeneous prime ideal that defines this variety.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02536v3</guid>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Kahle, Hal Schenck, Bernd Sturmfels, Maximilian Wiesmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On smoothness, tangent cones, and the metric geometry of definable sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14950</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14950v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present several definitive characterizations of the $C^1$ smoothness of definable sets in terms of their tangent cones and some other metric properties. In particular, we recover some of the beautiful characterizations presented by Ghomi and Howard (2014) and by Kurdyka, Le Gal, and Nhan (2018). For instance, we prove that for any $X\subset \mathbb{R}^n$ that is a locally closed $d$-dimensional definable set in an o-minimal structure, the following items are equivalent:
  (1) $X$ is Lipschitz normally embedded (LNE), $C_3(X,p)$ is a $d$-dimensional linear subspace for any $p\in X$ and depends continuously on $p$;
  (2) For each $p\in X$, $X$ is Lipschitz regular at $p$ and $C_4(X,p)$ is a $d$-dimensional linear subspace;
  (3) $X$ is a topological manifold and for each $p\in X$, $X$ is LNE at $p$ and $C_4(X,p)=C_3(X,p)$;
  (4) $X$ is a topological manifold, and $C_5(X,p)$ is a $d-$dimensional subset for any $p\in X$;
  (5) $X$ is $C^1$ smooth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14950v2</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'e Gadelha Rocha, Jos\'e Edson Sampaio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-negative polynomials on generalized elliptic curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13850v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the cone of non-negative polynomials on generalized elliptic curves. We show that the zero set of every extreme ray has dense real points. If a generalized elliptic curve is embedded via a complete linear system, then we show that the convex hull of its real points (taken inside any affine chart containing all real points) is a spectrahedron. On the way, we generalize a result by Geyer--Martens on 2-torsion points in the Picard group of smooth real curves (of arbitrary genus) to possibly singular and reducible ones.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13850v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mario Kummer, Alja\v{z} Zalar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Entanglement as a Cohomological Obstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.04326v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We recast quantum entanglement as a cohomological obstruction to reconstructing a global quantum state from locally compatible information. We address this by considering presheaf cohomologies of states and entanglement witnesses. Sheafification erases the global-from-local signature while leaving within-patch multipartite structure, captured by local entanglement groups introduced here. For smooth parameter families, the obstruction admits a differential-geometric representative obtained by pairing an appropriate witness field with the curvature of a natural unitary connection on the associated bundle of amplitudes. We also introduce a Quantum Entanglement Index (QEI) as an index-theoretic invariant of entangled states and explain its behavior. Finally, we outline a theoretical physics approach to probe these ideas in quantum many-body systems and suggest a possible entanglement-induced correction as an experimental validation. Detailed numerical implementations for concrete quantum many-body models are presented in the companion paper \cite{2026arXiv260113467I}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.04326v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuki Ikeda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deformations of Non-K\"ahler Hyperbolicity Notions and Modifications of Degenerate Balanced Manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19284v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study deformation properties of balanced hyperbolicity, with a particular emphasis on degenerate balanced manifolds and their behavior under smooth modifications.
  From a different perspective, we introduce two new notions of hyperbolicity for compact complex non-K\"ahler manifolds $X$ of complex dimension $\dim_{\mathbb{C}}X=n$, in general degree $2p$ with $1 \leq p \leq n-1$. These notions are motivated by the work of D.~Popovici and H.~Kasuya on partial hyperbolicity in arbitrary degree and by the work of F.~Haggui and S.~Marouani on $p$-K\"ahler hyperbolicity. The first notion, called \emph{$p$-SKT hyperbolicity}, extends SKT hyperbolicity and Gauduchon hyperbolicity to degree $2p$. Similarly, the second notion, called \emph{$p$-HS hyperbolicity}, generalizes the notion of strongly Gauduchon hyperbolicity introduced by Y.~Ma.
  We then analyze the relationships between these analytic notions and geometric notions of hyperbolicity, namely Brody/Kobayashi hyperbolicity and \emph{$p$-cyclic hyperbolicity} in degree $2p$ for $2 \leq p \leq n-1$. In addition, we study the behavior of $p$-HS hyperbolicity and $p$-K\"ahler hyperbolicity under holomorphic deformations, establishing openness results for these properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19284v4</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdelouahab Khelifati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adventures of Harish-Chandra in $\mathbb Z_2 \times \mathbb Z_2$-graded world</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.07803v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study $\mathbb Z_2\times\mathbb Z_2$ bi-graded Lie algebras. We describe their properties in relation to Lie superalgebras with some compatible structures. Then we focus on the approach to the Lie group--algebra correspondence based on Harish-Chandra pairs and provide some examples of application of it in the bi-graded setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07803v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olga Chekeres, Alexei Kotov, Vladimir Salnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
