<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG</link>
    <description>math.AG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 03:02:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>An algorithm for annihilator and Bernstein-Sato polynomial of a rational function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.00280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.00280v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The singularity theory of rational functions, i.e., the quotient of two polynomials, has been investigated in the past two decades. The Bernstein-Sato polynomial of a rational function has recently been introduced by Takeuchi. However, only trivial examples are known. We provide an algorithm for computing the Bernstein-Sato polynomial in this context. The strategy is to compute the annihilator of the rational function by using the annihilator of the pair consisting of the numerator and denominator of the quotient. In a natural way a non-vanishing condition on the Bernstein-Sato ideal of the pair appears. This method has been implemented in freely available computer algebra system SINGULAR. It relies on Gr\"obner bases in noncommutative PBW algebras. The algorithm allows us to exhibit some explicit non-trivial examples and to support some existing conjectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.00280v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuel Gonz\'alez-Villa, Edwin Le\'on-Cardenal, Viktor Levandovskyy, Jorge Mart\'in-Morales</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Log Canonical Thresholds for Plane Curves in Arbitrary Characteristic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.00503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.00503v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We generalize the formula for the log canonical threshold(LCT) of plane curves over the complex numbers to arbitrary characteristics. Our proof relies purely on valuation theory, instead of on the theory of $D$-modules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.00503v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chih-Kuang Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Note on $\mathbb{Q}$-Gorenstein surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.00732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.00732v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct a normal projective $\mathbb{Q}$-Gorenstein surface over an algebraically closed field whose canonical ring is not finitely generated. Moreover, we provide a counterexample to the minimal model program for $\mathbb{Q}$-Gorenstein surfaces, which was previously unknown in positive characteristic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.00732v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nao Moriyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Affine hyperplane arrangements at finite distance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.00847</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.00847v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the relative homology group of an affine hyperplane arrangement and its Poincar\'e dual, the cohomology at finite distance of the complement. We give an Orlik--Solomon-type description of the latter, and identify it with the vector space of logarithmic forms having vanishing residues at infinity. To this end, we introduce a partial version of wonderful compactifications, which could be relevant in other contexts where blow-ups only occur at infinity. Finally, we show that the cohomology at finite distance coincides with the vector space of canonical forms in the sense of positive geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.00847v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ana\"elle Pfister</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The geometry of Nekrasov's gauge origami theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.00984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.00984v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nekrasov's gauge origami theory provides a (complex) 4-dimensional generalization of the ADHM quiver and its moduli spaces of representations. We describe the origami moduli space as the zero locus of an isotropic section of a quadratic vector bundle on a smooth space. This allows us to give an algebro-geometric definition of the origami partition function in terms of Oh--Thomas virtual cycles. The key input is the computation of a sign associated to each torus fixed point of the moduli space. Furthermore, we establish an integrality result and dimensional reduction formulae, and discuss an application to non-perturbative Dyson--Schwinger equations following Nekrasov's work. Finally, we conjecture a description of the origami moduli space in terms of certain 2-dimensional framed sheaves on $\mathbb{P}^1 \times \mathbb{P}^1 \times \mathbb{P}^1 \times \mathbb{P}^1$, which we verify at the level of torus fixed points.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.00984v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noah Arbesfeld, Martijn Kool, Woonam Lim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal algebraic tangent cone of torsion-free sheaves via valuations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.01112v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a valuation-theoretic framework for studying tangent cones of torsion-free sheaves on algebraic varieties. To analyze these objects, we introduce a slope stability theory, including the Harder-Narasimhan filtrations, for finitely generated $\mathbb{R}$-graded modules over finitely generated $\mathbb{R}_{\geq 0}$-graded algebras. Using it, we show that there is a canonically determined tangent cone of torsion-free sheaves, up to the expected equivalence ambiguity, for quasi-regular valuations, which generalize Chen-Sun [3].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.01112v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yohei Hada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stubborn Polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.01191v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The relationship between nonnegative polynomials and sums of squares is a classical topic in real algebraic geometry. We study \emph{stubborn polynomials} $f$ on a real variety $X$, which are polynomials nonnegative on $X$, such that no odd power of $f$ is a sum of squares. Previously, stubborn polynomials were studied only in the globally nonnegative case, with results restricted to polynomials nonnegative on $\mathbb{P}^2$. We fully characterize stubborn polynomials on smooth curves, showing that a polynomial on a smooth totally real curve is stubborn if and only if all of its zeros are real. This implies that there exist smooth curves with no stubborn polynomials in low degree, while stubborn polynomials must exist in sufficiently high degrees on curves with positive genus. We explore the much more delicate situation with singular and reducible curves. While being real-rooted always implies being stubborn, there also exist singular curves with no stubborn polynomials at all.
  We then analyze the case of ternary sextics, i.e.,~polynomials of degree $6$ on $\mathbb{P}^2$. We prove the Conjecture of Blekherman, Kozhasov, and Reznick that a nonnegative ternary sextic is stubborn if and only if its real delta-invariant is at least 9. To analyze this case, we develop results for lifting stubborn polynomials from curves to higher dimensional varieties and use the theory of weak Del Pezzo surfaces. We complement these results with structural properties of stubborn polynomials and present many explicit examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.01191v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Baldi, Grigoriy Blekherman, Khazhgali Kozhasov, Daniel Plaumann, Bruce Reznick, Rainer Sinn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ulrich Sheaves on the Hilbert Square of K3 and Abelian Surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01218</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.01218v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove the existence of Ulrich sheaves on the Hilbert scheme of two points on a polarized K3 surface or an abelian surface. The construction proceeds by descending Ulrich bundles on the surface to the symmetric square and lifting them to the Hilbert square via the crepant Hilbert Chow resolution. Finally, we estimate a bound for Ulrich complexity of the Hilbert square.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.01218v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anindya Mukherjee, Pabitra Barik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchical Locally Recoverable Codes on surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.01464v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct locally recoverable codes with hierarchy from surfaces in $\mathbb{A}^3$ admitting a fibration by curves of Artin-Schreier or Kummer type. We derive the parameters of our codes by leveraging the geometry and arithmetic of the fibration, which is obtained by projection onto one of the coordinates. As a byproduct, we obtain estimates for (and in one case an explicit count of) the number of rational points in certain families of surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.01464v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carolina Araujo, Luana Costa, Beth Malmskog, Jorge Mello, Eliza Menezes, Cec\'ilia Salgado, Lara Vicino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimally Packing a Large Square by Unit Squares</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01484</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.01484v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that a large square of sidelength $x$ can be packed by unit squares in a manner so that the wasted space $W(x) = O(x^{3/5})$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.01484v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rory McClenagan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new criterion for the absolute irreducibility of multivariate polynomials over finite fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.01583v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A key property of an algebraic variety is whether it is absolutely irreducible, meaning that it remains irreducible over the algebraic closure of its defining field, and determining absolute irreducibility is important in algebraic geometry and its applications in coding theory, cryptography, and other fields.
  Among the applications of absolute irreducibility are bounding the number of rational points via the Weil conjectures and establishing exceptional APN and permutation properties of functions over finite fields. In this article, we present a new criterion for the absolute irreducibility of hypersurfaces defined by multivariate polynomials over finite fields. Our criterion does not require testing for irreducibility in the ground or extension fields, assuming that the leading form is square-free. We just require multivariate GCD computations and the square-free property. Since almost all polynomials are known to be square-free, our absolute irreducibility criterion is valid for almost all multivariate polynomials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.01583v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Agrinsoni, Heeralal Janwa, Moises Delgado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mok tensors and Orbifold Quotients of Bounded symmetric domains without ball factors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.01980v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we characterize the compact orbifolds, quotients $ X = \mathcal{D}/ \Gamma$ of a bounded symmetric domain $\mathcal{D}$ with no higher dimensional ball factor by the action of a discontinuous group $\Gamma$, as those projective orbifolds with ample orbifold canonical divisor which admit a Mok curvature type tensor of orbifold type and satisfying certain other conditions implying the existence of a finite smooth covering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.01980v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabrizio Catanese (Universit\"at Bayreuth), Marco Franciosi (Universit\'a di Pisa)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singularities in any Characteristic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.02042</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.02042v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give an overview of the fundamental definitions and results concerning hypersurface singularities, defined by convergent power series over an arbitrary real valued field. This approach combines, on the one hand, the classical case of analytic power series over the complex numbers with formal power series over arbitrary fields, but on the other hand, it goes significantly beyond that. Besides general definitions and basic results, we report on the classification of contact simple and right simple singularities in positive characteristic. Some of the results are new in this general setting, for which we provide complete proofs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.02042v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gert-Martin Greuel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trigonal and embedded tropical curves of low genus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.02257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.02257v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In algebraic geometry, trigonal curves can always be embedded into Hirzebruch surfaces. In tropical geometry, the notion of trigonality does not have a unique translation. We focus on the characterization in terms of the existence of a degree 3 morphism to a line, and discuss relations to possible embeddings into $\mathbb R^2$ reflecting an embedding into a Hirzebruch surface. Our results can be divided into three parts: for tropical curves of low genus 3 and 4, we discuss the relation between a trigonal morphism and an embedding dual to the polygon of a Hirzebruch surface, building on works on embeddings of hyperelliptic tropical curves and curves of low genus. We compare obstructions for embeddings with obstructions for the existence of a degree 3 morphism to a line. Finally, we showcase examples where a non-smooth embedding can be unfolded to reflect certain features of a degree 3 morphism to a line.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.02257v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hannah Markwig, Angelina Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The theorem of Maehara-Severi for maps of general type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.02314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.02314v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a finiteness result for dominant rational maps whose orbifold base is of general type. Our finiteness result generalizes Maehara's theorem that a given variety dominates only finitely many projective varieties of general type up to birational equivalence, and also answers a question of Campana on the finiteness of Bogomolov sheaves. We give several further applications, including finiteness results for maps to curves, abelian varieties, and K3 surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.02314v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Finn Bartsch, Ariyan Javanpeykar, Erwan Rousseau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The singular Hitchin fibration, cameral data, and representation theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.00274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.00274v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For a complex reductive group $G$, we consider the locus $M^d$ in the moduli stack of $G$-Higgs bundles on which the centraliser dimension of the Higgs field takes a constant value $d&gt; rk(G)$. We describe a non-abelian structure for the Hitchin fibration on $M^d$, under mild conditions on the geometry of the centraliser level set $\mathfrak{g}_d$ in the Lie algebra. If $G$ is a classical group, we also show that the restriction of the Hitchin map to the locus of generically semisimple Higgs bundles in $M^d$ factors through an abelian fibration. The abelianised fibres can be described using a generalisation of the cameral data of Donagi and Gaitsgory.
  We apply these constructions to $G_\mathbb{R}$-Hitchin fibrations for real forms $G_\mathbb{R}$. In particular we give a cameral description for an abelianisation of the $G_\mathbb{R}$-Hitchin fibration, which extends the known description in the quasi-split case. We determine this explicitly in the examples $G_\mathbb{R} = SU(p,q)$ and $G_{\mathbb{R}} = SO^*(4m+2)$. Our local results also give a connection between the geometry of the Hitchin fibration on $M^d$ and the representation theory of the Lie algebra $\mathfrak{g}$, via the orbit method. As a corollary, we determine an explicit asymptotic relationship between two notions of multiplicity, one attached to an adjoint orbit in $\mathfrak{g}$ and one attached to a primitive ideal of the universal enveloping algebra of $\mathfrak{g}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.00274v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Fr\"uh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topology and Geometry of the Learning Space of ReLU Networks: Connectivity and Singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.00693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.00693v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Understanding the properties of the parameter space in feed-forward ReLU networks is critical for effectively analyzing and guiding training dynamics. After initialization, training under gradient flow decisively restricts the parameter space to an algebraic variety that emerges from the homogeneous nature of the ReLU activation function. In this study, we examine two key challenges associated with feed-forward ReLU networks built on general directed acyclic graph (DAG) architectures: the (dis)connectedness of the parameter space and the existence of singularities within it. We extend previous results by providing a thorough characterization of connectedness, highlighting the roles of bottleneck nodes and balance conditions associated with specific subsets of the network. Our findings clearly demonstrate that singularities are intricately connected to the topology of the underlying DAG and its induced sub-networks. We discuss the reachability of these singularities and establish a principled connection with differentiable pruning. We validate our theory with simple numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.00693v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Nurisso, Pierrick Leroy, Giovanni Petri, Francesco Vaccarino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear Operators $T:\mathbb{R}[x_1,\dots,x_n]\to\mathbb{R}[x_1,\dots,x_n]$ and $K$-Positivity Preserver: A Short Review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.00967</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.00967v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the current short review we present the latest developments on linear maps $T:\mathbb{R}[x_1,\dots,x_n]\to\mathbb{R}[x_1,\dots,x_n]$, especially of $K$-positivity preserver, i.e., $Tp\geq 0$ on $K\subseteq\mathbb{R}^n$ for all $p\in\mathbb{R}[x_1,\dots,x_n]$ with $p\geq 0$ on $K$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.00967v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philipp J. di Dio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Factorization algebras in quite a lot of generality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.01292v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This is a first stab at a mathematical framework in which one can study quantum field theories on spacetimes with quite general geometries. We will study these theories via their factorization algebras. The aim is to identify a minimalist formalism that makes sense of factorization algebras in any geometric context. This formalism extends the technology of factorization algebras to many new contexts, including those arising in arithmetic quantum field theories.
  In order to make sense of factorization algebras on a geometric object X, one needs two ingredients. First, one needs an additional piece of structure on X that we call an "isolability structure." This is the data required to say whether two (generalized) points of X are "distant." This is encoded as a functor from a certain combinatorial category of cographs. Second, one needs some sort of sheaf theory. The isolability structure then induces on the category of sheaves a kind of twofold symmetric monoidal structure. Factorization algebras are then defined in terms of this structure.
  This paper develops this formalism. We describe how some existing theories of factorization algebras fit into this framework, and we give a construction of the Beilinson-Drinfeld Grassmannian as a factorization stack that works in quite a lot of generality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.01292v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Clark Barwick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Squares in arithmetic progression over certain non-primitive quartic number fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.01380v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $D$ be a square-free integer. Under certain conditions on $D$, we characterize non-constant arithmetic progressions of squares over quadratic extensions of $\mathbb{Q}(\sqrt{D})$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.01380v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jnt.2025.11.005</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Number Theory 282 (2026) 13-30</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Enrique Gonz\'alez-Jim\'enez, Nguyen Xuan Tho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the squareness of the discriminant of elliptic curves with an isogeny</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01384</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.01384v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We establish a classification of the values of \( N \) for which an elliptic curve defined over \( \mathbb{Q} \) with square discriminant admits an \( N \)-isogeny. Furthermore, we determine the values of \( N \) for which two elliptic curves defined over \( \mathbb{Q} \), both possessing square discriminants, are \( N \)-isogenous. In both cases, we explicitly parametrize the corresponding \( j \)-invariants of the elliptic curves associated with these problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.01384v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s13398-025-01811-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Revista de la Real Academia de Ciencias Exactas, F\'isicas y Naturales. Serie A. Matem\'atica 120 (2026), no. 1, Paper No. 20</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Enrique Gonz\'alez-Jim\'enez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quadratic points on the Fermat quartic over number fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.01398v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $C$ be a curve defined over a number field $K$. A point $P\in C(\overline{\mathbb{Q}})$ is called $K$-quadratic if $[K(P):K]=2$. Let $K$ be a number field such that the rank of the elliptic curves $E_1:\,y^2= x^3 + 4x$ and $E_2:\,y^2= x^3 - 4x$ over $K$ are $0$. Under the above condition, we prove that the set of $K$-quadratic points on the Fermat quartic $F_4\colon X^4+Y^4=Z^4$ is finite and computable and we provide a procedure to compute this finite set. In particular, we explicitly compute all the $K$-quadratic points if $[K:\mathbb{Q}]&lt;8$. Moreover, if the degree of $K$ is odd, we prove that all the $K$-quadratic points corresponds just to the $\mathbb{Q}$-quadratic points</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.01398v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrique Gonz\'alez-Jim\'enez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-valued flat connections in several variables on arbitrary Riemann surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.01461v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Polylogarithms on Riemann surfaces may be constructed efficiently in terms of flat connections that can enjoy various algebraic and analytic properties. In this paper, we present a single-valued and modular invariant connection ${\cal J}_\text{DHS}$ on the configuration space $\text{Cf}_n(\Sigma)$ of an arbitrary number $n$ of points on an arbitrary compact Riemann surface $\Sigma$ with or without punctures. The connection ${\cal J}_\text{DHS}$ generalizes an earlier construction for a single variable and is built out of the same integration kernels. We show that ${\cal J}_\text{DHS}$ is flat on $\text{Cf}_n(\Sigma)$. For the case without punctures, we relate it to the meromorphic multiple-valued Enriquez connection ${\cal K}_\text{E}$ in $n$ variables on the universal cover $\tilde \Sigma$ of $\Sigma$ by the composition of a gauge transformation and an automorphism of the Lie algebra in which ${\cal J}_\text{DHS}$ and ${\cal K}_\text{E}$ take values. In a companion paper, we shall establish the equivalence between the flatness of these connections and the corresponding interchange and Fay identities, for arbitrary compact Riemann surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.01461v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric D'Hoker, Oliver Schlotterer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Genus-0 Surface Parameterization using Spherical Beltrami Differentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.01589v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spherical surface parameterization is a fundamental tool in geometry processing and imaging science. For a genus-0 closed surface, many efficient algorithms can map the surface to the sphere; consequently, a broad class of task-driven genus-0 mapping problems can be reduced to constructing a high-quality spherical self-map. However, existing approaches often face a trade-off between satisfying task objectives (e.g., landmark or feature alignment), maintaining bijectivity, and controlling geometric distortion. We introduce the Spherical Beltrami Differential (SBD), a two-chart representation of quasiconformal self-maps of the sphere, and establish its correspondence with spherical homeomorphisms up to conformal automorphisms. Building on the Spectral Beltrami Network (SBN), we propose a neural optimization framework BOOST that optimizes two Beltrami fields on hemispherical stereographic charts and enforces global consistency through explicit seam-aware constraints. Experiments on large-deformation landmark matching and intensity-based spherical registration demonstrate the effectiveness of our proposed framework. We further apply the method to brain cortical surface registration, aligning sulcal landmarks and jointly matching cortical sulci depth maps, showing improved task fidelity with controlled distortion and robust bijective behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.01589v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhehao Xu, Lok Ming Lui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantitativity on the number of rational points in the Mordell conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.01820v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove an explicit upper bound on the number of rational points on a smooth projective curve of genus at least two over a number field. This gives explicit constants in the uniform Mordell conjecture proposed by Mazur and proved by Vojta, Dimitrov-Gao-Habegger, and K\"uhne. The main body of this paper consists of two parts: Part I for arithmetic estimates and Part II for analytic estimates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.01820v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiawei Yu, Xinyi Yuan, Shengxuan Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sheets, Jordan classes and induced orbits in the exotic and enhanced modules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.02404</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.02404v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Kato developed an exotic Deligne-Langlands correspondence using a geometric model for the multiparameter affine Hecke algebra of type C, based on his exotic nilpotent cone. Achar-Henderson and Springer showed that this exotic nilpotent is intimately related to another, apparently simpler variety called the enhanced nilpotent cone. Each of these is defined as the Hilbert nullcone of a polar module, the exotic Sp(2n)-module and the enhanced GL(n)-module, respectively.
  In this paper we conduct a detailed study of the geometry of these two modules, by introducing the Jordan stratification, simultaneously generalising classical results on the adjoint representation as well as the symmetric space associated to (gl(2n), sp(2n)). One of the key tools we develop is the theory of induced orbits in the enhanced and exotic nilpotent cones, following the work of Lusztig-Spaltenstein. Our main application is a classification of sheets in these modules, inspired by a theorem of Borho.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.02404v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Filippo Ambrosio, Giovanna Carnovale, Francesco Esposito, Neil Saunders, Lewis Topley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spherical representations of unitary groups at ramified places and the arithmetic inner product formula</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.02492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.02492v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this article, we study admissible representations of even unitary groups over local fields, where the quadratic extension is ramified, with invariant vectors under the action of the stabilizer of a unimodular lattice and some properties of the corresponding integral model of unitary Shimura varieties. As a direct application, we are able to improve the arithmetic inner product formula so that the places with local root number \((-1)\) are allowed to be ramified.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.02492v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhuoni Chi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the $p$-adic theory of local models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2201.01234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2201.01234v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove the Scholze--Weinstein conjecture on the existence and uniqueness of local models for local Shimura varieties, as well as the test function conjecture of Haines--Kottwitz in this framework. To this end, we establish a specialization principle for well-behaved $p$-adic kimberlites, show that these include the v-sheaf local models, determine their special fibers using hyperbolic localization for the \'etale cohomology of small v-stacks, and analyze the resulting specialization morphism using convolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2201.01234v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Ansch\"utz, Ian Gleason, Jo\~ao Louren\c{c}o, Timo Richarz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wobbly moduli of chains, equivariant multiplicities and $\mathrm{U}(n_0,n_1)$-Higgs bundles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08563</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.08563v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We give a birational description of the reduced schemes underlying the irreducible components of the nilpotent cone and the $\CC^\times$-fixed point locus of length two in the moduli space of Higgs bundles. Using these results, we prove Drinfeld's conjecture for the sublocus of type $(n_0,n_1)$ fixed points. We introduce the notion of $\U(n_0,n_1)$-wobbliness (stronger than the one of wobbliness) and show that fixed point components of type $(n_0,n_1)$ are wobbly in rank higher than three, if and only if they are also $\U(n_0,n_1)$-wobbly. This yields a computable criterion to check wobbliness of fixed point components, that simplifies the existing ones. We analyse the virtual equivariant multiplicities of fixed points of type $(n_0,n_1)$ and their Euler pairings with downward flows for type $(1,\dots, 1)$ fixed points. We find that both invariants fail to fully detect all wobbly components for ordered partitions other than $(2,1)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.08563v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ana Pe\'on-Nieto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum cohomology of projective bundles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.03696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.03696v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct an I-function of the projective bundle P(V) associated with a not necessarily split vector bundle V\to B as a Fourier transform of the S^1-equivariant J-function of the total space of V and show that it lies on the Givental Lagrangian cone of P(V). Using this result, we show that the quantum cohomology D-module of P(V) splits into the direct sum of the quantum cohomology D-modules of the base space B. This has applications to the semisimplicity of big quantum cohomology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.03696v4</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroshi Iritani, Yuki Koto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Construction of free arrangements using point-line operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20024</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20024v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct new examples of free curve arrangements in the complex projective plane using point-line operators recently defined by the second author. In particular, we construct a new example of a conic-line arrangement with ordinary quasi-homogeneous singularities that has non-trivial monodromy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20024v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Piotr Pokora, Xavier Roulleau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stokes phenomenon of Kloosterman and Airy connections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09582v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We define categories of Stokes filtered and Stokes graded $G$-local systems for reductive groups $G$ and use the formalism of Tannakian categories to show that they are equivalent to the category of $G$-connections. We then use the interpretation of moduli spaces of Stokes filtered $G$-local systems as braid varieties to prove physical rigidity of two well-known families of cohomologically rigid connections, the Kloosterman and Airy connections. In the Kloosterman case, our proof relies on Steinberg's cross-section.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09582v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Hohl, Konstantin Jakob</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Log Baum--Bott Residues for foliations by curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04015</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04015v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove a Baum--Bott type residual formula for one-dimensional holomorphic foliations, and logarithmic along free divisors. More precisely, this provides a Baum--Bott theorem for a foliated triple $(X, \mathcal{F}, D)$, where $\mathcal{F}$ is a foliation by curves and $D$ is a free divisor on a complex manifold $X$. From the local point of view, we show that the log Baum--Bott residues are a generalization of the Aleksandrov logarithmic index for vector fields with isolated singularities on hypersurfaces. We also show how these new indices are related to Poincar\'e's Problem for foliations by curves. In the case of foliated surfaces, we show that the differences between the logarithmic residues and Baum--Bott indices along invariant curves can be expressed in terms of the GSV and Camacho--Sad indices. We also obtain a Baum--Bott type formula for singular varieties via log resolutions. Finally, we prove a weak global version of the Zariski--Lipman conjecture for compact algebraic surfaces, in the form of a foliated smoothness criterion, suggesting the appearance of saddle-nodes in the singularity reduction on singular surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04015v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maur\'icio Corr\^ea, Fernando Louren\c{c}o, Diogo Machado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Logarithmic $\bf{\partial\bar\partial}$-lemma and several geometric applications (with an Appendix joint with Sheng Rao)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09447v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove a $\partial\bar{\partial}$-type lemma on compact K\"ahler manifolds for logarithmic differential forms valued in the dual of a certain pseudo-effective line bundle, thereby confirming a conjecture proposed by X. Wan.
  We then derive several applications, including strengthened results by H. Esnault-E. Viehweg on the degeneracy of the spectral sequence at the $E_1$-stage for projective manifolds associated with the logarithmic de Rham complex, as well as by L. Katzarkov-M. Kontsevich-T. Pantev on the unobstructed locally trivial deformations of a projective generalized log Calabi-Yau pair with some weights, both of which are extended to the broader context of compact K\"ahler manifolds.
  Furthermore, we establish the K\"ahler version of an injectivity theorem originally formulated by F. Ambro in the algebraic setting. Notably, while O. Fujino previously addressed the K\"ahler case, our proof takes a different approach by avoiding the reliance on mixed Hodge structures for cohomology with compact support.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09447v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Runze Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Teissier's example of an equisingularity class that cannot be defined over the rationals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10863</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10863v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A result of Teissier says that the cone over one of classical polygon examples in the real projective space gives, by complexification, a surface singularity which is not Whitney equisingular to a singularity defined over the field of rational numbers Q. In this note we correct the example and give a complete proof of Tesissier's result.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10863v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.4064/1p241208-25-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Annales Mathematici Polonici 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Adam Parusi\'nski, Laurentiu Paunescu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compact Moduli Spaces of Marked Cubic Plane Curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14927v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study compactifications of the moduli space of a plane cubic curve marked by \(n\) labeled points up to projective equivalence via Geometric Invariant Theory (GIT). Specifically, we provide a complete description of the GIT walls and show that the moduli-theoretic wall-crossing can be understood through analysis of the singularities of the plane curves and the position of the points.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14927v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aaron Goodwin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smooth Calabi-Yau varieties with large index and Betti numbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.07031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.07031v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A normal variety $X$ is called Calabi-Yau if $K_X \sim_{\mathbb Q} 0$. The index of $X$ is the smallest positive integer $m$ so that $m K_X \sim 0$. We construct smooth, projective Calabi-Yau varieties in every dimension with doubly exponentially growing index, which we conjecture to be maximal in every dimension. We also construct smooth, projective Calabi-Yau varieties with extreme topological invariants; namely, their Euler characteristics and the sums of their Betti numbers grow doubly exponentially. These are conjecturally extremal in every dimension. The varieties we construct are known in small dimensions but we believe them to be new in general. This work builds off of the singular Calabi-Yau varieties found by Esser, Totaro, and Wang in arXiv:2209.04597.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.07031v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jas Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The variety of nilpotent pairs $(A,B)$ with $[A,B] = \lambda I$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20199</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20199v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $k$ be an algebraically closed field of characteristic $p &gt;0$. We consider the variety of nilpotent pairs $(A,B)$ with $[A,B]=\lambda I$, namely the set of pairs $ X = \{ (A,B) \in M_n(k) \times M_n(k) \mid A,B \text{ nilpotent}, [A,B]=\lambda I, \lambda \in k \}$. We prove that if $n=pr$, then $X$ is irreducible of dimension $n^2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20199v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vlad Roman, Robert M. Guralnick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On p-Jordan Constant of Cremona Group of Rank 2 in Odd Characteristic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.15522v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We bound the indices of normal abelian subgroups in finite groups contained in the Cremona group of rank 2 over a field of odd characteristic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.15522v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifei Chen, Constantin Shramov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complements of caustics of the real $J_{10}$ singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03883v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The complete list of connected components of the set of Morse functions in the deformations of function singularities of class $J_{10}$ is given. Thus, the isotopy classification of Morse perturbations of parabolic real function singularities is finished.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03883v4</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. A. Vassiliev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixed Hodge structures for vanishing cycles and orbifold cohomology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13223v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Above a Laurent polynomial f one makes grow a vector space of vanishing cycles (after the work of Sabbah, singularity setting), a graded Milnor ring (after the work of Kouchnirenko) and an orbifold cohomology ring (after the work of Borisov, Chen and Smith). Under suitable assumptions, these structures are isomorphic and these identifications are interesting because some results are more explicit in one setting than in another. In particular, and in order to understand better the real structures and the dualities appearing in the singularity setting, we first look for the counterpart of Sabbah's mixed Hodge structures, initially defined on the space of vanishing cycles, on the orbifold cohomology ring. Then, we discuss to what extent the orbifold Poincar\'e duality defined by Chen and Ruan provides a polarization of this mixed Hodge structure. We study in details the Hodge-Tate case, which can be read off from the ages of the sectors, a variation of the hard Lefschetz condition introduced by Fernandez. These notes go along with prior works of Fernandez and Wang.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13223v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antoine Douai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rationality of the trivial lattice rank weighted motivic height zeta function for elliptic surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.15543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.15543v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $k$ be a perfect field with $\mathrm{char}(k)\neq 2,3$, set $K=k(t)$, and let $\mathcal{W}_n^{\min}$ be the moduli stack of minimal elliptic curves over $K$ of Faltings height $n$ from the height-moduli framework of Bejleri-Park-Satriano applied to $\overline{\mathcal{M}}_{1,1}\simeq \mathcal{P}(4,6)$. For $[E]\in \mathcal{W}_n^{\min}$, let $S \to \mathbb{P}^1_{k}$ be the associated elliptic surface with section. Motivated by the Shioda-Tate formula, we consider the trivariate motivic height zeta function \[ \mathcal{Z}(u,v;t):= \sum_{n\ge0}\Bigl(\sum_{[E]\in \mathcal{W}_n^{\min}} u^{T(S)}v^{\mathrm{rk}(E/K)}\Bigr)t^n \in K_0(\mathrm{Stck}_k)[u,v][[t]] \] which refines the height series by weighting each height stratum with the trivial lattice rank $T(S)$ and the Mordell--Weil rank $\mathrm{rk}(E/K)$. We prove rationality for the trivial lattice specialization $Z_{\mathrm{Triv}}(u;t)=\mathcal{Z}(u,1;t)$ by giving an explicit finite Euler product. We conjecture irrationality for the N\'eron-Severi $Z_{\mathrm{NS}}(w;t)=\mathcal{Z}(w,w;t)$ and the Mordell-Weil $Z_{\mathrm{MW}}(v;t)=\mathcal{Z}(1,v;t)$ specializations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.15543v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun-Yong Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$K$-Equivalence and Integral Cohomology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.22085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.22085v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce an integral version of the Hodge polynomial, which encodes the integral cohomology of smooth projective varieties. We prove it extends to a function which is well-defined on the Grothendieck ring of varieties and we obtain as a consequence that $K$-equivalent smooth projective varieties have isomorphic integral cohomology groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.22085v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Satriano, Evan Sundbo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Categories of Line Defects and Cohomological Hall Algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.07134v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Any four-dimensional Supersymmetric Quantum Field Theory with eight supercharges can be associated to a monoidal category of BPS line defects. Any Coulomb vacuum of such a theory can be conjecturally associated to an ``algebra of BPS particles'', exemplified by certain Cohomological Hall Algebras. We conjecture the existence of a monoidal functor from the category of line defects to a certain category of bimodules for the BPS Algebra in any Coulomb vacuum. We describe images of simple objects under the conjectural functor and study their monoidal structure in examples. We conjecture that the functor may be an equivalence of dg-categories and test the conjecture at the level of the equivariant Witten indices of the spaces of morphisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.07134v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davide Gaiotto, Nikita Grygoryev, Wei Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Borel-Weil factorization for super Grassmannians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05167</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05167v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This article deals with computing the cohomology of Schur functors applied to tautological bundles on super Grassmannians. We show that in a range of cases, the cohomology is a free module over the cohomology of the structure sheaf and that the space of generators is an irreducible representation of the general linear supergroup that can be constructed via explicit multilinear operations. Our techniques come from commutative algebra: we relate this cohomology calculation to Tor groups of certain algebraic varieties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05167v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steven V Sam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuity of the solution map for hyperbolic polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01321v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Hyperbolic polynomials are monic real-rooted polynomials. By Bronshtein's theorem, the increasingly ordered roots of a hyperbolic polynomial of degree $d$ with $C^{d-1,1}$ coefficients are locally Lipschitz and the solution map "coefficients-to-roots" is bounded. We prove continuity of this solution map from hyperbolic polynomials of degree $d$ with $C^d$ coefficients to their increasingly ordered roots with respect to the $C^d$ structure on the source space and the Sobolev $W^{1,q}$ structure, for all $1 \le q&lt;\infty$, on the target space. Continuity fails for $q=\infty$. As a consequence, we obtain continuity of the local surface area of the roots as well as local lower semicontinuity of the area of the zero sets of hyperbolic polynomials. We also discuss applications for the eigenvalues of Hermitian matrices and singular values.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01321v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam Parusi\'nski, Armin Rainer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relating flat connections and polylogarithms on higher genus Riemann surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07640v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we relate two recent constructions that generalize classical (genus-zero) polylogarithms to higher-genus Riemann surfaces. A flat connection valued in a freely generated Lie algebra on a punctured Riemann surface of arbitrary genus produces an infinite family of homotopy-invariant iterated integrals associated to all possible words in the alphabet of the Lie algebra generators. Each iterated integral associated to a word is a higher-genus polylogarithm. Different flat connections taking values in the same Lie algebra on a given Riemann surface may be related to one another by the composition of a gauge transformation and an automorphism of the Lie algebra, thus producing closely related families of polylogarithms. In this paper we provide two methods to explicitly construct this correspondence between the meromorphic multiple-valued connection introduced by Enriquez in e-Print 1112.0864 and the non-meromorphic single-valued and modular-invariant connection introduced by D'Hoker, Hidding and Schlotterer, in e-Print 2306.08644.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07640v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric D'Hoker, Benjamin Enriquez, Oliver Schlotterer, Federico Zerbini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifiability of Deep Polynomial Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.17093v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Polynomial Neural Networks (PNNs) possess a rich algebraic and geometric structure. However, their identifiability -- a key property for ensuring interpretability -- remains poorly understood. In this work, we present a comprehensive analysis of the identifiability of deep PNNs, including architectures with and without bias terms. Our results reveal an intricate interplay between activation degrees and layer widths in achieving identifiability. As special cases, we show that architectures with non-increasing layer widths are generically identifiable under mild conditions, while encoder-decoder networks are identifiable when the decoder widths do not grow too rapidly compared to the activation degrees. Our proofs are constructive and center on a connection between deep PNNs and low-rank tensor decompositions, and Kruskal-type uniqueness theorems. We also settle an open conjecture on the dimension of PNN's neurovarieties, and provide new bounds on the activation degrees required for it to reach the expected dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.17093v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantin Usevich, Ricardo Borsoi, Clara D\'erand, Marianne Clausel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Geometric P=W conjecture and Thurston's compactification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07211</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07211v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we use new results together with established facts about Thurston's compactification of Teichm\"uller space to address the geometric P=W conjecture for $\mathrm{SL}(2,\mathbb{C})$, which concerns projective compactifications of character varieties of closed surfaces. In particular, we construct a projective compactification of the $\mathrm{SL}(2,\mathbb{C})$-character variety of any closed surface of genus $g&gt;1$, in which the boundary divisors are toric varieties and the dual intersection complex is a sphere. A main technical step, of independent interest, is the derivation of an explicit formula for a well-known embedding of the set of isotopy classes of multicurves on a closed surface of genus $g$ into $\mathbb{N}^{9g-9}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07211v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashwin Ayilliath-Kutteri, Mohammad Farajzadeh-Tehrani, Charles Frohman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calabi-Yau structures on derived and singularity categories of symmetric orders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.03836v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct left and right Calabi-Yau structures on derived respectively singularity categories of symmetric orders $\Lambda$ over commutative Gorenstein rings $R$. For this, we first construct Calabi-Yau structures over $R$ by lifting Amiot's construction of Calabi-Yau structures on Verdier quotients to the dg level. Then we prove base change properties relating Calabi-Yau structures over $R$ to those over the base field $k$. As a result, we prove the existence of a right Calabi-Yau structure on the dg singularity category associated with $\Lambda$ which is a cyclic lift of the weak Calabi-Yau structure constructed by the first-named author and Iyama. We also show the existence of a left Calabi-Yau structure on the dg bounded derived category of $\Lambda$. This is a non-commutative generalization of a result by Brav and Dyckerhoff. By combining the existence of the right Calabi-Yau structure on the dg singularity category with a structure theorem by Keller and the second-named author, we deduce that under suitable hypotheses, the singularity category associated with $\Lambda$ is triangle equivalent to a generalized cluster category in the sense of Amiot.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.03836v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Norihiro Hanihara, Junyang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
