<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.SI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.SI</link>
    <description>nlin.SI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.SI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2024 19:15:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>PainleveBacklundCheck: A Sympy-powered Kivy app for the Painlev\'e property of nonlinear dispersive PDEs and auto-B\"acklund transformations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00052v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the present work we revisit the Painlev\'e property for partial differential equations. We consider the PDE variant of the relevant algorithm on the basis of the fundamental work of Weiss, Tabor and Carnevale and explore a number of relevant examples. Subsequently, we present an implementation of the relevant algorithm in an open-source platform in Python and discuss the details of a Sympy-powered Kivy app that enables checking of the property and the derivation of associated auto-B{\"a}ck{u}nd transform when the property is present. Examples of the relevant code and its implementation are also provided, as well as details of its open access for interested potential users.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00052v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shrohan Mohapatra, P. G. Kevrekidis, Stephane Lafortune</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On SK and KK Integrable Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00671v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To obtain new integrable nonlinear differential equations there are some well-known methods such as Lax equations with different Lax representations. There are also some other methods which are based on integrable scalar nonlinear partial differential equations. We show that some systems of integrable equations published recently are the ${\cal M}_{2}$-extension of integrable scalar equations. For illustration we give Korteweg-de Vries, Kaup-Kupershmidt, and Sawada-Kotera equations as examples. By the use of such an extension of integrable scalar equations we obtain some new integrable systems with recursion operators. We give also the soliton solutions of the system equations and integrable standard nonlocal and shifted nonlocal reductions of these systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00671v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Metin G\"urses, Asl{\i} Pekcan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Miura transformations and large-time behaviors of the Hirota-Satsuma equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01215</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01215v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The good Boussinesq equation has several modified versions such as the modified Boussinesq equation, Mikhailov-Lenells equation and Hirota-Satsuma equation. This work builds the full relations among these equations by Miura transformation and invertible linear transformations and draws a pyramid diagram to demonstrate such relations. The direct and inverse spectral analysis shows that the solution of Riemann-Hilbert problem for Hirota-Satsuma equation has simple pole at origin, the solution of Riemann-Hilbert problem for the good Boussinesq equation has double pole at origin, while the solution of Riemann-Hilbert problem for the modified Boussinesq equation and Mikhailov-Lenells equation doesn't have singularity at origin. Further, the large-time asymptotic behaviors of the Hirota-Satsuma equation with Schwartz class initial value is studied by Deift-Zhou nonlinear steepest descent analysis. In such initial condition, the asymptotic expressions of the Hirota-Satsuma equation and good Boussinesq equation away from the origin are proposed and it is displayed that the leading term of asymptotic formulas match well with direct numerical simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01215v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Deng-Shan Wang, Cheng Zhu, Xiaodong Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrable deformations of Rikitake systems, Lie bialgebras and bi-Hamiltonian structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01073</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01073v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Integrable deformations of a class of Rikitake dynamical systems are constructed by deforming their underlying Lie-Poisson Hamiltonian structures as linearizations of Poisson--Lie structures on certain (dual) Lie groups. By taking into account that there exists a one-to one correspondence between Poisson--Lie groups and Lie bialgebra structures, a number of deformed Poisson coalgebras can be obtained, which allow the construction of integrable deformations of coupled Rikitake systems. Moreover, the integrals of the motion for coupled systems can be explicitly obtained by means of the deformed coproduct map. The same procedure can be also applied when the initial system is bi-Hamiltonian with respect to two different Lie-Poisson algebras. In this case, to preserve a bi-Hamiltonian structure under deformation, a common Lie bialgebra structure for the two Lie-Poisson structures has to be found. Coupled dynamical systems arising from this bi-Hamiltonian deformation scheme are also presented, and the use of collective `cluster variables', turns out to be enlightening in order to analyse their dynamical behaviour. As a general feature, the approach here presented provides a novel connection between Lie bialgebras and integrable dynamical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01073v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Angel Ballesteros, Alfonso Blasco, Ivan Gutierrez-Sagredo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jacobi last multiplier and two-dimensional superintegrable oscillators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.08837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.08837v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we examine the role of the Jacobi last multiplier in the context of two-dimensional oscillators. We first consider two-dimensional unit-mass oscillators admitting a separable Hamiltonian description, i.e., $H = H_1 + H_2$, where $H_1$ and $H_2$ are the Hamiltonians of two one-dimensional unit-mass oscillators; it is shown that there exists a third functionally-independent first integral $\Theta$, thereby ensuring superintegrablility. Various examples are explicitly worked out. We then consider position-dependent-mass oscillators and the Bateman pair, where the latter consists of a pair of dissipative linear oscillators. Quite remarkably, the Bateman pair is found to be superintegrable, despite admitting a Hamiltonian which cannot be separated into those of two isolated (non-interacting) one-dimensional oscillators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.08837v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akash Sinha, Aritra Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reality conditions for the KdV equation and exact quasi-periodic solutions in finite phase spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.10859</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.10859v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the present paper reality conditions for quasi-periodic solutions of the KdV equation are determined completely. As a result, solutions in the form of non-linear waves can be plotted and investigated.
  The full scope of obtaining finite-gap solutions of the KdV equation is presented. It is proven that the multiply periodic $\wp_{1,1}$-function on the Jacobian variety of a hyperelliptic curve of arbitrary genus serves as the finite-gap solution, the genus coincides with the number of gaps. The subspace of the Jacobian variety where $\wp_{1,1}$, as well as other $\wp$-functions, are bounded and real-valued is found in any genus. This result covers every finite phase space of the KdV hierarchy, and can be extended to other completely integrable equations. A method of effective computation of this type of solutions is suggested, and illustrated in genera $2$ and $3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.10859v3</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julia Bernatska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large-space and long-time asymptotic behaviors of $N_{\infty}$-soliton solutions for the focusing Hirota equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.08924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.08924v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Hirota equation is one of the higher-order extensions of the nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation, and can describe the ultra-short optical pulse propagation in the form $ iq_t+\alpha(q_{xx}+ 2|q|^2q)+i\beta (q_{xxx}+ 6|q|^2q_x)=0,\, (x,t)\in\mathbb{R}^2\, (\alpha,\,\beta\in\mathbb{R})$. In this paper, we analytically explore the large-space and long-time asymptotic behaviors of a soliton gas (the limit $N\to \infty$ of $N$-soliton solutions) for the Hirota equation including the complex modified KdV equation by using the Riemann-Hilbert problems with discrete spectra restricted in intervals $(ia, ib)\cup (-ib, -ia)\, (0&lt;a&lt;b)$. We find that this soliton gas tends slowly to the Jaocbian elliptic wave solution with an error $\mathcal{O}(|x|^{-1})$ (zero exponentially quickly ) as $x\to -\infty$ ($x\to +\infty$). We also present the long-time asymptotics of the soliton gas under the different velocity conditions: $x/t&gt;4\beta b^2,\, \xi_c&lt;x/t&lt;4\beta b^2,\, x/t&lt;\xi_c$. Moreover, we analyze the property of the soliton gas for the case of the discrete spectra filling uniformly a quadrature domain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.08924v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weifang Weng, Zhenya Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multidimensional nonhomogeneous quasi-linear systems and their Hamiltonian structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.10445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.10445v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we investigate multidimensional first-order quasi-linear systems and find necessary conditions for them to admit Hamiltonian formulation. The insufficiency of the conditions is related to the Poisson cohomology of the admissible Hamiltonian operators. We present in detail the example of two-dimensional, two-components systems of hydrodynamic type and of a real reduction of the 3-waves system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.10445v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Hu, Matteo Casati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact calculation of degrees for lattice equations: a singularity approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.16206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.16206v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The theory of degree growth and algebraic entropy plays a crucial role in the field of discrete integrable systems. However, a general method for calculating degree growth for lattice equations (partial difference equations) is not yet known. Here we propose a new method to rigorously compute the exact degree of each iterate for lattice equations. Our strategy is to extend Halburd's method, which is a novel approach to computing the exact degree of each iterate for mappings (ordinary difference equations) from the singularity structure, to lattice equations. First, we illustrate, without rigorous discussion, how to calculate degrees for lattice equations using the lattice version of Halburd's method and discuss what problems we need to solve to make the method rigorous. We then provide a framework to ensure that all calculations are accurate and rigorous. We also discuss how to detect the singularity structure of a lattice equation. Our method is not only accurate and rigorous but also can easily be applied to a wide range of lattice equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.16206v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takafumi Mase</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of KdV solitons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.15819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.15819v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove an orbital stability theorem of KdV $n$-solitons with explicit phase shifts in the soliton region with cones around the $x$-axis and lines determined by bound states of the KdV $n$-solitons removed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.15819v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Derchyi Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
