<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.SI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.SI</link>
    <description>nlin.SI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.SI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 04:15:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On B type family of Dubrovin-Frobenius manifolds and their integrable systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.09054</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.09054v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: According to D.Zuo and an unpulished work of M.Bertola, there is a two--index series of Dubrovin--Frobenius manifold structures associated to a B type Coxeter group. We study the relations between these structures for the different values of these indices. We show that part of the data of such Dubrovin--Frobenius manifold indexed by $(k,l)$ can be recovered by the $(k+r,l+r)$ Dubrovin--Frobenius manifold. Continuing the program of arXiv:2007.11974 we associate an infinite system of commuting PDEs to these Dubrovin--Frobenius manifolds and show that these PDEs extend the dispersionless BKP hierarchy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.09054v3</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey Basalaev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping partition functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.03568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.03568v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce an infinite group action on partition functions of WK type, meaning of the type of the partition function $Z^{\rm WK}$ in the famous result of Witten and Kontsevich expressing the partition function of $\psi$-class integrals on the compactified moduli space $\overline{\mathcal{M}}_{g,n}$ as a $\tau$-function for the Korteweg--de Vries hierarchy. Specifically, the group which acts is the group $\mathcal{G}$ of formal power series of one variable $\varphi(V)=V+O(V^2)$, with group law given by composition, acting in a suitable way on the infinite tuple of variables of the partition functions. In particular, any $\varphi \in \mathcal{G}$ sends the Witten--Kontsevich (WK) partition function $Z^{\rm WK}$ to a new partition function $Z^\varphi$, which we call the WK mapping partition function associated to $\varphi$. We show that the genus zero part of $\log Z^\varphi$ is independent of $\varphi$ and give an explicit recursive description for its higher genus parts (loop equation), and as applications of this obtain relationships of the $\psi$-class integrals to Gaussian Unitary Ensemble and generalized Br\'ezin--Gross--Witten correlators. In a different direction, we use $Z^\varphi$ to construct a new integrable hierarchy, which we call the WK mapping hierarchy associated to $\varphi$. We show that this hierarchy is a bihamiltonian perturbation of the Riemann--Hopf hierarchy possessing a $\tau$-structure, and prove that it is a universal object for all such perturbations. Similarly, for any $\varphi\in\mathcal{G}$, we define the Hodge mapping partition function associated to $\varphi$, prove that it is integrable, and study its role in hamiltonian perturbations of the Riemann--Hopf hierarchy possessing a $\tau$-structure. Finally, we establish a generalized Hodge--WK correspondence relating different Hodge mapping partition functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.03568v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Di Yang, Don Zagier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Connection problem for special function solutions of Painlev\'e III equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04852v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we compute the small and large $x$ asymptotics of the special function solutions of Painlev\'e-III equation. We use the representation of solution in terms of Toeplitz determinants of Bessel functions, which is new. Toeplitz determinants are rewritten as multiple contour integrals using Andr\`eief identity. Finally small and large $x$ asymptotics is obtained using elementary asymptotic methods. The claimed result has not appeared in the literature before. Our formulas are useful for numerical computations of corresponding solutions of Painlev\'e-III equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04852v3</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Pan, Andrei Prokhorov</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
