<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.SI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.SI</link>
    <description>nlin.SI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.SI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 02:49:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On Isospectral flows related to (dual) cubic strings: Novikov, DP peakons and B, C-Toda lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04828</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04828v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Degasperis--Procesi (DP) equation can be viewed as an isospectral deformation of the boundary value problem for the so-called cubic string, while the Novikov equation can be formally regarded as linked to the dual cubic string. However, their relationships have not been thoroughly investigated. This paper examines various intrinsic connections between these two systems from different perspectives. We uncover a bijective relationship between the DP and Novikov pure peakon trajectories. In particular, this allows us to derive, not previously known, explicit expressions for the constants of motion in the Novikov peakon dynamical system. We also establish a one-to-one correspondence between the corresponding discrete cubic and dual cubic boundary value problems. Furthermore, we propose a new integrable lattice that features bilinear relations involving both determinants and Pfaffians, demonstrating that it can be connected to both the B-Toda and C-Toda lattices, which correspond to isospectral flows, involving positive powers of the spectral parameter, associated with (dual) cubic strings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04828v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiang-Ke Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonintegrability of the Fredkin spin chain and its truncated versions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04838v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Conservation laws serve as the hallmark of integrability. The absence of conserved charges typically implies that the model is nonintegrable. The recently proposed Fredkin spin chain exhibits rich structures, and its ground state is analytically known. However, whether the Fredkin spin chain is integrable remains an open question. In this work, through rigorous analytical calculations, we demonstrate that the Fredkin spin chain, under both periodic and open boundary conditions, lacks local conserved charges, thereby confirming its nonintegrable nature. Furthermore, we find that when one or a portion of the Hamiltonian terms are removed (referred to as the truncated Fredkin spin chain), local conserved charges are still absent. Our findings suggest that in models involving three-site interactions, integrable models are generally rare.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04838v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Ming Fan, Kun Hao, Yang-Yang Chen, Kun Zhang, Xiao-Hui Wang, Vladimir Korepin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soliton Surfaces and the Geometry of Integrable Deformations of the $\mathbb{CP}^{N-1}$ Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05081</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05081v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The $\mathbb{CP}^{N-1}$ model is an analytically tractable $2d$ quantum field theory which shares several properties with $4d$ Yang-Mills theory. By virtue of its classical integrability, this model also admits a family of integrable higher-spin auxiliary field deformations, including the $T \overline{T}$ deformation as a special case. We study the $\mathbb{CP}^{N-1}$ model and its deformations from a geometrical perspective, constructing their soliton surfaces and recasting physical properties of these theories as statements about surface geometry. We examine how the $T \overline{T}$ flow affects the unit constraint in the $\mathbb{CP}^{N-1}$ model and prove that any solution of this theory with vanishing energy-momentum tensor remains a solution under analytic stress tensor deformations -- an argument that extends to generic dimensions and instanton-like solutions in stress tensor flows including the non-analytic, $2d$, root-$T \overline{T}$ case and classes of higher-spin, Smirnov-Zamolodchikov-type, deformations. Finally, we give two geometric interpretations for general $T \overline{T}$-like deformations of symmetric space sigma models, showing that such flows can be viewed as coupling the undeformed theory to a unit-determinant field-dependent metric, or using a particular choice of moving frame on the soliton surface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05081v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Ferko, Michele Galli, Zejun Huang, Gabriele Tartaglino-Mazzucchelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 3d mixed BF Lagrangian 1-form: a variational formulation of Hitchin's integrable system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05127v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the concept of gauged Lagrangian $1$-forms, extending the notion of Lagrangian $1$-forms to the setting of gauge theories. This general formalism is applied to a natural geometric Lagrangian $1$-form on the cotangent bundle of the space of holomorphic structures on a smooth principal $G$-bundle $\mathcal{P}$ over a compact Riemann surface $C$ of arbitrary genus $g$, with or without marked points, in order to gauge the symmetry group of smooth bundle automorphisms of $\mathcal{P}$. The resulting construction yields a multiform version of the $3$d mixed BF action with so-called type A and B defects, providing a variational formulation of Hitchin's completely integrable system over $C$. By passing to holomorphic local trivialisations and going partially on-shell, we obtain a unifying action for a hierarchy of Lax equations describing the Hitchin system in terms of meromorphic Lax matrices. The cases of genus $0$ and $1$ with marked points are treated in greater detail, producing explicit Lagrangian $1$-forms for the rational Gaudin hierarchy and the elliptic Gaudin hierarchy, respectively, with the elliptic spin Calogero-Moser hierarchy arising as a special subcase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05127v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincent Caudrelier, Derek Harland, Anup Anand Singh, Benoit Vicedo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractal decompositions and tensor network representations of Bethe wavefunctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.00923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.00923v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the entanglement structure of a generic $M$-particle Bethe wavefunction (not necessarily an eigenstate of an integrable model) on a 1d lattice by dividing the lattice into $L$ parts and decomposing the wavefunction into a sum of products of $L$ local wavefunctions. Using the fact that a Bethe wavefunction accepts a \textit{fractal} multipartite decomposition -- it can always be written as a linear combination of $L^M$ products of $L$ local wavefunctions, where each local wavefunction is in turn also a Bethe wavefunction -- we then build \textit{exact, analytical} tensor network representations with finite bond dimension $\chi=2^M$, for a generic planar tree tensor network (TTN), which includes a matrix product states (MPS) and a regular binary TTN as prominent particular cases. For a regular binary tree, the network has depth $\log_{2}(N/M)$ and can be transformed into an adaptive quantum circuit of the same depth, composed of unitary gates acting on $2^M$-dimensional qudits and mid-circuit measurements, that deterministically prepares the Bethe wavefunction. Finally, we put forward a much larger class of \textit{generalized} Bethe wavefunctions, for which the above decompositions, tensor network and quantum circuit representations are also possible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.00923v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhayan Sahu, Guifre Vidal</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
