<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.CP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.CP</link>
    <description>q-fin.CP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.CP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 04:12:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Pricing Catastrophe Bonds -- A Probabilistic Machine Learning Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00697v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper proposes a probabilistic machine learning method to price catastrophe (CAT) bonds in the primary market. The proposed method combines machine-learning-based predictive models with Conformal Prediction, an innovative algorithm that generates distribution-free probabilistic forecasts for CAT bond prices. Using primary market CAT bond transaction records between January 1999 and March 2021, the proposed method is found to be more robust and yields more accurate predictions of the bond spreads than traditional regression-based methods. Furthermore, the proposed method generates more informative prediction intervals than linear regression and identifies important nonlinear relationships between various risk factors and bond spreads, suggesting that linear regressions could misestimate the bond spreads. Overall, this paper demonstrates the potential of machine learning methods in improving the pricing of CAT bonds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00697v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-fin.PR</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaowei Chen, Hong Li, Yufan Lu, Rui Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning tensor networks with parameter dependence for Fourier-based option pricing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00701v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A long-standing issue in mathematical finance is the speed-up of pricing options, especially multi-asset options. A recent study has proposed to use tensor train learning algorithms to speed up Fourier transform (FT)-based option pricing, utilizing the ability of tensor networks to compress high-dimensional tensors. Another usage of the tensor network is to compress functions, including their parameter dependence. In this study, we propose a pricing method, where, by a tensor learning algorithm, we build tensor trains that approximate functions appearing in FT-based option pricing with their parameter dependence and efficiently calculate the option price for the varying input parameters. As a benchmark test, we run the proposed method to price a multi-asset option for the various values of volatilities and present asset prices. We show that, in the tested cases involving up to about 10 assets, the proposed method is comparable to or outperforms Monte Carlo simulation with $10^5$ paths in terms of computational complexity, keeping the comparable accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00701v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rihito Sakurai, Haruto Takahashi, Koichi Miyamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DAM: A Universal Dual Attention Mechanism for Multimodal Timeseries Cryptocurrency Trend Forecasting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00522v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the distributed systems landscape, Blockchain has catalyzed the rise of cryptocurrencies, merging enhanced security and decentralization with significant investment opportunities. Despite their potential, current research on cryptocurrency trend forecasting often falls short by simplistically merging sentiment data without fully considering the nuanced interplay between financial market dynamics and external sentiment influences. This paper presents a novel Dual Attention Mechanism (DAM) for forecasting cryptocurrency trends using multimodal time-series data. Our approach, which integrates critical cryptocurrency metrics with sentiment data from news and social media analyzed through CryptoBERT, addresses the inherent volatility and prediction challenges in cryptocurrency markets. By combining elements of distributed systems, natural language processing, and financial forecasting, our method outperforms conventional models like LSTM and Transformer by up to 20\% in prediction accuracy. This advancement deepens the understanding of distributed systems and has practical implications in financial markets, benefiting stakeholders in cryptocurrency and blockchain technologies. Moreover, our enhanced forecasting approach can significantly support decentralized science (DeSci) by facilitating strategic planning and the efficient adoption of blockchain technologies, improving operational efficiency and financial risk management in the rapidly evolving digital asset domain, thus ensuring optimal resource allocation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00522v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yihang Fu, Mingyu Zhou, Luyao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mathematics of Differential Machine Learning in Derivative Pricing and Hedging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01233v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This article introduces the groundbreaking concept of the financial differential machine learning algorithm through a rigorous mathematical framework. Diverging from existing literature on financial machine learning, the work highlights the profound implications of theoretical assumptions within financial models on the construction of machine learning algorithms.
  This endeavour is particularly timely as the finance landscape witnesses a surge in interest towards data-driven models for the valuation and hedging of derivative products. Notably, the predictive capabilities of neural networks have garnered substantial attention in both academic research and practical financial applications.
  The approach offers a unified theoretical foundation that facilitates comprehensive comparisons, both at a theoretical level and in experimental outcomes. Importantly, this theoretical grounding lends substantial weight to the experimental results, affirming the differential machine learning method's optimality within the prevailing context.
  By anchoring the insights in rigorous mathematics, the article bridges the gap between abstract financial concepts and practical algorithmic implementations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01233v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro Duarte Gomes</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
