<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.CP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.CP</link>
    <description>q-fin.CP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.CP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 04:01:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling of Measurement Error in Financial Returns Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07405v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we consider the modeling of measurement error for fund returns data. In particular, given access to a time-series of discretely observed log-returns and the associated maximum over the observation period, we develop a stochastic model which models the true log-returns and maximum via a L\'evy process and the data as a measurement error there-of. The main technical difficulty of trying to infer this model, for instance Bayesian parameter estimation, is that the joint transition density of the return and maximum is seldom known, nor can it be simulated exactly. Based upon the novel stick breaking representation of [12] we provide an approximation of the model. We develop a Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) algorithm to sample from the Bayesian posterior of the approximated posterior and then extend this to a multilevel MCMC method which can reduce the computational cost to approximate posterior expectations, relative to ordinary MCMC. We implement our methodology on several applications including for real data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07405v1</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>q-fin.ST</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ajay Jasra, Mohamed Maama, Aleksandar Mijatovi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limit Order Book Dynamics and Order Size Modelling Using Compound Hawkes Process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.08927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.08927v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Hawkes Process has been used to model Limit Order Book (LOB) dynamics in several ways in the literature however the focus has been limited to capturing the inter-event times while the order size is usually assumed to be constant. We propose a novel methodology of using Compound Hawkes Process for the LOB where each event has an order size sampled from a calibrated distribution. The process is formulated in a novel way such that the spread of the process always remains positive. Further, we condition the model parameters on time of day to support empirical observations. We make use of an enhanced non-parametric method to calibrate the Hawkes kernels and allow for inhibitory cross-excitation kernels. We showcase the results and quality of fits for an equity stock's LOB in the NASDAQ exchange and compare them against several baselines. Finally, we conduct a market impact study of the simulator and show the empirical observation of a concave market impact function is indeed replicated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.08927v5</guid>
      <category>q-fin.TR</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konark Jain, Nick Firoozye, Jonathan Kochems, Philip Treleaven</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
