<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.CP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.CP</link>
    <description>q-fin.CP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.CP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 02:30:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Signal Extraction from Order Flow: A Matched Filter Perspective on Normalization and Market Microstructure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.18648</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.18648v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate that the choice of normalization for order flow intensity is fundamental to signal extraction in finance, not merely a technical detail. Through theoretical modeling, Monte Carlo simulation, and empirical validation using Korean market data, we prove that market capitalization normalization acts as a ``matched filter'' for informed trading signals, achieving 1.32--1.97$\times$ higher correlation with future returns compared to traditional trading value normalization. The key insight is that informed traders scale positions by firm value (market capitalization), while noise traders respond to daily liquidity (trading volume), creating heteroskedastic corruption when normalizing by trading volume. By reframing the normalization problem using signal processing theory, we show that dividing order flow by market capitalization preserves the information signal while traditional volume normalization multiplies the signal by inverse turnover -- a highly volatile quantity. Our theoretical predictions are robust across parameter specifications and validated by empirical evidence showing 482\% improvement in explanatory power. These findings have immediate implications for high-frequency trading algorithms, risk factor construction, and information-based trading strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.18648v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sungwoo Kang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Institutional Backing and Crypto Volatility: A Hybrid Framework for DeFi Stabilization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19251v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Decentralized finance (DeFi) lacks centralized oversight, often resulting in heightened volatility. In contrast, centralized finance (CeFi) offers a more stable environment with institutional safeguards. Institutional backing can play a stabilizing role in a hybrid structure (HyFi), enhancing transparency, governance, and market discipline. This study investigates whether HyFi-like cryptocurrencies, those backed by institutions, exhibit lower price risk than fully decentralized counterparts. Using daily data for 18 major cryptocurrencies from January 2020 to November 2024, we estimate panel EGLS models with fixed, random, and dynamic specifications. Results show that HyFi-like assets consistently experience lower price risk, with this effect intensifying during periods of elevated market volatility. The negative interaction between HyFi status and market-wide volatility confirms their stabilizing role. Conversely, greater decentralization is strongly associated with increased volatility, particularly during periods of market stress. Robustness checks using quantile regressions and pre-/post-Terra Luna subsamples reinforce these findings, with stronger effects observed in high-volatility quantiles and post-crisis conditions. These results highlight the importance of institutional architecture in enhancing the resilience of digital asset markets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19251v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <category>q-fin.TR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10614-025-11179-6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Computational Economics, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ihlas Sovbetov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Needles in a haystack: using forensic network science to uncover insider trading</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.18918</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.18918v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Although the automation and digitisation of anti-financial crime investigation has made significant progress in recent years, detecting insider trading remains a unique challenge, partly due to the limited availability of labelled data. To address this challenge, we propose using a data-driven networks approach that flags groups of corporate insiders who report coordinated transactions that are indicative of insider trading. Specifically, we leverage data on 2.9 million trades reported to the U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) by company insiders (C-suite executives, board members and major shareholders) between 2014 and 2024. Our proposed algorithm constructs weighted edges between insiders based on the temporal similarity of their trades over the 10-year timeframe. Within this network we then uncover trends that indicate insider trading by focusing on central nodes and anomalous subgraphs. To highlight the validity of our approach we evaluate our findings with reference to two null models, generated by running our algorithm on synthetic empirically calibrated and shuffled datasets. The results indicate that our approach can be used to detect pairs or clusters of insiders whose behaviour suggests insider trading and/or market manipulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.18918v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gian Jaeger, Wang Ngai Yeung, Renaud Lambiotte</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heston vol-of-vol and the VVIX</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19611</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19611v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Heston stochastic volatility model is arguably, the most popular stochastic volatility model used to price and risk manage exotic derivatives. In spite of this, it is not necessarily easy to calibrate to the market and obtain stable exotic option prices with this model. This paper focuses on the vol-of-vol parameter and its relation with the volatility of volatility index (VVIX) level. Four different approaches to estimate the VVIX in the Heston model are presented: two based on the known transition density of the variance, one analytical approximation, and one based on the Heston PDE which computes the value directly out of the underlying SPX500. Finally we explore their use to improve calibration stability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19611v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jherek Healy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Counterexamples for FX Options Interpolations -- Part I</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19621v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This article provides a list of counterexamples, where some of the popular fx option interpolations break down. Interpolation of FX option prices (or equivalently volatilities), is key to risk-manage not only vanilla FX option books, but also more exotic derivatives which are typically valued with local volatility or local stochastic volatilility models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19621v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jherek Healy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visualization of The Content of Surah al Fiil using Marker-Based Augmented Reality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17895v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study presents the development of a marker-based augmented reality (AR) application designed to visualize the content of Surah al-Fil as an interactive and context-rich medium for Islamic education. Using a research and development approach, the system was developed through structured stages including data collection, user requirement analysis, interface design, 3D asset creation using Blender, and integration of Unity 3D with the Vuforia SDK. The application features key visual elements such as the elephant army, the Kaaba, and the Ababil birds, which were modeled in detail and linked to high-contrast image markers to ensure accurate and stable AR tracking. Functional testing demonstrated strong technical performance, achieving a 95 percent marker detection accuracy at an optimal distance of 30-40 cm with consistent real-time rendering across multiple Android devices. User evaluations involving students and Islamic education teachers indicated high acceptance, with an overall satisfaction score of 4.7 out of 5 in terms of usability, visual appeal, interactivity, and learning effectiveness. These findings indicate that AR-based learning media can enhance learner engagement, deepen understanding of Quranic narratives, and provide immersive insights into historical and spiritual contexts. Overall, this study demonstrates that marker-based AR technology has significant potential to support innovation in digital Islamic education by enriching traditional learning with interactive and visually intuitive experiences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17895v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wisnu Uriawan, Ahmad Badru Al Husaeni, Dzakwanfaiq Nauval, Farid Muhtar Fathir, Mahesa Adlan Falah, Muhammad Miftahur Rizki Awalin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous-time reinforcement learning for optimal switching over multiple regimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04697v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper studies the continuous-time reinforcement learning (RL) for optimal switching problems across multiple regimes. We consider a type of exploratory formulation under entropy regularization where the agent randomizes both the timing of switches and the selection of regimes through the generator matrix of an associated continuous-time finite-state Markov chain. We establish the well-posedness of the associated system of Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman (HJB) equations and provide a characterization of the optimal policy. The policy improvement and the convergence of the policy iterations are rigorously established by analyzing the system of equations. We also show the convergence of the value function in the exploratory formulation towards the value function in the classical formulation as the temperature parameter vanishes. Finally, a reinforcement learning algorithm is devised and implemented by invoking the policy evaluation based on the martingale characterization. Our numerical examples with the aid of neural networks illustrate the effectiveness of the proposed RL algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04697v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yijie Huang, Mengge Li, Xiang Yu, Zhou Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
