<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.CP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.CP</link>
    <description>q-fin.CP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.CP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 04:14:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Layer Deep xVA: Structural Credit Models, Measure Changes and Convergence Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14766</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.14766v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a structural default model for portfolio-wide valuation adjustments (xVAs) and represent it as a system of coupled backward stochastic differential equations. The framework is divided into four layers, each capturing a key component: (i) clean values, (ii) initial margin and Collateral Valuation Adjustment (ColVA), (iii) Credit/Debit Valuation Adjustments (CVA/DVA) together with Margin Valuation Adjustment (MVA), and (iv) Funding Valuation Adjustment (FVA). Because these layers depend on one another through collateral and default effects, a naive Monte Carlo approach would require deeply nested simulations, making the problem computationally intractable.
  To address this challenge, we use an iterative deep BSDE approach, handling each layer sequentially so that earlier outputs serve as inputs to the subsequent layers. Initial margin is computed via deep quantile regression to reflect margin requirements over the Margin Period of Risk. We also adopt a change-of-measure method that highlights rare but significant defaults of the bank or counterparty, ensuring that these events are accurately captured in the training process.
  We further extend Han and Long's (2020) a posteriori error analysis to BSDEs on bounded domains. Due to the random exit from the domain, we obtain an order of convergence of $\mathcal{O}(h^{1/4-\epsilon})$ rather than the usual $\mathcal{O}(h^{1/2})$.
  Numerical experiments illustrate that this method drastically reduces computational demands and successfully scales to high-dimensional, non-symmetric portfolios. The results confirm its effectiveness and accuracy, offering a practical alternative to nested Monte Carlo simulations in multi-counterparty xVA analyses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.14766v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kristoffer Andersson, Alessandro Gnoatto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Filtered not Mixed: Stochastic Filtering-Based Online Gating for Mixture of Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02969v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose MoE-F - a formalized mechanism for combining $N$ pre-trained Large Language Models (LLMs) for online time-series prediction by adaptively forecasting the best weighting of LLM predictions at every time step. Our mechanism leverages the conditional information in each expert's running performance to forecast the best combination of LLMs for predicting the time series in its next step. Diverging from static (learned) Mixture of Experts (MoE) methods, our approach employs time-adaptive stochastic filtering techniques to combine experts. By framing the expert selection problem as a finite state-space, continuous-time Hidden Markov model (HMM), we can leverage the Wohman-Shiryaev filter. Our approach first constructs N parallel filters corresponding to each of the $N$ individual LLMs. Each filter proposes its best combination of LLMs, given the information that they have access to. Subsequently, the N filter outputs are optimally aggregated to maximize their robust predictive power, and this update is computed efficiently via a closed-form expression, generating our ensemble predictor. Our contributions are: **(I)** the MoE-F plug-and-play filtering harness algorithm, **(II)** theoretical optimality guarantees of the proposed filtering-based gating algorithm (via optimality guarantees for its parallel Bayesian filtering and its robust aggregation steps), and **(III)** empirical evaluation and ablative results using state-of-the-art foundational and MoE LLMs on a real-world __Financial Market Movement__ task where MoE-F attains a remarkable 17\% absolute and 48.5\% relative F1 measure improvement over the next best performing individual LLM expert predicting short-horizon market movement based on streaming news. Further, we provide empirical evidence of substantial performance gains in applying MoE-F over specialized models in the long-horizon time-series forecasting domain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02969v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raeid Saqur, Anastasis Kratsios, Florian Krach, Yannick Limmer, Jacob-Junqi Tian, John Willes, Blanka Horvath, Frank Rudzicz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Liquidity Jump, Liquidity Diffusion, and Crypto Wash Trading</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05803v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We hypothesize that at least a portion of the short-term price jumps in the crypto market are manifestations of liquidity fluctuation caused by wash trading practices. We develop a model to decompose asset liquidity into two components: liquidity jump and liquidity diffusion, which proxy the size and probability of wash trading, respectively. Using the US stock trading data as benchmark, we establish that the combination of high liquidity diffusion and high liquidity jump indicates wash trading, while large-volume trades with high liquidity jump but low liquidity diffusion are actually legitimate trades. The liquidity measures provide a useful tool to all market participants, including researchers, regulators, market makers and investors to understand the interplay between liquidity fluctuation (jump) and liquidity volatility (diffusion), and make appropriate decisions in crypto trading.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05803v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>q-fin.ST</category>
      <category>q-fin.TR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qi Deng, Zhong-Guo Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
