<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.CP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.CP</link>
    <description>q-fin.CP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.CP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 05:03:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying Cryptocurrency Unpredictability: A Comprehensive Study of Complexity and Forecasting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09079v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper offers a thorough examination of the univariate predictability in cryptocurrency time-series. By exploiting a combination of complexity measure and model predictions we explore the cryptocurrencies time-series forecasting task focusing on the exchange rate in USD of Litecoin, Binance Coin, Bitcoin, Ethereum, and XRP. On one hand, to assess the complexity and the randomness of these time-series, a comparative analysis has been performed using Brownian and colored noises as a benchmark. The results obtained from the Complexity-Entropy causality plane and power density spectrum analysis reveal that cryptocurrency time-series exhibit characteristics closely resembling those of Brownian noise when analyzed in a univariate context. On the other hand, the application of a wide range of statistical, machine and deep learning models for time-series forecasting demonstrates the low predictability of cryptocurrencies. Notably, our analysis reveals that simpler models such as Naive models consistently outperform the more complex machine and deep learning ones in terms of forecasting accuracy across different forecast horizons and time windows. The combined study of complexity and forecasting accuracies highlights the difficulty of predicting the cryptocurrency market. These findings provide valuable insights into the inherent characteristics of the cryptocurrency data and highlight the need to reassess the challenges associated with predicting cryptocurrency's price movements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09079v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.ST</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3703412.3703420</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>4th International Conference on AI-ML Systems (AIMLSystems 2024), October 08-11, 2024, Baton Rouge, LA, USA. ACM, New York, NY, USA, 8 pages</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Puoti, Fabrizio Pittorino, Manuel Roveri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LOB-Bench: Benchmarking Generative AI for Finance - an Application to Limit Order Book Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09172v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: While financial data presents one of the most challenging and interesting sequence modelling tasks due to high noise, heavy tails, and strategic interactions, progress in this area has been hindered by the lack of consensus on quantitative evaluation paradigms. To address this, we present LOB-Bench, a benchmark, implemented in python, designed to evaluate the quality and realism of generative message-by-order data for limit order books (LOB) in the LOBSTER format. Our framework measures distributional differences in conditional and unconditional statistics between generated and real LOB data, supporting flexible multivariate statistical evaluation. The benchmark also includes features commonly used LOB statistics such as spread, order book volumes, order imbalance, and message inter-arrival times, along with scores from a trained discriminator network. Lastly, LOB-Bench contains "market impact metrics", i.e. the cross-correlations and price response functions for specific events in the data. We benchmark generative autoregressive state-space models, a (C)GAN, as well as a parametric LOB model and find that the autoregressive GenAI approach beats traditional model classes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09172v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>q-fin.TR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peer Nagy, Sascha Frey, Kang Li, Bidipta Sarkar, Svitlana Vyetrenko, Stefan Zohren, Ani Calinescu, Jakob Foerster</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
