<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.CP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.CP</link>
    <description>q-fin.CP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.CP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 02:36:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Unsupervised Learning-based Calibration Scheme for Rough Volatility Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02135v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Existing deep learning-based calibration scheme for rough volatility models predominantly rely on supervised learning frameworks, which incur significant computational costs due to the necessity of generating massive synthetic training datasets. In this work, we propose a novel unsupervised learning-based calibration scheme for rough volatility models that eliminates the data generation bottleneck. Our approach leverages the backward stochastic differential equation (BSDE) representation of the pricing function derived by Bayer et al. \cite{bayer2022pricing}. By treating model parameters as trainable variables, we simultaneously approximate the BSDE solution and optimize the parameters within a unified neural network training process, with the terminal misfit as the loss. We theoretically establish that the mean squared error between the model-implied prices and market data is bounded by the loss function. Furthermore, we prove that the loss can be minimized to an arbitary degree, depending on the model's market fitting capacity and the universal approximation capability of neural networks. Numerical experiments for both simulated and historical S\&amp;P 500 data based on rough Bergomi (rBergomi) model demonstrate the efficiency and accuracy of the proposed scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02135v3</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Changqing Teng, Guanglian Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causal Regime Detection in Energy Markets With Augmented Time Series Structural Causal Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.04361v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Energy markets exhibit complex causal relationships between weather patterns, generation technologies, and price formation, with regime changes occurring continuously rather than at discrete break points. Current approaches model electricity prices without explicit causal interpretation or counterfactual reasoning capabilities. We introduce Augmented Time Series Causal Models (ATSCM) for energy markets, extending counterfactual reasoning frameworks to multivariate temporal data with learned causal structure. Our approach models energy systems through interpretable factors (weather, generation mix, demand patterns), rich grid dynamics, and observable market variables. We integrate neural causal discovery to learn time-varying causal graphs without requiring ground truth DAGs. Applied to real-world electricity price data, ATSCM enables novel counterfactual queries such as "What would prices be under different renewable generation scenarios?".</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.04361v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.OT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dennis Thumm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Causal Market Simulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04469</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.04469v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Market generators using deep generative models have shown promise for synthetic financial data generation, but existing approaches lack causal reasoning capabilities essential for counterfactual analysis and risk assessment. We propose a Time-series Neural Causal Model VAE (TNCM-VAE) that combines variational autoencoders with structural causal models to generate counterfactual financial time series while preserving both temporal dependencies and causal relationships. Our approach enforces causal constraints through directed acyclic graphs in the decoder architecture and employs the causal Wasserstein distance for training. We validate our method on synthetic autoregressive models inspired by the Ornstein-Uhlenbeck process, demonstrating superior performance in counterfactual probability estimation with L1 distances as low as 0.03-0.10 compared to ground truth. The model enables financial stress testing, scenario analysis, and enhanced backtesting by generating plausible counterfactual market trajectories that respect underlying causal mechanisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.04469v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>stat.OT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dennis Thumm, Luis Ontaneda Mijares</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
