<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AT</link>
    <description>math.AT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 04:00:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Equivariant Poincar\'e-Hopf theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15103</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15103v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we employ the framework of localization algebras to compute the equivariant K-homology class of the Euler characteristic operator, a central object in studying equivariant index theory on manifolds. This approach provides a powerful algebraic language for analyzing differential operators on equivariant structures and allows for the application of Witten deformation techniques in a K-homological context. Utilizing these results, we establish an equivariant version of the Poincar\'e-Hopf theorem, extending classical topological insights to the equivariant case, inspired by the results of L\"uck-Rosenberg. This work thus offers a new perspective on the localization techniques in the equivariant K-homology, highlighting their utility in deriving explicit formulas for index-theoretic invariants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15103v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongzhi Liu, Hang Wang, Zijing Wang, Shaocong Xiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cohomotopy Sets of $(n-1)$-connected $(2n+2)$-manifolds for small $n$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16055</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16055v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $M$ be a closed orientable $(n-1)$-connected $(2n+2)$-manifold, $n\geq 2$. In this paper we combine the Postnikov tower of spheres and the homotopy decomposition of the reduced suspension space $\Sigma M$ to investigate the cohomotopy sets $\pi^\ast(M)$ for $n=2,3,4$, under the assumption that $M$ has $2$-torsion-free homology. All cohomotopy sets $\pi^i(M)$ of such manifolds $M$ are characterized except $\pi^4(M)$ for $n=3,4$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16055v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pengcheng Li, Jianzhong Pan, Jie Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological obstruction to the training of shallow ReLU neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14837v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Studying the interplay between the geometry of the loss landscape and the optimization trajectories of simple neural networks is a fundamental step for understanding their behavior in more complex settings. This paper reveals the presence of topological obstruction in the loss landscape of shallow ReLU neural networks trained using gradient flow. We discuss how the homogeneous nature of the ReLU activation function constrains the training trajectories to lie on a product of quadric hypersurfaces whose shape depends on the particular initialization of the network's parameters. When the neural network's output is a single scalar, we prove that these quadrics can have multiple connected components, limiting the set of reachable parameters during training. We analytically compute the number of these components and discuss the possibility of mapping one to the other through neuron rescaling and permutation. In this simple setting, we find that the non-connectedness results in a topological obstruction, which, depending on the initialization, can make the global optimum unreachable. We validate this result with numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14837v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Nurisso, Pierrick Leroy, Francesco Vaccarino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete transforms of quantized persistence diagrams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.17093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.17093v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Topological data analysis leverages topological features to analyze datasets, with applications in diverse fields like medical sciences and biology. A key tool of this theory is the persistence diagram, which encodes topological information but poses challenges for integration into standard machine learning pipelines. We introduce Qupid (QUantized Persistence and Integral transforms of Diagrams), a novel and simple method for vectorizing persistence diagrams. First, Qupid uses a binning procedure to turn persistence diagrams into finite measures on a grid and then applies discrete transforms to these measures. Key features are the choice of log-scaled grids that emphasize information contained near the diagonal in persistence diagrams, combined with the use of discrete transforms to enhance and efficiently encode the obtained topological information. We conduct an in-depth experimental analysis of Qupid, showing that the simplicity of our method results in very low computational costs while preserving highly competitive performances compared to state-of-the-art methods across numerous classification tasks on both synthetic and real-world datasets. Finally, we provide experimental evidence that our method is robust to a decrease in the grid resolution used.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.17093v3</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Etienne Van Huffel, Olympio Hacquard, Vadim Lebovici, Matteo Palo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Galois Correspondence for n-Stacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00281</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00281v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove a Galois correspondence for $n$-stacks. It gives a correspondence between the $\infty$-category of Deligne-Mumford $n$-stacks finite \'etale over a connected scheme $X$ and the $\infty$-category of $n$-stacks of finite sets with an action of the fundamental group of $X$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00281v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxiang Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orthogonal M\"obius Inversion and Grassmannian Persistence Diagrams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.06870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.06870v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce Orthogonal M\"obius Inversion $\mathsf{OI}$, a concept analogous to M\"obius inversion on finite posets, which is applicable to order-preservings functions from a finite poset to the Grassmannian $\mathsf{Gr}(V)$ of an inner product space $V$. This notion critically relies on the inner product structure on $V$ enabling it to capture much finer information than standard integer-valued persistence diagrams.
  Orthogonal Inversion is a special case of the broader concept of Orthomodular Inversion, where the target space is any orthomodular lattice, which we also identify.
  We apply Orthogonal Inversion in order to construct a "non-negative" persistence diagram for any given multiparameter filtration $\mathsf{F}$ of a finite simplicial complex $K$, indexed over an arbitrary finite poset $P$. This is done by applying it to the birth-death spaces of $\mathsf{F}$. Analogously to $1$-parameter classical persistence diagrams, these multiparameter Grassmannian persistence diagrams offer straightforward interpretability. Specifically, to a segment $(b, d) \in \mathsf{Seg}(P)$, (1) the Grassmannian persistence diagram canonically assigns a vector subspace of $C_{\rho}^K$ consisting of cycles that are born at $b$ and become boundaries at $d$ and (2) this assignment is exhaustive at the homology level.
  In the case of 1-parameter filtrations, we also study a variant of Orthogonal Inversion that is applicable to persistent Laplacian kernels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.06870v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aziz Burak G\"ulen, Facundo M\'emoli, Zhengchao Wan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
