<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AT</link>
    <description>math.AT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 04:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On Colimits and Model Structures in Various Categories of Manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15511</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15511v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: After explaining the importance of model categories in abstract homotopy theory, we provide concrete examples demonstrating that various categories of manifolds do not have all finite colimits, and hence cannot be model categories. We then consider various enlargements of our categories of manifolds, culminating in categories of presheaves. We explain how to produce model structures on these enlarged categories, culminating with answering an open problem involving Poincar\'{e} spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15511v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David White</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Density Sensitive Bifiltered Dowker Complexes via Total Weight</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15592v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce a density-sensitive bifiltration on Dowker complexes. Previously, Dowker complexes were studied to address directional or bivariate data whereas density-sensitive bifiltrations on \v{C}ech and Vietoris--Rips complexes were suggested to make them more robust. We combine these two lines of research, noting that the superlevels of the total weight function of a Dowker complex can be identified as an instance of Sheehy's multicover filtration. An application of the multicover nerve theorem then provides a form of Dowker duality that is compatible with this filtration. As a consequence, we find that the subdivision intrinsic \v{C}ech complex admits a smaller model. Moreover, regarding the total weight function as a counting measure, we generalize it to arbitrary measures and prove a density-sensitive stability theorem for the case of probability measures. Additionally, we provide an algorithm to calculate the appearances of simplices in our bifiltration and present computational examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15592v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niklas Hellmer, Jan Spali\'nski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The handlebody group is a virtual duality group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15515v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that the mapping class group of a handlebody is a virtual duality group, in the sense of Bieri and Eckmann. In positive genus we give a description of the dualising module of any torsion-free, finite-index subgroup of the handlebody mapping class group as the homology of the complex of non-simple disc systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15515v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dan Petersen, Richard D. Wade</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Borel and genuine $C_2$-equivariant Adams spectral sequences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.12883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.12883v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We find out some relations between the classical Adams spectral sequences for stunted real projective spectra, the Borel $C_2$-equivariant Adams spectral sequence for the 2-completed sphere, and the genuine $C_2$-equivariant Adams spectral sequence for the 2-completed sphere. This allows us to understand the genuine $C_2$-equivariant Adams spectral sequence from the Borel Adams spectral sequences. We show that the Borel Adams spectral sequence is computable as a classical Adams spectral sequence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.12883v3</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sihao Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A proof of the generalized geometric boundary theorem using filtered spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.14650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.14650v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the Appendix A of [Beh12], Behrens proved a generalization of the classical geometric boundary theorem [Rav86, Thm. 2.3.4]. In this article, I will give another proof of the generalized geometric boundary theorem using the filtered spectra, and correct an error in [Beh12, Lem. A.4.1].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.14650v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sihao Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Picard group of the stable module category for infinite groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.08260v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce the stable module $\infty$-category for groups of type $\Phi$ as an enhancement of the stable category defined by N. Mazza and P. Symonds. For groups of type $\Phi$ which act on a tree, we show that the stable module $\infty$-category decomposes in terms of the associated graph of groups. For groups which admit a finite-dimensional cocompact model for the classifying space for proper actions, we exhibit a decomposition in terms of the stable module $\infty$-categories of their finite subgroups. We use these decompositions to provide methods to compute the Picard group of the stable module category. In particular, we provide a description of the Picard group for countable locally finite $p$-groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.08260v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan Omar G\'omez</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
