<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AT</link>
    <description>math.AT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 01:30:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Hypercubical manifolds in homotopy type theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19402v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Homotopy type theory is a logical setting in which one can perform geometric constructions and proofs in a synthetic way. Namely, types can be interpreted as spaces up to homotopy, and proofs as homotopy invariant constructions. In this context, we introduce a type which corresponds to the hypercubical manifold, a space first introduced by Poincar\'e in 1895. Its importance stems from the fact that it provides an approximation of the group Q of quaternionic units, in the sense of being the first step of a cellular resolution of Q. In order to ensure the validity of our definition, we show that it satisfies the expected property: it is the homotopy quotient of the 3-sphere by the expected action of Q. This is non-trivial and requires performing subtle combinatorial computations based on the flattening lemma, thus illustrating the effective nature of homotopy type theory. Finally, based on the previous construction, we introduce new higher-dimensional generalizations of this manifold, which correspond to better cellular approximations of Q, converging toward a delooping of Q.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19402v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Mimram, \'Emile Oleon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study of higher-order interactions in unweighted, undirected networks using persistent homology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19448v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Persistent homology has been studied to better understand the structural properties and topology features of weighted networks. It can reveal hidden layers of information about the higher-order structures formed by non-pairwise interactions in a network. Studying of higher-order interactions (HoIs) of a system provides a more comprehensive understanding of the complex system; moreover, it is a more precise depiction of the system as many complex systems, such as ecological systems and biological systems, etc., demonstrate HoIs. In this study, the weighted simplicial adjacency matrix has been constructed using the concept of adjacency strength of simplices in a clique complex obtained from an unweighted, undirected network. This weighted simplicial adjacency matrix is thus used to calculate the global measure, which is called generalised weighted betweenness centrality, which further helps us in calculating the persistent homology on the given simplicial complex by constructing a filtration on it. Moreover, a local measure called maximal generalised degree centrality has also been established for better understanding of the network topology of the studied simplicial complex. All the generalizations given in this work can be reduced to the graph-theoretic case. i.e., for a simplicial complex of dimension 1. Three different filtration schemes for constructing the sequence of simplicial complexes have been given with the help of both global and local measures, and by using these measures, the topology of higher-order structures of the studied network due to the interactions of their vertices has been compared. Further, the illustration of established definitions has been given using a real-life network by calculating Betti numbers up to dimension two.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19448v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Udit Raj, Slobodan Maleti\'c, Sudeepto Bhattacharya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elliptic arrangements of complex multiplication type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19638v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We provide a natural definition of an elliptic arrangement, extending the classical framework to an elliptic curve E with complex multiplication. We analyse the intersections of elements of the arrangement and their connected components as End(E)-modules. Furthermore, we prove that the combinatorial data of elliptic arrangements define both an arithmetic matroid and a matroid over the ring End(E). In this way, we obtain a class of arithmetic matroids that is different from the class of arithmetic matroids realizable via toric arrangements. Finally, we show that the Euler characteristic of the complement is an evaluation of the arithmetic Tutte polynomial.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19638v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Moci, Roberto Pagaria, Maddalena Pismataro, Alejandro Vargas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Representation Stability for Marked Graph Complexes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.05461v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove a sharp representation stability result for graph complexes with a distinguished vertex, and prove that the chains realizing this sharp bound pass to non-trivial families of graph homology classes. This result may be interpreted as a higher genus generalization of Hersh and Reiner's stability bound for configuration spaces of points in odd dimensional Euclidean space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.05461v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enoch Fedah, Benjamin C. Ward</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twisted Graded Categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11240</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.11240v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a presentably symmetric monoidal $\infty$-category $\mathcal{C}$ and an $\mathbb{E}_{\infty}$-monoid $M$, we introduce and classify twisted graded categories, which generalize the Day convolution structure on $\mathrm{Fun}(M, \mathcal{C})$. These are characterized by a braiding encoded in symmetric group actions on tensor powers, whose character we show depends only on the $\mathbb{T}$-equivariant monoidal dimension. We analyze the $\mathbb{T}$-action on the dimension of invertible objects and identify it with the $\mathbb{T}$-transfer map. Finally, we compute braiding characters in examples arising from higher cyclotomic extensions, such as the $(\mathbb{S}, n+1)$-oriented extension of $\mathrm{Mod}_{En}^{\wedge}$ at all primes and heights, and of the cyclotomic closure of $\mathrm{Vect}^n$ at low heights.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.11240v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shai Keidar, Shaul Ragimov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The stable cohomology of the moduli space of curves with level structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.06183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.06183v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that in a stable range, the rational cohomology of the moduli space of curves with level structures is the same as that of the ordinary moduli space of curves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.06183v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Putman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monoidal Envelopes of Families of $\infty$-Operads and $\infty$-Operadic Kan Extensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.10813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.10813v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We provide details of the proof of Lurie's theorem on operadic Kan extensions. Along the way, we generalize the construction of monoidal envelopes of $\infty$-operads to families of $\infty$-operads and use it to construct the fiberwise direct sum functor, both of which we characterize by certain universal properties. Aside from their uses in the proof of Lurie's theorem, these results and constructions have their independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.10813v2</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kensuke Arakawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dimension and partial groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19854</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19854v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A partial group with $n+1$ elements is, when regarded as a symmetric simplicial set, of dimension at most $n$. This dimension is $n$ if and only if the partial group is a group. As a consequence of the first statement, finite partial groups are genuinely finite, despite being seemingly specified by infinitely much data. In particular, finite partial groups have only finitely many im-partial subgroups. We also consider dimension of partial groupoids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19854v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philip Hackney, R\'emi Molinier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Minimal Non Hausdorff Counterexample in Covering Space Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00031v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Classical covering space theory shows that for a connected, locally path connected, semilocally simply connected, and Hausdorff space, there is a perfect correspondence between covering maps and subgroups of its fundamental group. Three key features make the theory work: unique path and homotopy lifting, discrete fibres supporting a properly discontinuous group of deck transformations, and a well defined monodromy action. In this paper, we exhibit a minimal example where the total space fails to be Hausdorff, and we show that this single failure destroys all three pillars at once. Our example uses the line with k origins together with a simple map into a punctured disk whose fibre over the puncture consists of k indistinguishable points. In this setting path lifting and monodromy both fail, and yet the total space has trivial fundamental group even though none of the usual generalizations of covering spaces can accommodate it. This example illustrates in the simplest possible way why Hausdorff separation is essential to classical covering space theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00031v3</guid>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhiram Sripat</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
