<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AT</link>
    <description>math.AT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 02:35:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The Convex Matching Distance in Multiparameter Persistence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02944v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the convex matching distance, a novel metric for comparing functions with values in the real plane. This metric measures the maximal bottleneck distance between the persistence diagrams associated with the convex combinations of the two function components. Similarly to the traditional matching distance, the convex matching distance aggregates the information provided by two real-valued components. However, whereas the matching distance depends on two parameters, the convex matching distance depends on only one, offering improved computational efficiency. We further show that the convex matching distance can be more discriminative than the traditional matching distance in certain cases, although the two metrics are generally not comparable. Moreover, we prove that the convex matching distance is stable and characterize the coefficients of the convex combination at which it is attained. Finally, we demonstrate that this new aggregation framework benefits from the computational advantages provided by the Pareto grid, a collection of curves in the plane whose points lie in the image of the Pareto critical set associated with functions assuming values on the real plane.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02944v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrizio Frosini, Ulderico Fugacci, Eloy Mosig Garc\'ia, Nicola Quercioli, Sara Scaramuccia, Francesca Tombari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holomorphic linking numbers, ABC Massey products, and Calabi-Yau 3-folds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02187</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02187v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: On compact K\"ahler manifolds, we relate ABC Massey products arising from complex analytic cycles to holomorphic linking numbers. This enables us to construct a family of simply connected projective 3-folds with trivial canonical bundle, equipped with a non-vanishing ABC Massey product.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02187v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luc\'ia Mart\'in-Merch\'an, Jonas Stelzig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fundamental groups and descriptive set theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02355v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the homotopy of loops in a fixed path-connected Polish space from a descriptive set-theoretic viewpoint. We show that many analytic equivalence relations arise this way, and many do not. We also study the "free group" over an equivalence relation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02355v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fanxin Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On hyperbolic links associated to Eulerian cycles on ideal right-angled hyperbolic $3$-polytopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03017</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.03017v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider Eulerian cycles without transversal selfintersections in $4$-valent planar graphs. We prove that any cycle of this type in the graph of an ideal right-angled hyperbolic $3$-polytope corresponds to a hyperbolic link such that its complement consists of $4$-copies of this polytope glued according to its checkerboard coloring. Moreover, this link consists of trivially embedded circles bijectively corresponding to the vertices of the polytope. For such cycles we prove that the $3$-antiprism $A(3)$ (octahedron) has exactly $2$ combinatorially different cycles, the $4$-antiprism $A(4)$ has exactly $7$ combinatorially different cycles, and these cycles correspond to $7$ cycles (perhaps combinatorially equivalent) on any polytope different from antiprisms, and any antiprism $A(k)$ has at least $2$ combinatorially different cycles. The $2$-fold branched covering space corresponding to our link is a small cover over some simple $3$-polytope. This small cover is defined by a Hamiltonian cycle on it. We show that any compact hyperbolic $3$-polytope with a Hamiltonian cycle arises in this way.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.03017v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikolai Erokhovets</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A remark on Continuous K-theory and Fourier-Sato transform</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02329v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this note, we prove a generalization of Efimov's computation for the universal localizing invariant of categories of sheaves with certain microsupport constraints. The proof is based on certain categorical equivalences given by the Fourier-Sato transform, which is different from the original proof. As an application, we compute the universal localizing invariant of the category of almost quasi-coherent sheaves on the Novikov toric scheme introduced by Vaintrob.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02329v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bingyu Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matrix Invariants as Homotopy Invariants in Finite $T_0$-spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16861</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16861v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish a bijection between the set of finite topological $T_0$-spaces (or partially ordered sets) and equivalence classes of square matrices. The absolute value of the determinant or the rank of these matrices serve as simple homotopy invariants for the corresponding topological spaces, and consequently, for finite simplicial complexes. To conclude, we explore further relationships and problems concerning finite posets within the context of these matrices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16861v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro J. Chocano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A stable $\infty$-category for equivariant $KK$-theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2102.13372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2102.13372v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For a countable group $G$ we construct a small, idempotent complete, symmetric monoidal, stable $\infty$-category $\mathrm{KK}^{G}_{\mathrm{sep}}$ whose homotopy category recovers the triangulated equivariant Kasparov category of separable $G$-$C^*$-algebras, and exhibit its universal property. Likewise, we consider an associated presentably symmetric monoidal, stable $\infty$-category $\mathrm{KK}^{G}$ which receives a symmetric monoidal functor $\mathrm{kk}^{G}$ from possibly non-separable $G$-$C^*$-algebras and discuss its universal property. In addition to the symmetric monoidal structures, we construct various change-of-group functors relating these KK-categories for varying $G$. We use this to define and establish key properties of a (spectrum valued) equivariant, locally finite $K$-homology theory on proper and locally compact $G$-topological spaces, allowing for coefficients in arbitrary $G$-$C^*$-algebras. Finally, we extend the functor $\mathrm{kk}^{G}$ from $G$-$C^*$-algebras to $G$-$C^*$-categories. These constructions are key in a companion paper about a form of equivariant Paschke duality and assembly maps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2102.13372v5</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ulrich Bunke, Alexander Engel, Markus Land</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simplicial presheaves of Green complexes and twisting cochains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.09627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.09627v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct three simplicial presheaves on the site of ringed spaces, and in particular on that of complex manifolds. The descent objects for these simplicial presheaves yield Toledo--Tong's twisting cochains, simplicial twisting cochains, and complexes that appear in Green's thesis on Chern classes for coherent analytic sheaves, respectively. We thus extend the aforementioned constructions to the equivariant setting, and more generally to stacks. This is the first step in achieving push-forwards in K-theory and Riemann--Roch theorems for appropriate stacks, as was achieved by Toledo and Tong for arbitrary complex manifolds, and further pursued by O'Brian and Green.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.09627v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timothy Hosgood, Mahmoud Zeinalian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Higher Topological T-duality Functors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.12039</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.12039v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We use String Field Theory (SFT) to construct a higher analogue of Bunke-Schick's functor $P: \mathbf{Top}^{op} \to \mathbf{Set}$ \cite{BunkeS1} by geometrizing $P.$ We use the projection of SFT onto its massless modes \cite{SFTDiffeo} to construct the category $\C$ whose objects are pairs (which we identify with SFT backgrounds) and whose maps are morphisms of pairs (which are gauge transformations). Using $\C$ and categorical equivalence, for any $CW-$complex $X$ we define the moduli space $G(X)$ of SFT backgrounds which are pairs over $X$ up to gauge equivalence. We use the homotopy theory of the moduli space $G(X)$ to define functors on the category of $CW-$complexes $P_k:\mathbf{CW}^{op} \to \mathbf{Grpd}$ such that $P_0 \simeq P,$ $P_1$ is nontrivial and $P_k(X)$ are always trivial for $k \geq 2.$ Arrows in $P_1(X)$ are shown to be isotopy classes of maps in the mapping class group of $X$ acting on (isomorphism classes of) pairs over $X.$ We discuss applications to Topological T-duality for triples and to modelling doubled geometries and T-folds \cite{HullT}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.12039v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashwin S. Pande</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
