<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AT</link>
    <description>math.AT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 05:03:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On the rational $C_2$-homotopy type of ${BSU_{\mathbb{R}}}_m$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07982</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07982v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by a problem in motivic homotopy theory considered by Asok-Fasel-Hopkins, we give a description of the rational $C_2$-equivariant homotopy type of the classifying space ${BSU_{\mathbb{R}}}_m$ in terms of equivariant Eilenberg-Maclane spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07982v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eunice Sukarto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On essential simplicial maps $S^3 \rightarrow S^2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08584v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A fiber-uniform bound on the complexity of an essential simplicial map $S^3\rightarrow S^2$ is proven, and the tightness of the bound is investigated. It follows that the triangulation of the Hopf map constructed by Madahar and Sarkaria is minimal in its homotopy class in terms of the number of 3-simplices in the triangulation of $S^3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08584v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail V. Bludov, Sergei Vad. Fomin, Oleg R. Musin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast free resolutions of bifiltered chain complexes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08652</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08652v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a $k$-critical bifiltration, every simplex enters along a staircase with at most $k$ steps. Examples with $k&gt;1$ include degree-Rips bifiltrations and models of the multicover bifiltration. We consider the problem of converting a $k$-critical bifiltration into a $1$-critical (i.e. free) chain complex with equivalent homology. This is known as computing a free resolution of the underlying chain complex and is a first step toward post-processing such bifiltrations.
  We present two algorithms. The first one computes free resolutions corresponding to path graphs and assembles them to a chain complex by computing additional maps. The simple combinatorial structure of path graphs leads to good performance in practice, as demonstrated by extensive experiments. However, its worst-case bound is quadratic in the input size because long paths might yield dense boundary matrices in the output. Our second algorithm replaces the simplex-wise path graphs with ones that maintain short paths which leads to almost linear runtime and output size.
  We demonstrate that pre-computing a free resolution speeds up the task of computing a minimal presentation of the homology of a $k$-critical bifiltration in a fixed dimension. Furthermore, our findings show that a chain complex that is minimal in terms of generators can be asymptotically larger than the non-minimal output complex of our second algorithm in terms of description size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08652v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ulrich Bauer, Tamal K. Dey, Michael Kerber, Florian Russold, Matthias S\"ols</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Persistent Homology for Labeled Datasets: Gromov-Hausdorff Stability and Generalized Landscapes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08794</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08794v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Techniques from metric geometry have become fundamental tools in modern mathematical data science, providing principled methods for comparing datasets modeled as finite metric spaces. Two of the central tools in this area are the Gromov-Hausdorff distance and persistent homology, both of which yield isometry-invariant notions of distance between datasets. However, these frameworks do not account for categorical labels, which are intrinsic to many real-world datasets, such as labeled images, pre-clustered data, and semantically segmented shapes. In this paper, we introduce a general framework for labeled metric spaces and develop new notions of Gromov-Hausdorff distance and persistent homology which are adapted to this setting. Our main result shows that our persistent homology construction is stable with respect to our novel notion of Gromov-Hausdorff distance, extending a classic result in topological data analysis. To facilitate computation, we also introduce a labeled version of persistence landscapes and show that the landscape map is Lipschitz.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08794v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yaoying Fu, Evgeniya Lagoda, Shiying Li, Tom Needham, Lander Ver Hoef, Morgan Weiler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reeb Graph of Sample Thickenings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08159v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the Reeb graph of a thickening of points sampled from an unknown space. Our main contribution is a framework to transfer reconstruction results similar to the well-known work of Niyogi, Smale, and Weinberger to the setting of Reeb graphs. To this end, we first generalize and study the interleaving distances for Reeb graphs. We find that many of the results previously established for constructible spaces also hold for general topological spaces. We use this to show that under certain conditions for topological spaces with real-valued Lipschitz maps, the Reeb graph of a sample thickening approximates the Reeb graph of the underlying space. Finally, we provide an algorithm for computing the Reeb graph of a sample thickening.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08159v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H{\aa}vard Bakke Bjerkevik, Nello Blaser, Lars M. Salbu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Paschke duality and assembly maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2107.02843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2107.02843v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct a natural transformation between two versions of $G$-equivariant $K$-homology with coefficients in a $G$-$C^{*}$-category for a countable discrete group $G$. Its domain is a coarse geometric $K$-homology and its target is the usual analytic $K$-homology. Following classical terminology, we call this transformation the Paschke transformation. We show that under certain finiteness assumptions on a $G$-space $X$, the Paschke transformation is an equivalence on $X$. As an application, we provide a direct comparison of the homotopy theoretic Davis-L\"uck assembly map with Kasparov's analytic assembly map appearing in the Baum-Connes conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2107.02843v4</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ulrich Bunke, Alexander Engel, Markus Land</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The plus construction with respect to subrings of the rationals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11839v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct explicit models of universal $H \mathbb{Z}[J^{-1}]$-acyclic spaces $\mathcal M$, for any subset $J$ of the prime numbers. The corresponding nullification functors provide thus plus construction functors for ordinary homology with $\mathbb{Z}[J^{-1}]$ coefficients. Motivated by classical results about Quillen's plus construction for integral homology, we prove that the $H \mathbb{Z}[J^{-1}]$-acyclization functor and the $\mathcal M$-cellularization functor coincide. We show that the acyclization-plus construction fiber sequence is always a cofiber sequence for simply connected spaces, but almost never so when the plus construction is not simply connected, unlike in the classical case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11839v4</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guille Carri\'on Santiago, Ram\'on Flores, J\'er\^ome Scherer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twisted Graded Categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11240</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.11240v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a presentably symmetric monoidal $\infty$-category $\mathcal{C}$ and an $\mathbb{E}_{\infty}$-monoid $M$, we introduce and classify twisted graded categories, which generalize the Day convolution structure on $\mathrm{Fun}(M, \mathcal{C})$. These are characterized by a braiding encoded in symmetric group actions on tensor powers, whose character we show depends only on the $\mathbb{T}$-equivariant monoidal dimension. We analyze the $\mathbb{T}$-action on the dimension of invertible objects and identify it with the $\mathbb{T}$-transfer map. Finally, we compute braiding characters in examples arising from higher cyclotomic extensions, such as the $(\mathbb{S}, n+1)$-oriented extension of $\mathrm{Mod}_{En}^{\wedge}$ at all primes and heights, and of the cyclotomic closure of $\mathrm{Vect}^n$ at low heights.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.11240v3</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shai Keidar, Shaul Ragimov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approaches to critical point theory via sequential and parametrized topological complexity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01980v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Lusternik-Schnirelmann category of a space was introduced to obtain a lower bound on the number of critical points of a $C^1$-function on a given manifold. Related to Lusternik-Schnirelmann category and motivated by topological robotics, the topological complexity (TC) of a space is a numerical homotopy invariant whose topological properties are an active field of research. The notions of sequential and parametrized topological complexity extend the ideas of topological complexity. While the definition of TC is closely related to Lusternik-Schnirelmann category, the connections of sequential and parametrized TC to critical point theory have not been fully explored yet. In this article we apply methods from Lusternik-Schnirelmann theory to establish various lower bounds on numbers of critical points of functions in terms of sequential and parametrized TCs. We carry out several consequences and applications of these bounds, among them a computation of the parametrized TC of the unit tangent bundles of $(4m-1)$-spheres.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01980v3</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephan Mescher, Maximilian Stegemeyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nilpotence of $\eta$ in \'etale motivic spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09476v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that every object of the stable \'etale motivic homotopy category over any scheme is $\eta$-complete. In some cases we show that in fact the fourth power of $\eta$ is null, whereas the third power of $\eta$ is always nonvanishing, similar to the situation in topology. Moreover, we prove an \'etale version of May's nilpotence conjecture, that states that $H\mathbb{Z} \in \mathrm{Sp}$ detects the vanishing of $\mathbf{E}_\infty$-rings. We use this to show a version of Nishida's nilpotence theorem in $\mathrm{SH}_{\operatorname{\acute{e}t}}(S)$, i.e. that any positive degree self map of the unit is nilpotent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09476v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Klaus Mattis, Swann Tubach</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oriented Grassmannian Bundle, Normal Curvature Reduction, and Persistent Homology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22603v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a smooth closed orientable submanifold $M \subset \mathbb{R}^D$ with narrow cycles. We embed $M$ into a scaled oriented Grassmannian bundle via the Gauss map in order to enlarge the scale of these cycles. Under mild assumptions, we show that this embedding reduces the normal curvature of the embedded submanifold in directions where the original normal curvature is large. For smooth closed hypersurfaces, we further show that this construction increases the distance between antipodal points of narrow cycles for fixed volume.
  We then obtain an explicit range of radii for which the ambient \v{C}ech complex on this Grassmannian bundle is homotopy equivalent to the embedded manifold, yielding lower bounds on the scales at which the \v{C}ech filtration recovers the homology of $M$. Since the distance induced by the embedding depends on both positions and oriented tangent spaces, we work with Whitney $C^1$ convergence of embeddings and prove that the associated \v{C}ech persistent homology is stable with respect to the interleaving distance. Finally, we describe a procedure for computing a distance matrix for a finite subset with respect to this embedding and illustrate the construction on several examples, including an approximate quasi-halo orbit in the Saturn--Enceladus system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22603v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongwoo Gang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
