<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AT</link>
    <description>math.AT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 03:02:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Rational sequential parametrized topological complexity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01123</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01123v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Sequential parametrized topological complexity is a numerical homotopy invariant of a fibration, which arose in the robot motion planning problem with external constraints. In this paper, we study sequential parametrized topological complexity in view of rational homotopy theory. We generalize results on topological complexity, and in particular, give an explicit algebraic upper bound for sequential parametrized topological complexity when a fibration admits a certain decomposition, which is a generalization of the result of Hamoun, Rami and Vandembroucq on topological complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01123v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuki Minowa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of Bipath Persistence Diagrams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01614v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, bipath persistent homology has been proposed as an extension of standard persistent homology, along with its visualization (bipath persistence diagram) and computational methods. In the setting of standard persistent homology, the stability theorem with respect to real-valued functions on a topological space is one of the fundamental results, which gives a mathematical justification for using persistent homology to noisy data. In proving the stability theorem, the algebraic stability theorem/the isometry theorem for persistence modules plays a central role. In this point of view, the stability property for bipath persistent homology is desired for analyzing data. In this paper, we prove the stability theorem of bipath persistent homology with respect to bipath functions on a topological space. This theorem suggests a stability of bipath persistence diagrams: small changes in a bipath function (except at their ends) result in only small changes in the bipath persistence diagram. Similar to the stability theorem of standard persistent homology, we deduce the stability theorem of bipath persistent homology by using the algebraic stability theorem/the isometry theorem of bipath persistence modules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01614v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunsuke Tada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On uniqueness of the equivariant smooth structure on a real moment-angle manifold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00446v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The paper is devoted to the well-known problem of smooth structures on moment-angle manifolds. Each real or complex moment-angle manifold has an equivariant smooth structure given by an intersection of quadrics corresponding to a geometric realisation of a polytope. In 2006 F.Bosio and L.Meersseman proved that complex moment-angle manifolds of combinatorially equivalent simple polytopes are equivariantly diffeomorphic. Using arguments from calculus we derive from this result that real moment-angle manifolds of combinatorially equivalent simple polytopes are equivariantly diffeomorphic and the polytopes are diffeomorphic as manifolds with corners.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00446v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikolai Erokhovets, Elena Erokhovets</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiplicative structures on comodules in higher categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01002v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we study multiplicative structures on comodules over bialgebras in the setting of $\infty$-categories. We show that the $\infty$-category of comodules over an $(\mathcal{O},\mathbf{Ass})$-bialgebra in a mixed $(\mathcal{O},\mathbf{Ass})$-duoidal $\infty$-category has the structure of an $\mathcal{O}$-monoidal $\infty$-category for any $\infty$-operad $\mathcal{O}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01002v1</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takeshi Torii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Completions and DK-equivalences of ${\Theta_n}$-spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01687</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01687v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We establish Rezk completion functors for $\Theta_n$ spaces with respect to each and all of the completeness conditions. As a consequence, we obtain a characterization of Dwyer-Kan equivalences between Segal $\Theta_n$ spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01687v2</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miika Tuominen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Point Cloud Clustering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.16716</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.16716v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present Topological Point Cloud Clustering (TPCC), a new method to cluster points in an arbitrary point cloud based on their contribution to global topological features. TPCC synthesizes desirable features from spectral clustering and topological data analysis and is based on considering the spectral properties of a simplicial complex associated to the considered point cloud. As it is based on considering sparse eigenvector computations, TPCC is similarly easy to interpret and implement as spectral clustering. However, by focusing not just on a single matrix associated to a graph created from the point cloud data, but on a whole set of Hodge-Laplacians associated to an appropriately constructed simplicial complex, we can leverage a far richer set of topological features to characterize the data points within the point cloud and benefit from the relative robustness of topological techniques against noise. We test the performance of TPCC on both synthetic and real-world data and compare it with classical spectral clustering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.16716v3</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ICML 2023 - 40th International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Vincent P. Grande, Michael T. Schaub</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Galois Symmetry of $Gal(\overline{\mathbb{Q}}/\mathbb{Q})$ on Topological Manifold Structures of Varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.05229</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.05229v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a definition of the profinite normal structure set for the set of all manifolds in a fixed profinite homotopy type. Using this framework, we prove that the Galois action of $Gal(\overline{\mathbb{Q}}/\mathbb{Q})$ on the underlying topological manifold structures of smooth, complete, simply-connected complex varieties defined over $\overline{\mathbb{Q}}$ of dimension at least $3$ factors through the abelianization of $Gal(\overline{\mathbb{Q}}/\mathbb{Q})$. Moreover, this abelian action extends canonically to the entire profinite normal structure set. This result provides an answer to the question by Sullivan in the case of topological manifold structures of simply-connected varieties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.05229v3</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Runjie Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cubical Approximation for Directed Topology II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.16619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.16619v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The paper establishes an equivalence between directed homotopy categories of (diagrams of) cubical sets and (diagrams of) directed topological spaces. This equivalence both lifts and extends an equivalence between classical homotopy categories of cubical sets and topological spaces. Some simple applications include combinatorial descriptions and subsequent calculations of directed homotopy monoids and directed singular $1$-cohomology monoids. Another application is a characterization of isomorphisms between small categories up to zig-zags of natural transformations as directed homotopy equivalences between directed classifying spaces. Cubical sets throughout the paper are taken to mean presheaves over the minimal symmetric monoidal variant of the cube category. Along the way, the paper characterizes morphisms in this variant as the interval-preserving lattice homomorphisms between finite Boolean lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.16619v3</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanjeevi Krishnan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An algebraic model for the constant loops map</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18726v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For any simplicial complex $X$ with a total ordering of its vertices, one can construct a chain complex $\mathbb{L}_\bullet(X)$ generated by necklaces of simplices in $X$, which computes the homology of the free loop space of the geometric realization of $X$. Motivated by string topology, we describe two explicit chain maps $C_\bullet(X) \to \mathbb{L}_\bullet(X)$, where $C_\bullet(X)$ denotes the simplicial chains in $X$, lifting the homology map induced by embedding points in $|X|$ into constant loops in the free loop space of $|X|$. One of the maps has a convenient combinatorial description, while the other is described in terms of higher structure on $C_\bullet(X)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18726v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luis Fernandez, Manuel Rivera, Thomas Tradler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification of fully dualizable linear categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.16337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.16337v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that if $R$ is a G-ring then every fully dualizable $R$-linear cocomplete category is equivalent to a twist by a $\mathbb{G}_m$-gerbe of the category of modules over a finite \'etale $R$-algebra. We also show that this holds more generally over an arbitrary commutative ring under an additional compact generation hypothesis. We include variants of these results that apply to $R$-linear graded categories, and to the context of $\infty$-categories linear over connective commutative ring spectra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.16337v2</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Germ\'an Stefanich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Corank spectral sequence for locally symmetric varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.07693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.07693v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct a new type of spectral sequences for the mixed Hodge structures on the cohomology of locally symmetric varieties. These spectral sequences converge to the edge components in the Hodge triangles, and the E1-terms are expressed by group cohomology associated to the cusps. They already degenerate at E1 in a certain range, which gives a simple expression of some Hodge components. An identity of holomorphic Euler numbers is obtained as a consequence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.07693v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shouhei Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lifting Galois representations via Kummer flags</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08888v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\Gamma$ be either i) the absolute Galois group of a local field $F$, or ii) the topological fundamental group of a closed connected orientable surface of genus $g$. In case i), assume that $\mu_{p^2} \subset F$. We give an elementary and unified proof that every representation $\rho_1: \Gamma \to \mathbf{GL}_d(\mathbb{F}_p)$ lifts to a representation $\rho_2: \Gamma \to \mathbf{GL}_d(\mathbb{Z}/p^2)$. [In case i), it is understood these are continuous.] The actual statement is much stronger: for all $r \geq 1$, under "suitable" assumptions, triangular representations $\rho_r: \Gamma \to \mathbf{B}_d(\mathbb{Z}/p^r)$ lift to $\rho_{r+1}: \Gamma \to \mathbf{B}_d(\mathbb{Z}/p^{r+1})$, in the strongest possible step-by-step sense. Here "suitable" is made precise by the concept of $\textit{Kummer flag}$. An essential aspect of this work, is to identify the common properties of groups i) and ii), that suffice to ensure the existence of such lifts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08888v3</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Conti, Cyril Demarche, Mathieu Florence</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MANTRA: The Manifold Triangulations Assemblage</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02392v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The rising interest in leveraging higher-order interactions present in complex systems has led to a surge in more expressive models exploiting higher-order structures in the data, especially in topological deep learning (TDL), which designs neural networks on higher-order domains such as simplicial complexes. However, progress in this field is hindered by the scarcity of datasets for benchmarking these architectures. To address this gap, we introduce MANTRA, the first large-scale, diverse, and intrinsically higher-order dataset for benchmarking higher-order models, comprising over 43,000 and 250,000 triangulations of surfaces and three-dimensional manifolds, respectively. With MANTRA, we assess several graph- and simplicial complex-based models on three topological classification tasks. We demonstrate that while simplicial complex-based neural networks generally outperform their graph-based counterparts in capturing simple topological invariants, they also struggle, suggesting a rethink of TDL. Thus, MANTRA serves as a benchmark for assessing and advancing topological methods, leading the way for more effective higher-order models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02392v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rub\'en Ballester, Ernst R\"oell, Daniel B\=in Schmid, Mathieu Alain, Sergio Escalera, Carles Casacuberta, Bastian Rieck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Cohen--Lenstra moments over function fields via the stable homology of non-splitting Hurwitz spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22210v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We compute the average number of surjections from class groups of quadratic function fields over $\mathbb F_q(t)$ onto finite odd order groups $H$, once $q$ is sufficiently large. These yield the first known moments of these class groups, as predicted by the Cohen--Lenstra heuristics, apart from the case $H = \mathbb Z/3\mathbb Z$. The key input to this result is a topological one, where we compute the stable rational homology groups of Hurwitz spaces associated to non-splitting conjugacy classes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22210v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aaron Landesman, Ishan Levy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Equilibria in Generic Extensive form Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18449</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18449v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove the 2-player, generic extensive-form case of the conjecture of Govindan and Wilson (1997a,b) and Hauk and Hurkens (2002) stating that an equilibrium component is essential in every equivalent game if and only if the index of the component is nonzero. This provides an index-theoretic characterization of the concept of hyperstable components of equilibria in generic extensive-form games, first formulated by Kohlberg and Mertens (1986). We also illustrate how to compute hyperstable equilibria in multiple economically relevant examples and show how the predictions of hyperstability compare with other solution concepts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18449v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Pahl, Carlos Pimienta</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
