<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AT</link>
    <description>math.AT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Small Value of cohomological dimension of group homomorphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14615v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give the characterisation of cohomological dimension of group homomorphisms. In particular, we show the analogue of the Stallings-Swan theorem in the case of group epimorphisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14615v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nursultan Kuanyshov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$c$-structures and trace methods beyond connective rings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14774v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the notion of a $c$-category, which is a kind of category whose behaviour is controlled by connective ring spectra. More precisely, any $c$-category admits a finite step resolution by categories of compact modules over connective ring spectra. We introduce nilpotent extensions of $c$-categories, and show that they induce isomorphisms on truncating invariants, such as the fiber of the cyclotomic trace map. We show that for many stacks, the category of perfect complexes is naturally a $c$-category and deduce a generalization of the Dundas--Goodwillie--McCarthy theorem to such stacks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14774v1</guid>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ishan Levy, Vladimir Sosnilo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Intrinsic $L_{\infty}$-Algebra on the Khovanov-Sano Complex</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15018</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.15018v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper reinterprets the symmetries of equivariant Khovanov homology, discovered by Khovanov and Sano, within the Batalin-Vilkovisky (BV) formalism. We identify the Shumakovitch operator $\hat{\nu}$ as a BV Laplacian whose nilpotency, a consequence of the algebra's defining relations, induces an $L_{\infty}$-algebra on homology. We prove this structure is non-trivial through explicit computations of higher brackets. Furthermore, we construct a dual $L_{\infty}$-structure, suggesting a unifying homotopy $\mathfrak{sl}_2$ symmetry. The main result of this paper is to lift this structure from homology to the chain level. Applying the Homotopy Transfer Theorem, we construct an intrinsic $L_{\infty}$-algebra on the Khovanov-Sano complex, whose $\infty$-quasi-isomorphism class is a canonical link invariant. This provides a new algebraic framework in which we conjecture the origin of Steenrod operations in knot homology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.15018v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takahito Kuriya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computing 1-Periodic Persistent Homology with Finite Windows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.00709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.00709v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $K$ be a periodic cell complex endowed with a covering $q:K\to G$ where $G$ is a finite quotient space of equivalence classes under translations acting on $K$. We assume $G$ is embedded in a space whose homotopy type is a $d$-torus for some $d$, which introduces "toroidal cycles" in $G$ which do not lift to cycles in $K$ by $q$ . We study the behaviour of toroidal and non-toroidal cycles for the case $K$ is 1-periodic, i.e. $G=K/\mathbb{Z}$ for some free action of $\mathbb{Z}$ on $K$. We show that toroidal cycles can be entirely classified by endomorphisms on the homology of unit cells of $K$, and moreover that toroidal cycles have a sense of unimodality when studying the persistent homology of $G$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.00709v3</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam Onus, Primoz Skraba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the hit problem for the polynomial algebra and the algebraic transfer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02494v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates Singer's conjecture by examining the cohit module $\mathbb F_2\otimes_{\mathcal A}P^{\otimes h}$ for specific degrees and values of $h$. Utilizing hit problem techniques, we extend previous work by Mothebe et al. and establish key dimensional results. Notably, for $h\geq 6$, we prove that the cohit module's dimension in certain degrees matches the order of a specific factor group. Our contributions include demonstrating that certain non-zero elements do not belong to the image of the Singer algebraic transfer. All results were verified using the OSCAR computer algebra system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02494v4</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dang Vo Phuc</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A necessary condition for liftings of positive characteristic varieties with finite fundamental groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.07914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.07914v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce a necessary condition for the existence of characteristic zero liftings of certain smooth, proper varieties in positive characteristic, using etale homotopy theory and Wall's finiteness obstruction. For a variety with finite etale fundamental group pi, we define a notion of mod-l finite dominatedness based on the F_l-chain complex of the universal cover of its l-profinite etale homotopy type. We prove that such a variety X can be lifted to characteristic zero only if the above chain complex of X is quasi-isomorphic to a bounded complex of finitely generated projective F_l[pi]-modules. To prove this result, we extend Wall's discussions of finiteness obstructions to l-profinite complete spaces with finite fundamental group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.07914v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruida Di, Runjie Hu, Siqing Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nielsen numbers of $n$-valued maps on infra-solvmanifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13438v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We derive a formula for the Nielsen number $N(f)$ for every $n$-valued self-map $f$ of an infra-solvmanifold. To do this, we express $N(f)$ in terms of Nielsen coincidence numbers of single-valued maps on solvmanifolds, and derive a formula for Nielsen coincidence numbers in that setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13438v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karel Dekimpe, Lore De Weerdt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the computation of $\mathrm{Ext}_{\mathcal A}^{k,k+*}(\mathbb{Z}/2,\mathbb{Z}/2)$ for $k \leq 5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15611</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15611v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This Note presents a computational algorithm for determining a basis of the cohomology of the mod 2 Steenrod algebra, $\mathrm{Ext}_{\mathcal A}^{k, k+*}(\mathbb{Z}/2, \mathbb{Z}/2)$ for $k \leq 5$, based on the well-known generators and the Adams relations given in Chen's work [2]. The purpose of this algorithm is to verify the hand-computed results for $\mathrm{Ext}_{\mathcal A}^{4, 4+*}(\mathbb{Z}/2, \mathbb{Z}/2)$ presented in our corrected papers [8, 9, 10]. Combining our most recent works [11, 12], the verification of the domain and the codomain of the fourth algebraic transfer in specific degrees can now be completed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15611v3</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dang Vo Phuc</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normalized Derivations for Milnor's Primitive Operations on the Dickson Algebra and Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08861</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08861v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Our work investigates the action of primitive Milnor operations $St^{\Delta_i}$ on the Dickson algebra $D_n$ over $\mathbb{F}_p$, building upon a foundational formula by Nguyen Sum [3]. Our central contribution is the introduction of a normalized operator, $\delta_i$, by factoring out the ubiquitous invariant $Q_{n, 0}$. This normalization transforms $St^{\Delta_i}$ into a true derivation on the localized Dickson algebra, thereby establishing an elegant differential framework. This framework yields two new significant results: first, a closed-form formula for all higher iterates of the operator, revealing a strong factorial-based vanishing criterion for iterates of order $\geq p$. Second, the discovery of a normalized coordinate system where the action has constant coefficients. This latter insight reduces the problem of computing the associated Margolis homology to a standard Koszul complex computation, in direct analogy with a recent result by Ngo Anh Tuan [4]. As further consequences, we also construct a large family of kernel elements and describe the global structure of the action.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08861v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dang Vo Phuc</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Character Map in Twisted Equivariant Nonabelian Cohomology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2011.06533</link>
      <description>arXiv:2011.06533v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The fundamental notion of non-abelian generalized cohomology gained recognition in algebraic topology as the non-abelian Poincar\'e-dual to "factorization homology", and in theoretical physics as providing flux-quantization for non-linear Gauss laws. However, already the archetypical example -- unstable Cohomotopy, first studied almost a century ago by Pontrjagin -- has remained underappreciated as a cohomology theory and has only recently received attention as a flux-quantizaton law ("Hypothesis H").
  Here we lay out a general construction of the analogue of the Chern character map on twisted equivariant non-abelian cohomology theories (with equivariantly simply-connected classifying spaces) and illustrate the construction by spelling out a twisted equivariant form of Cohomotopy as an archetypical and intriguing running example, essentially by computing its equivariant Sullivan model.
  We close with an outlook on the application of this result to the rigorous deduction of anyonic quantum states on M5-branes wrapped over Seifert 3-orbifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2011.06533v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.4310/BPAM.250908174706</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Beijing Journal of Pure and Applied Mathematics, Vol. 2 No. 2 (2025) 515-617</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hisham Sati, Urs Schreiber</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
