<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.QA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.QA</link>
    <description>math.QA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.QA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 04:00:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Hidden structures behind ambient symmetries of the Maurer-Cartan equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06589v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For every differential graded Lie algebra $\mathfrak{g}$ one can define two different group actions on the Maurer-Cartan elements: the ubiquitous gauge action and the action of $\mathrm{Lie}_\infty$-isotopies of $\mathfrak{g}$, which we call the ambient action. In this note, we explain how the assertion of gauge triviality of a homologically trivial ambient action relates to the calculus of dendriform, Zinbiel, and Rota-Baxter algebras, and to Eulerian idempotents. In particular, we exhibit new relationships between these algebraic structures and the operad of rational functions defined by Loday.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06589v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Dotsenko, Sergey Shadrin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twisted unipotent groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07005v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the algebraic structure and representation theory of the Hopf algebras ${}_J\mathcal{O}(G)_J$ when $G$ is an affine algebraic unipotent group over $\mathbb{C}$ with $\mathrm{dim}(G) = n$ and $J$ is a Hopf $2$-cocycle for $G$. The cotriangular Hopf algebras ${}_J\mathcal{O}(G)_J$ have the same coalgebra structure as $\mathcal{O}(G)$ but a deformed multiplication. We show that they are involutive $n$-step iterated Hopf Ore extensions of derivation type. The 2-cocycle $J$ has as support a closed subgroup $T$ of $G$, and ${}_J\mathcal{O}(G)_J$ is a crossed product $S \#_{\sigma}U(\mathfrak{t})$, where $\mathfrak{t}$ is the Lie algebra of $T$ and $S$ is a deformed coideal subalgebra. The simple ${}_J\mathcal{O}(G)_J$-modules are stratified by a family of factor algebras ${}_J\mathcal{O}(Z_g)_J$, parametrised by the double cosets $TgT$ of $T$ in $G$. The finite dimensional simple ${}_J\mathcal{O}(G)_J$-modules are all 1-dimensional, so form a group $\Gamma$, which we prove to be an explicitly determined closed subgroup of $G$. A selection of examples illustrate our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07005v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ken A. Brown, Shlomo Gelaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gaudin models and moduli space of flower curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06424v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce and study the family of trigonometric Gaudin subalgebras in $U g^{\otimes n}$ for arbitrary simple Lie algebra $g$. This is the family of commutative subalgebras of maximal possible transcendence degree that serve as a universal source for higher integrals of the trigonometric Gaudin quantum spin chain attached to $g$. We study the parameter space that indexes all possible degenerations of subalgebras from this family. In particular, we show that (rational) inhomogeneous Gaudin subalgebras of $ U g^{\otimes n}$ previously studied in \cite{ffry} arise as certain limits of trigonometric Gaudin subalgebras. Moreover, we show that both families of commutative subalgebras glue together into the one parameterized by the space $\overline{\mathcal F}_n$, which is the total space of degeneration of the Deligne-Mumford space of stable rational curves $ \overline M_{n+2} $ to the moduli space of cactus flower curves $ \overline F_n $ recently introduced in \cite{iklpr}. As an application, we show that trigonometric Gaudin subalgebras act on tensor products of irreducible finite-dimensional $g$-modules without multiplicities, under some explicit assumptions on the parameters in terms of two different real forms of $\overline M_{n+2}$. This gives rise to a monodromy action of the affine cactus group on the set of eigenstates for the trigonometric Gaudin model. We also explain the relation between the trigonometric Gaudin model and the quantum cohomology of affine Grassmannians slices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06424v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksei Ilin, Joel Kamnitzer, Leonid Rybnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cluster Algebras and Dilogarithm Identities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06668v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This is a reasonably self-contained exposition of the fascinating interplay between cluster algebras and the dilogarithm in the recent two decades. The dilogarithm has a long and rich history since Euler. The most intriguing property of the function is that it satisfies various functional relations, which we call dilogarithm identities (DIs). In the 1990s Gliozzi and Tateo conjectured a family of DIs based on root systems, which vastly generalize the classic DIs such as Euler's and Abel's identities. On the other hand, the cluster algebras are a class of commutative algebras introduced by Fomin and Zelevinsky around 2000. It turned out that a DI is associated with each period in a cluster pattern of cluster algebra theory. In particular, they solve the conjecture on the DIs by Gliozzi and Tateo. We employ these DIs as the leitmotif and present several proofs, variations, and generalizations of them with various methods and techniques. The quantum DIs are also treated from the unified point of view with the classical ones.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06668v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomoki Nakanishi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Affine $\imath$quantum groups and Steinberg varieties of type C</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06865v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We provide a geometric realization of the quasi-split affine $\imath$quantum group of type AIII$_{2n-1}^{(\tau)}$ in terms of equivariant K-groups of non-connected Steinberg varieties of type C. This uses a new Drinfeld type presentation of this affine $\imath$quantum group which admits very nontrivial Serre relations. We then construct \`a la Springer a family of finite-dimensional standard modules and irreducible modules of this $\imath$quantum group, and provide a composition multiplicity formula of the standard modules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06865v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Changjian Su, Weiqiang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
