<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.QA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.QA</link>
    <description>math.QA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.QA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2024 05:26:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Zeta-polynomials, superpolynomials, DAHA and plane curve singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.02200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.02200v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We begin with modular form periods, a focal point of several Yuri Manin's works. The similarity is discussed between the corresponding zeta-polynomials and superpolynomials of algebraic links, closely related to Khovanov-Rozansky polynomials. We focus on DAHA superpolynomials and motivic ones, defined via compactified Jacobians of plane curve singularities and their counterparts in arbitrary ranks; the non-unibranch construction is new. They conjecturally coincide with the corresponding generalizations of L-functions and satisfy the Riemann Hypothesis in some sectors of the parameters. Presumably, the motivic ones an be interpreted as certain partition functions of Landau-Ginzburg models associated with plane curve singularities; RH for them is remarkably similar to the Lee-Yang circle theorem for Ising models. A q,t-deformation of the Witten index is obtained as an application. General perspectives of the motivic theory of isolated curve and surface singularities are discussed, including possible implications in number theory. Also, we introduce super-analogs of $\rho_{ab}$-invariants and discuss super-deformations of the Riemann's zeta. Among other topics: Verlinde algebras, and the topological vertex.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.02200v5</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ivan Cherednik</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
