<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.QA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.QA</link>
    <description>math.QA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.QA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2024 02:33:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Some isomorphisms between exceptional W-algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08371v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove some isomorphisms between exceptional W-algebras associated with exceptional simple Lie algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08371v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jethro van Ekeren, Shigenori Nakatsuka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Algebra of the Infrared with Twisted Masses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08372v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Algebra of the Infrared \cite{Gaiotto:2015aoa} is a framework to construct local observables, interfaces, and categories of supersymmetric boundary conditions of massive $\mathcal{N}=(2,2)$ theories in two dimensions by using information only about the BPS sector. The resulting framework is known as the ``web-based formalism.'' In this paper we initiate the generalization of the web-based formalism to include a much wider class of $\mathcal{N}=(2,2)$ quantum field theories than was discussed in \cite{Gaiotto:2015aoa}: theories with non-trivial twisted masses. The essential new ingredient is the presence of BPS particles within a fixed vacuum sector. In this paper we work out the web-based formalism for the simplest class of theories that allow for such BPS particles: theories with a single vacuum and a single twisted mass. We show that even in this simple setting there are interesting new phenomenon including the emergence of Fock spaces of closed solitons and a natural appearance of Koszul dual algebras. Mathematically, studying theories with twisted masses includes studying the Fukaya-Seidel category of A-type boundary conditions for Landau-Ginzburg models defined by a closed holomorphic one-form. This paper sketches a web-based construction for the category of A-type boundary conditions for one-forms with a single Morse zero and a single non-trivial period. We demonstrate our formalism explicitly in a particularly instructive example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08372v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahsan Z. Khan, Gregory W. Moore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simple Vertex Algebras Arising From Congruence Subgroups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.10090</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.10090v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Chiral de Rham complex introduced by Malikov et al. in 1998, is a sheaf of vertex algebras on any complex analytic manifold or non-singular algebraic variety. Starting from the vertex algebra of global sections of chiral de Rham complex on the upper half plane, we consider the subspace of $\Gamma$-invariant sections that are meromorphic at the cusps. The space is again a vertex operator algebra, with a linear basis consisting of lifting formulas of meromorphic modular forms. We will describe two types of lifting formulas, and generalize the Rankin-Cohen bracket to the meromorphic modular forms. As an application, we will show that the vertex algebras constructed by congruence subgroups are simple.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.10090v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuanzhong Dai, Bailin Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Unicity Theorem and the center of the ${\rm SL}_3$-skein algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16812v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The ${\rm SL}_3$-skein algebra $\mathscr{S}_{\bar{q}}(\mathfrak{S})$ of a punctured oriented surface $\mathfrak{S}$ is a quantum deformation of the coordinate algebra of the ${\rm SL}_3$-character variety of $\mathfrak{S}$. When $\bar{q}$ is a root of unity, we prove the Unicity Theorem for representations of $\mathscr{S}_{\bar{q}}(\mathfrak{S})$, in particular the existence and uniqueness of a generic irreducible representation. Furthermore, we show that the center of $\mathscr{S}_{\bar{q}}(\frak{S})$ is generated by the peripheral skeins around punctures and the central elements contained in the image of the Frobenius homomorphism for $\mathscr{S}_{\bar{q}}(\frak{S})$, a surface generalization of Frobenius homomorphisms of quantum groups related to ${\rm SL}_3$. We compute the rank of $\mathscr{S}_{\bar{q}}(\mathfrak{S})$ over its center, hence the dimension of the generic irreducible representation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16812v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hyun Kyu Kim, Zhihao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
