<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.QA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.QA</link>
    <description>math.QA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.QA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 03:48:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Non-stationary difference equation and affine Laumon space III : Generalization to $\widehat{\mathfrak{gl}}_N$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27142</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.27142v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a series of papers we have considered a non-stationary difference equation which was originally discovered for the deformed Virasoro conformal block. The equation involves mass parameters and, when they are tuned appropriately, the equation is regarded as a quantum KZ equation for $U_q(A_{1}^{(1)})$. We introduce a $\widehat{\mathfrak{gl}}_N$ generalization of the non-stationary difference equation. The Hamiltonian is expressed in terms of $q$-commuting variables and allows both factorized forms and a normal ordered form. By specializing the mass parameters appropriately, the Hamiltonian can be identified with the $R$-matrix of the symmetric tensor representation of $U_q(A_{N-1}^{(1)})$, which in turn comes from the 3D (tetrahedron) $R$-matrix. We conjecture that the affine Laumon partition function of type $A_{N-1}^{(1)}$ gives a solution to our $\widehat{\mathfrak{gl}}_N$ non-stationary difference equation. As a check of our conjecture, we work out the four dimensional limit and find that the non-stationary difference equation reduces to the Fuji-Suzuki-Tsuda system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.27142v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hidetoshi Awata, Koji Hasegawa, Hiroaki Kanno, Ryo Ohkawa, Shamil Shakirov, Jun'ichi Shiraishi, Yasuhiko Yamada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fusion Trees and Homological Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27218</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.27218v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We establish an identification between the spaces of $\alpha$-fusion trees in non-semisimple topological quantum computation (NSS TQC) and a family of homological representations of the braid group known as the Lawrence representations specialized at roots of unity. Leveraging this connection, we provide a new proof of Ito's colored Alexander invariant formula using graphical calculus. Inspired by Anghel's topological model, we derive a formula involving the Hermitian pairing of fusion trees. This formula verifies that non-semisimple quantum knot invariants can be explicitly encoded via the language of fusion trees in the NSS TQC mathematical architecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.27218v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sung Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum $K$-theoretic divisor axiom for flag manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16150v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove an identity for (torus-equivariant) 3-point, genus 0, $K$-theoretic Gromov-Witten invariants of flag manifolds $G/P$, which can be thought of as a replacement for the ``divisor axiom'' in their (torus-equivariant) quantum $K$-theory. This identity enables us to compute these invariants when two insertions are Schubert classes and the other a Schubert divisor class. Our type-independent proof utilizes the Chevalley formula for the (torus-equivariant) quantum $K$-theory ring of flag manifolds, which computes multiplications by Schubert divisor classes in terms of the quantum Bruhat graph.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16150v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cristian Lenart, Satoshi Naito, Daisuke Sagaki, Leonardo C. Mihalcea, Weihong Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal nets from minimal W-algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04270v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show the strong graded locality of all unitary minimal W-algebras, so that they give rise to irreducible graded-local conformal nets. Among these unitary vertex superalgebras, up to taking tensor products with free fermion vertex superalgebras, there are the unitary Virasoro vertex algebras (N=0) and the unitary N=1,2,3,4 super-Virasoro vertex superalgebras. Accordingly, we have a uniform construction that gives, besides the already known N=0,1,2 super-Virasoro nets, also the new N=3,4 super-Virasoro nets. All strongly rational unitary minimal W-algebras give rise to previously known completely rational graded-local conformal nets and we conjecture that the converse is also true. We prove this conjecture for all unitary W-algebras corresponding to the N=0,1,2,3,4 super-Virasoro vertex superalgebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04270v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00220-025-05468-2</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Communications in Mathematical Physics, volume 406, issue 12, (2025), article number 300</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sebastiano Carpi, Tiziano Gaudio</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
