<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.QA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.QA</link>
    <description>math.QA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.QA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 04:00:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A non-semisimple Kitaev lattice model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.09249v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The construction of the topologically protected code space of Kitaev's model for fault-tolerant quantum computation is extended from complex semisimple to arbitrary finite-dimensional Hopf algebras admitting pairs in involution. One input of the model are ribbon graphs, that is, the combinatorial data of cellular decompositions of oriented closed surfaces. The other input are certain Hopf bimodules that are closely related to the coefficients in Hopf-cyclic homology. As in previous generalisations of the Kitaev model, a Yetter-Drinfeld module is constructed and shown to be a topological invariant of the surface with boundary that is obtained by "thickening" the graph. The generalisation of the protected space is defined using bitensor products of modules-comodules. Provided that the Hopf bimodule coefficients correspond to pairs in involution, this is shown to depend only on the genus of the graph. As examples, group algebras of finite groups and bosonisations of Nichols algebras are considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.09249v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Halbig, Ulrich Kr\"ahmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher Chiral Algebras in a Polysimplicial Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09728</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.09728v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Vertex algebras are equivalent to translation-equivariant chiral algebras on $\mathbb{A}^1$, in the sense of Beilinson and Drinfeld. In this paper we give an algebraic construction of a chiral algebra on $\mathbb{A}^n$; this can be seen as an algebraic construction of a higher-dimensional vertex algebra.
  We introduce a model, in dg commutative algebras, of the derived algebra of functions on the configuration space of $k$ distinct labelled marked points in $\mathbb{A}^n$. Working in this model -- which we call the polysimplicial model -- we obtain a dg operad of chiral operations on a degree-shifted copy of the canonical sheaf. We prove that there is a quasi-isomorphism, to this dg operad, from the Lie-infinity operad. This result makes the shifted canonical sheaf into a first example of a homotopy polysimplicial chiral algebra on $\mathbb{A}^n$, in a sense which generalizes to higher dimensions Malikov and Schechtman's notion of a homotopy chiral algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.09728v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laura O. Felder, Zhengping Gui, Charles A. S. Young</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>(2+1)d Lattice Models and Tensor Networks for Gapped Phases with Categorical Symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09177</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.09177v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Gapped phases in 2+1 dimensional quantum field theories with fusion 2-categorical symmetries were recently classified and characterized using the Symmetry Topological Field Theory (SymTFT) approach arXiv:2408.05266, arXiv:2502.20440. In this paper, we provide a systematic lattice model construction for all such gapped phases. Specifically, we consider ``All boson type" fusion 2-category symmetries, all of which are obtainable from 0-form symmetry groups $G$ (possibly with an 't Hooft anomaly) via generalized gauging--that is, by stacking with an $H$-symmetric TFT and gauging a subgroup $H$. The continuum classification directly informs the lattice data, such as the generalized gauging that determines the symmetry category, and the data that specifies the gapped phase. We construct commuting projector Hamiltonians and ground states applicable to any non-chiral gapped phase with such symmetries. We also describe the ground states in terms of tensor networks. In light of the length of the paper, we include a self-contained summary section presenting the main results and examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.09177v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kansei Inamura, Sheng-Jie Huang, Apoorv Tiwari, Sakura Schafer-Nameki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Affine web of type Q</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09729</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.09729v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a new diagrammatic $\Bbbk$-linear monoidal supercategory $QWeb^\bullet$, the affine web supercategory of type $Q$, where $\Bbbk$ is a commutative ring of characteristic not two. This category is the affinization of the web category of type $Q$, originally introduced by Brown and Kujawa. It serves as the type $Q$ analog of the affine web category introduced by Davidson, Kujawa, Muth and Zhu, and independently by Wang and one of the authors. We obtain diagrammatic integral bases for the Hom-spaces of this category. We show that $QWeb^\bullet$ provides a combinatorial model for a natural monoidal supercategory of endosuperfunctors for Lie superalgebras of type $Q$. .</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.09729v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linliang Song, Xingyu Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On products of abelian skew braces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.09844v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The main objective of this paper is to study factorisations of skew left braces through abelian subbraces. We prove a skew brace theoretical analog of the classical It\^o's theorem about product of two abelian groups: if $B = A_1A_2$ is a skew brace which is the product of two abelian skew subbraces $A_1$ and $A_2$, and $A_1$ is a left and right ideal of $B$, then the commutator ideal $[B, B]^B$ of $B$ is an abelian brace. If $A_1$ is a left (non-necessarily right) ideal of $B$, we show that there exists a strong left ideal of $B$ contained in $A_1$ or $A_2$. We also show factorisations of relevant ideals of factorised braces that are sums and products of abelian subbraces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.09844v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Ballester-Bolinches, R. Esteban-Romero, P. P\'erez-Altarriba</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
