<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.QA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.QA</link>
    <description>math.QA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.QA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 05:00:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Irreduciblity of certain $\widehat{\mathfrak sl}_2$-modules of Wakimoto type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02718</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02718v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the irreducible smooth $\widehat{\mathfrak{sl}}_{2}$-modules recently constructed in arXiv:2404.03855, and demonstrate that these modules admit a Wakimoto-type realization at both critical and non-critical levels. In the critical level case, we identify simple quotients of these modules with the Wakimoto modules whose irreducibility was already established in arXiv:math/0602181, arXiv:1402.6100. We also generalize some Wakimoto modules constructed in arXiv:1409.5354 and identify them as generalized Whittaker modules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02718v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Drazen Adamovic, Veronika Pedic Tomic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Schur limit, modular differential equations and quantum monodromy traces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02102</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02102v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explore some aspects of the generalized Schur limit, defined in arXiv:2506.13764. Based on several examples, we conjecture that the generalized Schur limit as a function of $\alpha$ solves a modular linear differential equation of fixed order, with coefficients depending on $\alpha$. We also observe in examples that for Argyres-Douglas theories of type $(A_1,G)$ with $G=A_n,D_n$, the generalized Schur limit for certain negative integer values of $\alpha$, coincides with the trace of higher powers of the quantum monodromy operator. This hints at a more general correspondence between the wall-crossing invariant traces on the Coulomb branch and the generalized Schur limit, which is related to the Higgs branch.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02102v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anirudh Deb</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unipotent quantum coordinate ring and minuscule prefundamental representations: twisted case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02946v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the prefundamental modules $L_{s,a}^{\pm}$ over the Borel subalgebras of the twisted quantum loop algebras, which are introduced by Wang. A character formula for $L_{s,a}^{\pm}$ is obtained from that for the prefundamental modules over the untwisted quantum loop algebras by applying a character folding map. This allows us to realize minuscule prefundamental modules $L_{s,a}^{\pm}$ for types $A_{2n-1}^{(2)}$ and $D_{n+1}^{(2)}$ in terms of the unipotent quantum coordinate ring associated with the fundamental $s$-th coweight, where $s = 1$ for type $A_{2n-1}^{(2)}$ and $s = n$ for type $D_{n+1}^{(2)}$. This result is a continuation of the realization of (co)minuscule prefundamental modules established by earlier works [J-Kwon-Park, Int. Math. Res. Not., 2023] and [J-Kwon-Park, J. Algebra, 2025].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02946v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Il-Seung Jang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete quantum group coaction on the circle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.21638v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove by an explicit calculation that if any Kac-type $C^*$-algebraic discrete quantum group $\mathcal{Q}$ has a `weakly faithful' coaction on $C(S^1)$ which is `linear' in the sense that it leaves the space spanned by $\{ Z, \overline{Z} \}$ invariant, then $\mathcal{Q}$ must be classical, i.e. isomorphic with $C_0(\Gamma)$ for some discrete group $\Gamma$. This parallels the well-known result of non-existence of genuine compact quantum group symmetry obtained by the first author and his collaborators ([32] and the references therein).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.21638v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debashish Goswami, Suchetana Samadder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A construction of surface skein TQFTs and their extension to 4-dimensional 2-handlebodies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19352</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19352v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For a commutative Frobenius algebra $A$, we construct a $(2,3,3+\varepsilon)$-dimensional TQFT $\mathsf{AFK}_A$ that assigns to a 3-manifold a skein module of embedded $A$-decorated surfaces. These surface skein modules have been first defined by Asaeda--Frohman and Kaiser using skein relations that generalize the combinatorics of Bar-Natan's dotted cobordisms. For 3-manifolds with boundary, we show that surface skein modules carry an action by a certain surface skein category associated with the boundary, which yields a gluing formalism. Our main result concerns a partial extension of $\mathsf{AFK}_A$ to dimension 4, which uses an inductive state-sum construction following Walker. As an example, the equivariant version of Lee's deformation of dotted cobordisms yields a TQFT that extends to 4-dimensional 2-handlebodies but not 3-handlebodies. Finally, we characterize the attachment of 4-dimensional 2-handles by means of a certain Kirby color and use it to compute the invariants of 4-dimensional 2-handlebodies in examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19352v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leon J. Goertz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-semisimple CFT/TFT correspondence I: General setup</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21231</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21231v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We extend the TFT construction of CFT correlators of [arXiv:hep-th/0204148] to so-called finite logarithmic CFTs for which the algebraic input data is no longer semisimple but still finite. More specifically, starting from the data of a chiral CFT given in the form of a not necessarily semisimple modular tensor category C we use a three dimensional topological field theory with surface defects based on the surgery TFT of [arXiv:1912.02063] to construct a full CFT as a braided monoidal oplax natural transformation.
  We make our construction explicit in the example of the transparent surface defect, resulting in the so-called Cardy case. In particular, we consider topological line defects and their action on bulk fields in these logarithmic CFTs, providing a source of examples for non-invertible and non-semisimple topological symmetries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21231v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aaron Hofer, Ingo Runkel</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
