<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.QA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.QA</link>
    <description>math.QA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.QA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 04:00:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Homological Integrals for Weak Hopf Algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03057</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03057v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the notion of a homological integral for an infinite-dimensional weak Hopf algebra and use the homological integral to prove several structure theorems. For example, we prove that the Artin--Schelter property and the Van den Bergh condition are equivalent for a noetherian weak Hopf algebra, and that the antipode is automatically invertible in this case. We also prove a decomposition theorem that states that any weak Hopf algebra finite over an affine center is a direct sum of Artin--Schelter Gorenstein, Cohen--Macaulay, GK dimension homogeneous weak Hopf algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03057v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Rogalski, Robert Won, James J. Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Levi-Civita connection and Chern connections for cocycle deformations of K\"{a}hler manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03340</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03340v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider unitary cocycle deformations of covariant $\ast$-differential calculi. We prove that complex structures, holomorphic bimodules and Chern connections can be deformed to their noncommutative counterparts under such deformations. If we start with a K\"ahler manifold, then the Levi-Civita connection on the space of one forms of the deformed calculus can be expressed as a direct sum of the Chern connections on the twisted holomorphic and the anti-holomorphic bimodules. Our class of examples include toric deformations considered by Mesland and Rennie as well as cocycle deformations of the Heckenberger-Kolb calculi.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03340v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jyotishman Bhowmick, Bappa Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The stable limit DAHA: the structure of the standard representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03113v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove a number of results about the structure of the standard representation of the stable limit DAHA. More precisely, we address the triangularity, spectrum, and eigenfunctions of the limit Cherednik operators, and construct several PBW-type bases for the stable limit DAHA. We establish a remarkable triangularity property concerning the contribution of certain special elements of the PBW basis of a finite rank DAHA of high enough rank to the PBW expansion of a PBW basis element of the stable limit DAHA. The triangularity property implies the faithfulness of the standard representation. This shows that the algebraic structure defined by the limit operators associated to elements of the finite rank DAHAs is precisely the stable limit DAHA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03113v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bogdan Ion, Dongyu Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>W*-superrigidity for discrete quantum groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03266v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A discrete group $G$ is called W*-superrigid if the group $G$ can be entirely recovered from the ambient group von Neumann algebra $L(G)$. We introduce an analogous notion for discrete quantum groups. We prove that this strengthened quantum W*-superrigidity property holds for a natural family of co-induced discrete quantum groups. We also prove that, remarkably, most existing families of W*-superrigid groups are not quantum W*-superrigid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03266v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Milan Donvil, Stefaan Vaes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Condensations in higher categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.09566</link>
      <description>arXiv:1905.09566v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a higher-categorical generalization of the "Karoubi envelope" construction from ordinary category theory, and prove that, like the ordinary Karoubi envelope, our higher Karoubi envelope is the closure for absolute limits. Our construction replaces the idempotents in the ordinary version with a notion that we call "condensations." The name is justified by the direct physical interpretation of the notion of condensation: it encodes a general class of constructions which produce a new topological phase of matter by turning on a commuting projector Hamiltonian on a lattice of defects within a different topological phase, which may be the trivial phase. We also identify our higher Karoubi envelopes with categories of fully-dualizable objects. Together with the Cobordism Hypothesis, we argue that this realizes an equivalence between a very broad class of gapped topological phases of matter and fully extended topological field theories, in any number of dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1905.09566v3</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davide Gaiotto, Theo Johnson-Freyd</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A comparison between $SL_n$ spider categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.09289</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.09289v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove a conjecture of L\^{e} and Sikora by providing a comparison between various existing $SL_n$ skein theories. While doing so, we show that the full subcategory of the spider category, $\mathcal{S}p(SL_n)$, defined by Cautis-Kamnitzer-Morrison, whose objects are monoidally generated by the standard representation and its dual, is equivalent as a spherical braided category to Sikora's quotient category. This also answers a question from Morrison's Ph.D. thesis. Finally, we show that the skein modules associated to the CKM and Sikora's webs are isomorphic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.09289v5</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anup Poudel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Knizhnik-Zamolodchikov equations in Deligne categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02266v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the Knizhnik-Zamolodchikov equations in Deligne Categories in the context of $(\mathfrak{gl}_m,\mathfrak{gl}_{n})$ and $(\mathfrak{so}_m,\mathfrak{so}_{2n})$ dualities. We derive integral formulas for the solutions in the first case and compute monodromy in both cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02266v2</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pavel Etingof, Ivan Motorin, Alexander Varchenko, Isaac Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
