<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.QA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.QA</link>
    <description>math.QA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.QA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 04:00:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>How are pseudo-$q$-traces related to (co)ends?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.04532v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $\mathbb V$ be an $\mathbb N$-graded $C_2$-cofinite vertex operator algebra (VOA), not necessarily rational or self-dual. Using a special case of the sewing-factorization theorem from [GZ25a], we show that the end $\mathbb E=\int_{\mathbb M\in\mathrm{Mod}(\mathbb V)}\mathbb M\otimes_{\mathbb C}\mathbb M'$ in $\mathrm{Mod}(\mathbb{V}^{\otimes2})$ (where $\mathbb{M}'$ is the contragredient module of $\mathbb{M}$) admits a natural structure of associative $\mathbb C$-algebra compatible with its $\mathbb{V}^{\otimes2}$-module structure. Moreover, we show that a suitable category $\mathrm{Coh}_{\mathrm{L}}(\mathbb E)$ of left $\mathbb E$-modules is isomorphic, as a linear category, to $\mathrm{Mod}(\mathbb V)$, and that the space of vacuum torus conformal blocks is isomorphic to the space $\mathrm{SLF}(\mathbb E)$ of symmetric linear functionals on $\mathbb E$.
  Combining these results with the main theorem of [GZ25b], we prove a conjecture of Gainutdinov-Runkel: For any projective generator $\mathbb G$ in $\mathrm{Mod}(\mathbb V)$, the pseudo-$q$-trace construction yields a linear isomorphism from $\mathrm{SLF}(\mathrm{End}_{\mathbb V}(\mathbb{G})^{\mathrm{opp}})$ to the space of vacuum torus conformal blocks of $\mathbb V$.
  In particular, if $A$ is a unital finite-dimensional $\mathbb C$-algebra such that the category of finite-dimensional left $A$-modules is equivalent to $\mathrm{Mod}(\mathbb V)$, then $\mathrm{SLF}(A)$ is linearly isomorphic to the space of vacuum torus conformal blocks of $\mathbb V$. This confirms a conjecture of Arike-Nagatomo.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.04532v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bin Gui, Hao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Tensor Algebras to Hyperbolic Kac-Moody Algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03815v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a novel approach to study hyperbolic Kac-Moody algebras, and more specifically, the Feingold-Frenkel algebra $\mathfrak{F}$, which is based on considering the tensor algebra of level-one states before descending to the Lie algebra by converting tensor products into multiple commutators. This method enables us to exploit the presence of mutually commuting coset Virasoro algebras, whose number grows without bound with increasing affine level. We present the complete decomposition of the tensor algebra under the affine and coset Virasoro symmetries for all levels $\ell\leq 5$, as well as the maximal tensor ground states from which all elements of $\mathfrak{F}$ up to level five can be (redundantly) generated by the joint action of the affine and coset Virasoro generators, and subsequent conversion to multi-commutators, which are then expressed in terms of transversal and longitudinal DDF states. We outline novel directions for future work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03815v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Axel Kleinschmidt, Hannes Malcha, Hermann Nicolai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite 2-group gauge theory and its 3+1D lattice realization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.04693v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we employ the Tannaka-Krein reconstruction to compute the quantum double $\mathcal D(\mathcal G)$ of a finite 2-group $\mathcal G$ as a Hopf monoidal category. We also construct a 3+1D lattice model from the Dijkgraaf-Witten TQFT functor for the 2-group $\mathcal G$, generalizing Kitaev's 2+1D quantum double model. Notably, the string-like local operators in this lattice model are shown to form $\mathcal D(\mathcal G)$. Specializing to $\mathcal G = \mathbb{Z}_2$, we demonstrate that the topological defects in the 3+1D toric code model are modules over $\mathcal D(\mathbb{Z}_2)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.04693v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mo Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mock Modularity Of Twisted Index In CHL Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17182</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.17182v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the twisted partition function of quarter BPS states in CHL models and show that for a large class of single-centered black holes, the degeneracy of microstates is given by the Fourier coefficients of mock Jacobi forms. Our analysis is a continuation of the programme initiated by Dabholkar, Murthy and Zagier (DMZ) for $1/4$-BPS dyons in $\mathcal{N} = 4$ string theory and further extended by Bhand, Sen and Singh (BSS) to quarter BPS states in CHL models. We also present the multiplicative lift construction of the partition function and comment on the additive lift of the same.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.17182v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nabamita Banerjee, Vedant Bhutra, Ranveer Kumar Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skein theory for the Links-Gould polynomial</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19251v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Building further on work of Marin and Wagner, we give a cubic braid-type skein theory of the Links--Gould polynomial invariant of oriented links and prove that it can be used to evaluate any oriented link, adding this polynomial to the list of polynomial invariants that can be computed by skein theory. As a consequence, we prove that this skein theory is also shared by the $V_1$-polynomial defined by two of the authors, deducing the equality of the two link polynomials. This implies specialization properties of the $V_1$-polynomial to the Alexander polynomial and to the $\mathrm{ADO}_3$-invariant, the fact that it is a Vassiliev power series invariant, as well as a Seifert genus bound for knots.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19251v3</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stavros Garoufalidis, Matthew Harper, Rinat Kashaev, Ben-Michael Kohli, Jiebo Song, Guillaume Tahar</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
