<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.QA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.QA</link>
    <description>math.QA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.QA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 04:00:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Dual braided quantum $E(2)$ groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.13790</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.13790v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: An explicit construction of the braided dual of quantum $E(2)$ groups is described over the circle group $\mathbb{T}$ with respect to a specific $R$-matrix $R$. Additionally, the corresponding bosonization is also described.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.13790v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Atibur Rahaman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rigidity of quantum algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.07839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.07839v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given an associative $\mathbb{C}$-algebra $A$, we call $A$ strongly rigid if for any pair of finite subgroups of its automorphism groups $G, H,$ such that $A^G\cong A^H$, then $G$ and $H$ must be isomorphic. In this paper we show that a large class of filtered quantizations are strongly rigid. We also prove several other rigidity type results for various quantum algebras. For example, we show that given two non-isomorphic complex semi-simple Lie algebras $\mathfrak{g}_1, \mathfrak{g}_2$ of equal dimension, there are no injective $\mathbb{C}$-algebra homomorphisms between their enveloping algebras. We also show that any finite subgroup of automorphisms of a central reduction of a finite $W$-algebra $W_{\chi}(\mathfrak{g}, e)$ must be isomorphic to a subgroup of $Aut(\mathfrak{g}(e)).$ We solve the inverse Galois problem for a wide class of rational Cherednik algebras that includes all (simple) classical generalized Weyl algebras, and also for quantum tori. Finally, we show that the Picard group of an $n$-dimensional quantum torus $A_q$ (with $q$ not a root of unity) is isomorphic to the group of outer automorphisms of $A_q.$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.07839v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akaki Tikaradze</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A conjecture on monomial realizations and polyhedral realizations for crystal bases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06417</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06417v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Crystal bases are powerful combinatorial tools in the representation theory of quantum groups $U_q(\mathfrak{g})$ for a symmetrizable Kac-Moody algebras $\mathfrak{g}$. The polyhedral realizations are combinatorial descriptions of the crystal base $B(\infty)$ for Verma modules in terms of the set of integer points of a polyhedral cone, which equals the string cone when $\mathfrak{g}$ is finite dimensional simple. It is a fundamental and natural problem to find explicit forms of the polyhedral cone. The monomial realization expresses crystal bases $B(\lambda)$ of integrable highest weight representations as Laurent monomials with double indexed variables. In this paper, we give a conjecture between explicit forms of the polyhedral cones and monomial realizations. We prove the conjecture is true when $\mathfrak{g}$ is a classical Lie algebra, a rank $2$ Kac-Moody algebra or a classical affine Lie algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06417v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuki Kanakubo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Partition identities from higher level crystals of $A_1^{(1)}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.10279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2111.10279v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study perfect crystals for the standard modules of the affine Lie algebra $A_1^{(1)}$ at all levels using the theory of multi-grounded partitions. We prove a family of partition identities which are reminiscent of the Andrews-Gordon identities and companions to the Meurman-Primc identities, but with simple difference conditions involving absolute values.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2111.10279v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1090/proc/16417</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proc. Amer. Math. Soc. 153 (2025), 1363-1382</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jehanne Dousse, Leonard Hardiman, Isaac Konan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shifted twisted Yangians and Slodowy slices in classical Lie algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05492v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we introduce the shifted twisted Yangian of type {\sf AI}, following the work of Lu--Wang--Zhang, and we study their semiclassical limits, a class of Poisson algebras. We demonstrate that they coincide with the Dirac reductions of the semiclassical shifted Yangian for $\mathfrak{gl}_n$. We deduce that these shifted twisted Yangians admit truncations which are isomorphic to Slodowy slices for many non-rectangular nilpotent elements in types {\sf B}, {\sf C}, {\sf D}. As a direct consequence we obtain parabolic presentations of the semiclassical shifted twisted Yangian, analogous to those introduced by Brundan--Kleshchev for the Yangian of type {\sf A}. Finally we give Poisson presentations of Slodowy slices for all even nilpotent elements in types {\sf B}, {\sf C}, {\sf D}, generalising the recent work of the second author.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05492v4</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Tappeiner, Lewis Topley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Games and Synchronicity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15444v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the flavour of categorical quantum mechanics, we extend nonlocal games to allow quantum questions and answers, using quantum sets (special symmetric dagger Frobenius algebras) and the quantum functions of Musto, Reutter, and Verdon [arXiv:1711.07945]. Equations are presented using a diagrammatic calculus for tensor categories. To this quantum question and answer setting, we extend the standard definitions, including strategies, correlations, and synchronicity, and we use these definitions to extend results about synchronicity. We extend the graph homomorphism (isomorphism) game to quantum graphs, and show it is synchronous (bisynchronous) and connect its perfect (bi)strategies to quantum graph homomorphisms (isomorphisms). Our extended definitions agree with the existing quantum games literature, except in the case of synchronicity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15444v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adina Goldberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
