<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>stat.TH updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.TH</link>
    <description>stat.TH updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.TH" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 04:01:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Linear cost and exponentially convergent approximation of Gaussian Mat\'ern processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13000v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The computational cost for inference and prediction of statistical models based on Gaussian processes with Mat\'ern covariance functions scales cubicly with the number of observations, limiting their applicability to large data sets. The cost can be reduced in certain special cases, but there are currently no generally applicable exact methods with linear cost. Several approximate methods have been introduced to reduce the cost, but most of these lack theoretical guarantees for the accuracy. We consider Gaussian processes on bounded intervals with Mat\'ern covariance functions and for the first time develop a generally applicable method with linear cost and with a covariance error that decreases exponentially fast in the order $m$ of the proposed approximation. The method is based on an optimal rational approximation of the spectral density and results in an approximation that can be represented as a sum of $m$ independent Gaussian Markov processes, which facilitates easy usage in general software for statistical inference, enabling its efficient implementation in general statistical inference software packages. Besides the theoretical justifications, we demonstrate the accuracy empirically through carefully designed simulation studies which show that the method outperforms all state-of-the-art alternatives in terms of accuracy for a fixed computational cost in statistical tasks such as Gaussian process regression.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13000v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Bolin, Vaibhav Mehandiratta, Alexandre B. Simas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large data limits and scaling laws for tSNE</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13063v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work considers large-data asymptotics for t-distributed stochastic neighbor embedding (tSNE), a widely-used non-linear dimension reduction algorithm. We identify an appropriate continuum limit of the tSNE objective function, which can be viewed as a combination of a kernel-based repulsion and an asymptotically-vanishing Laplacian-type regularizer. As a consequence, we show that embeddings of the original tSNE algorithm cannot have any consistent limit as $n \to \infty$. We propose a rescaled model which mitigates the asymptotic decay of the attractive energy, and which does have a consistent limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13063v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryan Murray, Adam Pickarski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On uniqueness of the set of k-means</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13495v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We provide necessary and sufficient conditions for the uniqueness of the k-means set of a probability distribution. This uniqueness problem is related to the choice of k: depending on the underlying distribution, some values of this parameter could lead to multiple sets of k-means, which hampers the interpretation of the results and/or the stability of the algorithms. We give a general assessment on consistency of the empirical k-means adapted to the setting of non-uniqueness and determine the asymptotic distribution of the within cluster sum of squares (WCSS). We also provide statistical characterizations of k-means uniqueness in terms of the asymptotic behavior of the empirical WCSS. As a consequence, we derive a bootstrap test for uniqueness of the set of k-means. The results are illustrated with examples of different types of non-uniqueness and we check by simulations the performance of the proposed methodology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13495v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Javier C\'arcamo, Antonio Cuevas, Luis A. Rodr\'iguez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explainable Binary Classification of Separable Shape Ensembles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12994</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12994v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Materials scientists utilize image segmentation of micrographs to create large curve ensembles representing grain boundaries of material microstructures. Observations of these collections of shapes can facilitate inferences about material properties and manufacturing processes. We seek to bolster this application, and related engineering/scientific tasks, using novel pattern recognition formalisms and inference over large ensembles of segmented curves -- i.e., facilitate principled assessments for quantifying differences in distributions of shapes. To this end, we apply a composite integral operator to motivate accurate and efficient numerical representations of discrete planar curves over matrix manifolds. The main result is a rigid-invariant orthonormal decomposition of curve component functions into separable forms of scale variations and complementary features of undulation. We demonstrate how these separable shape tensors -- given thousands of curves in an ensemble -- can inform explainable binary classification of segmented images by utilizing a product maximum mean discrepancy to distinguish the shape distributions; absent labelled data, building interpretable feature spaces in seconds without high performance computation, and detecting discrepancies below cursory visual inspections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12994v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zachary Grey, Nicholas Fisher, Andrew Glaws, Gunay Dogan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Markov Random Fields with Proximity Constraints for Spatial Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13164v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The conditional autoregressive (CAR) model, simultaneous autoregressive (SAR) model, and its variants have become the predominant strategies for modeling regional or areal-referenced spatial data. The overwhelming wide-use of the CAR/SAR model motivates the need for new classes of models for areal-referenced data. Thus, we develop a novel class of Markov random fields based on truncating the full-conditional distribution. We define this truncation in two ways leading to versions of what we call the truncated autoregressive (TAR) model. First, we truncate the full conditional distribution so that a response at one location is close to the average of its neighbors. This strategy establishes relationships between TAR and CAR. Second, we truncate on the joint distribution of the data process in a similar way. This specification leads to connection between TAR and SAR model. Our Bayesian implementation does not use Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) for Bayesian computation, and generates samples directly from the posterior distribution. Moreover, TAR does not have a range parameter that arises in the CAR/SAR models, which can be difficult to learn. We present the results of the proposed truncated autoregressive model on several simulated datasets and on a dataset of average property prices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13164v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sudipto Saha, Jonathan R. Bradley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A theoretical perspective on mode collapse in variational inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13300v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: While deep learning has expanded the possibilities for highly expressive variational families, the practical benefits of these tools for variational inference (VI) are often limited by the minimization of the traditional Kullback-Leibler objective, which can yield suboptimal solutions. A major challenge in this context is \emph{mode collapse}: the phenomenon where a model concentrates on a few modes of the target distribution during training, despite being statistically capable of expressing them all. In this work, we carry a theoretical investigation of mode collapse for the gradient flow on Gaussian mixture models. We identify the key low-dimensional statistics characterizing the flow, and derive a closed set of low-dimensional equations governing their evolution. Leveraging this compact description, we show that mode collapse is present even in statistically favorable scenarios, and identify two key mechanisms driving it: mean alignment and vanishing weight. Our theoretical findings are consistent with the implementation of VI using normalizing flows, a class of popular generative models, thereby offering practical insights.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13300v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roman Soletskyi, Marylou Gabri\'e, Bruno Loureiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial Proportional Hazards Model with Differential Regularization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13420v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel Spatial Proportional Hazards model that incorporates spatial dependence through differential regularization. We address limitations of existing methods that overlook domain geometry by proposing an approach based on the Generalized Spatial Regression with PDE Penalization. Our method handles complex-shaped domains, enabling accurate modeling of spatial fields in survival data. Using a penalized log-likelihood functional, we estimate both covariate effects and the spatial field. The methodology is implemented via finite element methods, efficiently handling irregular domain geometries. We demonstrate its efficacy through simulations and apply it to real-world data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13420v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Tedesco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supervised Kernel Thinning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13749v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The kernel thinning algorithm of Dwivedi &amp; Mackey (2024) provides a better-than-i.i.d. compression of a generic set of points. By generating high-fidelity coresets of size significantly smaller than the input points, KT is known to speed up unsupervised tasks like Monte Carlo integration, uncertainty quantification, and non-parametric hypothesis testing, with minimal loss in statistical accuracy. In this work, we generalize the KT algorithm to speed up supervised learning problems involving kernel methods. Specifically, we combine two classical algorithms--Nadaraya-Watson (NW) regression or kernel smoothing, and kernel ridge regression (KRR)--with KT to provide a quadratic speed-up in both training and inference times. We show how distribution compression with KT in each setting reduces to constructing an appropriate kernel, and introduce the Kernel-Thinned NW and Kernel-Thinned KRR estimators. We prove that KT-based regression estimators enjoy significantly superior computational efficiency over the full-data estimators and improved statistical efficiency over i.i.d. subsampling of the training data. En route, we also provide a novel multiplicative error guarantee for compressing with KT. We validate our design choices with both simulations and real data experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13749v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Albert Gong, Kyuseong Choi, Raaz Dwivedi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Impact of Approximation Errors on Extreme Quantile Estimation with Applications to Functional Data Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.03581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.03581v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the effect of approximation errors in assessing the extreme behavior of heavy-tailed random objects. We give conditions for the approximation error such that the standard asymptotic results hold for the classical Hill estimator and the corresponding extreme quantile estimator. As an application, we consider the effect of discretization errors in the computation of the $L^p$-norms related to functional data. We approximate the norms both with Riemann sums and with Monte Carlo integration. We quantify connections between the number of observed functions, the number of discretization points, and the regularity of the underlying functions. In addition, we derive a new concentration inequality for order statistics. This, to the best of our knowledge, is the first Chernoff-type concentration inequality for order statistics presented in the literature that provides an explicit rate at which the ratio between order statistics and tail quantile function converges to one. In our application, the bound is used to provide concentration inequalities measuring the distance between the Hill estimator based on approximated norms and the one based on the true ones.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.03581v2</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jaakko Pere, Benny Avelin, Valentin Garino, Pauliina Ilmonen, Lauri Viitasaari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Concentration inequalities for high-dimensional linear processes with dependent innovations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.12395</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.12395v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop concentration inequalities for the $l_\infty$ norm of vector linear processes with sub-Weibull, mixingale innovations. This inequality is used to obtain a concentration bound for the maximum entrywise norm of the lag-$h$ autocovariance matrix of linear processes. We apply these inequalities to sparse estimation of large-dimensional VAR(p) systems and heterocedasticity and autocorrelation consistent (HAC) high-dimensional covariance estimation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.12395v2</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eduardo Fonseca Mendes, Fellipe Lopes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric ergodicity of trans-dimensional Markov chain Monte Carlo algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.00139</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.00139v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article studies the convergence properties of trans-dimensional MCMC algorithms when the total number of models is finite. It is shown that, for reversible and some non-reversible trans-dimensional Markov chains, under mild conditions, geometric convergence is guaranteed if the Markov chains associated with the within-model moves are geometrically ergodic. This result is proved in an $L^2$ framework using the technique of Markov chain decomposition. While the technique was previously developed for reversible chains, this work extends it to the point that it can be applied to some commonly used non-reversible chains. The theory herein is applied to reversible jump algorithms for three Bayesian models: a probit regression with variable selection, a Gaussian mixture model with unknown number of components, and an autoregression with Laplace errors and unknown model order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.00139v3</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qian Qin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimating Max-Stable Random Vectors with Discrete Spectral Measure using Model-Based Clustering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.01609</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.01609v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study introduces a novel estimation method for the entries and structure of a matrix $A$ in the linear factor model $\mathbf{X} = A\textbf{Z} + \textbf{E}$. This is applied to an observable vector $\mathbf{X} \in \mathbb{R}^d$ with $\textbf{Z} \in \mathbb{R}^K$, a vector composed of independently regularly varying random variables, and lighter tail noise $\textbf{E} \in \mathbb{R}^d$. The spectral measure of the regularly varying random vector $\mathbf{X}$ is subsequently discrete and completely characterised by the matrix $A$. It follows that the behaviour of its maxima can be modelled by a max-stable random vector with discrete spectral measure. Every max-stable random vector with discrete spectral measure can be written as a linear factor model. Each row of the matrix $A$ is supposed to be both scaled and sparse. Additionally, the value of $K$ is not known a priori. The problem of identifying the matrix $A$ from its matrix of pairwise extremal correlation is addressed. In the presence of pure variables, which are elements of $\mathbf{X}$ linked, through $A$, to a single latent factor, the matrix $A$ can be reconstructed from the extremal correlation matrix. Our proofs of identifiability are constructive and pave the way for our innovative estimation for determining the number of factors $K$ and the matrix $A$ from $n$ weakly dependent observations on $\mathbf{X}$. We apply the suggested method to weekly maxima rainfall and wildfires to illustrate its applicability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.01609v4</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexis Boulin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Organized State-Space Models with Artificial Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08928v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a state-space model (SSM) parametrized by some parameter $\theta$ and aim at performing joint parameter and state inference. A popular idea to carry out this task is to replace $\theta$ by a Markov chain $(\theta_t)_{t\geq 0}$ and then to apply a filtering algorithm to the extended, or self-organized SSM (SO-SSM). However, the practical implementation of this idea in a theoretically justified way has remained an open problem. In this paper we fill this gap by introducing constructions of $(\theta_t)_{t\geq 0}$ that ensure the validity of the SO-SSM for joint parameter and state inference. Notably, we show that such SO-SSMs can be defined even if $\|\mathrm{Var}(\theta_{t}|\theta_{t-1})\|\rightarrow 0$ slowly as $t\rightarrow\infty$. This result is important since these models can be efficiently approximated using a particle filter. While SO-SSMs have been introduced for online inference, the development of iterated filtering (IF) has shown that they can also serve for computing the maximum likelihood estimator of an SSM. We also derive constructions of $(\theta_t)_{t\geq 0}$ and theoretical guarantees tailored to these specific applications of SO-SSMs and introduce new IF algorithms. From a practical point of view, the algorithms we develop are simple to implement and only require minimal tuning to perform well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08928v3</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuan Chen, Mathieu Gerber, Christophe Andrieu, Randal Douc</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of existence and nonexistence of pivot on the coverage of empirical best linear prediction intervals for small areas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11238</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11238v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We advance the theory of parametric bootstrap in constructing highly efficient empirical best (EB) prediction intervals of small area means. The coverage error of such a prediction interval is of the order $O(m^{-3/2})$, where $m$ is the number of small areas to be pooled using a linear mixed normal model. In the context of an area level model where the random effects follow a non-normal known distribution except possibly for unknown hyperparameters, we analytically show that the order of coverage error of empirical best linear (EBL) prediction interval remains the same even if we relax the normality of the random effects by the existence of pivot for a suitably standardized random effects when hyperpameters are known. Recognizing the challenge of showing existence of a pivot, we develop a simple moment-based method to claim non-existence of pivot. We show that existing parametric bootstrap EBL prediction interval fails to achieve the desired order of the coverage error, i.e. $O(m^{-3/2})$, in absence of a pivot. We obtain a surprising result that the order $O(m^{-1})$ term is always positive under certain conditions indicating possible overcoverage of the existing parametric bootstrap EBL prediction interval. In general, we analytically show for the first time that the coverage problem can be corrected by adopting a suitably devised double parametric bootstrap. Our Monte Carlo simulations show that our proposed single bootstrap method performs reasonably well when compared to rival methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11238v2</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuting Chen, Masayo Y. Hirose, Partha Lahiri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General bounds on the quality of Bayesian coresets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.11780</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.11780v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Bayesian coresets speed up posterior inference in the large-scale data regime by approximating the full-data log-likelihood function with a surrogate log-likelihood based on a small, weighted subset of the data. But while Bayesian coresets and methods for construction are applicable in a wide range of models, existing theoretical analysis of the posterior inferential error incurred by coreset approximations only apply in restrictive settings -- i.e., exponential family models, or models with strong log-concavity and smoothness assumptions. This work presents general upper and lower bounds on the Kullback-Leibler (KL) divergence of coreset approximations that reflect the full range of applicability of Bayesian coresets. The lower bounds require only mild model assumptions typical of Bayesian asymptotic analyses, while the upper bounds require the log-likelihood functions to satisfy a generalized subexponentiality criterion that is weaker than conditions used in earlier work. The lower bounds are applied to obtain fundamental limitations on the quality of coreset approximations, and to provide a theoretical explanation for the previously-observed poor empirical performance of importance sampling-based construction methods. The upper bounds are used to analyze the performance of recent subsample-optimize methods. The flexibility of the theory is demonstrated in validation experiments involving multimodal, unidentifiable, heavy-tailed Bayesian posterior distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.11780v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Trevor Campbell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalised Bayes Linear Inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14145v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Motivated by big data and the vast parameter spaces in modern machine learning models, optimisation approaches to Bayesian inference have seen a surge in popularity in recent years. In this paper, we address the connection between the popular new methods termed generalised Bayesian inference and Bayes linear methods. We propose a further generalisation to Bayesian inference that unifies these and other recent approaches by considering the Bayesian inference problem as one of finding the closest point in a particular solution space to a data generating process, where these notions differ depending on user-specified geometries and foundational belief systems. Motivated by this framework, we propose a generalisation to Bayes linear approaches that enables fast and principled inferences that obey the coherence requirements implied by domain restrictions on random quantities. We demonstrate the efficacy of generalised Bayes linear inference on a number of examples, including monotonic regression and inference for spatial counts. This paper is accompanied by an R package available at github.com/astfalckl/bayeslinear.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14145v3</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lachlan Astfalck, Cassandra Bird, Daniel Williamson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faster Diffusion Sampling with Randomized Midpoints: Sequential and Parallel</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00924v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Sampling algorithms play an important role in controlling the quality and runtime of diffusion model inference. In recent years, a number of works~\cite{chen2023sampling,chen2023ode,benton2023error,lee2022convergence} have proposed schemes for diffusion sampling with provable guarantees; these works show that for essentially any data distribution, one can approximately sample in polynomial time given a sufficiently accurate estimate of its score functions at different noise levels. In this work, we propose a new scheme inspired by Shen and Lee's randomized midpoint method for log-concave sampling~\cite{ShenL19}. We prove that this approach achieves the best known dimension dependence for sampling from arbitrary smooth distributions in total variation distance ($\widetilde O(d^{5/12})$ compared to $\widetilde O(\sqrt{d})$ from prior work). We also show that our algorithm can be parallelized to run in only $\widetilde O(\log^2 d)$ parallel rounds, constituting the first provable guarantees for parallel sampling with diffusion models.
  As a byproduct of our methods, for the well-studied problem of log-concave sampling in total variation distance, we give an algorithm and simple analysis achieving dimension dependence $\widetilde O(d^{5/12})$ compared to $\widetilde O(\sqrt{d})$ from prior work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00924v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shivam Gupta, Linda Cai, Sitan Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feature learning in finite-width Bayesian deep linear networks with multiple outputs and convolutional layers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.03260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.03260v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Deep linear networks have been extensively studied, as they provide simplified models of deep learning. However, little is known in the case of finite-width architectures with multiple outputs and convolutional layers. In this manuscript, we provide rigorous results for the statistics of functions implemented by the aforementioned class of networks, thus moving closer to a complete characterization of feature learning in the Bayesian setting. Our results include: (i) an exact and elementary non-asymptotic integral representation for the joint prior distribution over the outputs, given in terms of a mixture of Gaussians; (ii) an analytical formula for the posterior distribution in the case of squared error loss function (Gaussian likelihood); (iii) a quantitative description of the feature learning infinite-width regime, using large deviation theory. From a physical perspective, deep architectures with multiple outputs or convolutional layers represent different manifestations of kernel shape renormalization, and our work provides a dictionary that translates this physics intuition and terminology into rigorous Bayesian statistics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.03260v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico Bassetti, Marco Gherardi, Alessandro Ingrosso, Mauro Pastore, Pietro Rotondo</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
