<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.bio-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph</link>
    <description>physics.bio-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 04:04:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid roles of adaptation and optimization in formation of vascular network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07824v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It was hypothesized that the structures of biological transport networks are the result of either energy consumption or adaptation dynamics. Although approaches based on these hypotheses can produce optimal network and form loop structures, we found that neither possesses complete ability to generate complex networks that resemble vascular network in living organisms, which motivated us to propose a hybrid approach. This approach can replicate the path dependency phenomenon of main branches and produce an optimal network that resembles the real vascular network. We further show that there is a clear transition in the structural pattern of the vascular network, shifting from `chive-like' to dendritic configuration after a period of sequenced adaptation and optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07824v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yawei Wang, Zilu Qin, Yubo Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does time to retreatment matter? An NTCP model to predict radionecrosis after repeat SRS for recurrent brain metastases incorporating time-dependent discounted dose</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07647</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07647v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Purpose: To develop and compare normal tissue complication probability (NTCP) models for recurrent brain metastases (BMs) treated with repeat single-fraction stereotactic radiosurgery (SRS), considering time-dependent discounted prior dose. Methods: We developed three NTCP models of BMs treated with GammaKnife-based SRS. The maximum dose to 0.2cc (D0.2cc) of each lesion-specific brain and one-year radionecrosis was fitted using a logistic model with equivalent-dose conversions in 2 Gy (EQD2). The M0 and M1-retreat modeled radionecrosis risk following SRS to 1029 non-recurrent lesions (patients=262) and 2nd SRS to 149 recurrent lesions (patients=87). The M1-combo model accounted for 2nd SRS and time-dependent discounted 1st SRS dose for recurrent lesions estimated by a modified Gompertzian function. Results: All three models fitted the data well (Chi-2 = 0.039-0.089 and p = 0.999-1.000). The fitted EQD250 was ~103 Gy for M0, ~88 Gy for M1-retreat, and ~165 Gy for M1-combo. The fitted EQD2_50 exhibited a progressively flatter dose-response curve across the three models, with values of 1.2 Gy for M0, 0.6 Gy for M1-retreat, and 0.4 Gy for M1-combo. For the brain D0.2cc of 29Gy and 19Gy, the steepest to shallowest dose-response or largest change in NTCP, i.e., NTCP29Gy - NTCP19Gy was observed in M1-retreat (0.16), M0 (0.14) and M1-combo (0.06). Conclusions: The model-fitted parameters predict that recurrent BMs have a lower threshold dose tolerance and a more gradual dose response for the 2nd SRS than non-recurrent BMs. This gradual dose-response becomes even more apparent when considering the time-dependent discounted 1st SRS as a cumulative 2nd SRS. Tailoring SRS retreatment protocols based on NTCP modeling can potentially enhance therapeutic efficacy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07647v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manju Sharma, Issam El Naqa, Penny K Sneed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>(Un)buckling mechanics of epithelial monolayers under compression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07928v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: When cell sheets fold during development, their apical or basal surfaces constrict and cell shapes approach the geometric singularity in which these surfaces vanish. Here, we reveal the mechanical consequences of this geometric singularity for tissue folding in a minimal vertex model of an epithelial monolayer. In simulations of the buckling of the epithelium under compression and numerical solutions of the corresponding continuum model, we discover an "unbuckling" bifurcation: At large compression, the buckling amplitude can decrease with increasing compression. By asymptotic solution of the continuum equations, we reveal that this bifurcation comes with a large stiffening of the epithelium. Our results thus provide the mechanical basis for absorption of compressive stresses by tissue folds such as the cephalic furrow during germband extension in Drosophila.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07928v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.TO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chandraniva Guha Ray, Pierre A. Haas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Useful autonomous quantum machines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.08739</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.08739v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Controlled quantum machines have matured significantly. A natural next step is to increasingly grant them autonomy, freeing them from time-dependent external control. For example, autonomy could pare down the classical control wires that heat and decohere quantum circuits; and an autonomous quantum refrigerator recently reset superconducting qubits to near their ground states, as is necessary before a computation. Which fundamental conditions are necessary for realizing useful autonomous quantum machines? Inspired by recent quantum thermodynamics and chemistry, we posit conditions analogous to DiVincenzo's criteria for quantum computing. Furthermore, we illustrate the criteria with multiple autonomous quantum machines (refrigerators, circuits, clocks, etc.) and multiple candidate platforms (neutral atoms, molecules, superconducting qubits, etc.). Our criteria are intended to foment and guide the development of useful autonomous quantum machines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.08739v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Antonio Mar\'in Guzm\'an, Paul Erker, Simone Gasparinetti, Marcus Huber, Nicole Yunger Halpern</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integer Topological Defects Reveal Anti-Symmetric Forces in Active Nematics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15431</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15431v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Cell layers are often categorized as contractile or extensile active nematics but recent experiments on neural progenitor cells with induced $+1$ topological defects challenge this classification. In a bottom-up approach, we first study a relevant particle-level model and then analyze a continuous theory derived from it. We show that both model and theory account qualitatively for the main experimental result, i.e. accumulation of cells at the core of any type of +1 defect. We argue that cell accumulation is essentially due to two generally ignored 'effective active forces'.
  We finally discuss the relevance and consequences of our findings in the context of other cellular active nematics experiments and previously proposed theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15431v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zihui Zhao, Yisong Yao, He Li, Yongfeng Zhao, Yujia Wang, Hepeng Zhang, Hugues Chat'e, Masaki Sano</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
