<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.bio-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph</link>
    <description>physics.bio-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 04:02:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Deep learning enables automated assessments of inflammatory response in zebrafish exposed to different pollutants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00603v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the field of environmental toxicology, rapid and precise assessment of the inflammatory response to pollutants in biological models is critical. This study leverages the power of deep learning to enable automated assessments of zebrafish, a model organism widely used for its translational relevance to human disease pathways. We present an innovative approach to assessing inflammatory responses in zebrafish exposed to various pollutants through an end-to-end deep learning model. The model employs a Unet-based architecture to automatically process high-throughput lateral zebrafish images, segmenting specific regions and quantifying neutrophils as inflammation markers. Alongside imaging, qPCR analysis offers gene expression insights, revealing the molecular impact of exposure on inflammatory pathways. Moreover, the deep learning model was packaged as a user-friendly executable file (.exe), facilitating widespread application by enabling use on virtually any computer without the need for specialized software or training.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00603v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lulu Xu, Peiwu Qin, Zhenglin Chen, Jiaqi Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Q-BiC: A biocompatible integrated chip for in vitro and in vivo spin-based quantum sensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01181v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Optically addressable spin-based quantum sensors enable nanoscale measurements of temperature, magnetic field, pH, and other physical properties of a system. Advancing the sensors beyond proof-of-principle demonstrations in living cells and multicellular organisms towards reliable, damage-free quantum sensing poses three distinct technical challenges. First, spin-based quantum sensing requires optical accessibility and microwave delivery. Second, any microelectronics must be biocompatible and designed for imaging living specimens. Third, efficient microwave delivery and temperature control are essential to reduce unwanted heating and to maintain an optimal biological environment. Here, we present the Quantum Biosensing Chip (Q-BiC), which facilitates microfluidic-compatible microwave delivery and includes on-chip temperature control. We demonstrate the use of Q-BiC in conjunction with nanodiamonds containing nitrogen vacancy centers to perform optically detected magnetic resonance in living systems. We quantify the biocompatibility of microwave excitation required for optically detected magnetic resonance both in vitro in HeLa cells and in vivo in the nematode Caenorhabditis elegans for temperature measurements and determine the microwave-exposure range allowed before detrimental effects are observed. In addition, we show that nanoscale quantum thermometry can be performed in immobilised but non-anaesthetised adult nematodes with minimal stress. These results enable the use of spin-based quantum sensors without damaging the biological system under study, facilitating the investigation of the local thermodynamic and viscoelastic properties of intracellular processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01181v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louise Shanahan, Sophia Belser, Jack W. Hart, Qiushi Gu, Julien R. E. Roth, Annika Mechnich, Michael Hoegen, Soham Pal, David Jordan, Eric A. Miska, Mete Atature, Helena S. Knowles</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Origin of Information Handling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04374</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04374v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A major challenge when describing the origin of life is to explain how instructional information control systems emerge naturally and spontaneously from mere molecular dynamics. So far, no one has clarified how information control emerged ab initio and how primitive control mechanisms in life might have evolved, becoming increasingly refined. Based on recent experimental results showing that chemical computation does not require the presence of life-related chemistry, we elucidate the origin and early evolution of information handling by chemical automata, from information processing (computation) to information storage (memory) and information transmission (communication). In contrast to other theories that assume the existence of initial complex structures, our narrative starts from trivial self-replicators whose interaction leads to the arising of more powerful molecular machines. By describing precisely the primordial transitions in chemistry-based computation, our metaphor is capable of explaining the above-mentioned gaps and can be translated to other models of computation, which allow us to explore biological phenomena at multiple spatial and temporal scales. At the end of our manuscript, we propose some ways to extend our ideas, including experimental validation of our theory (both in vitro and in silico).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04374v2</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amahury Jafet L\'opez-D\'iaz, Hiroki Sayama, Carlos Gershenson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergence of large-scale mechanical spiral waves in bacterial living matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06990v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Propagating spiral waves have been discovered in various chemical, biological and physical systems. Spiral waves in multicellular organisms are often associated with essential living functions. Although certain eukaryotic microorganisms have long been known to generate spiral waves, evidence of spiral wave pattern has not been lacking in the bacterial world. Here we report the discovery of a unique form of propagating spiral waves in dense bacterial populations where cells engage in cyclic force-generating processes driven by type-IV pilus motility. Specifically, we discovered that synchronization of pilus activity in the bacterial living matter leads to large-scale spatiotemporal regulation of tension force in the form of propagating spiral waves. Theoretical modelling reveals that the spiral tension waves result from nonreciprocity in cell-cell interactions. Our findings reveal a novel mechanism of large-scale force regulation in bacterial world and may shed light on the emergent mechanics of biofilms and microbiomes. Pilus-driven bacterial living matter also provides a mechanical active medium for studying electrical or chemical spiral waves in living systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06990v2</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41567-024-02457-5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nat. Phys. (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shiqi Liu, Ye Li, Yuhao Wang, Yilin Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Specific versus Nonspecific Solvent Interactions of a Biomolecule in Water</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.08217</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.08217v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Solvent interactions, particularly hydration, are vital in chemical and biochemical systems. Model systems unveil microscopic details of such interactions. We uncover a specific hydrogen-bonding motif of the biomolecular building block indole (C$_8$H$_7$N), tryptophan's chromophore, in water: a strong localized $\text{N-H}\cdots\text{OH}_2$ hydrogen bond, alongside unstructured solvent interactions. This insight is revealed from a combined experimental and theoretical analysis of indole's electronic structure in aqueous solution. We have recorded the complete X-ray photoemission and Auger spectrum of aqueous-phase indole, quantitatively explaining all peaks through \emph{ab initio} modeling. The efficient and accurate technique for modeling valence and core photoemission spectra involves the maximum-overlap method and the non-equilibrium polarizable-continuum model. A two-hole electron-population analysis quantitatively describes the Auger spectra. Core-electron binding energies for nitrogen and carbon highlight the specific interaction with a hydrogen-bonded water molecule at the N-H group and otherwise nonspecific solvent interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.08217v3</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.jpclett.3c01763</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. Chem. Lett. 14, 10499-10508 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lanhai He, Luk\'a\v{s} Toman\'ik, Sebastian Malerz, Florian Trinter, Sebastian Trippel, Michal Belina, Petr Slav\'i\v{c}ek, Bernd Winter, Jochen K\"upper</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
