<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.bio-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph</link>
    <description>physics.bio-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2024 04:00:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking the Cell Image Segmentation Models Robustness under the Microscope Optical Aberrations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.08549v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cell segmentation is essential in biomedical research for analyzing cellular morphology and behavior. Deep learning methods, particularly convolutional neural networks (CNNs), have revolutionized cell segmentation by extracting intricate features from images. However, the robustness of these methods under microscope optical aberrations remains a critical challenge. This study comprehensively evaluates the performance of cell instance segmentation models under simulated aberration conditions using the DynamicNuclearNet (DNN) and LIVECell datasets. Aberrations, including Astigmatism, Coma, Spherical, and Trefoil, were simulated using Zernike polynomial equations. Various segmentation models, such as Mask R-CNN with different network heads (FPN, C3) and backbones (ResNet, VGG19, SwinS), were trained and tested under aberrated conditions. Results indicate that FPN combined with SwinS demonstrates superior robustness in handling simple cell images affected by minor aberrations. Conversely, Cellpose2.0 proves effective for complex cell images under similar conditions. Our findings provide insights into selecting appropriate segmentation models based on cell morphology and aberration severity, enhancing the reliability of cell segmentation in biomedical applications. Further research is warranted to validate these methods with diverse aberration types and emerging segmentation models. Overall, this research aims to guide researchers in effectively utilizing cell segmentation models in the presence of minor optical aberrations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.08549v1</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boyuan Peng, Jiaju Chen, Qihui Ye, Minjiang Chen, Peiwu Qin, Chenggang Yan, Dongmei Yu, Zhenglin Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying Harmony between Direct and Indirect Pathways in The Basal Ganglia; Healthy and Parkinsonian States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.12540</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.12540v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The basal ganglia (BG) show a variety of functions for motor and cognition. There are two competitive pathways in the BG; direct pathway (DP) which facilitates movement and indirect pathway (IP) which suppresses movement. It is well known that diverse functions of the BG may be made through "balance" between DP and IP. But, to the best of our knowledge, so far no quantitative analysis for such balance was done. In this paper, as a first time, we introduce the competition degree ${\cal C}_d$ between DP and IP. Then, by employing ${\cal C}_d$, we quantify their competitive harmony (i.e., competition and cooperative interplay), which could lead to improving our understanding of the traditional "balance" so clearly and quantitatively. We first consider the case of normal dopamine (DA) level of $\phi^*=0.3$. In the case of phasic cortical input (10 Hz), a healthy state with ${\cal C}_d^* = 2.82$ (i.e., DP is 2.82 times stronger than IP) appears. In this case, normal movement occurs via harmony between DP and IP. Next, we consider the case of decreased DA level, $\phi = \phi^*(=0.3)~x_{DA}$ ($1 &gt; x_{DA} \geq 0$). With decreasing $x_{DA}$ from 1, the competition degree ${\cal C}_d$ between DP and IP decreases monotonically from ${\cal C}_d^*$, which results in appearance of a pathological Parkinsonian state with reduced ${\cal C}_d$. In this Parkinsonian state, strength of IP is much increased than that in the case of normal healthy state, leading to disharmony between DP and IP. Due to such break-up of harmony between DP and IP, impaired movement occurs. Finally, we also study treatment of the pathological Parkinsonian state via recovery of harmony between DP and IP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.12540v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sang-Yoon Kim, Woochang Lim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Motile bacteria crossing liquid-liquid interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.05095</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.05095v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Real-life bacteria often swim in complex fluids, but our understanding of the interactions between bacteria and complex surroundings is still evolving. In this work, rod-like \textit{Bacillus subtilis} swims in a quasi-2D environment with aqueous liquid-liquid interfaces, i.e., the isotropic-nematic coexistence phase of an aqueous chromonic liquid crystal. Focusing on the bacteria motion near and at the liquid-liquid interfaces, we collect and quantify bacterial trajectories ranging across the isotropic to the nematic phase. Despite its small magnitude, the interfacial tension of the order of 10 $\mathrm{\mu N/m}$ at the isotropic-nematic interface justifies our observations that bacteria swimming more perpendicular to the interface have a higher probability of crossing the interface. Our force-balance model, considering the interfacial tension, further predicts how the length and speed of the bacteria affect their crossing behaviors. We also find, as soon as the bacteria cross the interface and enter the nematic phase, they wiggle less, but faster, and that this occurs as the flagellar bundles aggregate within the nematic phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.05095v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiyong Cheon, Joowang Son, Sungbin Lim, Yundon Jeong, Jung-Hoon Park, Robert J. Mitchell, Jaeup U. Kim, Joonwoo Jeong</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
