<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.bio-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph</link>
    <description>physics.bio-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 04:03:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>True Solid-State Electrical Conduction of Proteins shows them to be Efficient Transport Media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18552</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.18552v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: While solid-state protein junctions have shown efficient electron transport over lengths that surpass those of conventional organic semiconducting systems, interfacial or contact effects may obscure the intrinsic protein charge transport properties. Therefore, contact resistance (RC) effects need to be quantified and then minimized, which poses a problem if 4-probe geometries cannot be used. Here we show how RC can be extracted quantitatively from the measured junction resistance (RP) by using the extrapolated zero-length resistance (RZLR) and short-circuit resistance (RS). We used AC (impedance spectroscopy) and DC measurements to examine charge transport in junctions of human serum albumin (HSA) and bacteriorhodopsin (bR) films with varying thicknesses. Three contact configurations, Si-Au, Au-EGaIn, and, in a micropore device (MpD), Au-Pd, were compared. While Si-Au and Au-EGaIn junctions exhibit substantial RC that we ascribe to interfacial oxides and electrostatic protein-electrode interactions, MpD effectively eliminates RC, enabling measuring the intrinsic electron transport across HSA and bR films. The exponential length dependence of RP shows a transport decay constant (beta) that varies with interfacial conditions, underscoring the role of contact engineering. By minimizing RC, exceptionally low beta values (0.7 to 1.1 per nm) are found, proving that, indeed, proteins can have outstanding charge transport efficiencies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.18552v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sudipta Bera, Ayelet Vilan, Sourav Das, Israel Pecht, David Ehre, Mordechai Sheves, David Cahen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Molecular Determinants of Orthosteric-allosteric Dual Inhibition of PfHT1 by Computational Assessment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.18559v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To overcome antimalarial drug resistance, carbohydrate derivatives as selective PfHT1 inhibitor have been suggested in recent experimental work with orthosteric and allosteric dual binding pockets. Inspired by this promising therapeutic strategy, herein, molecular dynamics simulations are performed to investigate the molecular determinants of co-administration on orthosteric and allosteric inhibitors targeting PfHT1. Our binding free energy analysis capture the essential trend of inhibitor binding affinity to protein from published experimental IC50 data in three sets of distinct characteristics. In particular, we rank the contribution of key residues as binding sites which categorized into three groups based on linker length, size of tail group, and sugar moiety of inhibitors. The pivotal roles of these key residues are further validated by mutant analysis where mutated to nonpolar alanine leading to reduced affinities to different degrees. The exception was fructose derivative, which exhibited a significant enhanced affinity to mutation on orthosteric sites due to strong changed binding poses. This study may provide useful information for optimized design of precision medicine to circumvent drug-resistant Plasmodium parasites with high efficacy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.18559v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Decheng Kong, Jinlong Ren, Zhuang Li, Guangcun Shan, Zhongjian Wang, Ruiqin Zhang, Wei Huang, Kunpeng Dou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermoregulation Variation in Vertebrates Reveals Differences in Thermal Fatigue Resistance of Bones</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18613</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.18613v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we propose the hypothesis that there is a significant difference in thermal cycling fatigue resistance between the bones of ectothermic and endothermic animals. We performed an experiment to test whether bones of endothermic animals, having potentially lost their ability to adapt to thermal cycling, exhibit reduced resistance to thermal fatigue compared to ectothermic animals, which may have retained this adaptive trait due to their environmental conditions. The change in stiffness were determined using shifts in the resonant peaks of the frequency spectrum obtained from Resonant Ultrasonic Spectroscopy (RUS). To achieve this, samples of compact (cortical) and spongy bone tissue were extracted and polished before undergoing a 29-day period of thermal cycling. The changes in the resonance frequencies were then observed. Changes in resonant frequencies imply corresponding changes in elastic constants. The primary findings indicated that bones from ectothermic species exhibited minimal changes in elastic properties compared to those from endothermic species, as evidenced by the smaller shifts in resonant peak magnitudes following thermal cycling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.18613v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Parker R. Brewster, Jake E. Akins, Casey M. Holycross, Farhad Farzbod</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single power-law rheology of crowded cytoplasm in living cells</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.18922v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cytoplasmic viscoelasticity is crucial for various intracellular processes. However, the dynamic shear modulus, $G(\omega)$, has been reported to vary considerably, often without consistent patterns or rules, even within the same cell. Thus, uncovering the physical basis of cytoplasmic rheology, and whether any universal feature exists, remains a major challenge. Here, we employed microrheology with a 3D feedback technique to minimize artifacts such as laser phototoxicity and examined cytoplasmic viscoelasticity across varied mechanical environments, cell types, and cytoskeletal disruptions. Unlike previous studies, a single power-law rheology $G(\omega)\propto(-i\omega)^{0.5}$ was observed over a broad frequency range for all conditions except ATP depletion. While the vimentin cytoskeleton significantly contributed to steady shear viscosity measured by pulling a particle over large distances, cytoskeletal disruptions had only a minor effect on locally measured viscoelasticity. These findings demonstrate that molecular crowding governs the observed universality, providing a framework to systematically investigate cytoplasmic mechanics across diverse cellular contexts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.18922v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Ebata, K. Nishizawa, F. A. S. van Esterik, Y. Tao, S. Inokuchi, H. Ise, D. Mizuno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for structural differences in spike glycoprotein variants of SARS-CoV-2: Infrared Spectroscopy, Circular Dichroism and Computational Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19766</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19766v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The SARS-CoV-2 pandemic has led to a significant emergence of highly mutated forms of viruses with a great ability to adapt to the human host. Some mutations resulted in changes in the amino acid sequences of viral proteins, including the Spike glycoproteins, affecting protein physico-chemical properties and functionalities. Here, we propose, for the first time to the best of our knowledge, a systematic and comparative study of the monomeric spike protein subunits 1 of three SARS-CoV-2 variants at pH 7.4, combining both an experimental approach, taking advantage of Attenuated Total Reflection Infrared and Circular Dichroism spectroscopies, and a computational approach via Molecular Dynamics simulations. Experimental data in combination with Molecular Dynamics and Surface polarity calculations provide a comprehensive understanding of variants proteins in terms of their secondary structure content, 3D conformational structure and order and interaction with the solvent. The present structural investigation clarifies which kind of changes in conformation and functionalities occurred as long as mutations appeared in amino acids sequences. This information is essential for preventive targeted actions, drug design, and biosensing applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19766v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tiziana Mancini, Nicole Luchetti, Salvatore Macis, Velia Minicozzi, Rosanna Mosetti, Alessandro Nucara, Stefano Lupi, Annalisa D Arco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Hope for Long Space Flights: Hypercapnia demonstrated suppression of metabolic acidosis in an experiment with prolonged stay of people in a closed life support system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.18551v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Humanity must solve the problems that threaten human health during long-term space flight. An unexpected solution is suggested by an experiment on people staying in a closed life support system model, conducted more than 50 years ago in Krasnoyarsk. The high level of carbon dioxide established after the start of the experiment changed the metabolism of the inhabitants. We present the interpretation of the results of the Krasnoyarsk experiment through understanding the effect of hypercapnia on metabolism for the first time in this work. Hypercapnia suppressed the possibility of developing metabolic acidosis and activated fat oxidation. The change in the respiratory quotient caused by hypercapnia stabilized the composition of the gas mixture in the closed life support system and ensured the stability of the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.18551v1</guid>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. A. Semyonov, A. A. Semyonova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Different behaviors of diffusing diffusivity dynamics based on three different definitions of fractional Brownian motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19190v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The effects of a "diffusing diffusivity" (DD), a stochastically time-varying diffusion coefficient, are explored within the frameworks of three different forms of fractional Brownian motion (FBM): (i) the Langevin equation driven by fractional Gaussian noise (LE-FBM), (ii) the Weyl integral representation introduced by Mandelbrot and van Ness (MN-FBM), and (iii) the Riemann-Liouville fractional integral representation (RL-FBM) due to L{\'e}vy. The statistical properties of the three FBM-generalized DD models are examined, including the mean-squared displacement (MSD), mean-squared increment (MSI), autocovariance function (ACVF) of increments, and the probability density function (PDF). Despite the long-believed equivalence of MN-FBM and LE-FBM, their corresponding FBM-DD models exhibit distinct behavior in terms of the MSD and MSI. In the MN-FBM-DD model, the statistical characteristics directly reflect an effective diffusivity equal to its mean value. In contrast, in LE-FBM-DD, correlations in the random diffusivity give rise to an unexpected crossover behavior in both MSD and MSI. We also find that the MSI and ACVF are nonstationary in RL-FBM-DD but stationary in the other two DD models. All DD models display a crossover from a short-time non-Gaussian PDF to a long-time Gaussian PDF. Our findings offer guidance for experimentalists in selecting appropriate FBM-generalized models to describe viscoelastic yet non-Gaussian dynamics in bio- and soft-matter systems with heterogeneous environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19190v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Wang, Aleksei V. Chechkin, Ralf Metzler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Viscosity's impact on nutrient uptake along the gut</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19235v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Through switching contraction patterns driving digestive flows, the small intestine balances nutrient uptake and waste removal. Complex segmentation contraction patterns are associated with higher nutrient uptake, while peristaltic contractions primarily serve to flush out unused remnants. However, the impact of the Non-Newtonian behavior of digestive fluids on the efficacy of these contraction patterns remains unclear. Here, we present finite-element simulations that model nutrient transport, diffusion, and uptake within both segmentation and peristaltic contractions along the small intestine for Newtonian and Non-Newtonian fluids. Our simulations reveal that diffusion plays a key role in uptake, with nutrient absorption directly linked to fluid viscosity, which governs molecular diffusivity. Further, we present an analytical prediction for uptake in peristalsis as a function of molecular diffusivity, which aligns closely with our simulation results. Notably, we find that shear-thinning properties of Non-Newtonian fluids enhance nutrient uptake, particularly in segmentation contractions compared to peristalsis. Our results demonstrate the fluid dynamical principles underlying intestinal digestion, showing how shear-thinning Non-Newtonian fluids promote efficient nutrient uptake without compromising the clearance of waste. This physical insight advances our understanding of digestive processes and provides a foundation for exploring the prevention of intestinal diseases such as bacterial overgrowth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19235v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.TO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevFluids.10.033103</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Fluids 10, 033103 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fabian Karl Henn, Karen Alim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oscillation death by mechanochemical feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19655</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19655v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Many cellular proteins, such as ERK, undergo oscillation death when cells are compressed, initiating many developmental processes in organisms. Whether such a transition arises from these proteins' specific biochemistry or generic dynamical features remains unclear. In this paper, we show that coupling mechanics to the chemistry of Hopf oscillators, such as ERK, through mechanochemical feedback (MCF) can generically drive oscillation death upon compression. We demonstrate this result using an active solid, a 1D ring of Brusselators coupled through damped springs, which we term Harmonic Brusselator Ring (HBR). Because of MCF, HBR's dynamics is non-Hermitian and breaks $\mathcal{PT}$-symmetry in a scale-dependent manner, generating a rich array of patterns, including traveling pulses, chimera states, intermittent fluctuations, and collective oscillation death. Furthermore, MCF engenders three dynamic phase transitions that separate the observed patterns into four phases. The underlying symmetry of HBR implies that the observed patterns and phases may generically arise in many natural and synthetic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19655v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Phanindra Dewan, Soumyadeep Mondal, Sumantra Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipative particle dynamics models of encapsulated microbubbles and gas vesicles for biomedical ultrasound simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19890v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ultrasound-guided drug and gene delivery (usdg) enables controlled and spatially precise delivery of drugs and macromolecules, encapsulated in microbubbles (embs) and submicron gas vesicles (gvs), to target areas such as cancer tumors. It is a non-invasive, high precision, low toxicity process with drastically reduced drug dosage. Rheological and acoustic properties of gvs and embs critically affect the outcome of usdg and imaging. Detailed understanding and modeling of their physical properties is thus essential for ultrasound-mediated therapeutic applications. State-of-the-art continuuum models of shelled bodies cannot incorporate critical details such as varying thickness of the encapsulating shell or specific interactions between its constituents and interior or exterior solvents. Such modeling approaches also do not allow for detailed modeling of chemical surface functionalizations, which are crucial for tuning the gv-blood interactions. We develop a general particle-based modeling framework for encapsulated bodies that accurately captures elastic and rheological properties of gvs and embs. We use dissipative particle dynamics to model the solvent, the gaseous phase in the capsid, and the triangulated surfaces of immersed objects. Their elastic behavior is studied and validated through stretching and buckling simulations, eigenmode analysis, shear flow simulations, and comparison of predicted gv buckling pressure with experimental data from the literature. The presented modeling approach paves the way for large-scale simulations of encapsulated bodies, capturing their dynamics, interactions, and collective behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19890v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikolaos Ntarakas, Ma\v{s}a Lah, Daniel Sven\v{s}ek, Tilen Potisk, Matej Praprotnik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dependence of the Radical Dynamics on the Beam Temporal Profile in FLASH Radiotherapy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19927v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Purpose: This study aims to investigate the impact of the beam temporal profile on the radical dynamics and inter-track interactions of FLASH radiotherapy, supporting parameter optimization for the equipment development and clinical implementation. Methods: MonteCarlo simulations based on the IRT method were performed to analyze the dynamics after irradiation, including single-pulse or multi-pulses irradiation, pulse repetition rate, width and dose. The physicochemical experiments were performed to measure the eaq-lifetimes for validation. The generation and recombination of OH and eaq-radicals were recorded under 6 MeV electron irradiation with varying beam temporal profiles. The radial distributions of the radicals were statistically analyzed, and the corresponding LETd and LETt were calculated. The inter-track interactions were assessed through a mathematical model. Results: The spatial distribution and temporal evolution of radicals were significantly affected by the beam time profiles. Compared with multi-pulses irradiation, single-pulse mode with a width less than 1/10 of the radical lifetime, a repetition interval longer than the radical lifetime, and a dose exceeding 1 Gy/pulse can lead to radicals rapid consumption, reducing the residual content. Instantaneous high dose rates induced radical tracks overlaps. When the single-pulse dose exceeded 1 Gy, the overlap probability approached 100%, aligning with the threshold for radical instantaneous combination. Conclusion: Under a low-duty cycle and high instantaneous dose-rate time profile, the radicals were rapidly consumed through track overlap hence reduced damage to normal tissues, inducing FLASH effect. The optimized time profile can be used to guide the development of equipment and parameter settings in clinical practice to maximize the FLASH effect, such as the laser accelerators and superconducting photocathode guns.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19927v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianhan Sun, Xianghui Kong, Jianfeng Lv, Xiaodong Liu, Jinghui Wang, Chen Lin, Tian Li, Yibao Zhang, Senlin Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Algorithms for Optimizing Mycorrhizal Inoculants Using Mycoponics: A Novel Framework for Nutrient Transfer and Protein Discovery in Precision Agriculture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18149v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Mycorrhizal fungi form vast subterranean networks that are critical for plant nutrient uptake, carbon sequestration, and ecosystem resilience. Despite their ecological importance, optimizing these networks for precision agriculture, forestry,and carbon sequestration remains an open challenge, particularly when it comes to understanding the complex molecular and quantum-scale processes that govern nutrient exchange. In this paper, we propose a novel experimental framework using mycoponics, a controlled, soil-less environment for the study of plant fungal symbiosis integrated with isotopic labeling and quantum dots to track real-time nutrient transfer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18149v2</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhiram Sripat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Turing pattern theory on homogeneous and heterogeneous higher-order temporal network system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.15736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.15736v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Reaction-diffusion processes on networked systems have received mounting attention in the past two decades, and the corresponding theory of network dynamics has been continuously enriched with the advancement of network science. Recently, time-varying features and many-body interactions have been discovered on various and numerous real-world networks, such as biological and social systems, and the study of contemporary network science has gradually moved away from historically static network frameworks that are based on pairwise interactions. We aim to propose a general and rudimentary framework for Turing instability of reaction-diffusion processes on higher-order temporal networks. Firstly, we define a brand Laplacian to depict higher-order temporal diffusion behaviors on networks. Furthermore, the general form of higher-order temporal reaction-diffusion systems with frequency of oscillation is defined, and a time-independent and concise form is obtained by equivalent substitution and method of averaging. Next, we discuss the two cases of homogeneous and heterogeneous network systems and give equivalent conditions of Turing instability through linear stability analysis. Finally, in the numerical simulation part, we verify and discuss the validity of the above theoretical framework and study the effect of the frequency of oscillation of higher-order temporal networks on reaction-diffusion processes. Our study has revealed that higher-order temporal reaction-diffusion, which takes into account both time-varying feature and many-body interactions, can formulate innovative and diverse patterns. Moreover, there are significant differences between patterns in continuous space and patterns on traditional networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.15736v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0211728</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Junyuan Shi, Linhe Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the mechanics of inhaled bronchial transmission of pathogenic microdroplets generated from the upper respiratory tract, with implications for infection onset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17895v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Could the microdroplets formed by viscoelastic stretching and break-up of mucosal liquids in the upper respiratory tract (URT), when inhaled further downwind, explain the brisk pace at which deep lung infections emerge following onset of initial infection at the URT? While it is well-established that particulates inhaled from outside can possibly penetrate to the lower airway only if they are &lt; 5 microns, the fate of particulates (many &gt; 5-microns in diameter) sheared away from the intra-URT mucosa during inhalation remains an open question. These particulates predominantly originate at the nasopharynx, oropharynx, and laryngeal chamber with the vocal folds. To resolve the posed question, this study considers a CT-based 3D anatomical airway reconstruction and isolates the tract from the laryngeal vocal fold region, mapping the entire tracheal cavity and concluding at generation 2 of the tracheobronchial tree. Through the delineated geometry, airflow simulation is conducted using the LES scheme to replicate relaxed inhalation at 15 L/min. Against the ambient air flux, numerical experiments have been performed to monitor the transport of liquid particulates with diameters 1-30 microns, bearing physical properties akin to aerosolized mucus with embedded virions. The full-scale numerical transmission trends to the lower airway were found consistent with the findings from a reduced-order mathematical model that conceptualized the impact of intra-airway vortex instabilities on local particle transport through point vortex idealization in an anatomy-guided 2D potential flow domain. The results collectively demonstrate markedly elevated trends of deep lung penetration by the URT-derived particulates, even if they are as large as 10- and 15 microns. The high viral load carried by such droplets to the bronchial spaces could mechanistically explain the accelerated seeding of infection in the lungs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17895v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saikat Basu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mechanistic Modeling of Lipid Nanoparticle Formation for the Delivery of Nucleic Acid Therapeutics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08577v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Nucleic acids such as mRNA have emerged as a promising therapeutic modality with the capability of addressing a wide range of diseases. Lipid nanoparticles (LNPs) as a delivery platform for nucleic acids were used in the COVID-19 vaccines and have received much attention. While modern manufacturing processes which involve rapidly mixing an organic stream containing the lipids with an aqueous stream containing the nucleic acids are conceptually straightforward, detailed understanding of LNP formation and structure is still limited and scale-up can be challenging. Mathematical and computational methods are a promising avenue for deepening scientific understanding of the LNP formation process and facilitating improved process development and control. This article describes strategies for the mechanistic modeling of LNP formation, starting with strategies to estimate and predict important physicochemical properties of the various species such as diffusivities and solubilities. Subsequently, a framework is outlined for constructing mechanistic models of reactor- and particle-scale processes. Insights gained from the various models are mapped back to product quality attributes and process insights. Lastly, the use of the models to guide development of advanced process control and optimization strategies is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08577v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pavan K. Inguva, Saikat Mukherjee, Pierre J. Walker, Vico Tenberg, Cedric Devos, Sunkyu Shin, Yanchen Wu, Srimanta Santra, Jie Wang, Shalini Singh, Mona A. Kanso, Shin Hyuk Kim, Bernhardt L. Trout, Martin Z. Bazant, Allan S. Myerson, Richard D. Braatz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weighted Point Configurations with Hyperuniformity: An Ecological Example and Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12807v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Random point configurations are said to be in hyperuniform states, if density fluctuations are anomalously suppressed in large-scale. Typical examples are found in Coulomb gas systems in two dimensions especially called log-gases in random matrix theory, in which points are repulsively correlated by long-range potentials. In infertile lands like deserts continuous survival competitions for water and nutrition will cause long-ranged repulsive interactions among plants. We have prepared digital data of spatial configurations of center-of-mass for bushes weighted by bush sizes which we call masses. Data analysis shows that such ecological point configurations do not show hyperuniformity as unmarked point processes, but are in hyperuniform states as marked point processes in which mass distributions are taken into account. We propose the non-equilibrium statistical-mechanics models to generate marked point processes having hyperuniformity, in which iterations of random thinning of points and coalescing of masses transform initial uncorrelated point processes into non-trivial point processes with hyperuniformity. Combination of real data-analysis and computer simulations shows the importance of strong correlations in probability law between spatial point configurations and mass distributions of individual points to realize hyperuniform marked point processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12807v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayana Ezoe, Makoto Katori, Tomoyuki Shirai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Curvature-sensing and generation by membrane proteins: a review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18311v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Membrane proteins are crucial in regulating biomembrane shapes and controlling the dynamic changes in membrane morphology during essential cellular processes. These proteins can localize to regions with their preferred curvatures (curvature sensing) and induce localized membrane curvature. Thus, this review describes the recent theoretical development in membrane remodeling performed by membrane proteins. The mean-field theories of protein binding and the resulting membrane deformations are reviewed. The effects of hydrophobic insertions on the area-difference elasticity energy and that of intrinsically disordered protein domains on the membrane bending energy are discussed. For the crescent-shaped proteins, such as Bin/Amphiphysin/Rvs superfamily proteins, anisotropic protein bending energy and orientation-dependent excluded volume significantly contribute to curvature sensing and generation. Moreover, simulation studies of membrane deformations caused by protein binding are reviewed, including domain formation, budding, and tubulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18311v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1039/D5SM00101C</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Hiroshi Noguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
