<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.bio-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph</link>
    <description>physics.bio-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 05:08:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Remember when? Deciphering Ediacaran-Cambrian Metazoan behaviour and temporal memory using fossil movement paths</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02940v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Evaluating the timing and trajectory of sensory system innovations is crucial for understanding the increase in phylogenetic, behavioural, and ecological diversity during the Ediacaran-Cambrian transition. Elucidation of sensory adaptations has relied on either body-fossil evidence based on anatomical features or qualitative descriptions of trace-fossil morphology, leaving a gap in the record of sensory system innovations between the development of basic sensory capacities and that of more advanced sensory organs and brains. Here, we examine fossil movement trajectories of Ediacaran and Cambrian grazers for the presence of autocorrelation. Our analysis reveals a lack of temporal correlation in the studied Ediacaran trajectories and its presence in both analysed Cambrian trajectories, indicating time-tuned behaviours were in place by the early Cambrian. These results support the Cambrian Information Revolution hypothesis and indicates that increases in cognitive complexity and behavioural strategies were yet another important evolutionary innovation that occurred during the Ediacaran Cambrian transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02940v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brittany A. Laing, M. Gabriela M\'angano, Luis A. Buatois, Glenn A. Brock, Romain Gougeon, Zoe Vestrum, Luke C. Strotz, Lyndon Koens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Materials and Design Strategies of Fully 3D Printed Biodegradable Wireless Devices for Biomedical Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02573</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02573v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Three-dimensional (3D) printing of bioelectronics offers a versatile platform for fabricating personalized and structurally integrated electronic systems within biological scaffolds. Biodegradable electronics, which naturally dissolve after their functional lifetime, minimize the long-term burden on both patients and healthcare providers by eliminating the need for surgical retrieval. In this study, we developed a library of 3D-printable, biodegradable electronic inks encompassing conductors, semiconductors, dielectrics, thereby enabling the direct printing of fully functional, multi-material, customizable electronic systems in a single integrated process. Especially, conjugated molecules were introduced to improve charge mobility, energy level alignment in semiconducting inks. This ink platform supports the fabrication of passive/active components and physical/chemical sensors making it suitable for complex biomedical applications. Versatility of this system was demonstrated through two representative applications: (i) wireless pressure sensor embedded within biodegradable scaffolds, (ii) wireless electrical stimulators that retain programmable electrical functionality in vivo and degrade post-implantation. This work establishes a foundation of modules for autonomous, biodegradable bioelectronic systems fabricated entirely via 3D printing, with implications for personalized diagnostics, therapeutic interfaces, and transient medical devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02573v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ju-Yong Lee, Jooik Jeon, Joo-Hyeon Park, Se-Hun Kang, Yea-seol Park, Min-Sung Chae, Jieun Han, Kyung-Sub Kim, Jae-Hwan Lee, Sung-Geun Choi, Sun-Young Park, Young-Seo Kim, Yoon-Nam Kim, Seung-Min Lee, Myung-Kyun Choi, Jun Min Moon, Joon-Woo Kim, Seung-Kwon Seol, Jeonghyun Kim, Jahyun Koo, Ju-Young Kim, Woo-Byoung Kim, Kang-Sik Lee, Jung Keun Hyun, Seung-Kyun Kang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Control across scales: signals, information, and adaptive biological mechanical function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03418v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Biological systems perform an astonishing array of dynamical processes -- including development and repair, regulation, behavior and motor control, sensing and signaling, and adaptation, among others. Powered by the transduction of stored energy resources, these behaviors enable biological systems to regulate functions, achieve specific outcomes, and maintain stability far from thermodynamic equilibrium. These behaviors span orders of magnitude in length and time: from nanometer-scale molecular motors driving morphogenesis to kilometer-scale seasonal migrations, and from millisecond reflexes to millennia of evolutionary adaptations. While physical laws govern the dynamics of biological systems, they alone are insufficient to fully explain how living systems sense, decide, adapt, and, ultimately, control their dynamics. In this article, we argue that control theory provides a powerful, unifying framework for understanding how biological systems regulate dynamics to maintain stability across length and time scales far from equilibrium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03418v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Clarke, Jake McGrath, Colin Johnson, Jos\'e Alvarado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chirality, confinement and dimensionality govern re-entrant transitions in active matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03448v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The non-equilibrium dynamics of individual chiral active particles underpin the complex behavior of chiral active matter. Here we present an exact analytical framework, supported by simulations, to characterize the steady states of two-dimensional chiral active Brownian particles and three-dimensional torque-driven counterparts in a harmonic trap. Using a Laplace-transform approach of the Fokker-Planck equation, we derive closed-form expressions for displacement moments and excess kurtosis, providing a precise probe of non-Gaussian statistics. Our analysis reveals three distinct regimes: bimodal active states with off-center peaks, Gaussian-like passive states, and weakly heavy-tailed distributions unique to two dimensions. We show that dimensionality plays a decisive role: in two dimensions, increasing chirality suppresses activity and restores passive behavior, while in three dimensions torque preserves activity along the torque axis, producing anisotropic steady states. These behaviors are captured by simple active length-scale arguments that map the boundaries between passive and active phases. Our results offer concrete experimental signatures - including kurtosis crossovers, off-center peaks, and torque-induced anisotropy - that establish confinement as a powerful tool to probe and control chiral and torque-driven active matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03448v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anweshika Pattanayak, Amir Shee, Debasish Chaudhuri, Abhishek Chaudhuri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Chaos to Coherence: Effects of High-Order Synaptic Correlations on Neural Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.00300v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recurrent Neural Network models have elucidated the interplay between structure and dynamics in biological neural networks, particularly the emergence of irregular and rhythmic activities in cortex. However, most studies have focused on networks with random or simple connectivity structures. Experimental observations find that high-order cortical connectivity patterns affect the temporal patterns of network activity, but a theory that relates such complex structure to network dynamics has yet to be developed. Here, we show that third- and higher-order cyclic correlations in synaptic connectivities greatly impact neuronal dynamics. Specifically, strong cyclic correlations in a network suppress chaotic dynamics and promote oscillatory or fixed activity. This change in dynamics is related to the form of the unstable eigenvalues of the random connectivity matrix. A phase transition from chaotic to fixed or oscillatory activity coincides with the development of a cusp at the leading edge of the eigenvalue support. We also relate the dimensions of activity to the network structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.00300v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nimrod Sherf, Xaq Pitkow, Kre\v{s}imir Josi\'c, Kevin E. Bassler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RinQ: Towards predicting central sites in proteins on current quantum computers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01501v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce RinQ, a hybrid quantum-classical framework for identifying functionally critical residues in proteins by formulating centrality detection as a Quadratic Unconstrained Binary Optimization (QUBO) problem. Protein structures are modeled as residue interaction networks (RINs), and the QUBO formulations are solved using D-Wave's simulated annealing. Applied to a diverse set of proteins, RinQ consistently identifies central residues that closely align with classical benchmarks, demonstrating both the accuracy and robustness of the approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01501v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shah Ishmam Mohtashim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonadiabatic force matching for alchemical free-energy estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14179</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14179v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a method to compute free-energy differences from nonadiabatic alchemical transformations using flow-based generative models. The method, nonadiabatic force matching, hinges on estimating the dissipation along an alchemical switching process in terms of a nonadiabatic force field that can be learned through stochastic flow matching. The learned field can be used in conjunction with short-time trajectory data to evaluate upper and lower bounds on the alchemical free energy that variationally converge to the exact value if the field is optimal. Applying the method to evaluate the alchemical free energy of atomistic models shows that it can substantially reduce the simulation cost of a free-energy estimate at negligible loss of accuracy when compared with thermodynamic integration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14179v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jorge L. Rosa-Ra\'ices, David T. Limmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
