<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.bio-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph</link>
    <description>physics.bio-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 05:02:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Individual particle persistence antagonizes global ordering in populations of nematically-aligning self-propelled particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.07054</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.07054v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The transition from individual to collective motion plays a significant role in many biological processes. While the implications of different types of particle-particle interactions for the emergence of particular modes of collective motion have been well studied, it is unclear how particular types of individual migration patterns influence collective motion. Here, motivated by swarming bacteria Myxococcus xanthus, we investigate the combined effects of the individual pattern of migration and of particle-particle interactions, on the emergence of collective migration. We analyze the effects of a feature of individual pattern migration, the persistence of motion, on the collective properties of the system that emerge from interactions among individuals; in particular, when nematic velocity alignment interaction mediates collective dynamics. We find, through computer simulations and mathematical analysis, that an initially disordered migratory state can become globally ordered by increasing either, the particle-particle alignment interaction strength or the persistence of individual migration. In contrast, we find that persistence prevents the emergence of global nematic order when both persistence and nematic alignment are comparatively high. We conclude that behavior at the population level does not only depend on interactions between individuals but also on the individuals' own intrinsic behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.07054v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.CG</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevE.111.025409</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JM Nava-Sedeno, R Klages, H Hatzikirou, A Deutsch. (2025) Phys. Rev. E 111, 025409</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Josu\'e Manik Nava-Sede\~no, Rainer Klages, Haralampos Hatzikirou, Andreas Deutsch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QuantumDNA: A Python Package for Analyzing Quantum Charge Dynamics in DNA and Exploring Its Biological Relevance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06883v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The study of DNA charge dynamics is a highly interdisciplinary field that bridges physics, chemistry, biology, and medicine, and plays a critical role in processes such as DNA damage detection, protein-DNA interactions, and DNA-based nanotechnology. However, despite significant advances in each of these areas, knowledge often remains inaccessible to other scientific communities, limiting the broader impact of advances across disciplines. To bridge this gap, we present QuantumDNA, an open-source Python package for simulating DNA charge transfer (CT) and excited states using quantum-physical methods. QuantumDNA combines an efficient Linear Combination of Atomic Orbitals (LCAO) approach with tight-binding (TB) models, incorporating open quantum systems techniques to account for environmental effects. This approach allows rapid yet accurate analysis of large DNA ensembles, enabling statistical studies of genetic and epigenetic phenomena. To ensure accessibility, the package features a graphical user interface (GUI), making it suitable for researchers across disciplines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06883v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dennis Herb, Marco Trenti, Marilena Mantela, Constantinos Simserides, Joachim Ankerhold, Mirko Rossini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Flagellar Morphology on Swimming Performance and Directional Control in Microswimmers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.07224</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.07224v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In a fluid environment, flagellated microswimmers propel themselves by rotating their flagella. The morphology of these flagella significantly influences forward speed, swimming efficiency, and directional stability, which are critical for their survival. This study begins by simulating the three-dimensional motion trajectories of microswimmers to analyze their kinematic characteristics. The simulation results demonstrate that microswimmers can actively adjust their forward direction by modifying the orientation of their flagella. We subsequently perform numerical simulations to visualize the flow fields generated by a microswimmer and examine the hydrodynamic interaction between the cell body and the flagella, focusing on their impacts on forward speed and swimming efficiency. Our findings indicate that forward speed and swimming efficiency are closely related to the filament radius, pitch angle, and contour length of the flagella, while the yaw angle of locomotion is determined by the helix radius and contour length of the flagella. Our findings indicate that the pitch angle for maximum forward speed is slightly smaller than that for maximum swimming efficiency, suggest that microswimmers can effectively alternate between states of maximum forward speed and maximum swimming efficiency by fine-tuning their pitch angle and adapting to varying ecological conditions. These morphological characteristics of microswimmers may result from species competition and natural selection. This research establishes an optimized model for microswimmers, providing valuable insights for the design of enhanced microrobots tailored to specific applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.07224v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baopi Liu, Lu Chen, Wenjun Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spontaneous and Induced Oscillations in Confined Epithelia</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02806v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The feedback between mechanical and chemical signals plays a key role in controlling many biological processes and collective cell behavior. Here we focus on the emergence of spatiotemporal density waves in a one-dimensional "cell train." Combining a minimal theoretical model with observations in an in vitro experimental system of MDCK epithelial cells confined to a linear pattern, we examine the spontaneous oscillations driven by the feedback between myosin activation and mechanical deformations and their effect on the response of the tissue to externally applied deformations. We show that the nature and frequency of spontaneous oscillations is controlled by the size of the cell train, with a transition from size-dependent standing waves to intrinsic spontaneous waves at the natural frequency of the tissue. The response to external boundary perturbations exhibit a resonance at this natural frequency, providing a possible venue for inferring the mechanochemical couplings that control the tissue behavior from rheological experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02806v3</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PRXLife.3.013002</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PRX Life 3, 2025, 013002</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Toshi Parmar, Liam P. Dow, Beth L. Pruitt, M. Cristina Marchetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum features of the transport through ion channels in the soft knock-on model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.03497</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.03497v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Ion channels are protein structures that facilitate the selective passage of ions across the membrane cells of living organisms. They are known for their high conductance and high selectivity. The precise mechanism between these two seemingly contradicting features is not yet firmly established. One possible candidate is the quantum coherence. In this work we study the quantum model of the soft knock-on conduction using the Lindblad equation taking into account the non-hermiticity of the model. We show that the model exhibits a regime in which high conductance coexists with high coherence. Our findings second the role of quantum effects in the transport properties of the ion channels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.03497v3</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1478-3975/ad9cde</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Biol. 22 016007 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mateusz Polakowski, Mi{\l}osz Panfil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scattering compensation through Fourier-domain intensity coupling in two-photon microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.15192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.15192v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Light penetration depth in biological tissue is limited by tissue scattering. Correcting scattering becomes particularly challenging in scenarios with limited photon availability and when access to the transmission side of the scattering tissue is not possible. Here, we introduce a new two-photon microscopy system with Fourier-domain intensity coupling for scattering correction (2P-FOCUS). 2P-FOCUS corrects scattering by intensity modulation in the Fourier domain, leveraging the nonlinearity of multiple-beam interference and two-photon excitation, eliminating the need for a guide star, iterative optimization, or measuring transmission or reflection matrices. 2P-FOCUS uses random patterns to probe scattering properties, combined with a single-shot algorithm to rapidly generate the correction mask. 2P-FOCUS can also correct scattering beyond the limitation of the memory effect by automatically customizing correction masks for each subregion in a large field-of-view. We provide several proof-of-principle demonstrations here, including focusing and imaging through a bone sample, and imaging neurons and cerebral blood vessels in the mouse brain ex vivo. 2P-FOCUS significantly enhances two-photon fluorescence signals by several tens of folds compared to cases without scattering correction at the same excitation power. 2P-FOCUS can also correct tissue scattering over a 230x230x500 um\textsuperscript{3} volume, which is beyond the memory effect range. 2P-FOCUS is able to measure, calculate, and correct scattering within a few seconds, effectively delivering more light deep into the scattering tissue. 2P-FOCUS could be broadly adopted for deep tissue imaging owing to its powerful combination of effectiveness, speed, and cost.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.15192v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Zepeda, Yucheng Li, Yi Xue</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
