<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.bio-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph</link>
    <description>physics.bio-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 04:14:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial Patterning and Selection: How the Environment Shapes Molecular Complexity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04547v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Assembly theory predicts that a distinguishing signature of life is its ability to produce complex molecules in abundance, opening new possibilities for life detection. Experimental validation of this approach has so far relied on abiotic controls like meteoritic material, or simple, well-mixed chemical systems. However, decades of research in self-organization have shown that spatial patterning can foster dynamical self-organization. This raises the possibility that systems with nontrivial spatial patterns might promote abiotic formation of molecules with higher than expected assembly indices, potentially leading to false positives in life detection approaches based on assembly theory. To explore this, we used a model of artificial chemistry to investigate how spatial organization can influence the development of molecular assembly indices. Our findings reveal that transport factors, such as diffusion, significantly affect the distribution of chemical species within a system. Additionally, system topology critically impacts the distribution of assembly indices: while it does not enable arbitrary complexity, ordered lattices can shift the threshold for abiotic chemistry upward. Moreover, we demonstrate that diffusion can impede the formation and detection of these high assembly index molecules, bearing important implications for life detection experiments and astrobiological missions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04547v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Champagne-Ruel, Christopher P. Kempes, Cole Mathis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physical interactions enable energy-efficient Turing patterns</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05093v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Patterns are ubiquitous in nature, but how they form is often unclear. Turing developed a seminal theory to explain patterns based on reactions that counteract the equalizing tendency of diffusion. These reactions require continuous energy input since the system otherwise would proceed to equilibrium, but what systems are energy-efficient is currently unclear. To address this question, we introduce a thermodynamically-consistent model of a Turing system. We reveal that repulsive interactions between the stereotypical activator and inhibitor reduce energy requirements significantly. Interestingly, efficient patterns occur for weak activity, albeit at reduced amplitude. Our results suggest that physical interactions might be central in forming natural patterns.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05093v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cathelijne ter Burg, David Zwicker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pose-Free 3D Quantitative Phase Imaging of Flowing Cellular Populations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04848v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: High-throughput 3D quantitative phase imaging (QPI) in flow cytometry enables label-free, volumetric characterization of individual cells by reconstructing their refractive index (RI) distributions from multiple viewing angles during flow through microfluidic channels. However, current imaging methods assume that cells undergo uniform, single-axis rotation, which require their poses to be known at each frame. This assumption restricts applicability to near-spherical cells and prevents accurate imaging of irregularly shaped cells with complex rotations. As a result, only a subset of the cellular population can be analyzed, limiting the ability of flow-based assays to perform robust statistical analysis. We introduce OmniFHT, a pose-free 3D RI reconstruction framework that leverages the Fourier diffraction theorem and implicit neural representations (INRs) for high-throughput flow cytometry tomographic imaging. By jointly optimizing each cell's unknown rotational trajectory and volumetric structure under weak scattering assumptions, OmniFHT supports arbitrary cell geometries and multi-axis rotations. Its continuous representation also allows accurate reconstruction from sparsely sampled projections and restricted angular coverage, producing high-fidelity results with as few as 10 views or only 120 degrees of angular range. OmniFHT enables, for the first time, in situ, high-throughput tomographic imaging of entire flowing cell populations, providing a scalable and unbiased solution for label-free morphometric analysis in flow cytometry platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04848v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enze Ye, Wei Lin, Shaochi Ren, Yakun Liu, Xiaoping Li, Hao Wang, He Sun, Feng Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elasticity and plasticity of epithelial gap closure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05110v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Epiboly, during which a tissue closes around the surface of the egg, pervades animal development. This epithelial gap closure involves cell intercalations at the edge of the gap. Here, inspired by serosa closure in the beetle Tribolium, we study the interplay between these plastic cell rearrangements and the elasticity of the tissue in a minimal continuum model of the closure of a circular gap bounded by a contractile actomyosin cable. We discover two different closure mechanisms at the tissue scale depending on the energy barrier $E_\text{b}$ to and the energy $\Delta E$ released by intercalation: If $E_\text{b}\gg\Delta E$, cells intercalate into the gap to close it. For a fluidised tissue in which $E_\text{b}\ll\Delta E$, however, cells deintercalate from the boundary into the bulk of the tissue, and we reveal an emergent mechanical role of inhomogeneities of the actomyosin cable. Our work thus explains the mechanical role of tissue fluidisation in Tribolium serosa closure and processes of epiboly and wound healing more generally.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05110v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.TO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maryam Setoudeh, Pierre A. Haas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Swarming and Flocking Unified Through Behavioral Imperfections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05140</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05140v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Natural flocks (aligned) and swarms (non-aligned) both exhibit features of criticality, challenging their treatment as two ends of the same phase transition. We present a model for the cohesion of active individuals, who spontaneously self-assemble into a near-critical state, whether aligned or not. In our framework, these individuals move in open space and possess differing self-propelling velocities. The emerging velocity fluctuations, shown to be correlated and scale-invariant, are triggered by inherent noise rooted in individual imperfections. Using the finite-size scaling theory, we show that our system exhibits criticality features observed in groups of midges and starlings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05140v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joao Liz\'arraga, Marcus de Aguiar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local Mechanical Response of Lipid Membranes to Tilt Deformation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05274v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Using molecular dynamics, this study investigates the local elastic properties of transverse shear deformation of lipid membranes. The analysis demonstrates that transverse shear deformation induces anisotropy in the local stress profile of the lipid bilayer, a phenomenon attributed to the Poynting effect. By analyzing the relationship between transverse shear stress and the induced anisotropy, the local transverse shear modulus is determined. From the local transverse shear modulus, several integral elastic parameters can be derived, including the monolayer tilt modulus, tilt-curvature coupling modulus, and curvature-gradient modulus. The calculated tilt modulus values show good agreement with results from an independent analysis of lipid director fluctuations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05274v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantin V. Pinigin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sensing environmental physical interaction to traverse cluttered obstacles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.13062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.13062v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The long-standing, dominant approach to robotic obstacle negotiation relies on mapping environmental geometry to avoid obstacles. However, this approach does not allow for traversal of cluttered obstacles, hindering applications such as search and rescue operations through earthquake rubble and exploration across lunar and Martian rocks. To overcome this challenge, robots must further sense and utilize environmental physical interactions to control themselves to traverse obstacles. Recently, a physics-based approach has been established towards this vision. Self-propelled robots interacting with obstacles results in a potential energy landscape. On this landscape, to traverse obstacles, a robot must escape from certain landscape basins that attract it into failure modes, to reach other basins that lead to successful modes. Thus, sensing the potential energy landscape is crucial. Here, we developed new methods and performed systematic experiments to demonstrate that the potential energy landscape can be estimated by sensing environmental physical interaction. We developed a minimalistic robot capable of sensing obstacle contact forces and torques for systematic experiments over a wide range of parameter space. Surprisingly, although these forces and torques are not fully conservative, they match the potential energy landscape gradients that are conservative forces and torques, enabling an accurate estimation of the potential energy landscape. Additionally, a bio-inspired strategy further enhanced estimation accuracy. Our results provided a foundation for further refining these methods for use in free-locomoting robots. Our study is a key step in establishing a new physics-based approach for robots to traverse clustered obstacles to advance their mobility in complex, real-world environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.13062v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yaqing Wang, Ling Xu, Chen Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic synaptic dynamics under learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13846</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13846v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Learning is based on synaptic plasticity, which affects and is driven by neural activity. Because pre- and postsynaptic spiking activity is shaped by randomness, the synaptic weights follow a stochastic process, requiring a probabilistic framework to capture the noisy synaptic dynamics. We consider a paradigmatic supervised learning example: a presynaptic neural population impinging in a sequence of episodes on a recurrent network of integrate-and-fire neurons through synapses undergoing spike-timing-dependent plasticity (STDP) with additive potentiation and multiplicative depression. We first analytically compute the drift- and diffusion coefficients for a single synapse within a single episode (microscopic dynamics), mapping the true jump process to a Langevin and the associated Fokker-Planck equations. Leveraging new analytical tools, we include spike-time--resolving cross-correlations between pre- and postsynaptic spikes, which corrects substantial deviations seen in standard theories purely based on firing rates. We then apply this microdynamical description to the network setup in which hetero-associations are trained over one-shot episodes into a feed-forward matrix of STDP synapses connecting to neurons of the recurrent network (macroscopic dynamics). By mapping statistically distinct synaptic populations to instances of the single-synapse process above, we self-consistently determine the joint neural and synaptic dynamics and, ultimately, the time course of memory degradation and the memory capacity. We demonstrate that specifically in the relevant case of sparse coding, our theory can quantitatively capture memory capacities which are strongly overestimated if spike-time--resolving cross-correlations are ignored. We conclude with a discussion of the many directions in which our framework can be extended.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13846v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jakob Stubenrauch, Naomi Auer, Richard Kempter, Benjamin Lindner</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
