<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.bio-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph</link>
    <description>physics.bio-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 04:00:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Costs and benefits of phytoplankton motility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14625v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The motility skills of phytoplankton have evolved and persisted over millions of years, primarily in response to factors such as nutrient and light availability, temperature and viscosity gradients, turbulence, and predation pressure. Phytoplankton motility is broadly categorized into swimming and buoyancy regulation. Despite studies in the literature exploring the motility costs and benefits of phytoplankton, there remains a gap in our integrative understanding of direct and indirect energy expenditures, starting from when an organism initiates movement due to any biophysical motive, to when the organism encounters intracellular and environmental challenges. Here we gather all available pieces of this puzzle from literature in biology, physics, and oceanography to paint an overarching picture of our current knowledge. The characterization of sinking and rising behavior as passive motility has resulted in the concept of sinking and rising internal efficiency being overlooked. We define this efficiency based on any energy dissipation associated with processes of mass density adjustment, as exemplified in structures like frustules and vacuoles. We propose that sinking and rising are active motility processes involving non-visible mechanisms, as species demonstrate active and rapid strategies in response to turbulence, predation risk, and gradients of nutrients, light, temperature, and viscosity. Identifying intracellular buoyancy-regulating dissipative processes offers deeper insight into the motility costs relative to the organism's total metabolic rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14625v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.13140/RG.2.2.30118.43844</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Peyman Fahimi, Andrew J. Irwin, Michael Lynch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous-time random walk model for the diffusive motion of helicases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15064v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: DNA helicases are molecular motors that use the energy from ATP hydrolysis to move along DNA, promoting the unwinding or rewinding of the double helix. Here, we use magnetic and optical tweezers to track the motion of three helicases, gp41, RecQ, and RecG, while they unwind or rewind a DNA hairpin. Their activity is characterized by measuring the helicase rate and diffusivity under different force and ATP conditions. We use a Continuous-Time Random Walk framework that allows us to compute the mean helicase displacement and its fluctuations analytically. Fitting the model to the measured helicase velocity and diffusivity allows us to determine the states and transitions in the helicase mechanochemical cycle. A general feature for all helicases is the need to incorporate an off-pathway pausing state to reproduce the data, raising the question of whether pauses play a regulatory role. Finally, we determine the thermodynamic uncertainty factor and the motor efficiency, finding that the rewinding RecG helicase reaches high efficiencies that approach 100$\%$ when operating uphill. Incorporating the analysis of fluctuations allows to better characterize the activity of molecular machines, which represents an advance in the field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15064v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Rodriguez-Franco, M. M. Spiering, F. Ritort, M. Ma\~nosas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elasticity of a Freely Jointed Chain with Quenched Disorder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14817</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14817v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a simple theoretical model, the Freely Jointed Chain with quenched hinges (qFJC), which captures the quenched disorder in the local bending stiffness of the polymer. In this article, we analyze the tensile elasticity of the qFJC in the Gibbs (fixed-force) ensemble. For finite-size systems, we obtain a recurrence relation of the exact free energy, which allows us to calculate the exact force-extension relation numerically for an arbitrary size of the system. In the thermodynamic limit, when $L({\rm contour \;length})\gg L_p({\rm persistence \;length})$, we obtain a framework to deal with quenched disorder in the polymer configuration. This allows us to obtain the response function for the discrete and continuous qFJC in the thermodynamic limit. It turns out that the extension of the continuous qFJC can be cast in a simple form. Furthermore, we have applied our analysis to rod-coil multiblock copolymers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14817v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minsu Yi, Panayotis Benetatos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoding Binding Pathways of Ligands in Prolyl Oligopeptidase</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15139</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15139v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neurodegenerative diseases, such as Alzheimer's and Parkinson's, pose a growing global health burden. Prolyl oligopeptidase (PREP) has emerged as a potential therapeutic target in these diseases. Recent studies have shown that direct interaction between PREP and pathological proteins, such as $\alpha$-synuclein and Tau, influences protein aggregation and neuronal function. While most known PREP inhibitors primarily target its enzymatic functions, a new class of ligands, known as HUPs, specifically modulates protein-protein interactions (PPIs), which are crucial in neurodegenerative diseases. These structurally distinct ligands exhibit diverse binding behaviors, highlighting the importance of understanding their binding pathways. In this study, we analyzed the binding pathways and stability of diverse ligands using molecular dynamics simulations and enhanced sampling techniques. Traditional inhibitors, such as KYP-2047, target the active site between the catalytic domains of PREP and the $\beta$-propeller domain, while HUP ligands bind to alternative regions, such as the hinge site, potentially disrupting non-enzymatic PPIs. We demonstrated that structural variations among ligands lead to distinct binding and unbinding pathways. Free-energy profiles from umbrella sampling revealed key kinetic bottlenecks and differences in pathways. For example, HUP-55 exhibits pathway hopping, characterized by diffuse exploration of binding regions before selecting an exit, while KYP-2047 prefers the central tunnel of the $\beta$-propeller domain even under perturbations. These results suggest that the dynamic interaction between ligands and PREP plays a critical role in their mechanism. The ability of HUPs to interact with multiple binding sites and adapt to PREP's conformational changes may be essential for their PPI-targeting effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15139v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katarzyna Walczewska-Szewc, Jakub Rydzewski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional Brownian motion with mean-density interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15255v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fractional Brownian motion is a Gaussian stochastic process with long-range correlations in time; it has been shown to be a useful model of anomalous diffusion. Here, we investigate the effects of mutual interactions in an ensemble of particles undergoing fractional Brownian motion. Specifically, we introduce a mean-density interaction in which each particle in the ensemble is coupled to the gradient of the total, time-integrated density produced by the entire ensemble. We report the results of extensive computer simulations for the mean-square displacements and the probability densities of particles undergoing one-dimensional fractional Brownian motion with such a mean-density interaction. We find two qualitatively different regimes, depending on the anomalous diffusion exponent $\alpha$ characterizing the fractional Gaussian noise. The motion is governed by the interactions for $\alpha &lt; 4/3$ whereas it is dominated by the fractional Gaussian noise for $\alpha &gt; 4/3$. We develop a scaling theory explaining our findings. We also discuss generalizations to higher space dimensions and nonlinear interactions as well as applications to the growth of strongly stochastic axons (e.g., serotonergic fibers) in vertebrate brains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15255v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan House, Skirmantas Janu\v{s}onis, Ralf Metzler, Thomas Vojta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sedimentation and shear-induced dynamics of spheroids in fluids with spatial viscosity variations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15340</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15340v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A generalized reciprocal theorem is used to relate the force and torque induced on a particle in an inertia-less fluid with small variation in viscosity to integrals involving Stokes flow fields and the spatial dependence of viscosity. These resistivity expressions are analytically evaluated using spheroidal harmonics and then used to obtain the mobility of the spheroid during sedimentation, and in linear flows, of a fluid with linear viscosity stratification. The coupling between the rotational and translational motion induced by stratification rotates the spheroid's centerline, creating a variety of rotational and translational dynamics dependent upon the particle's aspect ratio, $\kappa$, and the component of the stratification unit vector in the gravity direction, $d_g$. Spheroids with $0.55\lessapprox\kappa\lessapprox2.0$ exhibit the largest variety of settling behaviors. Interestingly, this range covers most microplastics and typical microorganisms. One of the modes include a stable orientation dependent only on $\kappa$ and $d_g$, but independent of initial orientation, thus allowing for the potential control of settling angles and sedimentation rates. In a simple shear flow, cross-streamline migration occurs due to the stratification-induced force generated on the particle. Similarly, a particle no longer stays at the stagnation point of a uniaxial extensional flow. While fully analytical results are obtained for spheroids, numerical simulations provide a source of validation. These simulations also provide additional insights into the stratification-induced force- and torque-producing mechanisms through the stratification-induced stress, which is not accessed in the reciprocal theorem-based analytical calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15340v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/jfm.2025.104</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Fluid Mechanics. 2025;1007:A53</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Arjun Sharma, Peter A. Bosler, Rama Govindarajan, Donald L. Koch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AI-driven control of bioelectric signalling for real-time topological reorganization of cells</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13489v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Understanding and manipulating bioelectric signaling could present a new wave of progress in developmental biology, regenerative medicine, and synthetic biology. Bioelectric signals, defined as voltage gradients across cell membranes caused by ionic movements, play a role in regulating crucial processes including cellular differentiation, proliferation, apoptosis, and tissue morphogenesis. Recent studies demonstrate the ability to modulate these signals to achieve controlled tissue regeneration and morphological outcomes in organisms such as planaria and frogs. However, significant knowledge gaps remain, particularly in predicting and controlling the spatial and temporal dynamics of membrane potentials (V_mem), understanding their regulatory roles in tissue and organ development, and exploring their therapeutic potential in diseases. In this work we propose an experiment using Deep Reinforcement Learning (DRL) framework together with lab automation techniques for real-time manipulation of bioelectric signals to guide tissue regeneration and morphogenesis. The proposed framework should interact continuously with biological systems, adapting strategies based on direct biological feedback. Combining DRL with real-time measurement techniques -- such as optogenetics, voltage-sensitive dyes, fluorescent reporters, and advanced microscopy -- could provide a comprehensive platform for precise bioelectric control, leading to improved understanding of bioelectric mechanisms in morphogenesis, quantitative bioelectric models, identification of minimal experimental setups, and advancements in bioelectric modulation techniques relevant to regenerative medicine and cancer therapy. Ultimately, this research aims to utilize bioelectric signaling to develop new biomedical and bioengineering applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13489v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gon\c{c}alo Hora de Carvalho</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
