<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.bio-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph</link>
    <description>physics.bio-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 04:01:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of binding three independent ligands to a single scaffold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.06599v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This note considers a system in which three ligands can independently bind to a scaffold. Such systems arise in diverse applications, including immunotherapy and synthetic biology. It is shown that there are unique steady states in each conservation class, and these are asymptotically stable. The dependency of the steady-state amount of fully bound complex, as a function of total scaffold, is analyzed as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.06599v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eduardo D. Sontag</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving sampling of binding free energy differences between covalently bound ligands in alternate binding pockets using MT-REXEE</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.06720v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The primary limitation for the application of alchemical free energy methods to a wider variety of complex molecular systems in achieving reasonable sampling. Flexible binding complexes often have high free energy barriers, which require prohibitively long simulations to sample sufficiently to obtain reliable free energy estimates. An example of such a system is the FabB--acyl chain complex, which features acyl chain substrates from 4 to 16 carbons in length. Previous experimental evidence supports that there are also at least two accessible binding pockets for the acyl chain bound to FabB. Sampling of both pockets would require prohibitively long MD simulations or the creation of complicated and nonobvious collective variables. With the multiple topology replica exchange of expanded ensemble (MT-REXEE) enhanced sampling approach, we can obtain highly efficient sampling between both pockets by adaptively growing and shrinking the chains in the simulation ensemble, allowing each simulation to visit chain lengths where transitions between the pockets do occur.
  To enable this enhanced sampling for the chain growth problem, we demonstrate a new and improved conformational swapping selection algorithm for MT-REXEE, and validate this algorithm on a previously studied simultaneous calculation of multiple relative binding free energies. Using the new swapping approach gives significantly enhanced sampling even for this simpler problem, as demonstrated by faster convergence of free energy estimates.
  This case study demonstrates the utility of MT-REXEE and its open-source implementation for systems that feature high free energy barriers for a subset of ligands of interest, demonstrating a valuable addition to the existing stable of enhanced sampling methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.06720v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anika Friedman, Michael Shirts</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An RBC-MsUQ Framework for Red Blood Cell Morpho-Mechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.06852v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Characterizing the morpho-mechanical properties of red blood cells (RBCs) is crucial for understanding microvascular transport mechanisms and cellular pathophysiological processes, yet current computational models are constrained by multi-source uncertainties including cross-platform experimental discrepancies and parameter identification stochasticity. We present RBC-MsUQ, a novel multi-stage uncertainty quantification framework tailored for RBCs. It integrates hierarchical Bayesian inference with diverse experimental datasets, establishing prior distributions for RBC parameters via microscopic simulations and literature-derived data. A dynamic annealing technique defines stress-free baselines, while deep neural network surrogates, optimized through sensitivity analysis, achieve sub-10$^{-2}$ prediction errors for efficient simulation approximation. Its two-stage hierarchical inference architecture constrains geometric and shear modulus parameters using stress-free state and stretching data in Stage I and enables full-parameter identification via membrane fluctuation and relaxation tests in Stage II. Applied to healthy and malaria-infected RBCs, the RBC-MsUQ framework produces statistically robust posterior distributions, revealing increased stiffness and viscosity in pathological cells. Quantitative model-experiment validation demonstrates that RBC-MsUQ effectively mitigates uncertainties through cross-platform data fusion, overcoming the critical limitations of existing computational approaches. The RBC-MsUQ framework thus provides a systematic paradigm for studying RBC properties and advancing cellular mechanics and biomedical engineering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.06852v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuo Wang, Lei Ma, Ling Guo, Xuejin Li, Tao Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiscale Microscopy via Automation: Dual Magnification ESEM Imaging by Frame Alternation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.06523v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In Environmental Scanning Electron Microscopy (ESEM) experiments, the acquisition parameters are generally kept constant throughout the collection of a data set. This limits data collection to one data set at a time, and frequent human interaction is required to maintain the image quality. Here, we use a custom-designed automation interface to minimize such supervision and allow for the collection of multiple interlaced data sets simultaneously. The oscillatory modes of an example catalytic system (hydrogen oxidation over Co foil) were employed as a tunable spatiotemporal test case. Using our automation interface, we can implement more advanced acquisition programs into the microscope that allow dual imaging - effectively bridging reaction monitoring between different length scales. By using automation to change the settings of the acquisition after each frame, we are able to capture alternating magnifications of the same process and sample location. Both a low magnification overview of the mesoscopic surface dynamics and a high magnification field of view of the ongoing structural changes of a selected surface motif were acquired. Using such truly correlative data captured with the dual magnification method, cross-scale correlations about catalytic systems including phase information can be established.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.06523v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maurits Vuijk, Johannes Zeininger, Luis Sandoval, G\"unther Rupprechter, Beatriz Roldan Cuenya, Karsten Reuter, Thomas Lunkenbein, Christoph Scheurer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modelling Human Skin Morphology and Simulating Transdermal Transport of 50 Chemicals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07123</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.07123v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: People use various products containing chemical substances that can diffuse through the human skin barrier and reach deeper layers. Therefore, it is essential to understand the transport mechanisms of these chemicals. We developed computable skin meshes for different anatomical regions of young and old skin in two and three dimensions. Numerical methods were applied to simulate the permeation of 50 chemicals. Diffusion coefficients, partition coefficients, and molecular weights were key factors that influenced diffusion and absorption. These findings provide insights into permeation pathways that can support the development and optimization of pharmaceutical formulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.07123v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Milana Tesfamarian, Arne N\"agel, Michael Heisig, Gabriel Wittum</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonequilibrium Work Fluctuations in Force-induced Melting of a Short B-DNA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.07354v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A system of a solvated canonical B-DNA of 12 base pairs with the specified sequence is initially equilibrated in a state of zero external force $f$ acting on it. After equilibration, a switching experiment is performed over the system by pulling one end of the DNA while restraining its other end. The finite time pulling process is performed at a constant rate of the applied force until a maximum value of 400 pN. The associated nonequilibrium work done $(W)$ during this process is determined by numerically integrating the force-extension curve as a function of the applied force. An ensemble of the work values, $P(W)$, is obtained by repeating the pulling experiment a large number of times. We determine the free energy difference $(\Delta F)$ between the equilibrium and force-induced melted states of the DNA by employing the Jarzynski equality. The value of $\Delta F$ is found to be in close agreement with the conventional equilibrium methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.07354v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Siva Nasarayya Chari, Prabal K. Maiti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Computational Optimisation Study of Hip Implant Using Density Mapping Functionally Graded Biomimetic TPMS-based Lattice Structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.08079v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study presents a computational optimisation framework of a hip implant through the development of a functionally graded biomimetic lattice structure, whose design was structurally optimised to limit stress shielding. The optimisation technique was inspired by the inverse of a bone remodelling algorithm, promoting an even stress distribution throughout the design region, by reducing the density and consequently the stiffness, in regions where strain energy was higher than the reference level. The result of the optimisation technique provided a non-uniform graded density distribution field that showed lower density level on the sides of the implant stem, and higher material density around the medial axis of the stem. The optimised material distribution was captured using mapping of a triply periodic minimal surface lattice structure on the implant, which resulted in porous lattice surfaces inside the solid implant. The performance of the porous implant design was evaluated through implementation of a finite element bone remodelling algorithm and comparing the bone response with a femur with fully solid implant model, in terms of stress distribution and mass change. The results of the analysis showed improved bone formation on the bone-implant interface, and enhanced stress transmission to the surrounding bone from the implant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.08079v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahtab Vafaeefar, Conall Quinn, Kevin M. Moerman, Ted J. Vaughan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying nonequilibrium degrees of freedom in high-dimensional stochastic systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08247</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.08247v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Any coarse-grained description of a nonequilibrium system should faithfully represent its latent irreversible degrees of freedom. However, standard dimensionality reduction methods typically prioritize accurate reconstruction over physical relevance. Here, we introduce a model-free approach to identify irreversible degrees of freedom in stochastic systems that are in a nonequilibrium steady state. Our method leverages the insight that a black-box classifier, trained to differentiate between forward and time-reversed trajectories, implicitly estimates the local entropy production rate. By parameterizing this classifier as a quadratic form of learned state representations, we obtain nonlinear embeddings of high-dimensional state-space dynamics, which we term Latent Embeddings of Nonequilibrium Systems (LENS). LENS effectively identifies low-dimensional irreversible flows and provides a scalable, learning-based strategy for estimating entropy production rates directly from high-dimensional time series data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.08247v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Catherine Ji, Ravin Raj, Benjamin Eysenbach, Gautam Reddy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compound Mutations in the Abl1 Kinase Cause Inhibitor Resistance by Shifting DFG Flip Mechanisms and Relative State Populations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14968v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The intrinsic dynamics of most proteins are central to their function. Protein tyrosine kinases such as Abl1 undergo significant conformational changes that modulate their activity in response to different stimuli. These conformational changes constitute a conserved mechanism for self-regulation that dramatically impacts kinases' affinities for inhibitors. Few studies have attempted to extensively sample the pathways and elucidate the mechanisms that underlie kinase inactivation. Seeking to bridge this knowledge gap, we present a thorough analysis of the ``DFG flip'' inactivation pathway in Abl1 kinase. By leveraging the power of the Weighted Ensemble methodology, which accelerates sampling without the use of biasing forces, we have comprehensively simulated DFG flip events in Abl1 and its inhibitor-resistant variants, revealing a rugged landscape punctuated by potentially druggable intermediate states. Through our strategy, we successfully simulated dozens of uncorrelated DFG flip events distributed along two principal pathways, identified the molecular mechanisms that govern them, and measured their relative probabilities. Further, we show that the compound Glu255Lys/Val Thr315Ile Abl1 variants owe their inhibitor resistance phenotype to an increase in the free energy barrier associated with completing the DFG flip. This barrier stabilizes Abl1 variants in conformations that can lead to loss of binding for Type-II inhibitors such as Imatinib or Ponatinib. Finally, we contrast our Abl1 observations with the relative state distributions and propensity for undergoing a DFG flip of evolutionarily-related protein tyrosine kinases with diverging Type-II inhibitor binding affinities. Altogether, we expect that our work will be of significant importance for protein tyrosine kinase inhibitor discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14968v2</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.7554/eLife.104519.1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>eLife14:RP104519 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel Monteiro da Silva, Kyle Lam, David C. Dalgarno, Brenda M. Rubenstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Costs and benefits of phytoplankton motility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14625v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The motility skills of phytoplankton have evolved and persisted over millions of years, primarily in response to factors such as nutrient and light availability, temperature and viscosity gradients, turbulence, and predation pressure. Phytoplankton motility is broadly categorized into swimming and buoyancy regulation. Despite studies in the literature exploring the motility costs and benefits of phytoplankton, there remains a gap in our integrative understanding of direct and indirect energy expenditures, starting from when an organism initiates movement due to any biophysical motive, to when the organism encounters intracellular and environmental challenges. Here we gather available pieces of this puzzle from literature in biology, physics, and oceanography to paint an overarching picture of our current knowledge. The characterization of sinking and rising behavior as passive motility has resulted in the concept of sinking and rising internal efficiency being overlooked. We define this efficiency based on any energy dissipation associated with processes of mass density adjustment, as exemplified in structures like frustules and vacuoles. We propose that sinking and rising are active motility processes involving non-visible mechanisms, as species demonstrate active and rapid strategies in response to turbulence, predation risk, and gradients of nutrients, light, temperature, and viscosity. Identifying intracellular buoyancy-regulating dissipative processes offers deeper insight into the motility costs relative to the organism's total metabolic rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14625v2</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.13140/RG.2.2.30118.43844</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Peyman Fahimi, Andrew J. Irwin, Michael Lynch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Residual U-Net for accurate and efficient prediction of hemodynamics in two-dimensional asymmetric stenosis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.05778v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study presents residual U-Net (U-ResNet), a deep learning surrogate model for predicting steady hemodynamic fields in two-dimensional asymmetric stenotic channels at Reynolds numbers ranging from 200 to 800. By integrating residual connections with multi-scale feature extraction, U-ResNet achieves exceptional accuracy while significantly reducing computational costs compared to computational fluid dynamics (CFD) approaches. Comprehensive evaluation against U-Net, Fourier Neural Operator (FNO), and U-Net enhanced Fourier Neural Operator (UFNO) demonstrates U-ResNet superior performance in capturing sharp hemodynamic gradients and complex flow features. For pressure prediction, U-ResNet achieves a normalized mean absolute error (NMAE) of 1.10%. Similarly, the performance of U-ResNet for wall shear stress (NMAE: 0.56%), velocity (NMAE: 1.06%), and vorticity (NMAE: 0.69%) consistently surpasses alternative architectures. Notably, U-ResNet demonstrates robust generalization to interpolated Reynolds numbers without retraining - a capability rarely achieved in existing models. From a computational perspective, U-ResNet delivers a 180-fold acceleration over CFD, reducing simulation time from approximately 30 minutes to 10 seconds per case. The model with non-dimensional formulation ensures scalability across vessel sizes and anatomical locations, enhancing its applicability to diverse clinical scenarios. These advances position U-ResNet as a promising auxiliary tool to complement CFD simulations for real-time clinical decision support, treatment planning, and medical device optimization. Future work will focus on extending the framework to three-dimensional geometries and integrating it with patient-specific data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.05778v4</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0274672</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physics of Fluids, 37(7):071925, 07 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xintong Zou, Suiyang Tong, Wenhui Peng, Qiuxiang Huang, Jianchun Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hemodynamic Markers: CFD-Based Prediction of Cerebral Aneurysm Rupture Risk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10524v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study investigates the influence of aneurysm evolution on hemodynamic characteristics within the sac region. Using computational fluid dynamics (CFD), blood flow through the parent vessel and aneurysm sac was analyzed to assess the impact on wall shear stress (WSS), time-averaged wall shear stress (TAWSS), and the oscillatory shear index (OSI), key indicators of rupture risk. Additionally, Relative Residence Time (RRT) and Endothelial Cell Activation Potential (ECAP) were examined to provide a broader understanding of the aneurysm's hemodynamic environment. Six distinct cerebral aneurysm (CA) models, all from individuals of the same gender, were selected to minimize gender-related variability.
  Results showed that unruptured cases exhibited higher WSS and TAWSS, along with lower OSI and RRT values patterns consistent with stable flow conditions supporting vascular integrity. In contrast, ruptured cases had lower WSS and TAWSS, coupled with elevated OSI and RRT, suggesting disturbed and oscillatory flow commonly linked to aneurysm wall weakening. ECAP was also higher in ruptured cases, indicating increased endothelial activation under unstable flow. Notably, areas with the highest OSI and RRT often aligned with vortex centers, reinforcing the association between disturbed flow and aneurysm instability.
  These findings highlight the value of combining multiple hemodynamic parameters for rupture risk assessment. Including RRT and ECAP provides deeper insight into flow endothelium-interactions, offering a stronger basis for evaluating aneurysm stability and guiding treatment decisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10524v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reza Bozorgpour, Jacob R. Rammer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Odd elasticity in disordered chiral active materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.04468v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Chiral active materials are abundant in nature, including the cytoskeleton with attached motor proteins, rotary clusters of bacteria flagella, and self-spinning starfish embryos. These materials break both time reversal and mirror-image (parity) symmetries due to injection of torques at the microscale. Recently, it was found that chiral active materials may show a new type of elastic response termed `odd' elasticity. Currently, odd elasticity is understood microscopically only in ordered structures, e.g., lattice designs of metamaterials. It still remains to explore how odd elasticity can emerge in natural or biological systems, which are usually disordered. To address this, we propose a minimal generic model for disordered `odd solids', using micropolar (Cosserat) elasticity in the presence of local active torques. We find that odd elasticity naturally emerges as a nonlinear effect of internal particle rotations. Exploring the viscoelasticity of this solid, when immersed in active self-spinning solvent (`odd fluid'), we discover both dynamically unstable regions and regions in which bulk waves can propagate even in an overdamped solid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.04468v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng-Tai Lee, Tom C. Lubensky, Tomer Markovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
