<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.bio-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph</link>
    <description>physics.bio-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 05:03:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The structure of the Maxwell spot centroid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.11194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.11194v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The dark entoptic Maxwell spot centroids seen through a blue filter, which coincide with the blue cone-free areas centered on the foveas, are shown to exhibit a structure. When observing through the green part of a blue-green exchange filter in a foveascope, after a fixation through the blue part, a small orange disc is seen around the centre of the pale green memory afterimage corresponding to the blue cone-free area. Using artificial pupils with different diameters, we show that this small circular pattern corresponds to the Airy disc due to the Fraunhofer diffraction through the pupil. Typically, for an eye with a 3 millimeter diameter pupil, the Airy disc exhibits a diameter of about 8 micrometers at the centre of the usual 100-150 micrometer Maxwell centroid. Fixation tests show that the towering central maximum of the Airy pattern irradiance corresponds to the preferred locus of the fixation of the eye near the centre of the blue cone-free area of the fovea. The locus of fixation in human vision thus appears to be located in the only area of the fovea where the large chromatic dispersion is cancelled, optimising the eye acuity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.11194v2</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Albert Le Floch, Guy Ropars</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error Thresholds in Presence of Epistatic Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11944v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Models for viral populations with high replication error rates (such as RNA viruses) rely on the quasispecies concept, in which mutational pressure beyond the so-called "Error Threshold" leads to a loss of essential genetic information and population collapse, an effect known as the "Error Catastrophe". We explain how crossing this threshold, as a result of increasing mutation rates, can be understood as a second order phase transition, even in the presence of lethal mutations. In particular, we show that, in fitness landscapes with a single peak, this collapse is equivalent to a ferro-paramagnetic transition, where the back-mutation rate plays the role of the external magnetic field. We then generalize this framework to rugged fitness landscapes, like the ones that arise from epistatic interactions, and provide numerical evidence that there is a transition from a high average fitness regime to a low average fitness one, similarly to single-peaked landscapes. The onset of the transition is heralded by a sudden change in the susceptibility to variations in the mutation rate. We use insight from Replica Symmetry Breaking mechanisms in spin glasses, in particular by considering the fluctuations of the genotype similarity distribution as the order parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11944v4</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevE.110.054412</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>David A. Herrera-Mart\'i</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $(2+\delta)$-dimensional theory of the electromechanics of lipid membranes: II. Balance laws</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.03863</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.03863v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This article is the second of a three-part series that derives a self-consistent theoretical framework of the electromechanics of arbitrarily curved lipid membranes. Existing continuum theories commonly treat lipid membranes as strictly two-dimensional surfaces. While this approach is successful in many purely mechanical applications, strict surface theories fail to capture the electric potential drop across lipid membranes, the effects of surface charges, and electric fields within the membrane. Consequently, they do not accurately resolve Maxwell stresses in the interior of the membrane and its proximity. Furthermore, surface theories are generally unable to capture the effects of distinct velocities and tractions at the interfaces between lipid membranes and their surrounding bulk fluids. To address these shortcomings, we apply a recently proposed dimension reduction method to the three-dimensional, electromechanical balance laws. This approach allows us to derive an effective surface theory without taking the limit of vanishing thickness, thus incorporating effects arising from the finite thickness of lipid membranes. We refer to this effective surface theory as $(2 + \delta)$-dimensional, where $\delta$ indicates the thickness. The resulting $(2 + \delta)$-dimensional equations of motion satisfy velocity and traction continuity conditions at the membrane-bulk interfaces, capture the effects of Maxwell stresses, and can directly incorporate three-dimensional constitutive models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.03863v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yannick A. D. Omar, Zachary G. Lipel, Kranthi K. Mandadapu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predictability of viral load dynamics in the early phases of SARS-CoV-2 through a model-based approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03158v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A pipeline to evaluate the evolution of viral dynamics based on a new model-driven approach has been developed in the present study. The proposed methods exploit real data and the multiscale structure of the infection dynamics to provide robust predictions of the epidemic dynamics. We focus on viral load kinetics whose dynamical features are typically available in the symptomatic stage of the infection. Hence, the epidemiological evolution is obtained by relying on a compartmental approach characterized by a varying infection rate to estimate early-stage viral load dynamics, of which few data are available. We test the proposed approach with real data of SARS-CoV-2 viral load kinetics collected from patients living in an Italian province. The considered database refers to early-phase infections, whose viral load kinetics have not been affected by the mass vaccination policies in Italy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03158v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Bondesan, Antonio Piralla, Elena Ballante, Antonino Maria Guglielmo Pitrolo, Silvia Figini, Fausto Baldanti, Mattia Zanella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $(2+\delta)$-dimensional theory of the electromechanics of lipid membranes: III. Constitutive models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11612v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This article concludes a three-part series developing a self-consistent theoretical framework of the electromechanics of lipid membranes at the continuum scale. Owing to their small thickness, lipid membranes are commonly modeled as two-dimensional surfaces. However, this approach breaks down when considering their electromechanical behavior as it requires accounting for their thickness. To address this, we developed a dimension reduction procedure in part 1 to derive effective surface theories explicitly capturing the thickness of lipid membranes. We applied this method to dimensionally reduce Gauss' law and the electromechanical balance laws and referred to the resulting theory as $(2+\delta)$-dimensional, where $\delta$ indicates the membrane thickness. However, the $(2+\delta)$-dimensional balance laws derived in part 2 are general, and specific material models are required to specialize them to lipid membranes. In this work, we devise appropriate three-dimensional constitutive models that capture the in-plane fluid and out-of-plane elastic behavior of lipid membranes. The viscous behavior is recovered by a three-dimensional Newtonian fluid model, leading to the same viscous stresses as strictly two-dimensional models. The elastic resistance to bending is recovered by imposing a free energy penalty on local volume changes. While this gives rise to the characteristic bending resistance of lipid membranes, it differs in its higher-order curvature terms from the Canham-Helfrich-Evans theory. Furthermore, motivated by the small mid-surface stretch of lipid membranes, we introduce reactive stresses that enforce mid-surface incompressibility, resulting in an effective surface tension. Finally, we use the constitutive and reactive stresses to derive the equations of motion describing the electromechanics of lipid membranes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11612v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yannick A. D. Omar, Zachary G. Lipel, Kranthi K. Mandadapu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
