<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.bio-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph</link>
    <description>physics.bio-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.bio-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 02:52:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Persistent Brownian Motions in Confluent Tissues</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.21922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.21922v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Biological tissues are active materials whose non-equilibrium dynamics emerge from distinct cellular force-generating mechanisms. Using a two-dimensional active foam model, we compare the effects of traction forces and junctional tension fluctuations on confluent tissue dynamics. While these two modes of activity produce qualitatively different cell shapes, rearrangement statistics, and spatiotemporal correlations in fluid states, we find that the long-time cellular motion universally converges to persistent Brownian dynamics. This universal feature contrasts with the non-universal correlations between cell geometry, rearrangement rate, and fluidity, which depend sensitively on the underlying modes of active force. Our results demonstrate that persistent Brownian motion provides a minimal framework for describing tissue dynamics, while distinct active forces leave identifiable structural and dynamical signatures, thereby enabling inference of the dominant active force in fluid state tissues.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.21922v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>q-bio.TO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Rizzi, Sangwoo Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From quantitative modeling of fluorescence experiments on biomolecules to the prediction of spectroscopic dye properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.21931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.21931v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fluorescence spectroscopy and modeling provide powerful means to characterize biomacromolecular structures, dynamics, and interactions. F\"orster resonance energy transfer serves as a key technique for this due to its nanometer-scale distance sensitivity. Quantitative interpretation of fluorescence data relies on models that link molecular structure to observable spectroscopic quantities and vice versa. Integrative modelling frameworks combine fluorescence observables with complementary structural information to infer molecular structures and conformational ensembles. This review outlines conceptual components of fluorescence-based modeling, discusses dye representations, and highlights advances toward refined models enabling quantitative structural analysis. Finally, we discuss the prediction of spectroscopic properties of dyes based on biomolecular structures and fluorescence assay design beyond traditional FRET applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.21931v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas-Otavio Peulen, Daria Maksutova, Thorben Cordes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-avoiding tethered surfaces are always flat</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.21714</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.21714v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The scaling behavior of fully flexible elastic tethered surfaces has been debated for decades. Some theories predict that self-avoiding surfaces would crumple in the absence of bending rigidity, while most simulations suggested that they would remain flat. Recent simulations on ideal membranes with lattice perforations suggest that systematically removing surface area from a membrane may provide an alternative way to crumpling self-avoiding surfaces. We perform extensive numerical simulations of two models of fully flexible elastic tethered surfaces in which self-avoidance can be systematically and continuously tuned to the ideal limit. We show that in the thermodynamic limit, these surfaces remain flat with a size exponent $\nu=1$ for any finite degree of self-avoidance, with or without membrane perforations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.21714v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. D. Chen, M. C. Gandikota, M. J. Kim, A. Cacciuto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limits of optimal decoding under synaptic coarse-tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.21758</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.21758v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Sensory information propagates through successive processing stages in the brain, where synaptic weight patterns between stations determine how downstream neurons decode information from upstream populations. Although optimized synaptic connectivity can enhance information transmission, it requires precise weight tuning. Recent evidence depicting substantial synaptic volatility raises two fundamental questions: How does coarse-tuning of synaptic connectivity affect information transmission? What strategies could the nervous system employ to maintain reliable communication despite synaptic fluctuations? We addressed these questions by analyzing the signal-to-noise ratio ($SNR$) for binary stimulus discrimination under two decoding schemes: a naive population average and an optimized linear decoder. For the naive decoder, we found that $SNR$ remains largely insensitive to synaptic imprecision, since performance is already limited by correlated noise in neuronal responses. For the optimal decoder, we identified three distinct regimes. Under weak coarse-tuning, $SNR^2$ scales linearly with population size $N$. Under moderate coarse-tuning, scaling becomes sublinear. Under strong coarse-tuning, the regime most consistent with observed neuronal heterogeneity, $SNR$ saturates and can not be improved by recruiting larger populations. This limitation persists even when incorporating feedforward or recurrent network architectures. These findings suggest that in the biologically relevant regime of strong coarse-tuning, naive and optimal decoders can achieve qualitatively similar performance. The analysis shows that effective readout under synaptic volatility is constrained to an invariant low-dimensional manifold aligned with the naive decoder, potentially pointing to a fundamental principle for robust neural computation in the face of ongoing synaptic remodeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.21758v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ori Hendler, Ronen Segev, Maoz Shamir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral entropy of the discrete Hasimoto effective potential exposes sub-residue geometric transitions in protein secondary structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.21787</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.21787v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Characterizing the geometric boundaries of protein secondary structures is fundamental to understanding macromolecular folding. By applying the discrete Hasimoto map to translate backbone geometry into a one-dimensional discrete nonlinear Schr\"{o}dinger potential $V_{\mathrm{re}}[n]$, we establish a frequency-domain framework for protein conformations. Short-time Fourier transform analysis across 320,453 residues from 1,986 non-redundant proteins defines a local spectral entropy $H_{\mathrm{spec}}$ that consistently orders structural states. Helical segments emerge as narrow-band low-entropy regimes dominated by zero-frequency components, whereas coils manifest as broadband noise. We demonstrate that boundaries separating these states exhibit step-like sharpness characteristic of a first-order-like geometric transition with a sub-residue median width of 0.145 residues. This abrupt kinematic transition provides a spatial counterpart to the cooperative Zimm--Bragg thermodynamic model of helix nucleation. The extreme spatial narrowness exposes an intrinsic limitation governed by the Gabor uncertainty principle, explaining why the pointwise integrability residual $E[n]$ acts as an effective high-pass filter for boundary detection. Guided by this limit we introduce a dual-probe approach combining the high-pass residual for local torsion discontinuities with a low-frequency energy ratio $R_{\mathrm{LF}}$ measuring the DC-dominated flatness of helical interiors. Unifying these complementary signals improves the detection area under the curve from 0.783 to 0.815. Because high-entropy broadband regions coincide with the flexible loops and hinges implicated in allostery, the spectral entropy of the Hasimoto potential may serve as a sequence-agnostic geometric proxy for mapping functional dynamics from backbone coordinates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.21787v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiquan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hydrodynamics of Dense Active Fluids: Turbulence-Like States and the Role of Advected Activity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.22044</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.22044v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Dense suspensions of self-propelled bacteria and related active fluids exhibit spontaneous flow generation, vortex formation, and spatiotemporally chaotic dynamics despite operating at vanishingly small Reynolds numbers. These phenomena, commonly referred to as active turbulence, display striking visual and statistical similarities to classical inertial turbulence while arising from fundamentally different nonequilibrium mechanisms. In this article, we present a combined review and theoretical study of hydrodynamic models for dense active fluids, with particular emphasis on bacterial suspensions described by the Toner--Tu--Swift--Hohenberg (TTSH) framework. We review key experimental and theoretical developments underlying the analogy between active and inertial turbulence, highlighting the emergence of multiple dynamical regimes and the conditions under which universal spectral and intermittent behavior arises in homogeneous systems. Moving beyond the conventional assumption of spatially uniform activity, we introduce a minimal model in which the activity field is heterogeneous and dynamically advected by the flow it generates. Thus treating activity as a spatiotemporally evolving field coupled to the TTSH dynamics, we investigate how advection and diffusion lead to sharp activity fronts, confinement of turbulent motion, and complex interfacial morphologies. Our numerical results demonstrate that spatial variations in activity can induce transient coexistence of distinct spectral regimes and that universality in active turbulence is inherently local and time-dependent in heterogeneous systems. These findings underscore the importance of treating activity as a dynamical field in its own right and provide a framework for studying active turbulence in more realistic, spatially structured biological and synthetic active matter systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.22044v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sandip Sahoo, Siddhartha Mukherjee, Samriddhi Sankar Ray</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local stabilizability implies global controllability in catalytic reaction systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06834v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Controlling complex reaction networks is a fundamental challenge in the fields of physics, biology, and systems engineering. Here, we prove a general principle for catalytic reaction systems with kinetics where the reaction order and the stoichiometric coefficient match: the local stabilizability of a given state implies global controllability within its stoichiometric compatibility class. In other words, if a target state can be maintained against small perturbations, the system can be controlled from any initial condition to that state. This result highlights a tight link between the local and global dynamics of nonlinear chemical reaction systems, providing a mathematical criterion for global reachability that is often elusive in high-dimensional systems. The finding illuminate the robustness of biochemical systems and offers a way to control catalytic reaction systems in a generic framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06834v3</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.SC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yusuke Himeoka, Shuhei A. Horiguchi, Naoto Shiraishi, Fangzhou Xiao, Tetsuya J. Kobayashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hermitian and non-Hermitian topology in active matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16143v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Self-propulsion is a quintessential aspect of biological systems, which can induce nonequilibrium phenomena that have no counterparts in passive systems. Motivated by biophysical interest together with recent advances in experimental techniques, active matter has been a rapidly developing field in physics. Meanwhile, over the past few decades, topology has played a crucial role to understand certain robust properties appearing in condensed matter systems. For instance, the nontrivial topology of band structures leads to the notion of topological insulators, where one can find robust gapless edge modes protected by the bulk band topology. We here review recent progress in an interdisciplinary area of research at the intersection of these two fields. Specifically, we give brief introductions to active matter and band topology in Hermitian systems, and then explain how the notion of band topology can be extended to nonequilibrium (and thus non-Hermitian) systems including active matter. We review recent studies that have demonstrated the intimate connections between active matter and topological materials, where exotic topological phenomena that are unfeasible in passive systems have been found. A possible extension of the band topology to nonlinear systems is also briefly discussed. Active matter can thus provide an ideal playground to explore topological phenomena in qualitatively new realms beyond conservative linear systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16143v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6633/ae2ee5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Rep. Prog. Phys. 89, 016501 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kazuki Sone, Kazuki Yokomizo, Kyogo Kawaguchi, Yuto Ashida</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
