<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO</link>
    <description>astro-ph.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 04:00:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological and Astrophysical Parameter Inference from Stacked Galaxy Cluster Profiles Using CAMELS-zoomGZ</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10942</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10942v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a study on the inference of cosmological and astrophysical parameters using stacked galaxy cluster profiles. Utilizing the CAMELS-zoomGZ simulations, we explore how various cluster properties--such as X-ray surface brightness, gas density, temperature, metallicity, and Compton-y profiles--can be used to predict parameters within the 28-dimensional parameter space of the IllustrisTNG model. Through neural networks, we achieve a high correlation coefficient of 0.97 or above for all cosmological parameters, including $\Omega_{\rm m}$, $H_0$, and $\sigma_8$, and over 0.90 for the remaining astrophysical parameters, showcasing the effectiveness of these profiles for parameter inference. We investigate the impact of different radial cuts, with bins ranging from $0.1R_{200c}$ to $0.7R_{200c}$, to simulate current observational constraints. Additionally, we perform a noise sensitivity analysis, adding up to 40\% Gaussian noise (corresponding to signal-to-noise ratios as low as 2.5), revealing that key parameters such as $\Omega_{\rm m}$, $H_0$, and the IMF slope remain robust even under extreme noise conditions. We also compare the performance of full radial profiles against integrated quantities, finding that profiles generally lead to more accurate parameter inferences. Our results demonstrate that stacked galaxy cluster profiles contain crucial information on both astrophysical processes within groups and clusters and the underlying cosmology of the universe. This underscores their significance for interpreting the complex data expected from next-generation surveys and reveals, for the first time, their potential as a powerful tool for parameter inference.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10942v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elena Hern\'andez-Mart\'inez, Shy Genel, Francisco Villaescusa-Navarro, Ulrich P. Steinwandel, Max E. Lee, Erwin T. Lau, David N. Spergel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpreting Dark Energy Data Away from $\Lambda$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10981v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dark energy away from a cosmological constant $\Lambda$ -- like early universe inflation that ends -- can be understood in terms of well defined physical behaviors. These guide dark energy into thawing or freezing classes, with $w_0$--$w_a$ arising as a physical calibration of the phase space. Other regions of phase space -- zones of avoidance -- require violation of some basic principle. We explore these cases, drawing a direct analogy with how nonGaussianity in inflation can add physics beyond standard dynamics. We examine the physics implications if the best fit of current data is taken to be truth, outlining four properties, and investigate the reality of phantom crossing $w=-1$, finding it significantly favored.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10981v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric V. Linder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectrum of high-frequency gravitational waves from graviton bremsstrahlung by the decay of inflaton: case with polynomial potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11175v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the generation of high-frequency gravitational waves (GWs) through graviton bremsstrahlung during the decay of inflaton in the post-inflationary universe, focusing on scenarios with a polynomial inflaton potential. Two main reheating channels are considered: decays into bosons (spin 0) and fermions (spin $\frac{1}{2}$). We compute the resulting GW spectra from three-body decays, where the inflaton decays into a pair of daughter particles and a graviton. We numerically compute the GW spectra for various polynomial exponents by employing two distinct approaches: one treating the inflaton as a collection of rest particles and the other treating it as a coherently oscillating classical field. In the former approach, only gravitons with energies below half the inflaton mass are produced, while the latter allows for the production of gravitons with arbitrarily high energies when the potential exponent is 4 or greater. This difference arises because the inflaton's oscillations are no longer described by a single harmonic mode but instead consist of infinitely many harmonic modes with different frequencies. As a result, the GW spectrum exhibits multiple peaks, with these peaks being less pronounced for higher powers of the potential. We also examine the dependence of the GW spectrum on the coupling constant between the inflaton and daughter particles. Our findings suggest that future GW detectors targeting GWs in the GHz band, such as resonant cavities, may have the capability to detect these signals, offering potential insights into the reheating phase of the early universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11175v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiheng Jiang, Teruaki Suyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Tracking Tapered Gridded Estimator for the 21-cm power spectrum from MWA drift scan observations II: The Missing Frequency Channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11380v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Missing frequency channels pose a problem for estimating $P(k_\perp,k_\parallel)$ the redshifted 21-cm power spectrum (PS) from radio-interferometric visibility data. This is particularly severe for the Murchison Widefield Array (MWA), which has a periodic pattern of missing channels that introduce spikes along $k_\parallel$. The Tracking Tapered Gridded Estimator (TTGE) overcomes this by first correlating the visibilities in the frequency domain to estimate the multi-frequency angular power spectrum (MAPS) $C_\ell(\Delta\nu)$ that has no missing frequency separation $\Delta\nu$. We perform a Fourier transform along $\Delta\nu$ to estimate $P(k_\perp,k_\parallel)$. Considering our earlier work, simulations demonstrate that the TTGE can estimate $P(k_\perp,k_\parallel)$ without any artifacts due to the missing channels. However, the spikes were still found to persist for the actual data, which is foreground-dominated. The current work presents a detailed investigation considering both simulations and actual data. We find that the spikes arise due to a combination of the missing channels and the strong spectral dependence of the foregrounds. Based on this, we propose and demonstrate a technique to mitigate the spikes. Applying this, we find the values of $P(k_\perp,k_\parallel)$ in the region $0.004 \leq k_\perp \leq 0.048\,{\rm Mpc^{-1}}$ and $k_\parallel &gt; 0.35 \,{\rm Mpc^{-1}}$ to be consistent with zero within the expected statistical fluctuations. We obtain the $2\sigma$ upper limit of $\Delta_{\rm UL}^2(k)=(918.17)^2\,{\rm mK^2}$ at $k=0.404\,{\rm Mpc^{-1}}$ for the mean squared brightness temperature fluctuations of the $z=8.2$ epoch of reionization (EoR) 21-cm signal. This upper limit is from just $\sim 17$ minutes of observation for a single pointing direction. We expect tighter constraints when we combine all $162$ different pointing directions of the drift scan observation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11380v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Khandakar Md Asif Elahi, Somnath Bharadwaj, Suman Chatterjee, Shouvik Sarkar, Samir Choudhuri, Shiv Sethi, Akash Kumar Patwa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the effect of different cosmologies on the Epoch of Reionization 21-cm signal with POLAR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11620v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A detection of the 21-cm signal power spectrum from the Epoch of Reionization is imminent, thanks to consistent advancements from telescopes such as LOFAR, MWA, and HERA, along with the development of SKA. In light of this progress, it is crucial to expand the parameter space of simulations used to infer astrophysical properties from this signal. In this work, we explore the role of cosmological parameters such as the Hubble constant $H_0$ and the matter clustering amplitude $\sigma_8$, whose values as provided by measurements at different redshifts are in tension. We run $N$-body simulations using GADGET-4, and post-process them with the reionization simulation code POLAR, that uses L-GALAXIES to include galaxy formation and evolution properties and GRIZZLY to execute 1-D radiative transfer of ionizing photons in the intergalactic medium (IGM). We compare our results with the latest JWST observations and explore which astrophysical properties for different cosmologies are necessary to match the observed UV luminosity functions at redshifts $z = 10$ and 9. Additionally, we explore the impact of these parameters on the observed 21-cm signal power spectrum, focusing on the redshifts within the range of LOFAR 21-cm signal observations ($z \approx 8.5-10$). Despite differences in cosmological and astrophysical parameters, the 21-cm power spectrum at these redshifts agrees with presently observed upper limits. This suggests the need for broader physical parameter spaces for inference modeling to account for all models that agree with observations. However, we also propose stronger constraining power by using a combination of galactic and IGM observables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11620v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anshuman Acharya, Qing-bo Ma, Sambit K. Giri, Benedetta Ciardi, Raghunath Ghara, Garrelt Mellema, Saleem Zaroubi, Ian Hothi, Ilian T. Iliev, L\'eon V. E. Koopmans, Michele Bianco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploiting the high-resolution NIKA2 data to study the intracluster medium and dynamical state of ACT-CL J0240.0+0116</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11668v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Having a detailed knowledge of the intracluster medium (ICM) to infer the exact cluster physics such as the cluster dynamical state is crucial for cluster-based cosmological studies. This knowledge limits the accuracy and precision of mass estimation, a key parameter for such studies. In this paper, we conduct an in-depth analysis of cluster ACT-CL J0240.0+0116 using a multi-wavelength approach, with a primary focus on high angular resolution Sunyaev-Zeldovich (SZ) thermal component observations obtained under the NIKA2 Sunyaev-Zeldovich Large Programme (LPSZ). We create composite images using NIKA2, X-ray, and optical galaxy number density maps. The results reveal distinct signs of disturbance within the cluster with the distributions of gas and member galaxies that do not overlap. We also find suggestions of an inflow of matter onto the cluster from the southwestern direction. Ultimately, we classify the cluster as disturbed, using morphological indicators derived from its SZ, X-ray, and optical image. The cluster SZ signal is also contaminated by a strong central point source. We adopt different approaches to handling this contaminant and find the estimates of our pressure and hydrostatic mass profiles robust to the point source mitigation model. The cluster hydrostatic mass is estimated at $4.25^{+0.50}_{-0.45\, } \times 10^{14} \,\mathrm{M}_{\odot}$ for the case where the point source was masked. These values are consistent with the mass estimated using only X-ray data and with those from previous SZ studies of the Atacama cosmology telescope (ACT) survey, with improved precision on the mass estimate. Our findings strongly suggest that ACT-CL J0240.0+0116 is a disturbed cluster system, and the detailed observations and derived values serve as a compelling case study for the capabilities of the LPSZ in mapping the cluster ICM with high precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11668v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Paliwal, M. De Petris, A. Ferragamo, R. Adam, P. Ade, H. Ajeddig, P. Andr\'e, E. Artis, H. Aussel, I. Bartalucci, A. Beelen, A. Beno\^it, S. Berta, L. Bing, O. Bourrion, M. Calvo, A. Catalano, F. De Luca, F. -X. D\'esert, S. Doyle, E. F. C. Driessen, G. Ejlali, A. Gomez, J. Goupy, C. Hanser, S. Katsioli, F. K\'eruzor\'e, C. Kramer, B. Ladjelate, G. Lagache, S. Leclercq, J. -F. Lestrade, J. F. Mac\'ias-P\'erez, S. C. Madden, A. Maury, P. Mauskopf, F. Mayet, J. -B. Melin, A. Monfardini, A. Moyer-Anin, M. Mu\~noz-Echeverr\'ia, L. Perotto, G. Pisano, E. Pointecouteau, N. Ponthieu, G. W. Pratt, V. Rev\'eret, A. J. Rigby, A. Ritacco, C. Romero, H. Roussel, F. Ruppin, K. Schuster, A. Sievers, C. Tucker, R. Wicker, R. Zylka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breaking Parity: the case of the Trispectrum from Chiral Scalar-Tensor Theories of Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11801v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, possible hints of parity violation have been observed in the connected galaxy four-point correlation function. Although the true origin of the signal from the analysis has been debated, should they have a physical origin, they might point to primordial non-Gaussianity and would be evidence of new physics. In this work, we examine the single-field slow-roll model of inflation within chiral scalar-tensor theories of modified gravity. These theories extend the Chern-Simons one by including parity-violating operators containing first and second derivatives of the non-minimally coupled scalar (inflaton) field. This model is capable of imprinting parity-violating signatures in late-time observables, such as the galaxy four-point correlation function. We perform an analysis of the graviton-mediated scalar trispectrum of the gauge-invariant curvature perturbation $\zeta(t,\mathbf{x})$. We estimate that for a set of parameters of the theory it is possible to produce a signal-to-noise ratio for the parity-violating part of the trispectrum of order one without introducing modifications to the single-field slow-roll setup. Even if the signal found in the analysis turns out to be spurious or if no parity violation is ever detected in the galaxy four-point correlation function, our analysis can be used to constrain the free parameters of these theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11801v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tommaso Moretti (Physics Dept., Naples, ITALY), Nicola Bartolo (Physics,Astronomy Dept.,INFN,INAF, Padova, ITALY), Alessandro Greco (Astronomy Dept., Gainesville, USA)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of non-minimally coupled dark energy in the geometrical trinity of gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10935</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10935v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Within the geometrical trinity of gravity, we analyze scalar field dark energy models minimally and non-minimally coupled to gravity, postulating that a Yukawa-like interacting term is \emph{in form} equivalent for general relativity, teleparallel and symmetric-teleparallel theories. Our analysis is pursued within two scalar field representations, where a quintessence and phantom pictures are associated with quasiquintessence and quasiphantom exotic fields. In the latter, we suggest how the phion-pressure can be built up without exhibiting a direct kinetic term. Accordingly, the stability analysis reveals that this quasiquintessence field provides a viable description of the universe indicating, when minimally coupled, how to unify dark energy and dark matter by showing an attractor point where $w_{\phi}=0$. Conversely, in the non-minimally coupling, the alternative field only leaves an attractor where dark energy dominates, mimicking \emph{de facto} a cosmological constant behavior. A direct study is conducted comparing the standard case with the alternative one, overall concluding that the behavior of quintessence is well established across all the gravity scenarios. However, considering the phantom field non-minimal coupled to gravity, the results are inconclusive for power-law potentials in Einstein theory, and for the inverse square power potential in both teleparallel and symmetric-teleparallel theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10935v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youri Carloni, Orlando Luongo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How accurate are transient spectral classification tools? -- A study using 4,646 SEDMachine spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10963v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Accurate classification of transients obtained from spectroscopic data are important to understand their nature and discover new classes of astronomical objects. For supernovae (SNe), SNID, NGSF (a Python version of SuperFit), and DASH are widely used in the community. Each tool provides its own metric to help determine classification, such as rlap of SNID, chi2/dof of NGSF, and Probability of DASH. However, we do not know how accurate these tools are, and they have not been tested with a large homogeneous dataset. Thus, in this work, we study the accuracy of these spectral classification tools using 4,646 SEDMachine spectra, which have accurate classifications obtained from the Zwicky Transient Facility Bright Transient Survey (BTS). Comparing our classifications with those from BTS, we have tested the classification accuracy in various ways. We find that NGSF has the best performance (overall Accuracy 87.6% when samples are split into SNe Ia and Non-Ia types), while SNID and DASH have similar performance with overall Accuracy of 79.3% and 76.2%, respectively. Specifically for SNe Ia, SNID can accurately classify them when rlap &gt; 15 without contamination from other types, such as Ibc, II, SLSN, and other objects that are not SNe (Purity &gt; 98%). For other types, determining their classification is often uncertain. We conclude that it is difficult to obtain an accurate classification from these tools alone. This results in additional human visual inspection effort being required in order to confirm the classification. To reduce this human visual inspection and to support the classification process for future large-scale surveys, this work provides supporting information, such as the accuracy of each tool as a function of its metric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10963v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Young-Lo Kim, Isobel Hook, Andrew Milligan, Llu\'is Galbany, Jesper Sollerman, Umut Burgaz, Georgios Dimitriadis, Christoffer Fremling, Joel Johansson, Tom\'as E. M\"uller-Bravo, James D. Neill, Jakob Nordin, Peter Nugent, Yu-Jing Qi, Philippe Rosnet, Yashvi Sharma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imprints of M87 Jet Precession on the Black Hole-Accretion Disk System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10965v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Observational constraints on the configuration of the black hole (BH)-accretion disk-jet system are crucial for addressing key questions in black hole growth, accretion disk physics, and jet formation. The recently reported jet precession in M87 provides a novel avenue to explore these long-standing issues. This precession, attributed to the accretion disk's response to the frame-dragging effect of a spinning supermassive black hole (SMBH), indicates a non-zero spin. The relatively short precession period ($\sim$11 years) implies a compact accretion disk. In contrast to the traditional view of a strictly collimated shape, the M87 jet is inferred to curve at the innermost regions connecting to the spinning BH, which explains the unexpectedly wide innermost projected jet width.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10965v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuzhu Cui, Weikang Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The inflation trilogy and primordial black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10996v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose an inflation scenario with three independent stages of cold, warm and thermal inflation, respectively, driven by different scalar fields, motivated by the large number of such fields predicted in most extensions of the Standard Model. We show, in particular, that the intermediate period of warm inflation naturally leads to large density fluctuations on small scales, which can lead to primordial black hole formation in the mass window where they may account for all dark matter. This type of scenario yields a distinctive primordial black hole mass function with a mass gap, with the final period of thermal inflation diluting the abundance of very light black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10996v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paulo B. Ferraz, Jo\~ao G. Rosa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Minimal Axio-dilaton Dark Sector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11099v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In scalar-tensor theories it is the two-derivative sigma-model interactions that like to compete at low energies with the two-derivative interactions of General Relativity (GR) $\unicode{x2014}$ at least once the dangerous zero-derivative terms of the scalar potential are suppressed (such as by a shift symmetry). But nontrivial two-derivative interactions require at least two scalars to exist and so never arise in the single-scalar models most commonly explored. Axio-dilaton models provide a well-motivated minimal class of models for which these self-interactions can be explored. We review this class of models and investigate whether these minimal two fields can suffice to describe both Dark Matter and Dark Energy. We find that they can $\unicode{x2014}$ the axion is the Dark Matter and the dilaton is the Dark Energy $\unicode{x2014}$ and that they robustly predict several new phenomena for the CMB and structure formation that can be sought in observations. These include specific types of Dark Energy evolution and small space- and time-dependent changes to particle masses post-recombination that alter the Integrated Sachs-Wolfe effect, cause small changes to structure growth and more.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11099v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam Smith, Maria Mylova, Philippe Brax, Carsten van de Bruck, C. P. Burgess, Anne-Christine Davis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a classification of UV completable Higgs inflation in metric-affine gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11277v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Towards a classification of UV completable Higgs inflation in the framework of parity-even metric-affine gravity, we investigate the particle spectrum of a deformed theory in the large-$N$ limit. In a simple Higgs inflation model in metric-affine gravity, it is known that its UV cutoff is much smaller than the Planck scale. While it calls for UV completion, a concrete example has not yet been found, even with the large-$N$ limit known as a successful technique to complete an original Higgs inflation defined on the Riemannian geometry. This motivates us to study how small deformation of the simple Higgs inflation affects the emergence and properties of dynamical fields particularly in the large-$N$ limit. As a UV theory has to be free of ghosts or tachyons at least around Minkowski space, we perform the parameter search and find the healthy parameter region where a new heavy particle can propagate without these pathologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11277v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yusuke Mikura, Yuichiro Tada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black holes, photon sphere, and cosmology in ghost-free $f(\mathcal{G})$ gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11530</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11530v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The improved version of ghost-free $f(\mathcal{G})$ gravity introduced in Phys.~Lett.~B \textbf{631} (2005), 1-6 is proposed and investigated. It is demonstrated that improved ghost-free $f(\mathcal{G})$ gravity may be consistently applied to describe the expanding universe (with horizon) as well as the static spacetime like black holes. Interestingly, such a theory looks like a close avatar of scalar-Einstein-Gauss-Bonnet gravity with the only difference that the scalar field is not a dynamical one so that many predictions of ghost-free $f(\mathcal{G})$ gravity are very similar to that of sEGB gravity.
  We discuss the gravitational wave in the improved model with the condition that the propagating speed of the gravitational wave is identical to that of the propagation speed of light. A model that describes inflation in the early universe and could satisfy the observational constraints is also constructed. The solution of ghost-free $f(\mathcal{G})$ gravity realising the given static spacetime with spherical symmetry is proposed. Some of such solutions realise explicitly the Reissner-Nordstr\"{o}m black hole or the Hayward black hole, which is a regular black hole without curvature singularity, We also construct a black hole in our theory which contains the Arnowitt-Deser-Misner (ADM) mass, the horizon radius, and the radius of the photon sphere as independent parameters. The radius of the black hole shadow in this model as well as photon sphere radius are estimated. It is shown that there exists a parameter region which satisfies the constraints coming from Event Horizon Telescope observations. Furthermore, we construct model where the radius of the black hole shadow or photon orbit is smaller than the horizon radius supposed from the ADM mass.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11530v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shin'ichi Nojiri, S. D. Odintsov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frequency shifts induced by light scalar fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11567v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Light scalar fields are frequently used in modern physics, for example, as candidates for dark energy or dark matter. Open quantum dynamical effects, like frequency shifts, induced by such fields in probe particles used in interferometry experiments might open up new perspectives for constraining such models. In this article, we consider a probe scalar particle as a rough approximation for an atom in matter wave interferometry and discuss the frequency shifts induced by interactions with an environment comprising either one of two screened scalar field models: chameleons or symmetrons. For the $n=-4$ chameleon, we revise a previously obtained expression for the induced frequency shift, but confirm that it can likely not be used to obtain new constraints. However, for symmetrons, we find that induced frequency shifts have the potential to tightly constrain previously unreachable parts of the parameter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11567v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian K\"ading</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin induction from scattering of two spinning black holes in dense clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11634v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study with numerical relativity the spin induction effect within close hyperbolic encounters for equal-mass black holes. We review the initially nonspinning case and explore the cases of initially aligned, anti-aligned and orthogonal spins with respect to the orbital angular momentum $\vec L$. We find that, for a given initial effective spin, the black hole with a smaller initial spin acquires a greater spin-up than the other black hole after the close hyperbolic encounter. We study three different scenarios regarding initial effective spin ($\chi_{\rm eff}=-0.1, \ 0.0, \ 0.1$), using three different scattering angles in order to obtain maximally spin-inducing scenarios. We also find that the final effective spins with respect to the initial spins are well-fitted by a parabola. When considering spins orthogonal to $\vec L$, we observe that the black hole spins precess, and that the induced spin in the $z$-direction depends quadratically on the value of the initial spins. These new phenomena suggest that dense black hole clusters are very interesting dynamical systems where black hole spins may acquire a non trivial distribution, both for aligned and isotropic spins.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11634v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jorge L. Rodr\'iguez-Monteverde, Santiago Jaraba, Juan Garc\'ia-Bellido</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-canonical 3-form dark energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11658</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11658v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this study, we meticulously construct a 3-form Lagrangian designed to mimic the dynamics of both dust matter in the past and dark energy driving the acceleration in the present era. A dynamical systems approach is used to investigate the underlying behavior of the cosmological background. By investigating the influence of the potential slope and initial conditions on the dynamical solutions, we identify distinct viable scenarios capable of replicating a De Sitter universe in the present epoch. An intriguing aspect of the model is the existence of solutions describing multiple inflationary phases in which the 3-form self-interacting potential decays rapidly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11658v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vitor da Fonseca, Bruno J. Barros, Tiago Barreiro, Nelson J. Nunes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Squeezed vacua and primordial features in effective theories of inflation at N2LO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11812v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A finite duration of cosmic inflation can result in features $\mathcal{P}_{\mathcal{R}}(k)=|\alpha_k-\beta_k\,\mathrm{e}^{\mathrm{i}\delta_k}|^2 \mathcal{P}_{\mathcal{R}}^{(0)}(k)$ in the primordial power spectrum that carry information about a quantum gravity phase before inflation. While the almost-scale-invariant power spectrum $\mathcal{P}_{\mathcal{R}}^{(0)}$ for the quasi-Bunch-Davies vacuum is fully determined by the inflationary background dynamics, the Bogoliubov coefficients $\alpha_k$ and $\beta_k$ for the squeezed vacuum depend on new physics beyond inflation and have been used to produce phenomenological templates for the features. In this paper, we consider a large class of effective theories of inflation and compute the relative phase $\delta_k$. While this phase vanishes in de Sitter space, here we show that it is fully determined by the inflationary background dynamics and we compute it up to the next-to-next-leading order (N2LO) in a Hubble-flow expansion. In particular, for the Starobinsky model of inflation we find that this relative phase can be expressed in terms of the scalar tilt $n_\mathrm{s}$ as $\delta_k=\frac{\pi}{2}(n_\mathrm{s}-1)-\frac{\pi}{4}(n_\mathrm{s}-1)^2\,\ln(k/k_*)$. The relative phase results in a negative shift and a running frequency that have been considered in the most studied phenomenological templates for primordial features, thus providing precise theoretical predictions for upcoming cosmological observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11812v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eugenio Bianchi, Mauricio Gamonal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a new model-independent calibration of Gamma-Ray Bursts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.13115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.13115v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Current data on baryon acoustic oscillations and Supernovae of Type Ia cover up to $z\sim 2.5$. These observations play a very important role in the determination of cosmological parameters and have been widely used to constrain the $\Lambda$CDM and models beyond it. To extend the investigation to higher $z$, Gamma-Ray Bursts (GRBs) stand out as one of the most promising observables since can probe the universe up to $z\sim9.4$. The use of GRB correlations is still a challenge due to the spread in their intrinsic properties. In this work, we propose an innovative and cosmology-independent method of calibration of the so-called 3D Dainotti correlation. We employ state-of-the-art data on Cosmic Chronometers (CCH) at $z\lesssim2$ and use the Gaussian Processes reconstruction tool. To match the CCH redshift range, we select 20 long GRBs in $0.553\leq z\leq1.96$ from the Platinum sample, which consists of well-defined GRB plateau properties that obey the fundamental plane relation. We verify that the choice of priors on the parameters of the Dainotti relation and the modelling of CCH uncertainties and covariance have negligible impact on our results. We also consider the case in which the redshift evolution of the physical features of the plane is accounted for. We find that the use of CCH allows us to identify a sub-sample of GRBs that adhere even more closely to the fundamental plane relation, with an intrinsic scatter of $\sigma_{int}=0.20^{+0.03}_{-0.05}$ when evolutionary effects are considered. In an epoch in which we strive to reduce uncertainties on the GRB correlations variables to tighten constraints on cosmological parameters, we have found a novel model-independent approach to pinpoint a sub-sample that can thus represent a valuable set of standardizable candles. This allows us to extend the distance ladder presenting a new catalogue of calibrated luminosity distances up to $z=5$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.13115v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arianna Favale, Maria Giovanna Dainotti, Adri\`a G\'omez-Valent, Marina Migliaccio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple peaks in gravitational waves induced from primordial curvature perturbations with non-Gaussianity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05034</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05034v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: First-order primordial curvature perturbations are known to induce gravitational waves at the second-order, which can in turn probe the small-scale curvature perturbations near the end of the inflation. In this work, we extend the previous analysis in the Gaussian case into the non-Gaussian case, with particular efforts to obtain some thumb rules of sandwiching the associated peaks in gravitational waves induced from multiple peaks of non-Gaussian curvature perturbations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05034v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2024/10/045</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Xiang-Xi Zeng, Rong-Gen Cai, Shao-Jiang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mach's principle and dark matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.07597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.07597v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we entertain a Machian setting where local physics is non-locally affected by the whole Universe, taking the liberty to identify the local (``Newton's bucket'') with our visible Universe, and the whole Universe (Mach's ``fixed stars'') with the global Universe beyond our horizon. Crucially, we allow for the two to have different properties, so that we are beyond the traditional FRW setting. For definiteness we focus on theories where non-locality arises from evolution in the laws of physics in terms of spatially global time variables dual to the constants of Nature. Since non-local theories are foliation-dependent, the {\it local} (but not the global) Hamiltonian constraint is lost. This is true not only while non-locality is taking place, but also after it ceases: the local Hamiltonian constraint is only recovered up to a constant in time, keeping a memory of the integrated past non-locality. We show that this integration constant is equivalent to preserving the local Hamiltonian constraint and adding an extra fluid with the same cosmological properties as conventional pressureless dark matter. The equivalence breaks down in terms of clustering properties, with the new component attracting other matter, but not budging from its location. This is the ultimate ``painted-on'' dark matter, attracting but not being attracted, and nailing down a preferred frame.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.07597v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joao Magueijo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectrum of global string networks and the axion dark matter mass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.17253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.17253v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Cold dark matter axions produced in the post-inflationary Peccei-Quinn symmetry breaking scenario serve as clear targets for their experimental detection, since it is in principle possible to give a sharp prediction for their mass once we understand precisely how they are produced from the decay of global cosmic strings in the early Universe. In this paper, we perform a dedicated analysis of the spectrum of axions radiated from strings based on large scale numerical simulations of the cosmological evolution of the Peccei-Quinn field on a static lattice. Making full use of the massively parallel code and computing resources, we executed the simulations with up to $11264^3$ lattice sites, which allows us to improve our understanding of the dependence on the parameter controlling the string tension and thus give a more accurate extrapolation of the numerical results. We found that there are several systematic effects that have been overlooked in previous works, such as the dependence on the initial conditions, contaminations due to oscillations in the spectrum, and discretisation effects, some of which could explain the discrepancy in the literature. We confirmed the trend that the spectral index of the axion emission spectrum increases with the string tension, but did not find a clear evidence of whether it continues to increase or saturates to a constant at larger values of the string tension due to the severe discretisation effects. Taking this uncertainty into account and performing the extrapolation with a simple power law assumption on the spectrum, we find that the dark matter mass is predicted in the range of $m_a \approx 95$-$450\,\mu\mathrm{eV}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.17253v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2024/10/043</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP10(2024)043</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ken'ichi Saikawa, Javier Redondo, Alejandro Vaquero, Mathieu Kaltschmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extract non-Gaussian Features in Gravitational Wave Observation Data Using Self-Supervised Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04350v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a self-supervised learning model to denoise gravitational wave (GW) signals in the time series strain data without relying on waveform information. Denoising GW data is a crucial intermediate process for machine-learning-based data analysis techniques, as it can simplify the model for downstream tasks such as detections and parameter estimations. We use the blind-spot neural network and train it with whitened strain data with GW signals injected as both input data and target. Under the assumption of a Gaussian noise model, our model successfully denoises 38% of GW signals from binary black hole mergers in H1 data and 49% of signals in L1 data detected in the O1, O2, and O3 observation runs with an overlap greater than 0.5. We also test the model's potential to extract glitch features, loud inspiral compact binary coalescence signals a few seconds before the merger, and unseen CCSN signals during training.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04350v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Chiung Lin, Albert K. H. Kong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sensing Gravity with Polarized Electromagnetic Radiation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.06513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.06513v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Polarization wiggling is a direct gravitational effect exerted by a gravitational field on any electromagnetic radiation traversing it. This effect is investigated in linear gravity for spacetimes with flat or conformally flat backgrounds. First, we show how the polarization wiggle rates can be computed in the conformal frame and transformed to the physical frame. Then it is shown that polarization wiggling is not sensitive to scalar perturbations to the metric, while vector and tensor perturbations do induce polarization wiggling. This poses two natural questions: Can polarized electromagnetic radiation be used to measure vectorial and tensorial components of gravitational fields directly? And if so, how? Next, polarization wiggling is studied for an arbitrary vector perturbation to the spacetime metric. In a stationary spacetime, the polarization wiggle rate is proportional to the difference in frame dragging rates between radiation emission and measurement events. We show how this can be used to measure the angular momentum of a gravitational source if the emitter orbits the gravitational source on a known orbit. Next, the effect of a gravitational tensor mode with arbitrary polarization is studied. Finally, the polarization wiggling effect induced by a gravitational tensor mode is analyzed. Two cases are demonstrated: A spacetime with a flat Minkowski background and an expanding cosmology with a conformally flat background. In both cases, the polarization wiggling frequency equals the frequency of the gravitational tensor mode, while the other state parameters are encoded in the polarization wiggling amplitude and phase of the polarized radiation. We show that measurements of polarization wiggling frequency, amplitude and phase of polarized radiation from different directions enables all state parameters of a gravitational tensor mode to be determined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.06513v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kjell Tangen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of interacting vector dark energy and fluid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.06565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.06565v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we study interaction between dark energy and dark matter, where dark energy is described by a massive vector field, and dark matter is modelled as a fluid. We present a new interaction term, which affects only perturbations and can give interesting phenomenology. Then we present a general Lagrangian for the interacting vector dark energy with dark matter. For the dark energy, we choose Proca theory with $G_{3}$ term to study its phenomenological consequence. For this model, we explore both background and perturbation dynamics. We also present the no-ghost condition for tensor modes, vector modes and scalar modes. Subsequently, we also study the evolution of the overdensities of both baryon and cold dark matter in the high$-k$ limit. We show that the effective gravitational coupling is modified for cold dark matter and baryon. We also choose a simple concrete model and numerically show a suppression of the effective gravitational coupling for cold dark matter. However, in this simple model, the suppression of the effective gravitational coupling does not result in a suppression of the matter overdensity compared to that in the $\Lambda$CDM model due to the modified background expansion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.06565v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masroor C. Pookkillath, Kazuya Koyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gemini Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01099v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The $S_8/\sigma_8$ tension in the large scale structure can be explained by decaying dark matter with an almost degenerate spectrum and small enough decay width. Here we propose the Gemini dark matter model, which contains a heavy mother particle $\chi_3$ and two twins $\chi_{1/2}$ which are almost degenerate in mass and are produced at the same time. The dark sector is charged under the same Froggatt-Nielsen symmetry that can explain the hierarchy of the Standard model Yukawa couplings. The slightly heavier $\chi_2$ decays into $\chi_1$ and the axionic component of the flavon, which washes out the small scale structure and resolves $S_8/\sigma_8$ tension. We present the production mechanism of Gemini dark matter and viable parameter regions. We find that despite the preferred dark matter mass being $\mathcal{O}(1)$--$\mathcal{O}(100)$ keV, they constitute cold dark matter. The Gemini dark matter model predicts an abundance of dark radiation that will be probed in future measurements of the cosmic microwave background.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01099v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Cheek, Yu-Cheng Qiu, Liang Tan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vector-like Quark Stabilised Higgs Inflation: Implications for Particle Phenomenology, Primordial Gravitational Waves and the Hubble Tension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02399v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Standard Model (SM) Higgs potential is likely to be metastable, in which case Higgs Inflation requires an extension of the SM to sufficiently stabilise the Higgs potential. Here we consider stabilisation by adding $n_{Q} \leq 3$ Vector-Like Quarks (VLQs) of mass $m_{Q}$. We consider isosinglet $T$ and $B$ vector quarks. Requiring stability of the finite temperature effective potential, we find that the upper bounds on $m_{Q}$ for $T$ quarks are 5.8 TeV (for $n_{Q} = 2$) and 55 TeV (for $n_{Q} = 3$). The upper bounds are generally smaller for $B$ vector quarks and are sensitive to the $t$-quark mass. The inflation predictions depend upon the conformal frame in which the model is renormalised. For renormalisation in the Einstein frame (Prescription I) the predictions are almost indistinguishable from the classical values: $n_s = 0.966$ and $r = 3.3 \times 10^{-3}$. Renormalisation in the Jordan frame (Prescription II) predicts larger values of $n_{s}$ and $r$, with $n_{s}$ generally in the range 0.980 to 0.990 and $r$ of the order of 0.01. The predicted range of $n_{s}$ is consistent with the CMB range obtained in Hubble tension solutions which modify the sound horizon at decoupling, whilst the predicted values of $r$ will be easily observable by forthcoming CMB experiments. The observational upper bound on $r$ generally imposes a stronger upper bound on $m_{Q}$ in Prescription II than the requirement of stability. We conclude that VLQ-stabilised Higgs Inflation with Prescription II renormalisation favours 1-10 TeV vector-like quarks that will be accessible to future colliders, and predicts a tensor-to-scalar ratio that will be observable in forthcoming CMB experiments and values of $n_{s}$ that favour an early-time solution to the Hubble tension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02399v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John McDonald</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the uncertainty of the White Dwarf Astrophysical Gravitational Wave Background</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10642v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Context: The astrophysical gravitational wave background (AGWB) is a stochastic gravitational wave (GW) signal that is emitted by different populations of inspiralling binary systems containing compact objects throughout the Universe. In the frequency range between 0.1 and 100 mHz it will be detected by future space-based gravitational wave detectors like the Laser Interferometer Space Antenna (LISA). Recently, we concluded that the white dwarf (WD) contribution to the AGWB dominates over that of black holes (BHs) and neutron stars (NSs).
  Aims: We aim to investigate the uncertainties of the WD AGWB that arise from the use of different stellar metallicities, different star formation rate density (SFRD) models, and different binary evolution models.
  Methods: We use the code developed before to determine the WD component of the AGWB. We use a metallicity dependent SFRD based on earlier work to construct five different SFRD models. We use four different population models that use different common-envelope treatment and six different metallicities for each model.
  Results: For all possible combinations, the WD component of the AGWB is dominant over other populations of compact objects. The effects of metallicity and population model are smaller than the effect of a (metallicity dependent) SFRD model. We find a range of about a factor of 5 in the level of the WD AGWB around a mid value of $\Omega_{\rm WD} = 4\times10^{-12}$ at 1 mHz and a shape that depends weakly on the model.
  Conclusions: We find an uncertainty for the WD component of the AGWB of about a factor 5. We note that there exist other uncertainties that have an effect on this signal as well. We discuss whether the turnover of the WD AGWB at 10 mHz will be detectable by LISA, and find that this is likely. We confirm the previous finding that the WD component of the AGWB dominates over other populations, in particular BHs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10642v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sophie Hofman (Radboud University), Gijs Nelemans (Radboud University, SRON)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black Holes, Warp Drives, and Energy Conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04495v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Following the work of H. Ellis, we study warp drives in the gravitational field of a Schwarzschild black hole. We find that as long as the warp drive crosses the black hole horizon at a subluminal speed, the horizon would be effectively absent inside the warp bubble. Moreover, we discover that the black hole's gravitational field can alleviate the violations of the weak energy condition (WEC) and the null energy condition (NEC) and therefore decrease the amount of negative energy required to sustain a warp drive, which may be instrumental for creating microscopic warp drives in lab experiments. We also consider the thermodynamics of a warp bubble interacting with a black hole and point out some paradoxes that may indicate a gap in our understanding of them from the thermodynamic point of view.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04495v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2024.138910</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physics Letters B, Volume 856, September 2024, 138910</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Remo Garattini, Kirill Zatrimaylov</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
