<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO</link>
    <description>astro-ph.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 08:50:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>CMB limits on decaying dark matter beyond the ionization threshold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13305</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13305v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The temperature and polarization anisotropies of the cosmic microwave background (CMB) have been used to set constraints on decaying dark matter models down to keV masses. In this work, we extend these limits down to the sub-keV mass range. Using principal component analysis, we estimate the lower bound on the decay lifetime for a basis of different dark matter masses and Standard Model final states, from which the bound on an arbitrary model can be calculated. We validate our principal component analysis using Markov chain Monte Carlo methods and Planck 2018 data. We perform a separate analysis for models decaying into photons below the hydrogen ionization threshold. We demonstrate that for these models, the effect of energy deposition can be captured approximately by a single parameter, but the redshift dependence of the effect is very different from higher-energy injections; in particular, the perturbations to CMB anisotropies are more sensitive to energy deposited around the time of recombination.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13305v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Clara Xu, Wenzer Qin, Tracy R. Slatyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Baby Universe Absorption Explain Dark Energy?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13306</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13306v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It has been proposed that the accelerated expansion of the universe can be explained by the merging of our universe with baby universes, resulting in dark energy with a phantom-like equation of state. However, the evidence in favor of it did not include the full set of cosmological observables. Here we examine the implications of this model for both early and late universe cosmology using data from Planck collaboration, DESI 2024 and other experiments. We find that the pure baby universe model gives a poor fit to current data. Extending it to include a contribution from the cosmological constant, we find two allowed regions of parameter space: one close to $\Lambda$CDM, and another with $\Lambda &lt;0$ plus the exotic dark energy component. The two regions can be significantly favored over $\Lambda$CDM, depending on the choice of supernova datasets, and they can ameliorate the Hubble tension to the level of $2\sigma$, depending on the supernova dataset. The model with $\Lambda&lt;0$ features an equation of state $w(a)$ with a pole singularity at early times.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13306v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Varun Muralidharan, James M. Cline</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DESI data and refinement of standard recombination theory help solve the Hubble tension problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13384</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13384v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The values of the Hubble constant obtained from the data of the early and of the late Universe differ by 10%. Data obtained by DESI Collaboration can help solve this problem, establishing with high precision the value of the product of the Hubble constant h and comoving of sound horizon at the end of drag epoch to be equal to 101.8 Mpc. This value agrees very well with the earlier refinement of the standard recombination theory and the value of the Hubble constant H0=73.5 km/s/Mpc obtained from measurements in the late Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13384v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. V. Shepelev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-redshift cosmography with a possible cosmic distance duality relation violation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13390v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Cosmic Distance Duality Relation (CDDR) defines a fundamental link in modern cosmology between geometric distance measurements and redshift. Any observed deviations from the CDDR could suggest the need for new physics beyond the $\Lambda$CDM model. In this study, we model geometric distances (both luminosity and angular) using a cosmographic expansion with the Pade method, which stabilizes the behavior of the cosmographic series at high redshifts. This approach allows us to determine geometric distances independently of any specific model. By incorporating updated data from supernovae (SN), baryon acoustic oscillations (BAO), and cosmic chronometers (CC), we obtain observational constraints for parametric models that quantify the CDDR, alongside all baseline cosmographic parameters. We find that potential CDDR violations introduce new statistical correlations in the cosmographic parameters ($H_0$, $q_0$, and $j_0$). However, within this framework, we do not observe significant deviations from the CDDR, and our results remain consistent with the predictions of the $\Lambda$CDM model. This work offers a novel and straightforward method for testing the CDDR by fixing background evolution through cosmographic techniques, thereby paving the way for new geometric observational tests of possible deviations from standard cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13390v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e F. Jesus, Mikael J. S. Gomes, Rodrigo F. L. Holanda, Rafael C. Nunes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of gamma-ray burst Amati relation based on Hubble data set and Pantheon+ samples</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13466v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using gamma-ray bursts as standard candles for cosmological parameter constraints rely on their empirical luminosity relations and low-redshift calibration. In this paper, we examine the Amati relation and its potential corrections based on the A118 sample of higher-quality gamma-ray bursts, using both Hubble data set and Pantheon+ samples as calibration samples in the redshift range of z &lt; 1.965. In calibrating gamma-ray bursts using these two datasets, we employ Gaussian processes to obtain corresponding Hubble diagrams to avoid the dependence on cosmological models in the calibration process. We first divided the low-redshift sample of GRBs into two bins and examined the Amati relation and its potential modifications. We found that under both calibrations, the Amati relation did not show evidence of redshift evolution (68% confidence level). For the other two Amati relations that include redshift evolution terms, the central values of the redshift evolution coefficients deviated from 0, but due to the limitations of the sample size and the increase in the number of parameters, most of the redshift evolution coefficients were not able to be excluded from 0 at the 1 sigma level. Therefore, to assess their situation across the entire redshift range, we employed MCMC to globally fit three types of Amati relations. By computing AIC and BIC, we found that for the GRB A118 sample, the standard Amati relation remains the most fitting empirical luminosity formula, and no potential redshift evolution trend was observed for two different low-redshift calibrating sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13466v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yufen Han, Jiaze Gao, Gang Liu, Lixin Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient estimation of rotation-induced bias to reconstructed CMB lensing power spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13612v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The cosmic microwave background (CMB) lensing power spectrum is a powerful probe of the late-time universe, encoding valuable information about cosmological parameters such as the sum of neutrino masses and dark energy equation of state. However, the presence of anisotropic cosmic birefringence can bias the reconstructed CMB lensing power spectrum using CMB polarization maps, particularly at small scales, and affect the constraints on these parameters. Upcoming experiments, which will be dominated by the polarization lensing signal, are especially susceptible to this bias. We identify the dominant contribution to this bias as an $N_L^{(1)}$-like noise, caused by anisotropic rotation instead of lensing. We show that, for an CMB-S4-like experiment, a scale-invariant anisotropic rotation field with a standard deviation of 0.05 degrees can suppress the small-scale lensing power spectrum ($L\gtrsim 2000$) at a comparable level to the effect of massive neutrino with $\sum_i m_{\nu_{i}}=50~\rm{meV}$, making rotation field an important source of degeneracy in neutrino mass measurement for future CMB experiments. We provide an analytic expression and a simulation-based estimator for this $N_L^{(1)}$-like noise, which allows for efficient forecasting and mitigation of the bias in future experiments. Furthermore, we investigate the impact of a non-scale-invariant rotation power spectrum on the reconstructed lensing power spectrum and find that an excess of power in the small-scale rotation power spectrum leads to a larger bias. Our work provides an effective numeric framework to accurately model and account for the bias caused by anisotropic rotation in future CMB lensing measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13612v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongbo Cai, Yilun Guan, Toshiya Namikawa, Arthur Kosowsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DESI Peculiar Velocity Survey -- Fundamental Plane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13842</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13842v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) Peculiar Velocity Survey aims to measure the peculiar velocities of early and late type galaxies within the DESI footprint using both the Fundamental Plane and Tully-Fisher relations. Direct measurements of peculiar velocities can significantly improve constraints on the growth rate of structure, reducing uncertainty by a factor of approximately 2.5 at redshift 0.1 compared to the DESI Bright Galaxy Survey's redshift space distortion measurements alone. We assess the quality of stellar velocity dispersion measurements from DESI spectroscopic data. These measurements, along with photometric data from the Legacy Survey, establish the Fundamental Plane relation and determine distances and peculiar velocities of early-type galaxies. During Survey Validation, we obtain spectra for 6698 unique early-type galaxies, up to a photometric redshift of 0.15. 64\% of observed galaxies (4267) have relative velocity dispersion errors below 10\%. This percentage increases to 75\% if we restrict our sample to galaxies with spectroscopic redshifts below 0.1. We use the measured central velocity dispersion, along with photometry from the DESI Legacy Imaging Surveys, to fit the Fundamental Plane parameters using a 3D Gaussian maximum likelihood algorithm that accounts for measurement uncertainties and selection cuts. In addition, we conduct zero-point calibration using the absolute distance measurements to the Coma cluster, leading to a value of the Hubble constant, $H_0 = 76.05 \pm 0.35$(statistical) $\pm 0.49$(systematic FP) $\pm 4.86$(statistical due to calibration) $\mathrm{km \ s^{-1} Mpc^{-1}}$. This $H_0$ value is within $2\sigma$ of Planck Cosmic Microwave Background results and within $1\sigma$, of other low redshift distance indicator-based measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13842v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Khaled Said, Cullan Howlett, Tamara Davis, John Lucey, Christoph Saulder, Kelly Douglass, Alex G. Kim, Anthony Kremin, Caitlin Ross, Greg Aldering, Jessica Nicole Aguilar, Steven Ahlen, Segev BenZvi, Davide Bianchi, David Brooks, Todd Claybaugh, Kyle Dawson, Axel de la Macorra, Biprateep Dey, Peter Doel, Kevin Fanning, Simone Ferraro, Andreu Font-Ribera, Jaime E. Forero-Romero, Enrique Gazta\~naga, Satya Gontcho A Gontcho, Julien Guy, Klaus Honscheid, Robert Kehoe, Theodore Kisner, Andrew Lambert, Martin Landriau, Laurent Le Guillou, Marc Manera, Aaron Meisner, Ramon Miquel, John Moustakas, Andrea Mu\~noz-Guti\'errez, Adam Myers, Jundan Nie, Nathalie Palanque-Delabrouille, Will Percival, Francisco Prada, Graziano Rossi, Eusebio Sanchez, David Schlegel, Michael Schubnell, Joseph Harry Silber, David Sprayberry, Gregory Tarl\'e, Mariana Vargas Magana, Benjamin Alan Weaver, Risa Wechsler, Zhimin Zhou, Hu Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capturing primordial non-Gaussian signatures in the late Universe by multi-scale extrema of the cosmic log-density field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13876v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct two new summary statistics, the scale-dependent peak height function (scale-PKHF) and the scale-dependent valley depth function (scale-VLYDF), and forecast their constraining power on PNG amplitudes $\{f_\mathrm{NL}^\mathrm{local}, f_\mathrm{NL}^\mathrm{equil},f_\mathrm{NL}^\mathrm{ortho}\}$ and standard cosmological parameters based on ten thousands of density fields drawn from \textsc{Quijote} and \textsc{Quijote-PNG} simulations at $z=0$. With the Fisher analysis, we find that the scale-PKHF and scale-VLYDF are capable of capturing a wealth of primordial information about the Universe. Specifically, the constraint on the scalar spectral index $n_s$ obtained from the scale-VLYDF (scale-PKHF) is 12.4 (8.6) times tighter than that from the power spectrum, and 3.9 (2.7) times tighter than that from the bispectrum. The combination of the two statistics yields constraints on $\{f_\mathrm{NL}^\mathrm{local}, f_\mathrm{NL}^\mathrm{equil}\}$ similar to those from the bispectrum and power spectrum combination, but provides a 1.4-fold improvement in the constraint on $f_\mathrm{NL}^\mathrm{ortho}$. After including the power spectrum, its constraining power well exceeds that of the bispectrum and power spectrum combination by factors of 1.1--2.9 for all parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13876v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yun Wang, Ping He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implications of Fermionic Dark Matter Interactions on Anisotropic Neutron Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14020</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14020v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The presence of Dark matter (DM) within a neutron star (NS) can substantially influence the macroscopic properties. It is commonly assumed that the pressure inside an NS is isotropic, but in reality, pressure is locally anisotropic. This study explores the properties of anisotropic NS with a subfraction of DM (isotropic) trapped inside. Implementing a two-fluid formalism with three Equations of State (EOS): AP3 (a realistic nucleon-nucleon interaction model), BSk22 (modeling atomic nuclei and neutron-matter), and MPA1 (considering relativistic effects in nuclear interactions). The properties of NS, such as mass ($M$), radius ($R$), and dimensionless tidal deformability ($\Lambda$), for various DM-anisotropic configurations, have been rigorously tested against observational constraints. These constraints include data from the binary NS merger GW170817, NICER x-ray measurements, and pulsar mass-radius observations. We observe that with increasing DM subfraction, higher anisotropies could also satisfy the observational constraints. Furthermore, increasing the coupling ($g$) between DM and its mediator leads to the formation of a core-halo structure, with a DM halo surrounding the baryonic matter (BM). Specifically, for coupling values of $g = 10^{-4}$, $10^{-3.7}$, and $10^{-3.5}$, we observe that the maximum radius ($R_{max}$) decreases with increasing anisotropy, which contrasts with the behavior at $g = 10^{-5}$ and in scenarios with no DM. Our analysis indicates that binary pulsar systems could potentially constrain the extent of admixed anisotropic NS or, more optimistically, provide evidence for the existence of DM-admixed anisotropic NS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14020v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Premachand Mahapatra, Chiranjeeb Singha, Ayush Hazarika, Prasanta Kumar Das</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Induced gravitational waves for arbitrary higher orders: vertex rules and loop diagrams in cosmological perturbation theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14052v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Gravitational waves induced by primordial perturbations serve as crucial probes for studying the early universe, providing a significant window into potential new physics during cosmic evolution. Due to the potentially large amplitudes of primordial perturbations on small scales, the contributions of high-order cosmological perturbations are highly significant. We propose a vertex approach applicable to the study of induced gravitational waves for arbitrary higher orders. Using the vertex approach and tree diagrams, we can directly derive the explicit expressions of higher-order induced gravitational waves without involving the complex and lengthy calculations of higher-order cosmological perturbations. Correlations between different tree diagrams correspond to the loop diagrams of two-point correlation functions of induced gravitational waves. Our investigation reveals that one-particle reducible diagrams impact tensor-scalar induced gravitational waves while leaving scalar induced gravitational waves unaffected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14052v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing-Zhi Zhou, Yu-Ting Kuang, Di Wu, H. L\"u, Zhe Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmic dance in the Shapley Concentration Core II. The uGMRT-MeerKAT view of filaments in the brightest cluster galaxies and tailed radio galaxies in the A3528 cluster complex</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14142</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14142v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Superclusters are the largest-scale environments where a number of galaxy clusters interact with each other through minor/major mergers and grow via accretion along cosmic filaments. We focus on the A3528 complex in the core of the Shapley Supercluster. This system includes three clusters, A3528 (composed itself by two sub-clusters, namely A3528N and A3528S), A3532 and A3530, and presents a mildly active dynamical state. We study how minor mergers affect the evolution of radio galaxies and whether they are able to re-accelerate relativistic electrons in the ICM. We used observations from the uGMRT (Band 3, 4 and 5) and MeerKAT (L-band) telescopes to obtain images and spectral index maps over a wide frequency band and spatial resolutions. We compare these data with those from the SRG/eROSITA X-ray telescope. We detect faint diffuse radio emission associated with the radio galaxies. The BCGs in A3528S and A3532 show filaments of diffuse radio emission which extend for $\sim200-400$ kpc out of the radio galaxy. The spectral index of these filaments is extremely steep and almost constant ($\alpha\sim -2, -2.5$). Contrary to the radio tails in A3528N, the spectral properties of these radio filaments are not consistent with standard models of plasma ageing. We also detect roundish diffuse radio emission around the BCG in A3528S which could be classified as a radio mini-halo. The radio tail in this cluster appears longer that in earlier detections, being $\sim300$ kpc long at all frequencies. We linked the presence of extended radio emission in the form of filaments and threads in the A3528 complex with the effect of minor mergers. This is reinforced by the increasing X-ray fluctuations in correspondence with the radio extended emission in A3528S. Despite the less energy involved, our findings support the hypothesis that these events can re-energise plasma originating from radio galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14142v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Di Gennaro, T. Venturi, S. Giacintucci, M. Br\"uggen, E. Bulbul, J. Sanders, A. Liu, X. Zhang, K. Trehaeven, D. Dallacasa, P. Merluzzi, T. Pasini, S. Bardelli, G. Bernardi, O. Smirnov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on primordial black holes in dSphs using radio observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14353v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Primordial black holes (PBHs) are hypothetical objects formed at the early epoch of the universe, which could be a type of dark matter (DM) candidate without the need for new particles. The abundance of PBH DM has been constrained strictly by many observations.In this work, with the radio observations of Fornax and Segue I, we constrain the abundance of PBH in dwarf spheroidal galaxies through the synchrotron self-Compton (SSC) effect of Hawking radiation electrons. By selecting optimal sources, we obtain the constraints on the fraction of PBH DM down to $\sim10^{-3}$ for Segue I and $\sim10^{-5}$ for Fornax at asteroidal mass. We also predict that, with 100 hours of future observation by the Square Kilometer Array, the SSC approach could place constraints comparable to the current strictest results for PBHs of $&lt;5\times10^{15}\,{\rm g}$. Better projected constraints can be obtained by including the inverse Compton scattering on cosmic microwave background photons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14353v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tian-Ci Liu, Xiao-Song Hu, Yun-Feng Liang, Ben-Yang Zhu, Xing-Fu Zhang, En-Wei Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Analytic Model of Gravitational Collapse Induced by Radiative Cooling: Instability Scale, Infall Velocity, and Accretion Rate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12940v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present an analytic description of the spherically symmetric gravitational collapse of radiatively cooling gas clouds. The approach is based on developing the "one-zone" density-temperature relationship of the gas into a full dynamical model. We convert this density-temperature relationship into a barotropic equation of state, which we use to calculate the density and velocity profiles of the gas. From these quantities we calculate the time-dependent mass accretion rate onto the center of the cloud. The approach clarifies the mechanism by which radiative cooling induces gravitational instability. In particular, we distinguish the rapid, quasi-equilibrium contraction of a cooling gas core to high central densities from the legitimate instability this contraction establishes in the envelope. We develop a refined criterion for the mass scale of this instability, based only on the chemical-thermal evolution in the core. We explicate our model in the context of a primordial mini-halo cooled by molecular hydrogen, and then provide two further examples, a delayed collapse with hydrogen deuteride cooling and the collapse of an atomic cooling halo. In all three cases, our results agree well with full hydrodynamical treatments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12940v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Gurian, Boyuan Liu, Donghui Jeong, Takashi Hosokawa, Shingo Hirano, Naoki Yoshida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence of Dark Energy Prior to its Discovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13427v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This is a review and statistical analysis of the evidence supporting the existence of a cosmological constant in the early 1990s, before its discovery made with distant supernovae in 1998. The earlier evidence was derived from newly precise measurements of the Universe, including its mass density, the Hubble constant, the age of the oldest stars, the filamentary large-scale structure, and the anisotropy of the cosmic microwave background. These measurements created tension for models assuming the cosmological constant was zero. This tension was alleviated by several insightful papers published before 1996, which proposed a cosmological constant that increased the expansion rate. Statistical analysis here shows that the probability of the cosmological constant being zero was demonstrably less than a few percent. Some models identified a best-fit value close to the modern estimate of Omega_Lambda ~ 0.7.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13427v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Geoffrey W. Marcy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matter really does matter, or Why $f(R,{\rm Matter})$ type theories are significant for gravitational physics and cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13594v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In a recent paper (Lacombe, Mukohyama, and Seitz, JCAP {\bf 2024}, 05, 064 (2024)), the authors provided an in-depth analysis of a class of modified gravity theories, generally called $f(R,{\rm Matter})$ theories, which assume the existence of a non-minimal coupling between geometry and matter. It was argued that if the matter sector consists of Standard Model particles, then these theories suffer from the presence of ghosts, or are just scalar/vector-tensor theories. Hence, the relevance of these theories for cosmology was questioned. It is the goal of the present work to carefully analyze, discuss, and assess the line of arguments proposed in Lacombe et al. JCAP {\bf 2024}, 05, 064 (2024). After a qualitative critical discussion of the five general arguments proposed for the validity of a gravitational theory, we present the theoretical foundations of the $f(R,{\rm Matter})$ theories, including their possible relations with quantum gravity, and discuss in detail the role of matter. The matter source discussed in Lacombe et al., consisting predominantly of a massless scalar field, is extremely restrictive, and rather irrelevant for cosmology and the description of the observational data. We also devote a detailed discussion of the problem of the energy scales of the $f(R,{\rm Matter})$ theories. To test the observational relevance of this type of theories we present the comparison of a simple theoretical model with a small set of observational data and with the $\Lambda$CDM paradigm. We conclude by pointing out that the analysis of Lacombe et al., JCAP {\bf 2024}, 05, 064 (2024), even very useful for the understanding of some limited aspects of the $f(R,{\rm Matter})$ theories, and of their theoretical foundations, cannot be considered as a valid or definite criticism of these approaches to gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13594v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tiberiu Harko, Miguel A. S. Pinto, Shahab Shahidi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lagrangian formulation of the Tsallis entropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13638v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the gravitational origin of the Tsallis entropy, characterized by the nonadditive index $\delta$. Utilizing Wald's formalism within the framework of $f(R)$ modified theories of gravity, we evaluate the entropy on the black hole horizon for constant curvature solutions to the spherically symmetric vacuum field equations. In so doing, we demonstrate that the Tsallis entropy can be effectively derived from a generalization of the Lagrangian $\mathcal{L}\propto R^{1+\epsilon}$, where $\epsilon=\delta-1$ quantifies small deviations from general relativity. In conclusion, we examine the physical implications of our findings in light of cosmological observations and elaborate on the possibility of solving the thermodynamic instability of Schwarzschild black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13638v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rocco D'Agostino, Giuseppe Gaetano Luciano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-dependent dark matter interactions at loop-level in Ar and Xe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13664v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Xenon and argon are the two noble gases used in tonne scale dark matter direct detection experiments. We compare the detection capability of both target elements for interactions due to a pseudoscalar mediator including loop-level contributions to the cross section. At tree-level this type of interaction depends on the nuclear spin and would thus not be detectable in argon-based detectors, since Ar has spin zero. However, at the loop-level the same interaction yields spin-independent contributions that would be detectable in an argon target and are not negligible with respect to the tree-level interactions in xenon, because these are momentum suppressed. In fact, the loop-level contributions are also important for xenon-based experiments at low recoil energies, which could change their discovery reach for this interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13664v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nassim Bozorgnia, Muping Chen, Graciela B. Gelmini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>g$\delta N$ formalism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13673</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13673v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The $\delta N$ formalism has been the major computational tool to study the superhorizon evolution of the scalar type perturbation sourced by scalar fields. Recently, this formalism was generalized to compute an arbitrary scalar, vector, and tensor type perturbations, including the gravitational waves (GWs), sourced by an arbitrary bosonic fields. In this paper, we explain how to use the generalized $\delta N$ formalism (the g$\delta N$ formalism), considering a model with U(1) gauge fields as a concrete example. Several new findings on this model and prospects on future gravitational wave experiments are also discussed, including the condition for the two linear polarizations of GWs to have different amplitudes. This paper provides a detailed explanation of our previous paper published in Physical Review Letters. We also discuss the Weinberg's adiabatic mode for an anisotropic background, showing a qualitative difference from the one for the FLRW background.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13673v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takahiro Tanaka, Yuko Urakawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low injection rate of cosmic-ray protons in the turbulent reacceleration model of radio halos in galaxy clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13846</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13846v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A giant radio halo (RH) is a diffuse synchrotron emission observed on the scale of megaparsecs (Mpc), typically found in the central region of merging galaxy clusters. Its large size and steep spectrum suggest that it originates from the re-energization of an aged population of cosmic ray electrons (CREs), while the secondary leptons produced in the $pp$ hadronic collision of cosmic ray protons (CRPs) may contribute to the emission. In this study, we investigate the reacceleration model including both primary and secondary CREs, assuming that the primary CRs originate from internal galaxies. In our new method, we follow the cosmological evolution of each cluster and calculate the energy spectra and one-dimensional spatial distributions of CRs. The primary CRE model with $\sim 3$ Gyr duration of reacceleration successfully reproduces the statistical properties of the RHs observed in the recent LOFAR survey, as well as the spectrum and profile of the Coma cluster. The gamma-ray and neutrino emissions produced by reaccelerated CRPs are consistent with the upper limits. However, if the CRP injection rate is high and the secondary CREs become significant, the model with the required $\sim 3$ Gyr reacceleration overproduces the number of RHs. The limit on the CRP injection rate, $L_{\rm p} \lesssim 10^{41}$ erg/s, is significantly lower than that expected from the early starburst activity or jets from active galactic nuclei. This discrepancy requires a revision of either the model of CR supply from galaxies or the turbulent reacceleration model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13846v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kosuke Nishiwaki, Katsuaki Asano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy-Momentum Squared Gravity: A Brief Overview</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14106v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we present a review of Energy-Momentum Squared Gravity (EMSG) -- more specifically, $f(R,T_{\mu\nu}T^{\mu\nu})$ gravity, where $R$ represents the Ricci scalar and $T_{\mu\nu}$ denotes the energy-momentum tensor. The inclusion of quadratic contributions from the energy-momentum components has intriguing cosmological implications, particularly during the Universe's early epochs. These effects dominate under high-energy conditions, enabling EMSG to potentially address unresolved issues in General Relativity (GR), such as the initial singularity and aspects of big-bang nucleosynthesis in certain models. The theory's explicit non-minimal coupling between matter and geometry leads to the non-conservation of the energy-momentum tensor, which prompts the investigation of cosmological scenarios through the framework of irreversible thermodynamics of open systems. By employing this formalism, we interpret the energy-balance equations within EMSG from a thermodynamic perspective, viewing them as descriptions of irreversible matter creation processes. Since EMSG converges to GR in a vacuum and differences emerge only in the presence of an energy-momentum distribution, these distinctions become significant in high-curvature regions. Therefore, deviations from GR are expected to be pronounced in the dense cores of compact objects. This review delves into these facets of EMSG, highlighting its potential to shed light on some of the fundamental questions in modern cosmology and gravitational theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14106v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/universe10090339</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Universe 2024, 10(9), 339</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ricardo A. C. Cipriano, Nailya Ganiyeva, Tiberiu Harko, Francisco S. N. Lobo, Miguel A. S. Pinto, Jo\~ao Lu\'is Rosa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suzaku Observations of the Cold Front in A3667: a Non-Equilibrium Ionization State of the Intracluster Medium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14204</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14204v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a systematic study of the thermodynamic properties of the intracluster medium (ICM), including the plasma conditions in the ICM, in the merging galaxy cluster A3667 using Suzaku. We analyze the X-ray spectra of the ICM between the northwestern and the southeastern radio relics across a prominent cold front in A3667 to search for the ICM in a non-equilibrium ionization (NEI) state. We find that the ICM inside the cold front exhibits an NEI state with an ionization parameter of $(2.5\pm0.7)\times10^{11}\,\mathrm{s\,cm^{-3}}$ at the $90\%$ confidence level, which is lower than that expected from a collisional ionization equilibrium (CIE) state of the ICM (i.e., $n_\mathrm{e}t &gt; 10^{12}\,\mathrm{s\,cm^{-3}}$). The timescale calculated from the ionization parameter of the ICM inside the cold front is $ 4.6\pm1.2\,\mathrm{Myr}$, which is much shorter than the thermal equilibration timescale. A weak transonic sloshing motion might explain the possibility that the ICM inside the cold front of A3667 is in the NEI state. In addition, the NEI state of the ICM in A3667 seems to be associated with the elongated radio halo bridging the region between the northwestern radio relic and the prominent cold front in A3667 across the cluster center.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14204v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mona Shishido, Yuusuke Uchida, Takayoshi Kohmura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Flea on the Elephant: tidal Love numbers in subsolar primordial black hole searches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14207v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Detecting subsolar objects in black hole binary mergers is considered a smoking gun signature of primordial black holes. Their supposedly vanishing tidal Love number is generically thought to help distinguish them from other subsolar and more deformable compact objects, such as neutron stars. We show that a large and detectable Love number of primordial black holes can be generated in the presence of even small disturbances of the system, thus potentially jeopardizing their discovery. However, such small perturbations are not tightly bound and are therefore disrupted before the mergers. We show that they leave a characteristic signature in the gravitational waveform that could be observed with current and future gravitational wave detectors. Thus, they may still hint towards the primordial nature of the black holes in the merger. Finally, we demonstrate that disregarding possible environmental effects in the matched-filter search for subsolar gravitational wave events can lead to a decreased sensitivity in the detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14207v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valerio De Luca, Gabriele Franciolini, Antonio Riotto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tidal deformability of black holes surrounded by thin accretion disks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14208v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The tidal Love numbers of self-gravitating compact objects describe their response to external tidal perturbations, such as those from a companion in a binary system, offering valuable insights into their internal structure. For static tidal fields, asymptotically flat black holes in vacuum exhibit vanishing Love numbers in general relativity, even though this property is sensitive to the presence of an external environment. In this work we study the tidal deformability of black holes surrounded by thin accretion disks, showing that the Love numbers could be large enough to mask any effect of modified gravity and to intrinsically limit tidal tests of black-hole mimickers. Furthermore, we investigate the measurability of the tidal parameters with next-generation gravitational wave experiments, like LISA and Einstein Telescope. Our findings suggest that these parameters could be measured with high precision, providing a powerful tool to probe the environment around coalescing binary systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14208v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrico Cannizzaro, Valerio De Luca, Paolo Pani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GALPs! Composite heavy axion-like Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14245</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14245v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a novel class of Dark Matter (DM) candidates in the form of a heavy composite Axion-Like Particle (ALP) with highly suppressed electromagnetic interactions, being stable even for masses exceeding the GeV scale. We argue that such a composite ALP emerges as a bound state -- the dark glueball -- due to confinement in a pure Yang-Mills dark sector. In a minimal ultraviolet complete QCD-like model, cosmological production of dark gluons as well as photons occurs via heavy fermion annihilation which effectively reheats both the dark and visible sectors setting up their temperature scales. Furthermore, effective interactions between glueballs and photons, resembling those of standard ALPs, are radiatively generated by heavy fermion loops. Consequently, DM glueballs interacting with photons are dubbed `Glueball ALPs' (GALPs). We uncover novel phenomenology of GALPs focusing on their unique astrophysical and cosmological signatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14245v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierluca Carenza, Roman Pasechnik, Zhi-Wei Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinetic Mixing, Proton Decay and Gravitational Waves in SO(10)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14350v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present an $SO(10)$ model in which a dimension five operator induces kinetic mixing at the GUT scale between the abelian subgroups $U(1)_{B-L}$ and $U(1)_R$. We discuss in this framework gauge coupling unification and proton decay, as well as the appearance of superheavy quasistable strings with $G\mu \sim 10^{-8} - 10^{-5}$, where $\mu$ denotes the dimensionless string tension parameter. We use Bayesian analysis to show that for $G\mu$ values $\sim 4 \times 10^{-7} - 10^{-5}$, the gravitational wave spectrum emitted from the quasistable strings is in good agreement with the recent pulsar timing array data. Corresponding to $G \mu$ values $\sim 10^{-8} - 2 \times 10^{-7}$, proton decay is expected to occur at a rate accessible in the Hyper-Kamiokande experiment. Finally, we present the gravitational wave spectrum emitted by effectively stable strings with $G\mu\approx 10^{-8}$ that have experienced a certain amount of inflation. This can be tested with future detectors in the $\mu$Hz frequency range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14350v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rinku Maji, Qaisar Shafi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weighing Milky Way and Andromeda in an expanding $\Lambda$CDM Universe: Decreasing the Local Group mass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.09546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.09546v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The dynamics of the Local Group (LG), especially the contribution of the Milky Way (MW) and Andromeda (M31) galaxies, is sensitive to the presence of dark energy. This work analyzes the evolution of the LG by considering it as a two-body problem in a homogeneous and isotropic expanding spacetime in a full $\Lambda$ cold dark matter $(\Lambda$CDM) background. Using the timing argument (TA), which links LG dynamics to LG mass, we find that the complete $\Lambda$CDM background predicts a $\sim 10 \%$ lower mass for the LG; while $\Lambda$ alone predicts a $\sim 10 \%$ higher mass. The TA mass is modified by (i) simulations and (ii) the effect of the Large Magellanic Cloud (LMC) to alleviate the poorly constrained internal mass distributions of M31 and the MW, their time evolution, and the unknown distribution of dark matter between them. First, using IllustrisTNG simulations, we accounted for the effects of two extended halos and their environment (rather than point particles) and predicted their mass $\left(3.89 \pm 0.62\right) \cdot 10^{12} M_{\odot}$. Second, the LMC effectively changes the separation and velocities of M31 toward the MW and reduces the predicted mass to $\left(2.33 \pm 0.72\right) \cdot 10^{12} M_\odot$. Despite the uncertainties around dark matter between these galaxies, the overall estimated mass is compatible with the mere sum of the MW and M31 masses. The total mass of the TA is compatible with other estimates, such as the Hubble flow and the Virial Theorem with other dwarf galaxies. The combined result shows, for the first time, that a lower mass estimate can be obtained from the TA, with a consistent embedding and other systematic effects, and without an additional dark matter halo around the galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.09546v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202449884</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>David Benisty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmology with Persistent Homology: a Fisher Forecast</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13985v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Persistent homology naturally addresses the multi-scale topological characteristics of the large-scale structure as a distribution of clusters, loops, and voids. We apply this tool to the dark matter halo catalogs from the Quijote simulations, and build a summary statistic for comparison with the joint power spectrum and bispectrum statistic regarding their information content on cosmological parameters and primordial non-Gaussianity. Through a Fisher analysis, we find that constraints from persistent homology are tighter for 8 out of the 10 parameters by margins of 13-50%. The complementarity of the two statistics breaks parameter degeneracies, allowing for a further gain in constraining power when combined. We run a series of consistency checks to consolidate our results, and conclude that our findings motivate incorporating persistent homology into inference pipelines for cosmological survey data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13985v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacky H. T. Yip, Matteo Biagetti, Alex Cole, Karthik Viswanathan, Gary Shiu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Quasar Catalogue for S-PLUS DR4 (QuCatS) and the estimation of photometric redshifts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09925</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09925v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The advent of massive broad-band photometric surveys enabled photometric redshift estimates for unprecedented numbers of galaxies and quasars. These estimates can be improved using better algorithms or by obtaining complementary data such as narrow-band photometry, and broad-band photometry over an extended wavelength range. We investigate the impact of both approaches on photometric redshifts for quasars using data from Southern Photometric Local Universe Survey (S-PLUS) DR4, Galaxy Evolution Explorer (GALEX) DR6/7, and the unWISE catalog for the Wide-field Infrared Survey Explorer (WISE) in three machine learning methods: Random Forest, Flexible Conditional Density Estimation (FlexCoDE), and Bayesian Mixture Density Network (BMDN). Including narrow-band photometry improves the root-mean-square error by 11% in comparison to a model trained with only broad-band photometry. Narrow-band information only provided an improvement of 3.8% when GALEX and WISE colours were included. Thus narrow bands play a more important role for objects that do not have GALEX or WISE counterparts, which respectively makes 92% and 25% of S-PLUS data considered here. Nevertheless, the inclusion of narrow-band information provided better estimates of the probability density functions obtained with FlexCoDE and BMDN. We publicly release a value-added catalogue of photometrically selected quasars with the photo-z predictions from all methods studied here. The catalogue provided with this work covers the S-PLUS DR4 area (~3000deg$^2$), containing 645 980, 244 912, 144 991 sources with the probability of being a quasar higher than, 80%, 90%, 95% up to r &lt; 21.3 and good photometry quality in the detection image. More quasar candidates can be retrieved from the S-PLUS data base by considering less restrictive selection criteria.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09925v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae971</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 2024, 531, 327-339</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>L. Nakazono, R. R. Valen\c{c}a, G. Soares, R. Izbicki, \v{Z}. Ivezi\'c, E. V. R. Lima, N. S. T. Hirata, L. Sodr\'e Jr., R. Overzier, F. Almeida-Fernandes, G. B. Oliveira Schwarz, W. Schoenell, A. Kanaan, T. Ribeiro, C. Mendes de Oliveira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmic Inflation at the Crossroads</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10647</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10647v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The capability of Cosmic Inflation to explain the latest Cosmic Microwave Background and Baryonic Acoustic Oscillation data is assessed by performing Bayesian model comparison within the landscape of nearly three-hundred models of single-field slow-roll inflation. We present the first Bayesian data analysis based on the third-order slow-roll primordial power spectra. In particular, the fourth Hubble-flow function $\epsilon_4$ remains unbounded while the third function verifies, at two-sigma, $\epsilon_{3}\in[-0.4,0.5]$, which is perfectly compatible with the slow-roll predictions for the running of the spectral index. We also observe some residual excess of $B$-modes within the BICEP/Keck data favoring, at a non-statistically significant level, non-vanishing primordial tensor modes: $\log(\epsilon_{1}) &gt; -3.9$, at $68\%$ confidence level. Then, for 283 models of single-field inflation, we compute the Bayesian evidence, the Bayesian dimensionality and the marginalized posteriors of all the models' parameters, including the ones associated with the reheating era. The average information gain on the reheating parameter $R_\mathrm{reh}$ reaches $1.3 \pm 0.18$ bits, which is more than a factor two improvement compared to the first Planck data release. As such, inflationary model predictions cannot meet data accuracy without specifying, or marginalizing over, the reheating kinematics. We also find that more than $40\%$ of the scenarios are now strongly disfavored, which shows that the constraining power of cosmological data is winning against the increase of the number of proposed models. In addition, about $20\%$ of all models have evidences within the most probable region and are all favored according to the Jeffreys' scale of Bayesian evidences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10647v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2024/07/087</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP2407:087,2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jerome Martin, Christophe Ringeval, Vincent Vennin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-redshift, small-scale tests of ultralight axion dark matter using Hubble and Webb galaxy UV luminosities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11071v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We calculate the abundance of UV-bright galaxies in the presence of ultralight axion (ULA) dark matter (DM), finding that axions suppress their formation with a non-trivial dependence on redshift and luminosity. We set limits on axion DM using both Planck cosmic microwave background (CMB) and UV luminosity function (UVLF) data. We exclude a single axion as all the DM for $m_{ax} &lt; 10^{-21.6}$ eV and limit axions with $-26 &lt; \log( m_{ax}/{eV}) &lt; -23$ to be less than $22\%$ of the DM (both limits at $95\%$ credibility). These limits use UVLF measurements from 24,000 sources from the Hubble Space Telescope (HST) that probe small-scale structure at redshifts $4 &lt; z &lt; 10$. We marginalize over a parametric model that connects halo mass and UV luminosity that has been shown to match hydrodynamical simulations. Our results bridge a window in axion mass and DM fraction previously unconstrained by cosmological data, between large-scale CMB and galaxy clustering and the small-scale Lyman-$\alpha$ forest. These high-$z$ measurements provide a powerful consistency check of low-$z$ tests of axion DM, which include the recent hint for a sub-dominant ULA DM fraction in Lyman-$\alpha$ forest data. We also consider a sample of 25 spectroscopically-confirmed high-$z$ galaxies from the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST). We find that these data are consistent with the HST UVLF assuming $\Lambda$CDM and our flexible parametric model of UV luminosity. Combining HST and JWST UVLF data does not improve our constraints beyond HST alone, but future JWST measurements have the potential to improve these results significantly. We also find an excess of low-mass halos ($&lt; 10^9 M_\odot$) at $z &lt; 3$, which could be probed by sub-galactic structure probes (e.g., stellar streams, satellite galaxies and strong lensing).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11071v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harrison Winch, Keir K. Rogers, Ren\'ee Hlo\v{z}ek, David J. E. Marsh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling nonlinear scales with COLA: preparing for LSST-Y1</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12344v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Year 1 results of the Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST) will provide tighter constraints on small-scale cosmology, beyond the validity of linear perturbation theory. This heightens the demand for a computationally affordable prescription that can accurately capture nonlinearities in beyond-$\Lambda$CDM models. The COmoving Lagrangian Acceleration (COLA) method, a cost-effective \textit{N}-body technique, has been proposed as a viable alternative to high-resolution \textit{N}-body simulations for training emulators of the nonlinear matter power spectrum. In this study, we evaluate this approach by employing COLA emulators to conduct a cosmic shear analysis with LSST-Y1 simulated data across three different nonlinear scale cuts. We use the $w$CDM model, for which the \textsc{EuclidEmulator2} (\textsc{ee2}) exists as a benchmark, having been trained with high-resolution \textit{N}-body simulations. We primarily utilize COLA simulations with mass resolution $M_{\rm part}\approx 8 \times 10^{10} ~h^{-1} M_{\odot}$ and force resolution $\ell_{\rm force}=0.5 ~h^{-1}$Mpc, though we also test refined settings with $M_{\rm part}\approx 1 \times 10^{10} ~h^{-1}M_{\odot}$ and force resolution $\ell_{\rm force}=0.17 ~h^{-1}$Mpc. We find the performance of the COLA emulators is sensitive to the placement of high-resolution \textit{N}-body reference samples inside the prior, which only ensure agreement in their local vicinity. However, the COLA emulators pass stringent criteria in goodness-of-fit and parameter bias throughout the prior, when $\Lambda$CDM predictions of \textsc{ee2} are computed alongside every COLA emulator prediction, suggesting a promising approach for extended models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12344v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Gordon, Bernardo F. de Aguiar, Jo\~ao Rebou\c{c}as, Guilherme Brando, Felipe Falciano, Vivian Miranda, Kazuya Koyama, Hans A. Winther</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ELG Spectroscopic Systematics Analysis of the DESI Data Release 1</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.16657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.16657v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) uses more than 2.4 million Emission Line Galaxies (ELGs) for 3D large-scale structure (LSS) analyses in its Data Release 1 (DR1). Such large statistics enable thorough research on systematic uncertainties. In this study, we focus on spectroscopic systematics of ELGs. The redshift success rate ($f_{\rm goodz}$) is the relative fraction of secure redshifts among all measurements. It depends on observing conditions, thus introduces non-cosmological variations to the LSS. We, therefore, develop the redshift failure weight ($w_{\rm zfail}$) and a per-fibre correction ($\eta_{\rm zfail}$) to mitigate these dependences. They have minor influences on the galaxy clustering. For ELGs with a secure redshift, there are two subtypes of systematics: 1) catastrophics (large) that only occur in a few samples; 2) redshift uncertainty (small) that exists for all samples. The catastrophics represent 0.26\% of the total DR1 ELGs, composed of the confusion between O\,\textsc{ii} and sky residuals, double objects, total catastrophics and others. We simulate the realistic 0.26\% catastrophics of DR1 ELGs, the hypothetical 1\% catastrophics, and the truncation of the contaminated $1.31&lt;z&lt;1.33$ in the \textsc{AbacusSummit} ELG mocks. Their $P_\ell$ show non-negligible bias from the uncontaminated mocks. But their influences on the redshift space distortions (RSD) parameters are smaller than $0.2\sigma$. The redshift uncertainty of \Yone ELGs is 8.5 km/s with a Lorentzian profile. The code for implementing the catastrophics and redshift uncertainty on mocks can be found in https://github.com/Jiaxi-Yu/modelling_spectro_sys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.16657v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaxi Yu, Ashley J. Ross, Antoine Rocher, Ot\'avio Alves, Arnaud de Mattia, Daniel Forero-S\'anchez, Jean-Paul Kneib, Alex Krolewski, TingWen Lan, Michael Rashkovetskyi, Jessica Nicole Aguilar, Steven Ahlen, Stephen Bailey, David Brooks, Edmond Chaussidon, Todd Claybaugh, Axel de la Macorra, Arjun Dey, Biprateep Dey, Peter Doel, Kevin Fanning, Jaime E. Forero-Romero, Enrique Gazta\~naga, Satya Gontcho A Gontcho, Klaus Honscheid, Cullan Howlett, Stephanie Juneau, Theodore Kisner, Anthony Kremin, Andrew Lambert, Martin Landriau, Laurent Le Guillou, Michael E. Levi, Marc Manera, Paul Martini, Aaron Meisner, Ramon Miquel, John Moustakas, Eva-Maria Mueller, Andrea Mu\~noz-Guti\'errez, Adam D. Myers, Jundan Nie, Gustavo Niz, Nathalie Palanque-Delabrouille, Will J. Percival, Claire Poppett, Francisco Prada, Mehdi Rezaie, Graziano Rossi, Eusebio Sanchez, Edward F. Schlafly, David Schlegel, Michael Schubnell, Hee-Jong Seo, David Sprayberry, Gregory Tarl\'e, Benjamin A. Weaver, Pauline Zarrouk, Cheng Zhao, Rongpu Zhou, Hu Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new non-parametric method to infer galaxy cluster masses from weak lensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07026</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07026v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a new, non-parametric method to infer deprojected 3D mass profiles $M(r)$ of galaxy clusters from weak gravitational lensing observations. The method assumes spherical symmetry and a moderately small convergence, $\kappa \lesssim 1$. The assumption of spherical symmetry is an important restriction, which is, however, quite common in practice, for example in methods that fit lensing data to an NFW profile. Unlike other methods, our method relies on spherical symmetry only at radii larger than the radius $r$ at which the mass $M$ is inferred. That is, the method works even if there is a non-symmetric inner region. We provide an efficient implementation in Julia code that runs in a few milliseconds per galaxy cluster. We explicitly demonstrate the method by using data from KiDS DR4 to infer mass profiles for two example clusters, Abell 1835 and Abell 2744, finding results consistent with existing literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07026v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Mistele, Amel Durakovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observational evidence for Early Dark Energy as a unified explanation for Cosmic Birefringence and the Hubble tension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.09521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.09521v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We test the $n$=3 Ultralight Axion-like model of Early Dark Energy (EDE) with the observations of the $EB$ mode of the cosmic microwave background (CMB) radiation, and local expansion rate measurements. We find that the shape of the CMB $EB$ angular power spectrum is sensitive to the background cosmological parameters. Unlike previous articles which fix the background cosmology and fit % \lu{with fitting} the coupling constant and rotation angles, we run Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) simulations to fit the $\Lambda$CDM + EDE parameters simultaneously. We find that the EDE model with $n$=3 can provide a good fit to the observed CMB $EB$ spectra, consistent with a Hubble constant value that is in good agreement with the locally measured value. Our result is the first to show that axion-like EDE can provide a unified explanation for the observed cosmic birefringence and the Hubble tension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.09521v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joby Kochappan, Lu Yin, Bum-Hoon Lee, Tuhin Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hubble Tension or Distance Ladder Crisis?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11031v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present an up-to-date compilation of published Hubble constant ($H_0$) measurements that are independent of the CMB sound horizon scale. This compilation is split in two distinct groups: A. Distance Ladder Measurements sample comprising of 19 recent measurements, primarily from the past four years, utilizing various rung 2 calibrators and rung 3 cosmic distance indicators. B.One-Step Measurements sample including 31 measurements of $H_0$ that are independent of both the CMB sound horizon scale and the distance ladder approach. These 31 measurements are derived from diverse probes such as Cosmic Chronometers, gamma-ray attenuation, strong lensing, megamasers etc. Statistical analysis reveals a significant distinction between the two samples. The distance ladder-based sample yields a best fit $H_0 = 72.76 \pm 0.50$ km s$^{-1}$ Mpc$^{-1}$ with $\chi^2/dof=0.52$ indicating some correlations. The one-step measurements result in $H_0 = 69.01 \pm 0.49$ km s$^{-1}$ Mpc$^{-1}$ with $\chi^2/dof=1.43$ indicating some internal tension. If two outlier measurements are removed (TDCOSMO.I-2019 known to have systematics and MCP-2020) the best fit of the one step sample reduces to $H_0 = 68.3 \pm 0.5$ km s$^{-1}$ Mpc$^{-1}$ with $\chi^2/dof=1.01$, fully self-consistent and consistent with sound horizon based measurements. A Kolmogorov-Smirnov test yields a p-value of 0.0001 suggesting that the two samples are fundamentally distinct, with a probability of less than 0.01% that they are drawn from the same underlying distribution. These findings suggest that the core of the Hubble tension lies not between early and late-time measurements, but between distance ladder measurements and all other $H_0$ determinations. This discrepancy points to either a systematic effect influencing all distance ladder measurements or a fundamental physics anomaly affecting at least one rung of the distance ladder.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11031v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leandros Perivolaropoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing the Speed of Gravity with Black Hole Ringdown</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.10272</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.10272v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate how the speed of gravitational waves, $c_{GW}$, can be tested by upcoming black hole ringdown observations. We do so in the context of hairy black hole solutions, where the hair is associated with a new scalar degree of freedom, forecasting that LISA and TianQin will be able to constrain deviations of $c_{GW}$ from the speed of light at the ${\cal O}(10^{-4})$ level from a single supermassive black hole merger. We discuss how these constraints depend on the nature of the scalar hair, what different aspects of the underlying physics they are sensitive to in comparison with constraints derived from gravitational wave propagation effects, which observable systems will place the most stringent bounds, and that constraints are expected to improve by up to two orders of magnitude with multiple observations. This is especially interesting for dark energy-related theories, where existing bounds from GW170817 need not apply at lower frequencies and where upcoming bounds from lower-frequency missions will therefore be especially powerful. As such, we also forecast analogous bounds for the intermediate-frequency AEDGE and DECIGO missions. Finally, we discuss and forecast analogous black hole ringdown constraints at higher frequencies (so from LVK, the Einstein Telescope and Cosmic Explorer) and in what circumstances they can yield new information on top of existing constraints on $c_{GW}$. All calculations performed in this paper are reproducible via a companion Mathematica notebook.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.10272v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.107.124054</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 107, 124054, Published 28 June 2023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sergi Sirera, Johannes Noller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical anisotropy of primordial gravitational waves from generalized $\delta N$ formalism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.08497</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.08497v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this letter, we demonstrate how to use the generalized $\delta N$ formalism, which enables us to compute the evolution of all the large scale fluctuations, including gravitational waves, solely by solving the evolution of the background homogeneous Universe. Using the Noether charge density, we derive an analytic formula which describes the mapping between the fluctuations at the horizon crossing and the sourced gravitational waves at the end of inflation. This formula can apply also to an inflation model with an anisotropic background. Using this formula, we discuss the condition for the non-vanishing linear polarization and the qualitative difference between single- and multi-gauge field models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.08497v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takahiro Tanaka, Yuko Urakawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Bursty Star Formation on [CII] Line Intensity Mapping of High-redshift Galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.04204</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.04204v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Bursty star formation -- a key prediction for high-redshift galaxies from cosmological simulations explicitly resolving stellar feedback in the interstellar medium -- has recently been observed to prevail among galaxies at redshift $z \gtrsim 6$. Line intensity mapping (LIM) of the 158 $\mu$m [CII] line as a star formation rate (SFR) indicator offers unique opportunities to tomographically constrain cosmic star formation at high redshift, in a way complementary to observations of individually detected galaxies. To understand effects of bursty star formation on [CII] LIM, which remain unexplored in previous studies, we present an analytic modeling framework for high-$z$ galaxy formation and [CII] LIM signals that accounts for bursty star formation histories induced by delayed supernova feedback. We use it to explore and characterize how bursty star formation can impact and thus complicate the interpretation of the [CII] luminosity function and power spectrum. Our simple analytic model indicates that bursty star formation mainly affects low-mass galaxies by boosting their average SFR and [CII] luminosity, and in the [CII] power spectrum it can create a substantial excess in the large-scale clustering term. This distortion results in a power spectrum shape which cannot be explained by invoking a mass-independent logarithmic scatter. We conclude that burstiness must be accounted for when modeling and analyzing [CII] datasets from the early universe, and that in the extreme, the signature of burstiness may be detectable with first-generation experiments such as TIME, CONCERTO, and CCAT-DSS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.04204v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lun-Jun Liu, Guochao Sun, Tzu-Ching Chang, Steven R. Furlanetto, Charles M. Bradford</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational particle production and the Hubble tension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.16791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.16791v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The effect of gravitational particle production of scalar particles on the total effective cosmic energy density (in the era after photon decoupling till the present) is considered. The effect is significant for heavy particles. It is found that gravitational particle production results in an effective increase in the directly measured value of the Hubble constant $H_0$ while it does not affect the value of the Hubble constant in the calculation of the number density of baryons at present time that is used to calculate recombination redshift. This may explain why the Hubble constant determined by local measurements and non-local measurements (such as CMB) are different. This suggests that gravitational particle production may have a non-negligible impact on the $H_0$ tension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.16791v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/universe10090338</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Universe 2024, 10, 338</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Recai Erdem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tilt in quadratic gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10377v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, tilted source solutions in both Einstein-Hilbert General Relativity (GR) and Quadratic Gravity (QG) for the anisotropic Bianchi V model are addressed. Since the excellent CMBR match of Starobinsky's inflation with Planck's team measurements data, QG has acquired a prominent status in the effective sense, for sufficiently strong gravity fields. The main interest is in the numeric time evolution to the past towards the singularity and the behavior of the kinematic variables, vorticity, acceleration, and the expansion of this source substance. In QG we found that for universes with higher and smaller matter densities fall into the Kasner or isotropic singularity attractors to the past, respectively. We also found that the Kasner singularity attractor to the past has always zero vorticity, for both GR and QG theories. While for QG the isotropic singularity attractor may have divergent vorticity. For the set of assumptions and conditions supposed in this work, the isotropic singularity attractor, favors QG as compared to GR. Only in QG we were able to find a geometric singularity with divergences in all of the kinematic variables of the substance, decreasing to finite values to the future, upon time reversing. That is, we obtained an initial kinematic singularity substance, that approaches a perfect fluid source.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10377v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-024-13171-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Volume 84, article number 843, (2024), European Physical Journal C</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Waleska P. F. de Medeiros, Matheus J. Lazo, Daniel M\"uller, Dinalva A. Sales</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting a Gravitational-Wave Background from Inflation with Null Energy Condition Violation: Prospects for Taiji</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08375</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.08375v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The null energy condition (NEC) is a fundamental principle in general relativity, and its violation could leave discernible signatures in gravitational waves (GWs). A violation of the NEC during the primordial era would imprint a blue-tilted spectrum on the stochastic gravitational wave background (SGWB) at nanohertz frequencies, potentially accounting for the recently detected signal by pulsar timing arrays. Remarkably, models of NEC violation during inflation also predict a nearly scale-invariant GW spectrum in the millihertz frequency range, which could be detectable by upcoming space-based GW detectors such as Taiji. The observation of this distinctive spectrum would provide compelling evidence for new physics beyond the standard cosmological paradigm. In this study, we explore Taiji's ability to detect an SGWB arising from NEC violation during inflation, considering various foregrounds and noise sources, including an extragalactic foreground from binary black hole mergers throughout the universe, a galactic foreground from white dwarf binaries, and the intrinsic noise of the Taiji detector. Employing comprehensive Bayesian parameter estimation techniques to analyze simulated Taiji data, we demonstrate a remarkable precision improvement of three orders of magnitude compared to the NANOGrav 15-year data set for measuring the tensor power spectrum amplitude, $P_{T,2}$, during the second inflationary stage. This substantial enhancement in measurement capabilities underscores Taiji's potential as a powerful probe for investigating the NEC violation in the early Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.08375v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zu-Cheng Chen, Lang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charged analog of anisotropic dark energy star in Rastall gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13538</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.13538v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dark energy is one of the potential strategies for preventing compact objects from gravitationally collapsing into singularities. Because it is the cause of the accelerated expansion of our universe, it has the greatest impact on the cosmos. Thus, it is plausible that dark energy will interact with any stellar object that is compact in the universe [\textit{Phys. Rev. D} \textbf{103}, 084042 (2021)]. Our main goal in this work is to create a simplified model, in the Rastall gravitational framework, of a charged strange star coupled to anisotropic dark energy in Krori-Barua spacetime [\textit{J. Phys. A, Math. Gen.} \textbf{8}:508, 1975]. Here, we consider a specific strange star object, Her X-1, with observed values of mass $=(0.85 \pm 0.15)M_{\odot}$ and radius $= 8.1_{-0.41}^{+0.41}$ km., so that we can develop our model. In this context, we began by modeling dark energy using the equation of state (EoS), in which the dark energy density is proportional to the isotropic perfect fluid matter-energy density. The Darmois-Israel condition has been used to calculate the unknown constants that are present in the metric. We perform a detailed analysis of the model's physical properties, including the mass-radius relation, pressure, density, metric function, and dark energy parameters, by varying the Rastall coupling parameter. We also examine the stability and force equilibrium of our proposed stellar configuration. Following a comprehensive theoretical analysis, we discovered that our suggested model is both singularity-free and meets all stability requirements needed to be a stable, physically reasonable stellar model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.13538v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pramit Rej</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the fermion-field nontopological solitons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01227</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01227v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Nontopological fermionic solitons exist across a diverse range of particle physics models and have rich cosmological implications. This study establishes a general framework for calculating fermionic soliton profiles under arbitrary scalar potentials, utilizing relativistic mean field theory to accurately depict the interaction between the fermion condensate and the background scalar field. Within this framework, the conventional fermion bound states are revealed as a subset of fermionic solitons. In addition, we demonstrate how the analytical formulae in previous studies are derived as special cases of our algorithm, discussing the validity of such approximations. Furthermore, we explore the phenomenology of fermionic solitons, highlighting new formation mechanisms and evolution paths, and reconsidering the possibility of collapse into primordial black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01227v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ke-Pan Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Axion Stars: Mass Functions and Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09499</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09499v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The QCD axion and axion-like particles, as leading dark matter candidates, can also have interesting implications for dark matter substructures if the Peccei-Quinn symmetry is broken after inflation. In such a scenario, axion perturbations on small scales will lead to the formation of axion miniclusters at matter-radiation equality, and subsequently the formation of axion stars. Such compact objects open new windows for indirect searches for axions. We compute the axion star mass function based on recent axion minicluster studies and Bose star simulations. Applying this mass function, we find post-inflation axion-like particles with masses $1.8 \times 10^{-21}~{\rm eV}&lt;m_a&lt; 3.3 \times 10^{-17}~{\rm eV}$ are constrained by the lack of dynamical heating of stars in ultrafaint dwarfs. We also find that current microlensing surveys are insensitive to QCD axion stars. While we focus on the gravitational detectability of axion stars, our result can be directly applied to other interesting signatures of axion stars, e.g. their decay to photons, that require as input the abundance, mass, and density distribution of axion stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09499v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jae Hyeok Chang, Patrick J. Fox, Huangyu Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Sector Tunneling Field Potentials for a Dark Big Bang</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05752</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05752v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: All of the significant evidence for dark matter observed thus far has been through its gravitational interactions. After 40 years of direct detection experiments, the parameter space for Weakly Interacting Massive Particles (WIMPs) as dark matter candidates is rapidly approaching the neutrino floor. In this light, we consider a dark sector that is strongly decoupled from the visible sector, interacting exclusively through gravity. In this model, proposed by Freese and Winkler (arXiv:2302.11579), dark matter can be produced through a first-order phase transition in the dark sector dubbed the Dark Big Bang. In this study we fully determine the allowed region of parameter space for the tunneling potential that leads to the realization of a Dark Big Bang and is consistent with all experimental bounds available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05752v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Richard Casey, Cosmin Ilie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Excluding Primordial Black Holes as Dark Matter Based on Solar System Ephemeris</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10799</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10799v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Current cosmological constraints allow primordial black holes (PBHs) to constitute dark matter in the mass range of $10^{18}$-$10^{22}$g. We show that a major portion of this logarithmic window can be ruled-out based on the Solar System ephemeris, given that the external mass enclosed within 50 au from the Sun did not change by more than $\sim 5\times 10^{-14}$ solar masses per year in recent decades.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10799v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abraham Loeb (Harvard)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unitarity, Causality, and Solar System Bounds, Significantly Limit Using Gravitational Waves to Test General Relativity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12118v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The prospect of detecting/constraining deviations from general relativity by studying gravitational waves (GWs) from merging black holes has been one of the primary motivations of GW interferometers like LIGO/Virgo. Within pure gravity, the only possible way deviations can arise is from the existence of higher order derivative corrections, namely higher powers of the Riemann curvature tensor, in the effective action. Any observational bounds imply constraints on the corresponding Wilson coefficients. At the level of the action, one can imagine the coefficients are sufficiently large so as to be in principle detectable. However, from the point of view of some fundamental principles, namely causality and unitarity, this is much less clear, as we examine here. We begin by reviewing certain known bounds on these coefficients, which together imply a low cut off on the effective theory. We then consider a possible mechanism to generate such terms, namely in the form of many minimally coupled light scalars that can be integrated out to give these higher order operators. We show that a by product of this is the generation of quantum corrections to Newton's potential, whose observable consequences are already ruled out by solar system tests. We point out that over 7 orders of magnitude of improvement in interferometer sensitivity would be required to avoid such solar system constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12118v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Cassem, Mark P. Hertzberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
