<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO</link>
    <description>astro-ph.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 04:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Supermassive black holes from inflation constrained by dark matter substructure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11098</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11098v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent James Webb Space Telescope observations of high-redshift massive galaxy candidates have initiated renewed interest in the important mystery around the formation and evolution of our Universe's largest supermassive black holes (SMBHs). We consider the possibility that some of them were seeded by the direct collapse of primordial density perturbations from inflation into primordial black holes and analyze the consequences of this on current dark matter substructures assuming non-Gaussian primordial curvature perturbation distributions. We derive bounds on the enhanced curvature perturbation amplitude from the number of dwarf spheroidal galaxies in our Galaxy, observations of stellar streams and gravitational lensing. We find this bound region significantly overlaps with that required for SMBH seed formation and enables us to probe Gaussian and non-Gaussian curvature perturbations corresponding to the SMBH seeds in the range ${\cal O}(10^5$-$10^{12}) M_\odot$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11098v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shin'ichiro Ando, Shyam Balaji, Malcolm Fairbairn, Nagisa Hiroshima, Koji Ishiwata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic Alignments and Spin Correlations of [OII] Emitters at $z=1.2$ and $z=1.5$ from HSC Narrow-band Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11462v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Galaxies are known to be aligned toward specific directions within the large-scale structure. Such alignment signals become important for controlling the systematics of weak lensing surveys and for constraining galaxy formation and evolution scenarios. We measure the galaxy-ellipticity and ellipticity-ellipticity correlation functions for blue star-forming galaxies at $z=1.19$ and $z=1.47$ that are selected by detecting [OII] emission lines in narrow-band filters of the Hyper Suprime-Cam on the Subaru Telescope. Assuming that disk galaxies are thin and rotation-supported, we also measure the spin correlation function by estimating spin directions with ellipticities and position angles. Above $1 \; h^{-1}{\rm Mpc}$, we do not find significant signals for galaxy-ellipticity, ellipticity-ellipticity, or spin correlations at both redshifts. Below $1 \; h^{-1}{\rm Mpc}$, a weak deviation from zero is seen at $z=1.47$, implying weak spin-filament correlations, but it is not verified by the direct comparison between angles of spins and filaments. The linear alignment model fit yields the amplitude parameter $A_{\rm NLA}=1.38\pm2.32$ at $z=1.19$ and $0.45\pm2.09$ at $z=1.47$ ($95\%$ confidence levels). We discuss various observational and physical origins that affect the search for alignments of disk galaxies at high redshifts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11462v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Motonari Tonegawa, Teppei Okumura, Masao Hayashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JWST Validates HST Distance Measurements: Selection of Supernova Subsample Explains Differences in JWST Estimates of Local H0</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11770</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11770v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: JWST provides new opportunities to cross-check the HST Cepheid/SNeIa distance ladder, which yields the most precise local measure of H0. We analyze early JWST subsamples (~1/4 of the HST sample) from the SH0ES and CCHP groups, calibrated by a single anchor (N4258). We find HST Cepheid distances agree well (~1 sigma) with all 8 combinations of methods, samples, and telescopes: JWST Cepheids, TRGB, and JAGB by either group, plus HST TRGB and Miras. The comparisons explicitly include the measurement uncertainty of each method in N4258, an oft-neglected but dominant term. Mean differences are ~0.03 mag, far smaller than the 0.18 mag "Hubble tension." Combining all measures produces the strongest constraint yet on the linearity of HST Cepheid distances, 0.994+-0.010, ruling out distance-dependent bias or offset as the source of the tension at ~7 sigma. Yet, measurements of H0 from current JWST subsamples produce large sampling differences whose size and direction we can directly estimate from the full HST set. We show that Delta(H0)~2.5 km/s/Mpc between the CCHP JWST program and the full HST sample is entirely consistent with differences in sample selection. Combining all JWST samples produces a new, distance-limited set of 16 SNeIa at D&lt;25 Mpc and more closely resembles the full sample thanks to "reversion to the mean" of larger samples. Using JWST Cepheids, JAGB, and TRGB, we find 73.4+-2.1, 72.2+-2.2, and 72.1+-2.2 km/s/Mpc, respectively. Explicitly accounting for SNe in common, the combined-sample three-method result from JWST is H0=72.6+-2.0, similar to H0=72.8 expected from HST Cepheids in the same galaxies. The small JWST sample trivially lowers the Hubble tension significance due to small-sample statistics and is not yet competitive with the HST set (42 SNeIa and 4 anchors), which yields 73.2+-0.9. Still, the joint JWST sample provides important crosschecks which the HST data passes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11770v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam G. Riess, Dan Scolnic, Gagandeep S. Anand, Louise Breuval, Stefano Casertano, Lucas M. Macri, Siyang Li, Wenlong Yuan, Caroline D. Huang, Saurabh Jha, Yukei S. Murakami, Rachael Beaton, Dillon Brout, Tianrui Wu, Graeme E. Addison, Charles Bennett, Richard I. Anderson, Alexei V. Filippenko, Anthony Carr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing Gravity with Realistic Gravitational Waveforms in Pulsar Timing Arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11774v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the effects of relaxing the assumption that gravitational waves composing the stochastic gravitational wave background (SGWB) are uncorrelated between frequencies in analyses of the data from Pulsar Timing Arrays (PTAs). While individual monochromatic plane waves are often a good approximation, a background composed of astrophysical sources cannot be monochromatic since an infinite plane wave carries no signal. We consider how relaxing this assumption allows us to extract potential information about modified dispersion relations and other fundamental physics questions, as both the group and phase velocity of waves become relevant. After developing the formalism we carry out simple Gaussian wavepacket examples and then consider more realistic waveforms, such as that from binary inspirals. When the frequency evolves only slowly across the PTA temporal baseline, the monochromatic assumption at an effective mean frequency remains a good approximation and we provide scaling relations that characterize its accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11774v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wayne Hu, Qiuyue Liang, Meng-Xiang Lin, Mark Trodden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CRKSPH - A Conservative Reproducing Kernel Smoothed Particle Hydrodynamics Scheme</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1605.00725</link>
      <description>arXiv:1605.00725v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a formulation of smoothed particle hydrodynamics (SPH) that utilizes a first-order consistent reproducing kernel, a smoothing function that exactly interpolates linear fields with particle tracers. Previous formulations using reproducing kernel (RK) interpolation have had difficulties maintaining conservation of momentum due to the fact the RK kernels are not, in general, spatially symmetric. Here, we utilize a reformulation of the fluid equations such that mass, linear momentum, and energy are all rigorously conserved without any assumption about kernel symmetries, while additionally maintaining approximate angular momentum conservation. Our approach starts from a rigorously consistent interpolation theory, where we derive the evolution equations to enforce the appropriate conservation properties, at the sacrifice of full consistency in the momentum equation. Additionally, by exploiting the increased accuracy of the RK method's gradient, we formulate a simple limiter for the artificial viscosity that reduces the excess diffusion normally incurred by the ordinary SPH artificial viscosity. Collectively, we call our suite of modifications to the traditional SPH scheme Conservative Reproducing Kernel SPH, or CRKSPH. CRKSPH retains many benefits of traditional SPH methods (such as preserving Galilean invariance and manifest conservation of mass, momentum, and energy) while improving on many of the shortcomings of SPH, particularly the overly aggressive artificial viscosity and zeroth-order inaccuracy. We compare CRKSPH to two different modern SPH formulations (pressure based SPH and compatibly differenced SPH), demonstrating the advantages of our new formulation when modeling fluid mixing, strong shock, and adiabatic phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1605.00725v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jcp.2016.12.004</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>CRKSPH - A Conservative Reproducing Kernel Smoothed Particle Hydrodynamics Scheme, J. Comput. Phys. 332 (2017) 160-209</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas Frontiere, Cody D. Raskin, J. Michael Owen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic thermodynamic relation for dissipative and non-dissipative universes in a flat FLRW cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11279v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: To clarify a holographic modified thermodynamic relation, the present study applies a general formulation for cosmological equations in a flat FLRW universe to the first law of thermodynamics, using the Bekenstein-Hawking entropy $S_{\rm{BH}}$ and a dynamical Kodama-Hayward temperature $T_{\rm{KH}}$. For the general formulation, both an effective pressure $p_{e}$ of cosmological fluids for dissipative universes (e.g., bulk viscous cosmology) and an extra driving term $f_{\Lambda}(t)$ for non-dissipative universes (e.g., time-varying $\Lambda (t)$ cosmology) are phenomenologically assumed. When $f_{\Lambda}(t)$ is constant, the modified thermodynamic relation is equivalent to the formulation of the first law in standard cosmology. One side of this modified relation describes thermodynamic quantities in the bulk and can be divided into two time-derivative terms, namely $\dot{\rho}$ and $\dot{V}$ terms, where $\rho$ is the mass density of cosmological fluids and $V$ is the Hubble volume. Using the Gibbons-Hawking temperature $T_{\rm{GH}}$, the other side of this relation, $T_{\rm{KH}} \dot{S}_{\rm{BH}}$, can be formulated as the sum of $T_{\rm{GH}} \dot{S}_{\rm{BH}}$ and $[(T_{\rm{KH}}/T_{\rm{GH}}) -1] T_{\rm{GH}} \dot{S}_{\rm{BH}}$, which are equivalent to the $\dot{\rho}$ and $\dot{V}$ terms, respectively, with the magnitude of the $\dot{V}$ term being proportional to the square of the $\dot{\rho}$ term. In addition, the modified thermodynamic relation for constant $f_{\Lambda}(t)$ is examined by applying the equipartition law of energy on the horizon. This modified thermodynamic relation reduces to a kind of extended holographic-like connection when a constant $T_{\rm{KH}}$ universe is considered. The evolution of thermodynamic quantities is also discussed, using a constant $T_{\rm{KH}}$ model, extending a previous analysis [Phys. Rev. D 108, 083515 (2023) (arXiv:2306.11285)].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11279v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nobuyoshi Komatsu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From 100 MHz to 10 GHz: Unveiling the spectral evolution of the X-shaped radio galaxy in Abell 3670</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11377v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: X-shaped radio galaxies (XRGs) are characterised by two pairs of misaligned lobes, namely the active lobes hosting radio jets and the wings. None of the formation mechanisms proposed so far can exhaustively reproduce the diverse features observed among XRGs. The emerging evidence is the existence of sub-populations of XRGs forming via different processes. The brightest cluster galaxy in Abell 3670 (A3670) is a dumbbell system hosting the XRG MRC 2011-298. The morphological and spectral properties of this interesting XRG have been first characterised through Karl G. Jansky Very Large Array (JVLA) data at 1-10 GHz. In the present work, we followed-up MRC 2011-298 with the upgraded Giant Metrewave Radio Telescope (uGMRT) at 120-800 MHz to further constrain its properties and origin. We carried out a detailed spectral analysis sampling different spatial scales. Integrated radio spectra, spectral index maps, radio colour-colour diagrams, and radiative age maps of both the active lobes and prominent wings have been employed to test the origin of the source. We confirm a progressive spectral steepening from the lobes to the wings. The maximum radiative age of the source is $\sim 80$ Myr, with the wings being older than the lobes by $\gtrsim 30$ Myr in their outermost regions. The observed properties are in line with an abrupt reorientation of the jets by $\sim 90$ deg from the direction of the wings to their present position. This formation mechanism is further supported by the comparison with numerical simulations in the literature, which additionally highlight the role of hydrodynamic processes in the evolution of large wings such as those of MRC 2011-298. Potentially, the coalescence of supermassive black holes could have triggered the spin-flip of the jets. Moreover, we show that the S-shape of the radio jets is likely driven by precession with a period $P \sim 10$ Myr.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11377v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Bruno, M. Brienza, A. Zanichelli, M. Gitti, F. Ubertosi, K. Rajpurohit, T. Venturi, D. Dallacasa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classicality of Stochastic Noise Away From Quasi-de Sitter Inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11640v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It is well known that a coarse-grained scalar field living on a de~Sitter (dS) background exhibits classical stochastic behavior, driven by a noise whose amplitude is set by the Hubble constant $H$. The coarse-graining is achieved by discarding wave numbers larger than a cutoff $\sigma H$ and demanding that $\sigma \ll 1$. Similar results hold for quasi-dS space, where the equation of state parameter $w$ is close to $-1$. Here we present exact expressions for the noise amplitude of a free massless field on an inflationary background with constant $w &lt; -1/3$. We find that a classical stochastic behavior can emerge for $-5/3 &lt; w &lt; -1/3$. Furthermore, as we move away from $w = -1$ and approach $w = -1/3$, the constraint $\sigma \ll 1$ is relaxed and larger cutoffs ($\sigma \sim 1$) become feasible, too. However, in general the amplitude of the noise depends on $\sigma$, except in the quasi-dS regime $w \approx -1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11640v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahdiyar Noorbala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observational Constraints on Extended Starobinsky and Weyl Gravity Model of Inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.01010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.01010v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present constraints on the extended Starobinsky and Weyl gravity model of inflation using updated available observational data. The data includes cosmic microwave background (CMB) anisotropy measurements from Planck and BICEP/Keck 2018 (BK18), as well as large-scale structure data encompassing cosmic shear and galaxy autocorrelation and cross-correlation functions measurements from Dark Energy Survey (DES), baryonic acoustic oscillation (BAO) measurements from 6dF, MGS and BOSS, and distance measurements from supernovae type Ia from Pantheon+ samples. By introducing a single additional parameter, each model extends the Starobinsky model to encompass larger region of parameter space while remaining consistent with all observational data. Our findings demonstrate that the inclusion of higher-order terms loosen the constraint on the upper bound of $e$-folding number $N_{\rm e}$ due to the presence of small additional parameter. The maximum limit on $N_{\rm e}$ could be refined by considering the reheating process to $N_{\rm e}&lt;55-59$ for $k_{*}=0.002, 0.05$ Mpc$^{-1}$. These models extend viable range of tensor-to-scalar ratio~($r$) to very small value $r&lt;0.002$ in contrast to the original $R^2$ Starobinsky model. In addition, our results continue to emphasize the tension in $H_0$ and $S_8$ between early-time CMB measurements and late-time large-scale structure observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.01010v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jheap.2024.07.005</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Piyabut Burikham, Teeraparb Chantavat, Pongsapat Boonaom</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Addressing the Hubble tension in Yukawa cosmology?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.02512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.02512v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In Yukawa cosmology, a recent discovery revealed a relationship between baryonic matter and the dark sector. The relation is described by the parameter {\alpha} and the long-range interaction parameter {\lambda} - an intrinsic property of the graviton. Applying the uncertainty relation to the graviton raises a compelling question: Is there a quantum mechanical limit to the measurement precision of the Hubble constant (H0)? We argue that the uncertainty relation for the graviton wavelength {\lambda} can be used to explain a running of H0 with redshift. We show that the uncertainty in time has an inverse correlation with the value of the Hubble constant. That means that the measurement of the Hubble constant is intrinsically linked to length scales (redshift) and is connected to the uncertainty in time. On cosmological scales, we found that the uncertainty in time is related to the look-back time quantity. For measurements with a high redshift value, there is more uncertainty in time, which leads to a smaller value for the Hubble constant. Conversely, there is less uncertainty in time for local measurements with a smaller redshift value, resulting in a higher value for the Hubble constant. Therefore, due to the uncertainty relation, the Hubble tension is believed to arise from fundamental limitations inherent in cosmological measurements. Finally, our findings indicate that the mass of the graviton fluctuates with specific scales, suggesting a possible mass-varying mechanism for the graviton.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.02512v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.dark.2024.101584</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physics of the Dark Universe, 2024, 101584, ISSN 2212-6864</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kimet Jusufi (State U., Tetova), Esteban Gonz\'alez (Catolica del Norte U.), Genly Leon (Catolica del Norte U.,DUT, Durban)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A comparison between Shapefit compression and Full-Modelling method with PyBird for DESI 2024 and beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07283v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: DESI aims to provide one of the tightest constraints on cosmological parameters by analysing the clustering of more than thirty million galaxies. However, obtaining such constraints requires special care in validating the methodology and efforts to reduce the computational time required through data compression and emulation techniques. In this work, we perform a rigorous validation of the PyBird power spectrum modelling code with both a traditional emulated Full-Modelling approach and the model-independent ShapeFit compression approach. By using cubic box simulations that accurately reproduce the clustering and precision of the DESI survey, we find that the cosmological constraints from ShapeFit and Full-Modelling are consistent with each other at the $\sim0.5\sigma$ level for the $\Lambda$CDM model. Both ShapeFit and Full-Modelling are also consistent with the true $\Lambda$CDM simulation cosmology down to a scale of $k_{\mathrm{max}} = 0.20 h\mathrm{Mpc}^{-1}$ even after including the hexadecapole. For extended models such as the wCDM and the oCDM models, we find that including the hexadecapole can significantly improve the constraints and reduce the modelling errors with the same $k_{\mathrm{max}}$. While their discrepancies between the constraints from ShapeFit and Full-Modelling are more significant than $\Lambda$CDM, they remain consistent within $0.7\sigma$. Lastly, we also show that the constraints on cosmological parameters with the correlation function evaluated from PyBird down to $s_{\mathrm{min}} = 30 h^{-1} \mathrm{Mpc}$ are unbiased and consistent with the constraints from the power spectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07283v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. Lai, C. Howlett, M. Maus, H. Gil-Mar\'in, H. E. Noriega, S. Ram\'irez-Solano, P. Zarrouk, J. Aguilar, S. Ahlen, O. Alves, A. Aviles, D. Brooks, S. Chen, T. Claybaugh, T. M. Davis, K. Dawson, A. de la Macorra, P. Doel, J. E. Forero-Romero, E. Gazta\~naga, S. Gontcho A Gontcho, K. Honscheid, S. Juneau, M. Landriau, M. Manera, R. Miquel, E. Mueller, S. Nadathur, G. Niz, N. Palanque-Delabrouille, W. Percival, C. Poppett, M. Rezaie, G. Rossi, E. Sanchez, M. Schubnell, D. Sprayberry, G. Tarl\'e, M. Vargas-Maga\~na, L. Verde, S. Yuan, R. Zhou, H. Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Damping wings in the Lyman-{\alpha} forest: a model-independent measurement of the neutral fraction at 5.4&lt;z&lt;6.1</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12273v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent observations have positioned the endpoint of the Epoch of Reionisation (EoR) at redshift $z \sim 5.3$. However, observations of the Lyman-$\alpha$ forest have not yet been able to discern whether reionisation occurred slowly and late, with substantial neutral hydrogen persisting at redshift $\sim 6$, or rapidly and earlier, with the apparent late end driven by the fluctuating UV background. Gunn-Peterson (GP) absorption troughs are solid indicators that reionisation is not complete until $z=5.3$, but whether they contain significantly neutral gas has not yet been proven. We aim to answer this question by directly measuring, for the first time, the neutral hydrogen fraction ($x_\mathrm{HI}$) at the end of the EoR ($5 \lesssim z \lesssim 6$) in high-redshift quasars spectra. For high neutral fractions $x_\mathrm{HI}\gtrsim0.1$, GP troughs exhibit damping wing (DW) absorption extending over $1000$ km s$^{-1}$ beyond the troughs. While conclusively detected in Lyman-$\alpha$ emission lines of quasars at $z\geq7$, DWs are challenging to observe in the general Lyman-$\alpha$ forest due to absorption complexities and small-scale stochastic transmission features. We report the first successful identification of the stochastic DW signal adjacent to GP troughs at redshifts $z=5.6$ through careful stacking of the dark gaps in Lyman-$\alpha$ forest. We use the signal to present a measurement of the corresponding global $x_\mathrm{HI}=0.19\pm0.07$ $(_{-0.16}^{+0.11})$ at $1\sigma$ $(2\sigma)$ at $z=5.6$ and a limit $x_\mathrm{HI}&lt;0.44$ at $z=5.9$. The detection of this signal demonstrates the existence of substantially neutral islands near the conclusion of the EoR, unequivocally signaling a late-and-slow reionization scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12273v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202450798</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A 688, L26 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Benedetta Spina, Sarah E. I. Bosman, Frederick B. Davies, Prakash Gaikwad, Yongda Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hubble Tension or Distance Ladder Crisis?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11031v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present an up-to-date compilation of published Hubble constant ($H_0$) measurements that are independent of the CMB sound horizon scale. This compilation is categorized into two distinct groups: A. Distance Ladder Measurements: This group comprises 19 recent measurements, primarily from the past four years, utilizing various rung 2 calibrators and rung 3 cosmic distance indicators. B.One-Step Measurements: This category includes 31 measurements of $H_0$ that are independent of both the CMB sound horizon scale and the distance ladder approach. These are derived from diverse probes such as Cosmic Chronometers, gamma-ray attenuation, time-delay strong lensing, megamasers etc. Statistical analysis reveals a significant distinction between these two groups. The distance ladder-based measurements yield a weighted mean $H_0 = 72.76 \pm 0.50$ km s$^{-1}$ Mpc$^{-1}$, while the one-step measurements result in a weighted mean $H_0 = 69.01 \pm 0.49$ km s$^{-1}$ Mpc$^{-1}$. To quantify the statistical significance of this difference, we implemented a Kolmogorov-Smirnov (KS) test, which yielded a p-value of 0.000102. This extremely low p-value strongly indicates that the two samples are fundamentally distinct, with a probability of less than 0.01\% that they are drawn from the same underlying distribution. These findings suggest that late-time one-step measurements of $H_0$ are more consistent with early-time measurements, indicating that the core of the Hubble tension lies not between early-time and late-time measurements per se, but specifically between distance ladder measurements and all other $H_0$ determinations. This discrepancy points to either a systematic effect influencing all distance ladder measurements or a fundamental physics anomaly affecting at least one rung of the distance ladder.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11031v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leandros Perivolaropoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sensitivity to anisotropic stochastic gravitational-wave background with space-borne networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.01541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.01541v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Single gravitational-wave detectors face inherent limitations in detecting the anisotropy of the stochastic background. In this work, we explore the sensitivity to anisotropic backgrounds with a network of space-borne detectors. We find that the separation between detectors plays an important role in determining the sensitivity. For the first time, we observe as large as three orders of magnitude enhancement in detection sensitivity for the multipoles with $l=5$ and 6, compared to coinciding detectors. Coordinating and optimizing the separation between two space-borne detectors can significantly enhance the network's sensitivity to the multipole components of the stochastic background. For the TianQin + LISA network, benefiting from detector separation, it is possible to achieve sensitivity levels of 2-3 orders of magnitude better than using TianQin or LISA detector alone. These findings pave the way to uncover the underlying physics of anisotropy through gravitational-wave detections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.01541v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheng-Cheng Liang, Zhi-Yuan Li, En-Kun Li, Jian-dong Zhang, Yi-Ming Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting cosmological scalar fields using orbital networks of quantum sensors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.17873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.17873v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this Letter, we propose to detect the interaction of a hypothetical coherently evolving cosmological scalar field with an orbital network of quantum sensors, focusing on the GPS satellite network as a test example. Cosmological scenarios, such as a scalar-tensor theory for dark energy or the axi-Higgs model, suggest that such a field may exist. As this field would be (approximately) at rest in the CMB frame, it would exhibit a dipole as a result of the movement of our terrestrial observers relative to the CMB. While the current sensitivity of the GPS network is insufficient to detect a cosmological dipole, future networks of quantum sensors on heliocentric orbits, using state-of-the-art atomic clocks, can reach and exceed this requirement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.17873v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review D 110, 043028, 21 August 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yu Li, Ruolin Liu, Conner Dailey, Niayesh Afshordi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JWST MIRI detections of H$\alpha$ and [O III] and direct metallicity measurement of the $z=10.17$ lensed galaxy MACS0647$-$JD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16200v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: JWST spectroscopy has revolutionized our understanding of galaxies in the early universe. Covering wavelengths up to $5.3\,{\rm \mu m}$, NIRSpec can detect rest-frame optical emission lines H$\alpha$ out to $z = 7$ and [O III] to $z = 9.5$. Observing these lines in more distant galaxies requires longer wavelength spectroscopy with MIRI. Here we present MIRI MRS IFU observations of the lensed galaxy merger MACS0647$-$JD at $z = 10.165$. With exposure times of 4.2 hours in each of two bands, we detect H$\alpha$ at $9\sigma$, [O III]$\,\lambda5008$ at $11\sigma$, and [O III]$\,\lambda4960$ at $3\sigma$. Combined with previously reported NIRSpec spectroscopy that yields seven emission lines including the auroral line [O III]$\,\lambda4363$, we present the first direct metallicity measurement of a $z &gt; 10$ galaxy: $12+{\rm log(O/H)}= 7.79\pm0.09$, or $0.13^{+0.02}_{-0.03}\,Z_{\odot}$. This is similar to galaxies at $z \sim 4 - 9$ with direct metallicity measurements, though higher than expected given the high specific star formation rate ${\rm log(sSFR / yr^{-1})} = -7.4 \pm 0.3$. We further constrain the ionization parameter ${\rm log}(U)$ = $-1.9 \pm 0.1$, ionizing photon production efficiency ${\rm log}(\xi_{\rm ion})$ = $25.3\pm0.1$, and star formation rate $5.0\pm0.6\,M_{\odot}/{\rm yr}$ within the past $10\,{\rm Myr}$. These observations demonstrate the combined power of JWST NIRSpec and MIRI for studying galaxies in the first $500$ million years.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16200v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tiger Yu-Yang Hsiao, Javier \'Alvarez-M\'arquez, Dan Coe, Alejandro Crespo G\'omez,  Abdurro'uf, Pratika Dayal, Rebecca L. Larson, Arjan Bik, Carmen Blanco-Prieto, Luis Colina, Pablo Guillermo P\'erez-Gonz\'alez, Luca Costantin, Carlota Prieto-Jim\'enez, Angela Adamo, Larry D. Bradley, Christopher J. Conselice, Seiji Fujimoto, Lukas J. Furtak, Taylor A. Hutchison, Bethan L. James, Yolanda Jim\'enez-Teja, Intae Jung, Vasily Kokorev, Matilde Mingozzi, Colin Norman, Massimo Ricotti, Jane R. Rigby, Keren Sharon, Eros Vanzella, Brian Welch, Xinfeng Xu, Erik Zackrisson, Adi Zitrin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New search pipeline for gravitational waves with higher-order modes using mode-by-mode filtering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17400v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Nearly all template-based gravitational wave (GW) searches only include the quasi-circular quadrupolar modes of the signals in their templates. Including additional degrees of freedom in the GW templates corresponding to higher-order harmonics, orbital precession, or eccentricity is challenging because: ($i$) the size of template banks and the matched-filtering cost increases significantly with the number of degrees of freedom, $(ii)$ if these additional degrees are not included properly, the search can lose sensitivity overall (due to an increase in the rate of background triggers). Here, we focus on including aligned-spin higher harmonics in GW search templates. We use a new mode-by-mode filtering approach, where we separately filter GW strain data with three harmonics [namely $(\ell, |m|)=(2,2)$, $(3,3)$ and $(4,4)$]. This results in an increase in the matched-filtering cost by only a factor of $3$ compared to that of a $(2,2)$-only search. We develop computationally cheap trigger-ranking statistics to optimally combine the different signal-to-noise ratios (SNR) timeseries from different harmonics, which ensure only physically-allowed combinations of the different harmonics are triggered on. We use an empirical template-dependent background model in our ranking statistic to account for non-Gaussian transients. In addition, we develop a tool called band eraser which specifically excises narrow time-varying noisy bands in time-frequency space (without having to excise entire time chunks in the data). New GW candidate events that we detect using our $\texttt{IAS-HM}$ search pipeline and the details of our template banks are discussed in accompanying papers: Wadekar et al. [1] and [2] respectively. Apart from higher harmonics, we expect our methodology to also be useful for cheap and optimal searches including orbital precession and eccentricity in GW waveforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17400v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Digvijay Wadekar, Tejaswi Venumadhav, Javier Roulet, Ajit Kumar Mehta, Barak Zackay, Jonathan Mushkin, Matias Zaldarriaga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Axion Stars from Strings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19389</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19389v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that if dark matter consists of QCD axions in the post-inflationary scenario more than ten percent of it efficiently collapses into Bose stars at matter-radiation equality. Such a result is mostly independent of the present uncertainties on the axion mass. This large population of solitons, with asteroid masses and Earth-Moon distance sizes, might plausibly survive until today, with potentially interesting implications for phenomenology and experimental searches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19389v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Gorghetto, Edward Hardy, Giovanni Villadoro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AtLAST Science Overview Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01413v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Submillimeter and millimeter wavelengths provide a unique view of the Universe, from the gas and dust that fills and surrounds galaxies to the chromosphere of our own Sun. Current single-dish facilities have presented a tantalising view of the brightest (sub-)mm sources, and interferometers have provided the exquisite resolution necessary to analyse the details in small fields, but there are still many open questions that cannot be answered with current facilities. In this report we summarise the science that is guiding the design of the Atacama Large Aperture Submillimeter Telescope (AtLAST). We demonstrate how tranformational advances in topics including star formation in high redshift galaxies, the diffuse circumgalactic medium, Galactic ecology, cometary compositions and solar flares motivate the need for a 50m, single-dish telescope with a 1-2 degree field of view and a new generation of highly multiplexed continuum and spectral cameras. AtLAST will have the resolution to drastically lower the confusion limit compared to current single-dish facilities, whilst also being able to rapidly map large areas of the sky and detect extended, diffuse structures. Its high sensitivity and large field of view will open up the field of submillimeter transient science by increasing the probability of serendipitous detections. Finally, the science cases listed here motivate the need for a highly flexible operations model capable of short observations of individual targets, large surveys, monitoring programmes, target of opportunity observations and coordinated observations with other observatories. AtLAST aims to be a sustainable, upgradeable, multipurpose facility that will deliver orders of magnitude increases in sensitivity and mapping speeds over current and planned submillimeter observatories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01413v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark Booth, Pamela Klaassen, Claudia Cicone, Tony Mroczkowski, Martin A. Cordiner, Luca Di Mascolo, Doug Johnstone, Eelco van Kampen, Minju M. Lee, Daizhong Liu, John Orlowski-Scherer, Am\'elie Saintonge, Matthew W. L. Smith, Alexander Thelen, Sven Wedemeyer, Kazunori Akiyama, Stefano Andreon, Doris Arzoumanian, Tom J. L. C. Bakx, Caroline Bot, Geoffrey Bower, Roman Braj\v{s}a, Chian-Chou Chen, Elisabete da Cunha, David Eden, Stefano Ettori, Brandt Gaches, Evanthia Hatziminaoglou, Patricia Luppe, Benjamin Magnelli, Jonathan P. Marshall, Francisco Miguel Montenegro-Montes, Michael Niemack, Conor Nixon, Imke de Pater, Yvette Perrott, Sandra I. Raimundo, Elena Redaelli, Anita Richards, Matus Rybak, Nikolina \v{S}ar\v{c}evi\'c, Dmitry Semenov, Silvia Spezzano, Sundar Srinivasan, Thomas Stanke, Paola Andreani, Maria T. Beltr\'an, Bryan J. Butler, Sebastiano Cantalupo, Miguel Chavez Dagostino, Ana Duarte-Cabral, Bjorn Emonts, Leigh Fletcher, Dale E. Gary, Stanislav Gunar, Alvaro Hacar, Bendix Hagedorn, Tomek Kaminski, Fiona Kirton, Katherine de Kleer, Eduard Kontar, Yi-Jehng Kuan, John Lightfoot, Enrique Lopez-Rodriguez, Andreas Lundgren, Stefanie N. Milam, Atul Mohan, Raphael Moreno, Galina G. Motorina, Arielle Moullet, Kate Pattle, Alberto Pellizzoni, Nicolas Peretto, Joanna Ramasawmy, Claudio Ricci, Andrew J. Rigby, \'Alvaro S\'anchez-Monge, Maryam Saberi, Masumi Shimojo, Aurora Simionescu, Mark Thompson, Alessio Traficante, Cristian Vignali, Stephen M. White</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comment on "No Black Holes from Light" [arXiv:2405.02389]</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06714</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.06714v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that black holes can be made of light by adding gravity to the discussion of Alvarez-Dominguez et al., arXiv:2405.02389 [PRL 130, 041401 (2024)].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.06714v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abraham Loeb (Harvard)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Non-Thermal Gravitinos Through Large-Scale Structure Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10585</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10585v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the effects of non-thermally produced dark matter on large-scale structure formation, focusing on the gravitino dark matter. Our analysis shows that large-scale structure measurements from the SDSS LRG data offer a promising approach to probing non-thermally produced gravitinos. Specifically, if gravitinos resulting from neutralino decay constitute a fraction $F_\text{dec}=0.35~(0.1)$ of the dark matter component, the data exclude bino-like neutralino with a mass $m_{\chi_1^0}\lesssim25~(11)\text{ GeV}$. Furthermore, this constraint appears to be largely independent of the gravitino mass.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10585v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weiyi Deng, Liyuan Guo, Chengcheng Han, Zhanhong Lei</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
