<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO</link>
    <description>astro-ph.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 04:00:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The distribution of the gravitational-wave background from supermassive black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17010v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The recent detection of gravitational waves (GWs) by pulsar timing array (PTA) collaborations spurred a variety of questions regarding the origin of the signal and the properties of its sources. The amplitude of a GW background produced by inspiralling supermassive black holes (SMBHs) can be predicted in a relatively robust manner from the present-day merged remnants, observed as single SMBHs at the centers of galaxies, but falls short of the signal measured by PTAs by a significant amount, requiring equal mass mergers, extremely short delay times, and no accretion in order to achieve a modest consistency. In this work, we revisit NANOGrav's 15-yr data set and reassess the aforementioned discrepancy using the full spectral information captured by PTA data. As previously noted in the literature, the discrete number of point sources contributing to the background may lead to deviations in the observed spectrum relative to the average ($h^2_c \propto f^{-4/3}$) due to Poisson fluctuations, providing additional information about the source population beyond the background amplitude. We derive a simple expression for the characteristic strain distribution given a SMBH model, which is generally applicable regardless of the method used to model the black hole population. We then refit the NANOGrav free spectrum using a minimal model based on the local mass function, showing that the current GW measurement requires roughly $\sim 10$ times more black holes than suggested by local observations and disfavors mass functions dominated by few very heavy sources, with the typical mass that contributes to the background $\lesssim 10^{10}M_{\odot}$. Given the range of SMBH models found to be consistent with the isotropic background, we address what is the typical number sources that would be individually detectable, given the current sensitivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17010v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriela Sato-Polito, Matias Zaldarriaga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The HYENAS project: a prediction for the X-ray undetected galaxy groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17012v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Galaxy groups contain the majority of bound mass with a significant portion of baryons due to the combination of halo mass and abundance (Cui 2024). Hence they serve as a crucial missing piece in the puzzle of galaxy formation and the evolution of large-scale structures in the Universe. In observations, mass-complete group catalogues are normally derived from galaxy redshift surveys detected through various three-dimensional group-finding algorithms. Confirming the reality of such groups, particularly in the X-rays, is critical for ensuring robust studies of galaxy evolution in these environments. Recent works have reported numerous optical groups that are X-ray undetected (see, e.g., Popesso et al. 2024), sparking debates regarding the reasons for the unexpectedly low hot gas fraction in galaxy groups. To address this issue, we utilise zoomed-in simulations of galaxy groups from the novel HYENAS project to explore the range of hot gas fractions within galaxy groups and investigate the intrinsic factors behind the observed variability in X-ray emission. We find that the halo formation time can play a critical role -- we see that groups in halos that formed earlier exhibit up to an order of magnitude brighter X-ray luminosities compared to those formed later. This suggests that undetected X-ray groups are preferentially late-formed halos and highlights the connection between gas fraction and halo formation time in galaxy groups. Accounting for these biases in galaxy group identification is essential for advancing our understanding of galaxy formation and achieving precision in cosmological studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17012v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weiguang Cui, Fred Jennings, Romeel Dave, Arif Babul, Ghassem Gozaliasl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining galaxy properties with complete samples of lenses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17019v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The statistics of Einstein radii for a sample of strong lenses can provide valuable constraints on the underlying mass distribution. The correct interpretation, however, relies critically on the modelling of the selection of the sample, which has proven to be a limiting factor. This may change thanks to upcoming uniform high-resolution imaging surveys that cover a large fraction of the sky, because they can provide complete lens samples, with well understood selection criteria. To explore how the observed distribution of Einstein radii depends on the galaxy properties, we simulated a realistic complete sample of strong lenses, predicting a number density of lenses of about 2.5 deg$^{-2}$ for a \Euclid-like setup. Such data can break the degeneracy between the stellar initial mass function (IMF) and the inner slope of the density profile of dark matter, without having to rely on additional information from stellar dynamics. We found that a survey covering only 50 deg$^2$ can already provide tight constraints: assuming that the cosmology is known, the dark matter slope is recovered with an uncertainty of $3.5\%$, while the uncertainty in the ratio between the true stellar mass and that inferred from stellar population modelling was found to be $10\%$. These findings highlight the potential of this method when applied to samples of lenses with well-understood selection functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17019v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qing Zhou (Leiden Observatory), Alessandro Sonnenfeld (Shanghai Jiao Tong University), Henk Hoekstra (Leiden Observatory)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Interacting Dark Matter, Core Collapse and the Galaxy-Galaxy Strong Lensing Discrepancy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17024</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17024v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Gravitational lensing by galaxy clusters has emerged as a powerful tool to probe the standard Cold Dark Matter (CDM) paradigm of structure formation in the Universe. Despite the remarkable explanatory power of CDM on large scales, tensions with observations on small scales have been reported. Recent studies find that the observational cross-section for Galaxy-Galaxy Strong Lensing (GGSL) in clusters exceeds the CDM prediction by more than an order of magnitude, and persists even after rigorous examination of various possible systematics. We investigate the impact of modifying the internal structure of cluster dark matter sub-halos on GGSL and report that altering the inner density profile, given by $r^{\gamma}$, to steeper slopes with $\gamma &gt; 2.5$ can alleviate the GGSL discrepancy. Deviating from the $\gamma \sim 1.0$ cusps that CDM predicts, these steeper slopes could arise in models of self-interacting dark matter undergoing core collapse. Our results motivate additional study of sub-halo core collapse in dense cluster environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17024v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Isaque Dutra, Priyamvada Natarajan, Daniel Gilman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time Non-locality in Dark Matter and LSS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17025v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the intriguing phenomenon of time non-locality in the evolution of dark matter and Large Scale Structure (LSS). Recently in\,\cite{Donath:2023sav}, it was shown that time non-locality emerges in bias tracer fluctuations, which are $SO(3)$ scalars in real space, at fifth order in the perturbation expansion in dark matter overdensity. We demonstrate that by breaking the symmetry down to $SO(2)$, which is the case whenever line-of-sight effects become important, such as for flux fluctuations in the Lyman $\alpha$ forest, the temporal non-locality appears at the third order in expansion. Additionally, within the framework of EFTofLSS, we demonstrate that time non-locality manifests in the effective stress tensor of dark matter, which is a second rank tensor under $SO(3)$ transformations, again at the third order in dark matter overdensity. Furthermore, we highlight the effectiveness of the standard $\Pi$ basis\,\cite{Mirbabayi:2014zca} in handling time non-local operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17025v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arhum Ansari, Arka Banerjee, Sachin Jain, Shaunak Padhyegurjar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caustic area biases and how to deal with them</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17027v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quadruply-imaged strongly lensed quasars (quads) are routinely used for measurements of the expansion rate of the Universe with time delays. It has recently been suggested that any quad lens is subject to a Malmquist-like bias that causes the inferred area enclosed within the tangential caustic to be systematically underestimated, and that such a bias might translate into a corresponding bias on the expansion parameter. In this work we extended that analysis by also considering the effect of Eddington bias. We found that the sign and amplitude of the combined bias depend on the functional form of the caustic area distribution of the lens population and on the noise associated with the caustic area estimation process. Based on simulations, we estimated that the corresponding impact on $H_0$ is on the order of a percent or smaller. If the likelihood of the lensing data is known, then the bias can be accounted for when modelling the lens population. However, ignoring the criteria used to select a quad might lead to a bias at the lens modelling stage that causes the inferred caustic area to be overestimated. Such a bias disappears for lens models that are well constrained by the data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17027v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Sonnenfeld (Shanghai Jiao Tong University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of extragalactic point sources on the low-frequency sky spectrum and cosmic dawn global 21-cm measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17031v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Contribution of resolved and unresolved extragalactic point sources to the low-frequency sky spectrum is a potentially non-negligible part of the astrophysical foregrounds for cosmic dawn 21-cm experiments. The clustering of such point sources on the sky, combined with the frequency-dependence of the antenna beam, can also make this contribution chromatic. By combining low-frequency measurements of the luminosity function and the angular correlation function of extragalactic point sources, we develop a model for the contribution of these sources to the low-frequency sky spectrum. Using this model, we find that the contribution of sources with flux density $&gt;10^{-6}\,$Jy to the sky-averaged spectrum is smooth and of the order of a few kelvins at 50 - $200\,$MHz. We combine this model with measurements of the galactic foreground spectrum and convolve the result with the beam of the conical log-spiral antenna planned as part of the Radio Experiment for the Analysis of Cosmic Hydrogen (REACH) project. We find that the contribution of point sources to resultant spectrum is $\sim0.4\%$ of the total foregrounds, but still larger by at least an order of magnitude than the standard predictions for the cosmological 21-cm signal. As a result, not accounting for the point-source contribution leads to a systematic bias in 21-cm signal recovery. We show, however, that in the REACH case, this reconstruction bias can be removed by modelling the point-source contribution as a power law with a running spectral index. We make our code publicly available as a Python package labelled epspy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17031v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shikhar Mittal (TIFR), Girish Kulkarni (TIFR), Dominic Anstey (Cambridge), Eloy de Lera Acedo (Cambridge)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-definition imaging of an extended filament connecting active quasars at cosmic noon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17035v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Filaments connecting halos are a long-standing prediction of cold dark matter theories. We present a novel detection of the cosmic web emission connecting two massive quasar-host galaxies at cosmic noon in the MUSE Ultra Deep Field (MUDF) using unprecedentedly deep observations that unlock a high-definition view of the filament morphology, a measure of the transition radius between the intergalactic and circumgalactic medium, and the characterization of the surface brightness profiles along the filament and in the transverse direction. Through systematic comparisons with simulations, we validate the filaments' typical density predicted in the current cold dark matter model. Our analysis of the MUDF field, an excellent laboratory for quantitatively studying filaments in emission, opens a new avenue to understanding the cosmic web that, being a fundamental prediction of cosmology, bears key information on the essence of dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17035v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davide Tornotti, Michele Fumagalli, Matteo Fossati, Alejandro Benitez-Llambay, David Izquierdo-Villalba, Andrea Travascio, Fabrizio Arrigoni Battaia, Sebastiano Cantalupo, Alexander Beckett, Silvia Bonoli, Pratika Dayal, Valentina D'Odorico, Rajeshwari Dutta, Elisabeta Lusso, Celine Peroux, Marc Rafelski, Mitchell Revalski, Daniele Spinoso, Mark Swinbank</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Gravitational Wave Probe to the Nature of Dark Energy from the Aging of the Universe: Can Future Detectors Achieve it?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17041v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One of the most dominant energy budget of the Universe is Dark Energy, which remains enigmatic since the claim of its existence from the observation of late-time cosmic acceleration. We propose a new way of inferring this by measuring the aging of the Universe using only gravitational wave (GW) signals from coalescing binary compact objects of any masses. We show that the aging of the Universe will lead to a change in the observed chirp mass of the GW sources inferred from different stages of its coalesces by monitoring a coherent source from two far-apart GW frequencies for a few years. We show that coordinated GW detectors which can reach a relative uncertainty on chirp mass measurement of about $10^{-9}$, can measure a tiny departure of about $2\%$ from the dark energy equation of state parameter $w_0=-1$ and its variation with cosmic time by using stellar origin binary black holes up to redshift $z=5$ in 10 years of observation time without using any external calibrator. If the next generation of GW detectors can achieve this precision, then it can open a new window to discover the fundamental nature of dark energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17041v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suvodip Mukherjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting evolution of domain walls and their gravitational radiation with CosmoLattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17053</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17053v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Employing the publicly available CosmoLattice code, we conduct numerical simulations of a domain wall network and the resulting gravitational waves (GWs) in a radiation-dominated Universe in the $Z_2$-symmetric scalar field model. In particular, the domain wall evolution is investigated in detail both before and after reaching the scaling regime, using the combination of numerical and theoretical methods. We demonstrate that the total area of closed walls is negligible compared to that of a single long wall stretching throughout the simulation box. Therefore, the closed walls are unlikely to have a significant impact on the overall network evolution. This is in contrast with the case of cosmic strings, where formation of loops is crucial for maintaining the system in the scaling regime. To obtain the GW spectrum, we develop a technique that separates physical effects from numerical artefacts arising due to finite box size and non-zero lattice spacing. Our results on the GW spectrum agree well with Refs. [29, 30], which use different codes. Notably, we observe a peak at the Hubble scale, an exponential falloff at scales shorter than the wall width, and a plateau/bump at intermediate scales. We also study sensitivity of obtained results on the choice of initial conditions. We find that different types of initial conditions lead to qualitatively similar domain wall evolution in the scaling regime, but with important variations translating into different intensities of GWs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17053v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. Dankovsky, E. Babichev, D. Gorbunov, S. Ramazanov, A. Vikman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>STag II: Classification of Serendipitous Supernovae Observed by Galaxy Redshift Surveys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17204</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17204v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With the number of supernovae observed expected to drastically increase thanks to large-scale surveys like the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI), it is necessary that the tools we use to classify these objects keep up with this increase. We previously created Supernova Tagging and Classification (STag) to address this problem by employing machine learning techniques alongside logistic regression in order to assign 'tags' to spectra based on spectral features. STag II is a continuation of this work, which now makes use of model supernova spectra combined with real DESI spectra in order to train STag to better deal with realistic data. We also make use of the rlap score as a trustworthiness cut, making for a more robust and accurate supernova classifier than before.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17204v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>W. Davison, D. Parkinson, S. BenZvi, A. Palmese, J. Aguilar, S. Ahlen, D. Brooks, T. Claybaugh, A. de la Macorra, Arjun Dey, P. Doel, E. Gazta\~naga, S. Gontcho A Gontcho, C. Howlett, S. Juneau, T. Kisner, A. Kremin, A. Lambert, M. Landriau, L. Le Guillou, A. Meisner, R. Miquel, J. Moustakas, A. D. Myers, C. Poppett, F. Prada, M. Rezaie, G. Rossi, E. Sanchez, E. F. Schlafly, M. Schubnell, D. Sprayberry, G. Tarl\'e, B. A. Weaver, H. Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CMBFSCNN: Cosmic Microwave Background Polarization Foreground Subtraction with Convolutional Neural Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17685v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In our previous study, we introduced a machine-learning technique, namely CMBFSCNN, for the removal of foreground contamination in cosmic microwave background (CMB) polarization data. This method was successfully employed on actual observational data from the Planck mission. In this study, we extend our investigation by considering the CMB lensing effect in simulated data and utilizing the CMBFSCNN approach to recover the CMB lensing B-mode power spectrum from multi-frequency observational maps. Our method is first applied to simulated data with the performance of CMB-S4 experiment. We achieve reliable recovery of the noisy CMB Q (or U) maps with a mean absolute difference of $0.016\pm0.008\ \mu$K (or $0.021\pm0.002\ \mu$K) for the CMB-S4 experiment. To address the residual instrumental noise in the foreground-cleaned map, we employ a "half-split maps" approach, where the entire dataset is divided into two segments sharing the same sky signal but having uncorrelated noise. Using cross-correlation techniques between two recovered half-split maps, we effectively reduce instrumental noise effects at the power spectrum level. As a result, we achieve precise recovery of the CMB EE and lensing B-mode power spectra. Furthermore, we also extend our pipeline to full-sky simulated data with the performance of LiteBIRD experiment. As expected, various foregrounds are cleanly removed from the foreground contamination observational maps, and recovered EE and lensing B-mode power spectra exhibit excellent agreement with the true results. Finally, we discuss the dependency of our method on the foreground models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17685v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ye-Peng Yan, Si-Yu Li, Guo-Jian Wang, Zirui Zhang, Jun-Qing Xia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting kHz gravitons from a neutron star merger with a multi-mode resonant bar</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16898v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a multi-mode bar consisting of mass elements of decreasing size for the direct detection of stimulated absorption of up to kHz gravitons from a neutron star merger and post-merger. We find that the multi-mode detector has normal modes that retain the coupling strength to the gravitational wave of the largest mass-element, while only having an effective mass comparable to the mass of the smallest element. This allows the normal modes to have graviton absorption rates due to the tonne-scale largest mass, while the single graviton absorption process in the normal mode could be resolved through energy measurements of a mass-element in-principle smaller than pico-gram scale. This improves the transduction of the single-graviton signal compared to a single-mode detector, enhancing the feasibility of detecting single gravitons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16898v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Germain Tobar, Igor Pikovski, Michael Edmund Tobar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forecast measurement of the 21 cm global spectrum from Lunar orbit with the Vari-Zeroth-Order Polynomial (VZOP) method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17000v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The cosmic 21 cm signal serves as a crucial probe for studying the evolutionary history of the Universe. However, detecting the 21 cm signal poses significant challenges due to its extremely faint nature. To mitigate the interference from the Earth's radio frequency interference (RFI), the ground and the ionospheric effects, the Discovering the Sky at the Longest Wavelength (DSL) project will deploy a constellation of satellites in Lunar orbit, with its high-frequency daughter satellite tasked with detecting the global 21 cm signal from cosmic dawn and reionization era (CD/EoR). We intend to employ the Vari-Zeroth-Order Polynomial (VZOP) for foreground fitting and subtracting. We have studied the effect of thermal noise, thermal radiation from the Moon, the Lunar reflection, anisotropic frequency-dependent beam, inaccurate antenna beam pattern, and RFI contamination. We discovered that the RFI contamination can significantly affect the fitting process and thus prevent us from detecting the signal. Therefore, experimenting on the far side of the moon is crucial. We also discovered that using VZOP together with DSL, after 1080 orbits around the Moon, which takes about 103 days, we can successfully detect the CD/EoR 21 cm signal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17000v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianyang Liu, Jiajun Zhang, Yuan Shi, Junhua Gu, Quan Guo, Yidong Xu, Furen Deng, Fengquan Wu, Yanping Cong, Xuelei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explaining PTA Results by Metastable Cosmic Strings from SO(10) GUT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17014v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In a recent paper (see https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevD.108.095053), we have demonstrated that the 2023 PTA results, which hint at a stochastic gravitational wave (GW) background at nanohertz frequencies, point towards a promising model-building route for realizing $SO(10)$ Grand Unification with embedded inflation. The proposed supersymmetric scenario solves the doublet-triplet splitting without fine-tuning, accounts for charged fermion and neutrino masses, avoids conflicts with current proton decay bounds, and includes only representations no larger than the adjoint. It features multi-step breaking of $SO(10)$ to the Standard Model gauge symmetry, with inflation embedded such that metastable cosmic strings are produced at the end of inflation. This cosmic string network generates a stochastic GW background that can explain the PTA results. In this paper, we provide a detailed analysis of the singled out GUT model class, focusing on how the gauge coupling unification condition affects the scales of multi-step $SO(10)$ breaking and the preferred GW spectra. The lowest breaking scale, linked to inflation, the generation of right-handed neutrino masses for the seesaw mechanism, and metastable cosmic string production, coincides with the range suggested by the PTA results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17014v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Antusch, Kevin Hinze, Shaikh Saad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytic bounds on late-time axion-scalar cosmologies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17030</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17030v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The cosmological dynamics of multiple scalar/pseudoscalar fields are difficult to solve, especially when the field-space metric is curved. This presents a challenge in determining whether a given model can support cosmic acceleration, without solving for the on-shell solution. In this work, we present bounds on late-time FLRW-cosmologies in classes of theories that involve arbitrary numbers of scalar and pseudoscalar fields coupled both kinetically (leading to a curved field space metric) and through scalar potentials. Such bounds are proven analytically, independently of initial conditions, with no approximation in the field equations and without referring to explicit solutions. Besides their broad applications to cosmological model building, our bounds can be applied to studying asymptotic cosmologies of certain classes of string compactifications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17030v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gary Shiu, Flavio Tonioni, Hung V. Tran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal Dark Matter with Low-Temperature Reheating</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17039</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17039v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explore the production of thermal dark matter (DM) candidates (WIMPs, SIMPs, ELDERs and Cannibals) during cosmic reheating. Assuming a general parametrization for the scaling of the inflaton energy density and the standard model (SM) temperature, we study the requirements for kinetic and chemical DM freeze-out in a model-independent way. For each of the mechanisms, up to two solutions that fit the entire observed DM relic density exist, for a given reheating scenario and DM mass. As an example, we assume a simple particle physics model in which DM interacts with itself and with SM through contact interactions. We find that low-temperature reheating can accommodate a wider range of couplings and larger masses than those permitted in the usual instantaneous high-temperature reheating. This results in DM solutions for WIMPs reaching masses as high as $10^{14}$~GeV, whereas for SIMPs and ELDERs, we can reach masses of $10^{13}$~GeV. Interestingly, current experimental data already constrain the enlarged parameter space of these models with low-reheating temperatures. Next-generation experiments could further probe these scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17039v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicol\'as Bernal, Kuldeep Deka, Marta Losada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tachyonic production of dark relics: classical lattice vs. quantum 2PI in Hartree truncation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17468v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the out-of-equilibrium production of non-minimally coupled self-interacting scalar dark matter during reheating using classical lattice simulations. The outcomes of the classical simulations are in qualitative agreement with the previous results obtained using the quantum 2PI approach in the Hartree truncation. In particular, the novel non-linear resonance found in the 2PI Hartee study is present also in the classical lattice simulations and can dominate the final dark matter yield. For the parameters considered, the difference in final value of the scalar two-point function between the two approaches is a factor of O(1).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17468v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kimmo Kainulainen, Sami Nurmi, Olli V\"ais\"anen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local primordial non-Gaussianity from the large-scale clustering of photometric DESI luminous red galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.01753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.01753v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We use angular clustering of luminous red galaxies from the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) imaging surveys to constrain the local primordial non-Gaussianity parameter $\fnl$. Our sample comprises over 12 million targets, covering 14,000 square degrees of the sky, with redshifts in the range $0.2&lt; z &lt; 1.35$. We identify Galactic extinction, survey depth, and astronomical seeing as the primary sources of systematic error, and employ linear regression and artificial neural networks to alleviate non-cosmological excess clustering on large scales. Our methods are tested against simulations with and without $\fnl$ and systematics, showing superior performance of the neural network treatment. The neural network with a set of nine imaging property maps passes our systematic null test criteria, and is chosen as the fiducial treatment. Assuming the universality relation, we find $\fnl = 34^{+24(+50)}_{-44(-73)}$ at 68\%(95\%) confidence. We apply a series of robustness tests (e.g., cuts on imaging, declination, or scales used) that show consistency in the obtained constraints. We study how the regression method biases the measured angular power-spectrum and degrades the $\fnl$ constraining power. The use of the nine maps more than doubles the uncertainty compared to using only the three primary maps in the regression. Our results thus motivate the development of more efficient methods that avoid over-correction, protect large-scale clustering information, and preserve constraining power. Additionally, our results encourage further studies of $\fnl$ with DESI spectroscopic samples, where the inclusion of 3D clustering modes should help separate imaging systematics and lessen the degradation in the $\fnl$ uncertainty.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.01753v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae886</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Mehdi Rezaie, Ashley J. Ross, Hee-Jong Seo, Hui Kong, Anna Porredon, Lado Samushia, Edmond Chaussidon, Alex Krolewski, Arnaud de Mattia, Florian Beutler, Jessica Nicole Aguilar, Steven Ahlen, Shadab Alam, Santiago Avila, Benedict Bahr-Kalus, Jose Bermejo-Climent, David Brooks, Todd Claybaugh, Shaun Cole, Kyle Dawson, Axel de la Macorra, Peter Doel, Andreu Font-Ribera, Jaime E. Forero-Romero, Satya Gontcho A Gontcho, Julien Guy, Klaus Honscheid, Dragan Huterer, Theodore Kisner, Martin Landriau, Michael Levi, Marc Manera, Aaron Meisner, Ramon Miquel, Eva-Maria Mueller, Adam Myers, Jeffrey A. Newman, Jundan Nie, Nathalie Palanque-Delabrouille, Will Percival, Claire Poppett, Graziano Rossi, Eusebio Sanchez, Michael Schubnell, Gregory Tarl\'e, Benjamin Alan Weaver, Christophe Y\`eche, Zhimin Zhou, Hu Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unifying inflationary and reheating solution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.10570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.10570v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The conventional background solution for the evolution of a single canonical inflaton field performs admirably in extreme scenarios such as the slow-roll phase (where the slow-roll parameter is much less than one) and the deep reheating era (where the Hubble parameter is much smaller than the effective mass of the potential and the field oscillates around the minimum of the potential), but fails to accurately depict the dynamics of the Universe around the end of inflation and the initial oscillatory phases. This article proposes a single, unified, model-independent, parametrized analytical solution for such models that bridges the gap between these two extremes, providing a near-accurate comprehensive description of the evolution of the Universe. This novel strategy has the potential to substantially enhance both quantitative and qualitative cosmological observational predictions, and, as a consequence, can further constrain the inflationary models more effectively using future observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.10570v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2024/05/045</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 05(2024)045</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Manjeet Kaur (DU), Debottam Nandi (DU), Sharath Raghavan B</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extracting $H_{0}$ and $r_{d}$ in Pacif Parametrization Models through Late-Time Dataset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.10499</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.10499v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study examines five models derived from the Pacif parametrization scheme of the Hubble parameter ($H$), yielding various linear to quintic forms of the deceleration parameter (DP). Our goal is to explore the impact of these DP variations on late-time evolution and their potential to alleviate cosmological tensions. To enhance model constraints, we introduce non-diagonal elements into the covariance matrix to better capture statistical properties by simulating data point correlations. We also test the sensitivity of $H_{0}$ and $r_{d}$ to the Pacif parametrization scheme, treating the sound horizon $r_{d}$ as a free parameter to avoid imposing a CMB prior. This allows late-time data to constrain $r_{d}$ alongside other cosmological parameters, incorporating recent Baryon Acoustic Oscillations (BAO) measurements and Hubble data from Cosmic Chronometers Methods, Type Ia Supernovae (SNIa), Gamma-Ray Bursts (GRBs), and Quasars over a redshift range of \(0.106 &lt; z &lt; 2.33\). Our analysis provides optimal fit values for $H_{0}$ and $r_{d}$, showing notable consistency with Planck CMB data. By using the Akaike information criterion, we analyze the models and conclude that all models have good agreement with the most recent observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.10499v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Himanshu Chaudhary, Shibesh Kumar Jas Pacif, G. Mustafa, Amine Bouali, Faisal Javed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multifield curved solid: Early dark energy and perturbation instabilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.14108</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.14108v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a multifield dark energy model with a nonflat field-space metric, in which one field is dynamical while the others have constant spatial gradients. The model is predictive at the background level, leading to an early dark energy component at high redshifts and a suppressed fraction of late-time anisotropy. Both features have simple expressions in terms of the curvature scale of the field-space, and correspond to stable points in the phase space of possible solutions. Because of the coupling between time and space-dependent scalar fields, vector field perturbations develop tachyonic instabilities at scales below the Hubble radius, thus being potentially observable in the number count of galaxies. Overall, the presence of a nontrivial field-space curvature also leads to the appearance of instabilities on scalar perturbations, which can impact the matter density distribution at large scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.14108v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.123539</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Juan P. Beltr\'an Almeida, Alejandro Guarnizo, Thiago S. Pereira, C\'esar A. Valenzuela-Toledo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quintessential interpretation of the evolving dark energy in light of DESI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05722v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The recent result of Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) in combination with other cosmological data shows evidence of the evolving dark energy parameterized by $w_0w_a$CDM model. We interpret this result in terms of a quintessential scalar field and demonstrate that it can explain the DESI result even though it becomes eventually phantom in the past. Relaxing the assumption on the functional form of the equation-of-state parameter $w=w(a)$, we also discuss a more realistic quintessential model. The implications of the DESI result for Swampland conjectures, cosmic birefringence, and the fate of the Universe are discussed as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05722v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.L121305</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109 (2024) no.12, L121305</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yuichiro Tada, Takahiro Terada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The second data release from the European Pulsar Timing Array V. Search for continuous gravitational wave signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.16226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.16226v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present the results of a search for continuous gravitational wave signals (CGWs) in the second data release (DR2) of the European Pulsar Timing Array (EPTA) collaboration. The most significant candidate event from this search has a gravitational wave frequency of 4-5 nHz. Such a signal could be generated by a supermassive black hole binary (SMBHB) in the local Universe. We present the results of a follow-up analysis of this candidate using both Bayesian and frequentist methods. The Bayesian analysis gives a Bayes factor of 4 in favor of the presence of the CGW over a common uncorrelated noise process, while the frequentist analysis estimates the p-value of the candidate to be 1%, also assuming the presence of common uncorrelated red noise. However, comparing a model that includes both a CGW and a gravitational wave background (GWB) to a GWB only, the Bayes factor in favour of the CGW model is only 0.7. Therefore, we cannot conclusively determine the origin of the observed feature, but we cannot rule it out as a CGW source. We present results of simulations that demonstrate that data containing a weak gravitational wave background can be misinterpreted as data including a CGW and vice versa, providing two plausible explanations of the EPTA DR2 data. Further investigations combining data from all PTA collaborations will be needed to reveal the true origin of this feature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.16226v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Antoniadis, P. Arumugam, S. Arumugam, S. Babak, M. Bagchi, A. S. Bak Nielsen, C. G. Bassa, A. Bathula, A. Berthereau, M. Bonetti, E. Bortolas, P. R. Brook, M. Burgay, R. N. Caballero, A. Chalumeau, D. J. Champion, S. Chanlaridis, S. Chen, I. Cognard, S. Dandapat, D. Deb, S. Desai, G. Desvignes, N. Dhanda-Batra, C. Dwivedi, M. Falxa, I. Ferranti, R. D. Ferdman, A. Franchini, J. R. Gair, B. Goncharov, A. Gopakumar, E. Graikou, J. M. Grie{\ss}meier, L. Guillemot, Y. J. Guo, Y. Gupta, S. Hisano, H. Hu, F. Iraci, D. Izquierdo-Villalba, J. Jang, J. Jawor, G. H. Janssen, A. Jessner, B. C. Joshi, F. Kareem, R. Karuppusamy, E. F. Keane, M. J. Keith, D. Kharbanda, T. Kikunaga, N. Kolhe, M. Kramer, M. A. Krishnakumar, K. Lackeos, K. J. Lee, K. Liu, Y. Liu, A. G. Lyne, J. W. McKee, Y. Maan, R. A. Main, S. Manzini, M. B. Mickaliger, I. C. Nitu, K. Nobleson, A. K. Paladi, A. Parthasarathy, B. B. P. Perera, D. Perrodin, A. Petiteau, N. K. Porayko, A. Possenti, T. Prabu, H. Quelquejay Leclere, P. Rana, A. Samajdar, S. A. Sanidas, A. Sesana, G. Shaifullah, J. Singha, L. Speri, R. Spiewak, A. Srivastava, B. W. Stappers, M. Surnis, S. C. Susarla, A. Susobhanan, K. Takahashi, P. Tarafdar, G. Theureau, C. Tiburzi, E. van der Wateren, A. Vecchio, V. Venkatraman Krishnan, J. P. W. Verbiest, J. Wang, L. Wang, Z. Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: Extragalactic Point Sources in the Southern Surveys at 150, 220 and 280 GHz observed between 2008-2010</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.17535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.17535v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a multi-frequency, multi-epoch catalog of extragalactic sources. The catalog is based on 150, 220, and 280 GHz observations carried out in 2008, 2009, and 2010 using the Millimeter Bolometric Array Camera on the Atacama Cosmology Telescope. We also present and release 280 GHz maps from 2008 and 2010. The catalog contains 483 sources found in a sky area of ${\sim}600$ square degrees. It was obtained by cross-matching sources found in 11 sub-catalogs, one for each season and frequency band. We also include co-added data from ${\sim}150$ and ${\sim}160$ square degrees using two and three years of overlapping observations. We divide the sources into two populations, synchrotron and dusty emitters, based on their spectral behavior in the 150-280 GHz frequency range. We find 284 synchrotron sources and 183 dusty source candidates. Our cross-matching with catalogs from radio to X-ray results in 251 synchrotron sources (88%) and 92 dusty sources (51%) with counterparts and suggests that 91 dusty candidates are not in existing catalogs. We study the variability and number counts of each population. In the case of synchrotron sources, we find year-to-year variability, with a mean value around 35%. As expected, we find no evidence of dusty source variability. Our number counts generally agree with previous measurements and models, except for dusty sources at 280 GHz, where some models overestimate our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.17535v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cristian Vargas (Instituto de Astrof\'isica and Centro de Astro-Ingenie\'ia, Facultad de F\'isica, Pontificia Universidad Cat\'olica de Chile, Av. Vicu\~na Mackenna 4860, 7820436 Macul, Santiago, Chile), Carlos H. L\'opez-Caraballo (Instituto de Astrof\'isica de Canarias, E-38200 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain, Departamento de Astrof\'isica, Universidad de La Laguna, E-38206 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain), Elia S. Battistelli (Sapienza - University of Rome - Physics department, Piazzale Aldo Moro 5 I-00185, Rome, Italy), Rolando Dunner (Instituto de Astrof\'isica and Centro de Astro-Ingenie\'ia, Facultad de F\'isica, Pontificia Universidad Cat\'olica de Chile, Av. Vicu\~na Mackenna 4860, 7820436 Macul, Santiago, Chile), Gerrit Farren (Kavli Institute for Cosmology Cambridge, Madingley Road, Cambridge CB3 0HA, UK), Megan Gralla (Department of Astronomy/Steward Observatory, University of Arizona, 933 N. Cherry Ave., Tucson, AZ 85721, USA), Kirsten R. Hall (Center for Astrophysics | Harvard &amp; Smithsonian, 60 Garden St., Cambridge, MA 02138, USA), Carlos Herv\'ias-Caimapo (Instituto de Astrof\'isica and Centro de Astro-Ingenie\'ia, Facultad de F\'isica, Pontificia Universidad Cat\'olica de Chile, Av. Vicu\~na Mackenna 4860, 7820436 Macul, Santiago, Chile), Matt Hilton (Astrophysics Research Centre, School of Mathematics, Statistics, and Computer Science, University of KwaZulu-Natal, Westville Campus, Durban 4041, South Africa), Adam D. Hincks (David A. Dunlap Department of Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics, University of Toronto, 50 St. George St., Toronto ON M5S 3H4, Canada, Specola Vaticana), Kevin Huffenberger (Department of Physics, Florida State University, Tallahassee FL, USA 32306), Tobias Marriage (The William H. Miller III Department of Physics and Astronomy, Johns Hopkins University, 3701 San Martin Drive, Baltimore, MD 21220, USA), Tony Mroczkowski (European Southern Observatory, Karl-Schwarzschild-Str. 2, D-85748, Garching, Germany), Michael D. Niemack (Department of Physics, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14853, USA, Department of Astronomy, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14853, USA), Lyman Page (Joseph Henry Laboratories of Physics, Jadwin Hall, Princeton University, Princeton, NJ, USA 08544), Bruce Partridge (Department of Physics and Astronomy, Haverford College, Haverford, PA, USA 19041), Felipe Rojas (Instituto de Astrof\'isica and Centro de Astro-Ingenie\'ia, Facultad de F\'isica, Pontificia Universidad Cat\'olica de Chile, Av. Vicu\~na Mackenna 4860, 7820436 Macul, Santiago, Chile), Francesca Rizzo (Cosmic Dawn Center, Denmark, Niels Bohr Institute, University of Copenhagen, Jagtvej 128, 2200 Copenhagen N, Denmark), Crist\'obal Sif\'on (Instituto de F\'isica, Pontificia Universidad Cat\'olica de Valpara\'iso, Casilla 4059, Valpara\'iso, Chile), Suzanne Staggs (Joseph Henry Laboratories of Physics, Jadwin Hall, Princeton University, Princeton, NJ, USA 08544), Edward J. Wollack (NASA/Goddard Space Flight Center, Greenbelt, MD, USA 20771)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large extra dimensions from higher-dimensional inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.20282</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.20282v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose the possibility that compact extra dimensions can obtain large size by higher dimensional inflation, relating the weakness of the actual gravitational force to the size of the observable universe. Solution to the horizon problem implies that the fundamental scale of gravity is smaller than $10^{13}$ GeV which can be realised in a braneworld framework for any number of extra dimensions. However, requirement of (approximate) flat power spectrum of primordial density fluctuations consistent with present observations makes this simple proposal possible only for one extra dimension at around the micron scale. After the end of five-dimensional inflation, the radion modulus can be stabilised at a vacuum with positive energy of the order of the present dark energy scale. An attractive possibility is based on the contribution to the Casimir energy of right-handed neutrinos with a mass at a similar scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.20282v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.103508</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109 (2024) 103508</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Luis A. Anchordoqui, Ignatios Antoniadis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Axion dark matter with not quite black hole domination</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.17073</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.17073v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the effects of an early cosmological period dominated by primordial 2-2-holes on axion dark matter. The 2-2-holes emerge as a new family of horizonless classical solutions for ultracompact matter distributions in quadratic gravity, a candidate theory of quantum gravity. Thermal 2-2-holes, sourced by relativistic thermal gas, exhibit Hawking-like radiation and fulfill the entropy-area law before they become remnants with almost no radiation. In this paper, we consider the remnant contribution to dark matter (DM) small and adopt the axion DM scenario by the misalignment mechanism. We show that a 2-2-hole domination phase in the evolution of the universe changes the axion mass window obtained from the dark matter abundance constraints. The biggest effect occurs when the remnants have the Planck mass, which is the case for a strongly coupled quantum gravity. The change in abundance constraints for the Planck mass 2-2-hole remnants amounts to that of the primordial black hole (PBH) counterpart. Therefore, since we use the revised constraints from gravitational waves on the initial fraction of 2-2-holes, the results here can also be considered the updated version of the PBH case. As a result, the lower limit on the axion mass is found as $m_a \sim10^{-9}$ eV. Furthermore, the domination scenario itself constrains the remnant mass $ M_{\mathrm{min}}$ considerably. Given that we focus on the pre-BBN domination scenario in order not to interfere with BBN (Big Bang nucleosynthesis) constraints, the remnant mass window becomes $m_{\mathrm{Pl}} \lesssim M_{\mathrm{min}} \lesssim 0.1\;\rm{g}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.17073v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.55730/1300-0101.2758</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Turk. J. Phys. 48 (2024) 3, 50-74</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ufuk Aydemir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The European Low Frequency Survey on the Simons Array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10309v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we present the European Low Frequency Survey (ELFS), a project that will enable foregrounds-free measurements of the primordial $B$-mode polarization and a detection of the tensor-to-scalar ratio, $r$, to a level $\sigma(r) = 0.001$ by measuring the Galactic and extra-galactic emissions in the 5--120\,GHz frequency window. Indeed, the main difficulty in measuring the B-mode polarization comes from the fact that many other processes in the Universe also emit polarized microwaves, which obscure the faint Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) signal. The first stage of this project is being carried out in synergy with the Simons Array (SA) collaboration, installing a 5.5--11\,GHz (X-band) coherent receiver at the focus of one of the three 3.5\,m SA telescopes in Atacama, Chile, followed by the installation of the QUIJOTE-MFI2 in the 10--20 GHz range. We designate this initial iteration of the ELFS program as ELFS-SA. The receivers are equipped with a fully digital back-end that will provide a frequency resolution of 1\,MHz across the band, allowing us to clean the scientific signal from unwanted radio frequency interference, particularly from low-Earth orbit satellite mega constellations. This paper reviews the scientific motivation for ELFS and its instrumental characteristics, and provides an update on the development of ELFS-SA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10309v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proc. SPIE conference on Astronomical Telescopes + Instrumentation, Yokohama, 16-22 June 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Aniello Mennella, Kam Arnold, Susanna Azzoni, Carlo Baccigalupi, A. J. Banday, Rita Bel\'en Barreiro, Darcy Barron, Marco Bersanelli, Francisco J. Casas, Sean Casey, Elena de la Hoz, Cristian Franceschet, Michael E. Jones, Ricardo T. Gen\'ova-Santos, R. Hoyland, Adrian T. Lee, Enrique Martinez-Gonzalez, Filippo Montonati, Jos\'e-Alberto Rubi\~no-Mart\'in, Angela Taylor, Patricio Vielva</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
