<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO</link>
    <description>astro-ph.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 04:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The causal effect of cosmic filaments on dark matter halos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13010v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The way in which the large-scale cosmic environment affects galactic properties is not yet understood. Dark matter halos, which embed galaxies, initially evolve following linear theory. Their subsequent evolution is driven by non-linear structure formation in the halo region and in its outer environment. In this work, we present the first study where we explicitly control the linear part of the evolution of the halo, thus revealing the role of non-linear effects on halo formation. We focus specifically on the effect of proximity to a large cosmological filament. We employ the splicing method to keep fixed the initial density, velocity, and potential fields where a halo will form while changing its outer environment, from an isolated state to one where the halo is near a large filament. In the regime of Milky Way-mass halos, we find that mass and virial radius of such halos are not affected by even drastic changes of environment, whereas halo spin and shape orientation with respect to a massive filament is largely impacted, with fluctuations of up to 80 % around the mean value. Our results suggest that halo orientation and shape cannot be predicted accurately from a local analysis in the initial conditions alone. This has direct consequences on the modeling of intrinsic alignment for cosmic shear surveys, like Euclid. Our results highlight that non-linear couplings to the large-scale environment may have an amplitude comparable to linear effects, and should thus be treated explicitly in analytical models of dark matter halo formation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13010v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anatole Storck, Corentin Cadiou, Oscar Agertz, Daniela Gal\'arraga-Espinosa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The relative constraining power of the high-$z$ 21-cm dipole and monopole signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13020</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13020v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The 21-cm background is a promising probe of early star formation and black hole activity. While a slew of experiments on the ground seek to detect the 21-cm monopole and spatial fluctuations on large $\sim 10$ arcminute scales, little work has been done on the prospects for detecting the 21-cm dipole signal or its utility as a probe of early galaxies. Though an intrinsically weak signal relative to the monopole, its direction is known well from the cosmic microwave background and wide-field surveys, plus as a relative measurement the dipole could help relax instrumental requirements. In order to understand the constraining power of the dipole, in this work we perform parameter inference on mock datasets that include the dipole, monopole, or both signals. We find that while the monopole does provide the best constraints for a given integration time, constraints from a dipole measurement are competitive, and can in principle constrain the cosmic star formation rate density and efficiency of X-ray photon production in early $z \sim 15$ galaxies to better than a factor of $\sim 2$. This result holds for most of the available prior volume, which is set by constraints on galaxy luminosity functions, the reionization history, and upper limits from 21-cm power spectrum experiments. We also find that predictions for the monopole from a dipole measurement are robust to different choices of signal model. As a result, the 21-cm dipole signal is a valuable target for future observations and offers a robust cross-check on monopole measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13020v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jordan Mirocha, Chris Anderson, Tzu-Ching Chang, Olivier Dor\'e, Adam Lidz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Updated cosmological constraints in extended parameter space with Planck PR4, DESI BAO, and SN: dynamical dark energy, neutrino masses, lensing anomaly, and the Hubble tension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13022v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the updated constraints on cosmological parameters in a 12 parameter cosmology extended with dynamical dark energy parameters ($w_0$, $w_a$), sum of neutrino masses ($\sum m_{\nu}$), effective number of neutrinos ($N_{\rm eff}$), scaling of the lensing amplitude ($A_{\rm lens}$), and running of the scalar spectral index ($\alpha_s$). For 'CMB' data, we use the latest Planck PR4 (2020) HiLLiPoP and LoLLiPoP likelihoods, Planck PR4+ACT DR6 lensing, and Planck 2018 lowl-$l$ TT likelihoods. Also, we use the latest DESI DR1 BAO likelihoods and SNeIa likelihoods from the Pantheon+ and DESY5 samples. We find: i) Contrary to the findings of DESI collaboration, we find that the CMB+BAO+Pantheon+ leads to the inclusion of cosmological constant within $2\sigma$, while CMB+BAO+DESY5 excludes the same at more than 2$\sigma$. Thus, the dynamical nature of dark energy cannot yet be considered a robust cosmological signature. As pointed out in earlier literature, the DESY5 SNe sample might have systematics which are driving the exclusion of cosmological constant. ii) We find that for certain data combinations lead to a 1$\sigma$+ detection of $\sum m_{\nu}$, and we get a posterior peak in all dataset combinations, which is an encouraging trend towards future detection. We also provide a robust bound of $\sum m_{\nu} \lesssim 0.3$ eV (95%). Given the current uncertainty in determining the correct underlying cosmological model, we prescribe this bound for the cosmology and particle physics community. iii) With CMB+BAO+SNe, we find that $A_{\rm lens}=1$ is included at 2$\sigma$ but not at $1\sigma$. This indicates that with Planck PR4 likelihoods, there is currently no lensing anomaly in a dynamical dark energy cosmology. iv) We find that even in this largely extended cosmology, the Hubble tension persists at the level of 3.2-3.9$\sigma$. (truncated)</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13022v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shouvik Roy Choudhury, Teppei Okumura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using Two-Frequency Dust Spectral Matching to Separate Galactic Synchrotron and Free-Free Temperature Foregrounds from the CMB</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13132v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a method for removing CMB and anomalous microwave emission (AME, or spinning dust) intensity signals at high to intermediate Galactic latitudes in temperature sky maps at frequencies roughly between 5 and 40 GHz. The method relies on the assumption of a spatially uniform combined dust (AME and thermal) rms spectral energy distribution for these regions, but is otherwise model independent. A difference map is produced from input maps at two different frequencies in thermodynamic temperature: the two frequencies are chosen such that the rms AME signal in the lower frequency (~5 - 40 GHz) map is equivalent to the thermal dust emission rms in the higher frequency (~95 - 230 GHz) map. Given the high spatial correlation between AME and thermal dust, the resulting difference map is dominated by synchrotron and free-free foreground components, and can thus provide useful insight into the morphology and possible spectral variations of these components at high latitudes. We show examples of these difference maps obtained with currently available WMAP and Planck data and demonstrate the efficacy of CMB and dust mitigation using this method. We also use these maps, in conjunction with Haslam 408 MHz and WHAM H-alpha observations, to form an estimate of the diffuse synchrotron spectral index in temperature on degree scales. The hybrid analysis approach we describe is advantageous in situations where frequency coverage is insufficient to break spectral degeneracies between AME and synchrotron.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13132v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. L. Weiland, Charles L. Bennett, Graeme E. Addison, Mark Halpern, Gary Hinshaw</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The model-independent evidence of cosmic acceleration revisited</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13399v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the null test of cosmic accelerated expansion by using the Baryon Acoustic Oscillation (BAO) measurements released by the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument, and we find that the latest BAO data alone can provide strong model-independent evidence for the existence of accelerated expansion in the Universe. Using Gaussian Process reconstruction, we derive the deceleration parameter $q(z)$ from the BAO data, revealing that accelerated expansion persisted until $z \lesssim 0.833$. By further incorporating data from Cosmic Chronometers and 6 expansion rate measured by type Ia supernovae, we find that accelerated expansion continued until $z \lesssim 0.417$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13399v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuchen Lu, Shengqing Gao, Yungui Gong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First Step Towards Matter Power Spectrum Reconstruction with Stage-III Weak Gravitational Lensing Surveys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13404</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13404v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Weak gravitational lensing (WL) surveys provide insight into the matter distribution over an extensive range of scales. Current WL results are in mild tension with cosmic microwave background measurements from the early Universe. Reconstructing the matter power spectrum from their measurements instead of condensing the information into a single cosmological parameter may help locate the origin of these differences. To investigate the cosmic shear measurements of Stage-III WL surveys, we compare their tomographic data by assuming a simple parametric model for the matter power spectrum. The model allows the comparison of surveys with different characteristics and, in an agnostic approach, gives insight into the shape of the matter power spectrum preferred by the data without assuming a cosmological model. For the matter power spectrum, we assume a double power law model in scale factor and wavenumber. The best-fit amplitude and exponents are inferred in an MCMC analysis. We identify the scales to which the data is most sensitive. We test the sensitivity to different assumptions of the intrinsic alignment strength. We find that Stage-III surveys' constraining power on the power spectrum shape and evolution is still limited. Most information can be summarised as an overall amplitude at a pivot point in wave number and scale factor, while constraints on the power law indices are considerably weaker. Nevertheless, all surveys prefer a weaker rate of growth from $z=$ 0.5 to 0.1 than predicted. The assumed intrinsic alignment strength is found to have no significant impact on the measured parameters and goodness of fit. Direct estimates of the matter power spectrum from Stage-III weak lensing surveys can, in principle, be used to locate the physical origin of the $S_8$ tension. We present a simple methodology for the first steps in this direction but find that current constraints are still weak.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13404v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeger C. Broxterman, Konrad Kuijken</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constant roll and non-Gaussian tail in light of logarithmic duality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13500v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The curvature perturbation in a model of constant-roll (CR) inflation is interpreted in view of the logarithmic duality discovered in Ref. [1] according to the $\delta N$ formalism. We confirm that the critical value $\beta:=\ddot{\varphi}/(H\dot{\varphi})=-3/2$ determining whether the CR condition is stable or not is understood as the point at which the dual solutions, i.e., the attractor and non-attractor solutions of the field equation, are interchanged. For the attractor-solution domination, the curvature perturbation in the CR model is given by a simple logarithmic mapping of a Gaussian random field, which can realise both the exponential tail (i.e., the single exponential decay) and the Gumbel-distribution-like tail (i.e., the double exponential decay) of the probability density function, depending on the value of $\beta$. Such a tail behaviour is important for, e.g., the estimation of the primordial black hole abundance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13500v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryoto Inui, Hayato Motohashi, Shi Pi, Yuichiro Tada, Shuichiro Yokoyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on $f(R)$ gravity from tSZE-selected SPT galaxy clusters and weak lensing mass calibration from DES and HST</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13556v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present constraints on the $f(R)$ gravity model using a sample of 1,005 galaxy clusters in the redshift range $0.25 - 1.78$ that have been selected through the thermal Sunyaev-Zel'dovich effect (tSZE) from South Pole Telescope (SPT) data and subjected to optical and near-infrared confirmation with the Multi-component Matched Filter (MCMF) algorithm. We employ weak gravitational lensing mass calibration from the Dark Energy Survey (DES) Year 3 data for 688 clusters at $z &lt; 0.95$ and from the Hubble Space Telescope (HST) for 39 clusters with $0.6 &lt; z &lt; 1.7$. Our cluster sample is a powerful probe of $f(R)$ gravity, because this model predicts a scale-dependent enhancement in the growth of structure, which impacts the halo mass function (HMF) at cluster mass scales. To account for these modified gravity effects on the HMF, our analysis employs a semi-analytical approach calibrated with numerical simulations. Combining calibrated cluster counts with primary cosmic microwave background (CMB) temperature and polarization anisotropy measurements from the Planck2018 release, we derive robust constraints on the $f(R)$ parameter $f_{R0}$. Our results, $\log_{10} |f_{R0}| &lt; -5.32$ at the 95 % credible level, are the tightest current constraints on $f(R)$ gravity from cosmological scales. This upper limit rules out $f(R)$-like deviations from general relativity that result in more than a $\sim$20 % enhancement of the cluster population on mass scales $M_\mathrm{200c}&gt;3\times10^{14}M_\odot$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13556v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. M. L. Vogt, S. Bocquet, C. T. Davies, J. J. Mohr, F. Schmidt, C. -Z. Ruan, B. Li, C. Hern\'andez-Aguayo, S. Grandis, L. E. Bleem, M. Klein, T. Schrabback, M. Aguena, D. Brooks, D. L. Burke, A. Campos, A. Carnero Rosell, J. Carretero, M. Costanzi, L. N. da Costa, M. E. S. Pereira, J. De Vicente, P. Doel, S. Everett, I. Ferrero, J. Frieman, J. Garc\'ia-Bellido, M. Gatti, G. Giannini, D. Gruen, R. A. Gruendl, S. R. Hinton, D. L. Hollowood, S. Lee, M. Lima, J. L. Marshall, J. Mena-Fern\'andez, R. Miquel, J. Myles, M. Paterno, A. Pieres, A. A. Plazas Malag\'on, C. L. Reichardt, A. K. Romer, S. Samuroff, A. Sarkar, E. Sanchez, I. Sevilla-Noarbe, M. Smith, E. Suchyta, M. E. C. Swanson, G. Tarle, V. Vikram, N. Weaverdyck, J. Weller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining Primordial Non-Gaussianity with Density-Split Clustering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13583v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Obtaining tight constraints on primordial non-Gaussianity (PNG) is a key step in discriminating between different models for cosmic inflation. The constraining power from large-scale structure (LSS) measurements is expected to overtake that from cosmic microwave background (CMB) anisotropies with the next generation of galaxy surveys including the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) and Euclid. We consider whether Density-Split Clustering (DSC) can help improve PNG constraints from these surveys for local, equilateral and orthogonal types. DSC separates a surveyed volume into regions based on local density and measures the clustering statistics within each environment. Using the Quijote simulations and the Fisher information formalism, we compare PNG constraints from the standard halo power spectrum, DSC power spectra and joint halo/DSC power spectra. We find that the joint halo/DSC power spectra outperform the halo power spectrum by factors of $\sim$ 1.4, 8.8, and 3.6 for local, equilateral and orthogonal PNG, respectively. This is driven by the higher-order information that DSC captures on small scales. We find that applying DSC to a halo field does not allow sample variance cancellation on large scales by providing multiple tracers of the same volume with different local PNG responses. Additionally, we introduce a Fourier space analysis for DSC and study the impact of several modifications to the pipeline, such as varying the smoothing radius and the number of density environments and replacing random query positions with lattice points.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13583v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Morawetz, Enrique Paillas, Will J. Percival</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Acquiring the Lefschetz thimbles: efficient evaluation of the diffraction integral for lensing in wave optics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12991v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Evaluating the Kirchhoff-Fresnel diffraction integral is essential in studying wave effects in astrophysical lensing, but is often intractable because of the highly oscillatory integrated. A recent breakthrough was made by exploiting the Picard-Lefschetz theory: the integral can be performed along the `Lefschetz thimbles' in the complex domain where the integrand is not oscillatory but rapidly converging. The application of this method, however, has been limited by both the unfamiliar concepts involved and the low numerical efficiency of the method used to find the Lefschetz thimbles. In this paper, we give simple examples of the Lefschetz thimbles and define the `flow lines' that facilitate the understanding of the concepts. Based on this, we propose new ways to obtain the Lefschetz thimbles with high numerical efficiency, which provide an effective tool for studying wave effects in astrophysical lensing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12991v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae2127</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Xun Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radio Lines from accreting Axion Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13121</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13121v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Axion-like particles, which we call axions, can compose the missing dark matter and may form substructures such as miniclusters and axion stars. We obtain the mass distributions of axion stars derived from their host miniclusters in our galaxy and find a significant number of axion stars reaching the decay mass, the critical mass set by the axion-photon coupling. Axion stars that have reached the decay mass can accrete surrounding axions either via or directly from their host miniclusters, subsequently converting them into radio photons through parametric resonance. We demonstrate that this accretion provides observable signals by proposing two scenarios: 1) external accretion of background dark matter occurring via miniclusters, and 2) internal accretion of isolated systems occurring directly from the minicluster onto its core. The emitted radio photons are nearly monochromatic with energies around the half of the axion mass. The radio-line signal emanating from such axion stars provides a distinctive opportunity searching for axions, overcoming the widespread radio backgrounds. We estimate the expected radio-line flux density to constrain the axion-photon coupling $g_{a\gamma\gamma}$ at each axion mass and find that the resultant line flux density is strong enough to be observed in radio telescopes such as LOFAR, FAST, ALMA, and upcoming SKA. We can constrain the axion-photon coupling down to $g_{a\gamma\gamma} \simeq 10^{-12} - 10^{-11}\,{\rm GeV}^{-1}$, reaching even $10^{-13}\,{\rm GeV}^{-1}$ depending on the accretion models of axion stars, over an axion mass range of $m_a\simeq 10^{-7} - 10^{-2}\,{\rm eV}$. From a different perspective, this radio-line signal could be a strong hint of an axion at the corresponding mass and also of axion stars within our galaxy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13121v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dennis Maseizik, Sagnik Mondal, Hyeonseok Seong, G\"unter Sigl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Induced gravitational waves, metastable cosmic strings and primordial black holes in GUTs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13584v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explore the cosmological and astrophysical implications of a realistic hybrid inflation model based on flipped $SU(5)$. The model contains superheavy metastable cosmic strings arising from a waterfall field that encounters a limited number of $e$-foldings during the inflationary phase. In addition to the gravitational waves emitted by the metastable strings, there also appear scalar induced gravitational waves linked to the waterfall phase transition. These two independent sources of gravitational waves can yield a combined spectrum that is compatible with the recent PTA measurements, and with additional features that can be probed in future experiments. We also show the appearance of primordial black holes with mass on the order of $10^{26}$ g from the waterfall phase transition, and with an abundance that can be tested in the gravitational lensing experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13584v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rinku Maji, Ahmad Moursy, Qaisar Shafi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrated perturbation theory for cosmological tensor fields. I. Basic formulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.10435</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.10435v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In order to extract maximal information about cosmology from the large-scale structure of the Universe, one needs to use every bit of signal that can be observed. Beyond the spatial distributions of astronomical objects, the spatial correlations of tensor fields, such as galaxy spins and shapes, are ones of promising sources that can be accessed in the era of large surveys in the near future. The perturbation theory is a powerful tool to analytically describe the behaviors and evolutions of correlation statistics on large scales for a given cosmology. In this paper, we formulate a nonlinear perturbation theory of tensor fields in general, based on the formulation of integrated perturbation theory for the scalar-valued bias, generalizing it to include the tensor-valued bias. To take advantage of rotational symmetry, the formalism is constructed on the basis of the irreducible decomposition of tensors, identifying physical variables which are invariant under the rotation of the coordinates system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.10435v5</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.063543</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 063543 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Takahiko Matsubara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrated perturbation theory for cosmological tensor fields. II. Loop corrections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.11085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.11085v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the previous paper [arXiv:2210.10435], the nonlinear perturbation theory of cosmological density field is generalized to include the tensor-valued bias of astronomical objects, such as spins and shapes of galaxies and any other tensors of arbitrary ranks which are associated with objects that we can observe. We apply this newly developed method to explicitly calculate nonlinear power spectra and correlation functions both in real space and in redshift space. Multi-dimensional integrals that appear in loop corrections are reduced to combinations of one-dimensional Hankel transforms, thanks to the spherical basis of the formalism, and the final expressions are numerically evaluated in a very short time using an algorithm of the fast Fourier transforms such as \textsc{FFTLog}. As an illustrative example, numerical evaluations of loop corrections of the power spectrum and correlation function of the rank-2 tensor field are demonstrated with a simple model of tensor bias.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.11085v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.063544</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 063544 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Takahiko Matsubara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrated perturbation theory for cosmological tensor fields. III. Projection effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.13304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.13304v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The integrated perturbation theory (iPT) is a set of methods in nonlinear perturbation theory for the structure formation in the Universe. In Papers I and II [arXiv:2210.10435, arXiv:2210.11085], the basic formalism and technical methods of the iPT for cosmological tensor fields are developed, generalizing the corresponding theory for scalar fields. In previous papers, methods to predict statistical quantities, such as power spectra, correlation functions, etc., of three-dimensional tensor fields are developed based on the iPT. However, observations of tensors, such as angular momenta and shapes of galaxies, etc., are only possible after the three-dimensional tensors are projected onto the two-dimensional sky. In this paper, power spectra and correlation functions of projected two-dimensional tensors are related to those of original three-dimensional tensors, so that one can make predictions for the observable statistics of projected tensor fields from the iPT. The relations are consistently represented on the basis of irreducible decomposition of both two- and three-dimensional tensors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.13304v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.063545</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 063545 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Takahiko Matsubara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Gravitational Lensing Imprints of DES Y3 Superstructures on the CMB: A Matched Filtering Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18278</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18278v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: $ $Low density cosmic voids gravitationally lens the cosmic microwave background (CMB), leaving a negative imprint on the CMB convergence $\kappa$. This effect provides insight into the distribution of matter within voids, and can also be used to study the growth of structure. We measure this lensing imprint by cross-correlating the Planck CMB lensing convergence map with voids identified in the Dark Energy Survey Year 3 data set, covering approximately 4,200 deg$^2$ of the sky. We use two distinct void-finding algorithms: a 2D void-finder which operates on the projected galaxy density field in thin redshift shells, and a new code, Voxel, which operates on the full 3D map of galaxy positions. We employ an optimal matched filtering method for cross-correlation, using the MICE N-body simulation both to establish the template for the matched filter and to calibrate detection significances. Using the DES Y3 photometric luminous red galaxy sample, we measure $A_\kappa$, the amplitude of the observed lensing signal relative to the simulation template, obtaining $A_\kappa = 1.03 \pm 0.22$ ($4.6\sigma$ significance) for Voxel and $A_\kappa = 1.02 \pm 0.17$ ($5.9\sigma$ significance) for 2D voids, both consistent with $\Lambda$CDM expectations. We additionally invert the 2D void-finding process to identify superclusters in the projected density field, for which we measure $A_\kappa = 0.87 \pm 0.15$ ($5.9\sigma$ significance). The leading source of noise in our measurements is Planck noise, implying that future data from the Atacama Cosmology Telescope (ACT), South Pole Telescope (SPT) and CMB-S4 will increase sensitivity and allow for more precise measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18278v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Umut Demirbozan, Seshadri Nadathur, Ismael Ferrero, Pablo Fosalba, Andras Kovacs, Ramon Miquel, Christopher T. Davies, Shivam Pandey, Monika Adamow, Keith Bechtol, Alex Drlica-Wagner, Robert Gruendl, Will Hartley, Adriano Pieres, Ashley Ross, Eli Rykoff, Erin Sheldon, Brian Yanny, Tim Abbott, Michel Aguena, Sahar Allam, Otavio Alves, David Bacon, Emmanuel Bertin, Sebastian Bocquet, David Brooks, Aurelio Carnero Rosell, Jorge Carretero, Ross Cawthon, Luiz da Costa, Maria Elidaiana da Silva Pereira, Juan De Vicente, Shantanu Desai, Peter Doel, Spencer Everett, Brenna Flaugher, Douglas Friedel, Josh Frieman, Marco Gatti, Enrique Gaztanaga, Giulia Giannini, Gaston Gutierrez, Samuel Hinton, Devon L. Hollowood, David James, Niall Jeffrey, Kyler Kuehn, Ofer Lahav, Sujeong Lee, Jennifer Marshall, Juan Mena-Fern\'andez, Joe Mohr, Justin Myles, Ricardo Ogando, Andr\'es Plazas Malag\'on, Aaron Roodman, Eusebio Sanchez, Ignacio Sevilla, Mathew Smith, Marcelle Soares-Santos, Eric Suchyta, Molly Swanson, Gregory Tarle, Noah Weaverdyck, Jochen Weller, Philip Wiseman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrated perturbation theory for cosmological tensor fields. IV. Full-sky formulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09038v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In Papers I-III [arXiv:2210.10435, arXiv:2210.11085, arXiv:2304.13304], we use the flat-sky and distant-observer approximations to develop a formalism with which the correlation statistics of cosmological tensor fields are calculated by the nonlinear perturbation theory, generalizing the integrated perturbation theory for scalar fields. In this work, the formalism is extended to include the full-sky and wide-angle effects in evaluating the power spectra and correlation functions of cosmological tensor fields of any rank. With the newly developed formalism, one can evaluate the nonlinear power spectra and correlation functions to arbitrary higher orders in principle. After describing the general formalism, we explicitly derive and give analytic results of the lowest-order linear theory for an illustrative purpose in this paper. The derived linear formulas with full-sky and wide-angle effects are numerically compared with the previous formulas with flat-sky and distant-observer limits in a simple model of tensor bias.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09038v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.063546</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 063546 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Takahiko Matsubara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Excess cataloged X-ray and radio sources at galaxy-cluster virial shocks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.16946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.16946v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We detect a highly significant excess of X-ray (2RXS) and radio (NVSS, GMRT, VLSSr) catalog sources when stacked around MCXC galaxy clusters and groups, narrowly confined within $\lesssim100\mathrm{\,kpc}$ of the $\sim2.4 R_{500}$ virial shock radius (inferred from previous continuum stacking), with similar X-ray ($\sim4\sigma$ for $443$ clusters) and radio ($\sim4\sigma$ for $485$ clusters) characteristics ($&gt;5\sigma$ joint). The excess sources show $10-100$ kpc scales, $L_X(0.1-2.4\mbox{ keV})\simeq10^{42-43}\mathrm{\,erg\,s^{-1}}$ or $\nu L_\nu(\nu=1.4\mbox{ GHz}) \simeq 10^{40-41}\mathrm{\,erg\,s^{-1}}$ luminosities, and a preferentially radial radio-polarization. The narrow localization and properties of the excess identify these sources not as AGN, often invoked speculatively for excess X-ray sources at cluster outskirts, but rather as infalling gaseous clumps interacting with the virial shock, probably galactic halos and possibly outflow remnants. The local excess of such discrete, radio-to-$\gamma$-ray sources around an object can probe its virial shock also at high redshifts and sub-cluster scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.16946v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gideon Ilani, Kuan-Chou Hou, Uri Keshet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unitarity in the non-relativistic regime and implications for dark matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02222v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Unitarity sets upper limits on partial-wave elastic and inelastic cross-sections, which are often violated by perturbative computations. We discuss the dynamics underlying these limits in the non-relativistic regime, namely long-range interactions, and show how the resummation of the 2-particle-irreducible diagrams arising from squaring inelastic processes unitarizes both elastic and inelastic cross-sections. We provide a simple prescription to obtain the unitarized cross-sections from those that do not include resummation of the squared inelastic processes. Our results are model-independent, apply to all partial waves, and affect elastic and inelastic cross-sections, with extensive implications for new physics scenarios, such as dark-matter freeze-out, indirect detection and self-interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02222v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2024.139022</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Lett. B 858 (2024) 139022</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Marcos M. Flores, Kalliopi Petraki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter from Anomaly Cancellation at the LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.03749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.03749v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We discuss a class of theories that predict a fermionic dark matter candidate from gauge anomaly cancellation. As an explicit example, we study the predictions in theories where the global symmetry associated with baryon number is promoted to a local gauge symmetry. In this context the symmetry-breaking scale has to be below the multi-TeV scale in order to be in agreement with the cosmological constraints on the dark matter relic density. The new physical "Cucuyo" Higgs boson in the theory has very interesting properties, decaying mainly into two photons in the low mass region, and mainly into dark matter in the intermediate mass region. We study the most important signatures at the Large Hadron Collider, evaluating the experimental bounds. We discuss the correlation between the dark matter relic density, direct detection and collider constraints. We find that these theories are still viable, and are susceptible to being probed in current, and future high-luminosity, running.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.03749v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jon Butterworth, Hridoy Debnath, Pavel Fileviez Perez, Yoran Yeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytic bounds on late-time axion-scalar cosmologies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17030</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17030v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The cosmological dynamics of multiple scalar/pseudoscalar fields are difficult to solve, especially when the field-space metric is curved. This presents a challenge in determining whether a given model can support cosmic acceleration, without solving for the on-shell solution. In this work, we present bounds on late-time FLRW-cosmologies in classes of theories that involve arbitrary numbers of scalar and pseudoscalar fields coupled both kinetically (leading to a curved field space metric) and through scalar potentials. Such bounds are proven analytically, independently of initial conditions, with no approximation in the field equations and without referring to explicit solutions. Besides their broad applications to cosmological model building, our bounds can be applied to studying asymptotic cosmologies of certain classes of string compactifications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17030v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gary Shiu, Flavio Tonioni, Hung V. Tran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>G\"odel-type spacetimes in $f(Q)$ gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04750</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04750v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: There is ongoing interest in the nonmetricity formulation of gravity. The nonlinear extension of the theory, called $f(Q)$ gravity, has recently been proposed and offers a promising avenue for addressing some of the long-standing challenges in cosmology and fundamental physics. A number of solutions have already been found that have confirmed the usefulness of the theory for astrophysics and cosmology. Motivated by earlier work on G\"odel-type spacetimes we investigate whether $f(Q)$ gravity admits such cosmological solutions, which entail causality violation. In the coincident gauge, which is shown to be a legitimate gauge because the connection field equations are satisfied, we find that G\"odel-type metrics are allowed by this modified gravity theory for any function $f(Q)$. Noncausal and causal solutions exist depending on the matter content. For a perfect fluid, out of all G\"odel-type metrics only G\"odel's original model is allowed in $f(Q)$ gravity, implying violation of causality. The requirement that energy conditions be obeyed by the fluid leads to mild restrictions on $f(Q)$. For a massless scalar field in the presence of a cosmological constant, there are causal solutions for any reasonable function $f(Q)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04750v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. M. Silva, M. J. Rebou\c{c}as, N. A. Lemos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on freeze-in dark matter from Lyman-$\alpha$ forest and 21-cm signal : single-field models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.08225v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We report new Lyman-$\alpha$ and 21-cm constraints on freeze-in dark matter (FIDM) which injects energy into the intergalactic medium either through annihilation or decay to photon(s) or electron-positron pair. With respect to Lyman-$\alpha$ we fix the baseline ionization history using low redshift data about astrophysical reionization, whereas for 21-cm signal we adopt the baseline values of 21-cm power spectrum through a standard modeling of star formation developed so far. Using the latest numerical tools, we show that (i) for sterile neutrino FIDM, current Lyman-$\alpha$ data and future sensitivity of SKA-low (1000 hrs) on the 21-cm power spectra excludes the FIDM mass up to $1.8\times 10^{-3}$ GeV at 95$\%$ CL and $5.46\times 10^{-4}$ GeV, respectively, and (ii) for millicharged FIDM, current Lyman-$\alpha$ data only excludes the millicharge down to $10^{-8}$ within the FIDM mass range of $10^{-3}-1$ GeV at 95$\%$ CL, suggesting that the surviving parameter space of millicharged FIDM is still intact.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.08225v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zixuan Xu, Quan Zhou, Sibo Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Lensing Tomography of Black Hole Ringdown</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10303v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Strong gravitational lensing occurs when photons pass through the vicinity of a black hole. We investigate this phenomenon in the context of a gravitational-wave event, specifically when a black hole is settling into its final state. The deflection angle of photons mimics the ringdown pattern of the gravitational wave at intermediate times. At late times it has an inverse cubic dependence on observation time. The deviation angle increases exponentially as photons approach the photon ring orbit, reflecting its unstable nature. Our findings are directly applicable to imaging scenarios involving stars against the background of compact binaries, or circumbinary accretion disks, particularly during the merger of two black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10303v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhen Zhong, Vitor Cardoso, Yifan Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
