<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO</link>
    <description>astro-ph.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 02:42:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting holographic dark energy from the perspective of multi-messenger gravitational wave astronomy: future joint observations with short gamma-ray bursts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06873v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The advent of third-generation (3G) gravitational-wave (GW) detectors opens new opportunities for multi-messenger observations of binary neutron star merger events, holding significant potential for probing the history of cosmic expansion. In this paper, we investigate the holographic dark energy (HDE) model by using the future GW standard siren data observed from the 3G GW detectors and the short $\gamma$-ray burst THESEUS-like detector joint observations. We find that GW data alone can achieve a relatively precise estimation of the Hubble constant, with precision of $0.2\%$-$0.6\%$, but its ability to constrain other cosmological parameters remains limited. Nonetheless, since the GW data can break parameter degeneracies generated by the mainstream EM observations, CMB + BAO + SN (CBS), GW standard sirens play a crucial role in enhancing the accuracy of parameter estimation. With the addition of GW data to CBS, the constraints on cosmological parameters $H_0$, $c$ and $\Omega_{\rm{m}}$ can be improved by $63\%$-$88\%$, $27\%$-$44\%$ and $55\%$-$70\%$. In summary, observations of GW standard sirens from 3G GW detectors could be pivotal in helping solve the Hubble tension and probe the fundamental nature of dark energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06873v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tao Han, Ze Li, Jing-Fei Zhang, Xin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prospects of a statistical detection of the 21-cm forest and its potential to constrain the thermal state of the neutral IGM during reionization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06879v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The 21-cm forest signal is a promising probe of the Epoch of Reionization complementary to other 21-cm line observables and Ly$\alpha$ forest signal. Prospects of detecting it have significantly improved in the last decade thanks to the discovery of more than 30 radio-loud quasars at these redshifts, upgrades to telescope facilities, and the notion that neutral hydrogen islands persist down to $z\lesssim 5.5$. We forward-model the 21-cm forest signal using semi-numerical simulations and incorporate various instrumental features to explore the potential of detecting the 21-cm forest at $z=6$, both directly and statistically, with the currently available (uGMRT) and forthcoming (SKA1-low) observatories. We show that it is possible to detect the 1D power spectrum of the 21-cm forest spectrum, especially at large scales of $k\lesssim8.5\,\rm MHz^{-1}$ with the $500\,\rm hr$ of the uGMRT time and $k\lesssim32.4\,\rm MHz^{-1}$ with the SKA1-low over $50\,\rm hr$ if the intergalactic medium (IGM) is $25\%$ neutral and these neutral hydrogen regions have a spin temperature of $\lesssim30\,\rm K$. On the other hand, we infer that a null-detection of the signal with such observations of 10 radio-loud sources at $z\approx6$ can be translated into constraints on the thermal and ionization state of the IGM which are tighter than the currently available measurements. Moreover, a null-detection of the 1D 21-cm forest power spectrum with only $50\,\rm hr$ of the uGMRT observations of 10 radio-loud sources can already be competitive with the Ly$\alpha$ forest and 21-cm tomographic observations in disfavouring models of significantly neutral and cold IGM at $z=6$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06879v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom\'a\v{s} \v{S}oltinsk\'y (TIFR, INAF-OATs), Girish Kulkarni (TIFR), Shriharsh P. Tendulkar (TIFR), James S. Bolton (University of Nottingham)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Astronomy with Dark Matter Detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06883v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a novel way of probing non-gravitational dark matter interactions: dark astronomy, which leverages the dark radiation emitted by dissipative dark sectors. If the mediator of the dark matter self interactions is a dark photon with a small mass that kinetically mixes with the visible photon, the dark radiation flux becomes accessible to underground experiments. We argue that the emission may be dominantly longitudinally polarized, thereby enhancing the sensitivity of direct detection experiments such as XENON and SENSEI to this signal. We introduce a new detection mechanism based on resonant dark-photon-to-photon conversion at the surface of conducting materials, which offers unique directional sensitivity to dark radiation. This mechanism facilitates the development of experiments that combine dark matter detection techniques with methods of traditional astronomy, opening the possibility to map dark radiation sources within our galaxy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06883v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gonzalo Alonso-\'Alvarez, David Curtin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How do uncertainties in galaxy formation physics impact field-level galaxy bias?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06886v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Our ability to extract cosmological information from galaxy surveys is limited by uncertainties in the galaxy-dark matter halo relationship for a given galaxy population, which are governed by the intricacies of galaxy formation. To quantify these uncertainties, we examine quenched and star-forming galaxies using two distinct approaches to modeling galaxy formation: UniverseMachine, an empirical semi-analytic model, and the IllustrisTNG hydrodynamical simulation. We apply a second-order hybrid N-body perturbative bias expansion to each galaxy sample, enabling direct comparison of modeling approaches and revealing how uncertainties in galaxy formation and the galaxy-halo connection affect bias parameters and non-Poisson noise across number density and redshift. Notably, we find that quenched and star-forming galaxies occupy distinct parts of bias parameter spacce, and that the scatter induced from these entirely different galaxy formation models is small when conditioned on similar selections of galaxies. We also detect a signature of assembly bias in our samples; this leads to small but significant deviations from predictions of the analytic bias, while samples with assembly bias removed match these predictions well. This work indicates that galaxy samples from a spectrum of reasonable, physically motivated models for galaxy formation roughly spanning our current understanding give a relatively small range of field-level galaxy bias parameters and relations. We estimate a set of priors from this set of models that should be useful in extracting cosmological information from LRG- and ELG-like samples. Looking forward, this indicates that careful estimates of the range of impacts of galaxy formation for a given sample and cosmological analysis will be an essential ingredient for extracting the most precise cosmological information from current and future large galaxy surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06886v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahlet Shiferaw, Nickolas Kokron, Risa H. Wechsler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The ACCEL2 Project: Precision Measurements of EFT Parameters and BAO Peak Shifts for the Lyman-$\alpha$ Forest</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06892v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present precision measurements of the bias parameters of the one-loop power spectrum model of the Lyman-alpha (Lya) forest, derived within the effective field theory of large-scale structure (EFT). We fit our model to the three-dimensional flux power spectrum measured from the ACCEL2 hydrodynamic simulations. The EFT model fits the data with an accuracy of below 2 percent up to a wavenumber of k = 2 h/Mpc. Further, we analytically derive how non-linearities in the three-dimensional clustering of the Lya forest introduce biases in measurements of the Baryon Acoustic Oscillations (BAO) scaling parameters in radial and transverse directions. From our EFT parameter measurements, we obtain a theoretical error budget of -0.2 (-0.3) percent for the radial (transverse) parameters at redshift two. This corresponds to a shift of -0.3 (0.1) percent for the isotropic (anisotropic) distance measurements. We provide an estimate for the shift of the BAO peak for Lya-quasar cross-correlation measurements assuming analytical and simulation-based scaling relations for the non-linear quasar bias parameters resulting in a shift of -0.2 (-0.1) percent for the radial (transverse) dilation parameters, respectively. This analysis emphasizes the robustness of Lya forest BAO measurements to the theory modeling. We provide informative priors and an error budget for measuring the BAO feature -- a key science driver of the currently observing Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI). Our work paves the way for full-shape cosmological analyses of Lya forest data from DESI and upcoming surveys such as the Prime Focus Spectrograph, WEAVE-QSO, and 4MOST.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06892v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roger de Belsunce, Shi-Fan Chen, Mikhail M. Ivanov, Corentin Ravoux, Solene Chabanier, Jean Sexton, Zarija Lukic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: Semi-Analytic Covariance Matrices for the DR6 CMB Power Spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07068</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07068v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Atacama Cosmology Telescope Data Release 6 (ACT DR6) power spectrum is expected to provide state-of-the-art cosmological constraints, with an associated need for precise error modeling. In this paper we design, and evaluate the performance of, an analytic covariance matrix prescription for the DR6 power spectrum that sufficiently accounts for the complicated ACT map properties. We use recent advances in the literature to handle sharp features in the signal and noise power spectra, and account for the effect of map-level anisotropies on the covariance matrix. In including inhomogeneous survey depth information, the resulting covariance matrix prescription is structurally similar to that used in the $\textit{Planck}$ Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) analysis. We quantify the performance of our prescription using comparisons to Monte Carlo simulations, finding better than $3\%$ agreement. This represents an improvement from a simpler, pre-existing prescription, which differs from simulations by $\sim16\%$. We develop a new method to correct the analytic covariance matrix using simulations, after which both prescriptions achieve better than $1\%$ agreement. This correction method outperforms a commonly used alternative, where the analytic correlation matrix is assumed to be accurate when correcting the covariance. Beyond its use for ACT, this framework should be applicable for future high resolution CMB experiments including the Simons Observatory (SO).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07068v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zachary Atkins, Zack Li, David Alonso, J. Richard Bond, Erminia Calabrese, Adriaan J. Duivenvoorden, Jo Dunkley, Serena Giardiello, Carlos Herv\'ias-Caimapo, J. Colin Hill, Hidde T. Jense, Joshua Kim, Michael D. Niemack, Lyman Page, Adrien La Posta, Thibaut Louis, Kavilan Moodley, Thomas W. Morris, Sigurd Naess, Crist\'obal Sif\'on, Edward J. Wollack</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Born approximation in wave optics gravitational lensing revisited</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07272</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07272v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Gravitational lensing of gravitational waves provides us with much information about the Universe, including the dark matter distribution at small scales. The information about lensed gravitational waves is encapsulated by an amplification factor, which is calculated by an integration of an oscillatory function. The Born approximation, which has been studied in terms of wave optics in gravitational lensing, may provide a means of overcoming the difficulty in evaluating the oscillating function and better understanding the connection between the amplification factor and the lens mass distribution. In this paper, we revisit the Born approximation for a single lens plane. We find that the distortion of gravitational waves induced by wave optics gravitational lensing is in general connected with the mass distribution of the lens object through a convolution integral, where the scale of the kernel is determined by the Fresnel scale. We then study the validivity and accuracy of the Born approximation specifically for the case of a point mass lens for which the exact analytical expression of the amplicfication factor is available. Using the dimensionless parameter $y$, which represents the normalized impact parameter, and the dimensionless parameter $w$, which denotes the normalized frequency, we show that the $n$-th term of the Born approximation scales as $y^{-2}w^{n-1}$. This indicates that, for the case of a point mass lens, the Born approximation is valid when $w$ is less than 1, with its accuracy scaling as $wy^{-2}$ in this regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07272v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hirotaka Yarimoto, Masamune Oguri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kick it like DESI: PNGB quintessence with a dynamically generated initial velocity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07418v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by the hint for time-dependent dynamical dark energy from an analysis of the DESI Baryon Accoustic Oscillation (BAO) data together with information from the Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) and Supernovae (SN), we relax the assumption of a vanishing initial velocity for a quintessence field. In particular we focus on pseudo-Nambu-Goldstone-Boson (PNGB) quintessence in the form of an axion like particle, that can arise as the phase of a complex scalar and could possess derivative couplings to fermions or topological couplings to abelian gauge fields, without upsetting the necessary flatness of its potential. We discuss mechanisms from the aforementioned interactions for sourcing an initial axion field velocity $\dot{\theta_i}$ at redshifts $3\leq z\leq 10$, that will "kick" it into motion. Driven by this initial velocity the axion will first roll up in its potential, similar to "freezing" dark energy. After it has reached the pinnacle of its trajectory, it will start to roll down, and behave as "thawing" quintessence. As a proof of concept we undertake a combined fit to BAO, SN and CMB data at the background level. We find that a scenario with $\dot{\theta_i}=\mathcal{O}(1) \; m_a$, where $m_a$ is the axion mass, is slightly preferred over both $\Lambda$CDM and the conventional "thawing" quintessence with $\dot{\theta_i}=0$. The best fit points for this case exhibit transplanckian decay constants and very flat potentials, which both are in tension with conjectures from string theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07418v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maximilian Berbig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of spatial curvature on forecast constraints from standard and differential redshift drift measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07532v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The redshift drift of objects following the cosmological expansion is a unique model-independent probe of background cosmology, detectable by astrophysical facilities presently under construction. Previous forecasts for such measurements assume flat universes. We explore the impact of relaxing this assumption on the constraining power of the redshift drift, focusing on the two most promising routes for its measurement: the SKA at low redshifts, and the Golden Sample for the ELT's ANDES spectrograph at higher redshifts. We also discuss the cosmological sensitivity of possible differential redshift drift measurements, both on their own and, for the specific case of the Golden Sample, in combination with the standard method. Overall, we find that the sensitivity of the redshift drift to curvature is comparable to that of matter (especially at low redshifts) and higher than the sensitivity to the dark energy equation of state. We also show that the sensitivity of redshift drift measurements to these cosmological parameters is asymmetric with respect to the curvature parameter, being different for open and closed universes with the same absolute value of the curvature parameter $\Omega_k$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07532v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. J. A. P. Martins, M. A. F. Melo e Sousa, S. Q. Fernandes, C. M. J. Marques</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The unexpected shape of the primordial black hole mass function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07709v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a Universe with nearly-Gaussian initial curvature perturbations, the abundance of primordial black holes can be derived from the curvature power spectrum. When the latter is enhanced within a narrow range around a characteristic scale, the resulting mass function has a single distinct peak, corresponding to Schwarzschild radii set by the horizon entry time of that scale. In contrast, we show (both numerically and by providing an analytic estimation) that a broad enhancement - such as a plateau bounded by infrared and ultraviolet scales - produces a bimodal mass function, with a primary peak close to the infrared scale. We find that the typical initial gravitational potential (compaction function), conditioned on meeting the threshold for critical collapse, is generated by a thin spherical shell with infrared radius and a thickness comparable to the ultraviolet scale. This suggests a higher-than-expected abundance of PBH originating from Type II initial fluctuations. Our results significantly impact overproduction bounds on the amplitude of the power spectrum, and tighten the viable mass range for primordial black holes as dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07709v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacopo Fumagalli, Jaume Garriga, Cristiano Germani, Ravi K. Sheth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiprobe Cosmology from the Abundance of SPT Clusters and DES Galaxy Clustering and Weak Lensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07765v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cosmic shear, galaxy clustering, and the abundance of massive halos each probe the large-scale structure of the universe in complementary ways. We present cosmological constraints from the joint analysis of the three probes, building on the latest analyses of the lensing-informed abundance of clusters identified by the South Pole Telescope (SPT) and of the auto- and cross-correlation of galaxy position and weak lensing measurements (3$\times$2pt) in the Dark Energy Survey (DES). We consider the cosmological correlation between the different tracers and we account for the systematic uncertainties that are shared between the large-scale lensing correlation functions and the small-scale lensing-based cluster mass calibration. Marginalized over the remaining $\Lambda$CDM parameters (including the sum of neutrino masses) and 52 astrophysical modeling parameters, we measure $\Omega_\mathrm{m}=0.300\pm0.017$ and $\sigma_8=0.797\pm0.026$. Compared to constraints from Planck primary CMB anisotropies, our constraints are only 15% wider with a probability to exceed of 0.22 ($1.2\sigma$) for the two-parameter difference. We further obtain $S_8\equiv\sigma_8(\Omega_\mathrm{m}/0.3)^{0.5}=0.796\pm0.013$ which is lower than the Planck measurement at the $1.6\sigma$ level. The combined SPT cluster, DES 3$\times$2pt, and Planck datasets mildly prefer a non-zero positive neutrino mass, with a 95% upper limit $\sum m_\nu&lt;0.25~\mathrm{eV}$ on the sum of neutrino masses. Assuming a $w$CDM model, we constrain the dark energy equation of state parameter $w=-1.15^{+0.23}_{-0.17}$ and when combining with Planck primary CMB anisotropies, we recover $w=-1.20^{+0.15}_{-0.09}$, a $1.7\sigma$ difference with a cosmological constant. The precision of our results highlights the benefits of multiwavelength multiprobe cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07765v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Bocquet, S. Grandis, E. Krause, C. To, L. E. Bleem, M. Klein, J. J. Mohr, T. Schrabback, A. Alarcon, O. Alves, A. Amon, F. Andrade-Oliveira, E. J. Baxter, K. Bechtol, M. R. Becker, G. M. Bernstein, J. Blazek, H. Camacho, A. Campos, A. Carnero Rosell, M. Carrasco Kind, R. Cawthon, C. Chang, R. Chen, A. Choi, J. Cordero, M. Crocce, C. Davis, J. DeRose, H. T. Diehl, S. Dodelson, C. Doux, A. Drlica-Wagner, K. Eckert, T. F. Eifler, F. Elsner, J. Elvin-Poole, S. Everett, X. Fang, A. Fert\'e, P. Fosalba, O. Friedrich, J. Frieman, M. Gatti, G. Giannini, D. Gruen, R. A. Gruendl, I. Harrison, W. G. Hartley, K. Herner, H. Huang, E. M. Huff, D. Huterer, M. Jarvis, N. Kuropatkin, P. -F. Leget, P. Lemos, A. R. Liddle, N. MacCrann, J. McCullough, J. Muir, J. Myles, A. Navarro-Alsina, S. Pandey, Y. Park, A. Porredon, J. Prat, M. Raveri, R. P. Rollins, A. Roodman, R. Rosenfeld, E. S. Rykoff, C. S\'anchez, J. Sanchez, L. F. Secco, I. Sevilla-Noarbe, E. Sheldon, T. Shin, M. A. Troxel, I. Tutusaus, T. N. Varga, N. Weaverdyck, R. H. Wechsler, H. -Y. Wu, B. Yanny, B. Yin, Y. Zhang, J. Zuntz, T. M. C. Abbott, P. A. R. Ade, M. Aguena, S. Allam, S. W. Allen, A. J. Anderson, B. Ansarinejad, J. E. Austermann, M. Bayliss, J. A. Beall, A. N. Bender, B. A. Benson, F. Bianchini, M. Brodwin, D. Brooks, L. Bryant, D. L. Burke, R. E. A. Canning, J. E. Carlstrom, J. Carretero, F. J. Castander, C. L. Chang, P. Chaubal, H. C. Chiang, T-L. Chou, R. Citron, C. Corbett Moran, M. Costanzi, T. M. Crawford, A. T. Crites, L. N. da Costa, M. E. S. Pereira, T. M. Davis, T. de Haan, M. A. Dobbs, P. Doel, W. Everett, A. Farahi, B. Flaugher, A. M. Flores, B. Floyd, J. Gallicchio, E. Gaztanaga, E. M. George, M. D. Gladders, N. Gupta, G. Gutierrez, N. W. Halverson, S. R. Hinton, J. Hlavacek-Larrondo, G. P. Holder, D. L. Hollowood, W. L. Holzapfel, J. D. Hrubes, N. Huang, J. Hubmayr, K. D. Irwin, D. J. James, F. K\'eruzor\'e, G. Khullar, K. Kim, L. Knox, R. Kraft, K. Kuehn, O. Lahav, A. T. Lee, S. Lee, D. Li, C. Lidman, M. Lima, A. Lowitz, G. Mahler, A. Mantz, J. L. Marshall, M. McDonald, J. J. McMahon, J. Mena-Fern\'andez, S. S. Meyer, R. Miquel, J. Montgomery, T. Natoli, J. P. Nibarger, G. I. Noble, V. Novosad, R. L. C. Ogando, S. Padin, P. Paschos, S. Patil, A. A. Plazas Malag\'on, C. Pryke, C. L. Reichardt, J. Roberson, A. K. Romer, C. Romero, J. E. Ruhl, B. R. Saliwanchik, L. Salvati, S. Samuroff, E. Sanchez, B. Santiago, A. Sarkar, A. Saro, K. K. Schaffer, K. Sharon, C. Sievers, G. Smecher, M. Smith, T. Somboonpanyakul, M. Sommer, B. Stalder, A. A. Stark, J. Stephen, V. Strazzullo, E. Suchyta, M. E. C. Swanson, G. Tarle, D. Thomas, C. Tucker, D. L. Tucker, T. Veach, J. D. Vieira, A. von der Linden, G. Wang, N. Whitehorn, W. L. K. Wu, V. Yefremenko, M. Young, J. A. Zebrowski, H. Zohren, DES Collaboration, SPT Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observing of background electromagnetic radiation of the real sky through the throat of a wormhole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06872v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The numerical investigation conducted in this paper addresses the problem of CMB radiation imaging as seen through the throat of the Ellis-Bronnikov-Morris-Thorne wormhole. It is assumed that both throats of the wormhole are relatively close to our stellar neighborhood, so close that the view of the ambient background radiation by an observer at the other throat of the wormhole is virtually identical to that seen from the Solar System neighborhood. A map of the temperature distribution of the cosmic microwave background radiation observed through the mouth of the wormhole has been constructed as well as a view of the Milky Way through the mouth of the wormhole. The resultant image contains characteristic details that enable it to be distinguished from an image produced by a black hole.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06872v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail Bugaev, Igor Novikov, Serge Repin, Polina Samorodskaya, Igor Novikov jr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of the quantum vacuum at a cosmic scale and of dark energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06876v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Einstein equation in a semi-classical approximation is applied to a spherical region of the universe, with the stress-energy tensor consisting of the mass density and pressure of the LambdaCDM cosmological model plus an additional contribution of the quantum vacuum. Expanding the equation in powers of Newton constant G, the vacuum contributes to second order. The result is that at least a part of the acceleration in the expansion of the universe may be due to the quantum vacuum fluctuations</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06876v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/e26121042</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Entropy 2024, 26, 1042</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Emilio Santos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conditions for Super-Eddington Accretion onto the First Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06888v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Observations of supermassive black holes at high redshift challenge our understanding of the evolution of the first generation of black holes (BHs) in proto-galactic environments. One possibility is that they grow much more rapidly than current estimates of feedback and accretion efficiency permit. Following our previous analysis of super-Eddington accretion onto stellar-mass black holes in mini-haloes under no-feedback conditions, we now investigate whether this can be sustained when thermal feedback is included. We use four sets of cosmological simulations at sub-pc resolution with initial black hole masses varying from $1 \times 10^3 - 6 \times 10^4 M_\odot$, exploring a range of feedback efficiencies. We also vary the feedback injection radius to probe the threshold of numerical overcooling. We find that super-Eddington growth sustained on the order of $\sim$$100 \, \rm kyr$ is possible with very weak thermal feedback efficiency in all environments and moderate efficiency for the $6 \times 10^4 M_\odot$ BH. Trans-Eddington growth is possible for a $3 \times 10^3 - 6 \times 10^6 M_\odot$ BH at moderate feedback efficiencies. We discuss the effectiveness of thermal feedback in heating the gas, suppressing accretion, and driving outflows at these parameter configurations. Our results suggest that super-Eddington growth may be possible in the presence of thermal feedback for black holes formed from the first stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06888v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simone T. Gordon, Britton D. Smith, Sadegh Khochfar, Ricarda S. Beckmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial Black Holes (as Dark Matter) from the Supercooled Phase Transitions with Radiative Symmetry Breaking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06889v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study in detail the production of primordial black holes (PBHs), as well as their mass and initial spin, due to the phase transitions corresponding to radiative symmetry breaking (RSB) and featuring a large supercooling. The latter property allows us to use a model-independent approach. In this context, we demonstrate that the decay rate of the false vacuum grows exponentially with time to a high degree of accuracy, justifying a time dependence commonly assumed in the literature. Our study provides ready-to-use results for determining the abundance, mass and initial spin of PBHs generated in a generic RSB model with large supercooling. We find that PBHs are generically produced in a broad region of the model-independent parameter space. Notably, we identify the subregion that may explain recently observed microlensing anomalies. Additionally, we show that a simple Standard-Model extension, with right-handed neutrinos and gauged $B-L$ featuring RSB, may explain an anomaly of this sort in a region of its parameter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06889v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Indra Kumar Banerjee, Francesco Rescigno, Alberto Salvio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The MUSE Ultra Deep Field (VIII): A 5 Mpc stretch of the z $\approx$ 4 cosmic web revealed in emission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06895v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We detect Ly$\alpha$ emission from a ~5 Mpc-long (comoving) portion of the cosmic web hosting an overdensity ($\delta \approx 25$) of 19 Ly$\alpha$ emitters (LAEs) at $z\approx 4$ within the MUSE Ultra Deep Field (MUDF), reaching an average surface brightness (SB) of $5\times 10^{-20}~\rm{erg~s^{-1}~ cm^{-2}~arcsec^{-2}}$. This large-scale structure has an average SB similar to the filament across the two MUDF quasars at $z\approx 3.22$. However, deep multiwavelength data do not show a clear presence of active galactic nuclei, suggesting that the emission is mainly regulated by the underlying gas density. We find $\approx 0.2$ dex higher star formation compared to control samples and a remarkable predominance (5/7) of blue-peaked emission lines in the spectra of the embedded LAEs, indicative of favorable conditions for gas accretion. Lastly, we quantify the contribution of intragalactic gas to the Ly$\alpha$ SB profile at large distances from LAEs. By studying samples of filaments detected in emission within diverse environments, we are finally gaining new insight into the physics of gas accretion within the cosmic web.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06895v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davide Tornotti, Michele Fumagalli, Matteo Fossati, Fabrizio Arrigoni Battaia, Alejandro Benitez-Llambay, Pratika Dayal, Rajeshwari Dutta, Celine Peroux, Marc Rafelski, Mitchell Revalski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonrelativistic Proca stars: Spherical stationary and multi-frequency states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06901</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06901v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we follow an effective theory approach to study the nonrelativistic limit of a selfgravitating and selfinteracting massive vector field. Our effective theory is characterized by three parameters: the field's mass $m_0$ and the selfinteraction constants $\lambda_n$ and $\lambda_s$. For definiteness, we focus on a systematic study of the equilibrium configurations, commonly referred to as Proca stars when they have finite energy. We identify two different types of Proca stars, depending on the specific sector of the effective theory that we are exploring. In the generic sector, defined by $\lambda_s\neq 0$, all equilibrium configurations are stationary states described by wave functions that evolve harmonically in time. However, in the symmetry-enhanced sector, for which $\lambda_s=0$, there exist multi-frequency states whose wave functions oscillate with two or three distinct frequencies in addition to the stationary states. We determine the conditions under which a ground state configuration with fixed particle number exists. When these conditions are met, we prove that the lowest energy is reached by a stationary spherically symmetric configuration of constant polarization that is linear or circular depending on the sign of $\lambda_s$. We numerically construct some illustrative examples of spherical stationary and multi-frequency solutions, analyze their properties, and compare them with our analytical predictions. Unlike stationary states and other soliton configurations, which form a discrete set in the solution space associated with fixed particle number, the symmetry-enhanced sector exhibits a continuum of solutions with multi-frequency states connecting stationary states of constant polarization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06901v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emmanuel Ch\'avez Nambo, Alberto Diez-Tejedor, Edgar Preciado-Govea, Armando A. Roque, Olivier Sarbach</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time to Sparkler. Accurate ages of lensed globular clusters at $z=1.4$ with JWST photometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06903v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Determining reliable ages for old stellar objects at different redshifts offers a powerful means to constrain cosmology without relying on a specific cosmological model: this is known as the cosmic clocks method. Globular clusters (GCs), long recognised as hosts of the Universe's oldest stars, have served as the archetypical cosmic clocks. However, their age estimates have traditionally been confined to redshift z=0, limiting their role to constraining the present-day age of the Universe. Here we explore how to measure reliable ages of GCs well beyond $z=0$, leveraging their potential to extend cosmic clock measurements to earlier epochs. Specifically, we use 6-band JWST/NIRCam high-precision photometry of candidate stellar clusters in the Sparkler galaxy, located at redshift $z$=1.378 and strongly lensed by the galaxy cluster SMACS J0723.3-7327. By employing stellar population models within a Bayesian inference framework, we constrain the GCs' ages, star formation histories, metallicities, and dust attenuation. The five compact sources previously identified as GCs, based on their red spectral energy distributions being consistent with the colours of old stellar systems, yield a formation age of $1.9\pm0.4$ Gyr on average. This result implies a total age of the Universe that aligns well with the $\Lambda$CDM model derived from Planck18 data. Recent space-based observations have uncovered a wealth of lensed GCs as well as globulars within the member galaxies of the clusters themselves. These findings suggest that the pool of objects available for cosmic clock studies is enormous. A systematic multi-band photometric survey of GCs in and behind galaxy clusters, using facilities like Euclid and JWST, would therefore be a powerful tool for estimating cluster ages across a large range of redshifts, allowing the Universe to be dated across an unprecedented range of epochs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06903v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elena Tomasetti, Michele Moresco, Carmela Lardo, Fr\'ed\'eric Courbin, Raul Jimenez, Licia Verde, Martin Millon, Andrea Cimatti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Constraints on Lorentz Invariance Violation at High Redshifts from Multiband of GRBs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07625v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the gravity quantum theory, the quantization of spacetime may lead to the modification of the dispersion relation between the energy and the momentum and the Lorentz invariance violation (LIV). High energy and long-distance gamma-ray bursts (GRBs) observations in the universe provide a unique opportunity to test the possibility of LIV. In this paper, by using 93 time delay GRBs covering the redshift range of $0.117 &lt; z &lt; 6.29$, we present a new idea of using cosmological model-independent (based on the luminosity distance data from 174 GRBs) to test the LIV. Combining the observation data from multiband of GRBs provides us with an opportunity to mitigate the potential systematic errors arising from variations in the physical characteristics among diverse object populations, and to add a higher redshift dataset for testing the energy-dependent velocity caused by the corrected dispersion relationship of photons. These robust limits of the energy scale for the linear and quadratic LIV effects are $E_{QG,1} \ge 1.40\times 10^{15}$ GeV, and $E_{QG,2} \ge 8.18\times 10^{9}$ GeV, respectively. It exhibits a significantly reduced value compared to the energy scale of Planck in both scenarios of linear and quadratic LIV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07625v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingyue Chen, Yu Pan, Tonghua Liu, Shuo Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalar-induced gravitational wave from domain wall perturbation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07677v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Domain walls represent two-dimensional topological defects that emerge from the spontaneous breaking of discrete symmetries in various new physics models. In this study, we undertake the first calculation of gravitational waves produced by scalar perturbations generated from the domain wall network. Our findings indicate that the gravitational wave spectrum is notably distinct from that of other sources. This opens up a promising avenue for future gravitational wave experiments aimed at exploring the role of domain walls in the early Universe. Our results could significantly enhance the capabilities of gravitational wave experiments, serving as a valuable method for testing new physics and better identifying diverse sources of gravitational waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07677v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bo-Qiang Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Wave Emission from a Cosmic String Loop, I: Global Case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.08456</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.08456v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the simultaneous decay of global string loops into scalar particles (massless and massive modes) and gravitational waves (GWs). Using field theory simulations in flat space-time of isolated loops with initial length $\sim 80-1700$ times their core width, we determine the power emitted into scalar particles, $P_{\varphi}$, and GWs, $P_{\rm GW}$, and characterize the loop decay timescale as a function of its initial length, energy and angular momentum. We quantify infrared and ultraviolet lattice dependencies of our results. For all type of loops and initial conditions considered, GW emission is always suppressed compared to particles as $P_{\rm GW}/P_{\varphi} \approx \mathcal{O}(10)(v/m_\text{p})^2\ll 1$, where $v$ is the vacuum expectation value associated with string formation. These conclusions are robust for the length-to-width ratios considered, with no indication they should change if the ratio is increased. The results suggest that the GW background from a global string network, such as in dark matter axion scenarios, will be suppressed compared to previous expectations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.08456v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.043522</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 110 (2024) 4, 043522</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jorge Baeza-Ballesteros, Edmund J. Copeland, Daniel G. Figueroa, Joanes Lizarraga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Model for the Redshift-Space Galaxy 4-Point Correlation Function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.15510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.15510v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The field of cosmology is entering an epoch of unparalleled wealth of observational data thanks to galaxy surveys such as DESI, Euclid, and Roman. Therefore, it is essential to have a firm theoretical basis that allows the effective analysis of the data. With this purpose, we compute the nonlinear, gravitationally-induced connected galaxy 4-point correlation function (4PCF) at the tree level in Standard Perturbation Theory (SPT), including redshift-space distortions (RSD). We begin from the trispectrum and take its inverse Fourier transform into configuration space, exploiting the isotropic basis functions of Cahn &amp; Slepian (2023). We ultimately reduce the configuration-space expression to low-dimensional radial integrals of the power spectrum. This model will enable the use of the BAO feature in the connected 4PCF to sharpen our constraints on the expansion history of the Universe. It will also offer an additional avenue for determining the galaxy bias parameters, and thus tighten our cosmological constraints by breaking degeneracies. Survey geometry can be corrected in the 4PCF, and many systematics are localized, which is an advantage over data analysis with the trispectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.15510v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William Ortol\'a Leonard, Zachary Slepian, Jiamin Hou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring the baryon fraction using galaxy clustering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19236</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19236v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The amplitude of the baryon signature in galaxy clustering depends on the cosmological baryon fraction. We consider two ways to isolate this signal in galaxy redshift surveys. First, we extend standard template-based Baryon Acoustic Oscillation (BAO) models to include the amplitude of the baryonic signature by splitting the transfer function into baryon and cold dark matter components with freely varying proportions. Second, we include the amplitude of the split as an extra parameter in Effective Field Theory of Large Scale Structure (EFT) models of the full galaxy clustering signal. We find similar results from both approaches. For the Baryon Oscillation Spectroscopic Survey (BOSS) data we find $f_b\equiv\Omega_b/\Omega_m=0.173\pm0.027$ for template fits post-reconstruction, $f_b=0.153\pm0.029$ for template fits pre-reconstruction, and $f_b=0.154\pm0.022$ for EFT fits, with an estimated systematic error of 0.013 for all three methods. Using reconstruction only produces a marginal improvement for these measurements. Although significantly weaker than constraints on $f_b$ from the Cosmic Microwave Background, these measurements rely on very simple physics and, in particular, are independent of the sound horizon. In a companion paper we show how they can be used, together with Big Bang Nucleosynthesis measurements of the physical baryon density and geometrical measurements of the matter density from the Alcock-Paczynski effect, to constrain the Hubble parameter. While the constraints on $H_0$ based on density measurements from BOSS are relatively weak, measurements from DESI and Euclid will lead to errors on $H_0$ that are competitive with those from local distance ladder measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19236v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Krolewski, Will J. Percival</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological parameters from the joint analysis of Density Split and Second Order Statistics: an Emulator based on the Halo Occupation Distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05098</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05098v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we develop a simulation-based model to predict the density split (DSS) and second-order shear and clustering statistics. A simulation-based model has the potential to model highly non-linear scales where current DSS models fail. To build this model, we use the $\texttt{AbacusSummit}$ N-body simulation suite from which we measure all necessary statistics and train an emulator based on $\texttt{CosmoPower}$. In that context, we discuss possible improvements for future emulators to make the measurement less noisy and biased, resulting in more accurate and precise model predictions.
  Regarding the emulator's accuracy, we find that the most important aspect is the average of the summary statistics over multiple-shot noise realizations of the foreground galaxies. However, these results probably depend on the chosen number density of the foreground galaxies. Regarding the parameter forecast based on preliminary LOWZxUNIONS data, we find that DSS has more constraining power to derive cosmological parameters and that the joint analysis with second-order statistics is particularly useful for extracting parameters of the galaxy-halo connection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05098v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.083517</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev.D 110, 083517 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pierre A. Burger, Enrique Paillas, Michael J. Hudson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutrino mass bounds from DESI 2024 are relaxed by Planck PR4 and cosmological supernovae</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14554v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The recent DESI 2024 Baryon Acoustic Oscillations (BAO) measurements combined with the CMB data from the Planck 18 PR3 dataset and the Planck PR4+ACT DR6 lensing data, with a prior on the sum of the neutrino masses $\sum m_\nu&gt;0$, leads to a strong constraint, $\sum m_\nu&lt;0.072$ eV, which would exclude the inverted neutrino hierarchy and put some tension on even the standard hierarchy. We show that actually this bound gets significantly relaxed when combining the new DESI measurements with the HiLLiPoP+LoLLiPoP likelihoods, based on the Planck 2020 PR4 dataset, and with supernovae datasets. We note that the fact that neutrino masses are pushed towards zero, and even towards negative values, is known to be correlated with the so-called $A_L$ tension, a mismatch between lensing and power spectrum measurements in the Planck PR3 data, which is reduced by HiLLiPoP+LoLLiPoP to less than 1$\sigma$. We find $\sum m_\nu&lt;0.1$ eV and $\sum m_\nu&lt;0.12$ eV, with the supernovae Pantheon+ and DES-SN5YR datasets respectively. The shift caused by these datasets is more compatible with the expectations from neutrino oscillation experiments, and both the normal and inverted hierarchy scenarios remain now viable, even with the $\sum m_\nu&gt;0$ prior. Finally, we analyze neutrino mass bounds in an extension of $\Lambda$CDM that addresses the $H_0$ tension, with extra fluid Dark Radiation, finding that in such models bounds are further relaxed and the posterior probability for $\sum m_\nu$ begins to exhibit a peak at positive values.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14554v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Itamar J. Allali, Alessio Notari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-definition imaging of a filamentary connection between a close quasar pair at z=3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17035v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Filaments connecting halos are a long-standing prediction of cold dark matter theories. We present a detection of the cosmic web emission connecting two quasar-host galaxies at redshift z ~3.22 in the MUSE Ultra Deep Field (MUDF). The very deep observations unlock a high-definition view of the filament morphology, a measure of the transition radius between the intergalactic and circumgalactic medium, and the characterization of the surface brightness profiles along the filament and in the transverse direction. Through systematic comparisons with simulations, we validate the filaments' typical density predicted in the current cold dark-matter model. Our analysis of the MUDF field, an excellent laboratory for quantitatively studying filaments in emission, opens a new avenue to constrain the physical properties of the cosmic web and to trace the distribution of dark matter on large scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17035v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davide Tornotti, Michele Fumagalli, Matteo Fossati, Alejandro Benitez-Llambay, David Izquierdo-Villalba, Andrea Travascio, Fabrizio Arrigoni Battaia, Sebastiano Cantalupo, Alexander Beckett, Silvia Bonoli, Pratika Dayal, Valentina D'Odorico, Rajeshwari Dutta, Elisabeta Lusso, Celine Peroux, Marc Rafelski, Mitchell Revalski, Daniele Spinoso, Mark Swinbank</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the horizon: Quantifying the full sky foreground wedge in the cylindrical power spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10686</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10686v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: One of the main obstacles preventing the detection of the redshifted 21-cm signal from neutral hydrogen in the early Universe is the astrophysical foreground emission, which is several orders of magnitude brighter than the signal. The foregrounds, due to their smooth spectra, are expected to predominantly occupy a region in the cylindrical power spectrum known as the foreground wedge. However, the conventional equations describing the extent of the foreground wedge are derived under a flat-sky approximation. This assumption breaks down for tracking wide-field instruments, thus rendering these equations inapplicable in these situations. In this paper, we derive equations for the full sky foreground wedge and show that the foregrounds can potentially extend far beyond what the conventional equations suggest. We also derive the equations that describe a specific bright source in the cylindrical power spectrum space. The validity of both sets of equations is tested against numerical simulations. Many current and upcoming interferometers (e.g., LOFAR, NenuFAR, MWA, SKA) are wide-field phase-tracking instruments. These equations give us new insights into the nature of foreground contamination in the cylindrical power spectra estimated using wide-field instruments. Additionally, they allow us to accurately associate features in the power spectrum to foregrounds or instrumental effects. The equations are also important for correctly selecting the "EoR window" for foreground avoidance analyses, and for planning 21-cm observations. In future analyses, it is recommended to use these updated horizon lines to indicate the foreground wedge in the cylindrical power spectrum accurately. The new equations for generating the updated wedge lines are made available in a Python library, pslines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10686v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Munshi, F. G. Mertens, L. V. E. Koopmans, A. R. Offringa, E. Ceccotti, S. A. Brackenhoff, J. K. Chege, B. K. Gehlot, S. Ghosh, C. H\"ofer, M. Mevius</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconstructing the Inflaton Potential: Primordial Black Holes and Gravitational Waves in Slow Roll and Ultra Slow Roll Single Field Inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12587</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12587v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present new single field inflationary scenarios that produce the critical abundance of primordial black holes as dark matter reconstructing the inflaton potential from an input power spectrum. The method is exact in the slow roll approximation but remains effective even when the slow roll conditions are temporarily violated such as in ultra slow roll models. With this method we construct new ultra slow roll scenarios and also models that reproduce the DM abundance within the slow roll regime. As a second application we consider a scalar power spectrum that generates a secondary gravitational wave background compatible with the one recently observed in Pulsar Timing Arrays experiments. These scenarios could be tested by future observations of $\mu-$distortions of the CMB.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12587v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriele Autieri, Michele Redi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Map-level baryonification: Efficient modelling of higher-order correlations in the weak lensing and thermal Sunyaev-Zeldovich fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.03822</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.03822v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Semi-analytic methods can generate baryon-corrected fields from N-body simulations (``baryonification'') and are rapidly becoming a ubiquitous tool in modeling structure formation on non-linear scales. We extend this formalism to consistently model the weak lensing and thermal Sunyaev-Zeldovich (tSZ) fields directly on the full-sky, with an emphasis on higher-order correlations. We use the auto- and cross- $N$th-order moments, with $N \in \{2, 3, 4\}$, as a summary statistic of the lensing and tSZ fields, and show that our model can jointly fit these statistics measured in IllustrisTNG to within measurement uncertainties, for scales above $\gtrsim 1 {\rm Mpc}$ and across multiple redshifts. The model predictions change only minimally when including additional information from secondary halo properties, such as halo concentration and ellipticity. Each individual moment is dependent on halos of different mass ranges and has different sensitivities to the model parameters. A simulation-based forecast on the ULAGAM simulation suite shows that the combination of all moments, measured from current and upcoming lensing and tSZ surveys, can jointly constrain cosmology and baryons to high precision. The lensing and tSZ field are sensitive to different combinations of the baryonification parameters, with degeneracy directions that are often orthogonal, and the combination of the two fields leads to significantly better constraints on both cosmology and astrophysics. Our pipeline for map-level baryonification is publicly available at https://github.com/DhayaaAnbajagane/BaryonForge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.03822v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.33232/001c.126788</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Dhayaa Anbajagane, Shivam Pandey, Chihway Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deciphering the spectral properties of the atypical radio relic in A115 using uGMRT, VLA, and LOFAR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07574v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The mega-parsec scale radio relics at the galaxy cluster periphery are intriguing structures. While textbook examples of relics posit arc-like elongated structures at the clusters' peripheries, several relics display more complex structures deviating from the conventional type. Abell 115 is a galaxy cluster, hosting an atypical radio relic at its northern periphery. Despite the multi-wavelength study of the cluster over the last decades, the origin of the radio relic is still unclear. In this paper, we present a multi-frequency radio study of the cluster to infer the possible mechanism behind the formation of the radio relic. We used new 400 MHz observations with the uGMRT, along with archival VLA 1.5 GHz observations and archival LOFAR 144 MHz observations. Our analysis supports the previous theory on the relic's origin from the passage of a shock front due to an off-axis merger, where the old population of particles from the radio galaxies at the relic location has been re-energised to illuminate the 2 Mpc radio relic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07574v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s12036-024-10026-8</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Swarna Chatterjee, Abhirup Datta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Redshift Distribution Inference through Joint Self-Calibration and Clustering-Redshift Synergy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12009v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Accurately characterizing the true redshift (true-$z$) distribution of a photometric redshift (photo-$z$) sample is critical for cosmological analyses in imaging surveys. Clustering-based techniques, which include clustering-redshift (CZ) and self-calibration (SC) methods--depending on whether external spectroscopic data are used--offer powerful tools for this purpose. In this study, we explore the joint inference of the true-$z$ distribution by combining SC and CZ (denoted as SC+CZ). We derive simple multiplicative update rules to perform the joint inference. By incorporating appropriate error weighting and an additional weighting function, our method shows significant improvement over previous algorithms. We validate our approach using a DES Y3 mock catalog. The true-$z$ distribution estimated through the combined SC+CZ method is generally more accurate than using SC or CZ alone. To account for the different constraining powers of these methods, we assign distinct weights to the SC and CZ contributions. The optimal weights, which minimize the distribution error, depend on the relative constraining strength of the SC and CZ data. Specifically, for a spectroscopic redshift sample that amounts to 1% of the photo-$z$ sample, the optimal combination reduces the total error by 20% (40%) compared to using CZ (SC) alone, and it keeps the bias in mean redshift [$\Delta \bar{z} / (1 + z) $] at the level of 0.3%. Furthermore, when CZ data is only available in the low-$z$ range and the high-$z$ range relies solely on SC data, SC+CZ enables consistent estimation of the true-$z$ distribution across the entire redshift range. Our findings demonstrate that SC+CZ is an effective tool for constraining the true-$z$ distribution, paving the way for clustering-based methods to be applied at $z\gtrsim 1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12009v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weilun Zheng, Kwan Chuen Chan, Haojie Xu, Le Zhang, Ruiyu Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DESI 2024 V: Full-Shape Galaxy Clustering from Galaxies and Quasars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12021</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12021v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the measurements and cosmological implications of the galaxy two-point clustering using over 4.7 million unique galaxy and quasar redshifts in the range $0.1&lt;z&lt;2.1$ divided into six redshift bins over a $\sim 7,500$ square degree footprint, from the first year of observations with the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI Data Release 1). By fitting the full power spectrum, we extend previous DESI DR1 baryon acoustic oscillation (BAO) measurements to include redshift-space distortions and signals from the matter-radiation equality scale. For the first time, this Full-Shape analysis is blinded at the catalogue-level to avoid confirmation bias and the systematic errors are accounted for at the two-point clustering level, which automatically propagates them into any cosmological parameter. When analysing the data in terms of compressed model-agnostic variables, we obtain a combined precision of 4.7\% on the amplitude of the redshift space distortion signal reaching similar precision with just one year of DESI data than with 20 years of observation from previous generation surveys. We analyse the data to directly constrain the cosmological parameters within the $\Lambda$CDM model using perturbation theory and combine this information with the reconstructed DESI DR1 galaxy BAO. Using a Big Bang Nucleosynthesis Gaussian prior on the baryon density parameter, and a Gaussian prior on the spectral index, we constrain the matter density is $\Omega_m=0.296\pm 0.010 $ and the Hubble constant $H_0=(68.63 \pm 0.79)[{\rm km\, s^{-1}Mpc^{-1}}]$. Additionally, we measure the amplitude of clustering $\sigma_8=0.841 \pm 0.034$. The DESI DR1 results are in agreement with the $\Lambda$CDM model based on general relativity with parameters consistent with those from Planck. The cosmological interpretation of these results in combination with external datasets are presented in a companion paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12021v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> DESI Collaboration, A. G. Adame, J. Aguilar, S. Ahlen, S. Alam, D. M. Alexander, M. Alvarez, O. Alves, A. Anand, U. Andrade, E. Armengaud, S. Avila, A. Aviles, H. Awan, S. Bailey, C. Baltay, A. Bault, J. Behera, S. BenZvi, F. Beutler, D. Bianchi, C. Blake, R. Blum, S. Brieden, A. Brodzeller, D. Brooks, E. Buckley-Geer, E. Burtin, R. Calderon, R. Canning, A. Carnero Rosell, R. Cereskaite, J. L. Cervantes-Cota, S. Chabanier, E. Chaussidon, J. Chaves-Montero, S. Chen, X. Chen, T. Claybaugh, S. Cole, A. Cuceu, T. M. Davis, K. Dawson, A. de la Macorra, A. de Mattia, N. Deiosso, A. Dey, B. Dey, Z. Ding, P. Doel, J. Edelstein, S. Eftekharzadeh, D. J. Eisenstein, A. Elliott, P. Fagrelius, K. Fanning, S. Ferraro, J. Ereza, N. Findlay, B. Flaugher, A. Font-Ribera, D. Forero-S\'anchez, J. E. Forero-Romero, C. Garcia-Quintero, L. H. Garrison, E. Gazta\~naga, H. Gil-Mar\'in, S. Gontcho A Gontcho, A. X. Gonzalez-Morales, V. Gonzalez-Perez, C. Gordon, D. Green, D. Gruen, R. Gsponer, G. Gutierrez, J. Guy, B. Hadzhiyska, C. Hahn, M. M. S Hanif, H. K. Herrera-Alcantar, K. Honscheid, C. Howlett, D. Huterer, V. Ir\v{s}i\v{c}, M. Ishak, S. Juneau, N. G. Kara\c{c}ayl{\i}, R. Kehoe, S. Kent, D. Kirkby, H. Kong, S. E. Koposov, A. Kremin, A. Krolewski, Y. Lai, T. -W. Lan, M. Landriau, D. Lang, J. Lasker, J. M. Le Goff, L. Le Guillou, A. Leauthaud, M. E. Levi, T. S. Li, K. Lodha, C. Magneville, M. Manera, D. Margala, P. Martini, M. Maus, P. McDonald, L. Medina-Varela, A. Meisner, J. Mena-Fern\'andez, R. Miquel, J. Moon, S. Moore, J. Moustakas, E. Mueller, A. Mu\~noz-Guti\'errez, A. D. Myers, S. Nadathur, L. Napolitano, R. Neveux, J. A. Newman, N. M. Nguyen, J. Nie, G. Niz, H. E. Noriega, N. Padmanabhan, E. Paillas, N. Palanque-Delabrouille, J. Pan, S. Penmetsa, W. J. Percival, M. M. Pieri, M. Pinon, C. Poppett, A. Porredon, F. Prada, A. P\'erez-Fern\'andez, I. P\'erez-R\`afols, D. Rabinowitz, A. Raichoor, C. Ram\'irez-P\'erez, S. Ramirez-Solano, M. Rashkovetskyi, C. Ravoux, M. Rezaie, J. Rich, A. Rocher, C. Rockosi, F. Rodr\'iguez-Mart\'inez, N. A. Roe, A. Rosado-Marin, A. J. Ross, G. Rossi, R. Ruggeri, V. Ruhlmann-Kleider, L. Samushia, E. Sanchez, C. Saulder, E. F. Schlafly, D. Schlegel, M. Schubnell, H. Seo, R. Sharples, J. Silber, A. Slosar, A. Smith, D. Sprayberry, T. Tan, G. Tarl\'e, S. Trusov, R. Vaisakh, D. Valcin, F. Valdes, M. Vargas-Maga\~na, L. Verde, M. Walther, B. Wang, M. S. Wang, B. A. Weaver, N. Weaverdyck, R. H. Wechsler, D. H. Weinberg, M. White, M. J. Wilson, J. Yu, Y. Yu, S. Yuan, C. Y\`eche, E. A. Zaborowski, P. Zarrouk, H. Zhang, C. Zhao, R. Zhao, R. Zhou, H. Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectra of magnetic fields from electroweak symmetry breaking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.00641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.00641v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We characterize magnetic fields produced during electroweak symmetry breaking by non-dynamical numerical simulations based on the Kibble mechanism. The generated magnetic fields were thought to have an energy spectrum $\propto k^3$ for small wavenumbers $k$, but here we show that it is actually a spectrum $\propto k^4$ along with characteristic fluctuations in the magnetic helicity. Using scaling results from MHD simulations for the evolution and assuming that the initial magnetic field is coherent on the electroweak Hubble scale, we estimate the magnetic field strength to be $\sim 10^{-13}\, {\rm G}$ on kpc scales at the present epoch for non-helical fields. For maximally helical fields we obtain $\sim 10^{-10}\, {\rm G}$ on Mpc scales. We also give scalings of these estimates for partially helical fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.00641v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tanmay Vachaspati, Axel Brandenburg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can decaying vacuum solve the H_0 Tension?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06756v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the present work we analyze two different models of interaction between dark energy and dark matter, also known as vacuum decay models or $\Lambda(t)$CDM models. In both models, when the $H_0$ parameter is constrained by the Planck distance priors, its value is compatible with a higher value of $H_0$, in agreement with SH0ES data, while simultaneously reducing the values of $\Omega_m$ and $\Omega_b$. In both models, we find $H_0=73.1\pm0.86$ at 68\% c.l. by combining Planck+SH0ES data. We also find the decay parameter to be $\varepsilon=0.0197^{+0.0032}_{-0.0027}$ for one model and $\varepsilon=0.0203\pm0.0034$ for the other one. From these analyses, a noninteracting model is excluded at least at $6\sigma$ c.l.! This shows that these types of models are promising in solving or at least alleviating the $H_0$ tension problem. Our analysis also shows a preference for the decay of vacuum into dark matter, in agreement to thermodynamic analyses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06756v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. S. Brito, J. F. Jesus, A. A. Escobal, S. H. Pereira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving the detection sensitivity to primordial stochastic gravitational waves with reduced astrophysical foregrounds -- II: subthreshold binary neutron stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01846</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01846v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Stochastic gravitational waves (GWs) consist of a primordial component from early Universe processes and an astrophysical component from compact binary mergers. To detect the primordial stochastic GW background (SGWB), the astrophysical foregrounds must be reduced to high precision, which is achievable for third-generation (3G) ground based GW detectors. Previous studies have shown that the foreground from individually detectable merger events can be reduced with fractional residual energy density below $10^{-3}$, and the residual foreground from subthreshold binary neutron stars (BNSs) will be the bottleneck if not be well cleaned. In this work, we propose that the foreground energy density of subthreshold BNSs $\Omega_{\rm sub}$ can be estimated via a population based approach from the individually detectable BNSs utilizing the isotropic orbital orientations of all BNSs, i.e., uniform distribution in $\cos\iota$, where $\iota$ is the BNS inclination angle with respect to the line of sight. Using this approach, we find $\Omega_{\rm sub}$ can be measured with percent-level uncertainty, assuming $O(10^5)$ individually detected BNSs in our simulations. This method represents a promising approach to tackling the foreground cleaning problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01846v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingzheng Li, Jiming Yu, Zhen Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Falsifying Anthropics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02993</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02993v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose using fuzzy axion dark matter to test the anthropic principle. A very light axion can be directly detectable, at least by black hole superradiance effects. The idea then is that gravitational and astrophysical observations can discover a light axion in the regime where it must be all of dark matter with abundance which must be set up by the anthropic principle, due to excessive primordial misalignment induced by inflation-induced Brownian drift of fluctuations. Yet it may turn out that dark matter is something else instead of this axion. Since the de Sitter-induced axion misalignment controlled only by the de Sitter curvature cannot be evaded, this would invalidate the anthropic prediction of the dark matter abundance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02993v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nemanja Kaloper, Alexander Westphal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyenas: X-ray Bubbles and Cavities in the Intra-Group Medium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14415v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the role of the Simba feedback model on the structure of the Intra-Group Medium (IGrM) in the new Hyenas suite of cutting-edge cosmological zoom-in simulations. Using 34 high-resolution zooms of halos spanning from $10^{13}-10^{14}$ $M_\odot$ at $z=0.286$, we follow halos for 700 Myr, over several major active galactic nuclei (AGN) jet feedback events. We use the MOXHA package to generate mock Chandra X-ray observations, as well as predictive mocks for the upcoming LEM mission, identifying many feedback-generated features such as cavities, shock-fronts, and hot-spots, closely mimicking real observations. Our sample comprises $105$ snapshots with identified cavities, $50$ with single bubbles and $55$ with two, and spans three orders of magnitude in observed cavity enthalpies, from $10^{41}-10^{44}$ erg/s. Comparing semi-major axis length, midpoint radius, and eccentricity to a matched sample of observations, we find good agreement in cavity dimensions with real catalogues. We estimate cavity power from our mock maps following observational procedures, showing that this is typically more than enough to offset halo cooling, particularly in low-mass halos, where we match the observed excess in energy relative to cooling. Bubble enthalpy as measured with the usual midpoint pressure typically exceeds the energy released by the most recent jet event, hinting that the mechanical work is done predominantly at a lower pressure against the IGrM. We demonstrate for the first time that X-ray cavities are observable in a modern large-scale simulation suite and discuss the use of realistic cavity mock observations as new halo-scale constraints on feedback models in cosmological simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14415v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae2592</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, Volume 536, Issue 1, January 2025, Pages 145 to 165</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fred J. Jennings, Arif Babul, Romeel Dave, Weiguang Cui, Douglas Rennehan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalar Dark Matter Production through the Bubble Expansion Mechanism:The Role of the Lorentz factor and Non-Renormalizable Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14592v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a Bubble Expansion mechanism for the production of scalar dark matter during a first-order phase transition in the very early Universe. Seeking for a dark matter energy density in agreement with observations, we study different renormalizable and non-renormalizable interactions between the dark matter species and the field undergoing the transition, considering all possible regimes for the Lorentz boost factor associated with the motion of the bubble wall. By employing a combination of analytical and numerical techniques, we demonstrate that sufficient dark matter production is achievable even in the previously unexplored low-velocity bubble expansion regime, enlarging the parameter space and possibilities of the scenario. Notably, for the non-renormalizable interactions it is found that the produced dark matter abundances exhibit a similar qualitative behavior to the renormalizable case, even for low Lorentz boost factors. Furthermore, for a transition around the electroweak scale, the associated gravitational wave spectrum is within the reach of future detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14592v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose A. R. Cembranos, Jes\'us Luque, Javier Rubio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A novel probe of graviton dispersion relations at nano-Hertz frequencies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10122v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We generalise Phinney's 'practical theorem' to account for modified graviton dispersion relations motivated by certain cosmological scenarios. Focusing on specific examples, we show how such modifications can induce characteristic localised distortions, bumps, in the frequency profile of the stochastic gravitational wave background emitted from distant binary sources. We concentrate on gravitational waves at nano-Hertz frequencies probed by pulsar timing arrays, and we forecast the capabilities of future experiments to accurately probe parameters controlling modified dispersion relations. Our predictions are based on properties of gravitational waves emitted in the first inspiral phase of the binary process, and do not rely on assumptions of non-linear effects occurring during the binary merging phase</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10122v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.124018</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Bill Atkins, Ameek Malhotra, Gianmassimo Tasinato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cutting rule for in-in correlators and cosmological collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07521v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We derive a cutting rule for equal-time in-in correlators including cosmological correlators based on Keldysh $r/a$ basis, which decomposes diagrams into fully retarded functions and cut-propagators consisting of Wightman functions. Our derivation relies only on basic assumptions such as unitarity, locality, and the causal structure of the in-in formalism, and therefore holds for theories with arbitrary particle contents and local interactions at any loop order. As an application, we show that non-local cosmological collider signals arise solely from cut-propagators under the assumption of microcausality. Since the cut-propagators do not contain (anti-)time-ordering theta functions, the conformal time integrals are factorized, simplifying practical calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07521v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yohei Ema, Kyohei Mukaida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact Solution to Standard Model Hydrodynamic Cosmological Perturbation Theory and its Implications for Acoustic Oscillations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.11735v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present an exact solution to standard model cosmological perturbation theory in a matter-dominated, adiabatic, hydrodynamic era. The solution is in the form of hypergeometric functions. While such functions can oscillate with the sound velocity, they can only do so at high frequency. There is thus a maximum wavelength to these oscillations, with this maximum wavelength serving to provide a horizon for acoustic oscillations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.11735v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philip D. Mannheim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hitting the slopes: A spectroscopic view of UV continuum slopes of galaxies reveals a reddening at z &gt; 9.5</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14532v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The UV continuum slope of galaxies, $\beta$, is a powerful diagnostic. Understanding the redshift evolution of $\beta$ and its dependence on key galaxy properties can shed light on the evolution of galaxy physical properties over cosmic time. In this study, we present $\beta$ measurements for 295 spectroscopically confirmed galaxies at $5.5&lt;z&lt;14.3$ selected primarily from JADES, where $\beta$ has been measured from high quality JWST NIRSpec/PRISM spectra. We find a median $\beta=-2.3$ across our full sample, and find mild increase in blueness of $\beta$ with increasing redshift and fainter UV magnitudes. Interestingly, we find evidence for the average $\beta$ at $z &gt; 9.5$ to begin to redden, deviating from the trend observed at $z &lt; 9.5$. By producing stacked spectra in bins of redshift and $\beta$, we derive trends between $\beta$ and dust attenuation, metallicity, ionization parameter, and stellar age indicators directly from spectra, finding a lack of dust attenuation to be the dominant driver of bluer $\beta$ values. We further report six galaxies with $\beta&lt;-3.0$, which show a range of spectroscopic properties and signs of significant LyC photon leakage. Finally, we show that the redder $\beta$ values at $z &gt; 9.5$ may require rapid build-up of dust reservoirs in the very early Universe or a significant contribution from the nebular continuum emission to the observed UV spectra, with the nebular continuum fraction depending on the gas temperatures and densities. Our modeling shows that in the absence of dust, nebular emission at $T &gt; 15,000$ K can reproduce the range of $\beta$ that we see in our sample. Higher gas temperatures driven by hot, massive stars can boost the fraction of nebular continuum emission, potentially explaining the observed $\beta$ values as well as bright UV magnitudes seen across galaxies at $z &gt; 10$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14532v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aayush Saxena, Alex J. Cameron, Harley Katz, Andrew J. Bunker, Jacopo Chevallard, Francesco D'Eugenio, Santiago Arribas, Rachana Bhatawdekar, Kristan Boyett, Phillip A. Cargile, Stefano Carniani, Stephane Charlot, Mirko Curti, Emma Curtis-Lake, Kevin Hainline, Zhiyuan Ji, Benjamin D. Johnson, Gareth C. Jones, Nimisha Kumari, Isaac Laseter, Michael V. Maseda, Brant Robertson, Charlotte Simmonds, Sandro Tacchella, Hannah Ubler, Christina C. Williams, Chris Willott, Joris Witstok, Yongda Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revise the Dark Matter-Phantom Scalar Field Interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06501v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The cosmological history and evolution are examined for gravitational models with interaction in the dark sector of the universe. In particular, we consider the dark energy to be described by a phantom scalar field and the dark matter $\rho _{m}$ as a pressureless ideal gas. We introduce the interacting function $Q=\beta \left( t\right) \rho_{m}$, where the function $% \beta \left( t\right) $ is considered to be proportional to $\dot{\phi}, \dot{\phi}^{2}H^{-1},~H$, or a constant parameter with dimensions of $\left[H_{0}\right] $. For the four interacting models, we study in details the phase space by calculating the stationary points. The latter are applied to reconstruct the cosmological evolution. Compactified variables are essential to understand the complete picture of the phase space and to conclude about the cosmological viability of these interacting models. The detailed analysis is performed for the exponential potential $V\left( \phi \right) =V_{0}e^{\lambda \phi }$. The effects of other scalar field potential functions on the cosmological dynamics are examined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06501v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andronikos Paliathanasis, Amlan Halder, Genly Leon</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
