<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO</link>
    <description>astro-ph.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 01:55:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling gravitational wave sources in the MillenniumTNG simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06311v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: (Edited) We introduce a flexible framework for building gravitational wave (GW) event catalogs in hydrodynamic simulations of galaxy formation. Our framework couples the state-of-the-art binary population synthesis code SEVN with Arepo-GW -- a module fully integrated into the moving-mesh code Arepo -- to assign merger events of binary compact objects to stellar particles in simulations by stochastically sampling merger tables generated with SEVN. Arepo-GW supports both on-the-fly operation, producing event catalogs during simulations, and post-processing, using snapshots from existing runs. The algorithm is fully parallel and can be readily adapted to outputs from other simulation codes. To demonstrate the capabilities of our new framework, we applied Arepo-GW in post-processing to simulations from the MillenniumTNG suite, including its flagship box. We investigate key properties of the resulting GW event catalog, built on SEVN predictions, focusing on comoving merger rates, formation efficiencies, delay-time distributions, and progenitor mass and metallicity distributions. We also examine how these properties vary with simulated volume. We find that GW progenitor rates closely track simulated star formation histories and are generally consistent with current observational constraints at low redshift, aside from a factor of $\sim 4.5$ excess in binary black hole mergers. Moreover, our binary black hole merger rates decline more slowly with redshift than current observational estimates for $z \lesssim 1$. Finally, the analysis of progenitor mass functions across different formation channels reveals only mild redshift evolution, while the binary black hole mass function displays features compatible with current observational determinations. These findings highlight the potential of our novel framework to enable detailed predictions for upcoming GW surveys within a full cosmological context.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06311v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico Marinacci, Marco Baldi, Giuliano Iorio, M. Celeste Artale, Michela Mapelli, Volker Springel, Sownak Bose, Lars Hernquist</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial Black Holes and their Mass Spectra: The Effects of Mergers and Accretion within Stasis Cosmologies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06551v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A variety of processes in the very early universe can give rise to a population of primordial black holes (PBHs) with an extended mass spectrum. For certain mass spectra of this sort, it has been shown that the evaporation of these PBHs into radiation can drive the universe toward an epoch of cosmological stasis which can persist for a significant number of $e$-folds of cosmological expansion. However, in general, the initial mass spectrum which characterizes a population of PBHs at the time of production can subsequently be distorted by processes such as mergers and accretion. In this paper, we examine the effects that these processes have on the spectra that lead to a PBH-induced stasis. Within such stasis models, we find that mergers have only a negligible effect on these spectra within the regime of interest for stasis. We likewise find that the effect of accretion is negligible in many cases of interest. However, we find that the effect of accretion on the PBH mass spectrum is non-negligible in situations in which this spectrum is particularly broad. In such situations, the stasis epoch is abridged or, in extreme cases, does not occur at all. Thus accretion plays a non-trivial role in constraining the emergence of stasis within scenarios which lead to extended PBH mass spectra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06551v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keith R. Dienes, Lucien Heurtier, Fei Huang, Tim M. P. Tait, Brooks Thomas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking AI-evolved cosmological structure formation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06731v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The potential of deep learning-based image-to-image translations has recently attracted significant attention. One possible application of such a framework is as a fast, approximate alternative to cosmological simulations, which would be particularly useful in various contexts, including covariance studies, investigations of systematics, and cosmological parameter inference. To investigate different aspects of learning-based cosmological mappings, we choose two approaches for generating suitable cosmological matter fields as datasets: a simple analytical prescription provided by the Zel'dovich approximation, and a numerical N-body method using the Particle-Mesh approach. The evolution of structure formation is modeled using U-Net, a widely employed convolutional image translation framework. Because of the lack of a controlled methodology, validation of these learned mappings requires multiple benchmarks beyond simple visual comparisons and summary statistics. A comprehensive list of metrics is considered, including higher-order correlation functions, conservation laws, topological indicators, and statistical independence of density fields. We find that the U-Net approach performs well only for some of these physical metrics, and accuracy is worse at increasingly smaller scales, where the dynamic range in density is large. By introducing a custom density-weighted loss function during training, we demonstrate a significant improvement in the U-Net results at smaller scales. This study provides an example of how a family of physically motivated benchmarks can, in turn, be used to fine-tune optimization schemes -- such as the density-weighted loss used here -- to significantly enhance the accuracy of scientific machine learning approaches by focusing attention on relevant features.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06731v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaofeng Dong, Nesar Ramachandra, Salman Habib, Katrin Heitmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CURLING -- II. Improvement on the $H_{0}$ Inference from Pixelized Cluster Strong Lens Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07131v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Strongly lensed supernovae (glSNe) provide a powerful, independent method to measure the Hubble constant, $H_{0}$, through time delays between their multiple images. The accuracy of this measurement depends critically on both the precision of time delay estimation and the robustness of lens modeling. In many current cluster-scale modeling algorithms, all multiple images used for modeling are simplified as point sources to reduce computational costs. In the first paper of the CURLING program, we demonstrated that such a point-like approximation can introduce significant uncertainties and biases in both magnification reconstruction and cosmological inference. In this study, we explore how such simplifications affect $H_0$ measurements from glSNe. We simulate a lensed supernova at $z=1.95$, lensed by a galaxy cluster at $z=0.336$, assuming time delays are measured from LSST-like light curves. The lens model is constructed using JWST-like imaging data, utilizing both Lenstool and a pixelated method developed in CURLING. Under a fiducial cosmology with $H_0=70\rm \ km \ s^{-1}\ Mpc^{-1}$, the Lenstool model yields $H_0=69.91^{+6.27}_{-5.50}\rm \ km\ s^{-1}\ Mpc^{-1}$, whereas the pixelated framework improves the precision by over an order of magnitude, $H_0=70.39^{+0.82}_{-0.60}\rm \ km \ s^{-1}\ Mpc^{-1}$. Our results indicate that in the next-generation observations (e.g., JWST), uncertainties from lens modeling dominate the error budget for $H_0$ inference, emphasizing the importance of incorporating the extended surface brightness of multiple images to fully leverage the potential of glSNe for cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07131v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yushan Xie, Huanyuan Shan, Yiping Shu, Nan Li, Ji Yao, Ran Li, Xiaoyue Cao, Zizhao He, Yin Li, Eric Jullo, Jean-Paul Kneib, Guoliang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The cosmic web's Lyman-$\alpha$ glow at $z \approx 2.5$; varying hydrodynamic models, dust, and wide-field, narrow-band imaging detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07259</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07259v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The diffuse glow of the cosmic web in Lyman-$\alpha$ emission has long been predicted, yet remained elusive to direct wide field detection. We present theoretical calculations that, when compared with recent observations made using the Condor Array Telescope in New Mexico reported in Lanzetta et al. 2024, point to its discovery at $z \approx 2.5$. Synthetic Lyman-$\alpha$ surface brightness maps are constructed from five state-of-the-art hydrodynamic simulations (Illustris-TNG, SIMBA, EAGLE, CROCODILE, and Sherwood), incorporating dust attenuation, star formation, collisional excitation, and recombination physics. Our cosmic web Lyman-$\alpha$ surface brightness predictions are consistent with the UV excess detected at high significance in the recent deep, wide field, narrow-band imaging Condor data. The calculations presented here thus demonstrate that diffuse Lyman-$\alpha$ emission is observable with current (and next-generation) wide field low surface brightness facilities, opening the path to direct cartographic mapping of the cosmic web. These findings mark a turning point: for the first time, cosmology moves beyond inference from absorption and high-density peaks, into panoramic imaging of the faint intergalactic scaffolding that underpins structure formation in the Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07259v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleksii Sokoliuk, John K. Webb, Kenneth M. Lanzetta, Michael M. Shara, Stefan Gromoll, James S. Bolton, Robert F. Carswell, Gaspar Galaz, C\'edric Ledoux, Gaspare Lo Curto, Alain Smette, David Valls-Gabaud, Anja von der Linden, Frederick M. Walter, Joris Witstok</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rolling with modular symmetry: quintessence and de Sitter in heterotic orbifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22781v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Modular invariance is a fundamental symmetry in string compactifications, constraining both the structure of the effective theory and the dynamics of moduli and matter fields. It has also gained renewed importance in the context of swampland conjectures and, independently, flavour physics. We investigate a modular-invariant scalar potential arising from heterotic orbifolds, where the flavour structure and moduli dynamics are jointly shaped by the underlying geometry. Focusing on a string-inspired, two-moduli truncation, we uncover a rich vacuum structure featuring anti-de Sitter minima and unstable de Sitter saddle points. We identify large regions in moduli space supporting multifield hilltop quintessence consistent with observations. All solutions satisfy refined swampland de Sitter bounds. Our results illustrate how modular symmetry can guide the construction of controlled, string-motivated quintessence scenarios within consistent effective theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22781v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hansel Gordillo-Ruiz, Miguel Hernandez-Segura, Ignacio Portillo-Castillo, Saul Ramos-Sanchez, Ivonne Zavala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Helicity, Magnetic Monopoles, and Higgs Winding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25734v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Changes in magnetic helicity are often discussed across a variety of fields, from condensed matter physics to early universe cosmology. It is frequently stated that the helicity change is given by the integral of the gauge field strength tensor and its dual over spacetime, $\int F \wedge F$. However, this is incorrect when magnetic monopoles once exist in the spacetime. In this paper, we show the correct formula of the helicity change in such a case for the Maxwell theory with the magnetic monopoles. We also discuss what happens when we embed the Maxwell theory with magnetic monopoles into non-Abelian gauge theories. We show that a similar formula holds for the 't Hooft--Polyakov monopole. In particular, we find the winding numbers and the zeroes of the Higgs field in the non-Abelian gauge theory play a crucial role in the helicity change. The same discussion is also applicable to the electroweak theory, and we discuss the implication of our findings to the baryon number change via the chiral anomaly in the early universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25734v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hajime Fukuda, Yuta Hamada, Kohei Kamada, Kyohei Mukaida, Fumio Uchida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Preferential Accretion onto the Secondary Black Hole Strengthens Gravitational Wave Signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06325v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Pulsar timing arrays have recently found evidence for nanohertz gravitational waves that are consistent with being produced by a cosmological population of binary supermassive black holes (SMBHs). However, the amplitude of this gravitational wave background is larger than predicted from theoretical and empirical models of SMBH binary populations. We investigate preferential accretion onto the secondary, less massive SMBH of the binary as a potential solution to this discrepancy. We carry out the first observationally-based analysis of the effect of preferential accretion on the SMBH binary population, and we find that preferential accretion onto the secondary SMBH increases the binary SMBH mass ratio, causing many minor galaxy mergers to lead to major SMBH mergers. The fraction of SMBH mergers that are major mergers increases by a factor of 2-3 when preferential accretion is included. Further, we find that only a small amount of preferential accretion (10% total SMBH mass growth) is needed to bring the predicted gravitational wave background amplitude into agreement with observations. Preferential accretion has an even larger effect on gravitational wave signals detected by LISA, which will probe SMBH binaries at higher redshifts where the environment is more gas-rich, and can also help explain the rapid build up of overmassive black holes at high redshifts observed by the James Webb Space Telescope. It also shortens the time to the first detection of an individual SMBH binary emitting continuous waves. Preferential accretion strengthens the gravitational wave signals produced by any binary embedded in a circumbinary disk, including LIGO sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06325v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julia M. Comerford, Joseph Simon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are all Binary Black Holes Detected by LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA Following the Universal Time-Delay Distributions? Probably Not</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06352</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06352v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The delay time distribution (DTD) of binary black hole (BBH) mergers encodes the evolutionary link between the formation history and gravitational-wave (GW) emission. We present a non-parametric reconstruction of the mass-dependent DTD using the BBHs from the GWTC-4 that avoids restrictive assumptions of only power-law forms. Our analysis reveals for the first time the signature for mass-dependent evolutionary pathways: lower-mass systems ($20$-$40\,M_\odot$) are consistent with a scale-invariant DTD, whereas higher-mass BBHs ($40$-$100\,M_\odot$) provide the first direct tentative evidence of DTD that deviate from simple power laws, with a pronounced preference for rapid mergers around $2-6$ Gyrs. These findings reveal the advantage of the non-parametric technique in reconstructing the mass-dependent DTD and discovering for the first-time the presence of a potential time-scale associated with high-mass GW events.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06352v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samsuzzaman Afroz,  Navdha, Suvodip Mukherjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The radial acceleration relation at the EDGE of galaxy formation: testing its universality in low-mass dwarf galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06905v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A tight correlation between the baryonic and observed acceleration of galaxies has been reported over a wide range of mass ($10^8 &lt; M_{\rm bar}/{\rm M}_\odot &lt; 10^{11}$) - the Radial Acceleration Relation (RAR). This has been interpreted as evidence that dark matter is actually a manifestation of some modified weak-field gravity theory. In this paper, we study the radially resolved RAR of 12 nearby dwarf galaxies, with baryonic masses in the range $10^4 &lt; M_{\rm bar}/{\rm M}_\odot &lt; 10^{7.5}$, using a combination of literature data and data from the MUSE-Faint survey. We use stellar line-of-sight velocities and the Jeans modelling code GravSphere to infer the mass distributions of these galaxies, allowing us to compute the RAR. We compare the results with the EDGE simulations of isolated dwarf galaxies with similar stellar masses in a $\Lambda$CDM cosmology. We find that most of the observed dwarf galaxies lie systematically above the low-mass extrapolation of the RAR. Each galaxy traces a locus in the RAR space that can have a multi-valued observed acceleration for a given baryonic acceleration, while there is significant scatter from galaxy to galaxy. Our results indicate that the RAR does not apply to low-mass dwarf galaxies and that the inferred baryonic acceleration of these dwarfs does not contain enough information, on its own, to derive the observed acceleration. The simulated EDGE dwarfs behave similarly to the real data, lying systematically above the extrapolated RAR. We show that, in the context of modified weak-field gravity theories, these results cannot be explained by differential tidal forces from the Milky Way, nor by the galaxies being far from dynamical equilibrium, since none of the galaxies in our sample seems to experience strong tides. As such, our results provide further evidence for the need for invisible dark matter in the smallest dwarf galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06905v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mariana P. J\'ulio, Justin I. Read, Marcel S. Pawlowski, Pengfei Li, Daniel Vaz, Jarle Brinchmann, Martin P. Rey, Oscar Agertz, Tom Holmes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Dark Matter and Dark Energy in a model of Non-Canonical Scalar-Tensor Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07103</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07103v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a model of non-canonical scalar-tensor theory in which the kinetic term in the Brans-Dicke action is replaced by a non-canonical scalar field Lagrangian $\mathcal{L}(X, \phi)= \lambda X^\alpha \phi^\beta - V(\phi)$ where $X = (1/2) \partial_{\mu} \phi \partial^{\mu} \phi$ and $\alpha$, $\beta$ and $\lambda$ are parameters of the model. This can be considered as a simple non-canonical generalization of the Brans-Dicke theory with a potential term which corresponds to a special case of this model with the values of the parameter $\alpha = 1$, $\beta = -1$ and $\lambda = 2w_{_{BD}}$ where $w_{_{BD}}$ is the Brans-Dicke parameter. Considering a spatially flat Friedmann-Robertson-Walker Universe with scale factor $a(t)$, it is shown that, in the matter free Universe, the kinetic term $\lambda X^\alpha \phi^\beta$ can lead to a power law solution $a(t)\propto t^{n}$ but the maximum possible value of $n$ turns out to be $(1+\sqrt{3})/4 \approx 0.683$. When $\alpha \geq 18$, this model can lead to a solution $a(t)\propto t^{2/3}$, thereby mimicking the evolution of scale factor in a cold dark matter dominated epoch with Einstein's General Relativity (GR). With the addition of a linear potential term $V(\phi) = V_{0}\phi$, it is shown that this model mimics the standard $\Lambda$CDM model type evolution of the Universe. The larger the value of $\alpha$, the closer the evolution of $a(t)$ in this model to that in the $\Lambda$CDM model based on Einstein's GR. The purpose of this paper is to demonstrate that this model with a linear potential can mimic the GR based $\Lambda$CDM model. However, with an appropriate choice of the potential $V(\phi)$, this model can provide a unified description of both dark matter and dynamical dark energy, as if it were based on Einstein's GR.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07103v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nihal Jalal Pullisseri, Sanil Unnikrishnan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the cosmological 21~cm global signal from the Antarctic ice sheet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07198v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The redshifted 21 cm line, arising from neutral hydrogen, offers a unique probe into the intergalactic medium and the first stars and galaxies formed in the early universe. However, detecting this signal is a challenging task because of artificial radio-frequency interference (RFI) and systematic errors such as ground effects. The interior of the Antarctic continent provides an excellent location to make such observations, with minimal RFI and relatively stable foreground signals. Moreover, a flat plateau in central Antarctica, with an ice cap over 2000 m deep, will show less ground reflection of radio waves, reducing the signal complexity in the area around the probing antenna. It may be advantageous to perform cosmological 21 cm experiments in Antarctica, and a 21 cm Antarctic global spectrum experiment can potentially be deployed on the Antarctic ice cap. We have performed preliminary instrumental design, system calibration, and implementation of such an instrument optimized for extreme cold and capable of long-term autonomous operation. This system shows the ability to effectively detect the 21~cm signal, confirming Antarctica as an excellent observational site for radio cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07198v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shijie Sun, Jiaqin Xu, Minquan Zhou, Shenzhe Xu, Fengquan Wu, Haoran Zhang, Juyong Zhang, Bin Ma, Zhaohui Shang, Xuelei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-energy variability of the gravitationally lensed blazar PKS 1830-211</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07220</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07220v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The production site and process responsible for the highly variable high-energy emission observed from blazar jets are still debated. Gravitational lenses can be used as microscopes to investigate the nature of such sources. We study the broad-band spectral properties and the high-energy variability of the gravitationally-lensed blazar PKS 1830-211, for which radio observations have revealed two images, to put constraints on the jet physics and the existence of a gravitationally-induced time delay and magnification ratio between the images. We utilize Swift/XRT, Nustar, and Fermi-LAT observations from 2016 and 2019 to compare periods of low activity and high activity in PKS 1830-211. Short-timescale variability is elucidated with an unbinned power spectrum analysis of time-tagged NuSTAR photon data. To study the gravitationally-induced time delay in the gamma-ray light curve observed with Fermi-LAT, we improve existing autocorrelation function based methods. Our modified auto-correlation method yields a delay of t_0=21.1 +/- 0.1 d and magnification factor a=0.13 +/- 0.01. These parameters remain time-invariant. In data from 2016 and 2019, the X-ray spectra remain remarkably stable, contrasting with extreme changes in gamma-rays. Both states can be fitted with a single component from Comptonisation of infrared emission from the dusty torus, with different gamma-ray states arising solely from a shift in the break of the electron energy distribution. The detection of a consistent lag throughout the whole light curve suggests that they originate from a persistent location in the jet.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07220v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sarah M. Wagner, Jeffrey D. Scargle, Greg Madejski, Andrea Gokus, Krzysztof Nalewajko, Patrick G\"unther, Karl Mannheim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing evolution of Long GRB properties through their cosmic formation history aided by Machine Learning predicted redshifts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07306</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07306v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Gamma-ray Bursts (GRBs) are valuable probes of cosmic star formation reaching back into the epoch of reionization, and a large dataset with known redshifts ($z$) is an important ingredient for these studies. Usually, $z$ is measured using spectroscopy or photometry, but $\sim80\%$ of GRBs lack such data. Prompt and afterglow correlations can provide estimates in these cases, though they suffer from systematic uncertainties due to assumed cosmologies and due to detector threshold limits. We use a sample with $z$ estimated via machine learning models, based on prompt and afterglow parameters, without relying on cosmological assumptions. We then use an augmented sample of GRBs with measured and predicted redshifts, forming a larger dataset. We find that the predicted redshifts are a crucial step forward in understanding the evolution of GRB properties. We test three cases: no evolution, an evolution of the beaming factor, and an evolution of all terms captured by an evolution factor $(1+z)^\delta$. We find that these cases can explain the density rate in the redshift range between 1-2, but neither of the cases can explain the derived rate densities at smaller and higher redshifts, which may point towards an evolution term different than a simple power law. Another possibility is that this mismatch is due to the non-homogeneity of the sample, e.g., a non-collapsar origin of some long GRB within the sample.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07306v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dhruv S. Bal, Aditya Narendra, Maria Giovanna Dainotti, Nikita S. Khatiya, Aleksander L. Lenart, Dieter H. Hartmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Inflation and Reheating Features in the Higgs-$R^2$ Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.04924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.04924v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigated inflation in the Higgs-$R^2$ model and assumed the trajectory to follow a single-field approximation called minimal two-field mode. Using this approximation, we tried to constrain the Higgs' non-minimal coupling $\xi$. During inflation, we investigated the effect of $\xi$ on the non-gaussianity. We found that $\xi$ could not provide the large non-gaussianity. In this paper, we divided the preheating stage to be quadratic regime and quartic regime. During the quadratic regime, the gauge bosons' production is the most dominant. However, it could not drain the whole inflaton's energy. Thus, we introduced a dark matter candidate with a large coupling that could drain the whole inflaton's energy. We also found that if $\xi&lt;4.2$, the oscillation on the quadratic regime continued to the quartic regime. The reheating temperature obtained by this mode can be reached to be $\sim 10^{10}$ GeV and strongly depends on the remaining inflaton's energy density. On contrary, if $\xi&gt;4.2$, the oscillation only happens at the quadratic regime. As we assumed the Pauli exclusion principle does exist during the quadratic regime, the instant decay of gauge bosons to fermions is restricted. Hence we expected, the reheating temperature to be low for about $\sim 10^9$ GeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.04924v5</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2025.117149</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nucl. Phys. B 1020 (2025) 117149 Nucl. Phys. B 1020 (2025) 117149 Nucl. Phys. B 1020 (2025) 117149</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Norma Sidik Risdianto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Foreground Removal in Ground-Based CMB Observations Using a Transformer Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09071v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a novel method for Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) foreground removal based on deep learning techniques. This method employs a Transformer model, referred to as \texttt{TCMB}, which is specifically designed to effectively process HEALPix-format spherical sky maps. \texttt{TCMB} represents an innovative application in CMB data analysis, as it is an image-based technique that has rarely been utilized in this field. Using simulated data with noise levels representative of current ground-based CMB polarization observations, the \texttt{TCMB} method demonstrates robust performance in removing foreground contamination. The mean absolute variance for the reconstruction of the noisy CMB Q/U map is significantly less than the CMB polarization signal. To mitigate biases caused by instrumental noise, a cross-correlation approach using two half-mission maps was employed, successfully recovering CMB EE and BB power spectra that align closely with the true values, and these results validate the effectiveness of the \texttt{TCMB} method. Compared to the previously employed convolutional neural network (CNN)-based approach, the \texttt{TCMB} method offers two significant advantages: (1) It demonstrates superior effectiveness in reconstructing CMB polarization maps, outperforming CNN-based methods. (2) It can directly process HEALPix spherical sky maps without requiring rectangular region division, a step necessary for CNN-based approaches that often introduces uncertainties such as boundary effects. This study highlights the potential of Transformer-based models as a powerful tool for CMB data analysis, offering a substantial improvement over traditional CNN-based techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09071v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ye-Peng Yan, Si-Yu Li, Yang Liu, Jun-Qing Xia, Hong Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmology with One Galaxy: Auto-Encoding the Galaxy Properties Manifold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17568v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Cosmological simulations like CAMELS and IllustrisTNG characterize hundreds of thousands of galaxies using various internal properties. Previous studies have demonstrated that machine learning can be used to infer the cosmological parameter $\Omega_m$ from the internal properties of even a single randomly selected simulated galaxy. This ability was hypothesized to originate from galaxies occupying a low-dimensional manifold within a higher-dimensional galaxy property space, which shifts with variations in $\Omega_m$. In this work, we investigate how galaxies occupy the high-dimensional galaxy property space, particularly the effect of $\Omega_m$ and other cosmological and astrophysical parameters on the putative manifold. We achieve this by using an autoencoder with an Information-Ordered Bottleneck (IOB), a neural layer with adaptive compression, to perform dimensionality reduction on individual galaxy properties from CAMELS simulations, which are run with various combinations of cosmological and astrophysical parameters. We find that for an autoencoder trained on the fiducial set of parameters, the reconstruction error increases significantly when the test set deviates from fiducial values of $\Omega_m$ and $A_{\text{SN1}}$, indicating that these parameters shift galaxies off the fiducial manifold. In contrast, variations in other parameters such as $\sigma_8$ cause negligible error changes, suggesting galaxies shift along the manifold. These findings provide direct evidence that the ability to infer $\Omega_m$ from individual galaxies is tied to the way $\Omega_m$ shifts the manifold. Physically, this implies that parameters like $\sigma_8$ produce galaxy property changes resembling natural scatter, while parameters like $\Omega_m$ and $A_{\text{SN1}}$ create unsampled properties, extending beyond the natural scatter in the fiducial model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17568v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/add724</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The Astrophysical Journal, 986(2), 133 (June 2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Amanda Lue, Shy Genel, Marc Huertas-Company, Francisco Villaescusa-Navarro, Matthew Ho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark sirens and the impact of redshift precision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17747v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: With the growing number of gravitational wave detections, achieving a competitive measurement of $H_0$ with dark sirens is becoming increasingly feasible. The expansion of the Ligo-Virgo-KAGRA Collaboration into a four detector network will reduce both the localisation area and the luminosity distance uncertainty associated with each gravitational wave event. It is therefore essential to identify and mitigate other major sources of error that could increase the uncertainty in $H_0$. In this work, we explore three scenarios relevant to the dark siren method in future observing runs. First, we demonstrate that there is a precision gain offered by a catalogue of spectroscopic-like redshifts compared to photometric-like redshifts, with the greatest improvements observed in smaller localisation areas. Second, we show that redshift outliers (as occur in realistic photometric redshift catalogues), do not introduce bias into the measurement of $H_0$. Finally, we find that uniformly sub-sampling spectroscopic-like redshift catalogues increases the uncertainty in $H_0$ as the completeness fraction is decreased; at a completeness of 50% the benefit of spectroscopic redshift precision is outweighed by the degradation from incompleteness. In all three scenarios, we obtain unbiased estimates of $H_0$. We conclude that a competitive measurement of $H_0$ using the dark siren method will require a hybrid catalogue of both photometric and spectroscopic redshifts, at least until highly complete spectroscopic catalogues become available. This, however, will come at the cost of a more complex selection function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17747v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Madeline L. Cross-Parkin, Cullan Howlett, Tamara M. Davis, Nandita Khetan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Wave Memory of Primordial Black Hole Mergers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01356</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01356v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The gravitational wave signal of binary compact objects has two main contributions at frequencies below the characteristic merger frequency: the gravitational wave signal associated with the early inspiral stage of the binary and the non-linear gravitational wave memory. We compare the sensitivity of upcoming gravitational wave detectors to these two contributions, with a particular interest in events with a merger phase at frequencies higher than the detector's peak sensitivity. We demonstrate that for light primordial black holes, current and upcoming detectors are more sensitive to the inspiral signal. Our analysis incorporates the evolution history of primordial black hole binaries, key to accurately estimating the relevant event rates. We also discuss the waveform templates of the memory signal at ground- and space-based interferometers, and the implications for a matched filtering search. This allows us to compare the sensitivity of high-frequency gravitational wave detectors, sensitive to the merger phase, with the sensitivity of existing interferometers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01356v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Silvia Gasparotto, Gabriele Franciolini, Valerie Domcke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prospects for disentangling dark matter with weak lensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02233v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the degeneracy between the effects of ultra-light axion dark matter and baryonic feedback in suppressing the matter power spectrum. We forecast that galaxy shear data from the Rubin Observatory's Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST) could limit an axion of mass $m = 10^{-25}\,\mathrm{eV}$ to be $\lesssim 5\%$ of the dark matter, stronger than any current bound, if the interplay between axions and feedback is accurately modelled. Using a halo model emulator to construct power spectra for mixed cold and axion dark matter cosmologies, including baryonic effects, we find that galaxy shear is sensitive to axions from $10^{-27}\,\mathrm{eV}$ to $10^{-21}\,\mathrm{eV}$, with the capacity to set competitive bounds across much of this range. For axions with $m \sim 10^{-25}\,\mathrm{eV}$, the scales at which axions and feedback impact structure formation are similar, introducing a parameter degeneracy. We find that, with an external feedback constraint, we can break the degeneracy and constrain the axion transfer function, such that LSST could detect a $10^{-25}\,\mathrm{eV}$ axion comprising 10\% of the dark matter at $\sim 3 \sigma$ significance. Direct reconstruction of the non-linear matter power spectrum provides an alternative way of analysing weak lensing surveys, with the advantage of identifying the scale-dependent features in the data that the dark matter model imposes. We advocate for dedicated cosmological hydrodynamical simulations with an axion dark matter component so that upcoming galaxy and cosmic microwave background lensing surveys can disentangle the dark matter-baryon transfer function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02233v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/staf1321</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Mon Not R Astron Soc (2025) 2698-2713</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Calvin Preston, Keir K. Rogers, Alexandra Amon, George Efstathiou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are magnetic fields in cosmic voids primordial?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14774v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The nature of magnetic fields in the voids of the large-scale structure of the Universe has been a multifaceted open puzzle for decades. On one hand, their origin is not clear with most of the magnetogenesis models using physics beyond the standard model in the early Universe, and on the other hand, their existence and potential role in explaining the spectra of TeV blazars have been intensely debated in the past decade. Here, we propose a mechanism, within classical electrodynamics, that could fill the voids with late-Universe fields and, under certain conditions, dispel the need for primordial fields altogether to explain the void fields. Specifically, we use the dipole component of the galactic fields to generate space-filling magnetic fields in voids with white-noise spectrum and sufficient amplitude to explain the lack of GeV halos around TeV blazars observed by Fermi-LAT. A definitive test for such fields in the voids will be the white-noise spectral shape, which will constrain possible plasma processes in the voids to the ones that allow for the propagation of these dipole fields into the voids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14774v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Deepen Garg, Ruth Durrer, Jennifer Schober</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct reconstruction of the Reionization history from 21cm 2D Power Spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19925</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19925v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The 21cm line from the spin-flip transition of neutral hydrogen (HI) provides a unique window into the Epoch of Reionization (EoR), the final phase transition of our Universe. The Square Kilometre Array (SKA) enables precise measurements of 21cm fluctuations that trace ionization, temperature, and density fluctuations of the intergalactic medium (IGM). Nevertheless, a direct reconstruction of the timeline of the EoR in terms of the progress of ionization remains an ongoing challenge due to the highly non-Gaussian nature and thus intractable likelihood of the 21cm signal. Here, we present EoRFlow, a simulation-based inference (SBI) framework for reconstructing the global neutral hydrogen fraction $x_{\mathrm{HI}}(z)$ directly from 2D cylindrically averaged power spectra (2DPS) of the 21cm signal. We validate our method on realistic mock datasets for SKA-Low. Bypassing the need for explicit likelihood formulations, our approach enables fast, unbiased posterior estimation of the $x_{\mathrm{HI}}$ evolution in narrow redshift slices, allowing for piecewise reconstruction of the global reionization history. By directly inferring the reionization history from 21cm power spectra, our framework provides a scalable and robust path forward for 21cm cosmology in the SKA era.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19925v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/10/039</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP10(2025)039</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yannic Pietschke, Caroline Heneka, Tom Schlenker, Ayodele Ore, Benedikt Schosser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Requirements on bandpass resolution and measurement precision for LiteBIRD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22217</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.22217v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we study the impact of an imperfect knowledge of the instrument bandpasses on the estimate of the tensor-to-scalar ratio $r$ in the context of the next-generation LiteBIRD satellite. We develop a pipeline to integrate over the bandpass transmission in both the time-ordered data (TOD) and the map-making processing steps. We introduce the systematic effect by having a mismatch between the ``real'', high resolution bandpass $\tau$, entering the TOD, and the estimated one $\tau_s$, used in the map-making. We focus on two aspects: the effect of degrading the $\tau_s$ resolution, and the addition of a Gaussian error $\sigma$ to $\tau_s$. To reduce the computational load of the analysis, the two effects are explored separately, for three representative LiteBIRD channels (40 GHz, 140 GHz and 402 GHz) and for three bandpass shapes. Computing the amount of bias on $r$, $\Delta r$, caused by these effects on a single channel, we find that a resolution $\lesssim 1.5$ GHz and $\sigma \lesssim 0.0089$ do not exceed the LiteBIRD budget allocation per systematic effect, $\Delta r &lt; 6.5 \times 10^{-6}$. We then check that propagating separately the uncertainties due to a resolution of 1 GHz and a measurement error with $\sigma = 0.0089$ in all LiteBIRD frequency channels, for the most pessimistic bandpass shape of the three considered, still produces a $\Delta r &lt; 6.5 \times 10^{-6}$. This is done both with the simple deprojection approach and with a blind component separation technique, the Needlet Internal Linear Combination (NILC). Due to the effectiveness of NILC in cleaning the systematic residuals, we have tested that the requirement on $\sigma$ can be relaxed to $\sigma \lesssim 0.05$. (Abridged)</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.22217v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/10/038</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP10(2025)038</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>S. Giardiello (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. Carones (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), T. Ghigna (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), L. Pagano (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), F. Piacentini (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), L. Montier (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), R. Takaku (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), E. Calabrese (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), D. Adak (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), E. Allys (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. Anand (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), J. Aumont (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Ballardini (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. J. Banday (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), R. B. Barreiro (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), N. Bartolo (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), S. Basak (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Bersanelli (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. Besnard (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Bortolami (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), T. Brinckmann (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), F. J. Casas (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), K. Cheung (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Citran (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), L. Clermont (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), F. Columbro (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. Coppolecchia (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), F. Cuttaia (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), P. de Bernardis (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), E. de la Hoz (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. De Lucia (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), S. Della Torre (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), E. Di Giorgi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), P. Diego-Palazuelos (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), U. Fuskeland (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), G. Galloni (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Galloway (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Gerbino (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Gervasi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), R. T. G\'enova-Santos (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), C. Gimeno-Amo (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. Gruppuso (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Hazumi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), S. Henrot-Versill\'e (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), L. T. Hergt (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), B. Jost (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), K. Kohri (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), L. Lamagna (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), C. Leloup (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), F. Levrier (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. I. Lonappan (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. L\'opez-Caniego (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), G. Luzzi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), J. Macias-Perez (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), V. Maranchery (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), E. Mart\'inez-Gonz\'alez (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), S. Masi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), S. Matarrese (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), T. Matsumura (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), S. Micheli (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Migliaccio (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Monelli (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), G. Morgante (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), L. Mousset (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), R. Nagata (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. Novelli (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), F. Noviello (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), I. Obata (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. Occhiuzzi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. Paiella (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), D. Paoletti (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), G. Pascual-Cisneros (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), G. Patanchon (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Pinchera (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), G. Polenta (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), L. Porcelli (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), G. Puglisi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), N. Raffuzzi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Remazeilles (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. Rizzieri (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Ruiz-Granda (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), J. Sanghavi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), V. Sauvage (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), G. Savini (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Shiraishi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), G. Signorelli (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), R. M. Sullivan (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), Y. Takase (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), L. Terenzi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Tomasi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Tristram (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), L. Vacher (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), B. van Tent (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), P. Vielva (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), I. K. Wehus (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), G. Weymann-Despres (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), E. J. Wollack (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), Y. Zhou (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyper Suprime-Cam Y3 results: photo-$z$ bias calibration with lensing shear ratios and cosmological constraints from cosmic shear</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.21681v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present an independent calibration of the photometric redshift (photo-$z$) distributions for source galaxies in the HSC-Y3 weak lensing survey using small-scale galaxy-galaxy lensing. By measuring the tangential shear around spectroscopic lens galaxies from GAMA, SDSS, and DESI, divided into fifteen narrow redshift bins, we compute shear ratios that are sensitive to the mean redshift of source galaxies. Using a blinded analysis, we derive constraints on the photo-$z$ bias parameters in source bins 2, 3 and 4, achieving signal-to-noise ratios of 59, 75, and 62, respectively. Our constraints for $\Delta z_2$, $\Delta z_3$ and $\Delta z_4$ are consistent with those from HSC-Y3 cosmic shear modeling. We observe a mild shift in the $\Delta z_3$-$\Delta z_4$ plane due to the heterogeneous depth of the lens sample, which disappears when using only DESI-DR1 lenses. Combining shear-ratio measurements with cosmic shear data, we obtain joint constraints on cosmological parameters: $\Omega_{\rm m} = 0.304_{-0.029}^{+0.03}$ and $S_8 = 0.773_{-0.031}^{+0.031}$, consistent with cosmic shear-only results. This work demonstrates the utility of small-scale lensing as an independent probe for calibrating photometric redshift bias in weak lensing cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.21681v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Divya Rana, Surhud More, Hironao Miyatake, Sunao Sugiyama, Tianqing Zhang, Masato Shirasaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matter power spectrum reconstruction with KiDS-Legacy: Improved internal $\Lambda$CDM consistency and preference for strong baryonic feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08365v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Direct measurements of the matter power spectrum, $P_\mathrm{m}(k,z)$, provide a powerful tool to investigate observed tensions between models of structure growth while also testing the internal consistency of cosmological probes. We analyse cosmic shear data from the final data release of the Kilo-Degree Survey (KiDS), presenting a deprojected $P_\mathrm{m}(k,z)$, measured in up to three redshift bins. Compared to analyses using previous KiDS releases, we find improved internal consistency in the $z\lesssim0.7$ regime. At large scales, $k\lesssim0.1\,h\,\rm Mpc^{-1}$, our power spectrum reconstruction aligns with $\Lambda$CDM predictions with a density fluctuation amplitude $\sigma_8=0.81$. Furthermore, at small scales, $k=3$-$20\,h\,\rm Mpc^{-1}$, the average matter power spectrum is suppressed by $30\%\pm10\%\,{\rm (stat.)}\pm4\%\,{\rm (sys.)}$ with $2.8\sigma$ significance relative to a dark-matter-only model, consistent with expectations of strong baryonic feedback.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08365v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeger C. Broxterman, Patrick Simon, Lucas Porth, Konrad Kuijken, Angus H. Wright, Marika Asgari, Maciej Bilicki, Catherine Heymans, Hendrik Hildebrandt, Henk Hoekstra, Benjamin Joachimi, Shun-Sheng Li, Matteo Maturi, Lauro Moscardini, Mario Radovich, Robert Reischke, Maximilian Von Wietersheim-Kramsta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharpening the dark matter signature in gravitational waveforms I: Accretion and eccentricity evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.13053</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.13053v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dark matter overdensities around black holes can alter the dynamical evolution of a companion object orbiting around it, and cause a dephasing of the gravitational waveform. Here, we present a refined calculation of the co-evolution of the binary and the dark matter distribution, taking into account the accretion of dark matter particles on the companion black hole, and generalizing previous quasi-circular calculations to the general case of eccentric orbits. These calculations are validated by dedicated N-body simulations. We show that accretion can lead to a large dephasing, and therefore cannot be neglected in general. We also demonstrate that dark matter spikes tend to circularize eccentric orbits faster than previously thought.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.13053v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.063070</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 111, 063070 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Theophanes K. Karydas, Bradley J. Kavanagh, Gianfranco Bertone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Background-dependent and classical correspondences between $f(Q)$ and $f(T)$ gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.01104v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: $f(Q)$ and $f(T)$ gravity are based on fundamentally different geometric frameworks, yet they exhibit many similar properties. This article provides a comprehensive summary and comparative analysis of the various theoretical branches of torsional gravity and non-metric gravity, which arise from different choices of affine connection. We identify two types of background-dependent and classical correspondences between these two theories of gravity. The first correspondence is established through their equivalence within the Minkowski spacetime background. To achieve this, we develop the tetrad-spin formulation of $f(Q)$ gravity and derive the corresponding expression for the spin connection. The second correspondence is based on the equivalence of their equations of motion. Utilizing a metric-affine approach, we derive the general affine connection for static and spherically symmetric spacetime in $f(Q)$ gravity and compare its equations of motion with those of $f(T)$ gravity. Among others, our results reveal that, $f(T)$ solutions are not simply a subset of $f(Q)$ solutions; rather, they encompass a complex solution beyond $f(Q)$ gravity in black hole background.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.01104v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-025-14822-6</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Cheng Wu, Xin Ren, Yuhang Yang, Yu-Min Hu, Emmanuel N. Saridakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Semi-analytic Framework of Population III and Subsequent Galaxy Formation on Cosmological N-body Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17540</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17540v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop a new semi-analytic framework of Population (Pop) III and subsequent galaxy formation designed to run on dark matter halo merger trees. In our framework, we consider the effect of the Lyman-Werner flux from Pop III and II stars and the dark matter baryon streaming velocity on the critical halo mass for the Pop III formation. Our model incorporates the Lyman-Werner feedback in a self-consistent way, therefore, the spatial variation of Lyman-Werner feedback naturally emerges. The Pop III mass depends on the properties of a halo as reproducing radiative hydrodynamical simulation results. We perform statistical studies of Pop III stars by applying this framework to high-resolution cosmological N-body simulations with a maximum box size of 16 Mpc/h and enough mass resolution to resolve Pop III-forming halos. A top-heavy initial mass function emerges and two peaks corresponding to the H$_2$ ($20 \lesssim z \lesssim 25$) and atomic cooling halos ($z \lesssim 15$) exist in the distribution. Supermassive stars can be formed in the atomic cooling halos, and the fractions of such supermassive stars increase with the value of streaming velocity. At least an 8 Mpc/h simulation box and the self-consistent model for the Lyman-Werner feedback are necessary to correctly model the Pop III formation in the atomic cooling halos. Our model predicts one supermassive star per halo with several $10^9$ Msun at z=7.5, which is enough to reproduce a high redshift quasar.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17540v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomoaki Ishiyama, Shingo Hirano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prospects of future MeV telescopes in probing weak-scale Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04907v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Galactic weak-scale Dark Matter (DM) particles annihilating into lepton-rich channels not only produce gamma-rays via prompt radiation but also generate abundant energetic electrons and positrons, which subsequently emit through bremsstrahlung or inverse Compton scattering (collectively called `secondary-radiation photons'). While the prompt gamma-rays concentrate at high-energy, the secondary emission falls in the MeV range, which a number of upcoming experiments (AMEGO, E-ASTROGAM, MAST...) will probe. We investigate the sensitivity of these future telescopes for weak-scale DM, focusing for definiteness on observations of the galactic center. We find that they have the potential of probing a wide region of the DM parameter space which is currently unconstrained. Namely, in rather optimistic configurations, future MeV telescopes could probe thermally-produced DM with a mass up to the TeV range, or GeV DM with an annihilation cross section 2 to 3 orders of magnitude smaller than the current bounds, precisely thanks to the significant leverage provided by their sensitivity to secondary emissions. We comment on astrophysical and methodological uncertainties, and compare with the reach of high-energy gamma ray experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04907v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.21468/SciPostPhys.19.3.080</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SciPost Phys. 19, 080 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Marco Cirelli, Arpan Kar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synthesizer: a Software Package for Synthetic Astronomical Observables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03888v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present Synthesizer, a fast, flexible, modular and extensible platform for modelling synthetic astrophysical observables. Synthesizer can be used for a number of applications, but is predominantly designed for generating mock observables from analytical and numerical galaxy formation simulations. These use cases include (but are not limited to) analytical modelling of the star formation and metal enrichment histories of galaxies, the creation of mock images and integral field unit observations from particle based simulations, detailed photoionisation modelling of the central regions of active galactic nuclei, and spectro-photometric fitting. We provide a number of stellar population synthesis models, photoionisation code configurations, dust models, and imaging configurations that can be used 'out-of-the-box' interactively. The code can be used to quantitatively test the dependence of forward modelled observables on various model and parameter choices, and rapidly explore large parameter ranges for calibration and inference tasks. We invite and encourage the community to use, test and develop the code, and hope that the foundation developed will provide a flexible framework for a number of tasks in forward and inverse modelling of astrophysical observables. The code is publicly available at https://synthesizer-project.github.io/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03888v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher C. Lovell, William J. Roper, Aswin P. Vijayan, Stephen M. Wilkins, Sophie Newman, Louise Seeyave</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral characterization and performance of SPT-SLIM on-chip filterbank spectrometers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02245</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02245v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The South Pole Telescope Shirokoff Line Intensity Mapper (SPT-SLIM) experiment is a pathfinder for demonstrating the use of on-chip spectrometers for millimeter Line Intensity Mapping. We present spectral bandpass measurements of the SLIM spectrometer channels made on site using a Fourier Transform Spectrometer during SPT-SLIMs first deployment the 2024-2025 austral summer observing season. Through this we demonstrate a technique for measuring the narrow band passes of the SPT-SLIM filterbanks that improves beyond the intrinsic resolution of a Fourier Transform Spectrometer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02245v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. S. Benson, K. Fichman, M. Adamic, A. J. Anderson, P. S. Barry, B. A. Benson, E. Brooks, J. E. Carlstrom, T. Cecil, C. L. Chang, K. R. Dibert, M. Dobbs, K. S. Karkare, G. K. Keating, A. M. Lapuente, M. Lisovenko, D. P. Marrone, J. Montgomery, T. Natoli, Z. Pan, A. Rahlin, G. Robson, M. Rouble, G. Smecher, V. Yefremenko, M. R. Young, C. Yu, J. A. Zebrowski, C. Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Quality Axion Dark Matter at Gravitational Wave Interferometers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14323</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14323v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Gravitational effects are known to violate global symmetries, threatening the Peccei-Quinn (PQ) solution to the strong CP problem. Ultraviolet completions featuring a gauged $U(1)$ symmetry, where $U(1)_{\rm PQ}$ arises as an accidental global symmetry, can suppress Planck-suppressed operators, enabling high-quality axions in a mass window where it can also account for the observed dark matter (DM) in the Universe. We show that in such models, the spontaneous breaking of the $U(1)$ gauge symmetry generates a strong stochastic gravitational wave background (SGWB) from gauge cosmic string loops. For breaking scales $\gtrsim 10^{14}$ GeV, the SGWB signal strength exceeds astrophysical foregrounds across a broad frequency range. Contrary to conventional gauge cosmic string scenarios, such quality axion models have a characteristic IR break frequency originating from the collapse of string-wall network around axion oscillation temperature. We propose this characteristic SGWB frequency-amplitude region, identified as \textit{Signature-Window-Axion-Gravitational waves} (SWAG), to be a novel probe of high-quality axion DM at future space and ground-based interferometers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14323v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Disha Bandyopadhyay, Debasish Borah, Nayan Das, Rome Samanta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extra Radiation Cosmologies: Implications of the Hubble Tension for eV-scale Neutrinos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25478v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a new analysis on sterile neutrino cosmologies using the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) second data release (DR2) baryon acoustic oscillation (BAO) measurements in combination with cosmic microwave background (CMB), CMB lensing, and supernova data. We show that BAO observables are intrinsically less sensitive to the combined effects of relativistic energy density, $N_{\rm eff}$, and the sum of neutrino masses, $\Sigma m_\nu$, which are both augmented in sterile neutrino cosmologies. With SH0ES local expansion rate, $H_0$, data, we find $N_{\rm eff} = 3.43 \pm 0.13$, reducing the Hubble tension to $2.4\sigma$. For a 0.1 eV sterile neutrino, we find $N_{\rm eff}=3.50$ as the best fit. For this representative $N_{\rm eff}$, we find an upper limit of $m_s &lt; 0.17$ eV (95% CL), greater than a factor of four weaker than standard constraints on $\Sigma m_\nu$. When SH0ES is included, light sterile neutrinos with masses $m_s\simeq0.1$-$0.2$ eV are favored at $\gtrsim 3\sigma$, whereas eV-scale sterile masses remain strongly excluded by the data in the cosmologies we study. Our findings confirm our previous results that partially thermalized sub-eV sterile neutrinos are preferred by the SH0ES $H_0$ data. The preferred $m_s$ mass scale overlaps with, but is not identical to, that favored in neutrino oscillation solutions to short-baseline anomalies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25478v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Helena Garc\'ia Escudero, Kevork N. Abazajian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WISPFI Experiment: Prototype Development</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01221</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01221v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Axions and axion-like particles (ALPs) are well-motivated dark matter (DM) candidates that couple to photons in external magnetic fields. The parameter space around $m_a \sim 50~\mu$eV remains largely unexplored by haloscope experiments. We present the first prototype of WISP Searches on a Fiber Interferometer (WISPFI), a table-top, model-independent scheme based on resonant photon-axion conversion in a hollow-core photonic crystal fiber (HC-PCF) integrated into a Mach-Zehnder interferometer (MZI). Operating near a dark fringe with active phase-locking, combined with amplitude modulation, the interferometer converts axion-induced photon disappearance into a measurable signal. A 2 W, 1550 nm laser is coupled into a 1 m-long HC-PCF placed inside a 2 T permanent magnet array, probing a fixed axion mass of $m_a \simeq 49~$meV with a projected sensitivity of $g_{a\gamma\gamma} \gtrsim 1.3 \times 10^{-9}~\text{GeV}^{-1}$ for a measurement time of 30 days. Future upgrades, including pressure tuning of the effective refractive index and implementation of a Fabry-P\'erot cavity, could extend the accessible mass range and improve sensitivity, establishing WISPFI as a scalable platform to explore previously inaccessible regions of the axion parameter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01221v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Josep Maria Batllori, Michael Frosz, Dieter Horns, Marios Maroudas</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
