<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO</link>
    <description>astro-ph.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 05:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Tracer Correlated Stacking: A Novel Way to Discover Anisotropy in nano-Hz Stochastic Gravitational Wave Background</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01499</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01499v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The isotropic stochastic gravitational wave background (SGWB) generated by a population of supermassive black hole binaries (BHBs) provides a unique window into their cosmic evolution. In addition to the isotropic power spectrum, the anisotropic component of the signal carries additional information about the supermassive black holes (BHs) and host galaxy connection. The measurement of this signal is usually carried out by angular power spectra, which is only a sufficient measure for a Gaussian and statistically isotropic distribution. In contrast, the contribution from supermassive BHBs in nano-hertz SGWB will be hosted by fewer massive galaxies, making the nano-hertz background anisotropic and non-Gaussian. As a result, the performance of angular power spectra in extracting the underlying physics is limited. In this work, we propose a novel technique called the Multi-Tracer Correlated Stacking, which enables the detection of anisotropies in the SGWB by stacking the signal from regions of the sky with tracers of BHs such as active galactic nucleus (AGNs), quasars, bright galaxies, etc., that can be mapped up to high redshift. We demonstrate this technique on a simulated supermassive BHBs distribution using an AGN catalog, which maps the underlying matter distribution approximately up to redshift $z=5$. This stacking technique uniquely distinguishes between isotropic and anisotropic distributions of SGWB source, surpassing the capabilities of angular power spectrum-based methods in detecting anisotropic signals. This highlights the effectiveness of this technique in detecting anisotropic SGWB signals and in the future, this technique can play a crucial role in its discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01499v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohit Raj Sah, Suvodip Mukherjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Turbulence: the Small-Scale Limit of the Cold-Dark-Matter Power Spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01524v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The matter power spectrum, $P(k)$, is one of the fundamental quantities in the study of large-scale structure in cosmology. Here, we study its small-scale asymptotic limit, and show that for cold dark matter in $d$ spatial dimensions, $P(k)$ has a universal $k^{-d}$ asymptotic scaling with the wave-number $k$, for $k \gg k_{\rm nl}$, where $k_{\rm nl}^{-1}$ denotes the length scale at which non-linearities in gravitational interactions become important. We propose a theoretical explanation for this scaling, based on a non-perturbative analysis of the system's phase-space structure. Gravitational collapse is shown to drive a turbulent phase-space flow of the quadratic Casimir invariant, where the linear and non-linear time scales are balanced, and this balance dictates the $k$ dependence of the power spectrum. A parallel is drawn to Batchelor turbulence in hydrodynamics, where large scales mix smaller ones via tidal interactions. The $k^{-d}$ scaling is also derived by expressing $P(k)$ as a phase-space integral in the framework of kinetic field theory, which is analysed by the saddle-point method; the dominant critical points of this integral are precisely those where the time scales are balanced. The coldness of the dark-matter distribution function -- its non-vanishing only on a $d$-dimensional sub-manifold of phase-space -- underpins both approaches. The theory is accompanied by $1\mathrm{D}$ Vlasov--Poisson simulations, which confirm it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01524v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yonadav Barry Ginat, Michael L. Nastac, Robert J. Ewart, Sara Konrad, Matthias Bartelmann, Alexander A. Schekochihin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological constraints from the Minkowski functionals of the BOSS CMASS galaxy sample</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01698v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For the first time, we develop a simulation-based model for the Minkowski functionals (MFs) of large-scale structure, which allows us to extract the full information available from the MFs (including both the Gaussian and non-Gaussian part), and apply it to the BOSS DR12 CMASS galaxy sample. Our model is based on high-fidelity mock galaxy catalogs constructed from the \textsc{Abacus}\textsc{Summit} simulations using the halo occupation distribution (HOD) framework, which include the redshift-space distortions and Alcock-Paczynski distortions, incorporate survey realism, including survey geometry and veto masks, and account for angular plus radial selection effects. The cosmological and HOD parameter dependence of the MFs is captured with a neural network emulator trained from the galaxy mocks with various cosmological and HOD parameters. To benchmark the constraining power of the MFs, we also train an emulator for the galaxy 2-point correlation function (2PCF) using the same pipeline. Having validated our approach through successful parameter recovery tests on both internal and external mocks, including non-HOD forward models of the halo-galaxy connection, we apply our forward model to analyze the CMASS data in the redshift range $0.45&lt;z&lt;0.58$. We find the MFs provide stronger constraints on the cosmological parameters than the 2PCF. The combination of the two gives $\omega_{\rm cdm}=0.1172^{+0.0020}_{-0.0023}$, $\sigma_8=0.783\pm 0.026$, and $n_s=0.966^{+0.019}_{-0.015}$, which are tighter by a factor of 2.0, 1.9, and 1.6 than the 2PCF alone. The derived constraint $f\sigma_8=0.453 \pm 0.016$ is also improved by a factor of 1.9, compared to the 2PCF, and agrees well with Planck 2018 predictions and other results from a series of studies in the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01698v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Liu, Enrique Paillas, Carolina Cuesta-Lazaro, Georgios Valogiannis, Wenjuan Fang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid-z: Enhancing Kilo-Degree Survey bright galaxy sample photometric redshifts with deep learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01942</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01942v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We employ deep learning (DL) to improve photometric redshifts (photo-$z$s) in the Kilo-Degree Survey Data Release 4 Bright galaxy sample (KiDS-Bright DR4). This dataset, used as a foreground for KiDS lensing and clustering studies, is flux-limited to $r&lt;20$ mag with mean $z=0.23$ and covers 1000 deg$^2$. Its photo-$z$s were previously derived with artificial neural networks from the ANNz2 package, trained on the Galaxy And Mass Assembly (GAMA) spectroscopy. Here we considerably improve over these previous redshift estimations by building a DL model, Hybrid-z, which combines four-band KiDS images with nine-band magnitudes from KiDS+VIKING. The Hybrid-z framework provides photo-$z$s for KiDS-Bright, with negligible mean residuals of O($10^{-4}$) and scatter at the level of $0.014(1+z)$ -- reduction by 20% over the previous nine-band derivations with ANNz2. We check our photo-$z$ model performance on test data drawn from GAMA, as well as from other KiDS-overlapping wide-angle spectroscopic surveys, namely SDSS, 2dFLenS, and 2dFGRS. We find stable behavior and consistent improvement over ANNz2 throughout. We finally apply Hybrid-z trained on GAMA to the entire KiDS-Bright DR4 sample of 1.2 million galaxies. For these final predictions, we design a method of smoothing the input redshift distribution of the training set, to avoid propagation of features present in GAMA, related to its small sky area and large-scale structure imprint in its fields. Our work paves the way towards the best-possible photo-$z$s achievable with machine learning for any galaxy type both for the final KiDS-Bright DR5 data and for future deeper imaging, such as from the Legacy Survey of Space and Time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01942v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anjitha John William, Priyanka Jalan, Maciej Bilicki, Wojciech A. Hellwing, Hareesh Thuruthipilly, Szymon J. Nakoneczny</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Wave Mountains: current-carrying domain walls</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01542</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01542v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Domain wall (DW) networks may have formed in the early universe following the spontaneous breaking of a discrete symmetry. Notably, several particle physics models predict the existence of current-carrying DWs, which can capture and store particles as zero modes on it. In this study, we demonstrate that gravitational waves (GWs) generated by current-carrying DWs with fermionic zeromodes exhibit a novel feature: an additional peak in the GW spectrum resembling mountains, arising from metastable topological remnants, which we term ``spherons.'' This distinct signature could be detectable in upcoming GW observatories such as LISA and ET. The results suggest that DW networks in beyond Standard Model scenarios could emit GW signals that are significantly stronger and with greater detectability than previously expected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01542v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anish Ghoshal, Yu Hamada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microlensing of lensed supernovae Zwicky &amp; iPTF16geu: constraints on the lens galaxy mass slope and dark compact object fraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01578</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01578v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: To date, only two strongly lensed type Ia supernovae (SNIa) have been discovered with an isolated galaxy acting as the lens: iPTF16geu and SN Zwicky. The observed image fluxes for both lens systems were inconsistent with predictions from a smooth macro lens model. A potential explanation for the anomalous flux ratios is microlensing: additional (de)magnification caused by stars and other compact objects in the lens galaxy. In this work, we combine observations of iPTF16geu and SN Zwicky with simulated microlensing magnification maps, leveraging their standardizable candle properties to constrain the lens galaxy mass slope, $\eta$, and the fraction of dark compact objects, $f_{\rm dc}$. The resulting mass slopes are $\eta = 1.70 \pm 0.07$ for iPTF16geu and $\eta = 1.81 \pm 0.10$ for SN Zwicky. Our results indicate no evidence for a population of dark compact objects, placing upper limits at the $95\%$ confidence level of $f_{\rm dc} &lt; 0.25$ for iPTF16geu and $f_{\rm dc} &lt; 0.47$ for SN Zwicky. Assuming a constant fraction of dark compact objects for both lensed SNe, we obtain $f_{\rm dc} &lt; 0.19$. These results highlight the potential of strongly lensed SNIa to probe the innermost parts of lens galaxies and learn about compact matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01578v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikki Arendse, Edvard M\"ortsell, Luke Weisenbach, Erin Hayes, Stephen Thorp, Suhail Dhawan, Ariel Goobar, Sacha Guerrini, Jacob Osman Hjortlund, Joel Johansson, Cameron Lemon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining the Gravitational Wave Speed in the Early Universe via Gravitational Cherenkov Radiation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01910</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01910v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Scalar particles traveling faster than a subluminal gravitational wave generate gravitons via gravitational Cherenkov radiation. In this paper, we investigate graviton production by the primordial plasma within the framework of modified gravity in the early Universe, generating a relic graviton background. We find that for the minimal model, where only the speed of gravitational waves is modified and a standard model plasma minimally couples to gravity, the relic graviton background can be enhanced by several orders of magnitude, but still agrees with the Big Bang Nucleosynthesis (BBN) bound in most cases. Moreover, we also find that for Horndeski theories, such as Galileon theory, the relic background produced by the thermalized scalar field can reach significant amplitudes, exceeding the BBN bound for a region of the parameter space. By requiring the relic graviton background to remain consistent with the BBN constraint, we derive limits on the gravitational wave speed at early times in these modified gravity theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01910v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paola C. M. Delgado, Alexander Ganz, Chunshan Lin, Roxane Th\'eriault</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lyman-alpha resonant-line radiative transfer in expanding media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01928v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Lyman-alpha (LyA) line of atomic hydrogen encodes crucial information about both the intrinsic sources and surrounding environments of star-forming regions throughout the Universe. Due to the complexity of resonant scattering, analytic solutions remain scarce, with most studies focusing on idealized, static configurations. However, observations of LyA emitting galaxies consistently reveal signatures of outflows, imprinted through red-peak dominance in spectral line profiles. In this paper, we derive novel analytic solutions for resonant-line radiative transfer in moving media, specifically homologous-like cloud expansion and unbounded cosmological flows, which capture the main physics of velocity gradients. To validate these analytic solutions and identify regimes where diffusion-based assumptions hold, we introduce a robust Gridless Monte Carlo Radiative Transfer (GMCRT) method. By integrating optical depths exactly in the comoving frame, GMCRT updates photon frequencies continuously to account for Doppler shifts induced by velocity gradients. We demonstrate excellent consistency between GMCRT and our analytic solutions in regimes where diffusion approximations apply. At higher velocities or lower optical depths, discrepancies highlight the limitations of simplified formalisms. We also provide scaling relations for a point source in a cloud with a maximum-to-thermal velocity ratio beta = V_max / v_th, as modifying the standard dependence on line centre optical depth of (atau_0)^1/3 by additional factors, e.g. characteristic escape frequency scale as x_esc ~ beta^1/3, force multipliers as M_F ~ beta^-1/3, and trapping time as t_trap ~ beta^-2/3. Our work complements numerical simulations by improving physical intuition about nonstatic environments when interpreting LyA observations and guiding future subgrid prescriptions in galaxy formation models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01928v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aaron Smith (UT Dallas), Kevin Lorinc (UT Dallas), Olof Nebrin (Stockholm), Bing-Xin Lao (Princeton)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dwarf Galaxies in the TNG50 Field: connecting their Star-formation Rates with their Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01946v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The dwarf galaxies comparable to the LMC and SMC, with stellar masses $7.5 &lt;{\rm log}(M_{\ast}/M_{\odot})&lt;9.5$, are found in a diversity of environments and have long quenching timescales. The way this phenomenon results from the dwarfs' halo properties or their locations in the large-scale structure is not well understood. We study the star-formation rates of dwarfs in the Illustris TNG50 simulation across different environments, focusing on the dwarfs having host halos with virial masses $9 &lt; {\rm log}(M_{200}/M_{\odot}) &lt; 11.5$, which we demonstrate are in the field as opposed to dwarf satellites in hosts with ${\rm log}(M_{200}/M_{\odot}) \geq 11.5$. Our field dwarf sample is heterogeneous, consisting of primary (central) galaxies, with smaller numbers of secondaries and dwarf galaxies that are on backsplash orbits around massive galaxies. We quantify the field dwarfs' large-scale environmental using the tidal index $\Theta_1$ and the distance to the nearest massive galaxy ${\rm d_{massive}}$, and we study how the quenched fraction and star-formation histories are correlated with these metrics. Those with ${\rm d_{massive}}&gt;1.5$ Mpc and $\Theta_1&lt;0$ are well isolated, with only $\sim 1\%$ being quenched. The quenched field dwarfs are in majority the backsplash dwarfs located in the neighborhood of cluster-scale halos. We discover a two-halo galactic conformity signal that arises from the tendency of the quenched dwarfs, particularly the backsplash sample, to have a quenched massive galaxy as a neighbor. We attribute the low quenched fractions of the simulated LMC/SMC analogs in the field to the locations of their low-mass hosts in the sparse large-scale environment, which predominate over the relatively small number of backsplash and pre-processed dwarfs in denser environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01946v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joy Bhattacharyya, Annika H. G. Peter, Alexie Leauthaud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A comparison of Bayesian and frequentist confidence intervals in the presence of a late Universe degeneracy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.16349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.16349v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Hubble tension is a problem in one-dimensional (1D) posteriors, since local $H_0$ determinations are only sensitive to a single parameter. Projected 1D posteriors for $\Lambda$CDM cosmological parameters become more non-Gaussian with increasing effective redshift when the model is fitted to redshift-binned data in the late Universe. We explain mathematically why this non-Gaussianity arises and show using observational Hubble data (OHD) that Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) marginalisation leads to 1D posteriors that fail to track the $\chi^2$ minimum at $68\%$ confidence level in high redshift bins. To gain a second perspective, we resort to profile likelihoods as a complementary technique. Doing so, we observe that $z \gtrsim 1$ cosmic chronometer (CC) data currently prefers a non-evolving (constant) Hubble parameter over a Planck-$\Lambda$CDM cosmology at $\sim 2 \sigma$. Within the Hubble tension debate, it is imperative that subsamples of data sets with differing redshifts yield similar $H_0$ values. In addition, we confirm that MCMC degeneracies observed in 2D posteriors are not due to curves of constant $\chi^2$. Finally, on the assumption that the Planck-$\Lambda$CDM cosmological model is correct, using profile likelihoods we confirm a $&gt;2 \sigma$ discrepancy with Planck-$\Lambda$CDM in a combination of CC and baryon acoustic oscillations (BAO) data beyond $ z \sim 1.5$. This confirms a discrepancy reported earlier with fresh methodology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.16349v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eoin \'O Colg\'ain, Saeed Pourojaghi, M. M. Sheikh-Jabbari, Darragh Sherwin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmography of the Local Universe by Multipole Analysis of the Expansion Rate Fluctuation Field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.12291v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish a relationship between the multipoles of the expansion rate fluctuation field $\eta,$ which capture in an accurate way deviations from isotropy in the redshift-distance relation, and the multipoles of the covariant cosmographic parameters-Hubble $\mathbb{H}_o$, deceleration $\mathbb{Q}_o$, jerk $\mathbb{J}_o$, and curvature $\mathbb{R}_o$. These parameters, derived from the third-order expansion of the luminosity distance with respect to redshift in a generic spacetime, provide model-independent insight into the geometry and symmetries of the cosmic line element without requiring the Cosmological Principle. Moreover, we demonstrate that although this approach is fully nonperturbative and does not rely on concepts such as peculiar velocities, it has the potential to constrain the motion of the matter frame at the observer's position relative to the cosmic microwave background. We use two analytical axisymmetric models, motivated by observational evidence, to test the formalism and the effectiveness of the third-order expansion of the luminosity distance. These models also help to predict the precision with which future surveys, like the Zwicky Transient Facility, will constrain the covariant cosmographic parameters in the local ($z&lt;0.1$) Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.12291v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2024/09/069</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP09(2024)069</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Basheer Kalbouneh, Christian Marinoni, Roy Maartens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weak-Lensing Shear-Selected Galaxy Clusters from the Hyper Suprime-Cam Subaru Strategic Program: I. Cluster Catalog, Selection Function and Mass--Observable Relation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11966</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11966v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the first step toward deriving cosmological constraints through the abundances of galaxy clusters selected in a $510\,\mathrm{deg}^2$ weak-lensing aperture mass map, constructed with the Year-Three shear catalog from the Hyper Suprime-Cam Subaru Strategic Program. We adopt a conservative source galaxy selection to construct a sample of $129$ weak-lensing peaks with a signal-to-noise ratio above $4.7$. We use semi-analytical injection simulations to derive the selection function and the mass--observable relation of our sample. These results take into account complicated uncertainties associated with weak-lensing measurements, such as the non-uniform survey depth and the complex survey geometry, projection effects from uncorrelated large-scale structures, and the intrinsic alignment of source galaxies. We also propose a novel modeling framework to make parts of the mass--observable relation insensitive to assumed cosmological parameters. Such a framework not only offers a great computational advantage to cosmological studies, but can also benefit future astrophysical studies using shear-selected clusters. Our results are an important step toward utilizing these cluster samples that are constructed nearly independent of any baryonic assumptions in upcoming deep-and-wide lensing surveys from the Vera Rubin Observatory, Euclid, and the Nancy Grace Roman Space Telescope.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11966v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kai-Feng Chen, I-Non Chiu, Masamune Oguri, Yen-Ting Lin, Hironao Miyatake, Satoshi Miyazaki, Surhud More, Takashi Hamana, Markus M. Rau, Tomomi Sunayama, Sunao Sugiyama, Masahiro Takada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extending the cosmic distance ladder two orders of magnitude with strongly lensed Cepheids, carbon AGB, and RGB stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09162</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09162v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Gravitational lensing by galaxy clusters can create extreme magnification near the cluster caustics, thereby enabling detection of individual luminous stars in high-redshift background galaxies. Those stars can include non-explosive standard candles such as Cepheid variables, carbon stars in the asymptotic giant branch, and stars at the tip of the red-giant branch out to $z\lesssim1$. A large number of such detections, combined with modeling of the magnification affecting these stars (including microlensing), opens the door to extending the distance range of these standard candles by two orders of magnitude, thereby providing a check on the distances derived from supernovae. Practical measurement of a distance modulus depends on measuring the apparent magnitude of a ``knee feature'' in the lensed luminosity function due to the great abundance of red-giant-branch stars just below the luminosity of the tip of the red-giant branch. As a bonus, strongly lensed stars detected in deep exposures also provide a robust method of mapping small dark-matter substructures, detections of which also cluster around the critical curves of small-scale dark matter halos.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09162v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. M. Diego, S. P. Willner, J. M. Palencia, R. A. Windhorst</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No massive black holes in the Milky Way halo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02386v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The gravitational wave detectors have unveiled a population of massive black holes that do not resemble those observed in the Milky Way and whose origin is debated. According to one possible explanation, these black holes may have formed from density fluctuations in the early Universe (primordial black holes), and they should comprise from several to 100% of dark matter to explain the observed black hole merger rates. If such black holes existed in the Milky Way dark matter halo, they would cause long-timescale gravitational microlensing events lasting years. The previous experiments were not sufficiently sensitive to such events. Here we present the results of the search for long-timescale microlensing events among the light curves of nearly 80 million stars located in the Large Magellanic Cloud that were monitored for 20 years by the OGLE survey. We did not find any events with timescales longer than one year, whereas all shorter events detected may be explained by known stellar populations. We find that compact objects in the mass range from $1.8 \times 10^{-4}$ to $6.3\,M_{\odot}$ cannot compose more than 1% of dark matter, and those in the mass range from $1.3 \times 10^{-5}$ to $860\,M_{\odot}$ cannot make up more than 10% of dark matter. Thus, primordial black holes in this mass range cannot simultaneously explain a significant fraction of dark matter and gravitational wave events.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02386v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41586-024-07704-6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature 632, 749 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>P. Mroz, A. Udalski, M. K. Szymanski, I. Soszynski, L. Wyrzykowski, P. Pietrukowicz, S. Kozlowski, R. Poleski, J. Skowron, D. Skowron, K. Ulaczyk, M. Gromadzki, K. Rybicki, P. Iwanek, M. Wrona, M. Ratajczak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Black Hole Mimickers: Electromagnetic and Gravitational Signatures of AdS Black Shells</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.08062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.08062v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study electromagnetic and gravitational properties of AdS black shells (also referred to as AdS black bubbles) -- a class of quantum gravity motivated black hole mimickers, that in the classical limit are described as ultra compact shells of matter. We find that their electromagnetic properties are remarkably similar to black holes. We then discuss the extent to which these objects are distinguishable from black holes, both for intrinsic interest within the black shell model, and as a guide for similar efforts in other sub-classes of exotic compact objects (ECOs). We study photon rings and lensing band characteristics, relevant for very large baseline inteferometry (VLBI) observations, as well as gravitational wave observables -- quasinormal modes in the eikonal limit and the static tidal Love number for non-spinning shells -- relevant for ongoing and upcoming gravitational wave observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.08062v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.024007</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 111, 024007 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Suvendu Giri, Ulf Danielsson, Luis Lehner, Frans Pretorius</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter Catalyzed Baryon Destruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18472v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: WIMP-type dark matter may have additional interactions that break baryon number, leading to induced nucleon decays which are subject to direct experimental constraints from proton decay experiments. In this work, we analyze the possibility of continuous baryon destruction, deriving strong limits from the dark matter accumulating inside old neutron stars, as such a process leads to excess heat generation. We construct the simplest particle dark matter model that breaks baryon and lepton numbers separately but conserves $B-L$. Virtual exchange by DM particles in this model results in di-nucleon decay via $nn\to n\bar\nu$ and $np\to ne^+$ processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18472v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.023005</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 111, 023005 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yohei Ema, Robert McGehee, Maxim Pospelov, Anupam Ray</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regularizing infrared divergences in de Sitter spacetime: Loops, dimensional regularization, and cutoffs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.07610v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Correlation functions of light scalar fields in de Sitter spacetime, computed via standard perturbation theory, often exhibit secular growth characterized by time-dependent divergent terms in the form of powers of $\ln a(t)$, where $a(t)$ is the scale factor describing cosmic expansion. It is widely believed that loop corrections further enhance this secular growth. We argue that this is not necessarily the case: Loop corrections can be systematically handled using standard perturbative techniques, such as dimensional regularization, without introducing new $\ln a(t)$ terms. We focus on a canonical massless scalar field $\varphi$ with self-interactions described by a potential $\mathcal{V}(\varphi)$, and analyze correlation functions represented by diagrams with a single vertex and an arbitrary number of loops. In this framework, infrared divergences can be systematically eliminated with counterterms at each order in perturbation theory, leading to loop-corrected correlation functions that are indistinguishable from their tree-level forms, with no secular growth from loops. Furthermore, adopting a Wilsonian perspective, we explore the role of cutoffs in computing loop corrections within effective field theory and identify the effective potential $\mathcal{V}_{\rm eff}(\varphi)$, which guarantees cutoff-independent observables. We conclude that when infrared comoving cutoffs are used to regularize loop integrals, time-dependent Wilsonian coefficients are necessary to maintain cutoff-free correlation functions. Neglecting this time dependence results in secular growth from loops.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.07610v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.123536</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 123536 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Javier Huenupi, Ellie Hughes, Gonzalo A. Palma, Spyros Sypsas</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
