<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO</link>
    <description>astro-ph.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 02:03:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A formula for the area of a triangle: Useless, but explicitly in Deep Sets form</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.22786v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Any permutation-invariant function of data points $\vec{r}_i$ can be written in the form $\rho(\sum_i\phi(\vec{r}_i))$ for suitable functions $\rho$ and $\phi$. This form - known in the machine-learning literature as Deep Sets - also generates a map-reduce algorithm. The area of a triangle is a permutation-invariant function of the locations $\vec{r}_i$ of the three corners $1\leq i\leq 3$. We find the polynomial formula for the area of a triangle that is explicitly in Deep Sets form. This project was motivated by questions about the fundamental computational complexity of $n$-point statistics in cosmology; that said, no insights of any kind were gained from these results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.22786v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Connor Hainje, David W. Hogg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Eras Tour: Mapping the Eras of Taylor Swift to the Cosmological Eras of the Universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.22795v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper explores an unexpected yet compelling parallel between the evolution of the universe, as described by cosmological eras, and the artistic evolution of Taylor Swift, delineated by her distinct album eras. By mapping key characteristics and transitions in the universe's history to corresponding themes and milestones in Swift's career, I offer a novel perspective on both. I culminate with predictions for Swift's future work and dare to ask a question of cosmic importance: Could Taylor Swift's thirteenth album hold the secret to the universe's ultimate destiny?</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.22795v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jane C. Bright</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum signatures and decoherence during inflation from deep subhorizon perturbations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23150v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In order to shed light on the quantum-to-classical transition of the primordial perturbations in single field inflation, we investigate the decoherence and associated quantum corrections to the correlation functions of superhorizon scalar curvature perturbations. The latter are considered as an open quantum system which undergoes quantum decoherence induced by a time-dependent environment of deep subhorizon tensorial modes through the trilinear interactions predicted by General Relativity. We first prove that, in full generality, a time dependent subhorizon environment can be relevant for decoherence during inflation, by considering derivativeless interactions, which, in our case, give the most important results. For the first time, the time dependence of the environment is properly taken into account by modifying the quantum master equation. Important non-Markovian effects pop up, instead, when dealing with derivative interactions. We adopt a possible way to treat them which has been recently proposed and seems well suited for our case. Our results show that when considering the interplay between derivativeless and derivative interactions, decoherence is slowed down. This underlines the importance of accounting for all the interactions in open quantum-system calculations in an inflationary setting. We finally compute the quantum corrections to cosmological correlation functions, by solving the transport equations induced by the quantum master equation. We also compare the results to the solutions obtained by an alternative method previously used in the literature. We observe a resummation of the quantum corrections to the power-spectrum, which is a general property of quantum master equations. We extend these results to the bispectrum, showing a decay of this correlation function in time which is analogous to the one found, previously, for the power-spectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23150v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francescopaolo Lopez, Nicola Bartolo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Constraints on Interacting Dark Energy from DESI DR2 BAO Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23225v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In its second data release (DR2), the \textit{Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument} (DESI) publicly released measurements of Baryon Acoustic Oscillations (BAO) from over 13.1 million galaxies and 1.6 million quasars, covering the redshift range $0.295 \leq z \leq 2.330$. In this work, we investigate the impact of this new dataset on dark sector interaction models, which are motivated by non-gravitational interactions between dark energy (DE) and dark matter (DM), commonly referred to as interacting dark energy models (IDE). We focus on two frameworks: the traditional IDE model and the recently proposed sign-switching Interacting model (S-IDE), aiming to derive new and robust constraints on both scenarios. After carefully selecting the sample for the joint analysis, ensuring compatibility among the data without significant tension, our main results indicate that both models can alleviate the $H_0$ tension, reducing it to moderate tension approximately $2.7\sigma$. The IDE model shows compatibility with the latest $S_8$ constraints from cosmic shear surveys, while the S-IDE model predicts lower values of $S_8$, which align with alternative perspectives on the $S_8$ tension. For the traditional IDE model, we derive new bounds for the coupling parameter, marking the strongest constraints to date through geometric measurements. This highlights the crucial role that supernova samples can play in refining these constraints. For the S-IDE model, we find mild evidence (approximately $2\sigma$) for the coupling parameter, suggesting a potential interaction between DE and DM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23225v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emanuelly Silva, Miguel A. Sabogal, Mateus S. Souza, Rafael C. Nunes, Eleonora Di Valentino, Suresh Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Constraints on Dark Photon Dark Matter with a Millimeter-Wave Dielectric Haloscope</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23354v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dark matter remains one of the most profound and unresolved mysteries in modern physics. To unravel its nature, numerous haloscope experiments have been implemented across various mass range. However, very few haloscope experiments conducted within millimeter-wave frequency range, which is in the favored mass region for well-motivated dark matter candidates. Here we designed and constructed a millimeter-wave dielectric haloscope featuring a dark matter detector composed of dielectric disks and a mirror. Using this setup, we conducted a search for dark photon dark matter and found no evidence for its existence. Our results established new constraints on the kinetic mixing parameter in the mass range from $387.72$ to $391.03$ $\mu eV$, improving the existing limits by two orders of magnitude. With future enhancements, our system has the potential to explore new parameter space for dark photon as well as axion dark matter within millimeter-wave frequency range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23354v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guoqing Wei, Diguang Wu, Runqi Kang, Qingning Jiang, Man Jiao, Xing Rong, Jiangfeng Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Sunyaev-Zel'dovich effect observations of galaxy cluster cavities with the Square Kilometre Array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23599v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Galaxy cluster X-ray cavities are inflated by relativistic jets that are ejected into the intracluster medium by active galactic nuclei (AGN). AGN jets prevent predicted cooling flow establishment at the cluster centre, and while this process is not well understood in existing studies, simulations have shown that the heating mechanism will depend on the type of gas that fills the cavities. Thermal and non-thermal distributions of electrons will produce different cavity Sunyaev Zel'dovich (SZ) effect signals, quantified by the 'suppression factor' f. This paper explores potential enhancements to prior constraints on the cavity gas type by simulating suppression factor observations with the Square Kilometre Array (SKA). Cluster cavities across different redshifts are observed to predict the optimum way of measuring f in future observations. We find that the SKA can constrain the suppression factor in the cavities of cluster MS 0735.6+7421 (MS0735) in as little as 4 h, with a smallest observable value of f~0.42. Additionally, while the SKA may distinguish between possible thermal or non-thermal suppression factor values within the cavities of MS0735 if it observes for more than 8 h, determining the gas type of other clusters will likely require observations at multiple frequencies. The effect of cavity line of sight (LOS) position is also studied, and degeneracies between LOS position and the measured value of f are found. Finally, we find that for small cavities (radius &lt; 80 kpc) at high redshift (z~1.5), the proposed high frequencies of the SKA (23.75-37.5 GHz) will be optimal, and that including MeerKAT antennas will improve all observations of this type.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23599v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/pasa.2025.13</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Publications of the Astronomical Society of Australia. 2025;42:e031</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sophia Geris, Yvette Perrott</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calibration requirements for Epoch of Reionization 21-cm signal observations -- IV. Bias and variance with time and frequency correlated residual gains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23825v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Observation of multifrequency angular power spectrum of the redshifted 21-cm brightness temperature fluctuation from the neutral hydrogen holds the key to understand the structure formation and its evolution during the reionization and post-reionization era. A major challenge in observing the neutral hydrogen arises from presence of strong foreground signals in the frequency range of interest. Mitigating the direct effect of foregrounds are being addressed through various techniques in literature. An additional second order effect arises, in presence of foreground, with limited accuracy in time and frequency dependent gain calibrations. This manifests as the residual gain and bandpass error in the observed data, introduces bias and increases uncertainty in the estimates of multifrequency angular power spectrum. In this work, we present an analytic method to estimate the bias and excess uncertainty in the estimates of multifrequency angular power spectrum in presence of residual gain and bandpass errors. We use this framework to estimate the effect of these errors for detection of redshifted 21-cm emission from a redshift of $\sim 8$ with the upcoming SKA1-Low. Due to the high baseline density at the required range of angular multipoles, the SKA1-Low is found to be a tuned instrument for the redshifted 21-cm signal detection. We find that, there are scenario with residual gain and bandpass errors where there can be significant bias in these estimates. Certain foreground mitigation strategies, is expected to reduce a part of the bias. The detailed study of different aspects of gain and bandpass errors and their relative effects are discussed. We find, with assumed models of gain and bandpass errors, signal detection is possible at this redshift with $128$ hours of observations. However, to achieve this one needs to have better calibration accuracy than present day interferometers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23825v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saikat Gayen, Jais Kumar, Prasun Dutta, Khandakar Md Asif Elahi, Samir Choudhuri, Nirupam Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modelling Gaia photometry signals of dark halos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23868</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23868v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We use the framework of microlensing to show that observations of binary systems, such as those made by {\it Gaia}, combined with follow-up weak lensing measurements, can provide a means to probe halos of exotic matter, possibly clumped around compact objects such as black holes. This could potentially cover a broad range of physical scenarios - from dark matter mini-halos to black holes with bosonic configurations around them, known as hair. Assuming that light can freely propagate through the halo of the exotic matter, the companion star will produce characteristic, sizable lensing signatures due to the deviation from a central gravitational potential. The signature of the multiple images, the magnification and the light-curve could be the smoking gun of such structures. We discuss how the precise observations of the {\it Gaia} survey offer an opportunity to search for new, yet undiscovered fundamental fields interacting gravitationally with baryons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23868v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George Pappas, Ippocratis D. Saltas, Laurent Eyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hint of $r\simeq 0.01$ after DESI DR2 ?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23918</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23918v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the report by BICEP and Keck collaborations, the tensor-to-scalar ratio is $r_{0.05}&lt;0.036$ (95\% C.L.) and $ &lt;1.3\sigma$ non-zero (with pre-DESI BAO data). However, recent datasets have significantly shifted the bestfit values of relevant $\Lambda$CDM cosmological parameters, and thus possibly alter the amplitude of lensing B-mode spectrum, which would affect the search for $r$. Here, the joint analysis of Planck and BICEP/Keck data with DESI DR2 reveals that the lower bound of $r_{0.05}$ is $2.0\sigma$ and $2.1\sigma$ non-zero for PantheonPlus and DES-Y5, respectively, and the bestfit $r$ is $r_{0.05}\simeq 0.01$. The results are consistent with those with DESI DR1, but slightly strengthened. There might be still systematic uncertainties in B-mode measurements due to the foreground contamination, however, our work is to not say what about the value of $r$, but emphasize that the detection for $r$ is model-dependent and depends potentially on our insight into the dark universe, highlighting the important role of cosmological surveys in comprehending our very early universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23918v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Wang, Yun-Song Piao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distortion of the CMB spectrum by the first molecules of the Dark Ages</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23971</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23971v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The formation of first stars and galaxies at the Cosmic Dawn had been preceded by the chain of primordial chemistry reactions during Dark Ages which generated first molecules, mostly H$_2$, HD, and HeH$^+$, so crucial for first stars to emerge. These molecules absorbed and scattered CMB quanta this way distorting CMB spectrum. Estimate how much bound-bound transitions between the rovibrational levels of H$_2$, HD, and HeH$^+$ molecules contribute to the distortion of CMB spectrum in the standard $\Lambda$CDM cosmology. We describe the kinetics of the formation of the first molecules with system of 166 chemical reactions involving 20 reagents. The system of differential equations is solved to describe the processes of spontaneous and collisional transitions between rovibrational levels of H$_2$, HD, and HeH$^+$ molecules. The populations of rovibrational levels and optical thickness of the gas in transition lines between these levels were used to estimate the differential brightness produced by the first molecules on the cosmic microwave background. It is shown that the signal from the first molecules in the standard $\Lambda$CDM cosmology takes the form of an absorption profile in the CMB spectrum and originates from the Dark Ages. H$_2$ shows multiple peaks, peaking at $\sim 10^{-3}$ Jy/sr between 50-120 GHz, with absorption from $300&gt;z&gt;200$. HD has double peaks, reaching $\sim 10^{-5}$ Jy/sr between 40-70 GHz, with absorption from $300&gt;z&gt;30$. HeH$^+$ has no features, peaks at $\sim 10^{-7}$ Jy/sr between 200-800 GHz, and absorbs mainly from $100&gt;z&gt;4$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23971v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yurii Kulinich, Bohdan Novosyadlyj</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TOPz: photometric redshifts using template fitting applied to GAMA survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24039</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24039v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context. Accurate photometric redshift (photo-z) estimation is crucial for cosmological and galaxy evolution studies, especially with the advent of large-scale photometric surveys.
  Aims. We develop a photo-z estimation code called TOPz (Tartu Observatory Photo-z) and apply it to the GAMA photometric catalogue.
  Methods. TOPz employs a Bayesian template-fitting approach to estimate photo-z from marginalised redshift posteriors. Using nine-band photometric data from the GAMA project, we assess the accuracy of TOPz by comparing its photo-z estimates to available spectroscopic redshifts. We generate synthetic galaxy spectra using the CIGALE software and run template set optimisation. We improve the photometry by applying flux and flux uncertainty corrections. An analytical prior is then imposed on the resulting posteriors to refine the redshift estimates.
  Results. The photo-z estimates produced by TOPz show good agreement with the spectroscopic redshifts. We demonstrate the redshift accuracy across various magnitude bins and test how the flux corrections and posteriors reflect the actual uncertainty of the estimates. We show that the TOPz results are consistent with those obtained from other photo-z codes applied to the same data set. Additionally, TOPz estimates stellar masses as a by-product, comparable to those calculated by other methods. We made the GAMA photo-z catalogue and all the codes and scripts used for the analysis and figures publicly available.
  Conclusions. TOPz is an advanced photo-z estimation code that integrates flux corrections, physical priors, and template set optimisation to provide state-of-the-art photo-z among competing template-based redshift estimators. Future work will focus on incorporating additional photometric data and applying the TOPz algorithm to J-PAS narrow-band survey, further validating and enhancing its capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24039v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Tempel, J. Laur, Z. R. Jones, R. Kipper, L. J. Liivam\"agi, D. Pandey, G. Sakteos, A. Tamm, A. N. Triantafyllaki, T. Tuvikene</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A direct detection method of galaxy intrinsic ellipticity-gravitational shear correlation in non-linear regimes using self-calibration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24269v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Intrinsic alignment (IA) of galaxies is a challenging source of contamination in the Cosmic shear (GG) signals. The galaxy intrinsic ellipticity-gravitational shear (IG) correlation is generally the most dominant component of such contamination for cross-correlating redshift bins. The self-calibration (SC) method is one of the most effective techniques to mitigate such contamination from the GG signal. In a photometric survey, the SC method first extracts the galaxy number density-galaxy intrinsic ellipticity (gI) correlation from the observed galaxy-galaxy lensing correlation using the redshift dependence of lens-source pairs. The IG correlation is computed through a scaling relation using the gI correlation and other lensing observables. We extend the SC method beyond the linear regime by modifying its scaling relation which can account for the non-linear galaxy bias model and various IA models. In this study, we provide a framework to detect the IG correlation for the redshift bins for source galaxies for the proposed year 1 survey of the Rubin Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST Y1). We tested the method for the tidal alignment and tidal torquing (TATT) model of IA and we found that the scaling relation is accurate within 10$\%$ and 20$\%$ for cross-correlating and auto-correlating redshift bins, respectively. Hence the suppression of IG contamination can be accomplished with a factor of 10 and 5, for cross-correlating and auto-correlating redshift bins, respectively. We tested the method's robustness and found that the suppression of IG contamination by a factor of 5 is still achievable for all combinations of cross-correlating bins even with the inclusion of a moderate amount of uncertainties on IA and bias parameters, respectively. [Abridged]</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24269v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Avijit Bera, Leonel Medina Varela, Vinu Sooriyaarachchi, Mustapha Ishak, Carter Williams, The LSST Dark Energy Science Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Early time solution as an alternative to the late time evolving dark energy with DESI DR2 BAO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24343</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24343v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) provided constraints on the expansion history from their Data Release 2 (DR2). The DESI baryon acoustic oscillation (BAO) measurements are well described by a flat $\Lambda$CDM model, but the preferred parameters are in mild ($2.3\sigma$) tension with those determined from the cosmic microwave background (CMB). The DESI collaboration has already explored a variety of solutions to this tension relying on variations in the late-time evolution of dark energy. Here we test an alternative -- the introduction of an ``early dark energy'' (EDE) component. We find that EDE models can alleviate the tension, though they lead to differences in other cosmological parameters that have observational implications. Particularly the EDE models that fit the acoustic datasets prefer lower $\Omega_m$, higher $H_0$, $n_s$ and $\sigma_8$ in contrast to the late-time solutions. We discuss the current status and near-future prospects for distinguishing amongst these solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24343v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Chaussidon, M. White, A. de Mattia, R. Gsponer, S. Ahlen, D. Bianchi, D. Brooks, T. Claybaugh, S. Cole, A. Cuceu, A. de la Macorra, P. Doel, S. Ferraro, A. Font-Ribera, J. E. Forero-Romero, E. Gazta\~naga, S. Gontcho A Gontcho, G. Gutierrez, J. Guy, C. Hahn, H. K. Herrera-Alcantar, K. Honscheid, M. Ishak, D. Kirkby, T. Kisner, A. Kremin, M. Landriau, L. Le Guillou, M. E. Levi, R. Miquel, J. Moustakas, G. Niz, W. J. Percival, F. Prada, I. P\'erez-R\`afols, A. J. Ross, G. Rossi, E. Sanchez, D. Schlegel, H. Seo, D. Sprayberry, M. Walther, B. A. Weaver</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of structure growth during dark energy domination: insights from the cross-correlation of DESI galaxies with CMB lensing and galaxy magnification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24385v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We use a Hybrid Effective Field Theory (HEFT) model to constrain the evolution of low-redshift $(z\lesssim0.4)$ matter fluctuations by cross-correlating DESI Bright Galaxy Survey (BGS) legacy imaging with the latest CMB lensing maps from Planck and ACT. Our tomographic BGS analysis finds that the evolution and amplitude of matter fluctuations align with CMB-conditioned $\Lambda$CDM predictions. When including DESI Baryon Acoustic Oscillation (BAO) measurements we obtain $\sigma_8 = 0.876^{+0.051}_{-0.067}$ from BGS alone. Jointly analyzing BGS and Luminous Red Galaxy (LRG) cross-correlations with the same CMB lensing maps yields $\sigma_8 = 0.791\pm0.021$. As a complementary approach we isolate the galaxy magnification signal from the cross-correlation of non-overlapping BGS and LRG photometric redshift bins, ruling out the null-magnification hypothesis at $11\sigma$. For the first time, we constrain structure growth from the (finite-difference calibrated) galaxy magnification signal and find $\sigma_8=0.720\pm0.047\,\,({\rm stat.})\pm0.050\,\,({\rm sys.})$ when adopting a linear bias model and including BAO data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24385v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noah Sailer, Joseph DeRose, Simone Ferraro, Shi-Fan Chen, Rongpu Zhou, Martin White, Joshua Kim, Mathew Madhavacheril</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gamma Lines and Dark Matter from Anomaly Cancellation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17976</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17976v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We discuss a simple theory for physics beyond the Standard Model where a Majorana dark matter is predicted from anomaly cancellation. We discuss in detail the minimal theory where the baryon number is a local symmetry spontaneously broken at the low scale. The correlation between the cosmological constraints on the dark matter relic density, the direct detection and collider bounds is investigated. We discuss in great detail the gamma lines from dark matter annihilation showing the possibility to test these predictions in the near future at gamma-ray telescopes such as CTA. We investigate all processes contributing to the total photon flux from dark matter annihilation and point out the unique features that can be used to test this theory for dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17976v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.055027</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review D 111, 055027 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hridoy Debnath, Pavel Fileviez Perez, Kevin Gonzalez-Quesada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalizing the Bogoliubov vs Boltzmann approaches in gravitational production</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21877v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the spectral behavior of scalar fluctuations generated by gravity during inflation and the subsequent reheating phase. We consider a non-perturbative Bogoliubov treatment within the context of pure gravitational reheating. We compute both long and short-wavelength spectra, first for a massless scalar field, revealing that the spectral index in part of the infrared (IR) regime varies between $-6$ and $-3$, depending on the post-inflationary equation of state (EoS), $0\leq w_\phi\leq1$. Furthermore, we study the mass-breaking effect of the IR spectrum by including finite mass, $m_{\chi}$, of the daughter scalar field. We show that for $m_{\chi}/H_{\rm e} \gtrsim 3/2$, where $H_{\rm e}$ is the Hubble parameter during inflation, the IR spectrum of scalar fluctuations experiences exponential mass suppression, while for smaller masses, $m_{\chi}/\He&lt;3/2$, the spectrum remains flat in the IR regime regardless of the post-inflationary EoS. For any general EoS, we also compute a specific IR scale, $k_m$, of fluctuations below which the IR spectrum will suffer from this finite mass effect. In the UV regime, oscillations of the inflaton background lead to interference terms that explain the high-frequency oscillations in the spectrum. Interestingly, we find that for any EoS, $1/9 \lesssim w_\phi \lesssim 1$, the spectral behavior turns out to be independent of the EoS, with a spectral index $ -6$. We have compared this Bogoliubov treatment for the UV regime to perturbative computations with solutions to the Boltzmann equation and found an agreement between the two approaches for any EoS, $0 \lesssim w_\phi \lesssim 1$. We also explore the relationship between the gravitational reheating temperature and the reheating EoS employing the non-perturbative analytic approach, finding that reheating can occur for $w_\phi \gtrsim 0.6$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21877v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayan Chakraborty, Simon Clery, Md Riajul Haque, Debaprasad Maity, Yann Mambrini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the structure of open clusters: geometric vs geomantic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.22800v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Understanding our place in the universe is an eternal quest. Through the analysis of the 3D structures of 66 nearby open clusters using Gaia DR3 data, we discovered an intriguing pattern: most clusters show their elongation directions pointing at the Sun, suggesting that the Solar System might just be the universe's favorite spot, a cosmic feng shui hotspot! This surprising result hints at a subtle blend of geometry and geomancy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.22800v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lu Li, Zhengyi Shao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Universe is Odd</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.22839v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The cosmological principle posits that the universe does not exhibit any specific preference for position or direction. However, it remains unclear whether the universe has a distinct preference for parity: whether certain properties are more likely to be classified as even or odd. In this study, we analyze the largest available galaxy group catalogs to explore this hypothesis: specifically, whether the number of galaxies within a galaxy group or cluster is more likely to be odd or even. Our findings convincingly indicate that the universe indeed favors odd numbers, with results achieving a significance level well above the $4.1-\sigma$ threshold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.22839v1</guid>
      <category>physics.pop-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiyin Shen, Nan Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Formation of the Little Red Dots from the Core-collapse of Self-interacting Dark Matter Halos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23710v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a statistical study on the formation and growth of black holes (BHs) seeded by gravothermal core-collapse of self-interacting dark matter (SIDM) halos at high redshifts, using a semi-analytical framework based on Monte-Carlo merger trees. We demonstrate that BH formation via gravothermal collapse naturally occurs in high-concentration halos at a characteristic mass scale determined by the SIDM cross section, and only during the early Universe. This mechanism is particularly promising for explaining the abundance of little red dots (LRDs) -- a population of early, apparently galaxy-less active galactic nuclei hosting supermassive BHs. By incorporating this seeding process with simplified models of BH growth and mergers, we successfully reproduce the observed LRD mass function for moderately large cross sections of $\sigma_{0m} \sim 30 \mathrm{cm^2\,g^{-1}}$ and $\omega \sim 80\,\mathrm{km\,s^{-1}}$, intriguingly consistent with independent local constraints derived from galaxy rotation curves. Our results highlight the potential of high-redshift BH statistics as a complementary probe for constraining SIDM models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23710v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fangzhou Jiang (Peking University Kavli Institute), Zixiang Jiang (Peking University Department of Astronomy), Haonan Zheng (Peking University Kavli Institute), Luis C. Ho (Peking University Kavli Institute, Peking University Department of Astronomy), Kohei Inayoshi (Peking University Kavli Institute), Xuejian Shen (MIT Department of Physics, MIT Kavli Institute), Mark Vogelsberger (MIT Kavli Institute), Wei-Xiang Feng (Tsinghua University Department of Physics)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Written in the Stars: How your (pens and) papers decide the fate of the arXiverse</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23957</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23957v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We all love the ecstasy that comes with submitting papers to journals or arXiv. Some have described it as yeeting their back-breaking products of labor into the void, wishing they could never deal with them ever again. The very act of yeeting papers onto arXiv contributes to the expansion of the arXiverse; however, we have yet to quantify our contribution to the cause. In this work, I investigate the expansion of the arXiverse using the arXiv astro-ph submission data from 1992 to date. I coin the term "the arXiverse constant", $a_0$, to quantify the rate of expansion of the arXiverse. I find that astro-ph as a whole has a positive $a_0$, but this does not always hold true for the six subcategories of astro-ph. I then investigate the temporal changes in $a_0$ for the astro-ph subcategories and astro-ph as a whole, from which I infer the fate of the arXiverse.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23957v1</guid>
      <category>physics.pop-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joanne Tan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Environmental effects in stellar mass gravitational wave sources I: Expected fraction of signals with significant dephasing in the dynamical and AGN channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24084</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24084v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the first overview of the expected quantity of signals which will showcase significant gravitational wave phase shifts caused by astrophysical environments, considering the upcoming A+ and A\# LIGO/Virgo/KAGRA, Cosmic Explorer and Einstein Telescope detectors. We construct and analyse two general families of dephasing prescriptions with extensions to eccentric sources, as well as collect five specific prescriptions for the fundamental smoking gun physical mechanisms at play in the dynamical and AGN formation channel for stellar mass binary black holes: Roemer delays, tidal forces and hydrodynamical interactions. We compute the expected fraction of signals containing astrophysical dephasing, as a function of environmental properties and based on observed distributions of binary parameters. We find that next generation detectors can expect to find environmental effects in hundreds of detected signals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24084v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenz Zwick, J\'anos Tak\'atsy, Pankaj Saini, Kai Hendriks, Johan Samsing, Christopher Tiede, Connar Rowan, Alessandro A. Trani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Swift analysis of the Eras tour set list and implications for astrophysics research (Taylor's version)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24188v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Popular culture plays a significant role in shaping public interest in science, and Taylor Swift's discography frequently incorporates astrophysics terminology. This study examines the occurrence of astrophysics-related words in her lyrics and their representation in the Eras tour set list. By analyzing the frequency of words in Swift's total discography, we identify that astrophysics is promoted the most within her most recent album, The Tortured Poets Department, whereas songs from Midnights promoted astrophysics the most throughout the Eras tour. We catagorize words into various disciplines of astrophysics and find that multimessenger astronomy is promoted the most, both in Swift's total discography and throughout the Eras tour. We perform Taylor expansion and predict $12 \pm 5$ astrophysical terms in Swift's next album. This analysis offers a unique perspective on the intersection of music and science, revealing how Swift's artistry may unintentionally promote interest in different fields of astrophysics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24188v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.ed-ph</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sophie L. Newman, Ana Sainz de Murieta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resolving the baryon assymmetry with RATS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24319v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Current leading theories of physics such as the Big Bang, the standard model of particle physics, and general relativity suggest that the universe should contain an equal amount of matter and antimatter. Yet observations have found a disproportionately large amount of matter, a phenomenon known as the baryon assymmetry problem. Since century-old established theories are traditionally impossible to refute, the only possible explanation is that the remaining antimatter is hidden in plain sight and remains to be observed. We propose the existence of anti-stars to solve the baryon assymetry in our new Reasonable Antimatter Theory of Stars (RATS). In this context, the RATS will create a framework to resolve the traditional tension between observers and theorists, and thus contribute to the peaceful and collaborative spirit of astronomy. Our method is the firing of neurons in our brains, typically known as a thought experiment. We still have no idea why or how this works, but it must be good because most of science was created this way. Our results are the result of our methods, which result in some text and the resulting conclusions. In order to encourage the reader to reach the end of this short paper, we do not want to spoil the conclusions here. Instead, the conclusions will conclude the paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24319v1</guid>
      <category>physics.pop-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Josiek, M. Bernini-Peron, G. Gonz\'alez-Tor\`a, R. R. Lefever, E. C. Sch\"osser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modified cosmology though spacetime thermodynamics and generalized mass-to-horizon entropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24355v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work we apply the gravity-thermodynamics approach for the case of generalized mass-to-horizon entropy, which is a two-parameter extension of Bekenstein-Hawking entropy that arises from the extended mass-to-horizon relation, that is in turn required in order to have consistency with the Clausius relation. We extract the modified Friedmann equations and we obtain an effective dark energy sector arising from the novel terms. We derive analytical solutions for the dark energy density parameter, the dark energy equation-of-state parameter, and the deceleration parameter, and we show that the Universe exhibits the usual thermal history with the succession of matter and dark energy epochs. Additionally, depending on the value of the entropy parameters, the dark energy equation-of-state parameter can either lie in the phantom regime at high redshifts entering into the quintessence regime at small redshifts, or it can lie in the quintessence regime at high redshifts and experience the phantom-divide crossing at small redshifts, while in the far future in all cases it asymptotically obtains the cosmological constant value $-1$. Finally, we perform observational confrontation with Supernova Type Ia (SNIa), Cosmic Chronometers (CC) and Baryonic Acoustic Oscillations (BAO) datasets, showing that the scenario is in agreement with observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24355v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Spyros Basilakos, Andreas Lymperis, Maria Petronikolou, Emmanuel N. Saridakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixed Warm Dark Matter Constraints using Milky Way Satellite Galaxy Counts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18917v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Warm dark matter has been strongly constrained in recent years as the sole component of dark matter. However, a less-explored alternative is that dark matter consists of a mixture of warm and cold dark matter (MWDM). In this work, we use observations of Milky Way satellite galaxies to constrain MWDM scenarios where the formation of small-scale structure is suppressed either by generic thermal relic warm dark matter or a sterile neutrino produced through the Shi-Fuller mechanism. To achieve this, we model satellite galaxies by combining numerical simulations with semi-analytical models for the subhalo population, and use a galaxy--halo connection model to match galaxies onto dark matter subhalos. By comparing the number of satellites predicted by MWDM models to the observed satellite population from the Dark Energy Survey and Pan-STARRS1, we constrain the fraction of warm dark matter, $f_{\rm WDM}$, as a function of its mass, $m_{\rm WDM}$. We exclude dark matter being composed entirely of thermal relic warm dark matter with $m_{\rm WDM} \leq 6.6 $ keV at a posterior ratio of 10:1, consistent with previous works. However, we find that warm dark matter with smaller mass is allowed when mixed with cold dark matter, and that the $f_{\rm WDM}$ constraints strengthen with decreasing $m_{\rm WDM}$ until they plateau at $f_{\rm WDM} \lesssim 0.45 $ for $m_{\rm WDM} \lesssim 1.5$ keV. Likewise, in the case of a sterile neutrino with mass of 7 keV produced through the Shi-Fuller mechanism, we exclude a fraction of $f_{\nu_s} \lesssim 0.45$, independent of mixing angle. Our results extend constraints on MWDM to a region of parameter space that has been relatively unconstrained with previous analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18917v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.063079</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 111, 063079 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Chin Yi Tan, Ariane Dekker, Alex Drlica-Wagner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining Reionization with Ly{\alpha} Damping-Wing Absorption in Galaxy Spectra: A Machine Learning Model Based on Reionization Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07377v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, NIRSpec PRISM/CLEAR observations by JWST have begun providing rest-frame UV continuum measurements of galaxies at $z\gtrsim7$, revealing signatures of Ly$\alpha$ damping-wing (DW) absorption by the intergalactic medium (IGM). We develop a methodology to constrain the global ionization fraction of the IGM $(Q_{\rm HII})$ using low-resolution spectra, employing the random forest classification (RFC) method. We construct mock spectra using the simulated galaxies and the IGM from the Cosmic Dawn II simulation and train RFC models to estimate $Q_{\rm HII}$ at the redshift of the source and to detect the presence of a damped Ly$\alpha$ absorber (DLA). We find that individual galaxy spectra with spectral bins between 1220 and 1270 {\AA} and with signal-to-noise ratios greater than 20 can place tight constraints on $Q_{\rm HII}$, provided the UV continuum is accurately modeled. This method is particularly effective for the early phase of reionization ($Q_{\rm HII}&lt;50\%$), when the IGM opacity is high in the DW. As a demonstration, we apply our model to existing NIRSpec PRISM/CLEAR spectra, placing upper bounds of $Q_{\rm HII}=59.6\%$, $5.6\%$, and $18.5\%$ at $z=7.7,~9.4,$ and $10.6$, respectively, with $68\%$ confidence, though several modeling uncertainties remain to be discussed. These constraints favor late-starting reionization models, where $\gtrsim 80\%$ of the IGM is ionized after $z=8$. We conclude that high-SNR observations of carefully selected targets around $z\sim7-9$ can effectively constrain reionization models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07377v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hyunbae Park, Intae Jung, Hidenobu Yajima, Jenny Sorce, Paul R. Shapiro, Kyungjin Ahn, Pierre Ocvirk, Romain Teyssier, Gustavo Yepes, Ilian T. Iliev, Joseph S. W. Lewis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can tensor-scalar induced GWs dominate PTA observations ?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00228</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00228v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Observational constraints on small-scale primordial gravitational waves are considerably weaker than those on large scales. We focus on scenarios with significant primordial gravitational waves and curvature perturbations on small scales, studying the energy density spectrum of the second-order TSIGW. By leveraging current data from CMB, BAO, and PTA, combined with the SNR analysis of LISA, we can investigate how tensor-scalar induced gravitational waves affect observations on various scales, thus constraining the parameter space for primordial gravitational waves and curvature perturbations. The Bayes factor analysis suggests that TSIGW+PGW might be more likely to dominate current PTA observations compared to SMBHB.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00228v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Di Wu, Jing-Zhi Zhou, Yu-Ting Kuang, Zhi-Chao Li, Zhe Chang, Qing-Guo Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmic Polarisation Rotation from CMB Data: a Review for GR110</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.07743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.07743v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We provide an update on the work of di Serego Alighieri (2015), focusing on recent developments regarding constraints on Cosmic Polarization Rotation (CPR), also known as Cosmic Birefringence (CB), derived from Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) polarization data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.07743v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Gruppuso, Sperello di Serego Alighieri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gamma-Ray Bursts Calibrated from the Observational $H(z)$ Data in Artificial Neural Network Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10037</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10037v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we calibrate the luminosity relation of gamma-ray bursts (GRBs) from an Artificial Neural Network (ANN) framework for reconstructing the Hubble parameter \unboldmath{$H(z)$} from the latest observational Hubble data (OHD) obtained with the cosmic chronometers method in a cosmology-independent way. We consider the physical relationships between the data to introduce the covariance matrix and KL divergence of the data into the loss function and calibrate the Amati relation ($E_{\rm p}$--$E_{\rm iso}$) by selecting the optimal ANN model with the A219 sample and the J220 sample at low redshift. Combining the Pantheon+ type Ia supernovae (SNe Ia) sample and Baryon acoustic oscillations (BAOs) from Dark Energy Spectroscopy Instrument (DESI) with GRBs at high redshift in the Hubble diagram by Markov Chain Monte Carlo numerical method, we find that the $\Lambda$CDM model is preferred over the $w$CDM and CPL models with joint constraints by the Akaike Information Criterion and Bayesian Information Criterion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10037v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhen Huang, Zhiguo Xiong, Xin Luo, Guangzhen Wang, Yu Liu, Nan Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equivalence of Dark Energy Models: A Theoretical and Bayesian Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12915v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore the background equivalence among three dark energy models by constructing explicit mappings between dynamical dark energy (DDE), interacting dark energy (IDE), and running vacuum (RV). In our approach, the dark sector functions that characterize each model-such as the equation of state parameter $\bar{w}(a)$ for DDE, the interaction term $Q$ for IDE, and the functional form $\Lambda(H)$ for RV-are transformed into one another under specific assumptions. Extending previous work by von Marttens et al. (2020), we demonstrate that running vacuum models, characterized by $\Lambda(H) = a_0 + a_1 \dot{H} + a_2 H^2$, can be reinterpreted as an interacting dark energy model with $Q = 3H\gamma \hat{\rho}_c$, which in turn is equivalent to a dynamic dark energy model with an appropriately defined $\bar{w}(a)$. Using Bayesian analysis with Type Ia supernovae, Baryon Acoustic Oscillations, and Cosmic Chronometers, our observational constraints confirm that these theoretical equivalences hold at the background level. This study underscores the importance of seeking convergence in dark energy models, facilitating a better understanding of the dark sector.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12915v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.dark.2025.101901</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>David Tamayo, Erick Urquilla, Isidro G\'omez-Vargas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Status of early dark energy after DESI: the role of $\Omega_m$ and $r_s H_0$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15541v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The EDE model is one of the promising solutions to the long-standing Hubble tension. This paper investigates the status of several EDE models in light of recent BAO observations from the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) and their implications for resolving the Hubble tension. The DESI Y1 BAO results deviate from the CMB and Type Ia supernova (SNeIa) observations in their constraints on the matter density $\Omega_m$ and the product of the sound horizon and the Hubble constant $r_s H_0$. Meanwhile, these EDE models happen to tend towards this deviation. Therefore, in this work, it is found that DESI Y1 BAO results strengthen the preference for EDE models and help to obtain a higher $H_0$. Even considering the Pantheon+ observations for SNeIa, which have an opposite tendency, DESI still dominates the preference for EDE. This was unforeseen in past SDSS BAO measurements and therefore emphasizes the role of BAO and SNeIa measurements in Hubble tension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15541v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun-Qian Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DESI results: Hint towards coupled dark matter and dark energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10806v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate a scenario where a dark energy quintessence field $\phi$ with positive kinetic energy is coupled with dark matter. With two different self-interaction potentials for the field and a particular choice of the coupling function, we show explicitly how the observable effective equation of state parameter $w_{\rm eff}$ for the dark energy field crosses the phantom barrier ($w_{\rm eff} = -1$) while keeping the equation of state of the quintessence field $w_\phi &gt; -1$. With appropriate choices of parameters, $w_{\rm eff}$ crosses the phantom divide around redshift $z\sim 0.5$, transitioning from $w_{\rm eff} &lt;-1$ in the past to $w_{\rm eff}&gt;-1$ today. This explains DESI observations well. Our analysis reveals that the model remains consistent within the $2\sigma$ confidence intervals provided by DESI for several combinations of the scalar field parameters, highlighting its potential in explaining the dynamics of dark energy arising from a simple Yukawa-type long-range interaction in the dark sector. While the current findings offer a promising framework for interpreting DESI observations, future work, including a comprehensive Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) analysis, is necessary to constrain the parameter space further and strengthen the statistical significance of the results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10806v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amlan Chakraborty, Prolay K. Chanda, Subinoy Das, Koushik Dutta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Energy within the Generalized Uncertainty Principle in Light of DESI DR2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20896</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20896v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study, we modify the $\Lambda$CDM model by introducing a deformed algebra within the framework of the Generalized Uncertainty Principle (GUP). We formulate the modified Raychaudhuri equation, where new terms are introduced which describe dynamical pressure components. For the quadratic GUP model, we derive the Hubble function, which leads to a time-dependent dark energy model. The free parameters are determined using late-time observational data, the Pantheon+ SNIa sample, the cosmic chronometers, and the DESI 2025 BAO data. We find that the modified model introduce only one new additional degree of freedom compared to the $\Lambda$CDM model. The GUP-Modified $\Lambda$CDM model provides a better fit to the data than the undeformed theory. Furthermore, we compare the same model with the DESI 2024 BAO data and find that the Bayesian evidence becomes stronger with the inclusion of the DESI 2025 release.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20896v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andronikos Paliathanasis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The mass accretion history of dark matter haloes down to Earth mass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.15894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.15894v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We take advantage of the unprecedented dynamical range provided by the "Cosmic-Zoom" project to study the mass accretion history (MAH) of present-day dark matter haloes over the entire mass range present in the $\Lambda$CDM paradigm when the dark matter is made of weakly interacting massive particles of mass $100\ \mathrm{GeV}$. In particular, we complement previous studies by exploring the MAHs of haloes with mass from $10^8\ h^{-1}\mathrm{M_{\odot}}$ down to Earth mass, $10^{-6}\ h^{-1}\mathrm{M_{\odot}}$. The formation redshift of low-mass haloes anti-correlates weakly with mass, peaking at $z=3$ for haloes of mass $10^{-4}\ h^{-1}\mathrm{M_{\odot}}$. Even lower masses are affected by the free-streaming cutoff in the primordial spectrum of density fluctuations and form at lower redshift. We compare MAHs in our simulations with predictions from two analytical models based on the extended Press-Schechter theory (EPS), and three empirical models derived by fitting and extrapolating either results from cosmological $N$-body simulations or Monte Carlo realizations of halo growth. All models fit our simulations reasonably well over the mass range for which they were calibrated. While the empirical models match better for more massive haloes, $M&gt;10^{10}\ h^{-1}\mathrm{M_{\odot}}$, the analytical models do better when extrapolated down to Earth mass. At the higher masses, we explore the correlation between local environment density and MAH, finding that biases are relatively weak, with typical MAHs for haloes in extremely low-density and in typical regions differing by less than $20$ percent at high redshift. We conclude that EPS theory predicts the hierarchical build-up of dark matter haloes quite well over the entire mass range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.15894v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae003</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>MNRAS, 2024, 527, 11740-11750</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yizhou Liu, Liang Gao, Sownak Bose, Carlos S. Frenk, Adrian Jenkins, Volker Springel, Jie Wang, Simon D. M. White, Haonan Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerated by Dark Matter: a High-redshift Pathway to Efficient Galaxy-scale Star Formation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10900</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10900v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the local Universe, star formation is typically inefficient both globally and when considered as the fraction of gas converted into stars per local free-fall time. An important exception to this inefficiency is regions of high gravitational accelerations $g$, or equivalently surface densities $\Sigma = g/(\pi\,G)$, where stellar feedback is insufficient to overcome the self-gravity of dense gas clouds. In this paper, I explore whether dark matter can play an analogous role in providing the requisite accelerations on the scale of entire galaxies in the early cosmos. The key insight is that characteristic accelerations in dark matter halos scale as $(1+z)^2$ at fixed halo mass. I show this is sufficient to make dark matter the source of intense accelerations that might induce efficient star formation on galactic scales at cosmic dawn in sufficiently massive halos. The mass characterizing this regime scales as $(1+z)^{-6}$ and corresponds to a relatively constant comoving number density of $n(&gt;\!M_{\rm vir}) \approx 10^{-4}\,{\rm Mpc}^{-3}$ at $z \gtrsim 8$. For somewhat rarer halos, this model predicts stellar masses of $M_{\star} \sim 10^{9}\,M_{\odot}$ can form in regions that end up with sizes $\mathcal{O}(100\,{\rm pc})$ over $40\,{\rm Myr}$ time-scales at $z\approx 12-14$; these numbers compare well to measurements for some of the brightest galaxies at that epoch from James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) observations. Dark matter and standard cosmological evolution may therefore be crucial for explaining the surprisingly high levels of star formation in the early Universe revealed by JWST.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10900v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Boylan-Kolchin (The University of Texas at Austin)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal and nonthermal dark matters with gravitational neutrino reheating</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12450</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12450v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We have discussed in detail how neutrinos produced from inflaton solely through gravitational interaction can successfully reheat the universe. For this, we have introduced the well-known Type-I seesaw neutrino model. Depending on seesaw model parameters, two distinct reheating histories have been realized and dubbed as i) Neutrino dominating: Following the inflaton domination, the universe becomes neutrino dominated, and their subsequent decay concludes the reheating process, and ii) Neutrino heating: Despite being sub-dominant compared to inflaton energy, neutrinos efficiently heat the thermal bath and produce the radiation dominated universe. Imposing baryon asymmetric yield, the $\Delta N_{\rm eff}$ constraint at Big Bang Nucleosynthesis (BBN) considering primordial gravitational waves (PGW), we have arrived at the following constraints on reheating equation of state to lie within $0.5\lesssim w_\phi\lesssim1.0$. In these neutrino-driven reheating backgrounds, we further performed a detailed analysis of both thermal and non-thermal production of dark matter (DM), invoking two minimal models, namely the Higgs portal DM and classical QCD pseudo scalar axion. An interesting correlation between seemingly uncorrelated DM and Type-I seesaw parameters has emerged when confronting various direct and indirect observations. When DMs are set to freeze-in, freeze-out, or oscillate during reheating, new parameter spaces open, which could be potentially detectable in future experiments, paving an indirect way to look into the early universe in the laboratory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12450v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.063546</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Md Riajul Haque, Debaprasad Maity, Rajesh Mondal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Direct Detection of Higgsino Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07768</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07768v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: While much supersymmetric weakly interacting massive particle (WIMP) parameter space has been ruled out, one remaining important candidate is Higgsino dark matter. The Higgsino can naturally realize the "inelastic dark matter" scenario, where the scattering off a nucleus occurs between two nearly-degenerate states, making it invisible to WIMP direct detection experiments if the splitting is too large to be excited. It was realized that a "luminous dark matter" detection process, where the Higgsino upscatters in the Earth and subsequently decays into a photon in a large neutrino detector, offers the best sensitivity to such a scenario. We consider the possibility of adding a large volume of a heavy element, such as Pb or U, around the detector. We also consider the presence of U and Th in the Earth itself, and the effect of an enhanced high-velocity tail of the dark matter distribution due to the presence of the Large Magellanic Cloud. These effects can significantly improve the sensitivity of detectors such as JUNO, SNO+, KamLAND, and Borexino, potentially making it possible in the future to cover much of the remaining parameter space for this classic supersymmetric WIMP dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07768v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.055030</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 111, 055030 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Peter W. Graham, Harikrishnan Ramani, Samuel S. Y. Wong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermo-Coupled Early Dark Energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09747v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Early dark energy solutions to the Hubble tension introduce an additional scalar field which is frozen at early times but becomes dynamical around matter-radiation equality. In order to alleviate the tension, the scalar's share of the total energy density must rapidly shrink from $\sim 10\%$ at the onset of matter domination to $\ll 1\%$ by recombination. This typically requires a steep potential that is imposed $\textit{ad hoc}$ rather than emerging from a concrete particle physics model. Here, we point out an alternative possibility: a homogeneous scalar field coupled quadratically to a cosmological background of light thermal relics (such as the Standard Model neutrino) will acquire an effective potential which can reproduce the dynamics necessary to alleviate the tension. We identify the relevant parameter space for this "thermo-coupled" scenario and study its unique phenomenology at the background level, including the back-reaction on the neutrino mass. Follow-up numerical work is necessary to determine the constraints placed on the model by early-time measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09747v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.063551</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 111 (2024) 6, 063551</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Marc Kamionkowski, Anubhav Mathur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tidal disruption of "snow clouds" by unassociated stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17419</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17419v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It has been suggested that star-forming galaxies may host a substantial, dark reservoir of gas in the form of planetary-mass molecular clouds that are so cold that $\text{H}_{2}$ can condense. Here we investigate the process of tidal disruption of such "snow clouds" by close passage of field stars. We construct a suite of simulations using the hydrodynamic formalism introduced by Carter and Luminet, and use it to explore the properties of the resulting tidal debris. The debris streams are tiny structures that are highly over-pressured relative to the ambient interstellar medium (ISM). They are also unusual in their composition--initially consisting of cold, gaseous He together with $\text{H}_{2}$ "snowballs" that may be as much as a metre in size. Each stream expands and cools and is subsequently shocked as it plows through the ISM; the snowballs are gradually eroded by the shocked gas. Snowballs streaming through the shocked ISM create microstructured plasma that is somewhat reminiscent of the "scattering screens" revealed by radio-wave scintillation studies. However, the tidal disruption rate is too low to account for the observed number of scattering screens if, as we assume here, the stars and clouds have no prior physical association so that disruptions occur as a result of chance encounters between stars and clouds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17419v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/adb74b</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ApJ 982, 61 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Arthur G. Suvorov, Mark A. Walker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Short Note on Spin Magnetization in QGP</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05052v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We outline the theory of spin magnetization applicable to the QGP (quark-gluon plasma) epoch of the Universe. We show that a fully spin-polarized single flavor up-quark gas could generate a cosmic magnetic fields in excess of $10^{15}$ Tesla, far in excess of a possible upper limit to the primordial field. The complete multi component ferro-magnetized primordial fermion gas we consider consists of (five) nearly free electrically charged quarks, and leptons (electrons, muons, tau). We present details of how the magnetization is obtained using a grand partition function approach and point to the role of the nonrelativistic particle component. In the range of temperature 150 MeV to 500 MeV our results are also of interest to laboratory QGP experiments. We show that the required polarization capable to explain large scale structure magnetic fields observed has $1/T$ scaling in the limit of high $T$, and could be very small, at pico-scale. In the other limit, as temperature decreases in the expanding Universe, we show that any magnetic fields present before hadronization can be carried forward to below quark confinement condition temperature by polarization of electrons and muons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05052v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Steinmetz, Johann Rafelski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gray-body factors: Method matters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17240</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17240v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The calculation of gray-body factors is essential for understanding Hawking radiation and black hole thermodynamics. While the formalism developed by Chandrasekhar is effective for static black holes, it faces significant challenges in Kerr spacetimes, particularly in the superradiant regime, where a specific choice of coordinates introduces numerical inaccuracies. To address these limitations, an alternative method based on re-scaling radial coordinates and employing Frobenius-like expansions has been investigated. We compare the gray-body factors obtained for a near-maximally rotating black hole using both methods and find that the Chandrasekhar formalism systematically overestimates the values in the superradiant regime compared to well-established analytical results. Specifically, for a spin parameter of $a_* = 0.999$, the Chandrasekhar method yields values approximately twice as large as the correct result. Since this approach has been implemented in \texttt{BlackHawk}, we assess the impact of these discrepancies on constraints derived from gamma-ray observations of highly spinning primordial black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17240v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Arbey, Marco Calz\`a, Yuber F. Perez-Gonzalez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Running vacuum and H^4-inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01041v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent studies of QFT in cosmological spacetime indicate that the speeding up of the present universe may not just be associated with a rigid cosmological term but with a running one that evolves with the expansion rate: $\Lambda=\Lambda(H)$. This running is inherited from the cosmic evolution of the vacuum energy density (VED), $\rho_{\rm vac}$, which is sensitive to quantum effects in curved spacetime that ultimately trigger that running. The VED is a function of the Hubble rate and its time derivatives: $\rho_{\rm vac}=\rho_{\rm vac}(H, \dot{H},\ddot{H},...)$. Two nearby points of the cosmic evolution during the FLRW epoch are smoothly related as $\delta\rho_{\rm vac}\sim {\cal O}(H^2)$. In the very early universe, in contrast, the higher powers of the Hubble rate take over and bring about a period of fast inflation. They originate from quantum effects on the effective action of vacuum, which we compute. Herein we focus on the lowest possible power for inflation to occur: $H^4$. During the inflationary phase, $H$ remains approximately constant and very large. Subsequently, the universe enters the usual FLRW radiation epoch. This new mechanism (`RVM-inflation') is not based on any supplementary `inflaton' field, it is fueled by pure QFT effects on the dynamical background and is different from Starobinsky's inflation, in which $H$ is never constant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01041v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joan Sol\`a Peracaula, Cristian Moreno-Pulido, Alex Gonz\'alez-Fuentes</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
