<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO</link>
    <description>astro-ph.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 04:04:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Little Red Dots from Small-Scale Primordial Black Hole Clustering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07171</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07171v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) observations have identified a class of compact galaxies at high redshifts ($4 \lesssim z \lesssim 11$), dubbed "little red dots" (LRDs). The supermassive black holes (SMBHs) of $10^{5-8}{\rm\,M}_{\odot}$ in LRDs favor a heavy-seed origin. We propose a mechanism for their formation: Clusters of primordial black holes, formed through long-short mode coupling on small scales in the early Universe, undergo sequential mergers over extended timescales. This mechanism can evade cosmic microwave background distortions and result in heavy-seed SMBHs via runaway mergers. We employ Monte Carlo simulations to solve the Smoluchowski coagulation equation and determine the runaway merging timescale. The resulting stochastic gravitational wave background offers a distinct signature of this process, and the forming SMBHs can be highly spinning at their formation due to the spin residual of the cluster from tidal fields. This mechanism may explain the rapidly spinning SMBHs in LRDs under the assumption of obscured active galactic nuclei.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07171v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Borui Zhang, Wei-Xiang Feng, Haipeng An</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ten-dimensional neural network emulator for the nonlinear matter power spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07177</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07177v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present GokuNEmu, a ten-dimensional neural network emulator for the nonlinear matter power spectrum, designed to support next-generation cosmological analyses. Built on the Goku $N$-body simulation suite and the T2N-MusE emulation framework, GokuNEmu predicts the matter power spectrum with $\sim 0.5 \%$ average accuracy for redshifts $0 \leq z \leq 3$ and scales $0.006 \leq k/(h\,\mathrm{Mpc}^{-1}) \leq 10$. The emulator models a 10D parameter space that extends beyond $\Lambda$CDM to include dynamical dark energy (characterized by $w_0$ and $w_a$), massive neutrinos ($\sum m_\nu$), the effective number of neutrinos ($N_\text{eff}$), and running of the spectral index ($\alpha_\text{s}$). Its broad parameter coverage, particularly for the extensions, makes it the only matter power spectrum emulator capable of testing recent dynamical dark energy constraints from DESI. In addition, it requires only $\sim $2 milliseconds to predict a single cosmology on a laptop, orders of magnitude faster than existing emulators. These features make GokuNEmu a uniquely powerful tool for interpreting observational data from upcoming surveys such as LSST, Euclid, the Roman Space Telescope, and CSST.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07177v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanhui Yang, Simeon Bird, Ming-Feng Ho, Mahdi Qezlou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design and optimization of neural networks for multifidelity cosmological emulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07184v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate and efficient simulation-based emulators are essential for interpreting cosmological survey data down to nonlinear scales. Multifidelity emulation techniques reduce simulation costs by combining high- and low-fidelity data, but traditional regression methods such as Gaussian processes struggle with scalability in sample size and dimensionality. In this work, we present T2N-MusE, a neural network framework characterized by (i) a novel 2-step multifidelity architecture, (ii) a 2-stage Bayesian hyperparameter optimization, (iii) a 2-phase $k$-fold training strategy, and (iv) a per-$z$ principal component analysis strategy. We apply T2N-MusE to selected data from the Goku simulation suite, covering a 10-dimensional cosmological parameter space, and build emulators for the matter power spectrum over a range of redshifts with different configurations. We find the emulators outperform our earlier Gaussian process models significantly and demonstrate that each of these techniques is efficient in training neural networks or/and effective in improving generalization accuracy. We observe a reduction in validation error by more than a factor of five compared to previous work. This framework has been used to build the most powerful emulator for the matter power spectrum, GokuNEmu, and will also be used to construct emulators for other statistics in future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07184v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanhui Yang, Simeon Bird, Ming-Feng Ho, Mahdi Qezlou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Braneworld Dark Energy in light of DESI DR2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07193</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07193v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent observational results from the DESI collaboration reveal tensions with the standard $\Lambda$CDM model and favor a scenario in which dark energy (DE) decays over time. The DESI DR2 data also suggest that the DE equation of state (EoS) may have been phantom-like ($w &lt; - 1$) in the past, evolving to $w &gt; - 1$ at present, implying a recent crossing of the phantom divide at $w = - 1$. Scalar field models of DE naturally emerge in ultraviolet-complete theories such as string theory, which is typically formulated in higher dimensions. In this work, we investigate a class of thawing scalar field models propagating on a (4+1)-dimensional phantom braneworld, and demonstrate that their effective EoS exhibits a phantom-divide crossing. Alongside the Hubble parameter and EoS of DE, we also analyse the evolution of the Om diagnostic, and demonstrate that the time dependence of these quantities is in excellent agreement with the DESI DR2 observations. Furthermore, we perform a comprehensive parameter estimation using Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) sampling, and find that the $\chi^2$ values for all our models are remarkably close to that of the widely used CPL parametrisation, indicating that our models fit the data very well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07193v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Swagat S. Mishra, William L. Matthewson, Varun Sahni, Arman Shafieloo, Yuri Shtanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CLASS_SZ II: Notes and Examples of Fast and Accurate Calculations of Halo Model, Large Scale Structure and Cosmic Microwave Background Observables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07346</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07346v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: These notes are very much work-in-progress and simply intended to showcase, in various degrees of details (and rigour), some of the cosmology calculations that class_sz can do. We describe the class_sz code in C, Python and Jax. Based on the Boltzmann code class, it can compute a wide range of observables relevant to current and forthcoming CMB and Large Scale Structure surveys. This includes galaxy shear and clustering, CMB lensing, thermal and kinetic Sunyaev and Zeldovich observables, Cosmic Infrared Background, cross-correlations and three-point statistics. Calculations can be done either within the halo model or the linear bias model. For standard $\Lambda$CDM cosmology and extensions, class_sz uses high-accuracy cosmopower emulators of the CMB and matter power spectrum to accelerate calculations. With this, along with efficient numerical integration routines, most class_sz output can be obtained in less than 500 ms (CMB $C_\ell$'s or matter $P(k)$ take $\mathcal{O}(1\mathrm{ms})$), allowing for fast or ultra-fast parameter inference analyses. Parts of the calculations are "jaxified", so the software can be integrated into differentiable pipelines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07346v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boris Bolliet, Aleksandra Kusiak, Fiona McCarthy, Alina Sabyr, Kristen Surrao, Jens Chluba, Carmen Embil Villagra, Simone Ferraro, Boryana Hadzhiyska, Dongwon Han, J. Colin Hill, Juan Francisco Mac\'ias-P\'erez, Mathew Madhavacheril, Abhishek Maniyar, Yogesh Mehta, Shivam Pandey, Emmanuel Schaan, Blake Sherwin, Alessio Spurio Mancini, \'I\~nigo Zubeldia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The z=1.03 Merging Cluster SPT-CL J0356-5337: New Strong Lensing Analysis with HST and MUSE</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07404</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07404v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a strong lensing analysis and reconstruct the mass distribution of SPT-CL J0356-5337, a galaxy cluster at redshift z = 1.034. Our model supersedes previous models by making use of new multi-band HST data and MUSE spectroscopy. We identify two additional lensed galaxies to inform a more well-constrained model using 12 sets of multiple images in 5 separate lensed sources. The three previously-known sources were spectroscopically confirmed by Mahler et al. (2020) at redshifts of z = 2.363, z = 2.364, and z = 3.048. We measured the spectroscopic redshifts of two of the newly-discovered arcs using MUSE data, at z = 3.0205 and z = 5.3288. We increase the number of cluster member galaxies by a factor of three compared to previous work. We also report the detection of extended Lya emission from several background galaxies. We measure the total projected mass density of the two major sub-cluster components, one dominated by the BCG, and the other by a compact group of luminous red galaxies. We find M_BCG(&lt; 80kpc) = 3.93+0.21-0.14 * 10^13Msun and M_LRG(&lt; 80kpc) = 2.92+0.16 -0.23 * 10^13Msun, yielding a mass ratio of 1.35+0.16 -0.08. The strong lensing constraints offer a robust estimate of the projected mass density regardless of modelling assumptions; allowing more substructure in this line of sight does not change the results or conclusions. Our results corroborate the conclusion that SPT-CL J0356-5337 is dominated by two mass components, and is likely undergoing a major merger on the plane of the sky</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07404v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grace Smith, Guillaume Mahler, Kate Napier, Keren Sharon, Matthew Bayliss, Bradford Benson, Lindsey Bleem, Benjamin Floyd, Vittorio Ghirardini, Michael D. Gladders, Gourav Khullar, Tim Schrabback</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Euclid: Early Release Observations. Weak gravitational lensing analysis of Abell 2390</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07629v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Euclid space telescope of the European Space Agency (ESA) is designed to provide sensitive and accurate measurements of weak gravitational lensing distortions over wide areas on the sky. Here we present a weak gravitational lensing analysis of early Euclid observations obtained for the field around the massive galaxy cluster Abell 2390 as part of the Euclid Early Release Observations programme. We conduct galaxy shape measurements using three independent algorithms (LensMC, KSB+, and SourceXtractor++). Incorporating multi-band photometry from Euclid and Subaru/Suprime-Cam, we estimate photometric redshifts to preferentially select background sources from tomographic redshift bins, for which we calibrate the redshift distributions using the self-organising map approach and data from the Cosmic Evolution Survey (COSMOS). We quantify the residual cluster member contamination and correct for it in bins of photometric redshift and magnitude using their source density profiles, including corrections for source obscuration and magnification. We reconstruct the cluster mass distribution and jointly fit the tangential reduced shear profiles of the different tomographic bins with spherical Navarro--Frenk--White profile predictions to constrain the cluster mass, finding consistent results for the three shape catalogues and good agreement with earlier measurements. As an important validation test we compare these joint constraints to mass measurements obtained individually for the different tomographic bins, finding good consistency. More detailed constraints on the cluster properties are presented in a companion paper that additionally incorporates strong lensing measurements. Our analysis provides a first demonstration of the outstanding capabilities of Euclid for tomographic weak lensing measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07629v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Schrabback (Universit\"at Innsbruck, Institut f\"ur Astro- und Teilchenphysik, Technikerstr. 25/8, 6020 Innsbruck, Austria, Universit\"at Bonn, Argelander-Institut f\"ur Astronomie, Auf dem H\"ugel 71, 53121 Bonn, Germany), G. Congedo (Institute for Astronomy, University of Edinburgh, Royal Observatory, Blackford Hill, Edinburgh EH9 3HJ, UK), R. Gavazzi (Aix-Marseille Universit\'e, CNRS, CNES, LAM, Marseille, France, Institut d'Astrophysique de Paris, UMR 7095, CNRS, and Sorbonne Universit\'e, 98 bis boulevard Arago, 75014 Paris, France), W. G. Hartley (Department of Astronomy, University of Geneva, ch. d'Ecogia 16, 1290 Versoix, Switzerland), H. Jansen (Universit\"at Innsbruck, Institut f\"ur Astro- und Teilchenphysik, Technikerstr. 25/8, 6020 Innsbruck, Austria), Y. Kang (Department of Astronomy, University of Geneva, ch. d'Ecogia 16, 1290 Versoix, Switzerland), F. Kleinebreil (Universit\"at Innsbruck, Institut f\"ur Astro- und Teilchenphysik, Technikerstr. 25/8, 6020 Innsbruck, Austria), H. Atek (Institut d'Astrophysique de Paris, UMR 7095, CNRS, and Sorbonne Universit\'e, 98 bis boulevard Arago, 75014 Paris, France), E. Bertin (Universit\'e Paris-Saclay, Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e, CEA, CNRS, AIM, 91191, Gif-sur-Yvette, France), J. -C. Cuillandre (Universit\'e Paris-Saclay, Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e, CEA, CNRS, AIM, 91191, Gif-sur-Yvette, France), J. M. Diego (Instituto de F\'isica de Cantabria, Edificio Juan Jord\'a, Avenida de los Castros, 39005 Santander, Spain), S. Grandis (Universit\"at Innsbruck, Institut f\"ur Astro- und Teilchenphysik, Technikerstr. 25/8, 6020 Innsbruck, Austria), H. Hoekstra (Leiden Observatory, Leiden University, Einsteinweg 55, 2333 CC Leiden, The Netherlands), M. K\"ummel (Universit\"ats-Sternwarte M\"unchen, Fakult\"at f\"ur Physik, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit\"at M\"unchen, Scheinerstrasse 1, 81679 M\"unchen, Germany), L. Linke (Universit\"at Innsbruck, Institut f\"ur Astro- und Teilchenphysik, Technikerstr. 25/8, 6020 Innsbruck, Austria), H. Miyatake (Kobayashi-Maskawa Institute for the Origin of Particles and the Universe, Nagoya University, Chikusa-ku, Nagoya, 464-8602, Japan, Institute for Advanced Research, Nagoya University, Chikusa-ku, Nagoya, 464-8601, Japan, Kavli Institute for the Physics and Mathematics of the Universe), N. Okabe (Physics Program, Graduate School of Advanced Science and Engineering, Hiroshima University, 1-3-1 Kagamiyama, Higashi-Hiroshima, Hiroshima 739-8526, Japan, Hiroshima Astrophysical Science Center, Hiroshima University, 1-3-1 Kagamiyama, Higashi-Hiroshima, Hiroshima 739-8526, Japan, Core Research for Energetic Universe, Hiroshima University, 1-3-1, Kagamiyama, Higashi-Hiroshima, Hiroshima 739-8526, Japan), S. Paltani (Department of Astronomy, University of Geneva, ch. d'Ecogia 16, 1290 Versoix, Switzerland), M. Schefer (Department of Astronomy, University of Geneva, ch. d'Ecogia 16, 1290 Versoix, Switzerland), P. Simon (Universit\"at Bonn, Argelander-Institut f\"ur Astronomie, Auf dem H\"ugel 71, 53121 Bonn, Germany), F. Tarsitano (Department of Astronomy, University of Geneva, ch. d'Ecogia 16, 1290 Versoix, Switzerland), A. N. Taylor (Institute for Astronomy, University of Edinburgh, Royal Observatory, Blackford Hill, Edinburgh EH9 3HJ, UK), J. R. Weaver (Department of Astronomy, University of Massachusetts, Amherst, MA 01003, USA), R. Bhatawdekar (ESAC/ESA, Camino Bajo del Castillo, s/n., Urb. Villafranca del Castillo, 28692 Villanueva de la Ca\~nada, Madrid, Spain), M. Montes (Institute of Space Sciences), P. Rosati (Dipartimento di Fisica e Scienze della Terra, Universit\`a degli Studi di Ferrara, Via Giuseppe Saragat 1, 44122 Ferrara, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), S. Toft (Cosmic Dawn Center, Niels Bohr Institute, University of Copenhagen, Jagtvej 128, 2200 Copenhagen, Denmark), B. Altieri (ESAC/ESA, Camino Bajo del Castillo, s/n., Urb. Villafranca del Castillo, 28692 Villanueva de la Ca\~nada, Madrid, Spain), A. Amara (School of Mathematics and Physics, University of Surrey, Guildford, Surrey, GU2 7XH, UK), L. Amendola (Institut f\"ur Theoretische Physik, University of Heidelberg, Philosophenweg 16, 69120 Heidelberg, Germany), S. Andreon (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Brera, Via Brera 28, 20122 Milano, Italy), N. Auricchio (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), C. Baccigalupi (IFPU, Institute for Fundamental Physics of the Universe, via Beirut 2, 34151 Trieste, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy, INFN, Sezione di Trieste, Via Valerio 2, 34127 Trieste TS, Italy, SISSA, International School for Advanced Studies, Via Bonomea 265, 34136 Trieste TS, Italy), M. Baldi (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia, Universit\`a di Bologna, Via Gobetti 93/2, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), A. Balestra (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Padova, Via dell'Osservatorio 5, 35122 Padova, Italy), S. Bardelli (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), P. Battaglia (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), R. Bender (Max Planck Institute for Extraterrestrial Physics, Giessenbachstr. 1, 85748 Garching, Germany, Universit\"ats-Sternwarte M\"unchen, Fakult\"at f\"ur Physik, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit\"at M\"unchen, Scheinerstrasse 1, 81679 M\"unchen, Germany), A. Biviano (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy, IFPU, Institute for Fundamental Physics of the Universe, via Beirut 2, 34151 Trieste, Italy), E. Branchini (Dipartimento di Fisica, Universit\`a di Genova, Via Dodecaneso 33, 16146, Genova, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Genova, Via Dodecaneso 33, 16146, Genova, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Brera, Via Brera 28, 20122 Milano, Italy), M. Brescia (Department of Physics "E. Pancini", University Federico II, Via Cinthia 6, 80126, Napoli, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Capodimonte, Via Moiariello 16, 80131 Napoli, Italy), J. Brinchmann (Instituto de Astrof\'isica e Ci\^encias do Espa\c{c}o, Universidade do Porto, CAUP, Rua das Estrelas, PT4150-762 Porto, Portugal, Faculdade de Ci\^encias da Universidade do Porto, Rua do Campo de Alegre, 4150-007 Porto, Portugal, European Southern Observatory, Karl-Schwarzschild-Str.~2, 85748 Garching, Germany), S. Camera (Dipartimento di Fisica, Universit\`a degli Studi di Torino, Via P. Giuria 1, 10125 Torino, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Torino, Via P. Giuria 1, 10125 Torino, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio Astrofisico di Torino, Via Osservatorio 20, 10025 Pino Torinese), G. Ca\~nas-Herrera (European Space Agency/ESTEC, Keplerlaan 1, 2201 AZ Noordwijk, The Netherlands, Institute Lorentz, Leiden University, Niels Bohrweg 2, 2333 CA Leiden, The Netherlands, Leiden Observatory, Leiden University, Einsteinweg 55, 2333 CC Leiden, The Netherlands), G. P. Candini (Mullard Space Science Laboratory, University College London, Holmbury St Mary, Dorking, Surrey RH5 6NT, UK), V. Capobianco (INAF-Osservatorio Astrofisico di Torino, Via Osservatorio 20, 10025 Pino Torinese), C. Carbone (INAF-IASF Milano, Via Alfonso Corti 12, 20133 Milano, Italy), V. F. Cardone (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Roma, Via Frascati 33, 00078 Monteporzio Catone, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Roma, Piazzale Aldo Moro, 2 - c/o Dipartimento di Fisica, Edificio G. Marconi, 00185 Roma, Italy), J. Carretero (Centro de Investigaciones Energ\'eticas, Medioambientales y Tecnol\'ogicas, Port d'Informaci\'o Cient\'ifica, Campus UAB, C. Albareda s/n, 08193 Bellaterra), S. Casas (Institute for Theoretical Particle Physics and Cosmology), F. J. Castander (Institute of Space Sciences, Institut d'Estudis Espacials de Catalunya), M. Castellano (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Roma, Via Frascati 33, 00078 Monteporzio Catone, Italy), G. Castignani (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), S. Cavuoti (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Capodimonte, Via Moiariello 16, 80131 Napoli, Italy, INFN section of Naples, Via Cinthia 6, 80126, Napoli, Italy), K. C. Chambers (Institute for Astronomy, University of Hawaii, 2680 Woodlawn Drive, Honolulu, HI 96822, USA), A. Cimatti (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "Augusto Righi" - Alma Mater Studiorum Universit\`a di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), C. Colodro-Conde (Instituto de Astrof\'isica de Canarias, V\'ia L\'actea, 38205 La Laguna, Tenerife, Spain), C. J. Conselice (Jodrell Bank Centre for Astrophysics, Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Manchester, Oxford Road, Manchester M13 9PL, UK), L. Conversi (European Space Agency/ESRIN, Largo Galileo Galilei 1, 00044 Frascati, Roma, Italy, ESAC/ESA, Camino Bajo del Castillo, s/n., Urb. Villafranca del Castillo, 28692 Villanueva de la Ca\~nada, Madrid, Spain), Y. Copin (Universit\'e Claude Bernard Lyon 1, CNRS/IN2P3, IP2I Lyon, UMR 5822, Villeurbanne, F-69100, France), A. Costille (Aix-Marseille Universit\'e, CNRS, CNES, LAM, Marseille, France), F. Courbin (Institut de Ci\`encies del Cosmos, Instituci\'o Catalana de Recerca i Estudis Avan\c{c}ats), H. M. Courtois (UCB Lyon 1, CNRS/IN2P3, IUF, IP2I Lyon, 4 rue Enrico Fermi, 69622 Villeurbanne, France), M. Cropper (Mullard Space Science Laboratory, University College London, Holmbury St Mary, Dorking, Surrey RH5 6NT, UK), A. Da Silva (Departamento de F\'isica, Faculdade de Ci\^encias, Universidade de Lisboa, Edif\'icio C8, Campo Grande, PT1749-016 Lisboa, Portugal, Instituto de Astrof\'isica e Ci\^encias do Espa\c{c}o, Faculdade de Ci\^encias, Universidade de Lisboa, Campo Grande, 1749-016 Lisboa, Portugal), H. Degaudenzi (Department of Astronomy, University of Geneva, ch. d'Ecogia 16, 1290 Versoix, Switzerland), G. De Lucia (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy), H. Dole (Universit\'e Paris-Saclay, CNRS, Institut d'astrophysique spatiale, 91405, Orsay, France), M. Douspis (Universit\'e Paris-Saclay, CNRS, Institut d'astrophysique spatiale, 91405, Orsay, France), F. Dubath (Department of Astronomy, University of Geneva, ch. d'Ecogia 16, 1290 Versoix, Switzerland), X. Dupac (ESAC/ESA, Camino Bajo del Castillo, s/n., Urb. Villafranca del Castillo, 28692 Villanueva de la Ca\~nada, Madrid, Spain), S. Dusini (INFN-Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy), S. Escoffier (Aix-Marseille Universit\'e, CNRS/IN2P3, CPPM, Marseille, France), M. Farina (INAF-Istituto di Astrofisica e Planetologia Spaziali, via del Fosso del Cavaliere, 100, 00100 Roma, Italy), R. Farinelli (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), S. Farrens (Universit\'e Paris-Saclay, Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e, CEA, CNRS, AIM, 91191, Gif-sur-Yvette, France), F. Faustini (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Roma, Via Frascati 33, 00078 Monteporzio Catone, Italy, Space Science Data Center, Italian Space Agency, via del Politecnico snc, 00133 Roma, Italy), S. Ferriol (Universit\'e Claude Bernard Lyon 1, CNRS/IN2P3, IP2I Lyon, UMR 5822, Villeurbanne, F-69100, France), F. Finelli (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INFN-Bologna, Via Irnerio 46, 40126 Bologna, Italy), P. Fosalba (Institut d'Estudis Espacials de Catalunya, Institute of Space Sciences), M. Frailis (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy), E. Franceschi (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), M. Fumana (INAF-IASF Milano, Via Alfonso Corti 12, 20133 Milano, Italy), S. Galeotta (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy), K. George (Universit\"ats-Sternwarte M\"unchen, Fakult\"at f\"ur Physik, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit\"at M\"unchen, Scheinerstrasse 1, 81679 M\"unchen, Germany), W. Gillard (Aix-Marseille Universit\'e, CNRS/IN2P3, CPPM, Marseille, France), B. Gillis (Institute for Astronomy, University of Edinburgh, Royal Observatory, Blackford Hill, Edinburgh EH9 3HJ, UK), C. Giocoli (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), J. Gracia-Carpio (Max Planck Institute for Extraterrestrial Physics, Giessenbachstr. 1, 85748 Garching, Germany), A. Grazian (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Padova, Via dell'Osservatorio 5, 35122 Padova, Italy), F. Grupp (Max Planck Institute for Extraterrestrial Physics, Giessenbachstr. 1, 85748 Garching, Germany, Universit\"ats-Sternwarte M\"unchen, Fakult\"at f\"ur Physik, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit\"at M\"unchen, Scheinerstrasse 1, 81679 M\"unchen, Germany), S. V. H. Haugan (Institute of Theoretical Astrophysics, University of Oslo, P.O. Box 1029 Blindern, 0315 Oslo, Norway), J. Hoar (ESAC/ESA, Camino Bajo del Castillo, s/n., Urb. Villafranca del Castillo, 28692 Villanueva de la Ca\~nada, Madrid, Spain), W. Holmes (Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology, 4800 Oak Grove Drive, Pasadena, CA, 91109, USA), I. M. Hook (Department of Physics, Lancaster University, Lancaster, LA1 4YB, UK), F. Hormuth (Felix Hormuth Engineering, Goethestr. 17, 69181 Leimen, Germany), A. Hornstrup (Technical University of Denmark, Elektrovej 327, 2800 Kgs. Lyngby, Denmark, Cosmic Dawn Center), P. Hudelot (Institut d'Astrophysique de Paris, UMR 7095, CNRS, and Sorbonne Universit\'e, 98 bis boulevard Arago, 75014 Paris, France), K. Jahnke (Max-Planck-Institut f\"ur Astronomie, K\"onigstuhl 17, 69117 Heidelberg, Germany), M. Jhabvala (NASA Goddard Space Flight Center, Greenbelt, MD 20771, USA), B. Joachimi (Department of Physics and Astronomy, University College London, Gower Street, London WC1E 6BT, UK), E. Keih\"anen (Department of Physics and Helsinki Institute of Physics, Gustaf H\"allstr\"omin katu 2, 00014 University of Helsinki, Finland), S. Kermiche (Aix-Marseille Universit\'e, CNRS/IN2P3, CPPM, Marseille, France), M. Kilbinger (Universit\'e Paris-Saclay, Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e, CEA, CNRS, AIM, 91191, Gif-sur-Yvette, France), B. Kubik (Universit\'e Claude Bernard Lyon 1, CNRS/IN2P3, IP2I Lyon, UMR 5822, Villeurbanne, F-69100, France), K. Kuijken (Leiden Observatory, Leiden University, Einsteinweg 55, 2333 CC Leiden, The Netherlands), M. Kunz (Universit\'e de Gen\`eve, D\'epartement de Physique Th\'eorique and Centre for Astroparticle Physics, 24 quai Ernest-Ansermet, CH-1211 Gen\`eve 4, Switzerland), H. Kurki-Suonio (Department of Physics, P.O. Box 64, 00014 University of Helsinki, Finland, Helsinki Institute of Physics, Gustaf H\"allstr\"omin katu 2, University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland), R. Laureijs (Kapteyn Astronomical Institute, University of Groningen, PO Box 800, 9700 AV Groningen, The Netherlands), A. M. C. Le Brun (Laboratoire d'etude de l'Univers et des phenomenes eXtremes, Observatoire de Paris, Universit\'e PSL, Sorbonne Universit\'e, CNRS, 92190 Meudon, France), D. Le Mignant (Aix-Marseille Universit\'e, CNRS, CNES, LAM, Marseille, France), S. Ligori (INAF-Osservatorio Astrofisico di Torino, Via Osservatorio 20, 10025 Pino Torinese), P. B. Lilje (Institute of Theoretical Astrophysics, University of Oslo, P.O. Box 1029 Blindern, 0315 Oslo, Norway), V. Lindholm (Department of Physics, P.O. Box 64, 00014 University of Helsinki, Finland, Helsinki Institute of Physics, Gustaf H\"allstr\"omin katu 2, University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland), I. Lloro (SKA Observatory, Jodrell Bank, Lower Withington, Macclesfield, Cheshire SK11 9FT, UK), G. Mainetti (Centre de Calcul de l'IN2P3/CNRS, 21 avenue Pierre de Coubertin 69627 Villeurbanne Cedex, France), D. Maino (Dipartimento di Fisica "Aldo Pontremoli", Universit\`a degli Studi di Milano, Via Celoria 16, 20133 Milano, Italy, INAF-IASF Milano, Via Alfonso Corti 12, 20133 Milano, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Milano, Via Celoria 16, 20133 Milano, Italy), E. Maiorano (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), O. Mansutti (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy), S. Marcin (University of Applied Sciences and Arts of Northwestern Switzerland, School of Computer Science, 5210 Windisch, Switzerland), O. Marggraf (Universit\"at Bonn, Argelander-Institut f\"ur Astronomie, Auf dem H\"ugel 71, 53121 Bonn, Germany), M. Martinelli (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Roma, Via Frascati 33, 00078 Monteporzio Catone, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Roma, Piazzale Aldo Moro, 2 - c/o Dipartimento di Fisica, Edificio G. Marconi, 00185 Roma, Italy), N. Martinet (Aix-Marseille Universit\'e, CNRS, CNES, LAM, Marseille, France), F. Marulli (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "Augusto Righi" - Alma Mater Studiorum Universit\`a di Bologna, via Piero Gobetti 93/2, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), R. J. Massey (Department of Physics, Institute for Computational Cosmology, Durham University, South Road, Durham, DH1 3LE, UK), S. Maurogordato (Universit\'e C\^ote d'Azur, Observatoire de la C\^ote d'Azur, CNRS, Laboratoire Lagrange, Bd de l'Observatoire, CS 34229, 06304 Nice cedex 4, France), E. Medinaceli (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), S. Mei (Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e, CNRS, Astroparticule et Cosmologie, 75013 Paris, France, CNRS-UCB International Research Laboratory, Centre Pierre Bin\'etruy, IRL2007, CPB-IN2P3, Berkeley, USA), Y. Mellier (Institut d'Astrophysique de Paris, 98bis Boulevard Arago, 75014, Paris, France, Institut d'Astrophysique de Paris, UMR 7095, CNRS, and Sorbonne Universit\'e, 98 bis boulevard Arago, 75014 Paris, France), M. Meneghetti (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), E. Merlin (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Roma, Via Frascati 33, 00078 Monteporzio Catone, Italy), G. Meylan (Institute of Physics, Laboratory of Astrophysics, Ecole Polytechnique F\'ed\'erale de Lausanne), J. J. Mohr (University Observatory, LMU Faculty of Physics, Scheinerstrasse 1, 81679 Munich, Germany), A. Mora (Telespazio UK S.L. for European Space Agency), M. Moresco (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "Augusto Righi" - Alma Mater Studiorum Universit\`a di Bologna, via Piero Gobetti 93/2, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), L. Moscardini (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "Augusto Righi" - Alma Mater Studiorum Universit\`a di Bologna, via Piero Gobetti 93/2, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), R. Nakajima (Universit\"at Bonn, Argelander-Institut f\"ur Astronomie, Auf dem H\"ugel 71, 53121 Bonn, Germany), C. Neissner (Institut de F\'isica d'Altes Energies, Port d'Informaci\'o Cient\'ifica, Campus UAB, C. Albareda s/n, 08193 Bellaterra), R. C. Nichol (School of Mathematics and Physics, University of Surrey, Guildford, Surrey, GU2 7XH, UK), S. -M. Niemi (European Space Agency/ESTEC, Keplerlaan 1, 2201 AZ Noordwijk, The Netherlands), C. Padilla (Institut de F\'isica d'Altes Energies), F. Pasian (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy), K. Pedersen (DARK, Niels Bohr Institute, University of Copenhagen, Jagtvej 155, 2200 Copenhagen, Denmark), W. J. Percival (Waterloo Centre for Astrophysics, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Ontario N2L 3G1, Canada, Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Ontario N2L 3G1, Canada, Perimeter Institute for Theoretical Physics, Waterloo, Ontario N2L 2Y5, Canada), V. Pettorino (European Space Agency/ESTEC, Keplerlaan 1, 2201 AZ Noordwijk, The Netherlands), S. Pires (Universit\'e Paris-Saclay, Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e, CEA, CNRS, AIM, 91191, Gif-sur-Yvette, France), G. Polenta (Space Science Data Center, Italian Space Agency, via del Politecnico snc, 00133 Roma, Italy), M. Poncet (Centre National d'Etudes Spatiales -- Centre spatial de Toulouse, 18 avenue Edouard Belin, 31401 Toulouse Cedex 9, France), L. A. Popa (Institute of Space Science, Str. Atomistilor, nr. 409 M\u{a}gurele, Ilfov, 077125, Romania), L. Pozzetti (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), F. Raison (Max Planck Institute for Extraterrestrial Physics, Giessenbachstr. 1, 85748 Garching, Germany), A. Renzi (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "G. Galilei", Universit\`a di Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy, INFN-Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy), J. Rhodes (Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology, 4800 Oak Grove Drive, Pasadena, CA, 91109, USA), G. Riccio (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Capodimonte, Via Moiariello 16, 80131 Napoli, Italy), E. Romelli (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy), M. Roncarelli (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), C. Rosset (Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e, CNRS, Astroparticule et Cosmologie, 75013 Paris, France), R. Saglia (Universit\"ats-Sternwarte M\"unchen, Fakult\"at f\"ur Physik, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit\"at M\"unchen, Scheinerstrasse 1, 81679 M\"unchen, Germany, Max Planck Institute for Extraterrestrial Physics, Giessenbachstr. 1, 85748 Garching, Germany), Z. Sakr (Institut f\"ur Theoretische Physik, University of Heidelberg, Philosophenweg 16, 69120 Heidelberg, Germany, Institut de Recherche en Astrophysique et Plan\'etologie, Universit\'e St Joseph, Faculty of Sciences, Beirut, Lebanon), D. Sapone (Departamento de F\'isica, FCFM, Universidad de Chile, Blanco Encalada 2008, Santiago, Chile), B. Sartoris (Universit\"ats-Sternwarte M\"unchen, Fakult\"at f\"ur Physik, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit\"at M\"unchen, Scheinerstrasse 1, 81679 M\"unchen, Germany, INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy), M. Schirmer (Max-Planck-Institut f\"ur Astronomie, K\"onigstuhl 17, 69117 Heidelberg, Germany), P. Schneider (Universit\"at Bonn, Argelander-Institut f\"ur Astronomie, Auf dem H\"ugel 71, 53121 Bonn, Germany), A. Secroun (Aix-Marseille Universit\'e, CNRS/IN2P3, CPPM, Marseille, France), G. Seidel (Max-Planck-Institut f\"ur Astronomie, K\"onigstuhl 17, 69117 Heidelberg, Germany), M. Seiffert (Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology, 4800 Oak Grove Drive, Pasadena, CA, 91109, USA), S. Serrano (Institut d'Estudis Espacials de Catalunya, Satlantis, University Science Park, Sede Bld 48940, Leioa-Bilbao, Spain, Institute of Space Sciences), C. Sirignano (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia "G. Galilei", Universit\`a di Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy, INFN-Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy), G. Sirri (INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), A. Spurio Mancini (Department of Physics, Royal Holloway, University of London, TW20 0EX, UK), L. Stanco (INFN-Padova, Via Marzolo 8, 35131 Padova, Italy), J. Steinwagner (Max Planck Institute for Extraterrestrial Physics, Giessenbachstr. 1, 85748 Garching, Germany), P. Tallada-Cresp\'i (Centro de Investigaciones Energ\'eticas, Medioambientales y Tecnol\'ogicas, Port d'Informaci\'o Cient\'ifica, Campus UAB, C. Albareda s/n, 08193 Bellaterra), I. Tereno (Departamento de F\'isica, Faculdade de Ci\^encias, Universidade de Lisboa, Edif\'icio C8, Campo Grande, PT1749-016 Lisboa, Portugal, Instituto de Astrof\'isica e Ci\^encias do Espa\c{c}o, Faculdade de Ci\^encias, Universidade de Lisboa, Tapada da Ajuda, 1349-018 Lisboa, Portugal), N. Tessore (Department of Physics and Astronomy, University College London, Gower Street, London WC1E 6BT, UK), R. Toledo-Moreo (Universidad Polit\'ecnica de Cartagena, Departamento de Electr\'onica y Tecnolog\'ia de Computadoras, Plaza del Hospital 1, 30202 Cartagena, Spain), F. Torradeflot (Port d'Informaci\'o Cient\'ifica, Campus UAB, C. Albareda s/n, 08193 Bellaterra, Centro de Investigaciones Energ\'eticas, Medioambientales y Tecnol\'ogicas), I. Tutusaus (Institut de Recherche en Astrophysique et Plan\'etologie), E. A. Valentijn (Kapteyn Astronomical Institute, University of Groningen, PO Box 800, 9700 AV Groningen, The Netherlands), L. Valenziano (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INFN-Bologna, Via Irnerio 46, 40126 Bologna, Italy), J. Valiviita (Department of Physics, P.O. Box 64, 00014 University of Helsinki, Finland, Helsinki Institute of Physics, Gustaf H\"allstr\"omin katu 2, University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland), T. Vassallo (Universit\"ats-Sternwarte M\"unchen, Fakult\"at f\"ur Physik, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit\"at M\"unchen, Scheinerstrasse 1, 81679 M\"unchen, Germany, INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy), G. Verdoes Kleijn (Kapteyn Astronomical Institute, University of Groningen, PO Box 800, 9700 AV Groningen, The Netherlands), A. Veropalumbo (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Brera, Via Brera 28, 20122 Milano, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Genova, Via Dodecaneso 33, 16146, Genova, Italy, Dipartimento di Fisica, Universit\`a di Genova, Via Dodecaneso 33, 16146, Genova, Italy), Y. Wang (Infrared Processing and Analysis Center, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, CA 91125, USA), J. Weller (Universit\"ats-Sternwarte M\"unchen, Fakult\"at f\"ur Physik, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit\"at M\"unchen, Scheinerstrasse 1, 81679 M\"unchen, Germany, Max Planck Institute for Extraterrestrial Physics, Giessenbachstr. 1, 85748 Garching, Germany), G. Zamorani (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), F. M. Zerbi (INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Brera, Via Brera 28, 20122 Milano, Italy), E. Zucca (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), M. Bolzonella (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy), C. Burigana (INAF, Istituto di Radioastronomia, Via Piero Gobetti 101, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INFN-Bologna, Via Irnerio 46, 40126 Bologna, Italy), L. Gabarra (Department of Physics, Oxford University, Keble Road, Oxford OX1 3RH, UK), J. Mart\'in-Fleitas (Aurora Technology for European Space Agency), S. Matthew (Institute for Astronomy, University of Edinburgh, Royal Observatory, Blackford Hill, Edinburgh EH9 3HJ, UK), A. Pezzotta (INAF - Osservatorio Astronomico di Brera, via Emilio Bianchi 46, 23807 Merate, Italy, Max Planck Institute for Extraterrestrial Physics, Giessenbachstr. 1, 85748 Garching, Germany), V. Scottez (Institut d'Astrophysique de Paris, 98bis Boulevard Arago, 75014, Paris, France, ICL, Junia, Universit\'e Catholique de Lille, LITL, 59000 Lille, France), M. Sereno (INAF-Osservatorio di Astrofisica e Scienza dello Spazio di Bologna, Via Piero Gobetti 93/3, 40129 Bologna, Italy, INFN-Sezione di Bologna, Viale Berti Pichat 6/2, 40127 Bologna, Italy), M. Viel (IFPU, Institute for Fundamental Physics of the Universe, via Beirut 2, 34151 Trieste, Italy, INAF-Osservatorio Astronomico di Trieste, Via G. B. Tiepolo 11, 34143 Trieste, Italy, SISSA, International School for Advanced Studies, Via Bonomea 265, 34136 Trieste TS, Italy, INFN, Sezione di Trieste, Via Valerio 2, 34127 Trieste TS, Italy, ICSC - Centro Nazionale di Ricerca in High Performance Computing, Big Data e Quantum Computing, Via Magnanelli 2, Bologna, Italy), D. Scott (Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, BC V6T 1Z1, Canada)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Whispers from the Early Universe: The Ringdown of Primordial Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07665v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the stochastic gravitational wave background (SGWB) generated by the ringdown phase of primordial black holes (PBHs) formed in the early universe. As the ringdown signal is independent of the PBH formation mechanism, the resulting SGWB offers a model-independent probe of PBHs. We numerically compute the ringdown waveform and derive the corresponding SGWB. We show that such a signal could be detected by future pulsar timing arrays (PTAs) for PBHs heavier than the solar mass. Additionally, we evaluate the SGWB from binary PBH mergers and demonstrate that it lies within the sensitivity bands of next-generation ground-based interferometers such as Cosmic Explorer and Einstein Telescope, suggesting a multi-band observational strategy for probing the PBH dark matter scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07665v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Yuan, Zhen Zhong, Qing-Guo Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring non-cold dark matter in a scenario of dynamical dark energy with DESI DR2 data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07798v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent observations of DESI hint that dark matter (DM) may not be cold but have a non-zero equation of state (EoS) parameter, and that dark energy (DE) may not be a cosmological constant. In this work, we explore the possibility of a non-zero DM EoS parameter within the framework of dynamical DE. We perform analysis by using the latest baryon acoustic oscillation (BAO) data from DESI DR2, the cosmic microwave background (CMB) data from Planck, and the type Ia supernova (SN) data from DESY5 and PantheonPlus. When using the combination of CMB, BAO, and SN data, our results indicate a preference for a non-zero DM EoS parameter at the $2.8\sigma$ and $3.3\sigma$ level within the content of a constant DE EoS. In contrast, for a time-evolving DE EoS parameterized by $w_0$ and $w_a$, this preference decreases to $0.8\sigma$ and $1.1\sigma$. Furthermore, allowing a non-zero DM EoS yields best-fit values of $w_0$ and $w_a$ that exhibit smaller deviations from the $\Lambda$CDM expectations, and Bayesian evidence analysis shows a comparable preference for this model relative to $\Lambda$CDM. The overall results of this work indicate that a non-zero DM EoS parameter warrants further exploration and investigation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07798v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tian-Nuo Li, Peng-Ju Wu, Guo-Hong Du, Yan-Hong Yao, Jing-Fei Zhang, Xin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fisher Score Matching for Simulation-Based Forecasting and Inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07833v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a method for estimating the Fisher score--the gradient of the log-likelihood with respect to model parameters--using score matching. By introducing a latent parameter model, we show that the Fisher score can be learned by training a neural network to predict latent scores via a mean squared error loss. We validate our approach on a toy linear Gaussian model and a cosmological example using a differentiable simulator. In both cases, the learned scores closely match ground truth for plausible data-parameter pairs. This method extends the ability to perform Fisher forecasts, and gradient-based Bayesian inference to simulation models, even when they are not differentiable; it therefore has broad potential for advancing cosmological analyses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07833v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ce Sui, Shivam Pandey, Benjamin D. Wandelt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing small-scale primordial power spectra with tensor-scalar induced gravitational waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07836v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Large-scale primordial perturbations have been well constrained by current cosmological observations, but the properties of small-scale perturbations remain elusive. This study focuses on second-order tensor-scalar induced gravitational waves (TSIGWs) generated by large-amplitude primordial scalar and tensor perturbations on small scales. We provide the analytical expressions for the kernel functions and the corresponding energy density spectra of second-order TSIGWs. By combining observations of SGWB across different scales, TSIGWs can be used to constrain small-scale primordial curvature perturbations and primordial gravitational waves. Furthermore, we discuss the feasibility of TSIGWs dominating the current PTA observations under various primordial power spectra scenarios. Our results indicate that TSIGWs generated by monochromatic primordial power spectra might be more likely to dominate the current PTA observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07836v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Di Wu, Zhi-Chao Li, Peng-Yu Wu, Fei-Yu Chen, Jing-Zhi Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Baryonification: An alternative to hydrodynamical simulations for cosmological studies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07892v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an improved baryonification (BFC) model that modifies dark-matter-only $N$-body simulations to generate particle-level outputs for gas, dark matter, and stars. Unlike previous implementations, our approach first splits each simulation particle into separate dark matter and baryonic components, which are then displaced individually using the BFC technique. By applying the hydrostatic and ideal gas equations, we assign pressure and temperature values to individual gas particles. The model is validated against hydrodynamical simulations from the FLAMINGO and TNG suites (which feature varied feedback prescriptions) showing good agreement at the level of density and pressure profiles across a wide range of halo masses. As a further step, we calibrate the BFC model parameters to gas and stellar mass ratio profiles from the hydrodynamical simulations. Based on these calibrations, we baryonify $N$-body simulations and compare the resulting total matter power spectrum suppressions to the ones from the same hydrodynamical simulation. Carrying out this test of the BFC method at each redshift individually, we obtain a 2 percent agreement up to $k=5\,h$/Mpc across all tested feedback scenarios. We also define a reduced, 2+1 parameter BFC model that simultaneously accounts for feedback variations (2 parameters) and redshift evolution (1 parameter). The 2+1 parameter model agrees with the hydrodynamical simulations to better than 2.5 percent over the scales and redshifts relevant for cosmological surveys. Finally, we present a map-level comparison between a baryonified $N$-body simulation and a full hydrodynamical run from the TNG simulation suite. Visual inspection of dark matter, gas, and stellar density fields, along with the integrated pressure map, shows promising agreement. Further work is needed to quantify the accuracy at the level of observables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07892v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aurel Schneider, Michael Kova\v{c}, Jozef Bucko, Andrina Nicola, Robert Reischke, Sambit K. Giri, Romain Teyssier, Tilman Tr\"oster, Alexandre Refregier, Matthieu Schaller, Joop Schaye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Semi-Analytic model for Effects of Fuzzy Dark Matter Granule Perturbations on Orbital Motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07963v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In fuzzy dark matter scenarios, the quantum wave nature of ultralight axion-like particles generates stochastic density fluctuations inside dark matter halos. These fluctuations, known as granules, perturb the orbits of subhalos and other orbiting bodies. While previous studies have simulated these effects using N-body techniques or modeled them statistically using diffusion approximations, we propose an alternative framework based on representing the perturbations as a Fourier series with random coefficients, which can be applied to individual orbits, not just populations. We extend the model to finite-size subhalos, identifying a critical length scale below which subhalos behave as point-mass particles. In contrast, larger subhalos exhibit suppressed perturbations from granules due to their extended mass profiles. Using FDM-Simulator, we validate our finite-size model by isolating granule accelerations and confirming their statistical effects on subhalo dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07963v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Zhao, Andrew Benson, Xiaolong Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints from CMB lensing tomography with projected bispectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07968v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We measure the angular power spectrum and bispectrum of the projected overdensity of photometric DESI luminous red galaxies, and its cross-correlation with maps of the Cosmic Microwave Background lensing convergence from \planck. This analysis is enabled by the use of the ``filtered-squared bispectrum'' approach, introduced in previous work, which we generalise here to the case of cross-correlations between multiple fields. The projected galaxy bispectrum is detected at very high significance (above $30\sigma$ in all redshift bins), and the galaxy-galaxy-convergence bispectrum is detected above $5\sigma$ in the three highest-redshift bins. We find that the bispectrum is reasonably well described over a broad range of scales by a tree-level prediction using the linear galaxy bias measured from the power spectrum. We carry out the first cosmological analysis combining projected power spectra and bispectra under a relatively simple model, and show that the galaxy bispectrum can be used in combination with the power spectrum to place a constraint on the amplitude of matter fluctuations, $\sigma_8$, an on the non-relativistic matter fraction $\Omega_m$. We find that data combinations involving the galaxy bispectrum recover constraints on these parameters that are in good agreement with those found from the traditional ``2$\times$2-point'' combination of galaxy-galaxy and galaxy-convergence power spectra, across all redshift bins.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07968v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lea Harscouet, David Alonso, Andrina Nicola, An\v{z}e Slosar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Baryonification II: Constraining feedback with X-ray and kinematic Sunyaev-Zel'dovich observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07991v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Baryonic feedback alters the matter distribution on small and intermediate scales, posing a challenge for precision cosmology. The new, component-wise baryonification (BFC) approach provides a self-consistent framework to model feedback effects for different observables. In this paper we use this framework to fit kinematic Sunyaev-Zel'dovich (kSZ) observations from the Atacama Cosmology Telescope (ACT) alongside halo X-ray gas fractions from eROSITA, investigating baryonic feedback in a cosmological context. We first show that the kSZ data from ACT is consistent with the gas fractions from eROSITA, both suggesting a feedback model that is stronger than what is assumed in most hydrodynamical simulations. This finding is in contrast to older, pre-eROSITA gas fraction measurements that point towards weaker feedback in tension with the kSZ results. We suspect these discrepancies to be due to selection bias in the pre-eROSITA sample, or differences in halo mass estimation between the two data sets. In a further step, we use the BFC model to predict the baryonic suppression of the matter power spectrum. Based on our combined fit to data from ACT and eROSITA, we find a power spectrum suppression that exceeds the percent-level at modes above $k=0.3-0.6 \,h\,\mathrm{Mpc}^{-1}$, growing to 2-8 percent at $k=1\,h\,\mathrm{Mpc}^{-1}$, and to 20-25 percent at $k=5\,h\,\mathrm{Mpc}^{-1}$, consistent with strong-feedback hydrodynamical simulations. Finally, we compare our best-fitting model to the observed gas density and pressure profiles of massive galaxy clusters from the X-COP sample, finding excellent agreement. These results show that BFC provides a self-consistent picture of feedback across mass- and length scales as well as different cosmological observables, thus making it promising for applications to multiwavelength studies to jointly constrain cosmology and baryonic effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07991v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Kova\v{c}, Andrina Nicola, Jozef Bucko, Aurel Schneider, Robert Reischke, Sambit K. Giri, Romain Teyssier, Matthieu Schaller, Joop Schaye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the statistical nature of Betti numbers and Euler characteristic of smooth random fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.06255v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We represent excursion sets of smooth random fields as unions of a topological basis consisting of a sequence of simply and multiply connected compact subsets of the underlying manifold. The associated coefficients, which are non-negative discrete random variables, reflect the randomness of the field. Betti numbers of the excursion sets can be expressed as summations over the coefficients, and the Euler characteristic and the sum of Betti numbers can also be expressed as their (alternating) sum. This enables understanding their statistical properties as sums (or differences) of discrete random variables. We examine the conditions under which each topological statistic can be asymptotically Gaussian as the size of the manifold and the resolution increase. The coefficients of the basis elements are then modeled as Binomial variables, and the statistical natures of Betti numbers, Euler character and sum of Betti numbers follow from this fundamental property. We test the validity of the modeling using numerical calculations, and identify threshold regimes where the topological statistics can be approximated as Gaussian variables. The new representation of excursion sets thus maps the properties of topological statistics to combinatorial structures, thereby providing mathematical clarity on their use for physical inference, particularly in cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.06255v1</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pravabati Chingangbam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First release of LiteBIRD simulations from an end-to-end pipeline</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07122v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The LiteBIRD satellite mission aims at detecting Cosmic Microwave Background $B$ modes with unprecedented precision, targeting a total error on the tensor-to-scalar ratio $r$ of $\delta r \sim 0.001$. Operating from the L2 Lagrangian point of the Sun-Earth system, LiteBIRD will survey the full sky across 15 frequency bands (34 to 448 GHz) for 3 years.The current LiteBIRD baseline configuration employs 4508 detectors sampling at 19.1 Hz to achieve an effective polarization sensitivity of $ 2 \mu\mathrm{K-arcmin}$ and an angular resolution of 31 arcmin (at 140 GHz).We describe the first release of the official LiteBIRD simulations, realized with a new simulation pipeline developed using the LiteBIRD Simulation Framework.This pipeline generates 500 full-sky simulated maps at a Healpix resolution of nside=512. The simulations include also one year of Time Ordered Data for approximately one-third of LiteBIRD's total detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07122v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Bortolami (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), N. Raffuzzi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), L. Pagano (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), G. Puglisi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. Anand (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. J. Banday (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), P. Campeti (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), G. Galloni (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. I. Lonappan (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Monelli (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Tomasi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), G. Weymann-Despres (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), D. Adak (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), E. Allys (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), J. Aumont (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), R. Aurvik (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), C. Baccigalupi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Ballardini (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), R. B. Barreiro (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), N. Bartolo (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), S. Basak (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Bersanelli (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. Besnard (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), T. Brinckmann (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), E. Calabrese (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), E. Carinos (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. Carones (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), F. J. Casas (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), K. Cheung (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Citran (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), L. Clermont (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), F. Columbro (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), G. Coppi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. Coppolecchia (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), F. Cuttaia (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), P. Dal Bo (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), P. de Bernardis (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), E. de la Hoz (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. De Lucia (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), S. Della Torre (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), P. Diego-Palazuelos (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), H. K. Eriksen (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), T. Essinger-Hileman (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), C. Franceschet (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), U. Fuskeland (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Galloway (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Gerbino (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Gervasi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), T. Ghigna (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), S. Giardiello (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), C. Gimeno-Amo (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), E. Gjerl{\o}w (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. Gruppuso (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Hazumi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), S. Henrot-Versill\'e (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), L. T. Hergt (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), E. Hivon (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), B. Jost (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), K. Kohri (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), L. Lamagna (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), T. Lari (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Lattanzi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), C. Leloup (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), F. Levrier (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. L\'opez-Caniego (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), G. Luzzi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), J. Macias-Perez (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), B. Maffei (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), E. Mart\'inez-Gonz\'alez (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), S. Masi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), S. Matarrese (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), T. Matsumura (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), S. Micheli (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), L. Montier (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), G. Morgante (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), L. Mousset (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), R. Nagata (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), T. Namikawa (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. Novelli (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), F. Noviello (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), I. Obata (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. Occhiuzzi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. Paiella (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), D. Paoletti (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), G. Pascual-Cisneros (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), F. Piacentini (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Pinchera (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), G. Polenta (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), L. Porcelli (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Remazeilles (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. Ritacco (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), A. Rizzieri (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), J. A. Rubi\~no-Mart\'in (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Ruiz-Granda (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), J. Sanghavi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), V. Sauvage (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Shiraishi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), G. Signorelli (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), S. L. Stever (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), R. M. Sullivan (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), Y. Takase (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), K. Tassis (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), L. Terenzi (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Tristram (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), L. Vacher (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), B. van Tent (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), P. Vielva (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), I. K. Wehus (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), M. Zannoni (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration), Y. Zhou (for the LiteBIRD Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating Retrieval-Augmented Generation Agents for Autonomous Scientific Discovery in Astrophysics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07155v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We evaluate 9 Retrieval Augmented Generation (RAG) agent configurations on 105 Cosmology Question-Answer (QA) pairs that we built specifically for this purpose.The RAG configurations are manually evaluated by a human expert, that is, a total of 945 generated answers were assessed. We find that currently the best RAG agent configuration is with OpenAI embedding and generative model, yielding 91.4\% accuracy. Using our human evaluation results we calibrate LLM-as-a-Judge (LLMaaJ) system which can be used as a robust proxy for human evaluation. These results allow us to systematically select the best RAG agent configuration for multi-agent system for autonomous scientific discovery in astrophysics (e.g., cmbagent presented in a companion paper) and provide us with an LLMaaJ system that can be scaled to thousands of cosmology QA pairs. We make our QA dataset, human evaluation results, RAG pipelines, and LLMaaJ system publicly available for further use by the astrophysics community.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07155v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xueqing Xu, Boris Bolliet, Adrian Dimitrov, Andrew Laverick, Francisco Villaescusa-Navarro, Licong Xu, \'I\~nigo Zubeldia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 GeV halo-like excess of the Galactic diffuse emission and implications for dark matter annihilation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07209v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fifteen years of the Fermi Large Area Telescope (LAT) data in the halo region of the Milky Way (MW) are analyzed to search for gamma rays from dark matter annihilation. Gamma-ray maps within the region of interest ($|l| \le 60$ deg, $10 \le |b| \le 60$ deg) are modeled using point sources, the GALPROP models of cosmic-ray interactions, isotropic background, and templates of Loop I and the Fermi bubbles, and then the presence of a halo-like component is further examined. A statistically significant halo-like excess is found with a sharp peak around 20 GeV, while its flux is consistent with zero below 2 GeV and above 200 GeV. Examination of the fit residual maps indicates that a spherically symmetric halo component fits the map data well. The radial profile agrees with annihilation by the smooth NFW density profile, and may be slightly shallower than this, especially in the central region. Various systematic uncertainties are investigated, but the 20 GeV peak remains significant. In particular, the halo excess with a similar spectrum is detected even relative to the LAT standard background model, which does not depend on GALPROP or other model templates. The halo excess can be fitted by the annihilation spectrum with a mass $m_\chi \sim$ 0.5-0.8 TeV and annihilation cross section $\langle \sigma \upsilon \rangle \sim$ (5-8)$\times 10^{-25} \ \rm cm^3 \, s^{-1}$ for the $b\bar{b}$ channel. This cross section is larger than the upper limits from dwarf galaxies and the canonical thermal relic value, but considering various uncertainties, especially the density profile of the MW halo, the dark matter interpretation of the 20 GeV ``Fermi halo'' remains feasible. The prospects for verification through future observations are briefly discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07209v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomonori Totani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational lensing rarely produces high-mass outliers to the compact binary population</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07964v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: All gravitational-wave signals are inevitably gravitationally lensed by intervening matter as they propagate through the Universe. When a gravitational-wave signal is magnified, it appears to have originated from a closer, more massive system. Thus, high-mass outliers to the gravitational-wave source population are often proposed as natural candidates for strongly lensed events. However, when using a data-driven method for identifying population outliers, we find that high-mass outliers are not necessarily strongly lensed, nor will the majority of strongly-lensed signals appear as high-mass outliers. This is both because statistical fluctuations produce a larger effect on observed binary parameters than does lensing magnification, and because lensing-induced outliers must originate from intrinsically high-mass sources, which are rare. Thus, the appearance of a single lensing-induced outlier implies the existence of many other lensed events within the catalog. We additionally show that it is possible to constrain the strong lensing optical depth, which is a fundamental quantity of our Universe, with the detection or absence of high-mass outliers. However, constraints using the latest gravitational-wave catalog are weak$\unicode{x2014}$we obtain an upper limit on the optical depth of sources at redshift $1$ magnified by a factor of $5$ or more of $\tau(\mu\geq5,z=1)\leq 0.035 \unicode{x2014}$and future observing runs will not make an outlier-based method competitive with other probes of the optical depth. Future work will investigate the ability of the full inferred population of compact binaries to inform the distribution of lenses in the Universe, opening a unique opportunity to access the high-redshift Universe and constrain cosmic structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07964v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amanda Farah, Jose Mar\'ia Ezquiaga, Maya Fishbach, Daniel Holz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on interacting dark energy revisited: implications for the Hubble tension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.05807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.05807v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We revisit a class of coupled dark energy models where dark energy interacts with dark matter via phenomenological energy exchange terms. We include the perturbation of the Hubble rate in the interaction term, which was absent in previous works. We also consider more recent data sets such as cosmic microwave background (CMB) anisotropies from \text{Planck} 2018, type I-a supernovae (SNIa) measurements from Pantheon+ and data from baryon acoustic oscillations (BAO), and redshift space distortions (RSD). One of the models presents a strong incompatibility when different cosmological datasets are used. We analyze the influence of the SH0ES Cepheid host distances on the results and, although for one model the discrepancy of $H_0$ is reduced to $3.2\sigma$ when compared to the value obtained by the \textit{Planck} collaboration and $3.6\sigma$ when compared to the SH0ES team, joint analysis is incompatible. Including BAO with RSD shows incompatibility with SH0ES for all models considered here. We perform a model comparison and although there is a preference for interacting dark energy over $\Lambda$CDM for all the models for joint analysis CMB+BAO+RSD+SNIa, most of the 2D contours do not overlap. We conclude that the models of interactions in the dark sector considered in this paper are not flexible enough to fit all the cosmological data including values of $H_0$ from SH0ES in a statistically acceptable way. Therefore, the addition of one extra degree of freedom (i.e. the coupling between dark matter and dark matter) does not help enough to alleviate the already existing tension in the vanilla $\Lambda$CDM, suggesting that the models would need to be modified to include further flexibility of predictions to help elucidate this issue.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.05807v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel A. Hoerning, Ricardo G. Landim, Luiza O. Ponte, Raphael P. Rolim, Filipe B. Abdalla, Elcio Abdalla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical Challenges in Modeling Gravothermal Collapse in Self-Interacting Dark Matter Halos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.12452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.12452v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: When dark matter has a large cross section for self scattering, halos can undergo a process known as gravothermal core collapse, where the inner core rapidly increases in density and temperature. To date, several methods have been used to implement Self-Interacting Dark Matter~(SIDM) in N-body codes, but there has been no systematic study of these different methods or their accuracy in the core-collapse phase. In this paper, we compare three different numerical implementations of SIDM, including the standard methods from the GIZMO and Arepo codes, by simulating idealized dwarf halos undergoing significant dark matter self interactions ($\sigma/m = 50$~cm$^2$/g). When simulating these halos, we also vary the mass resolution, time-stepping criteria, and gravitational force-softening scheme. The various SIDM methods lead to distinct differences in a halo's evolution during the core-collapse phase, as each results in spurious scattering rate differences and energy gains/losses. The use of adaptive force softening for gravity can lead to numerical heating that artificially accelerates core collapse, while an insufficiently small simulation time step can cause core evolution to stall or completely reverse. Additionally, particle numbers must be large enough to ensure that the simulated halos are not sensitive to noise in the initial conditions. Even for the highest-resolution simulations tested in this study ($10^6$ particles per halo), we find that variations of order $10\%$ in collapse time are still present. The results of this work underscore the sensitivity of SIDM modeling on the choice of numerical implementation and motivate a careful study of how these results generalize to halos in a cosmological context.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.12452v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2024/09/074</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 09 (2024) 074</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Igor Palubski, Oren Slone, Manoj Kaplinghat, Mariangela Lisanti, Fangzhou Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observational constraints on $\alpha$-Starobinsky inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05615v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work we revisit $\alpha$-Starobinsky inflation, also know as $E$-model, in the light of current CMB and LSS observations. The inflaton potential in the Einstein frame for this model contains a parameter $\alpha$ in the exponential, which alters the predictions for the scalar and tensor power spectra of Starobinsky inflation. We obtain these power spectra numerically without using slow-roll approximation and perform MCMC analysis to put constraints on parameters $M$ and $\alpha$ from Planck-2018, BICEP/Keck (BK18) and other LSS observations. We consider general reheating scenario by varying the number of e-foldings during inflation, $N_{pivot}$, along with the other parameters. We find $\log_{10}\alpha = 0.0^{+1.6}_{-5.6}$, $\log_{10}M= -4.91^{+0.69}_{-2.7}$ and $N_{pivot} = 53.2^{+3.9}_{-5}$ with $95\%$ C. L.. This implies that the present CMB and LSS observations are insufficient to constrain the parameter $\alpha$. We also find that there is no correlation between $N_{pivot}$ and $\alpha$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05615v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saisandri Saini, Akhilesh Nautiyal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A novel approach to cosmological non-linearities as an effective fluid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15295v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a two parameters extension of the flat $\Lambda$CDM model to capture the impact of matter inhomogeneities on our cosmological inference. Non virialized but non-linearly evolving overdense and underdense regions, whose abundance is quantified using the Press-Schechter formalism, are collectively described by two effective perfect fluids $\rho_{\rm{c}},\rho_{\rm{v}}$ with non vanishing equation of state parameters $w_{\rm{c,v}}\neq 0$. These fluids are coupled to the pressureless dust, akin to an interacting DM-DE scenario. The resulting phenomenology is very rich, and could potentially address a number of inconsistencies of the standard model, including a simultaneous resolution of the Hubble and $\sigma_8$ tensions. To assess the viability of the model, we set initial conditions compatible to the Planck 2018 best fit $\Lambda$CDM cosmology and fit its additional parameters using SN~Ia observations from DESY5, BAO distances from DESI DR2 and a sample of uncorrelated $f\sigma_8$ measurements. Our findings show that backreaction effects from the cosmic web could restore the concordance between early and late Universe cosmological probes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15295v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/zr92-m7py</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Leonardo Giani, Rodrigo Von Marttens, Ryan Camilleri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial Black Hole Formation via Inverted Bubble Collapse</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02291v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a novel mechanism of primordial black hole (PBH) formation through inverted bubble collapse. In this scenario, bubbles nucleate sparsely in an incomplete first-order phase transition, such that they remain isolated and do not percolate or collide with each other due to the extremely low nucleation rate. This is followed by a bulk phase transition in the rest of the universe that inverts these pre-existing bubbles into false vacuum regions. These spherically symmetric false-vacuum bubbles subsequently collapse to form PBHs. Unlike conventional PBH formation mechanisms associated with domain wall collapse or bubble coalescence, our inverted bubble collapse mechanism naturally ensures spherical collapse. We demonstrate that, when applied to the singlet extension of the Standard Model, this mechanism can produce highly monochromatic PBHs with masses up to ${\cal O}(10^{-7}\,\text{-}\,10^{-5}) M_\odot$, which potentially explain the microlensing events observed in the OGLE and Subaru HSC data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02291v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP07(2025)065</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 07 (2025) 065</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kai Murai, Kodai Sakurai, Fuminobu Takahashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasar Pairs as Large--Scale Structure tracers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.01251v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quasars are effective tracers of the large-scale distribution of galaxies at high redshift thanks to their high luminosity and dedicated surveys. Previous studies have shown that quasars exhibit a bias similar to that of rich groups, indicating that quasar pairs may be linked to higher density environments, serving as protocluster proxies. In this work, we aim to characterize close quasar pairs within the same halo by identifying them in redshift space. We analyze pair-quasar cross correlations and CMB-derived lensing convergence profiles centered in these systems. We have identified 2777 pairs of quasars in the redshift range from 1.2 to 2.8. Quasar pairs exhibit a distribution of relative luminosities that differs from that of random pairs with the same redshift distribution, indicating that quasars in these systems are distinct from isolated ones. The cross-correlation between pairs and quasars shows a larger amplitude than the auto-correlation function of quasars, suggesting these systems are more strongly biased toward the large-scale mass distribution and reside in more massive halos. This is further supported by higher convergence CMB lensing profiles of pairs compared to isolated quasars with a similar redshift distribution. Our results indicate that quasar pairs are suitable precursors to present-day clusters of galaxies, unlike isolated quasars, which are associated with less dense environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.01251v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mart\'in G. Richarte, Facundo Toscano, Diego G. Lambas, Heliana E. Luparello, Luiz Filipe Guimar\~aes, J\'ulio C. Fabris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alleviating the Hubble Tension with a Local Void and Transitions of the Absolute Magnitude</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13380v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Nowadays, one of the well-known serious challenges in cosmology is the Hubble tension, namely the discrepancy between the Hubble constants from the local observation of Type Ia supernova (SNIa) and the high-$z$ observation of cosmic microwave background (CMB). Here, we are interested in alleviating the Hubble tension with a local void. The key idea is assuming that we live in a locally underdense void, where one will feel a faster expansion rate compared to the cosmic average. In the literature, it was found that a local void cannot satisfyingly alleviate the Hubble tension, since it is not preferred over the $\Lambda$CDM model by the observations such as the Pantheon SNIa sample, especially in terms of the information criteria AIC and BIC. In the present work, we try to alleviate the Hubble tension with a local void and transitions of the absolute magnitude $M$, by using the Pantheon+ SNIa sample alone or jointly with the CMB data of Planck 2018. We find that the Hubble tension can be satisfyingly alleviated, while the $\Lambda$LTB void models are strongly preferred by the observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13380v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing-Yi Jia, Jia-Lei Niu, Da-Chun Qiang, Hao Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Milliarcsecond astrometric oscillations in active galactic nuclei as a precursor of multi-messenger gravitational wave events</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.02146v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The existence of supermassive black hole binaries (SMBHBs) is predicted by various cosmological and evolutionary scenarios for active galactic nuclei. These objects are considered as contributors into the gravitational wave (GW) background and emitters of discrete GW bursts. Yet, SMBHBs remain a rather elusive class of extragalactic objects. Previously we have identified the quasar J2102+6015 as potential SMBHB system based on its oscillating astrometric pattern. We analysed the available VLBI astrometry data and identified another case of astrometric oscillations in the source J0204+1514. We assume these oscillations as manifestations of orbital motion in a binary systems. We estimated parameters of the suspected SMBHB in this source and applied basic theoretical models for projecting its evolution toward coalescence. We also develop a toy model of SMBHB consistent with the discovered astrometric oscillations and give quantitative predictions of GW emission of such the source using the case of J0204+1514 as an example. As an ad hoc result, we also provide a re-assessed estimate of the redshift of J2102+6015, z=1.42. A toy model of the object containing SMBHB with parameters consistent with the observed astrometric oscillations of the source J0204+1514 enabled us to consider GW emission as the cause of the system's orbital evolution. Astrometric VLBI monitoring has an appreciable potential for future detections of SMBHBs as multi-messenger targets for both electromagnetic (in radio domain) and gravitational wave astronomy. To outline the contours of a future physical model connecting SMBHB with detectable GW manifestations, we apply the toy model to the source J0204+1514. We also provide justification for aiming future space-borne VLBI missions toward direct imaging of SMBHBs as a synergistic contribution into future multi-messenger studies involving prospective GW facilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.02146v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonid I. Gurvits, Alexander G. Polnarev, Sandor Frey, Oleg Titov, Angelina A. Osetrova, Xiaohui Fan, Alexey Melnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Axionic defects in the CMB: birefringence and gravitational waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.14104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.14104v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The evidence for a non-vanishing isotropic cosmic birefringence in recent analyses of the CMB data provides a tantalizing hint for new physics. Domain wall (DW) networks have recently been shown to generate an isotropic birefringence signal in the ballpark of the measured value when coupled to photons. In this work, we explore the axionic defects hypothesis in more detail and extending previous results to annihilating and late-forming networks, and by pointing out other smoking-gun signatures of the network in the CMB spectrum such as the anisotropic birefringent spectrum and B-modes. We also argue that the presence of cosmic strings in the network does not hinder a large isotropic birefringence signal because of an intrinsic environmental contribution coming from low redshifts thus leaving open the possibility that axionic defects can explain the signal. Regarding the remaining CMB signatures, with the help of dedicated 3D numerical simulations of DW networks, that we took as a proxy for the axionic defects, we show how the anisotropic birefringence spectrum combined with a tomographic approach can be used to infer the formation and annihilation time of the network. From the numerical simulations, we also computed the spectrum of gravitational waves (GWs) generated by the network in the post-recombination epoch and use previous searches for stochastic GW backgrounds in the CMB to derive for the first time a bound on the tension and abundance of networks with DWs that annihilate after recombination. Our bounds extend to the case where the network survives until the present time and improve over previous bounds by roughly one order of magnitude. Finally, we show the interesting prospects for detecting B-modes of DW origin with future CMB experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.14104v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ricardo Z. Ferreira, Silvia Gasparotto, Takashi Hiramatsu, Ippei Obata, Oriol Pujolas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are compact groups of galaxies special?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20357v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It is often believed that isolated compact groups (CGs) of galaxies are special systems, but only a few studies have compared CGs to regular groups. We study the global properties and internal correlations of a volume- and luminosity-complete subsample of 78 groups of four members (CG4s) within the HMCG Hickson-like sample of compact groups. We compared these CGs to those of a similarly built subsample (including the three-magnitude range of CG4s) of the Lim regular groups. The latter were split into three control samples: one with the four brightest members (Control4Bs), one with the four closest members to the brightest group galaxy (BGG; Control4Cs), and one with exactly four members (RG4s). The vast majority of CG4s are located within regular groups, and a large preponderance of the BGGs of these CG4s are the same as those of their host groups. CG4s are smaller than the groups of all other samples and more luminous than RG4s. Both results are a consequence of their selection as high surface brightness systems. However, CG4s (especially those split among several regular groups) have luminosities similar to Control4Cs. The CG4s also have higher velocity dispersions, probably because of a too-permissive redshift accordance criterion. The BGGs of the CG4s are not any more dominant in luminosity than those of RG4s, but they are significantly more offset relative to the group size because the Lim groups are built around their BGGs. In summary, compact groups have similar properties to regular groups of four galaxies and to the cores of regular groups once the selection criteria of CGs are considered. A large fraction of CGs are the cores of regular groups, which are isolated on the sky by construction but rarely isolated in real space (from simulations), indicating that they are often plagued by chance alignments of host group galaxies along the line of sight.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20357v5</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthieu Tricottet, Gary A. Mamon, Eugenia D\'iaz-Gim\'enez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Post-Starburst Pathway for the Formation of Massive Galaxies and Black Holes at z&gt;6</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07113v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Understanding the rapid formation of supermassive black holes (SMBHs) in the early universe requires insight into stellar mass growth in host galaxies. Here, we present NIRSpec rest-frame optical spectra and NIRCam imaging from JWST of two galaxies at z&gt;6, both hosting moderate-luminosity quasars. These galaxies exhibit Balmer absorption lines, similar to low-redshift post-starburst galaxies. Our analyses of the medium-resolution spectra and multiband photometry show bulk of the stellar mass (log (M_* / M_sun) &gt; 10.6) formed in starburst episodes at redshift 9 and 7. One of the galaxies shows a clear Balmer break and lacks spatially resolved H alpha emission. It falls well below the star formation main sequence at z = 6, indicating quiescence. The other is transitioning to quiescence; together, these massive galaxies are among the most distant post-starburst systems known. The blueshifted wings of the quasar [O III] emission lines suggest quasar-driven outflow possibly influencing star formation. Direct stellar velocity dispersion measurements reveal one galaxy follows the local black hole mass-sigma_* relation while the other is overmassive. The existence of massive post-starburst galaxies hosting billion-solar-mass BHs in short-lived quasar phases suggests SMBHs and host galaxies played a major role in each other's rapid early formation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07113v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masafusa Onoue, Xuheng Ding, John D. Silverman, Yoshiki Matsuoka, Takuma Izumi, Michael A. Strauss, Charlotte Ward, Camryn L. Phillips, Kei Ito, Irham T. Andika, Kentaro Aoki, Junya Arita, Shunsuke Baba, Rebekka Bieri, Sarah E. I. Bosman, Anna-Christina Eilers, Seiji Fujimoto, Melanie Habouzit, Zoltan Haiman, Masatoshi Imanishi, Kohei Inayoshi, Kazushi Iwasawa, Knud Jahnke, Nobunari Kashikawa, Toshihiro Kawaguchi, Kotaro Kohno, Chien-Hsiu Lee, Junyao Li, Alessandro Lupi, Jianwei Lyu, Tohru Nagao, Roderik Overzier, Jan-Torge Schindler, Malte Schramm, Matthew T. Scoggins, Kazuhiro Shimasaku, Yoshiki Toba, Benny Trakhtenbrot, Maxime Trebitsch, Tommaso Treu, Hideki Umehata, Bram Venemans, Marianne Vestergaard, Marta Volonteri, Fabian Walter, Feige Wang, Jinyi Yang, Haowen Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for exotic gravitational wave signals beyond general relativity using deep learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.20129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.20129v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The direct detection of gravitational waves by LIGO has confirmed general relativity (GR) and sparked rapid growth in gravitational wave (GW) astronomy. However, subtle post-Newtonian (PN) deviations observed during the analysis of high signal-to-noise ratio events from the observational runs suggest that standard waveform templates, which assume strict adherence to GR, might overlook signals from alternative theories of gravity. Incorporating these exotic signals into traditional search algorithms is computationally infeasible due to the vast template space required. This paper introduces a proof-of-principle deep learning framework for detecting exotic GW signals, leveraging neural networks trained on GR-based templates. Through their generalization ability, neural networks learn intricate features from the data, enabling the detection of signals that deviate from GR. We present the first study evaluating the capability of deep learning to detect beyond-GR signals, including a variety of PN orders. Our model achieves rapid and accurate identification of exotic GW signals across different luminosity distances, with performance comparable to GR-based detections. In particular, applying the model to the GW150914 event demonstrates excellent performance, highlighting the potential of AI-driven methods for detecting previously overlooked signals beyond GR. This work paves the way for new discoveries in gravitational wave astronomy, enabling the detection of signals that might escape traditional search pipelines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.20129v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/f85k-wtph</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review D 112, 024030 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Xin Wang, Xiaotong Wei, Chun-Yue Li, Tian-Yang Sun, Shang-Jie Jin, He Wang, Jing-Lei Cui, Jing-Fei Zhang, Xin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interacting phantom dark energy: new accelerating scaling attractors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18300v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We perform a detailed investigation of interacting phantom cosmology, by applying the powerful method of dynamical system analysis. We consider two well-studied interaction forms, namely one global and one local one, while the novel ingredient of our work is the examination of new potentials for the phantom field. Our analysis shows the existence of saddle matter-dominated points, stable dark-energy dominated points, and scaling accelerating solutions, that can attract the Universe at late times. As we show, some of the stable accelerating scaling attractors, in which dark matter and dark energy can co-exist, alleviating the cosmic coincidence problem, are totally new, even for the previously studied interaction rates, and arise purely from the novel potential forms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18300v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/7jrj-sn1z</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 112, no.2, 023519 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sudip Halder, S. D. Odintsov, Supriya Pan, Tapan Saha, Emmanuel N. Saridakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Spectre of Underdetermination in Modern Cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06095</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06095v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The scientific status of physical cosmology has been the subject of philosophical debate ever since detailed mathematical models of the Universe emerged from Einstein's general theory of relativity. Such debates have revolved around whether and to what extent cosmology meets established demarcation criteria for a discipline to be scientific, as well as determining how to best characterize cosmology as a science, given the unique challenges and limitations faced by a discipline which aims to study the origin, composition, and fate of the Universe itself. The present article revisits, in light of the dramatic progress in cosmology in recent decades, an earlier debate held in the 1950s between Herman Bondi and Gerald Whitrow regarding the scientific status of cosmology. We analyse cosmology's transition from an emerging science to a cornerstone of modern physics, highlighting its empirical successes in establishing the $\Lambda$-Cold Dark Matter ($\Lambda$CDM) model and in its delivery of various successful novel predictions. Despite this remarkable scientific success and progress, we argue that modern cosmology faces a further profound challenge: the permanent underdetermination of the microphysical nature of its exotic energy components: inflation, dark matter, and dark energy. Drawing historical parallels with the role of spectroscopy in revealing the microphysical nature of atomic physics, we argue that the epistemic barriers obstructing us from ascertaining the microphysical nature of these exotic energy components are significant, in turn casting doubt upon whether cosmology can ever transcend these particular epistemic challenges. We conclude by reflecting on the prospects for future breakthroughs and/or non-empirical arguments which could decide this issue conclusively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06095v2</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro G. Ferreira, William J. Wolf, James Read</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for Dark Matter with MeVCube</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13162</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13162v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: CubeSat technology is an emerging alternative to large-scale space telescopes due to its short development time and cost-effectiveness. MeVCube is a proposed CubeSat mission to study the least explored MeV gamma-ray sky, also known as the `MeV gap'. Besides being sensitive to a plethora of astrophysical phenomena, MeVCube can also be important in the hunt for dark matter. If dark matter is made up of evaporating primordial black holes, then it can produce photons in the sensitivity range of MeVCube. Besides, particle dark matter can also decay or annihilate to produce final state gamma-ray photons. We perform the first comprehensive study of dark matter discovery potential of a near-future MeVCube CubeSat mission. In all cases, we find that MeVCube will have much better discovery reach compared to existing limits in the parameter space. This may be an important step towards discovering dark matter through its non-gravitational interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13162v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akash Kumar Saha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational waves from vacuum bubbles: ultraviolet dependence on wall thickness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00939</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00939v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The gravitational wave (GW) spectrum from the first-order phase transition can be characterized by a few phenomenological parameters but with high degeneracies in model/data distinguishments. In this paper, we look into the high-frequency power law of the GW spectrum with preliminary numerical simulations for both quantum and semi-classical pictures of vacuum decay. We first reveal an anti-correlation of the high-frequency power law to a certain power of the ratio between the wall thickness and bubble radius at the onset of bubble collisions, which can be further approximated analytically by some other phenomenological model characteristics to break the model degeneracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00939v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun-Chen Wang, Shao-Jiang Wang, Zi-Yan Yuwen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\Lambda$CDM from broken diffeomorphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02541v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a simple field theory model with reduced invariance under diffeomorphisms whose energy-momentum tensor is identical to the sum of pressureless irrotational matter and a cosmological constant. The model action is built from a single scalar field with a canonical kinetic term without any potential or Lagrange multiplier terms. The coupling to gravity is realized through a particular transverse diffeomorphism invariant volume element. The corresponding sound speed is exactly zero in any background geometry and the model is dynamically identical to $\Lambda$CDM. By restoring the full diffeomorphism invariance through the introduction of Stueckelberg-like fields, we obtain an equivalent local scalar-vector theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02541v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/rxnw-gvyd</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Javier de Cruz P\'erez, Antonio L. Maroto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Simplest Dark Matter Model at the Edge of Perturbativity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02408</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02408v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Increasingly sensitive direct detection dark matter experiments are testing important regions of parameter space for WIMP dark matter and pushing many models to the multi-TeV regime. This brings into question the perturbativity of these models. In this context, and in light of the new limits from the LZ experiment, we investigate the status of the simplest thermal dark matter model: a singlet scalar, real or complex, coupled to the Higgs boson. We calculate the next-to-leading order (NLO) corrections to the direct detection rates as well as for the annihilations driving thermal freeze-out. For the complex case, we find that the entire perturbative region is excluded by direct detection. For the real case we find that the mass should be $\gtrsim 20\,{\rm TeV}$ at NLO, compared with the $\gtrsim 30\,{\rm TeV}$ LO limit. We highlight that a three-fold improvement on WIMP spin independent interactions can fully test the real scalar model in the perturbative regime. Finally, for both models, there is still an allowed (albeit narrow) region near the Higgs resonance where couplings are perturbative.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02408v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2025.139696</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Lett.B 868 (2025) 139696</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Escudero, Thomas Hambye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phantom matters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10410v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Cosmological observations of the recent universe suggest that dark energy equation of state parameter $w$ is growing with time, departing from a cosmological constant for which $w=-1$. Standard quintessence models allow for a varying $w\geq-1$, but observations report that a phantom regime, $w&lt;-1$, is quickly reached in the past. Often discarded because of uncertainties or parametrisation, we rather propose here to embrace the reality of this phantom regime. We revisit an elegant mechanism that accounts for it, thanks to a coupling of quintessence field(s) to matter (and possibly radiation). We show that this allows for steep scalar potentials, and illustrate this with string-inspired models, where $V=V_0\, e^{-\lambda\, \varphi}$ and $\lambda \geq \sqrt{2}$. Those provide solutions in very good agreement with observations, including the phantom regime. We then discuss poles that can appear in $w$, making it diverge at recent times ($z\leq 4$), and that could be detected by observations. We finally comment on an Early Dark Energy-like feature, that systematically appears for free from the models considered, and could be of interest for the Hubble tension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10410v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Andriot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational-Wave Background from Extragalactic Double White Dwarfs for LISA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18390v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent studies have revealed the contribution of extragalactic DWD to the astrophysical SGWB could be detectable in the mHz regime by LISA. Conversely, the presence of this SGWB could hamper the detection of cosmological SGWB, which are one of the key targets of GW astronomy. We aim to confirm the spectrum of the extragalactic DWD SGWB and estimate its detectability with LISA under different assumptions. We also aim at understanding the main uncertainties in the spectrum and estimate if the signal could be anisotropic. We use population synthesis code COSMIC with several assumptions on binary evolution and initial conditions. We incorporate a specific treatment to account for the mass transfer and tidal torques after DWDs formation. Our study is in global agreement with previous studies, although we find a lower contribution at high frequencies, due to a different treatment of mass transfer in stellar binaries. We find that the uncertainties in the amplitude are dominated by the SFR model, and to a lesser degree by the binary evolution model. The inclusion of tidal effects and mass transfer episodes in DWDs can change the amplitude of the estimated SGWB up to a factor 3 at the highest frequencies. For all the models, we find that this SGWB would be detectable observable by LISA after 4 years. Under the hypothesis of an homogeneous Universe beyond 200Mpc, anisotropies associated to the astrophysical population of DWDs will likely not be detectable. We provide fits of this SGWB under different assumptions to be used by the community. We demonstrate variability in SGWB predictions, emphasizing uncertainties due to different astrophysical assumptions. We highlight the importance of determining the position of the knee in the SGWB spectrum, as it provides insights on mass transfer models. The prediction of this SGWB is of critical importance for LISA in the context of observing other SGWB.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18390v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillaume Boileau, Tristan Bruel, Alexandre Toubiana, Astrid Lamberts, Nelson Christensen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological perturbations for smooth sign-switching dark energy models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18992v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we carry out a comprehensive perturbative analysis of four cosmological models featuring a sign-switching cosmological constant. Among these, we include the well-known $\Lambda_{\rm s}$CDM model, characterised by an abrupt transition from a negative to a positive cosmological constant. We also consider the L$\Lambda$CDM model, which exhibits a generalised ladder-step evolution, as well as the SSCDM and ECDM models, both of which undergo a smooth sign change at comparable redshifts. We solve the linear cosmological perturbation equations from the radiation-dominated era, imposing initial adiabatic conditions for matter and radiation, for modes well outside the Hubble radius in the early Universe. We analyse the behaviour of the matter density contrast, the gravitational potential, the linear growth rate, the matter power spectrum, and the $f\sigma_8$ evolution . These results are contrasted with predictions from the standard $\Lambda$CDM model and are confronted with observational data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18992v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mariam Bouhmadi-L\'opez, Be\~nat Ibarra-Uriondo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Significance of soft-scale breaking on primordial black hole production in Coleman-Weinberg type supercooling-phase transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23752</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.23752v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Ultra-supercooling phase transitions can generate large overdensities in the Universe, potentially leading to the formation of primordial black holes (PBHs), which can also be a dark matter candidate. In this work, we focus on the supercooling phase transition for the scale symmetry breaking based on the effective potential of the Coleman-Weinberg (CW) type. We investigate the effect on the PBH production in the presence of an additional mass term for the CW scalar field, what we call a soft-scale breaking term, which serves as the extra explicit-scale breaking term other than the quantum scale anomaly induced by the CW mechanism. We demonstrate that even a small size of the soft-scale breaking term can significantly affect the PBH production depending on its sign: a positive term slows down the phase transition, thereby enhancing the PBH abundance and improving the model's ability to account for dark matter; in contrast, a negative term suppresses the PBH formation. The inclusion of such soft-scale breaking terms broadens the viable parameter space and increases the flexibility of the framework. We further illustrate our results through two ultraviolet-complete realizations: i) a many-flavor QCD-inspired model as a reference model which can dynamically induce a positive-soft scale breaking; ii) a Higgs portal model with a $B-L$ scalar as the benchmark for the case where a negative-soft scale breaking is induced. Our study would provide a new testable link between PBH dark matter and gravitational wave signatures in the CW-type scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.23752v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>He-Xu Zhang, Katsuya Hashino, Hiroyuki Ishida, Shinya Matsuzaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational waves from a dilaton-induced, first-order QCD phase transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.01191v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that a `QCD dilaton' field, whose vacuum expectation value sets the strong coupling, can render the Quantum Chromodynamic (QCD) confinement transition first-order. The QCD dilaton is cosmologically attracted to a false vacuum at weak coupling in the early universe. Quantum tunnelling towards the true vacuum triggers prompt chiral symmetry breaking and confinement of QCD, leading to detonating bubbles of the hadronic phase. We find that plasma sound waves produced by this dilaton-induced, first-order QCD phase transition generate a stochastic gravitational wave signal strikingly similar to the recently detected gravitational wave background from Pulsar Timing Arrays. We briefly comment on how this theory can be probed through collider experiments and cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.01191v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksandr Chatrchyan, M. C. David Marsh, Charalampos Nikolis</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
