<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO</link>
    <description>astro-ph.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 04:00:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Systematics mitigation for catalogue-based angular power spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19912v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent work has developed a formalism for computing angular power spectra directly from catalogues containing field values at discrete positions on the sky, thereby circumventing the need to create pixelised maps of the fields, as well as avoiding aliasing and finite-resolution effects. Here, we adapt this formalism to incorporate template deprojection as a means of mitigating systematic biases in the measured angular power spectra. We also introduce and validate an alternative method of mitigating the so-called `deprojection bias', caused by the loss of modes after deprojection, employing the use of simple simulations to compute a transfer function. We find that this approach performs at least as well as existing methods, and is relatively insensitive to how well one can guess the true power spectrum of the observed field, except at the largest scales ($\ell \lesssim 3$). Additionally, we develop exact expressions for the bias introduced by deprojection in the shot-noise component, which further improves the accuracy of this approach. We test our formalism on simulated datasets, demonstrating its applicability both to discretely sampled fields, and to the special case of galaxy clustering, with the survey selection function defined in terms of a random catalogue or as a continuous sky map. After computing and removing the bias in the shot noise and using a transfer function to correct for the remaining mode loss, our formalism is able to produce unbiased measurements of the angular power spectrum in all scenarios tested here. Finally, we apply our formalism to real data and demonstrate that it produces results consistent with the standard map-based pseudo-$C_\ell$ formalism. We implement our method in the publicly available code NaMaster.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19912v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Cornish, David Alonso, Boris Leistedt, Kevin Wolz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Determining the Hubble Constant through Cross-Correlation of Galaxies and Gravitational Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19931v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Gravitational wave (GW) standard sirens have the potential to measure the Hubble constant $H_0$ in the local universe independently of the distance ladder, and thus offer unique new insights into the Hubble tension. A key challenge with standard sirens is detecting their electromagnetic counterparts, and therefore assigning redshifts to the measured distances. One promising way to proceed is to utilize GW `dark sirens' -- events without an identified electromagnetic counterpart -- and cross-correlate their angular distribution with that of galaxies. We present a quantitative study of how precisely the Hubble constant can be measured using tomographic cross-correlation between galaxies and GW sources. Overall, we find that the constraints on $H_0$ will be limited by the quality and quantity of GW data. We find that percent-level constraints on $H_0$ will primarily depend on achieving small distance uncertainties ($\sigma_{d_L}=0.1\,d_L$), obtaining a large number of GW dark sirens ($\gtrsim$$5{,}000$), and accurate sky localization in the tomographic analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19931v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaming Pan, Dragan Huterer, Camille Avestruz, Damon H. T. Cheung, Emery Trott, Neal Dalal, Donghui Jeong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confirming the uniformity of the Hubble flow with Pantheon+ Supernovae</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19945v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: According to the perturbed Friedmann model, the difference between Hubble constant measurements in two rest frames, at leading order in velocity, is determined solely by the relative motion of the observers and remains unaffected by the peculiar velocities of the sources. This implies that, when averaging over a sufficiently large and distant set of sources where local nonlinear inhomogeneities are diminished, such a difference should vanish, so that the Hubble flow is statistically uniform, as predicted by the Cosmological Principle -- a core assumption of the standard cosmological paradigm. In previous works, distance measurement compilations, e.g. the CosmicFlows-3 catalogue, were used for this purpose, as it comprises a large number ($\sim 10^4$) of sources of different types. Due to the increasing amount of precise luminosity distance measurements of Type Ia Supenovae (SNe) in the last few years, in this work we investigate whether we can confirm the uniformity of the Hubble flow with low-$z$ SN distances only. By means of the Pantheon+ and SH0ES compilation, we find that the results align well with previous works based on the CF3 catalogue, and are in good agreement with the expected Hubble variance in the standard model across cosmic scales of $20-150$ Mpc. Notably, the Hubble constant difference $\Delta H_0 \approx 0$ is observed at around $85$ Mpc. Despite the smaller sample size ($\sim 10^2$ versus $\sim 10^4$) relative to CF3 at those scales, our analysis show that the Pantheon+ and SH0ES dataset supports the standard model paradigm, which indicates that the Hubble flow becomes statistically uniform at around $70-100$ Mpc, which is compatible with independent determinations of the homogeneity scale based on galaxy number counts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19945v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoyun Shao, Carlos A. P. Bengaly</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eppur non si trovano: Comments on the Primordial Black Hole Limits in the Galactic Halo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20005v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a recent arXiv post, Hawkins &amp; Garcia-Bellido raised doubts on the results of 20-yr long OGLE photometric monitoring, which did not find a large number of gravitational microlensing events in the direction of the Magellanic Clouds. These results implied that primordial black holes and other compact objects with masses from 10^{-8} to 10^3 M_solar cannot comprise a substantial fraction of the Milky Way dark matter halo. Unfortunately, the Hawkins &amp; Garcia-Bellido post contained a number of scientific misrepresentations of our work. Here, we demonstrate that their arguments lack a solid basis or are simply incorrect. As we show below, "and yet they are not found" - compact objects (including primordial black holes) in the dark halo of the Milky Way remain undetected, despite extensive searches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20005v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Mr\'oz, A. Udalski, M. K. Szyma\'nski, I. Soszy\'nski, {\L}. Wyrzykowski, P. Pietrukowicz, S. Koz{\l}owski, R. Poleski, J. Skowron, D. Skowron, K. Ulaczyk, M. Gromadzki, K. Rybicki, P. Iwanek, M. Wrona, M. Ratajczak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MG-NECOLA: Fast Neural Emulators for Modified Gravity Cosmologies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20086v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Observations of the large-scale structure (LSS) provide a powerful test of gravity on cosmological scales, but high-resolution N-body simulations of modified gravity (MG) are prohibitively expensive. We present MG-NECOLA, a convolutional neural network that enhances fast MG-PICOLA simulations to near-N-body fidelity at a fraction of the cost. MG-NECOLA reproduces QUIJOTE-MG N-body results in the power spectrum and bispectrum with better than 1% accuracy down to non-linear scales ($k \simeq 1~h~\mathrm{Mpc}^{-1}$), while reducing computational time by several orders of magnitude. Importantly, although trained only on $f(R)$ models with massless neutrinos, the network generalizes robustly to scenarios with massive neutrinos, preserving accuracy to within 5% at non-linear scales. This combination of precision and robustness establishes MG-NECOLA as a practical emulator for producing large ensembles of high-fidelity simulations, enabling efficient exploration of modified gravity and beyond-$\Lambda$CDM cosmologies in upcoming surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20086v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Bayron Orjuela-Quintana, Mauricio Reyes, Elena Giusarma, Francisco Villaescusa-Navarro, Neerav Kaushal, C\'esar A. Valenzuela-Toledo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Joint Observation of the CSST Shear and clustering of astrophysical gravitational wave source measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20203v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive forecast for cosmological constraints using the joint observation of the cosmic shear signal from the Chinese Space Station Survey Telescope (CSST) and the clustering signal from the next-generation gravitational wave (GW) detector networks, e.g. Einstein Telescope (ET) and Cosmic Explorer (CE). By leveraging the angular clustering of astrophysical gravitational wave sources (AGWS) from the third-generation detectors and CSST's weak lensing surveys, we develop a theoretical framework to compute auto- and cross-angular power spectra of AGWS clustering, cosmic shear, and their cross-correlation. Mock datasets are generated by considering the detector-specific selection functions, uncertainties in luminosity distance, and weak lensing systematics. We employ the Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) methods to constrain the $\Lambda \mathrm{CDM}$ cosmological parameters, AWGS bias parameters, and star formation rate (SFR) parameters under three detector configurations. Our results demonstrate that the joint observation can achieve sub-$5\%$ precision on $H_0$ ($2.19\%$) and $w$ ($5.7\%$). Besides, the AGWS clustering bias parameters can be constrained to the precision of $4\%-5\%$, enabling the differentiation between stellar-origin compact binaries and primordial black hole scenarios. This multi-messenger approach can also be helpful to resolve mass-redshift degeneracies in the dark siren methods, providing independent validation for the Hubble tension. Our work indicates that the joint observation of the third-generation GW detectors and the CSST can be a powerful probe of the large-scale structure and the cosmic expansion history.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20203v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pengfei Su, Yan Gong, Qi Xiong, Dingao Hu, Hengjie Lin, Furen Deng, Xuelei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blue supergiants and the zero point of the Tully-Fisher relation: a path to a new independent test of the Hubble constant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20652</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20652v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Blue supergiant distances of nearby galaxies obtained with the flux-weighted gravity-luminosity relationship are used for a measurement of the zero points of Tully-Fisher relationships at different photometric passbands. The Cousins I-band and the infrared WISE bands W1 and W2 are investigated. The results are compared with previous work using Cepheid and Tip-of-the-Red-Giant-Branch distances. No significant differences were encountered. This supports the large values of the Hubble constant greater than 73km/s/Mpc found with the Tully-Fisher distance ladder work over the last decade. Applying blue supergiant distances on the I-band Tully-Fisher relation observations yields a Hubble constant H0 = 76.2+/-6.2 km/s/Mpc. The large uncertainty is caused by the still relatively small blue supergiant galaxies sample size but will be reduced in future work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20652v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2025, The Astrophysical Journal</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Rolf-Peter Kudritzki, Fabio Bresolin, Miguel A. Urbaneka, Eva Sextl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Niebla: an open-source code for modelling the extragalactic background light</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20664v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Extragalactic very high-energy (VHE; $E&gt;100\,$GeV) gamma rays suffer absorption in interactions with photons of the Extragalactic Background Light (EBL). The EBL is an isotropic diffuse photon field from optical to infrared wavelengths, which is difficult to measure directly due to strong foreground emission. We present niebla, the first open-source code to compute the EBL using a forward-folding approach that accepts fully customizable inputs. This software enables a detailed modelling of the influence of EBL opacities on VHE observations and facilitates the distinction between different dust reemission models. The code models the optical background primarily from stellar emission, by evolving the spectrum of a single stellar population as a function of redshift, considering mean metallicity evolution and star formation rate density. Additional sources to the EBL can be provided by the user. The code already includes optional contributions from, e.g., stripped stars, intra-halo light, or the decay of axion dark matter. The optical emissivity is then absorbed by interstellar dust and reemitted in the infrared regime. We provide multiple prescriptions to model this process, using spectral dust templates or a combination of blackbodies. We provide three EBL models calculated with different dust reemission prescriptions, which have been fitted to various observational data sets. In addition, we showcase the versatility of our model through a simulated observation of the blazar Markarian 501 in a high-flux state with the Large High Altitude Air Shower Observatory array. We find that the simulated VHE spectrum is highly sensitive to the EBL opacity coming from the infrared. Our model will therefore allow the community to distinguish between different dust reemission models and constrain EBL parameters with future observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20664v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sara Porras-Bedmar, Manuel Meyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring cosmic dipole with the GRB luminosity-time relation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20705v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a new analysis of cosmic dipole anisotropy using gamma-ray bursts (GRBs) as high-redshift standardizable candles. GRBs are ideal probes for testing the cosmological principle thanks to their high luminosity, wide redshift range, and nearly isotropic sky coverage. For the first time, we employ the luminosity-time (L-T) relation, known in the literature as the bidimensional X-ray Dainotti relation, corrected for redshift evolution, to standardize a sample of 176 long GRBs detected by \textit{Swift}. We test for dipolar modulations in the GRB Hubble diagram using both the Dipole Fit Method and a new approach introduced here, the Anisotropic Residual Analysis Method. Both methods yield consistent results: a dipole amplitude of $A_d \simeq 0.6 \pm 0.2$ pointing towards (RA, DEC) $\approx (134^\circ \pm 30^{\circ}, -36^\circ \pm 21^{\circ})$ (equatorial coordinates). As shown in the Appendix, this corresponds to a boost velocity of the observer with respect to the GRB rest-frame in the antipodal direction from the dipole direction. Extensive isotropy tests and 20,000 Monte Carlo simulations confirm that the detected signal cannot be explained by chance alignments or by the angular distribution of the GRB sample. We also show how, by incorporating a dipole term, residual correlations are eliminated, showing that the dipole model provides a better fit than standard isotropic $\Lambda$CDM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20705v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jessica Santiago, Kerkyra Asvesta, Maria Giovanna Dainotti, Pisin Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Iskay2: Signal Extraction of the Kinematic Sunyaev-Zel'dovich Effect Through The Pairwise Estimator. Pipeline and Validation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20715v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The peculiar motions of massive halos probe the distribution of matter in the universe, the gravitational potential, and the history of cosmic structure growth. The kinematic Sunyaev-Zeldovich (kSZ) effect offers a robust observational window into these properties. The pairwise kSZ estimator probes the pairwise momentum of groups of galaxies by cross-correlating cosmic microwave background (CMB) maps with spectroscopic galaxy catalogs, using galaxies to trace the positions of dark matter halos. This note introduces iskay2, an efficient pipeline designed to apply the pairwise kSZ estimator to maps of the CMB and large galaxy catalogs. Pairwise kSZ measurements obtained using this pipeline are compared to previously published results and are shown to be consistent within statistical expectations. This pipeline will enable high-precision measurements of the pairwise kSZ utilizing galaxy catalogs like DESI combined with past, current and next-generation high-resolution CMB experiments such as ACT, SPT and the Simons Observatory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20715v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patricio A. Gallardo, Yulin Gong, Boryana Hadzhiyska, Yun-Hsin Hsu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lens Model Accuracy in the Expected LSST Lensed AGN Sample</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20778v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Strong gravitational lensing of active galactic nuclei (AGN) enables measurements of cosmological parameters through time-delay cosmography (TDC). With data from the upcoming LSST survey, we anticipate using a sample of O(1000) lensed AGN for TDC. To prepare for this dataset and enable this measurement, we construct and analyze a realistic mock sample of 1300 systems drawn from the OM10 (Oguri &amp; Marshall 2010) catalog of simulated lenses with AGN sources at $z&lt;3.1$ in order to test a key aspect of the analysis pipeline, that of the lens modeling. We realize the lenses as power law elliptical mass distributions and simulate 5-year LSST i-band coadd images. From every image, we infer the lens mass model parameters using neural posterior estimation (NPE). Focusing on the key model parameters, $\theta_E$ (the Einstein Radius) and $\gamma_{lens}$ (the projected mass density profile slope), with consistent mass-light ellipticity correlations in test and training data, we recover $\theta_E$ with less than 1% bias per lens, 6.5% precision per lens and $\gamma_{lens}$ with less than 3% bias per lens, 8% precision per lens. We find that lens light subtraction prior to modeling is only useful when applied to data sampled from the training prior. If emulated deconvolution is applied to the data prior to modeling, precision improves across all parameters by a factor of 2. Finally, we combine the inferred lens mass models using Bayesian Hierarchical Inference to recover the global properties of the lens sample with less than 1% bias.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20778v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Padmavathi Venkatraman, Sydney Erickson, Phil Marshall, Martin Millon, Philip Holloway, Simon Birrer, Steven Dillmann, Xiangyu Huang, Sreevani Jaragula, Ralf Kaehler, Narayan Khadka, Grzegorz Madejski, Ayan Mitra, Kevin Reil, Aaron Roodman, the LSST Dark Energy Science Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Debiasing cosmological parameters from large-scale foreground contamination in Cosmic Microwave Background data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20785v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Current and future Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) experiments aim to achieve high-precision reconstruction of the CMB polarization signal, with the most ambitious objective being the detection of primordial $B$ modes sourced by cosmic inflation. Given the expected low amplitude of the signal, its estimate, parametrized by the tensor-to-scalar ratio $r$, is highly susceptible to contamination from Galactic foreground residuals that remain after component separation. In this work, we introduce an agnostic, model-independent procedure to construct a spectral template of residual foreground contamination in the observed angular power spectrum. Specifically, a cleaned multifrequency set of foreground-emission maps is blindly reconstructed from the observed data using the Generalized Needlet Internal Linear Combination (GNILC) technique. These maps are then combined with the weights adopted for CMB reconstruction, yielding an estimate of the spatial distribution of foreground residuals after component separation. The power spectrum of this residual map, after proper noise debiasing, is incorporated into the spectral model of the cosmological likelihood, thereby enabling unbiased inference of cosmological parameters. We validate the method on realistic simulations of a LiteBIRD-like experiment, focusing on constraints on the tensor-to-scalar ratio. We demonstrate that including the residual template in the likelihood yields unbiased estimates of $r$, regardless of its input value, the assumed foreground model, or the adopted masking strategy, thus proving the robustness of the proposed procedure. The pipeline has been made publicly available as part of the BROOM Python package (https://github.com/alecarones/broom).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20785v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Carones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Addressing Synchrotron Challenges for CMB Observations: ELFS-SA Collaboration for Robust Foreground Removal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20793v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Upcoming cosmic microwave background (CMB) experiments aim to detect primordial gravitational waves with unprecedented sensitivity. Effective foreground removal is essential to avoid biases in the measurement of the tensor-to-scalar ratio ($r$) in this high-precision regime. Recent analyses highlight the unexpected complexity of synchrotron emission at low frequencies, underscoring the need for more sensitive low-frequency data. To address this challenge, the European Low-Frequency Survey (ELFS) initiative and the Simons Array collaboration propose installing two European low-frequency receivers on one of the Simons Array telescopes. These receivers will enable measurements in the Southern Hemisphere between $6$ and $20$,GHz, complementary to those of current and proposed experiments targeting the measurement of cosmological gravitational waves. In this work, we study the benefits of combining these low-frequency observations with a representative future CMB experiment operating from the Southern Hemisphere. We find that the extra information can improve the knowledge of the underlying synchrotron spectral energy distribution (SED), with positive impacts on the robustness of measurement of the tensor-to-scalar ratio, $r$, against the complexity of low-frequency foregrounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20793v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. de la Hoz, A. Mennella, K. Arnold, C. Baccigalupi, A. J. Banday, R. B. Barreiro, D. Barron, M. Bersanelli, F. J. Casas, S. Casey, C. Franceschet, M. E. Jones, R. T. Gen\'ova-Santos, R. Hoyland, A. T. Lee, E. Martinez-Gonzalez, F. Montonati, J. -A. Rubi\~no-Mart\'in, A. C. Taylor, P. Vielva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Inference of Primordial Magnetic Field Parameters from CMB with Spherical Graph Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20795v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Deep learning has emerged as a transformative methodology in modern cosmology, providing powerful tools to extract meaningful physical information from complex astronomical datasets. This paper implements a novel Bayesian graph deep learning framework for estimating key cosmological parameters in a primordial magnetic field (PMF) cosmology directly from simulated Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) maps. Our methodology utilizes DeepSphere, a spherical convolutional neural network architecture specifically designed to respect the spherical geometry of CMB data through HEALPix pixelization. To advance beyond deterministic point estimates and enable robust uncertainty quantification, we integrate Bayesian Neural Networks (BNNs) into the framework, capturing aleatoric and epistemic uncertainties that reflect the model confidence in its predictions. The proposed approach demonstrates exceptional performance, achieving $R^{2}$ scores exceeding 0.89 for the magnetic parameter estimation. We further obtain well-calibrated uncertainty estimates through post-hoc training techniques including Variance Scaling and GPNormal. This integrated DeepSphere-BNNs framework not only delivers accurate parameter estimation from CMB maps with PMF contributions but also provides reliable uncertainty quantification, providing the necessary tools for robust cosmological inference in the era of precision cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20795v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan Alejandro Pinto Castro, H\'ector J. Hort\'ua, Jorge Enrique Garc\'ia-Farieta, Roger Anderson Hurtado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient analytic approximation for small-scale non-cold relic perturbations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20821v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a highly accurate analytic approximation for small-scale non-cold relic perturbations by solving the collisionless Boltzmann equation in the quasi-stationary regime. The approximation is implemented in CLASSIER (CLASS Integral Equation Revision), a modified version of the Boltzmann solver CLASS that replaces the traditional truncated Boltzmann hierarchy of non cold relic multipoles with a small set of integral equations solved iteratively. Applying it to massive neutrinos yields a factor-of-two reduction in total runtime relative to CLASSIER without the approximation. Compared to standard CLASS runs (with $\ell_{\rm max}^{\rm NCDM}=40$ and no late-time massive neutrino fluid approximation) under the same precision setting, CLASSIER with this approximation is faster by a factor of 3-6. The approximation faithfully reproduces the late-time behavior of massive neutrino perturbations and preserves sub-$0.1\%$ accuracy in the matter power spectrum today up to comoving wavenumber $k=100\,{\rm Mpc}^{-1}$. With this approximation, massive-neutrino perturbations are no longer the computational bottleneck on small scales for linear-theory predictions. The approach can be readily extendable to non-standard dark-matter models, and offers prospects for further efficiency gains in high-precision cosmological analyses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20821v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nanoom Lee, Yacine Ali-Ha\"imoud, Marc Kamionkowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tracing Inflationary Imprints Through the Dark Ages: Implications for Early Stars and Galaxies Formation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19863</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19863v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explore how inflationary features shape the early stages of cosmic structure formation. Using the transfer function formalism, we trace the evolution of primordial perturbations, showing how causal physics and oscillatory signatures from inflation influence the matter power spectrum. The variance of smoothed density fields is then applied to model the collapse of overdense regions and predict dark matter halo abundances through the Press-Schechter framework. Extending to the baryonic sector, we analyze primordial gas collapse in minihalos, emphasizing molecular hydrogen cooling and the thermochemical pathways leading to Population III star formation. Finally, we examine primordial black holes as potential seeds for early galaxies, connecting their accretion-driven growth to the stellar masses and disk properties of high-redshift systems. Our results indicate that oscillatory features from inflation can leave measurable imprints on halo abundances and early galaxy properties, providing a testable link between high-energy physics and astrophysical observations with JWST</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19863v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. El Bourakadi, M. Yu. Khlopov, M. Krasnov, H. Chakir, M. Bennai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterising the properties of the atmospheric emission at Teide Observatory in the 10-20 GHz range with QUIJOTE data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19878v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: QUIJOTE is a CMB experiment composed of two telescopes, QT1 and QT2, located at the Teide Observatory in Tenerife, Spain. The MFI instrument (2012-2018), installed on QT1, observed the sky at four frequency bands (11, 13, 17, and 19 GHz) with one degree angular resolution. Its successor, MFI2, began operations in 2024 and operates in the same bands. This paper has two main goals: first, to characterise the atmospheric conditions at Teide Observatory to improve existing models at these frequencies, and second, to empirically characterise atmospheric turbulence using QUIJOTE MFI and MFI2 observations. This work has implications for both atmospheric physics and CMB studies and can support future reanalyses of MFI data or the preparation of upcoming instruments such as the Tenerife Microwave Spectrometer. We used data from GPS antennas, the STELLA observatory, and radio soundings to derive median profiles and distributions of key atmospheric parameters for 2012-2018. MFI data were analysed to compute atmospheric structure functions at 17 and 19 GHz and to study the correlation properties of the atmospheric signal through cross-correlation between horns at the same frequency. MFI2 observations were used to estimate the atmospheric power spectrum and compare it with the structure function derived from MFI data. The water vapour density profile follows an exponential decay with a characteristic half-height of about 1000 m. Median PWV in 2012-2018 is 3.3 mm. For high PWV conditions, the structure function agrees with the Kolmogorov turbulence model. The slope of the power spectrum also matches the model prediction, within the frequency range limited by the outer scale and instrument noise. Finally, from the correlation function, we find that atmospheric conditions remain stable for about 1-2 hours.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19878v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Apolline Chappard, Jos\'e Alberto Rubi\~no-Mart\'in, Ricardo Tanaus\'u G\'enova Santos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ly{\alpha}NNA II: Field-level inference with noisy Ly{\alpha} forest spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19899v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Deep learning (DL) has been shown to outperform traditional, human-defined summary statistics of the Ly{\alpha} forest in constraining key astrophysical and cosmological parameters owing to its ability to tap into the realm of non-Gaussian information. An understanding of the impact of nuisance effects such as noise on such field-level frameworks, however, still remains elusive. In this work we conduct a systematic investigation into the efficacy of DL inference from noisy Ly{\alpha} forest spectra. Building upon our previous, proof-of-concept framework (Nayak et al. 2024) for pure spectra, we constructed and trained a ResNet neural network using labeled mock data from hydrodynamical simulations with a range of noise levels to optimally compress noisy spectra into a novel summary statistic that is exclusively sensitive to the power-law temperature-density relation of the intergalactic medium. We fit a Gaussian mixture surrogate with 23 components through our labels and summaries to estimate the joint data-parameter distribution for likelihood free inference, in addition to performing inference with a Gaussian likelihood. The posterior contours in the two cases agree well with each other. We compared the precision and accuracy of our posterior constraints with a combination of two human defined summaries (the 1D power spectrum and PDF of the Ly{\alpha} transmission) that have been corrected for noise, over a wide range of continuum-to-noise ratios (CNR) in the likelihood case. We found a gain in precision in terms of posterior contour area with our pipeline over the said combination of 65% (at a CNR of 20 per 6 km/s) to 112% (at 200 per 6 km/s). While the improvement in posterior precision is not as large as in the noiseless case, these results indicate that DL still remains a powerful tool for inference even with noisy, real-world datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19899v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Parth Nayak, Michael Walther, Daniel Gruen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Warped Dimensions at the Cosmological Collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19900</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19900v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Extra dimensions are present in many beyond the Standard Model scenarios, most notably in string theory. However, direct signatures of extra dimensions are difficult to observe in many cases. This is the situation, for example, if the energy scales associated with extra dimensions are close to the string or Grand Unification scale. The energetic early universe provides an exciting opportunity to overcome this challenge, since the heavy states associated with high-scale extra dimensions, such as scalar moduli and Kaluza-Klein (KK) gravitons, could have been produced on-shell at early epochs. In this work, we illustrate this by focusing on how such states can be produced during inflation and leave signatures in primordial non-Gaussianity (NG). Specifically, we consider a 5D spacetime with a warped extra dimension that remains stabilized as inflation proceeds in the four non-compact dimensions. By discussing an explicit stabilization mechanism, we compute the masses and couplings of the radion modulus and the KK graviton modes. Being gravitational degrees of freedom, these unavoidably couple to the field(s) generating curvature perturbation, and can lead to observable NG with a distinctive oscillatory shape and characteristic angular dependence. We give example benchmarks which can already be probed by the Planck data and identify targets for the future. Our study shows that cosmological surveys have the potential to observe on-shell imprints of extra dimensions in the coming years.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19900v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soubhik Kumar, Michael Nee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Synthetic Absorption Line Spectral Almanac (SALSA)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19904v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We create the first large-scale mock spectroscopic survey of gas absorption sightlines traversing the interstellar medium (ISM), circumgalactic medium (CGM), and intergalactic medium (IGM) surrounding galaxies of virtual Universes. That is, we create mock, or synthetic, absorption spectra by drawing lines-of-sight through cosmological hydrodynamical simulations, using a new mesh-free Voronoi ray-tracing algorithm. The result is the Synthetic Absorption Line Spectral Almanac (SALSA), which is publicly released on a feature-rich online science platform (www.tng-project.org/spectra). It spans a range of ions, transitions, instruments, observational characteristics, assumptions, redshifts, and simulations. These include, but are not limited to: (ions) HI, OI, CI, MgI, MgII, FeII, SiII, CaII, ZnII, SiIII, SiIV, NV, CII, CIV, OVI; (instruments) SDSS-BOSS, KECK-HIRES, UVES, COS, DESI, 4MOST, WEAVE, XSHOOTER; (model choices) with/without dust depletion, noise, quasar continua, foregrounds; (redshift) from z=0 to z~6; (ancillary data) integrated equivalent widths, column densities, distances and properties of nearby galaxies; (simulations) IllustrisTNG including TNG50, TNG-Cluster, EAGLE, and SIMBA. This scope is not fixed, and will grow and evolve with community interest and requests over time -- suggestions are welcome. The resulting dataset is generic and broadly applicable, enabling diverse science goals such as: (i) studies of the underlying physical gas structures giving rise to particular absorption signatures, (ii) galaxy-absorber and halo-absorber correlations, (iii) virtual surveys and survey strategy optimization, (iv) stacking experiments and the identification of faint absorption features, (v) assessment of data reduction methods and completeness calculations, (vi) inference of physical properties from observables, and (vii) apples-to-apples comparisons between simulations and data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19904v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dylan Nelson, Celine Peroux, Philipp Richter, Matthew M. Pieri, Sebastian Lopez, Rongmon Bordoloi, Siwei Zou, Joseph N. Burchett, Rebecca L. Davies, Rahul Ramesh, Matthew C. Smith, Sanchayeeta Borthakur, Christopher W. Churchill</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting White Dwarf Binary Mergers with Gravitational Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19913</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19913v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Mergers of white dwarf binaries are a possible progenitor channel for Type Ia supernovae. While white dwarfs are abundant in the universe and relatively well understood, their gravitational wave signals have not yet been directly observed. In order to detect gravitational waves from merging white dwarf binaries, a detector in the mid-band between LVK and LISA appears necessary. In this paper, we compute and discuss the gravitational waves emitted by inspiraling and merging white dwarf binaries, and assess their detectability with proposed space-based atom-interferometer detectors such as MAGIS Space and AEDGE. Gravitational waves from massive white dwarf binaries can be observed for many years before merger, offering a unique early warning of their final explosion. Our projections suggest that MAGIS Space could detect signals from Type Ia supernova progenitors at least once every four years, while AEDGE could observe at least a few hundred such events annually. The prolonged gravitational wave emission captured by atom-interferometers provides precise sky localisation and can allow observation of the final explosion with electromagnetic telescopes. The combined observation with electromagnetic radiation from the white dwarf binary coalescence could open a new pathway for multi-messenger astronomy involving some of the brightest transient events in the universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19913v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giona Sala, Chiara Brandenstein, Sebastian Baum, Peter W. Graham</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Interstellar Metals during Reionization with Radiative SPH Simulation: Metallicity and Emission Lines from the ISM at $10 \geq z \geq 5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20021</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20021v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We compare the \texttt{Technicolor Dawn} cosmological simulations with recent observations of galactic nebular line emission during the Epoch of Reionization, providing stringent tests of the predicted ionization and metal enrichment levels. We validate the simulated population with the UVLF and $M_{\mathrm{UV}}-M_*$ relation and see that the simulated results are consistent with observations at lower masses. We extract local gas volumetric grids of density and mass-weighted metallicity, then we use \texttt{Cloudy} to produce synthetic emission spectra of \species{H}{ii} regions. The mass-metallicity relation does not evolve, which is also consistent with observations. The predicted oxygen abundance exceeds observational inferences by about 0.5 dex, suggesting either overly efficient enrichment or weak feedback. However, applying the O32 diagnostic directly to our synthetic spectra shows an offset of 1 dex from the correct outputted gas-phase metallicity. This suggests that O32 is biased high at a level that is more than sufficient to account for the simulation-observation offset. The simulated galaxies' line diagnostics show mostly weaker [\species{O}{iii}] lines and lower diagnostic values of O3 and Ne3O2 compared to observations. This suggests higher ionization parameters within the simulated galactic population in general.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20021v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samir Kusmic, Kristian Finlator, Ezra Huscher, Maya Steen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photometrically Selected Protocluster Candidates at z~9-10 in the JWST COSMOS-Web field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20172v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: High-redshift protoclusters are crucial for understanding the formation of galaxy clusters and the evolution of galaxies in dense environments. The James Webb Space Telescope (JWST), with its unprecedented near-infrared sensitivity, enables the first exploration of protoclusters beyond $z&gt;$10. Among JWST surveys, COSMOS-Web Data Release 0.5 offers the largest area $\sim$0.27 deg$^2$, making it an optimal field for protocluster searches. In this study, we searched for protoclusters at $z\sim$9-10 using 366 F115W dropout galaxies. We evaluated the reliability of our photometric redshift by validation tests with the JADES DR3 spectroscopic sample, obtaining the likelihood of falsely identifying interlopers as $\sim25\%$. Overdensities ($\delta$) are computed by weighting galaxy positions with their photometric redshift probability density functions (PDF), using a 2.5 cMpc aperture and a redshift slice of $\pm$0.5. We selected the most promising core galaxies of protocluster candidate galaxies with an overdensity greater than the 95th percentile of the distribution of 366 F115W dropout galaxies. The member galaxies are then linked within an angular separation of 7.5 cMpc to the core galaxies, finding seven protocluster candidates. These seven protocluster candidates have inferred halo masses of $M_{\text{halo}} \sim 10^{11} M_{\odot}$. The detection of such overdensities at these redshifts provides a critical test for current cosmological simulations. However, confirming these candidates and distinguishing them from low-redshift dusty star-forming galaxies or Balmer-break galaxies will require follow-up near-infrared spectroscopic observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20172v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/pasa.2025.10096</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Cossas K. -W. Wu, Chih-Teng Ling, Tomotsugu Goto, Amos Y. -A. Chen, Tetsuya Hashimoto, Seong Jin Kim, Simon C. -C. Ho, Ece Kilerci, Tiger Yu-Yang Hsiao, Yuri Uno, Terry Long Phan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bound State Perturbations in the Interior of Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20305</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20305v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We revisit our earlier work and investigate the bound state perturbations in the interior of the Schwarzschild black hole. The bound sates are defined as the perturbations in the interior of the black hole with an imaginary spectrum which are regular at the center of black hole while their time-dependent profile falls off exponentially on the event horizon. Using the scale factor in the expanding direction in the interior of the black hole as the clock, we rewrite the corresponding Regge-Wheeler equation and solve it semi-analytically as well as numerically. We confirm that the bound state solutions exist for scalar, vector and axial tensor perturbations. It is shown that for a given value of $\ell &gt;s$, there are total $\ell-s$ such bound states. We obtain the universal lower bound $2 G M \omega_I &gt;1$ for the spectrum of bound state which is asymptotically saturated in the large $\ell$ limit. Furthermore, we obtain an upper bound on the spectrum of axial perturbations which for large $\ell$ scales like $2 G M \omega_I \lesssim 0.04\, \ell^4 $. As observed recently, these bound states have the curious property that the profile of the total wave function has a non-zero magnitude near the future event horizon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20305v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hassan Firouzjahi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the observation of cosmic strings via gravitational-wave lensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20442v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a framework for detecting gravitational-wave signals lensed by cosmic strings (CSs), addressing a key gap in current searches. CSs, whose detection would provide a unique probe of high-energy physics and the early Universe, possess distinct topological and geometric features that require a dedicated search strategy. Our approach employs a full-wave transmission factor, expressed analytically via Fresnel integrals, which captures the characteristic diffraction and interference effects of the conical spacetime around a straight CS. We contrast CS lensing with the well-studied point mass lens (PML) model, highlighting their fundamental differences: CS lensing depends on cosmological distances, string tension $\Delta$, and wavelength $\lambda$, and produces two non-amplified images set by the global conical geometry. In contrast, PML lensing is governed by the distance-independent ratio $\sim M_{Lz}/\lambda$, where $M_{Lz}$ represents the redshifted mass of the lens, with image properties derived from the lens equation. For BBH mergers lensed by CSs, we show that the waveforms exhibit a characteristic beating pattern or time-separated, exact replicas. We derive a detectability bound on the string tension and, using Bayesian model selection, demonstrate that CS lensing is distinguishable from both unlensed and PML-lensed signals across a wide region of parameter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20442v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleg Bulashenko, Nino Villanueva, Roberto Bada Nerin, Jos\'e A. Font</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symbolic Regression and Differentiable Fits in Beyond the Standard Model Physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20453v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate the efficacy of symbolic regression (SR) to probe models of particle physics Beyond the Standard Model (BSM), by considering the so-called Constrained Minimal Supersymmetric Standard Model (CMSSM). Like many incarnations of BSM physics this model has a number (four) of arbitrary parameters, which determine the experimental signals, and cosmological observables such as the dark matter relic density. We show that analysis of the phenomenology can be greatly accelerated by using symbolic expressions derived for the observables in terms of the input parameters. Here we focus on the Higgs mass, the cold dark matter relic density, and the contribution to the anomalous magnetic moment of the muon. We find that SR can produce remarkably accurate expressions. Using them we make global fits to derive the posterior probability densities of the CMSSM input parameters which are in good agreement with those performed using conventional methods. Moreover, we demonstrate a major advantage of SR which is the ability to make fits using differentiable methods rather than sampling methods. We also compare the method with neural network (NN) regression. SR produces more globally robust results, while NNs require data that is focussed on the promising regions in order to be equally performant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20453v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1098/rsta.2024.0593</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society A - RSTA-2024-0593.R1</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shehu AbdusSalam, Steven Abel, Deaglan Bartlett, Miguel Crispim Rom\~ao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GUT-Scale Smooth Hybrid Inflation with a Stabilized Modulus in Light of ACT and SPT Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20478v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyze a generalized framework of smooth F-term hybrid inflation (smFHI) consistent with gauge coupling unification within the Minimal Supersymmetric Standard Model (MSSM). The embedding of the model in two specific Supergravity settings addresses at the same time the $\eta$ problem and the compatibility with the recent ACT or SPT data. The one relies on the choice of a shift-symmetric K\"ahler potential for the inflaton which revitalizes the SUSY predictions of smFHI, whereas the other employs a K\"ahler potential associated with an hyperbolic K\"ahler manifold. An essential role in both our constructions is played by a decoupled superheavy field without superpotential and Kaehler potential inspired by string- and D-brane--based models. Our proposal can be realized for a variety of representations for the Higgs fields involved in smFHI and assures monotonic inflationary potential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20478v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Waqas Ahmed, Constantinos Pallis, Mansoor Ur Rehman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Validation of NANOGrav 15-year data and ACT data by modified inflation in entropic cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20484</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20484v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent evidences of stochastic gravitational wave background (SGWB) through Pulsar Time Array (PTA) observations hint towards an alternative inflationary scenario, compared to the usual inflation, for describing the early stage of the universe in order to be compatible with the PTA data. Moreover, currently the Atacama Cosmology Telescope (combined with the Planck 2018 and BAO) refines the constraint on inflationary observables, compared to the only-Planck 2018 measurements. In the present work, we simultaneously address these two issues by incorporating certain modification during inflation over the usual inflationary scenario. Such modification amplifies the primordial tensor perturbation over the modes that are sensitive to the NANOGrav frequency region. For this purpose, we take the thermodynamic route of cosmology where the entropy of the apparent horizon is given by a generalized form of entropy that is able to generalize the other known form of horizon entropies for suitable representations. The constraints on the model parameters coming from the ACT data also fit the NANOGrav 15-year data (based on numerical analysis), which reveal the model's compatibility with both the ACT and the PTA data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20484v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simone D'Onofrio, Sergei Odintsov, Tanmoy Paul</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong Lensing Model and Dust Extinction Maps of the Host Galaxy of Type Ia Supernova H0pe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20561</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20561v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Strong gravitational lensing by massive galaxy clusters offers particularly rare opportunities to observe multiple images of distant ($z\gtrsim2$) Type Ia supernovae (SNe) and resolve the properties of their host galaxies. A recent outstanding example is the Type Ia SN "H0pe" ($z=1.78$), discovered in James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) NIRCam images when it was still triply imaged by the galaxy cluster PLCK G165.7+67.0 (G165, $z=0.35$). In this work we build a new strong lensing model of G165, first by using only the position of multiple images of background galaxies. We then increase significantly the number of constraints around the position of SN H0pe by modeling the extended surface brightness of the SN host galaxy. The average uncertainty on mass model parameters is reduced by more than an order of magnitude. We also study the spatial distribution of dust in the arc to estimate the dust extinction at the position of SN H0pe. We find good statistical agreement of the extinction estimate at $\lesssim1\sigma$ with three fully independent methods based on spectral energy distribution fitting. Moreover, our extended-image lens model of G165 allows us to map the dust distribution of the host galaxy from the image plane to the source plane. Supernova H0pe exploded in a region with a relatively high extinction of $A_V \approx 0.9\ {\rm mag}$ at around $\sim 1\ {\rm kpc}$ from its host center. This work shows that extended image modeling in lensing clusters simultaneously reduces the uncertainty on lens model parameters and enables spatially resolved analyses of lensed transients host galaxies. Such modeling advances are expected to play an important role in future cosmological analyses using strongly lensed SNe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20561v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Galan, S. Schuldt, G. B. Caminha, S. H. Suyu, R. Ca\~nameras, S. Ertl, C. Grillo, A. Acebron, B. Frye, A. M. Koekemoer, R. Windhorst, J. M. Diego, N. Foo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QCD corrections to the electroweak sphaleron rate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20594v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The electroweak sphaleron rate in the high temperature phase of the Standard Model is inversely proportional to the weak-isospin conductivity. So far, only electroweak interactions were included in its computation. Here we take into account quark scattering through strong interactions at leading-log order. These reduce the quark contribution to the conductivity by up to 15 %, and the total conductivity by up to 6 %.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20594v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dietrich B\"odeker, Philipp Klose</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification of Radio Backgrounds at Cosmic Dawn and 21 cm Signal Confirmation Using Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04792v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Several ongoing and upcoming radio telescopes aim to detect either the global 21 cm signal or the 21 cm power spectrum. The extragalactic radio background, as detected by ARCADE-2 and LWA-1, suggests a strong radio background from cosmic dawn, which can significantly alter the cosmological 21 cm signal, enhancing both the global signal amplitude and the 21 cm power spectrum. In this paper, we employ an artificial neural network (ANN) to check if there is a radio excess over the cosmic microwave background in mock data, and if present, we classify its type into one of two categories, a background from high-redshift radio galaxies or a uniform exotic background from the early Universe. Based on clean data (without observational noise), the ANN can predict the background radiation type with $96\%$ accuracy for the power spectrum and $90\%$ for the global signal. Although observational noise reduces the accuracy, the results remain quite useful. We also apply ANNs to map the relation between the 21 cm power spectrum and the global signal. By reconstructing the global signal using the 21 cm power spectrum, an ANN can estimate the global signal range consistent with an observed power spectrum from SKA-like experiments. Conversely, we show that an ANN can reconstruct the 21 cm power spectrum over a wide range of redshifts and wavenumbers given the global signal over the same redshifts. Such trained networks can potentially serve as a valuable tool for cross-confirmation of the 21 cm signal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04792v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ae0587</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Sudipta Sikder, Anastasia Fialkov, Rennan Barkana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing CMB noise anisotropies from CMB delensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20919v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Un-doing the effect of gravitational lensing on the Cosmic Microwave Background (`de-lensing') is essential in shaping constraints on weak signals limited by lensing effects on the CMB, for example on a background of primordial gravitational waves. Removing these anisotropies induced by large-scale structures from the CMB maps also generally helps our view of the primordial Universe by sharpening the acoustic peaks and the damping tail. However, practical implementations of delensing transfer parts of these anisotropies to the noise maps. This will induce a new large scale `mean-field' bias to any anisotropy estimator applied to the delensed CMB, and this bias directly traces large-scale structures. This paper analytically quantifies this delensed noise mean-field and its impact on quadratic (QE) and likelihood-based lensing estimators. We show that for Simons-Observatory-like surveys, this mean-field bias can reach 15\% in cross-correlation with large-scale structures if unaccounted for. We further demonstrate that this delensed noise mean-field can be safely neglected in likelihood-based estimators without compromising the quality of lensing reconstruction or $B$-mode delensing, provided the resulting lensing map is properly renormalized.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20919v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/dcj9-hhl4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 112, 083538, Published 21 October, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Louis Legrand, Julien Carron</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indicator Functions: Distilling the Information from Gaussian Random Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.06668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.06668v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A random Gaussian density field contains a fixed amount of Fisher information on the amplitude of its power spectrum. For a given smoothing scale, however, that information is not evenly distributed throughout the smoothed field. We investigate which parts of the field contain the most information by smoothing and splitting the field into different levels of density (using the formalism of indicator functions), deriving analytic expressions for the information content of each density bin in the joint-probability distribution (given a distance separation). When we choose one particular distance regime (i.e., cells separated by $60$-$80h^{-1}$ Mpc), we find that the information in that range peaks at moderately rare densities (where the number of smoothed survey cells is roughly of order of magnitude 100). Counter-intuitively, we find that, for a finite survey volume (again at a particular distance range), indicator function analysis can outperform conventional two-point statistics while using only a fraction of the total survey cells, and we explain why. In light of recent developments in marked statistics (such as the indicator power spectrum and density-split clustering), this result elucidates how to optimize sampling for effective extraction of cosmological information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.06668v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Repp, Ravi K. Sheth, Istvan Szapudi, Yan-Chuan Cai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining exotic high-$z$ reionization histories with Gaussian processes and the Cosmic Microwave Background</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19096v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The large-angle polarization anisotropies in the Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) arise from Thomson scattering of CMB photons off free electrons in the post-recombination Universe. In the standard $\Lambda$ cold dark matter cosmological model, the free electron density increases at redshifts $z \lesssim 10$ as the first stars form, reionizing the intergalactic medium. We use \emph{Gaussian processes} to perform a model-independent reconstruction of the cosmic reionization history constrained by \textit{Planck} CMB data. Our approach recovers the standard reionization at $z \lesssim 10$ and places stringent limits on any additional high-$z$ reionization. From this reconstruction, we define a new derived parameter, the high-redshift contribution to the CMB optical depth, $\tau_{\mathrm{highz}}$, whose posterior distribution provides robust constraints on exotic energy injection scenarios. We demonstrate this for decaying dark matter with particle masses in the range $\mathcal{O}(1\,\text{MeV})$. A companion paper applies this framework to multi-axion models. All data and code are publicly available at: \href{https://github.com/Cheng-Hanyu/CLASS_reio_gpr}{github.com/Cheng-Hanyu/CLASS\_reio\_gpr}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19096v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanyu Cheng, Ziwen Yin, Eleonora Di Valentino, David J. E. Marsh, Luca Visinelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resolving the negative effective neutrino mass parameter with cosmic birefringence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22999</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.22999v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The recent measurement of baryonic acoustic oscillations by the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument reveals a mild tension with observations of the cosmic microwave background (CMB) within the standard $\Lambda$CDM cosmological model. This discrepancy leads to a preference for a total neutrino mass that is lower than the minimum value inferred from neutrino oscillation experiments. Alternatively, this tension can be eased within $\Lambda$CDM by assuming a higher optical depth ($\tau \simeq 0.09$), but such a value conflicts with large-scale CMB polarization data. We point out that cosmic birefringence, as suggested by recent Planck reanalyses, resolves this discrepancy if the birefringence angle varies significantly during reionization. Specifically, we consider the fact that the measured cosmic birefringence angle $\beta_0=0.34\pm0.09\,(1\,\sigma)\,$deg has the phase ambiguity, i.e., the measured rotation angle is described by $\beta=\beta_0+180n\,$deg ($n\in \mathbb{Z}$). We show that cosmic birefringence induced by axion-like particles with nonzero $n$ suppresses the reionization bump, allowing a higher $\tau$ consistent with data. We provide a viable parameter space where the birefringence effect simultaneously accounts for the low-$\ell$ polarization spectra, the Planck $EB$ correlations, and the elevated value of $\tau$, suggesting a key role for cosmic birefringence in current cosmological tensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.22999v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Toshiya Namikawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinetic Fragmentation of the QCD Axion on the Lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01822</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.01822v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Kinetic misalignment, one of the most compelling scenarios for the non-thermal generation of axion dark matter, is generally accompanied by axion fragmentation, a process in which the energy of the axion condensate is transferred to its perturbations. The dynamics of fragmentation, at least in the context of dark matter production, have so far been studied semi-analytically using perturbation theory. In this work, we present the first classical lattice simulation of kinetic axion fragmentation in the context of dark matter production, focusing on parameters relevant to the QCD axion. Our findings indicate that the non-perturbative dynamics captured by the lattice lead to a significantly broader spectrum of axion fluctuations, with a sustained transfer of energy to mildly relativistic modes and with smaller occupation numbers compared to the linear approximation. As a consequence, the final dark matter abundance is typically O(1) lower than in the linear approximation, which is itself O(1) lower than the zero-mode-only prediction. This broadening and suppression of the spectrum could have a significant impact on axion mini-halo formation, one of the main experimental handles on kinetic fragmentation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.01822v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Fasiello, Joanes Lizarraga, Alexandros Papageorgiou, Ander Urio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Persistent and serious challenge to the $\Lambda$CDM throne: Evidence for dynamical dark energy rising from combinations of different types of datasets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.22856v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We derive multiple constraints on dark energy and compare dynamical dark energy models with a time-varying equation of state ($w_0 w_a$CDM) versus a cosmological constant model ($\Lambda$CDM). We use Baryon Acoustic Oscillation (BAO) from DESI and DES, Cosmic Microwave Background from Planck with and without lensing from Planck and ACT (noted CMBL and CMB, respectively), supernova (SN), and cross-correlations between galaxy positions and galaxy lensing from DES. First, we use pairs or trios of datasets where we exclude one type of dataset each time and categorize them as ``NO SN", ``NO CMB" and ``NO BAO" combinations. In all cases, we find that the combinations favor the $w_0 w_a$CDM model over $\Lambda$CDM, with significance ranging from 2.3$\sigma$ to 3.3$\sigma$. For example, DESI+DESY6BAO+CMB yields 3.2$\sigma$ without SN, DESI+DESY6BAO+DESY5SN yields 3.3$\sigma$ without CMB, and CMB+DESY5SN+DES3x2pts yields 2.6$\sigma$ without BAO. The persistence of this pattern across various dataset combinations even when any of the datasets is excluded supports an overall validation of this trending result regardless of any specific dataset. Next, we use larger combinations of these datasets after verifying their mutual consistency within the $w_0 w_a$CDM model. We find combinations that give significance levels $\sim$4$\sigma$, with DESI+DESY6BAO+CMBL+DESY5SN reaching 4.4$\sigma$. In sum, while we need to remain prudent, the combination of the first step that supports a validation of the pattern of these results beyond any single type of dataset and their associated systematics, together with the second step showing high-significance results when such datasets are combined, presents a compelling overall portrait in favor of a dynamical dark energy with a time-evolving equation of state over a cosmological constant, and constitutes a serious challenge to the $\Lambda$CDM model's reign. Abridged.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.22856v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mustapha Ishak, Leonel Medina-Varela</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bright siren without electromagnetic counterpart by LISA-Taiji-TianQin network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04218</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04218v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Gravitational waves (GWs) with electromagnetic counterparts (EMc) offer a novel approach to measure the Hubble constant ($H_0$), known as bright sirens, enabling $H_0$ measurements by combining GW-derived distances with EM-derived redshifts. Host galaxy identification is essential for redshift determination but remains challenging due to poor GW sky localization and uncertainties in EMc models. To overcome these limitations, we exploit the ultra-high-precision localization ($\Delta \Omega_s \sim 10^{-4} \, \text{deg}^2$) with a space-based GW detector network (LISA-Taiji-TianQin), which permits unique host identification solely from GW signals. We integrate five massive black hole binary (MBHB) population models and two galaxy number density models to compute the redshift horizon for host galaxy identification and evaluate $H_0$ constraints. We find that (1) The network enhances localization by several orders of magnitude compared to single detectors; (2) The identification horizon reaches $z\sim 1.2$ for specific MBHBs in the most accurate localization case; (3) The population model choice critically impacts the outcomes: the most refined population models yield to independent EMc identification rate of 0.6-1 $\text{yr}^{-1}$ with $H_0$ constraints $&lt; 1\%$ fractional uncertainty, the less refined models lead to the rate $&lt;0.1\text{yr}^{-1}$ and $1-2\%$ uncertainty on $H_0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04218v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yejing Zhan, David Izquierdo-Villalba, Xiao Guo, Qing Yang, Daniele Spinoso, Fa-Yin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Hubble Tension resolved by the DESI Baryon Acoustic Oscillations Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17454</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.17454v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The $\Lambda$ cold dark matter ($\Lambda$CDM) cosmological model provides a good description of a wide range of astrophysical and cosmological observations. However, severe challenges to the phenomenological $\Lambda$CDM model have emerged recently, including the Hubble constant tension and the significant deviation from the $\Lambda$CDM model reported by the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) collaboration. Despite many explanations for the two challenges have been proposed, the origins of them are still intriguing mysteries. Here, we investigate the DESI Baryon Acoustic Oscillations (BAOs) measurements to interpret the Hubble constant tension. Employing a non-parametric method, we find that the dark energy equation of state $w(z)$ evolves with redshift from DESI BAO data and type Ia supernovae. From the Friedmann equations, the Hubble constant ($H_0$) is derived from $w(z)$ model-independently. We find that the values of $H_0$ show a descending trend as a function of redshift, and can effectively resolve the Hubble constant tension. Our study finds that the two unexpected challenges to the $\Lambda$CDM model can be understood in one physical framework, e.g., dynamical dark energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.17454v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>X. D. Jia, J. P. Hu, D. H. Gao, S. X. Yi, F. Y. Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Broader view of bimetric MOND</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.10882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.10882v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: All existing treatments of bimetric MOND (BIMOND) -- a class of relativistic versions of MOND -- have dealt with a rather restricted sub-class: The Lagrangian of the interaction between the gravitational degrees of freedom -- the two metrics -- is a function of a certain {\it single} scalar argument built from the difference in connections of the two metrics. I show that the scope of BIMOND is much richer: The two metrics can couple through several scalars to give theories that all have a "good" nonrelativistic (NR) limit -- one that accounts correctly, a-la MOND, for the dynamics of galactic systems, {\it including gravitational lensing}. This extended-BIMOND framework exhibits a qualitative departure from the way we think of MOND at present, as encapsulated, in all its aspects, by one "interpolating function" of one acceleration variable. After deriving the general field equations, I pinpoint the subclass of theories that satisfy the pivotal requirement of a good NR limit. These involve three independent, quadratic scalar variables. In the NR limit these scalars all reduce to the same acceleration scalar, and the NR theory then does hinge on one function of a {\it a single} acceleration variable -- representing the NR MOND "interpolating function", whose form is largely dictated by the observed NR galactic dynamics. However, these scalars behave differently, in different relativistic contexts. So, the full richness of the multi-variable Lagrangian, as it enters cosmology, for example, is hardly informed by what we learn from observations of galactic dynamics. In this paper, I present the formalism, with some generic examples. I also consider some cosmological solutions where the two metrics are small departures from one Friedman-Lemaitre-Robertson-Walker metric. This may offer a framework for describing cosmology within the extended BIMOND.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.10882v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.106.084010</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review D 106, 084010 (2022)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mordehai Milgrom</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unitarity, Causality, and Solar System Bounds May Significantly Limit the Use of Gravitational Waves to Test General Relativity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12118v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The prospect of detecting/constraining deviations from general relativity by studying gravitational waves (GWs) from merging black holes has been one of the primary motivations of GW interferometers like LIGO/Virgo. Within pure gravity, the only possible way deviations can arise is from the existence of higher order derivative corrections, namely higher powers of the Riemann curvature tensor, in the effective action. Any observational bounds imply constraints on the corresponding Wilson coefficients. At the level of the action, one can imagine the coefficients are sufficiently large so as to be in principle detectable. However, from the point of view of some fundamental principles, namely causality and unitarity, this is much less clear, as we examine here. We begin by reviewing certain known bounds on these coefficients, which together imply a low cut off on the effective theory. We then consider a possible mechanism to generate such terms, namely in the form of many scalars, minimally coupled to only gravity, that can be integrated out to give these higher order operators. We show that a by product of this is the generation of quantum corrections to Newton's potential, whose observable consequences are already ruled out by solar system tests. We point out that over 7 orders of magnitude of improvement in interferometer sensitivity would be required to avoid such solar system constraints. We also mention further constraints from Hawking radiation from black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12118v5</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Cassem, Mark P. Hertzberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pushing JWST to the extremes: search and scrutiny of bright galaxy candidates at z$\simeq$15-30</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05893</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.05893v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We designed customized Lyman-break color selection techniques to identify galaxy candidates in the redshift ranges $15 \leq z \leq 20$ and $20 \leq z \leq 28$. The selection was performed on the ASTRODEEP-JWST multi-band catalogs of the CEERS, Abell-2744, JADES, NGDEEP, and PRIMER survey fields, covering a total area of $\sim0.2$ sq. deg. We identify five candidates at $15 \leq z \leq 20$, while no objects are found based on the $z\gtrsim20$ color selection criteria. Despite exhibiting a $&gt;$1.5 mag break, all the objects display multimodal redshift probability distributions across different SED-fitting codes and methodologies. The alternative solutions correspond to poorly understood populations of low-mass quiescent or dusty galaxies at z$\sim$3-7. This conclusion is supported by the analysis of five F200W-dropout objects that we find to be interlopers on the basis of NIRSpec PRISM spectra: four dusty star-forming galaxies at z$\sim$2.2-6.6, and a passive galaxy at z=4.91 with log$(M_{\rm star}/{\rm M}_{\odot}) \lesssim$ 9. We measured the UV luminosity function under different assumptions on the contamination level within our sample. We find that if even a fraction of the candidates is indeed at $z\gtrsim15$, the resulting UV LF points to a very mild evolution compared to estimates at $z&lt;15$, implying a significant tension with existing theoretical models. In particular, confirming our bright ($M_{\text{UV}}&lt;-21$) candidates would require substantial revisions to the theoretical framework. In turn, if all these candidates will be confirmed to be interlopers, we conclude that future surveys may need ten times wider areas to select $M_{\text{UV}}\lesssim-20$ galaxies at $z&gt;15$. Observations in the F150W and F200W filters at depths comparable to those in the NIRCam LW bands are also required to mitigate contamination from rare red objects at z$\lesssim$8.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.05893v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Castellano, A. Fontana, E. Merlin, P. Santini, L. Napolitano, N. Menci, P. G. P\'erez-Gonz\'alez, A. Calabr\`o, D. Paris, L. Pentericci, J. Zavala, M. Dickinson, S. L. Finkelstein, T. Treu, R. O. Amorin, P. Arrabal Haro, P. Bergamini, L. Bisigello, M. Catone, E. Daddi, P. Dayal, A. Dekel, A. Ferrara, F. Fortuni, G. Gandolfi, M. Giavalisco, C. Grillo, S. T. Guida, N. P. Hathi, B. W. Holwerda, A. M. Koekemoer, V. Kokorev, Z. Li, M. Llerena, R. A. Lucas, S. Mascia, B. Metha, T. Morishita, T. Nanayakkara, F. Pacucci, G. Roberts-Borsani, G. Rodighiero, P. Rosati, V. Salazar, R. Schneider, R. S. Somerville, A. Taylor, M. Trenti, A. Trinca, X. Wang, P. J. Watson, L. Yang, L. Y. A. Yung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recoherence, adiabaticity, and Markovianity in Gaussian maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18648</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.18648v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Motivated by the recent discovery of situations where cosmological fluctuations recohere during inflation, we investigate the relationship between quantum recoherence (late-time purification after a transient phase of decoherence), adiabaticity, and Markovianity. To that end, we study a simple setup of two linearly-coupled harmonic oscillators, and compute the purity of one oscillator when the interaction is switched off. We find that there exists a critical value for the coupling strength below which the purity oscillates and above which it decays exponentially. This decay cannot be captured by perturbation theory; hence, decoherence is always a non-perturbative phenomenon. When the interaction is turned off, the purity either freezes to its value prior to the turn-off, or it smoothly goes back to a value very close to one (recoherence). This depends on the rate at which the turn-off occurs. We thus develop a new adiabatic-expansion scheme and find complete recoherence at any finite order in the inverse turn-off time. Therefore, decoherence is always a non-adiabatic effect. The critical value of the turn-off time above which recoherence takes place is then expressed in terms of the other time scales of the problem. Finally, we show that the dynamics of the system is never Markovian, even when decoherence takes place. We introduce a new measure of Markovianity dubbed the Bures velocity and use it to optimise Markovian approximations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.18648v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/r8pq-kms4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 112, 076014 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Dimitrios Kranas, Julien Grain, Vincent Vennin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Roman Observations Time Allocation Committee: Final Report and Recommendations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10574v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Nancy Grace Roman Space Telescope is poised to revolutionize our scientific understanding of exoplanets, dark matter, dark energy, and general astrophysics, including through an innovative community approach to defining and executing sky surveys. The Roman Observations Time Allocation Committee (ROTAC) was convened to recommend time allocations for the three Core Community Surveys (CCS) using the Wide Field Instrument (WFI): the High Latitude Wide Area Survey, the High Latitude Time Domain Survey, and the Galactic Bulge Time Domain Survey, as well as balance the time allocation for the General Astrophysics Surveys. Each CCS had a corresponding Definition Committee that collected community input and designed proposals for a nominal (in-guide) survey, as well as underguide and overguide options with smaller and larger time allocations, respectively. These options explored different ways of fulfilling the mission science requirements while maximizing general astrophysics science goals enabled by the surveys. In this report, the ROTAC lays out its recommendations for the three CCS observing designs and the WFI time allotment for CCS (74.5%) and the General Astrophysics Surveys (25.5%).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10574v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gail Zasowski, Saurabh W. Jha, Laura Chomiuk, Xiaohui Fan, Ryan Hickox, Dan Huber, Eamonn Kerins, Chip Kobulnicky, Tod Lauer, Masao Sako, Alice Shapley, Denise Stephens, David Weinberg, Ben Williams</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detectability of dark matter density distribution via gravitational waves from binary black holes in the Galactic center</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19327v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The fundamental nature of dark matter (DM) remains unknown, with significant uncertainties in its density profile. DM environments surrounding massive binary black holes (BBHs) modify their orbital dynamics, thereby altering gravitational wave (GW) emissions. For BBH systems at the Galactic Center, dynamical friction induced by DM spikes could produce detectable deviations in GW spectra, potentially observable by future space-based detectors. To address the uncertainties in the Galactic Center's DM profile, we systematically examine two scenarios: the generalized Navarro-Frenk-White (gNFW) profile and its post-spike modification. We investigate the evolutionary effects of DM dynamical friction and accretion on the eccentricity and semi-latus rectum of secondary black holes (BHs) in elliptical orbits. By constructing orbital models with varying initial eccentricities across the mass-semi-latus rectum parameter space and utilizing 30 years of simulated pulsar timing array data from the Square Kilometer Array (SKA), we identify detectable parameter regimes of DM effects and employ these GW observational signatures to constrain different DM density profiles. Our analysis reveals that among gNFW profiles ($\gamma=2,1.5,1,0.5$), only $\gamma=2$ produces significant detectable signatures. The formation of DM spikes further enhances these observable waveform deviations for all gNFW slopes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19327v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 112(2025),063055</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zhijin Li, Xiao Guo, Zhoujian Cao, Yun-Long Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining the axiverse with reionization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03535v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Axions that couple to electromagnetism are produced in the early Universe by, among other channels, freeze-in via the Primakoff process. For sufficiently large axion masses, the same coupling causes the axions to decay into two photons, which subsequently ionize the intergalactic medium. If this decay occurs in the redshift range $20 \lesssim z \lesssim 1100$, then the contribution to the cosmic microwave background optical depth $\tau_{\rm reio}$ can lead to a conflict with observations, excluding models with sufficiently strongly coupled, heavy axions and high reheating temperatures, $T_{\rm reh}$. Using large ensembles of explicit type IIB string theory models with up to $h^{1,1} = 100$ axions, we compute the full cosmic reionization history caused by the decays of multiple axions. We compare this to the posterior on the high-$z$ component of $\tau_{\rm reio}$ derived from model-independent constraints on the ionization state of the Universe, obtained in a full \textit{Planck} analysis presented in a companion paper. For $h^{1,1} = 20, 50, 100$, we find that approximately 15\%, 15\%, and 10\% of the models in the ensemble prefer $T_{\rm reh} \lesssim 10^{10}\,\text{GeV}$ at 95\% CL. We provide a publicly available code at:~\href{https://github.com/ZiwenYin/Reionization-with-multi-axions-decay}{github.com/ZiwenYin/Reionization-with-multi-axions-decay}, which computes the reionization history for arbitrary ensembles of decaying axions. Our analysis opens the door for future large-scale work studying the preference for low-temperature reheating in models with multiple axions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03535v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziwen Yin, Hanyu Cheng, Eleonora Di Valentino, Naomi Gendler, David J. E. Marsh, Luca Visinelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microlensing optical depth, event rate, and limits on compact objects in dark matter based on 20 yr of OGLE observations of the Small Magellanic Cloud</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13794</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13794v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Some previous studies have suggested that massive and intermediate-mass primordial black holes (PBHs) could comprise a substantial fraction of dark matter in the Universe. Such black holes, if they existed in the Milky Way halo, would give rise to long-duration microlensing events that may potentially last for years. However, earlier searches were not sufficiently sensitive to detect such events. Here, we present the results of searches for long-timescale gravitational microlensing events toward the Small Magellanic Cloud (SMC) using nearly 20 years of photometric observations collected by the Optical Gravitational Lensing Experiment (OGLE) from 2001 to 2020. We found six events, three of which are new discoveries. We use a sample of five events to measure the microlensing optical depth toward the SMC $\tau = (0.32 \pm 0.18) \times 10^{-7}$ and the event rate $\Gamma = (1.18 \pm 0.57) \times 10^{-7}\,\mathrm{yr}^{-1}\,\mathrm{star}^{-1}$. The properties of the detected events are consistent with lenses originating from known stellar populations within the SMC or in the Milky Way disk. No events with timescales longer than 1 yr were detected, which provides competitive limits on the fraction of massive compact objects, including PBHs, in the Milky Way dark matter halo. Together with the earlier OGLE studies of microlensing events in the direction of the Large Magellanic Cloud, these observations rule out PBHs and other compact objects with masses ranging from $10^{-8}$ to $10^3\,M_{\odot}$ as dominant components of dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13794v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4365/adf842</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ApJS 280, 49 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>P. Mr\'oz, A. Udalski, M. K. Szyma\'nski, I. Soszy\'nski, P. Pietrukowicz, S. Koz{\l}owski, R. Poleski, J. Skowron, D. Skowron, K. Ulaczyk, M. Gromadzki, K. Rybicki, P. Iwanek, M. Wrona, M. Ratajczak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling horizons in quantum critical collapse</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03584v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Critical gravitational collapse offers a unique window into regimes of arbitrarily high curvature, culminating in a naked singularity arising from smooth initial data -- thus providing a dynamical counterexample to weak cosmic censorship. Near the critical regime, quantum effects from the collapsing matter are expected to intervene before full quantum gravity resolves the singularity. Despite its fundamental significance, a self-consistent treatment has so far remained elusive. In this work, we perform a one-loop semiclassical analysis using the robust anomaly-based method in the canonical setup of Einstein gravity minimally coupled to a free, massless scalar field. Focusing on explicitly solvable critical solutions in both 2+1 and 3+1 dimensions, we analytically solve the semiclassical Einstein equations and provide definitive answers to several long-standing questions. We find that regularity uniquely selects a Boulware-like quantum state, encoding genuine vacuum polarization effects from the collapsing matter. Remarkably, the resulting quantum corrections manifest as a growing mode. Horizon-tracing analyses, incorporating both classical and quantum modes, reveal the emergence of a finite mass gap, signaling a phase transition from classical Type II to quantum-modified Type I behavior, thereby providing a quantum enforcement of the weak cosmic censorship. The most nontrivial aspect of our analysis involves dealing with non-conformal matter fields in explicitly time-dependent critical spacetimes. Along the way, we uncover intriguing and previously underexplored features of quantum field theory in curved spacetime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03584v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marija Toma\v{s}evi\'c, Chih-Hung Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Critical Collapse Abhors a Naked Singularity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03587</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03587v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Classical critical collapse yields naked singularities from smooth initial data, challenging cosmic censorship and shaping the spectrum of primordial black holes. We show that one-loop vacuum polarization near the threshold alters this outcome. In analytically tractable Einstein-scalar critical spacetimes, regularity uniquely selects a Boulware-like state whose stress tensor supplies a universal quantum growing mode. Its backreaction competes with the classical unstable mode, producing a shift of the critical point and a finite mass gap at the new threshold, thereby enforcing horizon formation even under arbitrary fine-tuning. In primordial collapse, the threshold shift enters exponentially into the formation fraction, while the gap truncates the low-mass tail -- effects that may reshape the predicted mass spectrum. These results provide the first consistent quantum treatment of critical collapse, offering definitive predictions for several long-standing problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03587v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marija Toma\v{s}evi\'c, Chih-Hung Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct Collapse Black Hole Candidates from Decaying Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25325v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Injecting 1-13.6 eV photons into the early universe can suppress the molecular hydrogen abundance and alter the star formation history dramatically enough to produce direct collapse black holes. These, in turn, could explain the recently observed population of puzzling high-redshift supermassive black holes that appear to require super-Eddington accretion. We show that axion dark matter decay in the intergalactic medium can account for this energy injection. We use a single zone model of the gas core and semi-analytically evolve its chemo-thermal properties to track the conditions for which the system becomes an atomic cooling halo-a necessary precursor for the production of heavy black hole seeds to explain the high-redshift black hole population. Windows of axions masses between 24.5-26.5 eV with photon couplings as low as $4\times 10^{-12}$/GeV may realize this atomic cooling halo condition. We highlight the significance of the band structure of molecular hydrogen on the effectiveness of this process and discuss estimates of the heavy seed population and prospects for testing this model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25325v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yash Aggarwal, James B. Dent, Philip Tanedo, Tao Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Helicity, Magnetic Monopoles, and Higgs Winding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25734v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Changes in magnetic helicity are often discussed across a variety of fields, from condensed matter physics to early universe cosmology. It is frequently stated that the helicity change is given by the integral of the gauge field strength tensor and its dual over spacetime, $\int F \wedge F$. However, this is incorrect when magnetic monopoles once exist in the spacetime. In this paper, we show the correct formula of the helicity change in such a case for the Maxwell theory with the magnetic monopoles. We also discuss what happens when we embed the Maxwell theory with magnetic monopoles into non-Abelian gauge theories. We show that a similar formula holds for the 't Hooft--Polyakov monopole. In particular, we find the winding numbers and the zeroes of the Higgs field in the non-Abelian gauge theory play a crucial role in the helicity change. The same discussion is also applicable to the electroweak theory, and we discuss the implication of our findings to the baryon number change via the chiral anomaly in the early universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25734v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hajime Fukuda, Yuta Hamada, Kohei Kamada, Kyohei Mukaida, Fumio Uchida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Dark Matter and Dark Energy in a model of Non-Canonical Scalar-Tensor Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07103</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07103v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a model of non-canonical scalar-tensor theory in which the kinetic term in the Brans-Dicke action is replaced by a non-canonical scalar field Lagrangian $\mathcal{L}(X, \phi)= \lambda X^\alpha \phi^\beta - V(\phi)$ where $X = (1/2) \partial_{\mu} \phi \partial^{\mu} \phi$ and $\alpha$, $\beta$ and $\lambda$ are parameters of the model. This can be considered as a simple non-canonical generalization of the Brans-Dicke theory with a potential term which corresponds to a special case of this model with the values of the parameter $\alpha = 1$, $\beta = -1$ and $\lambda = 2w_{_{BD}}$ where $w_{_{BD}}$ is the Brans-Dicke parameter. Considering a spatially flat Friedmann-Robertson-Walker Universe with scale factor $a(t)$, it is shown that, in the matter free Universe, the kinetic term $\lambda X^\alpha \phi^\beta$ can lead to a power law solution $a(t)\propto t^{n}$ but the maximum possible value of $n$ turns out to be $(1+\sqrt{3})/4 \approx 0.683$. When $\alpha \geq 18$, this model can lead to a solution $a(t)\propto t^{2/3}$, thereby mimicking the evolution of scale factor in a cold dark matter dominated epoch with Einstein's General Relativity (GR). With the addition of a linear potential term $V(\phi) = V_{0}\phi$, it is shown that this model mimics the standard $\Lambda$CDM model type evolution of the Universe. The larger the value of $\alpha$, the closer the evolution of $a(t)$ in this model to that in the $\Lambda$CDM model based on Einstein's GR. The purpose of this paper is to demonstrate that this model with a linear potential can mimic the GR based $\Lambda$CDM model. However, with an appropriate choice of the potential $V(\phi)$, this model can provide a unified description of both dark matter and dynamical dark energy, as if it were based on Einstein's GR.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07103v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nihal Jalal Pullisseri, Sanil Unnikrishnan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
