<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO</link>
    <description>astro-ph.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 04:00:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Signals of Bursts from the Very Early Universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00237v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider possible observable signals from explosive events in the very early universe, ``bursts". These could be expected in connection
  with massive black hole or ``baby universe'' formation. We anticipate that such major disruptions of spacetime would be associated with
  neutrino and perhaps other pulses. While these seem to be not
  detectable directly, we discuss how they could lead to potentially observable signals. We analyze how the pulses from very early times
  may ``escape'', that is
  propagate to the last scattering epoch at the time $t_{cmb}$ and later,
  or alternatively be absorbed earlier, ``contained''. The possibly detectable signals include effects on small regions of the CMB, a soft x-ray resulting from positron production, or a nonthermal addition to
  the relic neutrino background.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00237v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leo Stodolsky, J. Silk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Looking beyond lambda</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00359v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Widening cracks are appearing in the $\Lambda$CDM model and it is becoming increasingly clear that the standard cosmological model struggles to describe the full expansion history of the Universe as revealed by the Cosmic Microwave Background, Baryon Acoustic Oscillation measurements, and locally calibrated Type Ia supernovae. Taken at face value, recent results suggest a dark sector that may be more complex than commonly assumed. We must prepare for the possibility of moving beyond the $\Lambda$CDM era, where merely testing $w=-1$ is no longer sufficient, and embrace the challenge of unraveling the physics of dark matter, dark energy and gravity on cosmic scales. Guided by increasingly robust data - secured through considerable investment - we should pursue deeper understanding while being open to complexity in the dark sector, rather than settling for the simplest phenomenology. New data from new facilities and a new dark energy task force could help illuminate the path forward while changes to our scientific practices will be essential to navigate the potentially rocky road ahead.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00359v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41550-025-02627-2</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nat Astron 9, 1123 1128 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alexie Leauthaud, Adam Riess</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bubble in bubbles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00758</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00758v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the evolution and formation of double-layered vacuum bubbles during cosmological phase transitions with mltiple vacua. Using a semiclassical approach with initial velocity fluctuations, we demonstrate that under certain conditions, quantum effects do not lead to the formation of double-layered vacuum bubbles, while flyover transitions allow for their stable formation by overcoming successive potential barriers. The evolution of these bubbles, including wall acceleration, collisions, and the formation of trapped regions, is explored through numerical simulations. Our results show that the dynamics of double-layered bubbles differ significantly from standard single-wall bubbles, with implications for cosmological observables such as gravitational wave production and baryogenesis. These findings indicate that flyover transitions represent a complementary decay mechanism to the conventional quantum tunneling process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00758v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongdong Wei, Zong-Kuan Guo, Qiqi Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emulating Global 21 cm Cosmology Observations from the Lunar Far Side to Achieve Quick and Reliable Physical Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00976</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00976v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Efforts are underway to measure the global 21 cm signal from neutral hydrogen, which is a powerful probe of the early universe, using NASA radio telescopes on the far side of the Moon. Physics-based models of the signal are computationally expensive to perform Bayesian multi-parameter inferences, for which we have developed novel, publicly-available neural network emulators utilizing a Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) network and a Kolmogorov-Arnold Network (KAN). $\texttt{21cmLSTM}$ is currently the most accurate emulator in the community by leveraging the signal's temporally-correlated structure, and $\texttt{21cmKAN}$ maintains similar accuracy while training 75 times faster, by learning expressive functional transformations. Each emulator can fit realistic mock signals and obtain unbiased physical parameter constraints, with $\texttt{21cmKAN}$ able to complete end-to-end training and inference in under 30 minutes. The implementation of machine learning tools like these in data analysis pipelines is important to fully exploit upcoming measurements of the cosmological 21 cm signal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00976v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Dorigo Jones, J. O. Burns, D. Rapetti, Shah Mohammad Bahauddin, B. Reyes, D. W. Barker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An SIDM simulation of the merging cluster El Gordo and its tension between the post collision DM density profiles and weak lensing constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01298v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We review recent findings from a detailed simulation study of the merging cluster El Gordo and present new results inferred from weak lensing data. We found that the observed spatial offsets between the different mass components are well reproduced in merging simulations that include self-interacting dark matter (DM), with an elastic cross-section per unit mass of approximately \sigma_DM/m_X ~ 4 -5 cm^2/gr. Moreover, a relative line-of-sight peculiar velocity on the order of several hundred km/s is found between the two stellar components of the colliding subclusters. These findings strongly suggest the possibility that, in a very energetic cluster collision, DM could possess collisional properties. However, the self-interacting DM merger model presented here is not without difficulties. The values found for \sigma_DM/m_X being in conflict with the current upper bounds on cluster scales. As a solution to this tension we argue that in major cluster mergers the physical modeling of DM interactions, based on the scattering of DM particles, should be considered too simplistic. Additionally, the DM halos of the post-collision clusters have cored density profiles with core radii r_c ~ 300 kpc. Consequently, the associated reduced tangential shear lensing profiles consistently tend to zero at angles \theta &lt;~ 40^{''}. This result is inconsistent with what is deduced from the measured profiles. These profiles exhibit a diverging behavior when \theta --&gt; 0, as predicted by an NFW mass model. We argue that such contradictions cannot be easily reconciled within the DM models presented so far as an alternative to the collisionless paradigm. However, we suggest that this tension can be used as a unique test bed to probe new DM physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01298v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Valdarnini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Les Houches on Dark Universe 2025: Elements of cosmology beyond FLRW</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01320v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Modern cosmology is based on the cosmological principle, which states that the Universe is statistically homogeneous and isotropic. When applied in its strict -- rather than statistical -- sense, the cosmological principle leads to the Friedmann--Lema\^itre--Robertson--Walker (FLRW) model, which serves as background spacetime. This background is used to predict: (1) the dynamics of cosmic expansion; and (2) the kinematics of light propagation through the Universe, which dictates the interpretation of cosmological observations. In this lecture, we shall discuss the performance of the FLRW model for those purposes, and present some results on the so-called backreaction and fitting problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01320v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Fleury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Accurate Comprehensive Approach to Substructure: IV. Dynamical Friction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01553v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In three previous Papers we analysed the origin of the properties of halo substructure found in simulations. This was achieved by deriving them analytically in the peak model of structure formation, using the statistics of nested peaks (with no free parameter) plus a realistic model of subhalo stripping and shock-heating (with only one parameter). However, to simplify the treatment we neglected dynamical friction (DF). Here, we revisit that work by including it. That is done in a fully analytic manner, i.e. avoiding the integration of subhalo orbital motions. This leads to simple accurate expressions for the abundance and radial distribution of subhaloes of different masses, which disentangle the effects of DF from those of tidal stripping and shock-heating. This way we reproduce and explain the results of simulations and extend them to haloes of any mass, redshift and formation times in the desired cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01553v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eduard Salvador-Sol\'e, Alberto Manrique, Andreu Rocamora</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Perfect Host: JWST Cepheid Observations in a Background-Free SN Ia Host Confirm No Bias in Hubble-Constant Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01667v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cycle 1 JWST observations of Cepheids in SN Ia hosts resolved their red-giant-dominated NIR backgrounds, sharply reducing crowding and showing that photometric bias in lower-resolution HST data does not account for the Hubble tension. We present Cycle 2 JWST observations of &gt;100 Cepheids in NGC 3447, a unique system that pushes this test to the limit by transitioning from low to no background contamination. NGC 3447, an SN Ia host at D~25 Mpc, is an interacting pair comprising (i) a spiral with mixed stellar populations, typical of H0 calibrators, and (ii) a young, star-forming companion (NGC 3447A) devoid of old stars and hence stellar crowdinga rare "perfect host" for testing photometric bias. We detect ~60 long-period Cepheids in each, enabling a "three-way comparison" across HST, JWST, and background-free conditions. We find no component-to-component offset (sigma&lt;0.03 mag; a calibration independent test), and a 50% reduction in scatter to ~0.12 mag in the background-free case, the tightest seen for any SN Ia host. Across Cycles 1-2 we also measure Cepheids in all SH0ES hosts observed by JWST (19 hosts of 24 SNe Ia; &gt;50% of the sample) and find no evidence of bias relative to HST photometry, including for the most crowded, distant hosts. These observations constitute the most rigorous test yet of Cepheid distances and provide strong evidence for their reliability. Combining JWST Cepheid measurements in 19 hosts (24 SNe Ia) with HST data (37 hosts, 42 SNe Ia) yields H0 = 73.49 +/- 0.93 km/s/Mpc. Including 35 TRGB-based calibrations (from HST and JWST) totals 55 SNe Ia and gives H0 = 73.18 +/- 0.88 km/s/Mpc, ~6 sigma above the LambdaCDM+CMB expectation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01667v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam G. Riess, Siyang Li, Gagandeep S. Anand, Wenlong Yuan, Louise Breuval, Stefano Casertano, Lucas M. Macri, Dan Scolnic, Yukei S. Murakami, Alexei V. Filippenko, Thomas G. Brink</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the Dark Sector using the Fornax Satellite</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01713v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A long-range force acting only in the dark sector can displace the stellar component of satellite galaxies relative to their dark matter (DM) halos, thereby \emph{breaking} the weak equivalence principle (WEP) between DM and baryons. We investigate observational signatures of such WEP breaking using $N$-body simulations of a Fornax-like Milky Way (MW) satellite, implementing a fifth force between DM particles of amplitude $\beta$ relative to Newtonian gravity (with a screening length much larger than the MW halo size). We find that $\beta \gtrsim 0.6$ strips and unbinds the bulk of the stellar component, leaving at most a negligible bound remnant that fails to match the observed stellar content, surface-brightness, and line-of-sight velocity-dispersion profiles of Fornax. By contrast, $\beta \lesssim 0.2$ yields only mild stellar stripping and remains broadly consistent with current photometric and kinematic constraints within our modeling assumptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01713v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eyal Zamlung, Adi Nusser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One latent to fit them all: a unified representation of baryonic feedback on matter distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01881</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01881v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate and parsimonious quantification of baryonic feedback on matter distribution is of crucial importance for understanding both cosmology and galaxy formation from observational data. This is, however, challenging given the large discrepancy among different models of galaxy formation simulations, and their distinct subgrid physics parameterizations. Using 5,072 simulations from 4 different models covering broad ranges in their parameter spaces, we find a unified 2D latent representation. Compared to the simulations and other phenomenological models, our representation is independent of both time and cosmology, much lower-dimensional, and disentangled in its impacts on the matter power spectra. The common latent space facilitates the comparison of parameter spaces of different models and is readily interpretable by correlation with each. The two latent dimensions provide a complementary representation of baryonic effects, linking black hole and supernova feedback to distinct and interpretable impacts on the matter power spectrum. Our approach enables developing robust and economical analytic models for optimal gain of physical information from data, and is generalizable to other fields with significant modeling uncertainty.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01881v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shurui Lin, Yin Li, Shy Genel, Francisco Villaescusa-Navarro, Biwei Dai, Wentao Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alignment of spiral and elliptical galaxies from Siena Galaxy Atlas with filaments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02062v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The properties of galaxies are known to have been influenced by the large-scale structures that they inhabit. Theory suggests that galaxies acquire angular momentum during the linear stage of structure formation, and hence predict alignments between the spin of halos and the nearby structures of the cosmic web. In this study, we use the largest catalog of galaxies publicly available - the Siena Galaxy Atlas - to study the alignment of the spin normals of elliptical and spiral galaxies with filaments constructed by applying the Bisous process on galaxies ($z \le$ 0.2) from SDSS - DR12. Our sample comprises 32517 disk and 18955 elliptical galaxies that are within 2 Mpc of any filament spine. We find that the spin normals of elliptical galaxies exhibit a strong perpendicular alignment with respect to the orientation of the host filaments, inconsistent with random distributions by up to $\approx$ 13 $\sigma$. The spin axis of spiral galaxies shows a much weaker but nonzero alignment signal with their host filaments of $ \approx$ 2.8$\sigma$ when compared with random. These numbers depend on exactly how the significance is measured, as elucidated in the text. Furthermore, the significance of the alignment signal is examined as a function of distance from the filament spine. Spiral galaxies reach a maximum signal between 0.5 and 1 Mpc. elliptical galaxies reach their maximum significance between 0.2 and 0.5 Mpc. We also note that with a tailored selection of galaxies, as a function of both i) distance from the filaments \&amp; as a ii) function of absolute luminosity, the alignment significance can be maximized.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02062v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuvraj Muralichandran, Noam I. Libeskind, Elmo Tempel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological constraints from the Planck cluster catalogue with DES shear profiles and Chandra observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02068</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02068v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present cosmological constraints from the Planck PSZ2 cosmological cluster sample, using weak-lensing shear profiles from Dark Energy Survey (DES) data and X-ray observations from the Chandra telescope for the mass calibration. We compute hydrostatic mass estimates for all clusters in the PSZ2 sample with a scaling relation between their Sunyaev-Zeldovich signal and X-ray derived hydrostatic mass, calibrated with the Chandra data. We introduce a method to correct these masses with a hydrostatic mass bias using shear profiles from wide-field galaxy surveys. We simultaneously fit the number counts of the PSZ2 sample and the mass calibration with the DES data, finding $\Omega_\text{m}=0.312^{+0.018}_{-0.024}$, $\sigma_8=0.777\pm 0.024$, $S_8\equiv \sigma_8 \sqrt{\Omega_\text{m} / 0.3}=0.791^{+0.023}_{-0.021}$, and $(1-b)=0.844^{+0.055}_{-0.062}$ for our baseline analysis when combined with BAO data. When considering a hydrostatic mass bias evolving with mass, we find $\Omega_\text{m}=0.353^{+0.025}_{-0.031}$, $\sigma_8=0.751\pm 0.023$, and $S_8=0.814^{+0.019}_{-0.020}$. We verify the robustness of our results by exploring a variety of analysis settings, with a particular focus on the definition of the halo centre used for the extraction of shear profiles. We compare our results with a number of other analyses, in particular two recent analyses of cluster samples obtained from SPT and eROSITA data that share the same mass calibration data set. We find that our results are in overall agreement with most late-time probes, in very mild tension with CMB results (1.6$\sigma$), and in significant tension with results from eROSITA clusters (2.9$\sigma$). We confirm that our mass calibration is consistent with the eROSITA analysis by comparing masses for clusters present in both Planck and eROSITA samples, eliminating it as a potential cause of tension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02068v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Aymerich, S. Grandis, M. Douspis, G. W. Pratt, L. Salvati, F. Andrade-Santos, S. Bocquet, M. Costanzi, W. R. Forman, C. Jones, M. Aguena, F. Andrade-Oliveira, D. Bacon, D. Brooks, D. L. Burke, J. Carretero, L. N. da Costa, M. E. da Silva Pereira, T. M. Davis, J. De Vicente, S. Desai, H. T. Diehl, P. Doel, S. Everett, B. Flaugher, J. Frieman, E. Gaztanaga, D. Gruen, G. Gutierrez, S. R. Hinton, D. L. Hollowood, K. Honscheid, D. J. James, S. Lee, J. L. Marshall, J. Mena-Fern\'andez, R. Miquel, J. J. Mohr, R. L. C. Ogando, A. A. Plazas Malag\'on, A. Porredon, J. Prat, A. K. Romer, S. Samuroff, E. Sanchez, D. Sanchez Cid, M. Smith, E. Suchyta, M. E. C. Swanson, D. L. Tucker, N. Weaverdyck, J. Weller, M. Yamamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing the detectability of ionized Regions during the Epoch of Reionization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02148</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02148v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an improved matched filter method for detecting large ionized regions in 21 cm observations of the Epoch of Reionization. In addition to detection, the method constrains the properties of these regions, offering insights into the underlying source populations. Extending a previously developed Bayesian framework, we replace the spherical filter with an eight-parameter spheroidal filter, enabling a more flexible characterization of ionized bubbles. This enhancement significantly improves both detectability and recovery of bubble orientations. For a representative reionization scenario with mean ionization fraction $0.4$ at $z=7$, we find that a $10\sigma$ detection of the largest ionized region can be achieved with $\sim 1$, $2$, and $30$ h of observations using the SKA-low AA4, AA$^{\star}$, and AA2 configurations, respectively. Our method can help identify regions in the observed field that host large ionized bubbles, making them prime targets for deeper follow-up observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02148v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rutvik Ashish Mahajan, Raghunath Ghara, Nishant Pradeep Deo, Arnab Mishra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disentangling Target Lines from Interlopers and Continuum with Neural Networks: A SPHEREx Intensity Mapping Case Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02414v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Line-intensity mapping (LIM) traces the large-scale distribution of matter by measuring fluctuations in aggregate line emission from unresolved galaxies and the intergalactic medium, providing a powerful probe of both astrophysics and cosmology. However, interpreting LIM data is limited by our ability to disentangle the signal of a target spectral line from continuum emission and interloper lines, which are emissions from other redshifts that fall within the observed frequency band. Astrophysical modeling uncertainties further complicate matters, leaving the relative amplitudes of the map components poorly understood. In this paper, we present a neural-network (NN) approach to separate the three map components at the level of the angular power spectrum, explicitly accounting for uncertainties in their relative amplitudes. As test cases, we generate SPHEREx-like maps with variable interloper line luminosities across multiple frequency channels, with and without pixel-wise scatter and continuum contributions. We find that cross-channel correlations are essential for robust NN performance when scatter is present. The NN exhibits a hierarchy in residual errors: brighter components yield smaller residuals, and the dimmest the highest. Without continuum emission, the network recovers the target power spectrum to within $2.5\%$, while partially correcting the interloper spectra. With continuum included, the NN accurately reconstructs the power spectra of the continuum and target line, within $2\%$ and $6\%$, respectively, but fails to recover those of the interlopers. Reducing pixel-level scatter further improves performance, lowering residual errors to $1\%$ (continuum) and $3\%$ (target line).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02414v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marina S. Cagliari, Zucheng Gao, Azadeh Moradinezhad Dizgah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can an Anti-de Sitter Vacuum in the Dark Energy Sector Explain JWST High-Redshift Galaxy and Reionization Observations?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02431</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02431v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The James Webb Space Telescope's (JWST) discovery of an unexpectedly high abundance of UV-bright galaxies at redshifts $z &gt; 10$ poses a significant challenge to the standard $\Lambda$CDM cosmology. This work tests whether this tension can be resolved solely by modifying the cosmological background, without invoking significant evolution in the astrophysical properties of early galaxies. We investigate an alternative framework featuring the presence of an anti-de Sitter vacuum in the dark energy sector, a model that naturally arises in quantum gravity models like string theory and can enhance early structure formation. Using a self-consistent semi-analytical model that couples galaxy evolution with reionization, we confront this scenario with a wide range of observations. We first show that while a model tailored to fit the high-$z$ UV luminosity functions (UVLFs) shows promise, it is in strong tension with well-established cosmological constraints from the CMB and other low-redshift probes. Conversely, models within this framework that are consistent with these constraints provide only a modest boost to structure formation and fail to reproduce the observed JWST galaxy abundances at $z &gt; 10$. While these models remain consistent with the cosmic reionization history, our primary result is that this class of cosmological modifications is insufficient on its own to explain the galaxy excess. Our study underscores the critical importance of holistic testing for any beyond-$\Lambda$CDM proposal; apparent success in one observational regime does not guarantee overall viability. By demonstrating the limitations of a purely cosmological solution, our results strengthen the case that evolving astrophysical properties are a necessary ingredient for solving the challenge of early galaxy formation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02431v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anirban Chakraborty, Tirthankar Roy Choudhury, Anjan Ananda Sen, Purba Mukherjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinetic field theory of compact systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02459v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The kinetic field theory is developed without assumptions of statistical homogeneity and isotropy. In a solvable toy model with short-ranged interactions, we compare first-order perturbation theory to an iterated mean-field approximation scheme, demonstrating that the mean-field theory maintains positivity and captures collapse dynamics, allowing analytic estimates of blow-up times. In a self-gravitating sheet model, the first-order perturbation theory is shown to reproduce critical phenomena. This work suggests a path toward convergence analysis of the mean-field approximation and applications to more complex inhomogeneous systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02459v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthias Bartelmann, James Stokes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning for CMB Foreground Removal and Beam Deconvolution: A U-Net GAN Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00139</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00139v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Extracting cosmological information from microwave sky observations requires accurate estimation of the underlying Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) by removing foreground contamination, instrumental noise, and the effects of beam convolution. In this work, we develop a machine learning-based approach
  for CMB reconstruction using a generative adversarial network (GAN) architecture, where the generator is modeled as a U-Net-based convolutional neural network. To train the network, we generate realistic microwave sky maps by simulating Planck-like observations: scanning HEALPix-simulated skies with real Planck beam profile, actual scan patterns, and anisotropic noise consistent with Planck data. Our method achieves high-fidelity reconstruction, with the difference between the input and recovered maps being less than $2\mu\mathrm{K}$ (approximately $1\%$) outside the Galactic region. Even within the Galactic plane, the reconstruction error remains below $2-3\%$ in most areas, except for a few isolated pixels. Most importantly, we demonstrate for the first time that a GAN-based method can effectively correct for both foreground contamination and the systematic effects of non-circular beams and the asymmetric Planck scan pattern. Our results demonstrate the effectiveness of our method for robust and accurate recovery of the CMB signal, even in the presence of strong astrophysical foregrounds and instrumental systematics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00139v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Obasho M, Shambhavi Jaiswal, Santanu Das, Krishna Mohan Parattu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A generalized study of linear electromagnetic cascades in astrophysical sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00152</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00152v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: High-energy gamma rays can trigger electromagnetic cascades via pair production on ambient photons, reprocessing their energy to lower frequencies. A classic example is the cascade from the gamma rays produced by ultra-high-energy cosmic rays in extragalactic photon fields, whose universal spectral shape was first described by Berezinsky in the 1970s. Recently, internal cascades, developing within the gamma-ray sources themselves, have gained a prominent role, as the IceCube data suggest that most detected neutrinos originate in gamma-ray-opaque environments. We analyze under what conditions these internal cascades can approach a universal spectrum. Since the Berezinsky treatment breaks down if synchrotron losses dominate, we present a generalized theory incorporating synchrotron-dominated cascades. We show the emergence of universal cascade spectrum among various examples of high-energy sources containing non-thermal cosmic rays, and discuss the conditions for its appearance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00152v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Damiano F. G. Fiorillo, Federico Testagrossa, Chengchao Yuan, Maria Petropoulou, Walter Winter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasar Radiative Feedback May Suppress Galaxy Growth on Intergalactic Scales at $z = 6.3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00153</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00153v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present observational evidence that intense ionizing radiation from a luminous quasar suppresses nebular emission in nearby galaxies on intergalactic scales at $z=6.3$. Using JWST/NIRCam grism spectroscopy from the SAPPHIRES and EIGER programs, we identify a pronounced decline in [O III] $\lambda5008$ luminosity relative to the UV continuum ($L_{5008}/L_{1500}$) among galaxies within $\sim$10 comoving Mpc (cMpc) of the quasar J0100$+$2802, the most UV-luminous quasar known at this epoch ($M_{1450}=-29.26$). While $L_{1500}$ remains roughly constant with transverse distance, $L_{5008}$ increases significantly, suggesting suppression of very recent star formation toward the quasar. The effect persists after controlling for completeness, local density, and UV luminosity, and correlates with the projected photoionization-rate profile $\Gamma_{\mathrm{qso}}$. A weaker but directionally consistent suppression in $L_{5008}/L_{1500}$ is also observed along the line of sight. The transverse suppression radius ($\sim$8-10 cMpc) implies a recent radiative episode with a cumulative duration $\sim$4.5 Myr, shorter than required for thermal photoheating to dominate and thus more naturally explained by rapid H$_2$ photodissociation and related radiative processes. Environmental effects alone appear insufficient to explain the signal. Our results provide direct, geometry-based constraints on large-scale quasar radiative feedback and recent quasar lifetimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00153v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongda Zhu, Eiichi Egami, Xiaohui Fan, Fengwu Sun, George D. Becker, Christopher Cain, Huanqing Chen, Anna-Christina Eilers, Yoshinobu Fudamoto, Jakob M. Helton, Xiangyu Jin, Maria Pudoka, Andrew J. Bunker, Zheng Cai, Jaclyn B. Champagne, Zhiyuan Ji, Xiaojing Lin, Weizhe Liu, Hai-Xia Ma, Zheng Ma, Roberto Maiolino, George H. Rieke, Marcia J. Rieke, Pierluigi Rinaldi, Yang Sun, Wei Leong Tee, Feige Wang, Jinyi Yang, Minghao Yue, Junyu Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One-loop corrections to infrared GWs is forbidden by symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00420v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Small-scale scalar perturbations amplified during inflation can induce primordial gravitational waves through tensor-scalar interactions. A long-standing controversial issue is whether the one-loop corrections to tensor perturbations exist on large scales. Firstly, we demonstrate through direct one-loop calculations that one-loop corrections cancel each other out on large scales. We then proceed from the symmetry of the interacting system and directly prove, based on the Ward identity, the absence of one-loop corrections on large scales-without the need for specific loop diagram calculations. This is consistent with the results we previously obtained for scalar perturbations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00420v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng-Jun Fang, Han-Wen Hu, Zong-Kuan Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parallel Application of Slitless Spectroscopy to Analyze Galaxy Evolution (PASSAGE): Survey Overview</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00596</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00596v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: During the second half of Cycle 1 of the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST), we conducted the Parallel Application of Slitless Spectroscopy to Analyze Galaxy Evolution (PASSAGE) program. PASSAGE received the largest allocation of JWST observing time in Cycle 1, 591 hours of NIRISS observations to obtain direct near-IR imaging and slitless spectroscopy. About two thirds of these were ultimately executed, to observe 63 high-latitude fields in Pure Parallel mode. These have provided more than ten thousand near-infrared grism spectrograms of faint galaxies.
  PASSAGE brings unique advantages in studying galaxy evolution: A) Unbiased spectroscopic search, without prior photometric pre-selection. By including the most numerous galaxies, with low masses and strong emission lines, slitless spectroscopy is the indispensable complement to any pre-targeted spectroscopy; B) The combination of several dozen independent fields to overcome cosmic variance; C) Near-infrared spectral coverage, often spanning the full range from 1.0--2.3 $\mu$m, with minimal wavelength gaps, to measure multiple diagnostic rest-frame optical lines, minimizing sensitivity to dust reddening; D) JWST's unprecedented spatial resolution, in some cases using two orthogonal grism orientations, to overcome contamination due to blending of overlapping spectra; E) Discovery of rare bright objects especially for detailed JWST followup. PASSAGE data are public immediately, and our team plans to deliver fully-processed high-level data products.
  In this PASSAGE overview, we describe the survey and data quality, and present examples of these accomplishments in several areas of current interest in the evolution of emission-line galaxy properties, particularly at low masses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00596v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew A. Malkan, Vihang Mehta, Ayan Acharyya, Hollis Akins, Anahita Alavi, Hakim Atek, Ivano Baronchelli, Andrew J. Battisti, Kit Boyett, Marusa Bradac, Sean Tyler Bruton, Andrew Bunker, Adam J. Burgasser, Caitlin Casey, Nuo Chen, James Colbert, Y. Sophia Dai, Max Franco, Clea Hannahs, Santosh Harish, Farhanul Hasan, Matthew James Hayes, Alaina L. Henry, Mason Huberty, Jeyhan Kartaltepe, Keunho J. Kim, Nicha Leethochawalit, Jacob Levine, Sijia Li, Yu-Heng Lin, Yiaxiao Liu, Charlotte Mason, Daniel Masters, Henry McCracken, Takahiro Morishita, Kalina Nedkova, Marc Rafelski, Vivasvaan Aditya Raj, Guido Roberts-Borsani, Axel Runnholm, Michael James Rutkowski, Alberto Saldana-Lopez, Zahra Sattari Claudia Scarlata, Kasper Borello Schmidt, Marko Shuntov, Harry Teplitz, Michele Trenti, Tommaso Treu, Benedetta Vulcani, Peter J. Watson, Xin Wang, Zhuyun Zhuang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Energy and the Symbiosis Between Micro-physics and Cosmology (Naturally)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00688</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00688v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: These lectures aim to highlight the remarkable symbiosis that currently exists between the physics of the very small and the physics of the very large, using the unsolved puzzle of the nature of Dark Energy as a vehicle for so doing. The lectures first summarize what we know observationally about the properties of Dark Energy (and the Dark sector more broadly) and then discuss several approaches to explain them. Along the way this involves determining the types of interactions that would on general grounds be expected to be present in the low-energy limit of fundamental theories involving the many hierarchy of scales we see around us. This includes (but is not limited to) a discussion of technical naturalness (and `t Hooft naturalness) as well as the arguments for their use as a criterion for distinguishing amongst candidate theories. Some recent approaches I find promising are briefly summarized at the end.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00688v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. P. Burgess</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Big Bang Nucleosynthesis constraints on the cosmological evolution in a Universe with a Weylian Boundary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01162</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01162v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the effects that arise from the inclusion of Weylian boundary terms in the Einstein gravitational field equations in the Big Bang Nucleosynthesis (BBN) framework. With the help of the generalized Friedmann equations for a Universe with a Weylian boundary, obtained for a Friedmann-Lemaitre-Robertson-Walker FLRW metric, three distinct cosmological models can be constructed. The cosmological evolution is determined by a dissipative scalar field, and by the Weyl vector coming from the boundary. Several cosmological scenarios are obtained via the appropriate splitting of the generalized energy conservation equation. In the present work we obtain relevant constraints on these models by using the BBN data. In particular, the effects on the BBN that arise in the post warm-inflationary era will be examined by theoretically evaluating the measured abundances of relic nuclei (Hydrogen, Deuterium, Helium-3, Helium-4, and Lithium-7). We consider firstly the primordial mass fraction estimates, and their deviations due to changes in the freezing temperature, which impose an upper limit on the effective energy density obtained from the modified Friedmann equations. The deviation from the standard energy density of the radiative plasma is therefore constrained by the abundances of the Helium-4 nuclei. Secondly, an upper limit will be considered in a numerical analysis performed through the usage of the \texttt{PRyMordial} software package, with the help of which we calculate the primordial abundances of the light elements by evaluating the thermonuclear rates within the considered modified gravity framework. Finally, an MCMC analysis will validate the cosmological model with Weylian boundary contributions, imposing relevant constraints on the initial conditions of the cosmos. The methodology is implemented in the python code \texttt{genesys}, which is available on GitHub.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01162v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Teodora M. Matei, Cristian Croitoru, Tiberiu Harko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inflationary dynamics of non-minimally coupled $f(R)$ matter-curvature theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01532v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study examines how inflationary dynamics are affected by $f(R)$ theories with a non-minimal coupling between matter and curvature. Both positive and negative corrections to the minimal coupling of General Relativity are considered, and a robust numerical method is developed that evolves the metric and the inflaton field in this modified theory beyond slow-roll. Through a stability analysis, we find that positive models are inherently unstable during slow-roll, whereas negative ones can accommodate a stable attractor de Sitter solution. Using the amplitude of the scalar power spectrum from the latest data releases, we constrain the scale of the non-minimal coupling to be above $10^{13}$ GeV. In light of the 2018 Planck, BICEP/Keck and the recent Atacama Cosmology Telescope data for the scalar spectral index and tensor-to-scalar ratio, strong constraints on the coupling strength force the effects of these modified theories to be, at most, slightly above the perturbative level. Furthermore, we determine that the choice of the perfect fluid matter Lagrangian does not impact the inflationary observables at the pivot scale. Finally, we present the predicted observables for different inflationary potentials and show that even though classical gravity is still preferred by the data, there are areas of the parameter space that are viable for non-minimally coupled inflationary models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01532v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Barroso Varela, Orfeu Bertolami, Andreas Mantziris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recovering the Dust Mass Budget with PRIMA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01671v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Achieving a complete picture of galaxy evolution is a primary goal of extragalactic astrophysics. To accomplish this ambitious task, a wealth of multi-wavelength surveys have been devoted to assess the cosmic evolution of the cold gas and of the stellar mass across cosmic time. In this cosmic census, one elusive component is represented by interstellar dust. In this work, we exploit the IR mission PRIMA (covering wavelengths from 24 $\mu$m to 235 $\mu$m) to perform a deep survey (1000h on 1 deg$^2$) aimed at estimating the still poorly known dust mass function (DMF) at $z \sim 0.5 - 5$. We consider the spectro-photometric realization of the SPRITZ simulation and we compute the dust masses using single temperature Modified Grey Body functions. We show how PRIMA alone, thanks to its unprecedented sensitivities, will constrain the DMF at $z &lt; 1.5$, in terms of mass and faint-end slope. At $z &gt; 1.5$, we stress the key synergy with current or future sub-millimeter facilities, such as the JCMT/SCUBA-2, AtLAST, LMT and ALMA telescopes, that will allow us to probe the R$-$J regime of PRIMA selected galaxies. Finally, PRIMA, thanks to its large photometric coverage, will be able for the first time to constrain strictly the warm dust properties of a two component dust model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01671v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Traina, F. Pozzi, F. Calura, M. Costa, L. Bisigello, C. Gruppioni, L. Barchiesi, I. Delvecchio, L. Vallini, C. Vignali, V. Casasola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quark, lepton and right-handed neutrino production via inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01673</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01673v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Inflationary expansion of space-time provides us with an efficient particle production mechanism in the Early Universe. The fermion production efficiency depends critically on the particle mass, which is generated via the Yukawa coupling and sensitive to the corresponding scalar field value. During inflation, scalar fields experience large quantum fluctuations driving the average field values to the Hubble scale and above. This applies, in particular, to the Higgs field, making the Standard Model fermions very heavy and facilitating their production. Using the Bogolyubov coefficient approach, we compute the corresponding fermion abundance taking into account time dependence of the mass term. We find that the Standard Model fermion and the right-handed neutrino production grows dramatically compared to the naive estimate based on the low energy masses. The inflationary production mechanism can be the leading source of the right handed neutrinos, if they gain a Majorana mass from the Yukawa coupling to a light scalar. We also find a lower bound on the mass of fermionic dark matter, which can be produced by inflation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01673v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Duarte Feiteira, Fotis Koutroulis, Oleg Lebedev, Stefan Pokorski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alexei Starobinsky and Modern Cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01675v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Alexei Starobinsky is one of the main authors of inflationary cosmology. Here I will discuss the Starobinsky model and its generalizations, including the theory of $\alpha$-attractors. I will then describe the current status of these models in light of the latest observational results from ACT, SPT, and DESI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01675v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Linde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational waves induced by matter isocurvature in general cosmologies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02122v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The expansion history and content of the Universe between the end of inflation and the onset of Big Bang Nucleosynthesis is mostly unknown. In this paper, we study gravitational waves (GWs) induced by matter isocurvature fluctuations in a generic perfect fluid background as a novel probe of the physics of the very early Universe. We analytically compute the induced GW kernel and analyze the spectral GW energy density for a sharply peaked isocurvature power spectrum. We show that the spectral shape of the GW signal is sensitive to the equation of state parameter $w$ of the perfect fluid dominating the early Universe after inflation. We find that the GW amplitude is enhanced for a soft equation of state. Our framework can be applied to dark matter isocurvature and models leading to early matter-dominated eras, such as primordial black holes and cosmological solitons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02122v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillem Dom\`enech, Jan Tr\"ankle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral characterization and performance of SPT-SLIM on-chip filterbank spectrometers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02245</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02245v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The South Pole Telescope Shirokoff Line Intensity Mapper (SPT-SLIM) experiment is a pathfinder for demonstrating the use of on-chip spectrometers for millimeter Line Intensity Mapping. We present spectral bandpass measurements of the SLIM spectrometer channels made on site using a Fourier Transform Spectrometer during SPT-SLIMs first deployment the 2024-2025 austral summer observing season. Through this we demonstrate a technique for measuring the narrow band passes of the SPT-SLIM filterbanks that improves beyond the intrinsic resolution of a Fourier Transform Spectrometer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02245v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. S. Benson, K. Fichman, M. Adamic, A. J. Anderson, P. Barry, B. A. Benson, E. Brooks, J. E. Carlstrom, T. Cecil, C. L. Chang, K. R. Dibert, M. Dobbs, K. S. Karkare, G. K. Keating, A. M. Lapuente, M. Lisovenko, D. P. Marronexi, J. Montgomery, T. Natoli, Z. Pan, A. Rahlin, G. Robson, M. Rouble, G. Smecherxii, V. Yefremenko, M. R. Young, C. Yu, J. A. Zebrowski, C. Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supermassive black hole growth from stellar binary encounters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02316v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The growth of supermassive black holes (SMBHs) remains a central problem in astrophysics, with current observations providing only limited constraints on the underlying mechanisms. One possible growth channel is stellar accretion via the Hill's mechanism, wherein a SMBH tidally breaks up a passing binary star, capturing and eventually accreting a member of the binary. We adopt a model to predict capture rates from parameters that include the central number density of stars, the stellar velocity dispersion, the binary fraction, and black hole mass. We then use this model to estimate the growth of SMBHs across a range of galactic environments. In a data set of 30 galaxies of various types and masses, we identify two candidates with SMBHs for which stellar accretion may be a driver of recent growth. Closer to home, a recent analysis of observed hypervelocity stars from the Large Magellanic Cloud (LMC) implicates binary star interactions with a massive black hole. Every hypervelocity star produced in this way leaves a bound partner that may be accreted, providing an active growth channel for the LMC's black hole.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02316v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aubrey Jones, Benjamin C. Bromley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining interacting dark energy models with the halo concentration-mass relation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.02050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.02050v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The interacting dark energy (IDE) model is a promising alternative cosmological model which has the potential to solve the fine-tuning and coincidence problems by considering the interaction between dark matter and dark energy. Previous studies have shown that the energy exchange between the dark sectors in this model can significantly affect the dark matter halo properties. In this study, utilising a large set of cosmological $N$-body simulations, we analyse the redshift evolution of the halo concentration-mass ($c$-$M$) relation in the IDE model, and show that the $c$-$M$ relation is a sensitive proxy of the interaction strength parameter $\xi_2$, especially at lower redshifts. Furthermore, we construct parametrized formulae to quantify the dependence of the $c$-$M$ relation on $\xi_2$ at redshifts ranging from $z=0$ to $0.6$. Our parametrized formulae provide a useful tool in constraining $\xi_2$ with the observational $c$-$M$ relation. As a first attempt, we use the data from X-ray, gravitational lensing, and galaxy rotational curve observations and obtain a tight constraint on $\xi_2$, i.e. $\xi_2 = 0.071 \pm 0.034$. Our work demonstrates that the halo $c$-$M$ relation, which reflects the halo assembly history, is a powerful probe to constrain the IDE model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.02050v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stad1814</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yu Zhao, Yun Liu, Shihong Liao, Jiajun Zhang, Xiangkun Liu, Wei Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-tracing the primordial Universe with future surveys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.12994</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.12994v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The fluctuations generated by Inflation are nearly Gaussian in the simplest models, but may be non-Gaussian in more complex models, potentially leading to signatures in the late Universe. In particular, local type primordial non-Gaussianity induces scale-dependent bias in tracers of the matter distribution. This non-Gaussian imprint in the tracer power spectrum survives at late times on ultra-large scales where nonlinearity is negligible. In order to combat the problem of growing cosmic variance on these scales, we use a multi-tracer analysis that combines different tracers to maximise any primordial signal. Previous work has investigated the combination of a spectroscopic galaxy survey with a 21cm intensity mapping survey in single-dish mode. We extend this work by considering instead the case where the 21cm intensity mapping survey is optimised for interferometer mode. As examples, we use two multi-tracer pairs of surveys: one at high redshift ($1 \le z \le 2$) and one at very high redshift ($2 \le z \le 5$). The 21cm surveys are idealised surveys based on HIRAX and PUMA. We implement foreground-avoidance filters and use detailed models of the interferometer thermal noise. The galaxy surveys are idealised surveys based on Euclid and MegaMapper. Via a simple Fisher forecast, we illustrate the potential of the multi-tracer. Our results show a $\sim 20 - 30\%$ improvement in precision on local primordial non-Gaussianity from the multi-tracer. Furthermore, we investigate the effects on constraints of varying the parameter of non-Gaussian galaxy assembly bias and of varying the parameters of the intensity mapping foreground filters. We find that the non-Gaussian galaxy assembly bias parameter causes a greater change in the constraints on local primordial non-Gaussianity than the foreground filter parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.12994v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-024-12839-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>EPJC 84 (2024) 491</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mponeng Kopana, Sheean Jolicoeur, Roy Maartens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>STag II: Classification of Serendipitous Supernovae Observed by Galaxy Redshift Surveys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17204</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17204v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: With the number of supernovae observed expected to drastically increase thanks to large-scale surveys like the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI), it is necessary that the tools we use to classify these objects keep up with this increase. We previously created Supernova Tagging and Classification (STag) to address this problem by employing machine learning techniques alongside logistic regression in order to assign 'tags' to spectra based on spectral features. STag II is a continuation of this work, which now makes use of model supernova spectra combined with real DESI spectra in order to train STag to better deal with realistic data. We also make use of the rlap score as a trustworthiness cut, making for a more robust and accurate supernova classifier than before.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17204v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>W. Davison, D. Parkinson, S. BenZvi, A. Palmese, J. Aguilar, S. Ahlen, D. Brooks, T. Claybaugh, A. de la Macorra, Arjun Dey, P. Doel, E. Gazta\~naga, S. Gontcho A Gontcho, C. Howlett, S. Juneau, T. Kisner, A. Kremin, A. Lambert, M. Landriau, L. Le Guillou, A. Meisner, R. Miquel, J. Moustakas, A. D. Myers, C. Poppett, F. Prada, M. Rezaie, G. Rossi, E. Sanchez, E. F. Schlafly, M. Schubnell, D. Sprayberry, G. Tarl\'e, B. A. Weaver, H. Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimating Cosmological Parameters and Reconstructing Hubble Constant with Artificial Neural Networks: A Test with covariance matrix and mock H(z)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08369</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08369v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we reconstruct the H(z) based on observational Hubble data with Artificial Neural Network, then estimate the cosmological parameters and the Hubble constant. The training data we used are covariance matrix and mock H(z), which are generated based on the real OHD data and Gaussian Process(GP). The use of the covariance matrix propagates the correlated uncertainties and improves training efficiency. Using the reconstructed H(z) data, we first determine the Hubble constant and compare it with CMB-based measurements. To constrain cosmological parameters, we sample on the reconstructed data and calculate the corresponding posterior distributions with Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC). Through comprehensive statistical comparisons, we demonstrate that the parameter estimation using reconstructed samples achieves comparable statistical accuracy to the result derived from real OHD data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08369v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jie-feng Chen, Tong-Jie Zhang, Peng He, Tingting Zhang, Jie Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DESI 2024 V: Full-Shape Galaxy Clustering from Galaxies and Quasars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12021</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12021v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the measurements and cosmological implications of the galaxy two-point clustering using over 4.7 million unique galaxy and quasar redshifts in the range $0.1&lt;z&lt;2.1$ divided into six redshift bins over a $\sim 7,500$ square degree footprint, from the first year of observations with the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI Data Release 1). By fitting the full power spectrum, we extend previous DESI DR1 baryon acoustic oscillation (BAO) measurements to include redshift-space distortions and signals from the matter-radiation equality scale. For the first time, this Full-Shape analysis is blinded at the catalogue-level to avoid confirmation bias and the systematic errors are accounted for at the two-point clustering level, which automatically propagates them into any cosmological parameter. When analysing the data in terms of compressed model-agnostic variables, we obtain a combined precision of 4.7\% on the amplitude of the redshift space distortion signal reaching similar precision with just one year of DESI data than with 20 years of observation from previous generation surveys. We analyse the data to directly constrain the cosmological parameters within the $\Lambda$CDM model using perturbation theory and combine this information with the reconstructed DESI DR1 galaxy BAO. Using a Big Bang Nucleosynthesis Gaussian prior on the baryon density parameter, and a Gaussian prior on the spectral index, we constrain the matter density is $\Omega_m=0.296\pm 0.010 $ and the Hubble constant $H_0=(68.63 \pm 0.79)[{\rm km\, s^{-1}Mpc^{-1}}]$. Additionally, we measure the amplitude of clustering $\sigma_8=0.841 \pm 0.034$. The DESI DR1 results are in agreement with the $\Lambda$CDM model based on general relativity with parameters consistent with those from Planck. The cosmological interpretation of these results in combination with external datasets are presented in a companion paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12021v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/09/008</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Volume 2025, Issue 09, id.008</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. G. Adame, J. Aguilar, S. Ahlen, S. Alam, D. M. Alexander, M. Alvarez, O. Alves, A. Anand, U. Andrade, E. Armengaud, S. Avila, A. Aviles, H. Awan, S. Bailey, C. Baltay, A. Bault, J. Behera, S. BenZvi, F. Beutler, D. Bianchi, C. Blake, R. Blum, S. Brieden, A. Brodzeller, D. Brooks, E. Buckley-Geer, E. Burtin, R. Calderon, R. Canning, A. Carnero Rosell, R. Cereskaite, J. L. Cervantes-Cota, S. Chabanier, E. Chaussidon, J. Chaves-Montero, S. Chen, X. Chen, T. Claybaugh, S. Cole, A. Cuceu, T. M. Davis, K. Dawson, A. de la Macorra, A. de Mattia, N. Deiosso, A. Dey, B. Dey, Z. Ding, P. Doel, J. Edelstein, S. Eftekharzadeh, D. J. Eisenstein, A. Elliott, P. Fagrelius, K. Fanning, S. Ferraro, J. Ereza, N. Findlay, B. Flaugher, A. Font-Ribera, D. Forero-S\'anchez, J. E. Forero-Romero, C. Garcia-Quintero, L. H. Garrison, E. Gazta\~naga, H. Gil-Mar\'in, S. Gontcho A Gontcho, A. X. Gonzalez-Morales, V. Gonzalez-Perez, C. Gordon, D. Green, D. Gruen, R. Gsponer, G. Gutierrez, J. Guy, B. Hadzhiyska, C. Hahn, M. M. S Hanif, H. K. Herrera-Alcantar, K. Honscheid, C. Howlett, D. Huterer, V. Ir\v{s}i\v{c}, M. Ishak, S. Juneau, N. G. Kara\c{c}ayl{\i}, R. Kehoe, S. Kent, D. Kirkby, H. Kong, S. E. Koposov, A. Kremin, A. Krolewski, Y. Lai, T. -W. Lan, M. Landriau, D. Lang, J. Lasker, J. M. Le Goff, L. Le Guillou, A. Leauthaud, M. E. Levi, T. S. Li, K. Lodha, C. Magneville, M. Manera, D. Margala, P. Martini, M. Maus, P. McDonald, L. Medina-Varela, A. Meisner, J. Mena-Fern\'andez, R. Miquel, J. Moon, S. Moore, J. Moustakas, E. Mueller, A. Mu\~noz-Guti\'errez, A. D. Myers, S. Nadathur, L. Napolitano, R. Neveux, J. A. Newman, N. M. Nguyen, J. Nie, G. Niz, H. E. Noriega, N. Padmanabhan, E. Paillas, N. Palanque-Delabrouille, J. Pan, S. Penmetsa, W. J. Percival, M. M. Pieri, M. Pinon, C. Poppett, A. Porredon, F. Prada, A. P\'erez-Fern\'andez, I. P\'erez-R\`afols, D. Rabinowitz, A. Raichoor, C. Ram\'irez-P\'erez, S. Ramirez-Solano, M. Rashkovetskyi, C. Ravoux, M. Rezaie, J. Rich, A. Rocher, C. Rockosi, F. Rodr\'iguez-Mart\'inez, N. A. Roe, A. Rosado-Marin, A. J. Ross, G. Rossi, R. Ruggeri, V. Ruhlmann-Kleider, L. Samushia, E. Sanchez, C. Saulder, E. F. Schlafly, D. Schlegel, M. Schubnell, H. Seo, R. Sharples, J. Silber, A. Slosar, A. Smith, D. Sprayberry, T. Tan, G. Tarl\'e, S. Trusov, R. Vaisakh, D. Valcin, F. Valdes, M. Vargas-Maga\~na, L. Verde, M. Walther, B. Wang, M. S. Wang, B. A. Weaver, N. Weaverdyck, R. H. Wechsler, D. H. Weinberg, M. White, M. J. Wilson, J. Yu, Y. Yu, S. Yuan, C. Y\`eche, E. A. Zaborowski, P. Zarrouk, H. Zhang, C. Zhao, R. Zhao, R. Zhou, H. Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring HOD-dependent systematics for the DESI 2024 Full-Shape galaxy clustering analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12023</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12023v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We analyse the robustness of the DESI 2024 cosmological inference from the full shape of the galaxy power spectrum to uncertainties in the Halo Occupation Distribution (HOD) model of the galaxy-halo connection and the choice of priors on nuisance parameters. We assess variations in the recovered cosmological parameters across a range of mocks populated with different HOD models and find that shifts are often greater than 20% of the expected statistical uncertainties from the DESI data. We encapsulate the effect of such shifts in terms of a systematic covariance term, $\mathsf{C}_{\rm HOD}$, and an additional diagonal contribution quantifying the impact of our choice of nuisance parameter priors on the ability of the effective field theory (EFT) model to correctly recover the cosmological parameters of the simulations. These two covariance contributions are designed to be added to the usual covariance term, $\mathsf{C}_{\rm stat}$, describing the statistical uncertainty in the power spectrum measurement, in order to fairly represent these sources of systematic uncertainty. This novel approach should be more general and robust to the choice of model or additional external datasets used in cosmological fits than the alternative approach of adding systematic uncertainties to the recovered marginalised parameter posteriors. We compare the approaches within the context of a fixed $\Lambda$CDM model and demonstrate that our method gives conservative estimates of the systematic uncertainty that nevertheless have little impact on the final posteriors obtained from DESI data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12023v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/09/007</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 09 (2025) 007</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>N. Findlay, S. Nadathur, W. J. Percival, A. de Mattia, P. Zarrouk, H. Gil-Mar\'in, O. Alves, J. Mena-Fern\'andez, C. Garcia-Quintero, A. Rocher, S. Ahlen, D. Bianchi, D. Brooks, T. Claybaugh, S. Cole, A. de la Macorra, A. Dey, P. Doel, K. Fanning, A. Font-Ribera, J. E. Forero-Romero, E. Gazta\~naga, G. Gutierrez, C. Hahn, K. Honscheid, C. Howlett, S. Juneau, M. E. Levi, A. Meisner, R. Miquel, J. Moustakas, N. Palanque-Delabrouille, I. P\'erez-R\`afols, G. Rossi, E. Sanchez, D. Schlegel, M. Schubnell, H. Seo, D. Sprayberry, G. Tarl\'e, M. Vargas-Maga\~na, B. A. Weaver</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Angular bispectrum of matter number counts in cosmic structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05422v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The bispectrum of galaxy number counts is a key probe of large-scale structure, offering insights into the initial conditions of the Universe, the nature of gravity, and cosmological parameters. In this work, we present the first full-sky computation of the angular bispectrum in second-order perturbation theory without invoking the Limber approximation, and formulated for finite redshift bins via window functions. To our knowledge, even the Newtonian part within this setup is novel. Building on this, we also include, up to second order in perturbation theory, the dynamical general relativistic and radiation effects, together with the leading relativistic projection effects. For simplicity, we neglect tracer bias and line-of-sight integrated contributions, however note that in particular the former can be straightforwardly incorporated within our framework. We evaluate the bispectrum contributions for two redshift bins, $1.75 \leq z \leq 2.25$ and $0.55 \leq z \leq 0.65$, and compare our theoretical prediction against relativistic light-cone simulations, with line-of-sight integral effects removed so as to enable direct consistency checks. As expected, we find that the Newtonian contributions are typically one or more orders of magnitudes larger than the relativistic signal across the entire spectrum for both redshifts. At $z=2$, we find that projection and dynamical relativistic effects have comparable amplitudes on large scales; somewhat unexpectedly, however, radiation effects dominate the relativistic signal in the squeezed limit. At $z=0.6$, the expected hierarchy is recovered, though dynamical corrections remain non-negligible -- only a factor of 2-3 smaller than projection effects. Our theoretical results agree fairly well with simulation measurements for the total bispectrum. To facilitate future applications and reproducibility, we make the corresponding code publicly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05422v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Montandon, Enea Di Dio, Cornelius Rampf, Julian Adamek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interacting dark energy constraints from the full-shape analyses of BOSS DR12 and DES Year 3 measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.03390v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dark Scattering (DS) is an interacting dark energy model characterised by pure momentum exchange between dark energy and dark matter. It is phenomenologically interesting because it is unconstrained by CMB data and can alleviate the $S_8$ tension. We derive constraints on cosmological and DS parameters using three two-point correlation functions (3$\times$2pt) from the Dark Energy Survey third year data release (DES Y3). We then add information from the multipoles of the galaxy power spectrum combined with Baryonic Acoustic Oscillation (BAO) measurements using the twelfth data release of the Baryon Oscillation Spectroscopic Survey (BOSS DR12) and external BAO measurements. We compare results from the direct combination of the probes with the joint posterior distribution calculated with a normalising flow approach. Additionally, we run a CMB analysis with the Planck Public Release 4 (PR4) for comparison of the cosmological constraints. Overall, we find that the combination of probes allows minimising the projection effects and improves constraints without the need to include CMB information. It brings the marginalised posterior maxima closer to the corresponding best-fit values and weakens the sensitivity to the priors of the spectroscopic modelling nuisance parameters. These findings are highly relevant in light of forthcoming data of surveys like DESI, Euclid, and Rubin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.03390v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnrasl/slaf055</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society: Letters, Volume 541, Issue 1, July 2025, Pages L65-L70</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M. Tsedrik, S. Lee, K. Markovic, P. Carrilho, A. Pourtsidou, C. Moretti, B. Bose, E. Huff, A. Robertson, P. L. Taylor, J. Zuntz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Page Time of Primordial Black Holes in the Standard Model and Beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04430v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Page time marks the moment when the von Neumann entropy of the emitted Hawking radiation equals the Bekenstein-Hawking entropy of an evaporating black hole, which is assumed to quantify its degrees of freedom as seen from the outside. Beyond this point, from unitarity we would expect that the entropy of the radiation begins to decrease, ensuring that information is eventually recovered. In this work, we investigate the dependence of the Page time on black hole properties and the particle content of nature. Specifically, we analyze its sensitivity to the Standard Model (SM) and potential Beyond-the-SM degrees of freedom, incorporating the effects of particle masses. We find that a Schwarzschild primordial black hole (PBH) with an initial mass of $6.23\times 10^{14}~{\rm g}$ would have a Page time equal to the age of the Universe, assuming emission of SM particles only. We further explore the impact of a non-negligible PBH angular momentum, finding that light spin-2 particles are predominantly emitted before the Page time. Specifically, for initial angular momenta values exceeding $a_\star &gt; 0.5$, approximately $70\%$ of the total graviton emission occurs prior to the Page time for PBHs with an initial mass $M_{\rm BH} \lesssim 10^{10}~{\rm g}$. Finally, we discuss the implications for PBH phenomenology, particularly regarding potential constraints from $\Delta N_{\rm eff}$ measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04430v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuber F. Perez-Gonzalez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Assessing subhalo finders in cosmological hydrodynamical simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06932</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06932v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Cosmological simulations are essential for inferring cosmological and galaxy population properties based on forward-modelling, but this typically requires finding the population of (sub)haloes and galaxies that they contain. The properties of said populations vary depending on the algorithm used to find them, which is concerning as it may bias key statistics. We compare how the predicted (sub)halo mass functions, satellite radial distributions and correlation functions vary across algorithms in the dark-matter-only and hydrodynamical versions of the FLAMINGO simulations. We test three representative approaches to finding subhaloes: grouping particles in configuration- (Subfind), phase- (ROCKSTAR and VELOCIraptor) and history-space (HBT-HERONS). We also present HBT-HERONS, a new version of the HBT+ subhalo finder that improves the tracking of subhaloes. We find 10%-level differences in the $M_{\mathrm{200c}}$ mass function, reflecting different field halo definitions and occasional miscentering. The bound mass functions can differ by 75% at the high mass end, even when using the maximum circular velocity as a mass proxy. The number of well-resolved subhaloes differs by up to 20% near $R_{\mathrm{200c}}$, reflecting differences in the assignment of mass to subhaloes and their identification. The predictions of different subhalo finders increasingly diverge towards the centres of the host haloes. The performance of most subhalo finders does not improve with the resolution of the simulation and is worse for hydrodynamical than for dark-matter-only simulations. We conclude that HBT-HERONS is the preferred choice of subhalo finder due to its low computational cost, self-consistently made and robust merger trees, and robust subhalo identification capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06932v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor J. Forouhar Moreno, John Helly, Robert McGibbon, Joop Schaye, Matthieu Schaller, Jiaxin Han, Roi Kugel, Yannick M. Bahe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing the consistency of new Amati-correlated gamma-ray burst dataset cosmological constraints with those from better-established cosmological data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08429v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Gamma-ray bursts (GRBs) are promising cosmological probes for exploring the Universe at intermediate redshifts ($z$). We analyze 151 Fermi-observed long GRBs (datasets A123 and A28) to simultaneously constrain the Amati correlation and cosmological parameters within six spatially flat and nonflat dark energy models. We find that these datasets are standardizable via a single Amati correlation, suggesting their potential for cosmological analyses. However, constraints on the current value of the nonrelativistic matter density parameter from A123 and the combined A123 + A28 data exhibit $&gt;2\sigma$ tension with those derived from a joint analysis of better-established Hubble parameter [$H(z)$] and baryon acoustic oscillation (BAO) data for most considered cosmological models. This tension indicates that these GRB data are unsuitable for jointly constraining cosmological parameters with better-established $H(z)$ + BAO and similar data. Although the A28 data constraints are consistent with the $H(z)$ + BAO data constraints, its limited sample size (28 GRBs) and high intrinsic scatter ($\sim0.7$) diminishes its statistical power compared to existing datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08429v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shulei Cao, Bharat Ratra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of the counterterms in the conservation of superhorizon curvature perturbations at one loop</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12112v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, several papers have claimed that superhorizon curvature perturbations are not conserved at the one-loop level in single-field inflation models if there is a transient ultra-slow-roll period. In this work, we point out that the contributions from the counterterms were overlooked in the recent papers. We show that the counterterm contributions play a crucial role in canceling the one-loop power spectrum of superhorizon curvature perturbations in the comoving gauge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12112v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/r8bh-s48f</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Keisuke Inomata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lopsided and Bulging Distribution of Satellites around Paired Halos. II. 3D Analysis and Dependence on Projection and Selection Effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.14668v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We use the Illustris-TNG simulation to investigate the anisotropic distribution of subhalos in/around dark matter halo pairs. We measure the position angle ($\theta$) of each subhalo by the angle between the line connecting it to the nearest host halo and the line connecting the paired halos, and examine $P(\cos\theta)$ (the distribution of $\cos\theta$ of all subhalos) for halo pairs with various separations ($d_{\text{sep}}$), primary halo masses ($M_p$) and secondary-to-primary halo mass ratios ($M_s/M_p$). We find that $P(\cos\theta)$ generally exhibits a combined result of two distinct features: the `bulging' distribution characterized by an overabundance along the pairwise direction, and the `lopsided' distribution showing an overabundance in the region between the paired halos. The bulging signal is stronger for halo pairs with larger $d_{\text{sep}}$ and smaller $M_p$, while the lopsidedness strengthens as $M_p$ increases. Both signals depend weakly on $M_s/M_p$, and are primarily contributed by subhalos that are relatively distant from host halos. Remarkably, these measurements can be broadly reproduced by the overlap effect, provided the spatial alignment of halos is properly taken into account. Our findings suggest distinct origins: lopsidedness arises from simple halo overlap, while bulging reflects alignment with large-scale filaments. We examine the impact of projection and selection effects by conducting the same analysis in two dimensions and in a mock catalog that replicates the selection effects of the SDSS galaxy sample. We find that the 3D-to-2D projection significantly suppresses the bulging distribution, with particularly strong effects at large $d_{\text{sep}}$, small $M_p$, and large $M_s/M_p$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.14668v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qinglin Ma, Cheng Li, Yanhan Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutrino Emission and Plasma Heating from Primordial Black Holes: An Improved Approach to $N_\mathrm{eff}$ Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19498v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the impact of neutrino emission via Hawking radiation from primordial black holes (PBHs) on the cosmological effective number of neutrino species, $N_{\mathrm{eff}}$, after neutrino decoupling. By comparing this effect with observational limits, we derive bounds on the abundance of light PBHs. Our analysis incorporates two previously unaccounted-for effects: the emission of secondary neutrinos from unstable particles, which increases $N_{\mathrm{eff}}$, and the modification of the neutrino-photon temperature ratio due to particle emission heating the photon plasma, which lowers $N_{\mathrm{eff}}$. Overall, including these effects allows us to impose constraints on PBHs with initial masses in the range $10^9~{\rm g}\lesssim M_{\rm ini} \lesssim 10^{13}~{\rm g}$. However, our limits remain less stringent than those derived from Big Bang Nucleosynthesis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19498v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/08/049</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 08 (2025) 049</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>H\'ector Sanchis, Gabriela Barenboim, Yuber F. Perez-Gonzalez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear matter density perturbations in the $\Lambda_{\rm s}$CDM model: Examining growth dynamics and addressing the $S_8$ tension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20384</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20384v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate linear matter density perturbations in the $\Lambda_{\rm s}$CDM, in which the $\Lambda$ is replaced by late-time ($z\sim2$) mirror AdS-dS transition, resulting in distinct growth dynamics. We use two complementary approaches: (i) determining the initial density contrast and its evolution rate for a given collapse scale factor, (ii) computing the collapse scale factor for a specified initial density contrast and evolution rate. We derive analytical solutions for the growth rate $f=\Omega_{\rm m}^\gamma$ and growth index $\gamma$ in both models. Prior to the transition, the AdS-like $\Lambda$ reduces cosmic friction, causing linear matter density perturbations to grow more rapidly than in $\Lambda$CDM; this effect is most pronounced just before the transition, with a growth rate around $15\%$ higher than $\Lambda$CDM around $z\sim2$. After the transition, $\Lambda_{\rm s}$CDM behaves similarly to $\Lambda$CDM but features a larger cosmological constant, leading to higher $H(z)$ and greater cosmic friction that more effectively suppresses growth. Before the transition, $\gamma$ remains below both the $\Lambda$CDM and EdS values ($\gamma\approx6/11$); during the transition, it increases rapidly and then grows gradually, paralleling $\Lambda$CDM while remaining slightly higher in the post-transition era-though overall, it stays near $\gamma\sim0.55$. Using the Planck best-fit values, $\Omega_{\rm m0}=0.28$ for $\Lambda_{\mathrm{s}}$CDM and $\Omega_{\rm m0}=0.32$ for $\Lambda$CDM, we find $f=0.49$ and $f=0.53$, respectively. $\Lambda_{\rm s}$CDM predicts a value of $f=0.48$, recently obtained from LSS data when $\gamma$ is treated as a free parameter in $\Lambda$CDM. This suggests that $\Lambda_{\rm s}$CDM may resolve the structure growth anomaly, without deviating from $\gamma \sim 0.55$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20384v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/08/089</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 08 (2025) 089</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>\"Ozg\"ur Akarsu, Arman \c{C}am, Evangelos A. Paraskevas, Leandros Perivolaropoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Peaks sphericity of non-Gaussian random fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05434</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05434v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We formulate the statistics of peaks of non-Gaussian random fields and implement it to study the sphericity of peaks. For non-Gaussianity of the local type, we present a general formalism valid regardless of how large the deviation from Gaussian statistics is. For general types of non-Gaussianity, we provide a framework that applies to any system with a given power spectrum and the corresponding bispectrum in the regime in which contributions from higher-order correlators can be neglected. We present an explicit expression for the most probable values of the sphericity parameters, including the effect of non-Gaussianity on the shape. We show that the effects of small perturbative non-Gaussianity on the sphericity parameters are negligible, as they are even smaller than the subleading Gaussian corrections. In contrast, we find that large non-Gaussianity can significantly distort the peak configurations, making them much less spherical.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05434v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cristiano Germani, Mohammad Ali Gorji, Michiru Uwabo-Niibo, Masahide Yamaguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational wave signatures of preheating in Higgs--$R^2$ inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16907v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive analysis of the preheating dynamics and associated gravitational wave signatures in the Higgs--$R^2$ inflationary model. Using lattice simulations, we investigate the post-inflationary evolution of the system across the parameter space, covering both the Higgs-like and $R^2$-like scenarios. We demonstrate that the efficiency of preheating is significantly dependent on the nonminimal coupling parameter $\xi$. As the $\xi$ parameter increases, moving from the $R^2$-like regime to the Higgs-like regime, we observe more efficient preheating. Through detailed numerical computations, efficient preheating is shown to lead to stronger gravitational wave production. The amplitude of the gravitational wave spectrum varies by several orders of magnitude as we move from the $R^2$-like regime to the Higgs-like regime. The resultant gravitational wave signatures can serve as a potential observational probe to distinguish between different parameter regimes of the Higgs--$R^2$ model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16907v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinsu Kim, Zihao Yang, Ying-li Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Wave Signatures of Primordial Black Hole Reheating in Upcoming Interferometry Missions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18207v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the prospects of detecting a stochastic gravitational wave (GW) background from the primordial black hole (PBH) reheating epoch. If PBHs form during a non-standard cosmological phase prior to the radiation-dominated era, they can dominate the energy density of the Universe before evaporating via Hawking radiation. Such PBHs can generate induced GWs that may fall within the detectable range of future interferometry missions: (i) through isocurvature perturbations arising from the inhomogeneous spatial distribution of PBHs, and (ii) through the amplification of adiabatic perturbations triggered by the abrupt transition from PBH domination to radiation domination. We assess the detection prospects of such GW spectra using the signal-to-noise ratio, Fisher forecast analysis, and Markov chain Monte Carlo analysis with mock data from LISA and ET. Our findings reveal that ET exhibits superior sensitivity to both isocurvature- and adiabatic-induced GWs, covering a wide PBH mass range of $M_{\rm in} \in (0.5-4\times 10^7)$ g. However, we find that the relative uncertainties associated with the parameter of the isocurvature source are quite high. LISA, by contrast, is mostly sensitive to the adiabatic source, with $M_{\rm in} \in (2\times10^4-5\times 10^8)$ g. The combined effect of adiabatic and isocurvature sources on ET and LISA provides a multi-stage window into the post-inflationary Universe by constraining PBH mass, energy fraction, and the background equation of state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18207v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/08/074</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1475-7516/2025/08/074</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Debarun Paul, Md Riajul Haque, Supratik Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Dark Energy in light of the DESI DR2 Baryonic Acoustic Oscillations Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.06118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.06118v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding whether cosmic acceleration arises from a cosmological constant or a dynamical component is a central goal of cosmology, and the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) enables stringent tests with high-precision distance measurements. We analyze baryon acoustic oscillation (BAO) measurements from DESI Data Release 1 (DR1) and Data Release 2 (DR2), combined with Type Ia supernovae and a cosmic microwave background (CMB) distance prior. With the larger statistical power and wider redshift coverage of DR2, the preference for dynamical dark energy does not diminish relative to DR1. Using both a shape-function reconstruction and non-parametric approaches with a Horndeski-motivated correlation prior, we find that the dark-energy equation of state $w(z)$ varies with redshift. BAO data alone yield modest constraints, but in combination with independent supernova compilations and the CMB prior they strengthen the evidence for dynamics. Bayesian model comparison shows moderate support for departures from $\Lambda$CDM when multiple degrees of freedom in $w(z)$ are allowed, corresponding to $\approx3\sigma$ tension with $\Lambda$CDM (and higher for some data sets). Despite methodological differences, our results are consistent with companion DESI papers, underscoring the complementarity of approaches. Possible systematics remain under study; forthcoming DESI, \emph{Euclid}, and next-generation CMB data will provide decisive tests.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.06118v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gan Gu, Xiaoma Wang, Yuting Wang, Gong-Bo Zhao, Levon Pogosian, Kazuya Koyama, John A. Peacock, Zheng Cai, Jorge L. Cervantes-Cota, Mustapha Ishak, Arman Shafieloo, Ruiyang Zhao, Steven Ahlen, Davide Bianchi, David Brooks, Todd Claybaugh, Shaun Cole, Axel de la Macorra, Arnaud de Mattia, Peter Doel, Simone Ferraro, Jaime E. Forero-Romero, Enrique Gazta\~naga, Satya Gontcho A Gontcho, Gaston Gutierrez, ChangHoon Hahn, Cullan Howlett, Robert Kehoe, David Kirkby, Jean-Paul Kneib, Anthony Kremin, Ofer Lahav, Martin Landriau, Laurent Le Guillou, Alexie Leauthaud, Michael Levi, Marc Manera, Aaron Meisner, Ramon Miquel, John Moustakas, Andrea Mu\~noz-Guti\'errez, Seshadri Nadathur, Jeffrey A. Newman, Nathalie Palanque-Delabrouille, Will Percival, Francisco Prada, Ignasi P\'erez-R\`afols, Graziano Rossi, Lado Samushia, Eusebio Sanchez, David Schlegel, Hee-Jong Seo, David Sprayberry, Gregory Tarl\'e, Michael Walther, Benjamin Alan Weaver, Pauline Zarrouk, Cheng Zhao, Rongpu Zhou, Hu Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning-Based Analytical Expressions for Gray-Body Factors and Application to Primordial Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.18270v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Symbolic Regression (SR) is a machine learning approach that explores the space of mathematical expressions to identify those that best fit a given dataset, balancing both accuracy and simplicity. We apply SR to the study of Gray-Body Factors (GBFs), which play a crucial role in the derivation of Hawking radiation and are recognized for their computational complexity. We explore simple analytical forms for the GBFs of the Schwarzschild Black Hole (BH). We compare the results obtained with different approaches and quantify their consistency with those obtained by solving the Teukolsky equation. As a case study, we apply our pipeline, which we call \texttt{ReGrayssion}, to the study of Primordial Black Holes (PBHs) as Dark Matter (DM) candidates, deriving constraints on the abundance from observations of diffuse extragalactic $\gamma$-ray background. These results highlight the possible role of SR in providing human-interpretable, approximate analytical GBF expressions, offering a new pathway for investigating PBH as a DM candidate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.18270v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guan-Wen Yuan (UniTrento), Marco Calz\`a (UniTrento), Davide Pedrotti (UniTrento)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved Predictions on Higgs-Starobinsky Inflation and Reheating with ACT DR6 and Primordial Gravitational Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.04615v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the implications of recent CMB observations for Higgs-Starobinsky inflationary models and their associated reheating dynamics, utilizing data from ACT DR6, Planck 2018, BICEP/Keck 2018, and DESI, collectively referred to as P-ACT-LB-BK18. In addition to direct CMB constraints, we incorporate indirect bounds arising from the potential overproduction of primordial gravitational waves (PGWs), particularly through limits on the effective number of relativistic species, $\Delta N_{\rm eff}$, during Big Bang Nucleosynthesis (BBN). These constraints become especially relevant in scenarios featuring a stiff post-inflationary equation of state $w_{\rm RH}\geq 0.58$. Our analysis shows that, when both P-ACT-LB-BK18 data and $\Delta N_{\rm eff}$ bounds are considered, the viable number of inflationary e-folds is restricted to the range ($57.9$-$62.2$) at the $2\sigma$ confidence level (C.L.). Correspondingly, the reheating temperature is constrained to lie between the BBN energy scale and $10^{12}$ GeV, with the post-inflationary equation-of-state parameter satisfying $w_{\rm RH} &gt; 0.41$. However, no parameter space remains viable at the $1\sigma$ C.L. once $\Delta N_{\rm eff}$ constraints from PGWs are included, rendering the Higgs-Starobinsky model highly restricted.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.04615v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2025.139852</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Md Riajul Haque, Sourav Pal, Debarun Paul</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Hubble constant estimation with dark standard sirens and galaxy cluster catalogues</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14077</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14077v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we explore the possibility of using galaxy cluster catalogues to provide redshift support for a gravitational-wave dark standard siren measurement of the Hubble constant $H_0$. We adapt the cosmology inference pipeline gwcosmo to handle galaxy cluster catalogues. Together with binary black holes from the GWTC-3, we use galaxy cluster data from the PSZ2 and the eRASS catalogues. With these catalogues, we obtain $H_0 = 77^{+10}_{-10}$ and $81^{+8}_{-8}\, \text{km}\, \text{s}^{-1}\, \text{Mpc}^{-1}$ respectively, which demonstrates improvements on precision by factors of 10% and 38% respectively over the traditional galaxy catalogue result. This exploratory work paves the way towards precise and accurate cosmography making use of distant compact binary mergers from upcoming observing runs of the LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA detector network and future gravitational-wave observatories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14077v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Freija Beirnaert, Archisman Ghosh, Gergely D\'alya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Lyman-$\alpha$ emitter bispectrum as a probe of reionization morphology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.17188v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Ly$\alpha$ emitters (LAEs) have now been discovered out to redshift $z=13$, and are valuable probes of the reionization history at redshifts beyond the reach of other currently available tracers. Most inferences of the neutral hydrogen fraction from LAE observations rely on one-point and two-point statistics like the luminosity function and the power spectrum. We present here an analysis of the bispectrum of high-redshift LAEs and demonstrate its sensitivity to the Epoch of Reionization. We use the Sherwood-Relics suite of cosmological hydrodynamical simulations post-processed with the GPU-based radiative transfer code ATON-HE to generate realistic LAE mock catalogues for a wide range of reionization models, varying the ionization history and the source populations, including contributions of AGN to hydrogen reionization. We demonstrate that the bispectrum provides greater sensitivity than the power spectrum to both the timing and spatial morphology of reionization. Using reduced-$\chi^2$ analysis we further show that the bispectrum also responds more strongly to variations in source population and AGN contribution, apparently more efficiently capturing morphological features missed by two-point statistics. The redshift evolution of the bispectrum reflects the increased clustering of ionizing sources at earlier epochs. The sensitivity of the bispectrum to peculiar velocities underscores the importance of velocity corrections in comparisons to observations. Our findings demonstrate that the LAE bispectrum is a powerful higher-order statistic for probing reionization through current and future LAE surveys using telescopes such as Subaru and JWST.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.17188v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/staf1262</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, Volume 542, Issue 1, September 2025, Pages 486-507</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Soumak Maitra (TIFR), Girish Kulkarni, Shikhar Asthana, James S. Bolton, Martin G. Haehnelt, Laura Keating</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid and accurate numerical evolution of linear cosmological perturbations with non-cold relics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01956</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.01956v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We describe the implementation of a new approach to the numerical evaluation of the effects of non-cold relics on the evolution of cosmological perturbations. The Boltzmann hierarchies used to compute the contributions of these relics to the stress-energy tensor are replaced with a set of integral equations. These integral equations take the form of convolutions and are solved iteratively with the rest of the system. We develop efficient algorithms for evaluating these convolutions using non-uniform fast Fourier transforms (NUFFTs). This approach enables efficient and accurate evaluation of the cosmic microwave background anisotropies and matter power spectra, all the way through the history of the Universe, without relying on semi-analytic approximations at late times. We implement this method in the Boltzmann solver CLASS, resulting in a new code called CLASSIER (for CLASS Integral Equation Revision), and apply it to massive-neutrino perturbations as a demonstration. The implementation is optimized to accurately capture the distinct behaviors of perturbations in both super-/near-horizon and sub-horizon regimes. Our results match the accuracy of a fully converged Boltzmann hierarchy solution while avoiding numerical artifacts from truncation of the Boltzmann hierarchy at finite multipole and offering substantial speedups depending on the required precision and the range of scales of interest. This new framework provides a practical and robust alternative for the truncated Boltzmann hierarchy approach, especially for studying beyond $\Lambda$CDM non-cold relics with signatures on small scales. CLASSIER is publicly available at https://github.com/nanoomlee/CLASSIER.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.01956v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/fs6c-zbzf</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Nanoom Lee, Jos\'e Luis Bernal, Sven G\"unther, Lingyuan Ji, Marc Kamionkowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing Light Unaffiliated Mass Clumps in MACS 0416 on galaxy and galaxy cluster scales using JWST</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16034</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16034v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Light unaffiliated mass clumps (LUMCs), i.e. dark matter (DM) components without any stellar counterparts, have been reported in strong lensing mass reconstructions of MACS 0416, both on galaxy and galaxy cluster scales. On galaxy cluster scale, the most recent parametric study based on 303 multiple images features a LUMC, in the south of the cluster. On galaxy scale, the most recent GRALE non-parametric study based on 237 multiple images features two LUMCs, M1 and M2. Given the implications of these findings in the context of structure formation and evolution, we test these features parametrically, using LENSTOOL. First, we show that a mass model where each large scale DM component introduced in the modelling is associated with a stellar counterpart can reproduce the 303 multiple images, removing the need for any cluster scale LUMC in \lens. We then update the GRALE model using the 303 multiple images, finding that one of the two galaxy scale LUMC, M1, is no longer significant, while M2 remains. We test M2 by explicitely including it in our parametric model. We find that the inclusion of this LUMC does not improve the global RMS, but mildly improves locally the RMS for one multiple image located close to M2. Besides, the preferred mass for M2 corresponds to the lowest mass allowed by the adopted prior. M2 is therefore not strongly favoured by a parametric approach but it is not ruled out. We present a comparison of parametric and non-parametric models in the M2 area. Both approaches show very similar surface mass density at this location, with a 5-6 % difference between the mass maps. The difference is that GRALE favors a distinct mass substructure when LENSTOOL favors a more diffuse mass distribution. We have been able to propose a parametric mass model without including any LUMCs, providing further evidences for DM being associated with light in clusters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16034v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marceau Limousin, Derek Perera, Gregor Rihtarsic, Liliya L. R. Williams, Jori Liesenborgs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating the imprint of quintessence in cosmic magnification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.06200v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study cosmic magnification beyond lensing in a late-time universe dominated by quintessence and cold dark matter. The cosmic magnification angular power spectrum, especially going beyond the well-known lensing effect, provides an independent avenue for investigating the properties of quintessence, and hence, dark energy. By analysing the magnification power spectrum at different redshifts, it is possible to extract new information about the large-scale imprint of dark energy, including whether we are able to disentangle different models from one another. Using three well-known quintessence models, we analyse the cosmic magnification angular power spectrum while taking relativistic corrections into account. We found that it will be difficult to distinguish between quintessence models, and quintessence from the cosmological constant, in lensing magnification angular power spectrum on large scales, at redshifts $z \,{\leq}\, 1$; whereas, when relativistic corrections are incorporated, the total magnification angular power spectrum holds the potential to distinguish between the models, at the given $z$. At $z \,{\geq}\, 3$, the lensing magnification angular power spectrum can be a reasonable approximation of the total magnification angular power spectrum. We also found that both the total relativistic and the Doppler magnification signals, respectively, surpass cosmic variance at $z \,{\leq}\, 0.5$: hence the effect may be detectable at the given $z$. On the other hand, the ISW and the time-delay magnification signals, respectively, are surpassed by cosmic variance on all scales, at epochs up to $z \,{=}\, 4.5$, with the gravitational-potential magnification signal being zero.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.06200v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enas Mohamed (BIUST), Didam Duniya (BIUST), Hassan Abdalla (UCM, NWU,Omdurman), Bishop Mongwane (Cape Town)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Growth Index in the $\gamma\delta$CDM model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14749v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: To better distinguish the nature of $H_0$ and $S_8$ tensions, it is necessary to separate the effects of expansion and the growth of structure. The growth index $\gamma$ was identified as the most important parameter that characterizes the growth of density fluctuations independently of the effects of cosmic expansion. In the $\Lambda$CDM model, analyses performed with various cosmological datasets indicate that the growth index has to be larger than its theoretically predicted value. Cosmological models based on $f(R)$ gravity theories have scale-dependent growth indices, whose values are even more at odds with the growth rate data. In this work, we evaluate the growth index in the $\gamma\delta$CDM model both theoretically and numerically. Although based on $f(R)$ gravity theory, we show through several analyses with different combinations of datasets that the growth index in the $\gamma\delta$CDM model is very close in value to the $\Lambda$CDM and the $\omega$CDM models. The growth of structure is suppressed in the $\gamma\delta$CDM model, which is formulated with the extended gravitational growth framework. When faced with cosmological data, we also demonstrate that the $\gamma\delta$CDM model fits better than the $\Lambda$CDM and the $\omega$CDM models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14749v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cemsinan Deliduman, Furkan \c{S}akir Dilsiz, Selinay Sude Binici</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyper Suprime-Cam Y3 results: photo-$z$ bias calibration with lensing shear ratios and cosmological constraints from cosmic shear</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.21681v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present an independent calibration of the photometric redshift (photo-$z$) distributions for source galaxies in the HSC-Y3 weak lensing survey using small-scale galaxy-galaxy lensing. By measuring the tangential shear around spectroscopic lens galaxies from GAMA, SDSS, and DESI, divided into fifteen narrow redshift bins, we compute shear ratios that are sensitive to the mean redshift of source galaxies. Using a blinded analysis, we derive constraints on the photo-$z$ bias parameters in source bins 2, 3 and 4, achieving signal-to-noise ratios of 59, 75, and 62, respectively. Our constraints for $\Delta z_2$, $\Delta z_3$ and $\Delta z_4$ are consistent with those from HSC-Y3 cosmic shear modeling. We observe a mild shift in the $\Delta z_3$-$\Delta z_4$ plane due to the heterogeneous depth of the lens sample, which disappears when using only DESI-DR1 lenses. Combining shear-ratio measurements with cosmic shear data, we obtain joint constraints on cosmological parameters: $\Omega_{\rm m} = 0.286_{-0.074}^{+0.038}$ and $S_8 = 0.760_{-0.145}^{+0.044}$, consistent with cosmic shear-only results. This work demonstrates the utility of small-scale lensing as an independent probe for calibrating photometric redshift bias in weak lensing cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.21681v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Divya Rana, Surhud More, Hironao Miyatake, Sunao Sugiyama, Tianqing Zhang, Masato Shirasaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for echoes on the edge of quantum black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.00025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.00025v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: I perform a template-based search for stimulated emission of Hawking radiation (or Boltzmann echoes) by combining the gravitational wave data from 47 binary black hole merger events observed by the LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA collaboration. With a Bayesian inference approach, I found no statistically significant evidence for this signal in either of the 3 Gravitational Wave Transient Catalogs GWTC-1, GWTC-2 and GWTC-3. While the data does not provide definitive evidence against the presence of Boltzmann echoes, the Bayesian evidence for most events falls within the range of 0.3-1.6, with the hypothesis of a common (non-vanishing) echo amplitude for all mergers being weakly disfavoured at 2:5 odds. The only exception is GW190521, the most massive and confidently detected event ever observed, which shows a positive evidence of 9.2 for stimulated Hawking radiation. The ''look-elsewhere'' effect for this outlier event is assessed by applying two distinct methods to add simulated signals in real data, before and after the event, giving false (true) positive detection probabilities for higher Bayes factors of $1.5^{+1.2}_{-0.9}\%$, $4.4^{+2.0}_{-2.0} \%$ ($35 \pm 7 \%$, $35 \pm 15 \%$). An optimal combination of posteriors yields an upper limit of $A &lt; 0.4$ (at $90\%$ confidence level) for a universal echo amplitude, whereas $A \sim 1$ was predicted in the canonical model. To ensure the robustness of the results, I have employed an additional method to combine the events hierarchically. This approach involves using a target gaussian distribution and extracting the parameters from multiple uncertain observations, which may be affected by selection biases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.00025v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jahed Abedi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Effects of the Gravitational Coupling Variation on the Local $H_0$ Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.11947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.11947v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the effects of the time evolution of the matter-gravity coupling on the luminosity distance, showing it can provide a natural explanation to the apparent Hubble tension. The gravitational coupling evolution induces a modification of the Friedman equation with respect to the $\Lambda$CDM model, which we study in both the Einstein and Jordan frame. We consider a phenomenological parametrization of the low redshift variation of the coupling in a narrow redshift shell, showing how it can affect the distance of the anchors used to calibrate supernovae (SNe), while higher redshift background observations are not affected. This effect is purely geometrical, and it is not related to any change of the intrinsic SNe physical properties. The effects of a time varying gravity coupling only manifest on sufficiently long time scales, such as in cosmological observations at different redshifts, and if ignored lead to apparent tensions in the values of cosmological parameters estimated with observations from different epochs of the Universe history.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.11947v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/universe11080278</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Universe2025,11(8),278</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Enea Romano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalar-Gauss-Bonnet gravity: Infrared causality and detectability of GW observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10973</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10973v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate time delays of wave scatterings around black hole backgrounds in scalar-tensor effective field theories of gravity. The scalar-Gauss-Bonnet (sGB) couplings, being corrections of the lowest orders, can give rise to hairy black holes. By requiring infrared causality, we impose lower bounds on the cutoff scales of the theories. With these bounds, we further discuss the detectability of sGB gravity in gravitational waves from binary black hole mergers. Compared with the gravitational effective field theories that contain only the two tensor modes, adding extra degrees of freedom, such as adding a scalar, opens up a detectable window in the planned observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10973v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Kai Nie, Lin-Tao Tan, Jun Zhang, Shuang-Yong Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flipped Rotating Axion Non-minimally Coupled to Gravity: Baryogenesis and Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08720v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate that the co-genesis of baryon asymmetry and dark matter can be achieved through the rotation of an axion-like particle, driven by a flip in the vacuum manifold's direction at the end of inflation. This can occur if the axion has a periodic non-minimal coupling to gravity, while preserving the discrete shift symmetry. In non-oscillating inflation models, after inflation there is typically a period of kination (with $w = 1$). In this case, it is shown that the vacuum manifold of the axion is flipped and the axion begins rotating in field space, because it can slide across the decreasing potential barrier as in Ricci reheating. Such a rotating axion can generate the baryon asymmetry of the Universe through spontaneous baryogenesis, while at later epochs it can oscillate as dark matter. The period of kination makes the primordial gravitational waves (GW) generated during inflation sharply blue-tilted which constrains the parameter space due to GW overproduction, while being testable by next generation CMB experiments. As a concrete example, we show that such a cogenesis of baryon asymmetry and dark matter can be realized for the axion as the Majoron in the Type-I seesaw setup, predicting mass ranges for the Majoron below sub eVs, with right-handed neutrino mass above $\mathcal{O}(10^{8})$ GeV. We also show that in order to avoid fragmentation of the axion condensate during the rotation, we require the non-minimal coupling $\xi \sim (f/m_P)^2 $ or somewhat larger, where $f$ is the axion decay constant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08720v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao Chen, Suruj Jyoti Das, Konstantinos Dimopoulos, Anish Ghoshal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Spin-2 Field Solitons as a Source of Electromagnetic Radiation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.12569</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.12569v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Spin-$s$ light dark boson particles can exhibit wave-like behavior, capable of forming long-lived, coherent, spatially localized structures known as solitons. This work considers the possibility that a light spin-2 particle might be part of or all the dark matter content of the Universe, which could result in a significant fraction of solitons existing today in galactic halos. If these dark matter particles interact with electromagnetism through dimension-6 operators, the solitons may experience parametric resonance of photons triggered by the surrounding electromagnetic field. We explore the feasibility and key characteristics of this electromagnetic radiation, as well as the potential for detection through soliton mergers using ground-based facilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.12569v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/08/085</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 08 (2025) 085</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Enrico D. Schiappacasse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isotropic cosmic birefringence from string axion domain walls without cosmic strings, and DESI results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18417</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18417v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recently, results from the Atacama Cosmology Telescope (ACT) DR6 have shown a preference for isotropic cosmic birefringence, consistent with previous analyses based on Planck and WMAP data. Separately, the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) DR2 results suggest that dark energy evolves over cosmic history, pointing to new physics in the late-time universe. In this paper, we propose that domain walls associated with the string axion can naturally explain the isotropic cosmic birefringence, focusing on the case in which the axion starts near a hilltop. Interestingly, to avoid the domain wall problem, these walls must form well after recombination. The predicted rotation angle, $\beta \approx 0.21\,c_\gamma$ degrees (with anomaly coefficient $c_\gamma \approx 1$), is in excellent agreement with observations. This scenario can be further tested by probing anisotropic birefringence of photons emitted long after recombination, as well as gravitational waves. Moreover, starting the axion oscillation from a hilltop naturally enhances its abundance via anharmonic effects, thus contributing to the dark energy component. We discuss how this hilltop axion scenario may connect with the DESI results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18417v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/pjf4-sn4v</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 112 (2025) 043538</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Junseok Lee, Kai Murai, Fuminobu Takahashi, Wen Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Lyman-alpha and Continuum Origins Survey. I. Survey description and Ly$\alpha$ imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07056</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.07056v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Understanding the mechanisms driving the escape of ionizing or Lyman continuum (LyC) emission from the interstellar medium of galaxies is necessary to constrain the evolution of reionization, and the sources responsible for it. While progress has been made into identifying the global galaxy properties linked to the escape fraction of ionizing radiation, $f_{esc}^{LyC}$, little is currently known about how spatially resolved galaxy properties impact this parameter. We present Hubble Space Telescope (HST) imaging data obtained as part of the Lyman $\alpha$ and Continuum Origins Survey (LaCOS). LaCOS consists of HST imaging in 5 filters covering rest-frame optical and UV bands for a subsample of 42 galaxies in the Low redshift Lyman Continuum Survey, 22 being Lyman continuum emitters ($f_{esc}^{LyC}=0.01-0.49$). Here, we describe the sample, observations and data reduction, and investigate connections between global and sub-kpc Lyman $\alpha$ (Ly$\alpha$) emission, and $f_{esc}^{LyC}$. We confirm the correlation between $f_{esc}^{LyC}$ and EW$_{Ly\alpha}$ , and the anticorrelation with $r_{50}$, when using values obtained via global photometry. We also find correlations previously found with spectroscopy with global photometric $L_{Ly\alpha}$, $f_{esc}^{Ly\alpha}$, $\Sigma_{SFR}$ , and $f_{esc}^{LyC}$, but with a smaller degree of correlation ($\overline{|\Delta\tau|}\sim0.1$). We find correlations are strongest between $Ly\alpha$ observables ($L_{\rm Ly\alpha}$, EW$_{\rm Ly\alpha}$) and $f_{\rm esc}^{\rm LyC}$ when measured in a small aperture around the brightest UV source in each galaxy. We interpret these results as evidence that LyC photons escaping on the line-of-sight are contributed by a small number of UV-bright compact regions in most galaxies in LaCOS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.07056v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4365/adf227</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Alexandra Le Reste, Claudia Scarlata, Matthew Hayes, Jens Melinder, Alberto Saldana-Lopez, Aaron Smith, Axel Runnholm, Yu-Heng Lin, Ricardo O. Amor\'in, Hakim Atek, Sanchayeeta Borthakur, Cody A. Carr, Brian Fleming, Sophia R. Flury, Mauro Giavalisco, Alaina Henry, Anne E. Jaskot, Zhiyuan Ji, Intae Jung, Floriane Leclercq, Rui Marques-Chaves, Stephan R. McCandliss, M. S. Oey, G\"oran \"Ostlin, Swara Ravindranath, Daniel Schaerer, Trinh X. Thuan, Xinfeng Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prospective sensitivity of CTAO on detection of evaporating primordial black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17478v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: As the lifetime of a black hole decreases, the energy of the Hawking radiation it emits increases, ultimately culminating in its disappearance through a powerful burst of gamma rays. For primordial black holes (PBHs) with an initial mass of $\sim 5\times10^{14}$ g, their lifespans are expected to end in the present epoch. Detecting such PBH bursts would provide compelling evidence of their existence. The Cherenkov Telescope Array Observatory (CTAO) has the potential to observe these bursts at the high-energy end of the gamma-ray spectrum. To investigate this possibility, we conduct a study to evaluate the sensitivity of CTAO to the local burst rate density of PBHs. Our results suggest that during a 5-year observational campaign, CTAO could exclude a local burst rate density exceeding $\sim 36\ \mathrm{pc}^{-3}\ \mathrm{yr}^{-1}$, which represents an improvement of one order of magnitude over the upper limit set by the Large High Altitude Air Shower Observatory (LHAASO). In addition, we propose an observation strategy optimized for detecting PBH bursts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17478v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/09/004</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 09 (2025) 004</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Chen Yang, Jun-Da Pan, Xin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Self-Interacting Dark Matter via Gravitational-Wave Background from Eccentric Supermassive Black Hole Mergers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09219</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09219v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The nature of dark matter is still mysterious despite various astronomical evidence. As a possible candidate, self-interacting dark matter (SIDM) can potentially resolve some issues appearing in cold dark matter paradigm. Here we investigate how SIDM around supermassive black holes (SMBH) in galaxy centers may form a density spike and imprint in the spectrum shape of stochastic gravitational-wave background from SMBH binaries (SMBHBs). Employing a refined dynamical friction formula and consistently evolving the orbital dynamics, we demonstrate that current pulsar timing arrays (PTAs) data is sensitive to the cross section of SIDM with $\sigma(v)/m_\chi\lesssim0.66\,\mathrm{cm}^2/\mathrm{g}$, comparable to other astrophysical probes. We also highlight the importance of including the eccentricity of SMBHBs in the parameter inference, which would affect the results significantly. Our findings reveal the promising potential of PTAs observations in probing the nature of dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09219v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/lzqc-xr4c</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 112 (2025) 4, 043033</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mu-Chun Chen, Yong Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Influence of cosmic expansion on gravitational waveforms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.17886v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Gravitational waves undergo redshift as they propagate through the expanding universe, and the redshift may exhibit time-dependent drift. Consequently, for any isolated gravitational wave sources, the mass parameter $\mathcal{M}$ and the redshift $z$ exhibit an observational degeneracy, typically manifesting in the waveform as the redshifted mass $\mathcal{M}(1+z)$. Matching together the wave propagation and the wave generation solutions, we show that dimensionless source parameters depending on mass $\mathcal{M}$ can break this degeneracy. Notably, the postmerger signal from binary neutron stars contains several dimensionless parameters that satisfy this condition, including the quality factors of different frequency components and their frequency ratios. Considering the observations of solely the postmerger signal by the Neutron star Extreme Matter Observatory or the Einstein Telescope, based on the Fisher analysis, we find that the redshift can be measured with fractional uncertainties of $\sim30\%$ for sources at $0.01&lt;z&lt;0.09$. Additionally, we present a corrected derivation of the waveform phase correction due to the redshift drift effect, rectifying a sign error in previous studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.17886v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/wg63-t8bp</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Tan Liu, Wen-Fan Feng, Zong-Kuan Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New model of spontaneous scalarization of black holes induced by curvature and matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12137v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a new model of black hole spontaneous scalarization that combines a scalar--Gauss--Bonnet interaction with a non--minimal coupling to a U(1) gauge field (a dark photon or an electromagnetic field). This construction generalizes earlier single-coupling setups and allows both curvature--induced and matter--induced scalarization within one framework, which allows us to overcome the limitations of each mechanism alone. We focus on charged, spherically symmetric black holes and demonstrate that our model substantially expands the range of black hole masses and charges that permit scalar hair. Negative Gauss--Bonnet couplings, previously associated only with near--extremal charges or rapidly spinning black holes, now trigger scalarization for much broader charge intervals. We develop a numerical procedure to solve the field equations, and investigate the various properties of these black holes. This results in new branches emerging at distinct mass thresholds, a behavior not seen in the pure Einstein--scalar--Gauss--Bonnet or Einstein--scalar--Gauss--Bonnet--Ricci models. The scalar charge depends sensitively on the coupling parameters and on the $U(1)$ charge. Our analysis also shows that these black holes have larger entropy than their Reissner--Nordstr\"om counterparts and can become overcharged, surpassing the usual extremal limit of charge-to-mass ratio. Analyzing the scalar charge behavior suggests that adding matter-coupling appears to stabilize solutions that were previously prone to higher-order instabilities in pure Gauss--Bonnet models with quadratic coupling and broadens the range of possible configurations, making this model a promising candidate for further studies in strong gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12137v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/ln23-nhpn</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Zakaria Belkhadria, Salvatore Mignemi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Fluctuation to Polarization: Imprints of $O(1-10)\, \mathrm{Mpc}^{-1}$ Curvature Perturbations in CMB B-modes from Scalar-Induced Gravitational Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02044</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.02044v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Probing primordial curvature perturbations on small scales, beyond those accessible using cosmic microwave background (CMB) primary anisotropies and Lyman-$\alpha$ forest data, remains a major open challenge. Current constraints on the scalar power spectrum at these scales are either weak or rely heavily on model-dependent assumptions about small-scale structure. In this work, we propose a novel method to probe the small-scale primordial power spectrum using scalar-induced tensor perturbations, which are inevitably sourced by curvature perturbations at second order in cosmological perturbation theory. While induced tensor modes have traditionally been studied in the context of the stochastic gravitational wave background, we highlight a complementary observable: the distinctive pattern of B-mode polarization they imprint on the CMB. We compute the angular spectrum of these B-modes arising from enhanced scalar perturbations and show that the resulting signal can be competitive with inflationary predictions for values of the tensor-to-scalar ratio targeted in upcoming CMB experiments, most notably CMB-Stage 4. We map the region of the scalar power spectrum to which these future B-mode experiments will be sensitive and compare with existing constraints, finding it to exceed current sensitivities at $k \sim O(1-10)\, \mathrm{Mpc}^{-1}$. In addition to providing a new CMB-based probe of the small-scale power spectrum, this work also motivates dedicated B-mode searches at higher multipoles ($\ell \gtrsim 100$).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.02044v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aurora Ireland, Kuver Sinha, Tao Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for spatial coincidences between galaxy mergers and Fermi-LAT 4FGL-DR4 sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03970v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a systematic search for spatial association between a high confidence sample of 3,166 morphologically selected galaxy mergers drawn from the initial convolutional neural network (CNN) catalog of 328,151 candidate mergers and refined through SDSS cross-matching and the Fermi Large Area Telescope Fourth Source Catalog Data Release 4 (4FGL-DR4) catalog of gamma-ray sources detected by the Fermi Large Area Telescope (LAT). Using a conservative 4$\sigma$ positional uncertainty threshold and a Poisson based statistical framework, we identify 21 statistically significant associations with match probabilities $p &lt; 0.05$. Among these are known classes of gamma-ray emitters such as Flat-Spectrum Radio Quasars (FSRQs), BL Lacertae objects (BLL), and radio galaxies bolstering the hypothesis that merger driven processes can fuel high energy activity. Intriguingly, five of the associated sources remain unclassified in 4FGL-DR4, hinting at a possible link between galaxy mergers and a hitherto unrecognized population of gamma-ray sources. The dominance of AGN like matches supports the scenario in which mergers trigger accretion onto central supermassive black holes, initiating AGN activity observable at gamma-ray energies. Moreover, the recurrent presence of unassociated sources among secure matches underscores the potential of merger catalogs as physically motivated priors in gamma-ray source identification efforts. This work constitutes the first dedicated effort to explore associations between gamma-ray sources and a large, morphologically selected sample of galaxy mergers catalog, opening new avenues for understanding the role of galaxy interactions in high-energy astrophysics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03970v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siddhant Manna, Shantanu Desai</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
