<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO</link>
    <description>astro-ph.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 04:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The Luminosity of the Darkness: Schechter function in dark sirens</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13568v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Gravitational waves (GWs) offer a novel avenue for probing the Universe. One of their exciting applications is the independent measurement of the Hubble constant, $H_0$, using dark standard sirens, which combine GW signals with galaxy catalogues considering that GW events are hosted by galaxies. However, due to the limited reach of telescopes, galaxy catalogues are incomplete at high redshifts. The commonly used GLADE+ is complete only up to redshift $z=0.1$, necessitating a model accounting for the galaxy luminosity distribution accounting for the selection function of galaxies, typically described by the Schechter function. In this paper, we examine the influence of the Schechter function model on dark sirens, focusing on its redshift evolution and its impact on $H_0$ and rate parameters measurements. We find that neglecting the evolution of the Schechter function can influence the prior in redshift on GWs, which has particularly high impact for distant GW events with limited galaxy catalogue support. Moreover, conducting a joint estimation of $H_0$ and the rate parameters, we find that allowing them to vary fixes the bias in $H_0$ but the rate parameter $\gamma$ depends on the evolving Schechter function. Our results underscore the importance of incorporating an evolving Schechter function to account for changes in galaxy populations over cosmic time, as this impacts rate parameters to which $H_0$ is sensitive.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13568v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cezary Turski, Maria Lisa Brozzetti, Gergely D\'alya, Michele Punturo, Archisman Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forward vs Backward: Improving BAO Constraints with Field-Level Inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13588</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13588v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present results of field-level inference of the baryon acoustic oscillation (BAO) scale $r_s$ on rest-frame dark matter halo catalogs. Our field-level constraint on $r_s$ is obtained by explicitly sampling the initial conditions along with the bias and noise parameters via the LEFTfield EFT-based forward model. Comparing with a standard reconstruction pipeline applied to the same data and over the same scales, the field-level constraint on the BAO scale improves by a factor of $\sim 1.2-1.4$ over standard BAO reconstruction. We point to a surprisingly simple source of the additional information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13588v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ivana Babi\'c, Fabian Schmidt, Beatriz Tucci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Galaxy Surveys with Hybrid SBI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13591v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Simulation-based inference (SBI) has emerged as a powerful tool for extracting cosmological information from galaxy surveys deep into the non-linear regime. Despite its great promise, its application is limited by the computational cost of running simulations that can describe the increasingly-large cosmological datasets. Recent work proposed a hybrid SBI framework (HySBI), which combines SBI on small-scales with perturbation theory (PT) on large-scales, allowing information to be extracted from high-resolution observations without large-volume simulations. In this work, we lay out the HySBI framework for galaxy clustering, a key step towards its application to next-generation datasets. We study the choice of priors on the parameters for modeling galaxies in PT analysis and in simulation-based analyses, as well as investigate their cosmology dependence. By jointly modeling large- and small-scale statistics and their associated nuisance parameters, we show that HySBI can obtain 20\% and 60\% tighter constraints on $\Omega_m$ and $\sigma_8$, respectively, compared to traditional PT analyses, thus demonstrating the efficacy of this approach to maximally extract information from upcoming spectroscopic datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13591v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gemma Zhang, Chirag Modi, Oliver H. E. Philcox</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinguishing Distance Duality breaking models using electromagnetic and gravitational waves measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13613</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13613v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Several assumptions at the foundation of the standard cosmological model have as a direct consequence a specific relation between cosmological distances, known as the distance duality relation, whose violation would be a smoking gun of deviations from standard cosmology. We explore the role of upcoming gravitational wave observations in investigating possible deviations from the distance duality relation, alongside the more commonly used supernovae. We find that, when combined with baryon acoustic oscillations, gravitational waves will provide similar constraining power to the combination of baryon acoustic oscillations and supernovae. Moreover, the combination of observables with different sensitivities to electromagnetic and gravitational physics provides a promising way to discriminate among different physical mechanisms that could lead to violations of the distance duality relation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13613v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chiara De Leo, Matteo Martinelli, Rocco D'Agostino, Giulia Gianfagna, Carlos J. A. P. Martins</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Field-Level Comparison and Robustness Analysis of Cosmological N-Body Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13620v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the first field-level comparison of cosmological N-body simulations, considering various widely used codes: Abacus, CUBEP$^3$M, Enzo, Gadget, Gizmo, PKDGrav, and Ramses. Unlike previous comparisons focused on summary statistics, we conduct a comprehensive field-level analysis: evaluating statistical similarity, quantifying implications for cosmological parameter inference, and identifying the regimes in which simulations are consistent. We begin with a traditional comparison using the power spectrum, cross-correlation coefficient, and visual inspection of the matter field. We follow this with a statistical out-of-distribution (OOD) analysis to quantify distributional differences between simulations, revealing insights not captured by the traditional metrics. We then perform field-level simulation-based inference (SBI) using convolutional neural networks (CNNs), training on one simulation and testing on others, including a full hydrodynamic simulation for comparison. We identify several causes of OOD behavior and biased inference, finding that resolution effects, such as those arising from adaptive mesh refinement (AMR), have a significant impact. Models trained on non-AMR simulations fail catastrophically when evaluated on AMR simulations, introducing larger biases than those from hydrodynamic effects. Differences in resolution, even when using the same N-body code, likewise lead to biased inference. We attribute these failures to a CNN's sensitivity to small-scale fluctuations, particularly in voids and filaments, and demonstrate that appropriate smoothing brings the simulations into statistical agreement. Our findings motivate the need for careful data filtering and the use of field-level OOD metrics, such as PQMass, to ensure robust inference.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13620v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrian E. Bayer, Francisco Villaescusa-Navarro, Sammy Sharief, Romain Teyssier, Lehman H. Garrison, Laurence Perreault-Levasseur, Greg L. Bryan, Marco Gatti, Eli Visbal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Reheating Phase via Non-Helical Magnetogenesis and Secondary Gravitational Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13623</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13623v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the past two decades, significant advancements have been made in observational techniques to enhance our understanding of the universe and its evolutionary processes. However, our knowledge of the post-inflation reheating phase remains limited due to its small-scale dynamics. Traditional observations, such as those of the Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB), primarily provide insights into large-scale dynamics, making it challenging to glean information about the reheating era. In this paper, our primary aim is to explore how the generation of Gravitational Waves (GWs) spectra, resulting from electromagnetic fields in the early universe, can offer valuable insights into the Reheating dynamics. We investigate how the spectral shape of GWs varies across different frequency ranges, depending on the initial magnetic profile and reheating dynamics. For this, we consider a well-known non-helical magnetogenesis model, where the usual electromagnetic kinetic term is coupled with a background scalar. Notably, for such a scenario, we observe distinct spectral shapes with sufficiently high amplitudes for different reheating histories with the equation of state parametrized by ($w_{\rm re}$). We identify spectral breaks in the GW spectra for both $w_{\rm re}&lt;1/3$ and $w_{\rm re}&gt;1/3$ scenarios. We find that future GW experiments such as BBO, LISA, SKA, and DECIGO are well within the reach of observing those distinct spectral shapes and can potentially shed light on the underlying mechanism of the reheating phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13623v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhasis Maiti, Debaprasad Maity, Rohan Srikanth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Hubble constant estimation with dark standard sirens and galaxy cluster catalogues</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14077</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14077v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we explore the possibility of using galaxy cluster catalogues to provide redshift support for a gravitational-wave dark standard siren measurement of the Hubble constant $H_0$. We adapt the cosmology inference pipeline gwcosmo to handle galaxy cluster catalogues. Together with binary black holes from the GWTC-3, we use galaxy cluster data from the PSZ2 and the eRASS catalogues. With these catalogues, we obtain $H_0 = 77^{+10}_{-10}$ and $81^{+8}_{-8}\, \text{km}\, \text{s}^{-1}\, \text{Mpc}^{-1}$ respectively, which demonstrates improvements on precision by factors of 10% and 38% respectively over the traditional galaxy catalogue result. This exploratory work paves the way towards precise and accurate cosmography making use of distant compact binary mergers from upcoming observing runs of the LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA detector network and future gravitational-wave observatories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14077v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Freija Beirnaert, Archisman Ghosh, Gergely D\'alya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D matter power spectrum correspondence to 1D Lyman-alpha flux power spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14258</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14258v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The 3D distribution of matter at small scales encodes valuable information about the nature of dark matter and other fundamental physics. A prominent probe of such scales outside galaxies is the Lyman-alpha forest, which studies absorption features in the spectra of high-redshift quasars caused by neutral hydrogen. The measured quantity is the power spectrum of the absorbed flux, which indirectly traces the underlying matter distribution. However, the connection between the measured flux power spectrum and the underlying 3D dark matter power spectrum is highly nontrivial. The flux power spectrum (i) represents a one-dimensional projection of the density field; (ii) traces only neutral hydrogen, subject to thermodynamic pressure; and (iii) is a nonlinear function of local matter density. Additionally, thermal broadening and redshift-space distortions-determined not only by the hydrogen distribution but also by its thermal state and local velocity field-further complicate interpretation. To robustly constrain dark matter properties using the Lyman-alpha forest, these systematics must be carefully modeled and controlled. In this paper, we present a simple phenomenological recipe for mapping the 3D matter power spectrum to the flux power spectrum. We first motivate our approach in the linear regime, then extend it to later times and into the nonlinear regime. We validate our model against a broad suite of warm and cold dark matter simulations, demonstrating that our recipe yields consistent and accurate estimates across a wide parameter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14258v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ivan Ridkokasha, Andres Aramburo-Garcia, Kyrylo Bondarenko, Anastasia Sokolenko, Matthieu Schaller, Alexey Boyarsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The first direct imaging of the silhouette of a damped Lyman $\alpha$ system along the line-of-sight to a background galaxy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14293</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14293v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The H~{\sc i} gas distribution in damped Lyman $\alpha$ absorbers (DLAs) has remained elusive due to the point-source nature of background quasar emission. Observing DLAs against spatially extended background galaxies provides a new method for constraining their size and structure. Using the Keck Cosmic Web Imager, we present the first ``silhouette'' image of a DLA at $z=3.34$, identified in the spectrum of a background galaxy at $z=3.61$. Although the silhouette remains unresolved due to limited spatial resolution, this represents a successful proof-of-concept for studying DLA morphology using extended background sources. Possible residual emission in the DLA trough suggests an optical depth contrast exceeding $10^7$ in the internal structure, implying a sharp edge or patchy structure. A Lyman $\alpha$ emitter (LAE) at $z_{\rm LAE}=3.3433\pm0.0005$, consistent with the DLA redshift, is detected at an angular separation of $1.''73\pm0.''28$ ($12.9\pm2.1$ kpc). The DLA is surrounded by three galaxies within 140 kpc in projected distance and 500 km s$^{-1}$ in line-of-sight velocity, indicating that it resides in the circumgalactic medium of the LAE or within a galaxy group/protocluster environment. An O~{\sc i} $\lambda1302$ absorption at $z_{\rm OI}=3.3288\pm0.0004$ is also detected along the line of sight. This absorber may trace metal-enriched outflow from the LAE or a gas-rich galaxy exhibiting the highest star formation activity among the surrounding galaxies. Future large spectroscopic surveys of galaxies will expand such a DLA sample, and three-dimensional spectroscopy for it will shed new light on the role of intergalactic dense gas in galaxy formation and evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14293v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fuga Komori, Akio K. Inoue, Ken Mawatari, Yuma Sugahara, Hideki Umehata, Rhythm Shimakawa, Satoshi Yamanaka, Takuya Hashimoto, Jorryt Matthee, Toru Misawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards mapping turbulence in the intracluster medium IV. Using NewAthena/X-IFU and simulation based inference to constrain turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14378v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context. The NewAthena mission planned for launch in the mid-2030s will carry X-IFU, an integral field unit spectrometer that will enable unique insight in the X-ray hot universe through its combination of spectral and spatial capabilities. The high spectral resolution will allow a mapping of turbulent velocities of the hot gas in galaxy clusters, providing an unrivaled way to study the complex dynamics within galaxy clusters.
  Aims. This is the fourth in a series of papers aimed at forecasting the ability to investigate turbulence in the intracluster medium through the observation of the centroid shift caused by turbulent motions of the gas. In this paper we improve on previous methods by investigating the ability of simulation-based inference (SBI) to constrain the underlying nature of velocity fluctuations through the use of standard observational diagnostics, such as the structure function.
  Methods. We rely on a complex architecture of neural networks in order to model the likelihood and posterior distributions relevant to our case. We investigate its capability to retrieve the turbulence parameters on mock observations, and explore its capability to use alternative summary statistics.
  Conclusions. Our trained models are able to infer the parameters of the intracluster gas velocity power-spectrum in independently simulated X-IFU observations of a galaxy cluster. We evaluated the precision of the recovery for different models. We show the necessity to use methods such as SBI to avoid an under-estimation of the sources of variance by comparing the results to our previous paper. We confirm that sample variance severely impacts the precision of recovered turbulent features. Our results demonstrate the need for advanced modeling methods to tackle the complexity of the physical information nested within future observations expected from X-IFU/NewAthena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14378v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexe\"i Molin, Simon Dupourqu\'e, Nicolas Clerc, \'Etienne Pointecouteau, Fran\c{c}ois Pajot, Edoardo Cucchetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Wavelet Scattering Transform-Based Statistic for Cosmological Analysis of Large-Scale Structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14400v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we propose a novel method based on the wavelet scattering transform (WST) to distinguish large-scale structures of the universe across different cosmological models while mitigating tracer bias. By introducing a tailored data preprocessing strategy--particularly a high-density apodization technique--and defining a new statistical measure, the WST $m$-mode ratios, we assess performance using \texttt{CosmicGrowth} N-body simulations across three datasets: WMAP, mWMAP, and Planck. We find that only the WST ratio $R^{\rm wst}$ within the scale range $j \in [3,7]$ achieves a reduced chi-square for cosmological parameters $\chi^2_{\nu, \rm cos} \gg 1$ while maintaining $\chi^2_{\nu, \rm bias} \sim 1$ for tracer bias--a regime unattained by any other statistic. These results highlight $R^{\rm wst}$ as a promising tool for future galaxy surveys, offering strong cosmological sensitivity with effective bias mitigation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14400v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhujun Jiang, Xiaolin Luo, Wenying Du, Zhiwei Min, Fenfen Yin, Longlong Feng, Jiacheng Ding, Le Zhang, Xiao-Dong Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimizing Contaminant Leakage in Internal Linear Combination Maps Using a Data-Driven Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14644</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14644v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The thermal Sunyaev-Zel'dovich (tSZ) effect, the inverse-Compton scattering of cosmic microwave background (CMB) photons off high-energy electrons, is a powerful probe of hot, ionized gas in the Universe. It is often measured via cross-correlations of CMB data with large-scale structure (LSS) tracers to constrain gas physics and improve cosmological constraints. The largest source of bias to these measurements is the leakage of poorly understood thermal dust emission from star-forming galaxies -- the cosmic infrared background (CIB) -- into the tSZ maps. This CIB contamination is difficult to clean via multifrequency component separation methods, such as internal linear combination (ILC), due to uncertainty in its spectral energy distribution (SED), which exhibits spatial and line-of-sight variation and decorrelation. Thus, improved ILC-based techniques have been developed to null ("deproject") both the CIB and its first moment with respect to the emissivity index $\beta$ in order to robustly remove the CIB despite the lack of first-principles knowledge of its SED. While decreasing the bias, such procedures can significantly increase the noise in the resulting ILC maps. In this paper, we develop a data-driven algorithm for determining the optimal CIB SED to deproject when measuring a tSZ-LSS cross-correlation, obviating the need to deproject the first moment in the ILC map used for such a measurement. Our method gives an unbiased cross-correlation with increased signal-to-noise. We demonstrate its efficacy on simulations, finding a 60% improvement in the signal-to-noise ratio for an example tSZ cross-correlation with a halo sample at redshifts $0.8 &lt; z &lt; 1.8$, as compared to moment deprojection approaches. Though used here for CIB removal in tSZ cross-correlations, our method is broadly applicable to minimizing contaminant leakage in ILC maps. Our code is available in CIB-deproj.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14644v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kristen M. Surrao, Shivam Pandey, J. Colin Hill, Eric J. Baxter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The High-redshift Blazar MG3 J163554+3629: Physical Properties and the Enigma of Its Unexpected Supermassive Black Hole Growth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13593v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: There is general consensus that active galactic nuclei (AGNs) derive their radiating power from a supermassive black hole (SMBH) that accretes matter. Yet, their precise powering mechanisms and the resulting growth of the SMBH are poorly understood, especially for AGNs at high redshift. Blazars are AGNs pointing their jet toward the observer, thus being detectable from radio through gamma rays at high redshift due to Doppler boosting. The blazar MG3 J163554+3629 is located at redshift z=3.65 and it is a flat spectrum radio quasar (FSRQ). In this work, we show the results of the modeling of its spectral energy distribution (SED) from radio to gamma rays with a one-zone leptonic model. We estimate the uncertainties through a Markov Chain Monte Carlo approach. As a result, we infer the black hole mass M_BH = 1.1(+0.2,-0.1) x 10^9 Msun and a modest magnetic field of B = 6.56(+0.13,-0.09) x 10^-2 G in line with the Compton dominance observed in high-redshift FSRQs. The emitting region is outside the broad line region but within the region of the dust torus radius. The rather small accretion efficiency of eta=0.083 is not solely inferred through the SED modeling but also through the energetics. An evolution study suggests that in an Eddington-limited accretion process the SMBH did not have time enough to grow from an initial seed mass of ~10^6 Msun at z~30 into a mass of M_BH ~ 10^9 Msun at z=3.65. Faster mass growth might be obtained in a super-Eddington process throughout frequent episodes. Alternative scenarios propose that the existence of the jet itself can facilitate a more rapid growth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13593v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose Maria Sanchez Zaballa, Eugenio Bottacini, Andrea Tramacere</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing the intricacies of radio galaxies and filaments in the merging galaxy cluster Abell 2255. I. Insights from deep LOFAR-VLBI sub-arcsecond resolution images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13595</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13595v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: High sensitivity of modern interferometers is revealing a plethora of filaments surrounding radio galaxies, especially in galaxy cluster environments. The morphology and spectral characteristics of these thin structures require the combination of high-resolution and low frequency observations, which is best obtained using the LOw Frequency ARray (LOFAR) international stations. In this paper, we aim to detect and characterize non-thermal filaments observed close or as part of the radio galaxies in Abell 2255 using deep, LOFAR-VLBI observations at 144 MHz. These structures can be used to disentangle possible scenarios for the origin of the non-thermal filaments and connection to the motion of the host galaxy within the dense and turbulent intracluster medium (ICM), and consequent interaction between the ICM and radio jets. Combining multiple observations, we produced the deepest images ever obtained with LOFAR-VLBI targeting a galaxy cluster, using 56 hours of observations, reaching $0.3-0.5"$ resolution. We detailed throughout the paper the calibration and imaging strategy for the different targets, as well as the multitude of morphological features discovered. Thanks to the high-sensitivity of LOFAR-VLBI, we revealed unprecedented details for the main cluster radio galaxies, recovering in most cases also their more extended structure observed only at such low frequencies. In particular, we focused on the Original Tailed Radio Galaxy (Original TRG) where we distinguished many filaments constituting its tail with varying lengths ($80-110$ kpc) and widths ($3-10$ kpc). The final radio images showcase the potential of deep, high-resolution observations for galaxy clusters. With such approach, we enabled the study of these thin, elongated radio filaments: after being discovered, these filaments now require spectral studies to determine their formation mechanisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13595v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. De Rubeis, M. Bondi, A. Botteon, R. J. van Weeren, J. M. G. H. J. de Jong, L. Rudnick, G. Brunetti, K. Rajpurohit, C. Gheller, H. J. A. R\"ottgering</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Viability of post-inflationary freeze-in with precision cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13624</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13624v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Prediction of inflationary observables from the temperature fluctuation of Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) can play a pivotal role in predicting the reheating dynamics in the early universe. In this work, we highlight how the inflationary observables, in particular the spectral index $n_s$, can play a potential role in constraining the post-inflationary dark matter (DM) production. We demonstrate a novel way of constraining the non-thermal production of DM via UV freeze-in which is otherwise elusive in terrestrial experiments. We consider a scenario in which DM is produced from this thermal plasma via a dimension-five operator. The mutual connection between $n_s$ and relic density of DM via the reheating temperature, $T_{\rm RH}$, enables us to put constraints on the DM parameter space. For the minimal choice of the inflationary model parameters and DM mass between $1\,\rm MeV$ to $1\,\rm TeV$, we found that Planck alone can exclude the cut-off scale of the dimension-five operator $\Lambda \lesssim 10^{12}\,\rm GeV$ which is significantly stronger than any other existing constraints on such minimal scenario. If we impose the combined prediction form Planck and recently released data by ACT, the exclusion limit can reach up to the Planck scale for TeV-scale dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13624v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anirban Biswas, Sougata Ganguly, Dibyendu Nanda, Sujit Kumar Sahoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can local White Dwarfs constrain Dark Matter interactions?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13629v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate whether nearby white dwarfs (WDs) can constrain dark matter (DM) interactions with ordinary matter. As experimental sensitivity improves, driven by the Gaia mission, the sample volume of nearby WDs has been increasing over recent years. We carefully select a sample of ten cold, isolated, non-magnetic WDs within 13~pc of the Sun. We model their carbon-oxygen interior using a finite temperature relativistic equation of state and model atmospheres to infer their core temperatures. This enables us to perform a thorough estimation of the DM capture rate and evaporation mass using actual astrophysical observations. Given the low local DM density, we focus on DM that annihilates into long-lived mediators, which escape the WD and later decay into photons. While \textit{Fermi}-LAT data shows no significant gamma-ray excess, future telescopes, CTA North \&amp; South, LHAASO, SWGO, could probe DM-nucleon cross sections down to $\sim 10^{-41}~\text{cm}^2$ for DM masses above the TeV scale. Our results are competitive with current direct detection bounds (e.g., LZ) in the multi-TeV regime. This work underscores the importance of systematic WD studies in the broader landscape of DM detection and demonstrates the synergy between astrophysical and terrestrial searches in exploring DM interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13629v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pooja Bhattacharjee, Sandra Robles, Stephan A. Meighen-Berger, Francesca Calore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Present Status of Inflationary Cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13646</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13646v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We give a brief review of the basic principles of inflationary theory and discuss the present status of the simplest inflationary models that can describe Planck/BICEP/Keck observational data by choice of a single model parameter. In particular, we discuss the Starobinsky model, Higgs inflation, and $\alpha$-attractors, including the recently developed $\alpha$-attractor models with $SL(2,\mathbb{Z})$ invariant potentials. We also describe inflationary models providing a good fit to the recent ACT data, as well as the polynomial chaotic inflation models with three parameters, which can account for any values of the three main CMB-related inflationary parameters $A_{s}$, $n_{s}$ and $r$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13646v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renata Kallosh, Andrei Linde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling Electron Density Profile in Nearby Galaxies using SDSS MaNGA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13677v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Most observational studies of galactic-scale magnetic fields using Faraday rotation rely on estimates of thermal electron densities in galaxies and their radial variations. However, the spatial distribution of electrons in the interstellar medium (ISM) is not clearly known. In this study, we propose and utilize collision-excited doublet emission line ratios of [S\,\textsc{ii}] $\lambda\lambda$ 6716, 6731 \AA~and [O\,\textsc{ii}] $\lambda\lambda$ 3726, 3729 \AA \ to estimate the electron densities ($n_e$). To map their distribution in the galaxies, we employ Integral Field Unit (IFU) spectroscopic observations from the SDSS Mapping Nearby Galaxies at Apache Point Observatory (MaNGA) survey, utilising data products from both the \texttt{Pipe3D} and MaNGA Data Analysis Pipeline (DAP). We present a spatially resolved analysis of $13$ face-on galaxies (inclination, $i \leq 10^\circ$), including $9$ star-forming galaxies (SFGs) and $4$ Non-SFGs. Azimuthally averaged radial profiles of $n_e$ are obtained using two different binning schemes: linear and non-linear. For the \texttt{Pipe3D} case, both SFGs and non-SFGs exhibit $n_e$ gradients, with higher densities of $n_e$(S\,\textsc{ii}) = $165.6 \pm 20.8$ cm$^{-3}$ in the inner disk region (r/R$_e$ $\leq$ 1.5), which decrease to $31 \pm 4.5$ cm$^{-3}$ in the outer disk region (r/R$_e$ $&gt;$ 1.5). We also translate $n_e$ to the electron column density $N_e$ assuming an evenly distributed thin disk profile, fairly excluding the central bulge regions. These electron density estimates at different radii provide valuable insights for resolving ambiguities in current and future studies of magnetic fields in galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13677v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shivam Burman, Sunil Malik, Suprit Singh, Yogesh Wadadekar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Systems and Superstring Phases in the Early Universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14187</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14187v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the string theory dynamics of the volume scalar rolling down an exponential potential during the period between inflation and reheating, in a background of cosmic superstring loops. In the context of the LVS potential, we demonstrate the existence of a novel string loop attractor tracker solution, in which 75% of the energy density of the universe is in the form of a gas of fundamental cosmic superstring loops (a configuration preferred over the standard radiation tracker). On this tracker, it is the continual reduction in the string tension as the volume scalar evolves that makes the loops stable against decay. For more general non-LVS potentials, mixed radiation-loop trackers can also occur.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14187v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noelia S\'anchez Gonz\'alez, Joseph P. Conlon, Edmund J. Copeland, Edward Hardy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bispectrum from five-dimensional inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14225v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It was proposed that five-dimensional (5D) inflation can blow up the size of a compact dimension from the 5D Planck length to the micron size, as required by the dark dimension proposal, relating the weakness of the actual gravitational force to the size of the observable universe. Moreover, it was shown that 5D inflation can generate the (approximate) flat power spectrum of primordial density fluctuations consistent with present observations. Here we compute the bispectrum of primordial scalar perturbations and show that unlike the power spectrum, it differs from the four-dimensional case at all angular distances, due to the fact that in contrast to global dilatations, invariance under special conformal transformations is not restored at late times. Moreover there is an additional enhancement in the squeezed limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14225v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ignatios Antoniadis, Auttakit Chatrabhuti, Jules Cunat, Hiroshi Isono</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase Transitions in Dimensional Reduction up to Three Loops</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14335v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We perform the first computation of phase-transition parameters to cubic order in $\lambda\sim m^2/T^2$, where $m$ is the scalar mass and $T$ is the temperature, in a simple model resembling the Higgs sector of the SMEFT. We use dimensional reduction, including 1-loop matching corrections for terms of dimension 6 (in 4-dimensional units), 2-loop contributions for dimension-4 ones and 3-loops for the squared mass. We precisely quantify the size of the different corrections, including renormalisation-group running as well as quantum effects from light fields in the effective theory provided by the Coleman-Weinberg potential, and discuss briefly the implications for gravitational waves. Our results suggest that, for strong phase transitions, 1-loop corrections from dimension-6 operators can compete with 2-loop ones from quartic couplings, but largely surpass those from 3-loop thermal masses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14335v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikael Chala, Luis Gil, Zhe Ren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep learning-driven likelihood-free parameter inference for 21-cm forest observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14298v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The hyperfine structure absorption lines of neutral hydrogen in spectra of high-redshift radio sources, known collectively as the 21-cm forest, have been demonstrated as a sensitive probe to the small-scale structures governed by the dark matter (DM) properties, as well as the thermal history of the intergalactic medium regulated by the first galaxies during the epoch of reionization. By statistically analyzing these spectral features, the one-dimensional (1D) power spectrum of the 21-cm forest can effectively break the parameter degeneracies and constrain the properties of both DM and the first galaxies. However, conventional parameter inference methods face challenges due to computationally expensive simulations for 21-cm forest and the non-Gaussian signal characteristics. To address these issues, we introduce generative normalizing flows for data augmentation and inference normalizing flows for parameters estimation. This approach efficiently estimates parameters from minimally simulated datasets with non-Gaussian signals. Using simulated data from the upcoming Square Kilometre Array (SKA), we demonstrate the ability of the deep learning-driven likelihood-free approach to generate accurate posterior distributions, providing a robust and efficient tool for probing DM and the cosmic heating history using the 1D power spectrum of 21-cm forest in the era of SKA. This methodology is adaptable for scientific analyses with other unevenly distributed data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14298v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tian-Yang Sun, Yue Shao, Yichao Li, Yidong Xu, He Wang, Xin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fundamental constants: from measurement to the universe, a window on gravitation and cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07281</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07281v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Fundamental constants are a cornerstone of the physical laws. Any constant varying in space and/or time would signal a violation of local position invariance and be associated with a violation of the universality of free fall, and hence of the weak equivalence principle. It will reflect the existence of new degrees of freedom that couple to standard matter. Thus, testing for the stability of fundamental constants is of utmost importance for our understanding of gravity and for characterizing the domain of validity of General Relativity. Besides, it opens an independent window on dark matter and dark energy.
  As a consequence, thanks to the active development of experiments and of their accuracy, fundamental constants have become a key player in our search for physics beyond the standard model of and beyond General Relativity.
  This review details the roles of the fundamental constants in the laws of physics and in the construction of the International System of units. Then, the relations between constants, tests of the local position invariance and of the universality of free fall are exposed, as well as the construction of field theories that account for "varying constants". Then, the main experimental and observational constraints are described. It details the basics of each system, its dependence with respect to the primary parameters the variation of which can be constrained from observations, the known systematics effects and the most recent constraints. It also describes how these primary parameters can be related to the fundamental constants and the model-dependencies. Both time and space variation are considered. Given the huge increase of data and constraints, a general scheme to present experimental and observational results and to construct a collaborative data base that will be more efficient for the community and allow for better traceability, is proposed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07281v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Philippe Uzan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Redshift tomography of the kinematic matter dipole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13162</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13162v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The dipole anisotropy induced by our peculiar motion in the sky distribution of cosmologically distant sources is an important consistency test of the standard FLRW cosmology. In this work, we formalize how to compute the kinematic matter dipole in redshift bins. Apart from the usual terms arising from angular aberration and flux boosting, there is a contribution from the boosting of the redshifts that becomes important when considering a sample selected on observed redshift, leading to non-vanishing correction terms. We discuss examples and provide expressions to incorporate arbitrary redshift selection functions. We also discuss the effect of redshift measurement uncertainties in this context, in particular in upcoming surveys for which we provide estimates of the correction terms. Depending on the shape of a sample's redshift distribution and on the applied redshift cuts, the correction terms can become substantial, even to the degree that the direction of the dipole is reversed. Lastly, we discuss how cuts on variables correlated with observed redshift, such as color, can induce additional correction terms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13162v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian von Hausegger, Charles Dalang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model-independent $H_0$ within FLRW: Joint constraints from GWTC-3 standard sirens and strong lensing time delays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10346</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10346v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We use 47 gravitational-wave (GW) standard sirens from the third Gravitational-Wave Transient Catalog to calibrate distances in the strong gravitational lensing (SGL) system RXJ1131-1231 and constrain the Hubble constant ($H_0$) via the distance sum rule, without assuming a specific cosmological model. For $\Omega_K = 0$, we obtain $H_0 = 73.22^{+5.95}_{-5.43}$ ${\rm km}~{\rm s}^{-1}~{\rm Mpc}^{-1}$ and $H_0 = 70.40^{+8.03}_{-5.60}$ ${\rm km}~{\rm s}^{-1}~{\rm Mpc}^{-1}$ by breaking the mass-sheet transform using lens galaxy's mass models and stellar kinematics, respectively. Allowing $\Omega_K$ to vary increases the central value of $H_0$ and reduces its precision. We find that GW dark sirens have significant potential for calibrating SGL systems, due to their relatively higher redshifts. By combining 42 binary black holes and RXJ1131-1231, we obtain an $H_0$ constraint with a precision approximately $40\%$ better than the measurement from GW170817 using the Hubble law. This suggests that high-precision, model-independent $H_0$ measurements can be achieved with this method as the redshift range of GW dark sirens expands, even without the need for GW bright sirens.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10346v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ji-Yu Song, Jing-Zhao Qi, Jing-Fei Zhang, Xin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Parameter Dependence of $\mathbf{n_{s}}$ and $\mathbf{r}$ of the Scalar Power Spectrum during Single-Field Slow-Roll Inflation: A Comparative Study of Inflationary Potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11209v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Inflation in cosmology is a specific stage preceding the Big Bang, aimed at solving both old background problems and new perturbation issues. Single-field inflation is a candidate to illustrate the picture of the initial universe, and various potential functions lead to different scenarios during the inflationary stage. This paper introduces two essential parameters: the spectral index and the tensor-to-scalar ratio detected from the initial power spectrum, derived from the action of the scalar field and using approximation that the potential is flat. A brief overview of the origins of Starobinsky Inflation, Chaotic Inflation, Small Field Inflation, and Natural Inflation is also presented, along with their mathematical representations. Finally, the results derived from various inflation models regarding the index and ratio are tested using the Planck data, and the deviations in each model are analyzed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11209v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guanqiao Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confronting the low-scale seesaw and leptogenesis with neutrinoless double beta decay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10560v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We revisit the impact of heavy neutrinos with masses in the MeV-GeV range on neutrinoless double beta decay ($0\nu\beta\beta$) in view of updated results for the lifetime of this process. Working in a minimal realistic extension of the Standard Model by two right-handed neutrino flavours, we show that the non-observation of $0\nu\beta\beta$ will impose strong bounds on the heavy neutrino properties that are complementary to the limits obtained from Big Bang Nucleosynthesis and collider searches. For an inverted mass hierarchy of the light neutrinos we find that improved limits on $0\nu\beta\beta$ from next-generation experiments, assuming an improvement of two orders of magnitude on the current $0\nu\beta\beta$ limits will restrict the allowed parameter space for fixed mass splitting to narrow bands in the mass-mixing plane. Further combining this with the requirement to explain the baryon asymmetry of the universe via leptogenesis reduces these bands to windows in parameter space that are constrained in all directions and can be targeted by direct searches at accelerators, and restricts the mass splitting to values that can be resolved at experiments. For a normal mass hierarchy, restricting the allowed parameter will require even stronger $0\nu\beta\beta$ limits, and only parts of the parameter space can then be probed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10560v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP05(2025)090</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 05 (2025) 090</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>J. de Vries, M. Drewes, Y. Georis, J. Klari\'c, V. Plakkot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thin-wall vacuum decay in the presence of a compact dimension meets the $H_0$ and $S_8$ tensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18649</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18649v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The proposal of a rapid sign-switching cosmological constant in the late universe, mirroring a transition from anti-de Sitter (AdS) to de Sitter (dS) space, has significantly improved the fit to observational data and provides a compelling framework for ameliorating major cosmological tensions, such as the $H_0$ and $S_8$ tensions. An attractive theoretical realisation that accommodates the AdS $\to$ dS transition relies on the Casimir forces of fields inhabiting the bulk of a 5-dimensional (5-dim) set up. Among the fields characterising the dark sector, there is a real scalar field $\phi$ endowed with a potential holding two local minima with very small difference in vacuum energy and bigger curvature (mass) of the lower one. Shortly after the false vacuum tunnels to its true vacuum state, $\phi$ becomes more massive and its contribution to the Casimir energy becomes exponentially suppressed. The tunneling process then changes the difference between the total number of fermionic and bosonic degrees of freedom contributing to the quantum corrections of the vacuum energy, yielding the AdS $\to$ dS transition. We investigate the properties of this theoretical realisation to validate its main hypothesis and characterise free parameters of the model. We adopt the Coleman-de Luccia formalism for calculating the transition probability within the thin-wall approximation. We show that the Euclidean bounce configuration that drives the transition between $\phi$ vacua has associated at least a sixth order potential. We also show that distinctive features of the required vacuum decay to accommodate the AdS $\to$ dS transition are inconsistent with a 5-dim non-compact description of the instanton, for which the bounce is $O(5)$ symmetric, and instead call for a 5-dim instanton with a compact dimension, for which the bounce is $O(4)\times U(1)$ symmetric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18649v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luis A. Anchordoqui, Ignatios Antoniadis, Daniele Bielli, Auttakit Chatrabhuti, Hiroshi Isono</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pz Cats: Photometric redshift catalogs based on DES Y3 BAO sample</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04118v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Over the years, photometric redshift estimation (photo-z) has advanced through various methods. This study evaluates four distinct photo-z estimators-ANNz2, BPZ, ENF, and DNF-using the Dark Energy Survey Y3 BAO Sample. Unlike most studies, we explore selecting optimal galaxies based on their redshift Probability Distribution Function (PDF) by either reducing noise or identifying those approximating a Gaussian distribution. We cross-matched 25,760 galaxies drawn from four spectroscopic surveys with the photo-z sample to comprehend redshift bias and its 68th percentile $\sigma_{68}$. The lowest $\sigma$ for all estimators was found in the range $0.79&lt;z_p&lt;0.85$. Among the estimators, DMF exhibited the greatest bias, while ENF, ANNz2, and BPZ showed decreased precision outside 0.7 to 0.9 redshift range. To select galaxies with minimal bias, ANNz2 emerged as the most reliable algorithm across all criteria. PDFs selection significantly improves colour representation over the spectroscopic sample, underscoring the role of magnitude space in selection. While ANNz2 achieved superior precision, ENF poorly selected Gaussian PDFs, leaving few galaxies for LSS evaluation. Despite smooth PDFs, catastrophic redshift errors were present. Though DNF had the poorest precision, it offered enough galaxies for cosmological use. Subsampling galaxies with secondary peaks less than 30\% of the main peak height, termed Small Peaks, showed ANNz2 excelled. The catalogs produced have been published as Pz Cats within the ZENODO repository.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04118v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paula S. Ferreira, Ribamar R. R. Reis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Late-time cosmic acceleration from quantum gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12419</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12419v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We deepen the analysis of the cosmological acceleration produced by quantum gravity dynamics in the formalism of group field theory condensate cosmology, treated at the coarse-grained level via a phenomenological model, in the language of hydrodynamics on minisuperspace. Specifically, we conduct a detailed analysis of the late-time evolution, which shows a phantom-like phase followed by an asymptotic De Sitter expansion. We argue that the model indicates a recent occurrence of the phantom crossing and we extract a more precise expression for the effective cosmological constant, linking its value to other parameters in the model and to the scale of the quantum bounce in the early universe evolution. Additionally, we show how the phantom phase produced by our quantum gravity dynamics increases the inferred value of the current Hubble parameter based on observed data, indicating a possible quantum gravity mechanism for alleviating the Hubble tension. Our results represent a concrete example of how quantum gravity can provide an explanation for large-scale cosmological puzzles, in an emergent spacetime scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12419v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniele Oriti, Xiankai Pang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bispectrum at NLO in single field inflation: conservation and squeezed limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18187</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18187v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In a recent paper, we computed the bispectrum of primordial density perturbations in CMB to second order in the slow-roll parameters of single field inflation, and found logarithmic infrared contributions that diverge in both large physical distances and squeezed limit where one momentum vanishes. In this work, we provide an independent test of the result by checking its conservation and the validity of the consistency relation between the squeezed limit of the bispectrum and the square of the power spectrum. Despite the violation of the main assumption for its general proofs which is the finiteness of the relevant observables in these limits, we find that the identity continues to hold in the vicinity of the squeezed limit and large time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18187v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ignatios Antoniadis, Auttakit Chatrabhuti, Jules Cunat, Hiroshi Isono</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection for Intermediate-mass Binary Black Holes in Population III Star Clusters with TianQin</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15907v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Context. Population III star clusters are predicted to form in unenriched dark matter halos. Direct N-body simulation of Pop III clusters implies the possible formation and merger of intermediate-mass binary black holes (IMBBHs). The gravitational wave signals could be detected by space-borne gravitational wave detectors like TianQin. Aims. This study evaluates the potential of TianQin in detecting IMBBHs from Pop III star clusters, focusing on key factors such as the detection horizon, detection number, and Fisher uncertainty. Methods. A Monte Carlo simulation is employed to derive IMBBH sources, utilizing the IMRPhenomD waveform model to simulate catalogs of observable IMBBH mergers. The mass and redshift distributions are derived from direct N-body simulations of IMBBHs in Population III star clusters. Detection numbers are determined by calculating the signal-to-noise ratios (SNR) of the simulated signals and applying thresholds for detection. Fisher uncertainty is obtained through Fisher information matrix analysis. Results. The findings suggest that TianQin could achieve detection numbers within 5 years ranging from 1 in the most pessimistic scenario to 253 in the most optimistic scenario. Furthermore, TianQin can precisely constrain the IMBBH mass with a relative uncertainty of $10^{-6}$, coalescence time $t_c$ within 1 second, and sky location $\bar{\Omega}_S$ within 1 $\rm{deg}^2$. However, the luminosity distance $D_L$ and inclination angle $\iota$ exhibit substantial degeneracies, limiting their precise estimation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15907v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202453615</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A 697, A49 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hanzhang Wang, Shuai Liu, Han Wang, Hongyu Chen, Long Wang, Yiming Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
