<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO</link>
    <description>astro-ph.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 05:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial gravitational waves in DHOST inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13210v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider DHOST inflationary models with a shift symmetry leading to a de Sitter space-time at the background cosmological level. Deviations from scale invariance of the scalar and tensor perturbations follow from the breaking of the shift symmetry by quadratic and quartic operators. These models show a strong violation of the consistency relation of single-field inflationary models with a very flat spectrum of tensor perturbations. This opens up the prospects of future detection of primordial gravitational waves by mHz experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13210v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philippe Brax, Andrei Lazanu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Fast and Accurate Implementation of the Effective Fluid Approximation for Ultralight Axions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13662</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13662v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a numerically efficient and accurate implementation of the Passaglia-Hu effective fluid approximation for ultralight axions (ULAs) within the Boltzmann code CAMB. This method is specifically designed to evolve the axion field accurately across cosmological timescales, mitigating the challenges associated with its rapid oscillations. Our implementation is based on the latest version of CAMB, ensuring compatibility with other cosmological codes., e.g. for calculating cosmological parameter constraints. Compared to exact solutions of the Klein-Gordon equation, our method achieves sub-percent accuracy in the CMB power spectrum across a broad range of axion masses, from $10^{-28}\,\mathrm{eV}$ to $10^{-24}\,\mathrm{eV}$. We perform Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) analyses incorporating our implementation, and find improved constraints on the axion mass and abundance compared to previous, simpler fluid-based approximations. For example, using \Planck\ PR4 and DESI BAO data, we find $2\sigma$ upper limits on the axion fraction $f_{\rm ax} &lt; 0.0082$ and physical density $\Omega_{\rm ax}h^2 &lt; 0.0010$ for $m=10^{-28}$ eV. The code is publicly available at \url{https://github.com/adammoss/AxiCAMB}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13662v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam Moss, Lauren Gaughan, Anne M. Green</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Gauge Invariance of Secondary Gravitational Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13691v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Second-order tensor perturbations induced by primordial fluctuations play a crucial role in probing small-scale physics, but gauge dependence of their energy density has remained a fundamental challenge in cosmological perturbation theory. We address this issue by introducing a boundary condition-based filtering method that extracts physical radiation through the Sommerfeld criterion. We demonstrate that after filtering non-physical modes, the energy density of secondary gravitational waves becomes gauge-invariant and exhibits physically consistent behavior in the sub-horizon limit. This approach provides a unified framework for both adiabatic and isocurvature perturbations, enhancing theoretical predictions and observational signatures of early universe physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13691v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Yuan, Yizhou Lu, Zu-Cheng Chen, Lang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can $\nu$DM interactions solve the $S_8$ discrepancy?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13785v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present compelling evidence that Dark Matter (DM)-neutrino interactions can resolve the persistent structure growth parameter discrepancy, $S_8 = \sigma_8\,\sqrt{\Omega_m/0.3}$, between early and late universe observations. By incorporating cosmic shear measurements from current Weak Lensing (WL) surveys and leveraging an emulator based on true $N$-body simulations to account for nonlinear corrections, we demonstrate that an interaction strength of $u \sim 10^{-4}$ not only provides a coherent explanation for the high-multipole observations from the Atacama Cosmology Telescope (ACT), but also alleviates the $S_8$ discrepancy. Combining early universe constraints with DES Y3 cosmic shear data yields a nearly $3\sigma$ detection of non-zero DM-neutrino interactions, marking a significant breakthrough in cosmological research. Our findings challenge the standard $\Lambda$CDM paradigm and highlight the potential of future large-scale structure surveys, which can rigorously test this interaction and unveil the fundamental properties of dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13785v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Zu, William Giar\`e, Chi Zhang, Eleonora Di Valentino, Yue-Lin Sming Tsai, Sebastian Trojanowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Free-Streaming Neutrinos and Their Phase Shift in Current and Future CMB Power Spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13788v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The cosmic neutrino background and other light relics leave distinct imprints in the cosmic microwave background anisotropies through their gravitational influence. Since neutrinos decoupled from the primordial plasma about one second after the big bang, they have been free-streaming through the universe. This induced a characteristic phase shift in the acoustic peaks as a unique signature. In this work, we constrain the free-streaming nature of these relativistic species and other light relics beyond the Standard Model of particle physics by establishing two complementary template-based approaches to robustly infer the size of this phase shift from the temperature and polarization power spectra. One template shifts the multipoles in these spectra, while the other novel template more fundamentally isolates the phase shift at the level of the underlying photon-baryon perturbations. Applying these methods to Planck data, we detect the neutrino-induced phase shift at about $10\sigma$ significance, which rises to roughly $14\sigma$ with additional data from the Atacama Cosmology Telescope and the South Pole Telescope. We also infer that the data is consistent with the Standard Model prediction of three free-streaming neutrinos. In addition, we forecast the capabilities of future experiments which will enable significantly more precise phase-shift measurements, with the Simons Observatory and CMB-S4 reducing the $1\sigma$ uncertainties to roughly 4.3% and 2.5%, respectively. More generally, we establish a new analysis pipeline for the phase shift induced by neutrinos and other free-streaming dark radiation which additionally offers new avenues for exploring physics beyond the Standard Model in a signature-driven and model-agnostic way.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13788v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriele Montefalcone, Benjamin Wallisch, Katherine Freese</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inflaton Self Resonance, Oscillons, and Gravitational Waves in Small Field Polynomial Inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13811</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13811v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate the post-inflationary dynamics of a simple single-field model with a renormalizable inflaton potential featuring a near-inflection point at a field value $\phi_0$. Due to the concave shape of the scalar potential, the effective mass of the inflaton becomes imaginary during as well as for some period after slow-roll inflation. As a result, in the initial reheating phase, where the inflaton oscillates around its minimum with a large amplitude, some field fluctuations grow exponentially; this effect becomes stronger at smaller $\phi_0$. This aspect can be analyzed using the Floquet theorem. We also analytically estimate the backreaction time after which the perturbations affect the evolution of the average inflaton field. In order to fully analyze this non-perturbative regime, we perform a (classical) lattice simulation, which reveals that the exponential growth of field fluctuations can fragment the system. This leads to a large amount of non-Gaussianity at very small scales, but the equation of state remains close to matter-like. The evolution of the background field throughout the fragmentation phase can be understood using the Hartree approximation. For sufficiently small $\phi_0$ soliton-like objects, called oscillons in the literature, are formed. This leads to areas with high local over-density, $\delta \rho \gg \bar\rho$ where $\bar\rho$ is the average energy density. We speculate that this could lead to the formation of light primordial black holes, with lifetime $\gtrsim 10^{-19} \text{sec}$. Other possibly observational consequences, in particular gravitational waves in the $\text{MHz} - \text{GHz}$ range, are discussed as well. Although a complete analytical study is difficult in our case, we obtain a power law scaling for the potential observables on $\phi_0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13811v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuel Drees, Chenhuan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Cosmic Microwave Background -- Secondary Anisotropies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13913</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13913v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The cosmic microwave background (CMB), the relic radiation from the early Universe, offers a unique window into both primordial conditions and the intervening large-scale structure (LSS) it traverses. Interactions between CMB photons and the evolving Universe imprint secondary anisotropies -- modifications to the CMB's intensity and polarization caused by gravitational effects and scattering processes. These anisotropies serve as a powerful probe of fundamental physics while also revealing astrophysical processes governing the thermodynamics and distribution of baryonic matter. In this chapter, we provide a comprehensive review of the physical mechanisms underlying secondary anisotropies, their observational status, and their potential to advance precision cosmology. With the increasing sensitivity of CMB experiments and synergy with LSS surveys, secondary anisotropies are poised to unveil unprecedented insights into the Universe's composition, evolution, and dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13913v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico Bianchini, Abhishek S. Maniyar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinematics of the Sagittarius Dwarf Spheroidal core: A 5D Analysis for a 6D Methodology with Gaia DR3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11138</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11138v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Using Gaia DR3 data, we examine the kinematics of the central core of the Sagittarius (Sgr) dwarf spheroidal galaxy using data which includes proper motions and line-of-sight velocities for member stars in addition to their projected positions. We extract a sample of bright stars that are high-probability members of Sgr. We model the distances to these stars, which is the only missing phase-space component measurement from our 5D sample, highlighting how their corresponding uncertainties propagate to affect the kinematics. Using line-of-sight velocity data only, which are not affected by the distance uncertainties, and assuming a jeans-based equilibrium analysis, we obtain a velocity anisotropy of $\beta_a = -2.24 \pm 1.99$, which implies a system with tangentially-biased orbits. With the full 5D data, we project that the data will significantly improve upon measurements of the log-slope of the dark matter density profile and the stellar velocity anisotropy. Tests with mock distance data show an improvement of anisotropy errors of approximately an order of magnitude, and log slope at the half light radius of approximately half an order of magnitude.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11138v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Isabelle S. Goldstein, Louis E. Strigari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of the cosmological evolution parameters, energy conditions, and linear matter perturbations of an exponential-type model in $f(Q)$ gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12585</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12585v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study cosmological evolution in a flat FLRW spacetime in the context of modified STEGR gravity or $f(Q)$, using an exponential two-parameter model which represents a smooth perturbative expansion around the $\Lambda$CDM model. The cosmological analysis is carried out by calculating the Hubble parameter as a function of redshift, for selected values of the parameters. The Hubble parameter is obtained analytically by means of several approximations good enough to deviate slightly from the $\Lambda$CDM case. Several late-time cosmological parameters are computed, such as: dark energy state parameter, deceleration parameter, statefinder parameters. Additionally, we analyzed the behavior of the classical energy conditions WEC, SEC, NEC, and DEC for both the combination of matter and geometrical contribution and the geometrical contribution alone. Beyond the background level, linear matter perturbations are studied by calculating parameters relevant to structure growth and formation. The overall results indicate that the model may exhibit quintessence-like and phantom-like behavior and it impacts the growth of structures in the universe by means late-time deviations from the $\Lambda$CDM model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12585v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ivan R. Vasquez, A. Oliveros</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Galaxy infall models for arbitrary velocity directions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13149v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For most galaxies in the cosmos, our knowledge of their motion is limited to line-of-sight velocities from redshift observations. Peculiar motions on the sky are only measured for a few cases. With increasingly detailed observations, the assumption that line-of-sight velocities suffice for an accurate and precise reconstruction of galaxy kinematics needs to be re-investigated and the impact of perpendicular velocities to be quantified. We analyse the motion of two galaxies with arbitrary velocities, determine their mutual velocity on an arbitrary background, and compare this general relative velocity to the one from line-of-sight components only. The latter are known as ``minor and major infall models'' established by Karachentsev and Kashibadze (2006). Our derivations reveal that the infall models approximate the radial velocity between two galaxies by two different projections employing different information about the system. For galaxies with small angular separations, all infall models agree that the radial velocity is the difference of their line-of-sight velocities. For larger angles, the minor infall model is mostly suitable when perpendicular velocity components are negligible and there is no information about the tangential velocity of the binary. The major infall model is best suitable when the motion is mainly radial and symmetry assumptions cancel the tangential and one perpendicular component. The latter often requires to transition from galaxy binaries to groups or clusters, as we show quantitatively. We give an encompassing overview how the infall models over- and under-estimate general binary or $N$-body motions. We quantify the impact of perpendicular velocity components, sparse sampling, and deviations of the tracer-galaxies from the motion in an embedding gravitational potential which are related to the angular momentum of the structure. (abridged)</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13149v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jenny Wagner, David Benisty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electromagnetic leptogenesis with light-heavy sterile neutrinos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13150v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a novel leptogenesis scenario utilising the two-body decay of heavy right handed neutrino (RHN) via the electromagnetic dipole operator. While the requirement of the standard model (SM) gauge invariance requires such dipole operator only at dimension-6 forcing the generation of non-zero CP asymmetry from three-body decay with two-loop corrections, we write down dimension-5 dipole operators involving heavy RHN $N_R$ and its lighter counterpart $\nu_R$. This allows the generation of lepton asymmetry in $\nu_R$ from two-body decay of heavy RHN which later gets transferred to left handed leptons via sizeable Yukawa coupling with a neutrinophilic Higgs doublet. The asymmetry in left handed leptons is then converted to baryon asymmetry via electroweak sphalerons. The lepton number violation by heavy RHN also induces a one-loop Majorana mass of $\nu_R$ rendering the light neutrinos to be Majorana fermions. While smallness of the Majorana mass of $\nu_R$ prevents additional sources or washout of lepton asymmetry, it also constrains the scale of leptogenesis. For $\mathcal{O}(10)$ TeV scale leptogenesis, this leads to additional sterile neutrinos lighter than a few keV with interesting implications for a variety of observables including neutrino oscillation, warm dark matter as well as effective degrees of freedom within reach of future cosmic microwave background experiments. Additionally, heavy RHN can lead to observable monochromatic photon signatures at terrestrial experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13150v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debasish Borah, Arnab Dasgupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutrinophilic $\mathbf{\Lambda}$CDM Extension for EMPRESS, DESI and Hubble Tension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13153</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13153v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A number of recent cosmological observations have indicated the presence of new physics beyond the $\mathbf{\Lambda}$CDM model. Combining observations from EMPRESS on helium abundance and DESI on baryon acoustic oscillations with Hubble tension, we show that all of them can be explained concurrently with a extension of the $\mathbf{\Lambda}$CDM model with primordial neutrino asymmetry $\xi_{\nu}$ and additional contribution to the effective number of neutrinos $\delta N_{\rm eff}$. Based on the accurate treatments of neutrino decoupling and BBN processes, we present state-of-the-art constraints on neutrino asymmetry for the fixed or varying $N_{\rm eff}$. Comparing different extensions of the $\mathbf{\Lambda}$CDM model, we show that the neutrinophilic $\mathbf{\Lambda}$CDM extension with $\xi_{\nu} = 0.056 \pm 0.017 $ and $\delta N_{\rm eff} = 0.41 \pm 0.16$ is preferred by current observations, while the Hubble tension in this model is also alleviated to be $2.2 \sigma$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13153v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuan-Zhen Li, Jiang-Hao Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Measure of Assembly Bias: The Environment Dependence of the Luminosity Function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13204</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13204v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Assembly bias is the variation of clustering induced by correlations between the assembly history of dark matter halos and the large-scale environment at fixed halo mass. In this work, we use the cosmological magneto-hydrodynamical simulation TNG300 to investigate how assembly bias affects the environment-dependent galaxy luminosity function. We measure the luminosity functions in bins of large-scale environment for the original simulated galaxy sample and for a shuffled sample, where the galaxies are randomly reassigned among halos of similar mass to remove assembly bias. By comparing them, we find distinct signatures, showing variations in the number of galaxies at the $\sim10\%$ level across all luminosities. Assembly bias increases the tendency of galaxies to reside in denser environments and further dilutes underdense regions, beyond the trends governed by halo mass. When separating by color, we see that assembly bias has a much bigger effect on red galaxies fainter than $\mathrm{M_r} - 5 \log{h} = -18.5$, which accounts for a $\sim20\%$ increase in the number of galaxies in the densest environment and a remarkable $50\%$ decrease in the least dense regions. The ratio of these measurements for the densest and least dense regions provides a robust assembly bias signal for the faint red galaxies, larger than a factor of two. Overall, our results provide a novel sensitive measure of assembly bias, offering valuable insight for modeling the effect and a potential new route to detect it in observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13204v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yikun Wang (Department of Physics, Case Western Reserve University, Cleveland, USA), Idit Zehavi (Department of Physics, Case Western Reserve University, Cleveland, USA), Sergio Contreras (Donostia International Physics Center, Gipuzkoa, Spain), Shaun Cole (Institute for Computational Cosmology, Department of Physics, Durham University, Durham, UK), Peder Norberg (Institute for Computational Cosmology, Department of Physics, Durham University, Durham, UK, Centre for Extragalactic Astronomy, Department of Physics, Durham University, Durham, UK)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulations of the accreted stellar halos of low-mass field galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13317v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We predict the properties of stellar halos in galaxies of present-day virial mass $10^8 &lt; M_{200} &lt; 10^{12} {\rm M_\odot}$ by combining the GALFORM semi-analytic model of galaxy formation, the COCO cosmological N-body simulation, and the STINGS particle tagging technique. Galaxies in low mass halos have a wide range of stellar halo properties. Their diversity is much greater at fixed stellar mass than fixed virial mass. In the least massive DM halos capable of supporting galaxy formation, accreted mass fractions are &lt; 10 per cent, and the typical density profile of accreted stars is similar to that of stars formed in situ. In low mass galaxies, the radial scale lengths of accreted stellar halos are smaller than those of stellar disks formed in situ, but the accreted component is still diffuse, not bulge-like. At the scale of galaxies like M33, the surface density of accreted stars exceeds that of the in situ component at ~15kpc; the accreted surface density at this radius is $3.5\lesssim \log_{10} M_\star/{\rm M_\odot} \mathrm{kpc^{-2}} \lesssim 6$, varying systematically with virial mass. We compare our predictions to observations and other cosmological simulations. A small but significant number of $\sim 10^{12} {\rm M_\odot}$ halos with exceptionally inefficient star formation -- "failed Milky Ways" -- are more prominent in our model than others; the true abundance of this population is a potential constraint on galaxy formation physics and could be measured by low surface brightness surveys targeting field galaxies with M33-like stellar mass. The stellar particle data for our simulation is publicly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13317v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew P. Cooper (National Tsing Hua University, Taiwan), Carlos S. Frenk (Durham University), Wojciech A. Hellwing (Center for Theoretical Physics, Polish Academy of Sciences), Sownak Bose (Durham University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of inflationary models in higher-dimensional uniform inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13581v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider higher-dimensional uniform inflation, in which the extra dimensions expand at the same rate as three-dimensional non-compact space during inflation. We compute the cosmological perturbation in $D+4$ dimensions and derive the spectral index $n_s$ and the tensor-scalar ratio $r$. We analyze five inflationary models: chaotic inflation, natural inflation, quartic hilltop inflation, inflation with spontaneously broken SUSY, and $R^2$ inflation. By combining the results from these models with the Planck 2018 constraints, we discuss that it is not desirable for the extra-dimensional space to expand at the same rate as the three-dimensional non-compact space, except for the case of one extra dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13581v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takuya Hirose</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forecasted Detection Limits on the (Dark) Matter Density in Supermassive Black Hole Binaries for LISA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13601v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Supermassive black hole binaries (SMBHBs) are among the most powerful known sources of gravitational waves (GWs). Accordingly, these systems could dominate GW emission in the micro- and millihertz frequency range. Within this domain, SMBHs evolve rapidly and merge with each other. Dynamical friction from stars and gas at the centers of galaxies typically helps to bring together two SMBHs when they are at relatively far separations ($\approx$ kpc $-$ 100 pc), but becomes less efficient at smaller separations. However, dark matter (DM) spikes around SMBHs could enhance dynamical friction at close separations and, thus, shorten the evolution times. In this paper, we simulate the effects of DM spikes on GW signals in the micro- to millihertz frequency range and confirm that the GW signals from SMBHBs with DM spikes can be clearly distinguished from those without any additional matter. Making use of the projected sensitivity curve of the Laser Interferometer Space Antenna (LISA), we forecast upper limits for the (dark) matter density for given future SMBHB observations. We then compare these thresholds with the theoretical density profiles expected for self-interacting dark matter (SIDM) spikes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13601v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthias Daniel, Kris Pardo, Laura Sagunski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Study on the Line of Sight to Galaxies Detected at Gamma-ray Energies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13847</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13847v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The large-scale Universal structure comprises strands of dark matter and galaxies with large under-dense volumes known as voids. We measure the fraction of the line of sight that intersects voids for active galactic nuclei (AGN) detected by Fermi Large Area Telescope (LAT) and quasars from the Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS). This ``voidiness'' fraction is a rudimentary proxy for the density along the line of sight to the galaxies. The voidiness of SDSS-observed quasars (QSOs) is distinctly different from randomly distributed source populations, with a median p-value of $4.6\times10^{-5}$ and $\ll 1\times10^{-7}$, when compared with 500 simulated populations with randomly simulated locations but matching redshifts in the $0.1\leq z&lt;0.4$ and $0.4\leq z &lt; 0.7$ intervals, respectively. A similar comparison of the voidiness for LAT-detected AGN shows median p-values greater than 0.05 in each redshift interval. When comparing the SDSS QSO population to the LAT-detected AGN, we mitigate potential bias from a relationship between redshift and voidiness by comparing the LAT-detected AGN to a ``redshift-matched'' set of SDSS QSOs. The LAT-detected AGN between a redshift of 0.4 and 0.7 show higher voidiness compared to the redshift-matched SDSS QSO populations, with a median p-value of 2.3$\times10^{-5}$, (a $4.1\sigma$ deviation). No deviation is found when comparing the same populations between redshifts of 0.1 and 0.4 (p&gt;0.05). We do not study possible causes of this voidiness difference. It might relate to propagation effects from lower magnetic or radiative background fields within voids or to an environment more favorable for gamma-ray production for AGN near voids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13847v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amy Furniss, Josepf N. Amador, Olivier Hervet, Ollie Jackson, David A. Williams</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Various Dark Matter Halo Profiles in Milky Way and Andromeda Galaxies within the Framework of Standard Cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13861</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13861v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the rotation curves of the Milky Way galaxy (MW) and Andromeda galaxy (M31) by considering its bulge, disk, and halo components. We model the bulge region by the widely accepted de Vaucouleur's law and the disk region by the well established exponential profile. In order to understand the distribution of dark matter in the halo region, we consider three different dark matter profiles in the framework of the standard $\Lambda$CDM model namely, Navarro-Frenk-White (NFW), Hernquist and Einasto profiles. We use recent datasets of rotation curves of the Milky Way and Andromeda galaxy. The data consist of rotation velocities of the stars and gas in the galaxy as a function of the radial distance from the center. Using Bayesian statistics, we perform an overall fit including all the components, i.e., bulge, disk and halo with the data. Our results indicate that the NFW and Hernquist profiles are in concordance with the observational data points. However, the Einasto profile poorly explains the behaviour of dark matter in both the galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13861v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Darshan Kumar (HNAS), Nisha Rani (DU), Deepak Jain (DU), Shobhit Mahajan (DU), Amitabha Mukherjee (DU)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magrathea-Pathfinder: A 3D adaptive-mesh code for geodesic ray tracing in $N$-body simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.08744</link>
      <description>arXiv:2111.08744v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce Magrathea-Pathfinder, a relativistic ray-tracing framework that can reconstruct the past light cone of observers in cosmological simulations. The code directly computes the 3D trajectory of light rays through the null geodesic equations, with the weak-field limit as its only approximation. This approach offers high levels of versatility while removing the need for many of the standard ray-tracing approximations such as plane-parallel, Born, or multiple-lens. Moreover, the use of adaptive integration steps and interpolation strategies based on adaptive-mesh refinement (AMR) grids allows Magrathea-Pathfinder to accurately account for the non-linear regime of structure formation and fully take advantage of the small-scale gravitational clustering. To handle very large N-body simulations, the framework has been designed as a high-performance computing post-processing tool relying on a hybrid parallelization that combines MPI tasks with C++11 std::threads. In this paper, we describe how realistic cosmological observables can be computed from numerical simulation using ray-tracing techniques. We discuss in particular the production of simulated catalogues and sky maps that account for all the observational effects considering first-order metric perturbations (such as peculiar velocities, gravitational potential, integrated Sachs-Wolfe, time-delay, and gravitational lensing). We perform convergence tests of our gravitational lensing algorithms and conduct performance benchmarks of the null geodesic integration procedures. Magrathea-Pathfinder introduces sophisticated ray-tracing tools to make the link between the space of N-body simulations and light-cone observables. This should provide new ways of exploring existing cosmological probes and building new ones beyond standard assumptions in order to prepare for the next generation of large-scale structure surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2111.08744v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202142661 10.1051/0004-6361/202142661</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A 662, A114 (2022)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Michel-Andr\`es Breton, Vincent Reverdy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring Line-of-sight Distances to Haloes with Astrometric Lensing B-mode</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.10750</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.10750v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Relative astrometric shifts between multiply lensed images provide a valuable tool to investigate haloes in the intergalactic space. In strong lens systems in which a single lens plays the primary role in producing multiple images, the gravitational force exerted by line-of-sight (LOS) haloes can slightly change the relative positions of multiply lensed images produced by the dominant lens. In such cases, a LOS halo positioned sufficiently far from the dominant lens along the LOS can create a pattern in the reduced deflection angle that corresponds to the B-mode (magnetic or divergence-free mode). By measuring both the B-mode and E-mode (electric or rotation-free mode), we can determine the LOS distance ratios, as well as the 'bare' convergence and shear perturbations in the absence of the dominant lens. However, scale variations in the distance ratio lead to mass-sheet transformations in the background lens plane, introducing some uncertainty in the distance ratio estimation. This uncertainty can be significantly reduced by measuring the time delays between the lensed images. Additionally, if we obtain the redshift values of both the dominant and perturbing haloes, along with the time delays between the multiply lensed images that are affected by the haloes, the B-mode can break the degeneracy related to mass-sheet transformations in both the foreground and background lens planes. Therefore, measuring the astrometric lensing B-mode has the potential to substantially decrease the uncertainty in determining the Hubble constant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.10750v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaiki Taro Inoue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$5 \sigma$ tension between Planck cosmic microwave background and eBOSS Lyman-alpha forest and constraints on physics beyond $\Lambda$CDM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.16377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.16377v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We find that combined Planck cosmic microwave background, baryon acoustic oscillations and supernovae data analyzed under $\Lambda$CDM are in 4.9$\sigma$ tension with eBOSS Ly$\alpha$ forest in inference of the linear matter power spectrum at wavenumber $\sim 1 h\,\mathrm{Mpc}^{-1}$ and redshift = 3. Model extensions can alleviate this tension: running in the tilt of the primordial power spectrum ($\alpha_\mathrm{s} \sim -0.01$); a fraction $\sim (1 - 5)\%$ of ultra-light axion dark matter (DM) with particle mass $\sim 10^{-25}$ eV or warm DM with mass $\sim 10$ eV. The new DESI survey, coupled with high-accuracy modeling, will help distinguish the source of this discrepancy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.16377v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.7.L012018</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 7, L012018 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Keir K. Rogers, Vivian Poulin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SENSEI: First Direct-Detection Results on sub-GeV Dark Matter from SENSEI at SNOLAB</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.13342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.13342v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the first results from a dark matter search using six Skipper-CCDs in the SENSEI detector operating at SNOLAB. We employ a bias-mitigation technique of hiding approximately 46% of our total data and aggressively mask images to remove backgrounds. Given a total exposure after masking of 100.72 gram-days from well-performing sensors, we observe 55 two-electron events, 4 three-electron events, and no events containing 4 to 10 electrons. The two-electron events are consistent with pileup from one-electron events. Among the 4 three-electron events, 2 appear in pixels that are likely impacted by detector defects, although not strongly enough to trigger our "hot-pixel" mask. We use these data to set world-leading constraints on sub-GeV dark matter interacting with electrons and nuclei.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.13342v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.134.011804</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator> SENSEI Collaboration, Prakruth Adari, Itay M. Bloch, Ana M. Botti, Mariano Cababie, Gustavo Cancelo, Brenda A. Cervantes-Vergara, Michael Crisler, Miguel Daal, Ansh Desai, Alex Drlica-Wagner, Rouven Essig, Juan Estrada, Erez Etzion, Guillermo Fernandez Moroni, Stephen E. Holland, Jonathan Kehat, Yaron Korn, Ian Lawson, Steffon Luoma, Aviv Orly, Santiago E. Perez, Dario Rodrigues, Nathan A. Saffold, Silvia Scorza, Aman Singal, Miguel Sofo-Haro, Leandro Stefanazzi, Kelly Stifter, Javier Tiffenberg, Sho Uemura, Edgar Marrufo Villalpando, Tomer Volansky, Yikai Wu, Tien-Tien Yu, Timon Emken, Hailin Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A search for the fine-structure constant evolution from fast radio bursts and type Ia supernovae data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11691v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The search for a space-time variation of the fundamental constants has been explored over the years to test our physical theories. In this paper, we use the dispersion measure ($DM$) of fast radio bursts (FRB) combined with type Ia supernovae (SNe) data to investigate a possible redshift evolution of the fine-structure constant ($\alpha$), considering the runaway dilaton scenario, which predicts $\frac{\Delta \alpha}{\alpha} = - \gamma\ln{(1+z)}$, where $\gamma$ is a constant proportional to the current value of the coupling between the dilaton field and hadronic matter. We derive all the relevant expressions for the $DM$ dependence concerning the fine-structure constant and constrain the parameter $\gamma$ from measurements of 17 well-localized FRBs and 1048 SNe data from the Pantheon compilation. We also use Monte Carlo simulations to forecast the constraining power of larger samples of FRB measurements for data sets with $N = 500$ and $N = 1000$ points. We found that the uncertainty on $\gamma$ can be improved by one order of magnitude and that limits on $\frac{\Delta \alpha}{\alpha}$ beyond $\sigma \sim 10^{-2}$ will depend crucially on better control of statistical and systematic uncertainties of upcoming FRB data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11691v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/01/059</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 01, (2025) 059</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Thais Lemos, Rodrigo Gon\c{c}alves, Joel Carvalho, Jailson Alcaniz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying Lyman-$\alpha$ emissions from reionization fronts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14622v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: During reionization, intergalactic ionization fronts (I-fronts) are sources of Ly$\alpha$ line radiation produced by collisional excitation of hydrogen atoms within the fronts. In principle, detecting this emission could provide direct evidence for a reionizing intergalactic medium (IGM). In this paper, we use a suite of high-resolution one-dimensional radiative transfer simulations run on cosmological density fields to quantify the parameter space of I-front Ly$\alpha$ emission. We find that the Ly$\alpha$ production efficiency -- the ratio of emitted Ly$\alpha$ flux to incident ionizing flux driving the front -- depends mainly on the I-front speed and the spectral index of the ionizing radiation. IGM density fluctuations on scales smaller than the typical I-front width produce scatter in the efficiency, but they do not significantly boost its mean value. The Ly$\alpha$ flux emitted by an I-front is largest if 3 conditions are met simultaneously: (1) the incident ionizing flux is large; (2) the incident spectrum is hard, consisting of more energetic photons; (3) the I-front is traveling through a cosmological over-density, which causes it to propagate more slowly. We present a convenient parameterization of the efficiency in terms of I-front speed and incident spectral index. We make these results publicly available as an interpolation table and we provide a simple fitting function for a representative ionizing background spectrum. Our results can be applied as a sub-grid model for I-front Ly$\alpha$ emissions in reionization simulations with spatial and/or temporal resolutions too coarse to resolve I-front structure. In a companion paper, we use our results to explore the possibility of directly imaging Ly$\alpha$ emission around neutral islands during the last phases of reionization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14622v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/01/065</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP01(2025)065</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bayu Wilson, Anson D'Aloisio, Christopher Cain, Eli Visbal, George D. Becker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imaging reionization's last phases with I-front Lyman-$\alpha$ emissions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14625v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Long troughs observed in the $z &gt; 5.5$ Ly$\alpha$ and Ly$\beta$ forests are thought to be caused by the last remaining neutral patches during the end phases of reionization -- termed neutral islands. If this is true, then the longest troughs mark locations where we are most likely to observe the reionizing intergalactic medium (IGM). A key feature of the neutral islands is that they are bounded by ionization fronts (I-fronts) which emit Lyman series lines. In this paper, we explore the possibility of directly imaging the outline of neutral islands with a narrowband survey targeting Ly$\alpha$. In a companion paper, we quantified the intensity of I-front Ly$\alpha$ emissions during reionization and its dependence on the spectrum of incident ionizing radiation and I-front speed. Here we apply those results to reionization simulations to model the emissions from neutral islands. We find that neutral islands would appear as diffuse structures that are tens of comoving Mpc across, with surface brightnesses in the range $\approx 1 - 5\times 10^{-21}$ erg s$^{-1}$ cm$^{-2}$ arcsec$^{-2}$. The islands are brighter if the spectrum of ionizing radiation driving the I-fronts is harder, and/or if the I-fronts are moving faster. We develop mock observations for current and futuristic observatories and find that, while extremely challenging, detecting neutral islands is potentially within reach of an ambitious observing program with wide-field narrowband imaging. Our results demonstrate the potentially high impact of low-surface brightness observations for studying reionization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14625v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/01/066</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP01(2025)066</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bayu Wilson, Anson D'Aloisio, George D. Becker, Christopher Cain, Eli Visbal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining the impact of standard model phase transitions on primordial black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16563</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16563v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Phase transitions in the early universe lead to a reduction in the equation of state of the primordial plasma. This exponentially enhances the formation rate of primordial black holes. However, this sensitivity to the equation of state is the same that primordial black hole abundances show to the primordial curvature power spectrum amplitude. In this paper, we investigate peaked power spectra and show the challenges associated with motivating populations of primordial black holes with standard model enhancements. The parametrisation of different power spectra plays an important role in this discussion. The allowed parameter space consistent with a large QCD phase transition impact on the primordial black hole abundance differs greatly. This is particularly evident for broader spectra. We also show that, in our framework, the electroweak phase transition cannot significantly affect the overall abundance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16563v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/01/076</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Xavier Pritchard, Christian T. Byrnes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic Alignments and Spin Correlations of [OII] Emitters at $z=1.2$ and $z=1.5$ from HSC Narrow-band Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11462v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Galaxies are known to be aligned toward specific directions within the large-scale structure. Such alignment signals become important for controlling the systematics of weak lensing surveys and for constraining galaxy formation and evolution scenarios. We measure the galaxy-ellipticity and ellipticity-ellipticity correlation functions for blue star-forming galaxies at $z=1.19$ and $z=1.47$ that are selected by detecting [OII] emission lines in narrow-band filters of the Hyper Suprime-Cam on the Subaru Telescope. Assuming that disk galaxies are thin and rotation-supported, we also measure the spin correlation function by estimating spin directions with ellipticities and position angles. Above $1 \; h^{-1}{\rm Mpc}$, we do not find significant signals for galaxy-ellipticity, ellipticity-ellipticity, or spin correlations at both redshifts. Below $1 \; h^{-1}{\rm Mpc}$, a weak deviation from zero is seen at $z=1.47$, implying weak spin-filament correlations, but it is not verified by the direct comparison between angles of spins and filaments. The linear alignment model fit yields the amplitude parameter $A_{\rm NLA}=1.38\pm2.32$ at $z=1.19$ and $0.45\pm2.09$ at $z=1.47$ ($95\%$ confidence levels). We discuss various observational and physical origins that affect the search for alignments of disk galaxies at high redshifts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11462v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Motonari Tonegawa, Teppei Okumura, Masao Hayashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the impact of neutrino mass hierarchies on neutrino mass constraints in light of recent DESI data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03546v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent results from DESI combined with cosmic microwave background data give the tightest constraints on the sum of neutrino masses to date. However, these analyses approximate the neutrino mass hierarchy by three degenerate-mass (DM) neutrinos, instead of the normal (NH) and inverted hierarchies (IH) informed by terrestrial neutrino oscillation experiments. Given the stringency of the upper limits from DESI data, we test explicitly whether the inferred neutrino constraints are robust to the choice of neutrino mass ordering using both Bayesian and frequentist methods. For Planck data alone, we find that the DM hierarchy presents a good approximation to the physically motivated hierarchies while showing a strong dependence on the assumed lower bound of the prior, confirming previous studies. For the combined Planck and DESI baryon acoustic oscillation data, we find that assuming NH ($M_\mathrm{tot} &lt; 0.13\,\mathrm{eV}$) or IH ($M_\mathrm{tot} &lt; 0.16\,\mathrm{eV}$) loosens the Bayesian upper limits compared to the DM approximation ($M_\mathrm{tot} &lt; 0.086\,\mathrm{eV}$). The frequentist analysis shows that the different neutrino models fit the data equally well and the loosening of the constraints can thus be attributed to the lower bounds induced by NH and IH. Overall, we find that the DM hierarchy presents a good approximation to the physically motivated hierarchies also for Planck+DESI data as long as the corresponding lower neutrino mass bounds are imposed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03546v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laura Herold, Marc Kamionkowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining Millicharged dark matter with Gravitational positivity bounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04454</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04454v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Gravitational positivity bounds provide consistency conditions for effective field theories with gravity. They turn out to be phenomenologically useful by providing lower bounds in parameters of new physics beyond the Standard Models (BSM). In this paper, we derive constraints on millicharged fermion dark matter models with massless dark photon using gravitational positivity bounds. Combining them with upper bounds from cosmological and astrophysical observations, we can severely constrain the parameter space of the model. In particular, we show that when the dark matter mass is lighter than the solar core temperature, most of the parameter region is excluded by combining gravitational positivity bounds and the stellar bounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04454v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suro Kim, Pyungwon Ko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generation of effective massive Spin-2 fields through spontaneous symmetry breaking of scalar field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06572v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: General relativity and quantum field theory are the cornerstones of our understanding of physical processes, from subatomic to cosmic scales. While both theories work remarkably well in their tested domains, they show minimal overlap. However, our research challenges this separation by revealing that non-perturbative effects bridge these distinct domains. We introduce a novel mechanism wherein, at linear order, spin-2 fields around an arbitrary background acquire \emph{effective mass} due to the spontaneous symmetry breaking (SSB) of either global or local symmetry of complex scalar field minimally coupled to gravity. The action of the spin-2 field is identical to the extended Fierz-Pauli (FP) action, corresponding to the mass deformation parameter $\alpha = 1/2$. We show that this occurs due to the effect of SSB on the variation of the energy-momentum tensor of the matter field, which has a dominant effect during SSB. The extended FP action has a salient feature, compared to the standard FP action: the action has 6 degrees of freedom with no ghosts. For local $U(1)$ SSB, we establish that the effective mass of spin-2 fields is related to the mass of the gauge boson and the electric charge of the complex scalar field. Interestingly, our results indicate that the millicharged dark matter scalar fields, generating dark photons, can produce a mass of spin-2 fields of the same order as the Hubble constant $(H_0)$. Hence, we argue that the dark sector offers a natural explanation for the acceleration of the current Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06572v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Susobhan Mandal (IIT Bombay), S. Shankaranarayanan (IIT Bombay)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Attenuation of Cosmic Ray Electron Boosted Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02721</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02721v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a model of boosted dark matter (DM), where a fraction of DM is upscattered to relativistic energies by cosmic ray electrons. Such interactions responsible for boosting the DM also attenuate its flux at the Earth. Considering a simple model of constant interaction cross-section, we make analytical estimates of the variation of the attenuation ceiling with the DM mass and confirm it numerically. We then extend our analysis to a $Z'$-mediated leptophilic DM model. We show that the attenuation ceiling remains nearly model-independent for DM and mediator particles heavier than the electron, challenging some previous discussions on this topic. Using the XENONnT direct detection experiment, we illustrate how constraints based on energy-dependent scattering can significantly differ from those based on an assumed constant cross-section. This highlights the importance of re-evaluating these constraints in the context of specific models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02721v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.123023</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Tim Herbermann, Manfred Lindner, Manibrata Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cold Collapse and Bounce of an FLRW Cloud</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06785v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the collapse of spherical cold clouds beyond black hole formation to investigate the possibility of a bounce in the in-falling matter when a critical density or pressure is reached. As a first step, we analyse the pressureless collapse in general relativity (GR), where an analytic solution exists, and demonstrate that an equivalent Newtonian solution can be derived. Such equivalence also holds for spherically symmetric perfect fluids with uniform density and non-vanishing pressure. We numerically investigate the Newtonian collapse of such clouds with masses of $5$, $20$, and $1000$ M$_\odot$ obeying a polytropic equation of state (EoS). By choosing EoS parameters inspired by typical neutron star conditions, we observe bounces at and above nuclear saturation density. Assuming approximate uniformity, we explore the equivalent GR behaviour of the matter during the bounce. Our findings are as follows: (i) A GR bounce occurs around the ground state of the matter, characterized by $P = -\rho$. (ii) The GR solution differs significantly from the Newtonian result due to the presence of curvature ($k \neq 0$). (iii) Both the curvature and the ground state are crucial factors in allowing a GR bounce to occur.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06785v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/staf019</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Swaraj Pradhan, Michael Gabler, Enrique Gazta\~naga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D Localization of FRB 20190425A for Its Potential Host Galaxy and Implications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13973</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13973v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Fast radio bursts (FRBs) are high-energy, short-duration phenomena in radio astronomy. Identifying their host galaxies can provide insights into their mysterious origins. In this paper, we introduce a novel approach to identifying potential host galaxies in three-dimensional space. We use FRB 20190425A and GW190425 as an example to illustrate our method. Recently, due to spatial and temporal proximity, the potential association of GW190425 with FRB 20190425A has drawn attention, leading to the identification of a likely host galaxy, UGC 10667, albeit without confirmed kilonova emissions. We search for the host galaxy of FRB 20190425A with a full CHIME localization map. Regardless of the validity of the association between GW190425 and FRB 20190425A, we identify an additional potential host galaxy (SDSS J171046.84+212732.9) from the updated GLADE galaxy catalog, supplementing the importance of exploring the new volume. We employed various methodologies to determine the most probable host galaxy of GW190424 and FRB 20190425A, including a comparison of galaxy properties and constraints on their reported observation limits using various Kilonova models. Our analysis suggests that current observations do not definitively identify the true host galaxy. Additionally, the Kilonova models characterized by a gradual approach to their peak are contradicted by the observational upper limits of both galaxies. Although the absence of optical emission detection raises doubts, it does not definitively disprove the connection between GW and FRB.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13973v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ada28c</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>APJ, 2025, 979:95</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Da-Chun Qiang, Zhiqiang You, Sheng Yang, Zong-Hong Zhu, Ting-Wan Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmic voids and the kinetic analysis. IV. Hubble tension and the cosmological constant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09598v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The formation of the cosmic structures in the late Universe is considered using Vlasov kinetic approach. The crucial point is the use of the gravitational potential with repulsive term of the cosmological constant which provides a solution to the Hubble tension, that is the Hubble parameter for the late Universe has to differ from its global cosmological value. This also provides a mechanism of formation of stationary semi-periodic gravitating structures of voids and walls, so that the cosmological constant has a role of the scaling and hence can be compared with the observational data for given regions. The considered mechanism of the structure formation in late cosmological epoch then is succeeding the epoch described by the evolution of primordial density fluctuations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09598v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. G. Gurzadyan, N. N. Fimin, V. M. Chechetkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GLIMPSE: An ultra-faint $\simeq$ 10$^{5}$ $M_{\odot}$ Pop III Galaxy Candidate and First Constraints on the Pop III UV Luminosity Function at $z\simeq6-7$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11678v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Detecting the first generation of stars, Population III (PopIII), has been a long-standing goal in astrophysics, yet they remain elusive even in the JWST era. Here we present a novel NIRCam-based selection method for PopIII galaxies, and carefully validate it through completeness and contamination simulations. We systematically search ~500 arcmin$^{2}$ across JWST legacy fields for PopIII candidates, including GLIMPSE which, assisted by gravitational lensing, has produced JWST's deepest NIRCam imaging thus far. We discover one promising PopIII galaxy candidate (GLIMPSE-16043) at $z=6.50^{+0.03}_{-0.24}$, a moderately lensed galaxy (mu=2.9) with an intrinsic UV magnitude of $M_{UV}$=-15.89. It exhibits key PopIII features: strong H$\alpha$ emission (rest-frame EW $2810\pm550$\AA); a Balmer jump; no dust (UV slope $\beta=-2.34\pm0.36$); and undetectable metal lines (e.g., [OIII]; [OIII]/H$\beta$&lt;0.44) implying a gas-phase metallicity of Zgas/Zsun&lt;0.5%. These properties indicate the presence of a nascent, metal-deficient young stellar population (&lt;5Myr) with a stellar mass of $\simeq10^{5}M_{\odot}$. Intriguingly, this source deviates significantly from the extrapolated UV-metallicity relation derived from recent JWST observations at $z=4-10$, consistent with UV enhancement by a top-heavy PopIII initial mass function or the presence of an extremely metal-poor AGN. We also derive the first observational constraints on the PopIII UV luminosity function at z~6-7. The volume density of GLIMPSE-16043 ($\approx10^{-4}$ cMpc$^{-3}$) is in excellent agreement with theoretical predictions, independently reinforcing its plausibility. This study demonstrates the power of our novel NIRCam method to finally reveal distant galaxies even more pristine than the Milky Way's most metal-poor satellites, thereby promising to bring us closer to the first generation of stars than we have ever been before.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11678v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seiji Fujimoto, Rohan P. Naidu, John Chisholm, Hakim Atek, Ryan Endsley, Vasily Kokorev, Lukas J. Furtak, Richard Pan, Boyuan Liu, Volker Bromm, Alessandra Venditti, Eli Visbal, Richard Sarmento, Andrea Weibel, Pascal A. Oesch, Gabriel Brammer, Daniel Schaerer, Angela Adamo, Danielle A. Berg, Rachel Bezanson, Iryna Chemerynska, Ad\'ela\"ide Claeyssens, Miroslava Dessauges-Zavadsky, Anna Frebel, Damien Korber, Ivo Labbe, Rui Marques-Chaves, Jorryt Matthee, Kristen B. W. McQuinn, Julian B. Mu\~noz, Priyamvada Natarajan, Alberto Saldana-Lopez, Katherine A. Suess, Marta Volonteri, Adi Zitrin</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
