<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO</link>
    <description>astro-ph.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 05:00:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Oort Cloud Bombardment by Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.04922v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The realization that primordial black holes (PBHs) might be some fraction of the dark matter begged the question, how often do PBHs enter the solar system? For a Neptune radius solar system the answer is, rarely. For an Oort cloud sized system the answer is different. Simulations of bombardment of the Oort cloud by dark matter suggest that dislodgement of protocomets and their entry into the inner solar system can match the observed frequency of comets, if that PBH fraction is high enough. Comets were traditionally considered as messengers, usually omens. After 50 years of puzzlement regarding dark matter, we need a hint from the dark universe about the size and nature of dark matter particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.04922v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeremy Mould</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Establishing a relationship between the cosmological 21 cm power spectrum and interferometric closure phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.04965v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Measurements of the cosmic 21 cm signal need to achieve a high dynamic range to isolate it from bright foreground emissions. Calibration inaccuracies can compromise the spectral fidelity of the smooth foreground continuum, thereby limiting the dynamic range and potentially precluding the detection of the cosmic line signal. In light of this challenge, recent work has proposed using the calibration-independent closure phase to search for the spectral fluctuations of the cosmic 21 cm signal. However, so far there has been only a heuristic understanding of how closure phases map to the cosmological 21 cm power spectrum. This work aims to establish a more accurate mathematical relationship between closure phases and the cosmological power spectrum of the background line signal. Building on previous work, we treat the cosmic signal component as a perturbation to the closure phase and use a delay spectrum approach to estimate its power. We establish the relationship between this estimate and the cosmological power spectrum using standard Fourier transform techniques and validate it using simulated HERA observations. We find that, statistically, the power spectrum estimate from closure phases is approximately equal to the cosmological power spectrum convolved with a foreground-dependent window function, provided that the signal-to-foreground ratio is small. Compared with standard approaches, the foreground dependence of the window function results in an increased amount of mode-mixing and a more pronounced proliferation of foreground power along the line-of-sight dimension of the cylindrical power spectrum. These effects can be mitigated by flagging instances where the window function is broad. Crucial to gaining the necessary sensitivity, this mapping will allow us to average the measurements of closure triads of different shapes based on their imprint in cylindrical Fourier space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.04965v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202557511</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A, 705, A221 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pascal M. Keller, Bojan Nikolic, Nithyanandan Thyagarajan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Differentiable Stochastic Halo Occupation Distribution with Galaxy Intrinsic Alignments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.04977v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present diffHOD-IA, a fully differentiable implementation of a halo occupation distribution (HOD) model that incorporates galaxy intrinsic alignments (IA). Motivated by the diffHOD framework, we create a new implementation that extends differentiable galaxy population modeling to include orientation-dependent statistics crucial for weak gravitational lensing analyses. Our implementation combines this HOD formulation with an IA model, enabling end-to-end automatic differentiation from HOD and IA parameters through to the galaxy field. We additionally extend this framework to differentiably model two-point correlation functions, including galaxy clustering and IA statistics. We validate diffHOD-IA against the reference halotools-IA implementation using the Bolshoi-Planck simulation, demonstrating excellent agreement across both one-point and two-point statistics. We verify the accuracy of gradients computed via automatic differentiation by comparison with finite-difference estimates for both HOD and IA parameters. We present science use cases leveraging gradients in the simulations to recover the IA parameters of a galaxy field representative of the TNG300 simulation. Finally, we apply diffHOD-IA in a Hamiltonian Monte Carlo analysis and compare its performance with halotools-IA and a neural-network-based emulator, IAEmu. Unlike emulator-based approaches, diffHOD-IA provides differentiability at the catalog level, enabling integration into field-level inference pipelines and extension to arbitrary summary statistics for next-generation weak-lensing analyses. Our code is publicly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.04977v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sneh Pandya, Jonathan Blazek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Impact of Galaxy Formation on Galaxy Biasing, and Implications for Primordial non-Gaussianity Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04987</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.04987v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The parameter $f_{\textrm{NL}}$ measures the local non-Gaussianity in the primordial energy fluctuations of the Universe, with any deviation from $f_{\textrm{NL}}=0$ providing key constraints on inflationary models. Galaxy clustering is sensitive to $f_{\textrm{NL}}$ at large scale modes and the next generation of galaxy surveys will approach a statistical error of $\sigma_{f_{\textrm{NL}}}\sim1$. However, the systematic errors on these constraints are dominated by the degeneracy of $f_{\textrm{NL}}$ with the galaxy bias parameters $b_1$ (galaxy overdensities caused by mass perturbations) and $b_{\phi}$ (galaxy overdensities caused by primordial potential perturbations). It has been shown that the assumed scaling of $b_{\phi}(z)=2\delta_c (b_1(z)-1)$ is not accurate for realistically simulated galaxies, and depends both on the galaxy selection and the way that galaxies are modeled. To address this, we leverage the CAMELS-SAM pipeline to explore how varying parameters of galaxy formation affects $b_{\phi}$ and $b_1$ for various galaxy selections. We run separate-universe N-body simulations of $L=205 h^{-1}$ cMpc and $N=1280^3$ to measure $b_{\phi}$, and run 55 unique instances of the Santa Cruz semi-analytic model with varying parameters of stellar and AGN feedback. We find the behavior and evolution of a SC-SAM model's stellar-, SFR- and sSFR- to halo mass relationships track well with how $b_1$ and $b_{\phi}(b_1)$ change across redshift and selection for the SC-SAM. We find our variations of the SC-SAM encapsulate the $b_{\phi}$ behavior previously measured in IllustrisTNG, the Munich SAM, and Galacticus.Finally, we identify sSFR selections as particularly robust to varied galaxy modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.04987v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucia A. Perez, Shy Genel, Elisabeth Krause, Rachel S. Somerville</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wising up to CatWISE: using simulation-based inference to interpret the ecliptic bias and confirm the cosmic dipole excess</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05070v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We apply Simulation-Based Inference ('SBI') to the cosmic dipole problem for the first time, measuring the distribution of quasar counts over the sky in the CatWISE2020 ('CatWISE') sample. We show that the quadrupole anisotropy in CatWISE can be attributed to the correlation between WISE's scanning law and photometric uncertainty in the $W1$ and $W2$ magnitudes, inducing an Eddington bias which varies with sky position. After explicitly modelling this with SBI, we use a neural likelihood estimator to find the posterior distribution for CatWISE's dipole, confirming the presence of a dipole twice as large as the CMB expectation but more seriously misaligned with the CMB direction ($\approx 3 \sigma$). We also use our learned likelihood to infer the Bayesian evidence, learning that models which increase the scale of CatWISE's photometric errors are most favoured. This is strong evidence that the sample's errors are underestimated or that there is an additional, unresolved systematic producing the same effect as Eddington bias. While our results indicate that the cosmic dipole excess is a persistent issue for $\Lambda$CDM, we showcase that SBI can untangle the subtle and complex systematic issues affecting any sample derived from real astronomical data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05070v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oliver T. Oayda, Geraint F. Lewis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Galaxy Bias Profile of Cosmic Voids:A Comparison of Void Finders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05117v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cosmic voids, the largest underdense regions in the Universe, provide unique laboratories for studying galaxy formation and constitute powerful probes of cosmology. Recent work has shown that individual galaxy bias (b_i), which quantifies how each galaxy traces the underlying dark matter field, exhibits a characteristic radial dependence within spherical voids, defining a void bias profile in which galaxies near void centers display systematically lower bias values. We investigate how the environmental modulation of individual galaxy bias depends on the adopted void-finding algorithm by comparing measurements across five distinct void definitions: spherical voids 'sparkling', watershed-based methods ('zobov' and 'revolver' in two modes), and free-form integrated-density voids ('popcorn'). We apply these complementary void-finding algorithms to the same galaxy sample drawn from the IllustrisTNG simulation (TNG300-1 at $z=0$) and compute individual galaxy bias profiles as a function of distance from void centers. We quantify the correlation between b_i and the membership of the void catalogs and explore how this relationship varies with the integrated underdensity threshold for density-based methods. We find that the radial gradient of individual bias within voids, generally increasing from negative values at the void centers to higher values at the boundaries, is robust across most void definitions. However, density-threshold methods preferentially select galaxies with b_i&lt;0, while watershed methods without density constraints include substantial contamination from high-bias boundary galaxies. The correlation between negative bias and void membership is systematically strengthened as the integrated underdensity threshold becomes less restrictive, with popcorn achieving the highest purity in isolating anti-biased populations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05117v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ignacio G. Alfaro, Antonio D. Montero-Dorta, Jorge F. Bustillos, Dante J. Paz, Andr\'es N. Ruiz, Andr\'es Balaguera-Antol\'inez, Ravi K. Sheth, Facundo Rodriguez, Constanza A. Soto-Su\'arez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractal dimension of the cosmic web with different galaxy types</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05309v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The fractal dimension $D$ is used to map the large-scale galaxy distribution in the Universe by color types: blue, green and red. Using a $NUVrK$-complete COSMOS2020 subsample of 618,952 galaxies observed up to $z=4$, number densities were derived and plotted against two cosmological distance measures, the luminosity and comoving (galaxy area) distances, in order to estimate $D$ for each galaxy color type in two redshift intervals: $z\gtrless1$. We found a general gradient $D_{\mathrm{blue}}&gt; D_{\mathrm{red}}&gt;D_{\mathrm{green}}$ with $D=1.40-2.03$ for $z&lt;1$. For $1&lt;z\leq4$, the gradient changes to $D_{\mathrm{blue}}&gt;D_{\mathrm{green}}D_{\mathrm{red}}$, and the fractal dimension values are lower, $D=0.03-0.44$. These results suggest that the fractal dimension is a sensitive diagnostic for how galaxy populations trace the evolving cosmic web, and confirm the fractal dimension as a useful tool for observational mapping of large-scale structure by galaxy color.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05309v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ana Elisa Lima, Julianne C. Soares, Ana Carolina S. Tavares, Mariana V. Taveira, Sharon Teles, Amanda R. Lopes, Marcelo B. Ribeiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Energy After DESI DR2: Observational Status, Reconstructions, and Physical Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05368v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We review late-time cosmic acceleration after DESI Data Release~2 (DR2), emphasizing the interplay between Type~Ia supernovae (SNe~Ia), anisotropic BAO, CMB calibration, and perturbation-sensitive probes (RSD and weak lensing). DESI DR2 delivers percent-level BAO distance ratios over $0\lesssim z\lesssim2.5$, including a Ly$\alpha$-forest anchor at $z_{\rm eff}=2.33$. In CMB-calibrated combinations, flat $\Lambda$CDM exhibits a mild parameter mismatch, while allowing evolving dark energy (e.g.\ CPL $w_0$--$w_a$) can improve the fit; the preference is dataset-dependent and is particularly sensitive to redshift-dependent SN calibration/selection residuals at the few$\times10^{-2}$\,mag level. To sharpen likelihood-level interpretation, we provide two diagnostics: (i) an $r_d$-independent BAO-shape observable, $F_{\rm AP}(z)\equiv D_{\rm M}(z)/D_{\rm H}(z)$, constructed directly from published $(D_{\rm M}/r_d,\,D_{\rm H}/r_d)$ with covariance propagation; and (ii) a linear-response map from SN Hubble-diagram systematics $\delta\mu(z)$ to induced biases in $(w_0,w_a)$, yielding an explicit calibration requirement for DESI-era claims of evolving $w(z)$. We synthesize parametric and non-parametric reconstructions of $w(z)$ and $\rho_{\rm DE}(z)$ and map the resulting phenomenology to microphysical dark-energy and modified-gravity models subject to perturbation stability and gravitational-wave propagation constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05368v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Slava G. Turyshev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forecast on $f(R)$ Gravity with HI 21cm Intensity Mapping Surveys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05575v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Modified gravity theories offer a well-motivated extension of General Relativity and provide a possible explanation for the late-time accelerated expansion of the Universe. Among them, $f(R)$ gravity represents a minimal and theoretically appealing class, characterized by the Compton wavelength parameter $B_0$, which quantifies deviations from General Relativity. In this work, we explore the capability of future neutral hydrogen (HI) 21 cm intensity mapping (IM) observations to constrain $f(R)$ gravity at low redshifts. We perform Fisher-matrix forecasts for $B_0$ and standard cosmological parameters using upcoming 21 cm IM experiments, including BINGO and SKA1-MID (Band 1 and Band 2), both individually and in combination with Planck cosmic microwave background (CMB) priors. We find that even near-term experiments such as BINGO are able to place nontrivial bounds on $B_0$, $\sigma(B_0)\simeq 2.27\times 10^{-6}$, while SKA1-MID yields substantially tighter constraints, with SKA Band 2 providing the strongest sensitivity among the considered configurations, $\sigma(B_0)\simeq 6.37\times 10^{-8}$. We further demonstrate that the combination of low-redshift 21 cm IM data with CMB observations efficiently breaks degeneracies with background cosmological parameters and leads to a significant improvement in the constraints on $B_0$. These results highlight the potential of future HI intensity mapping surveys, in combination with CMB measurements, to provide stringent tests of General Relativity on cosmological scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05575v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanling Song, Yu Sang, Linfeng Xiao, Boyu Zhang, Bin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The kinematic cosmic dipole beyond Ellis and Baldwin</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05700v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The cosmic dipole anomaly, currently detected at a significance exceeding 5$\sigma$ in several independent survey poses a significant challenge to the standard model of cosmology. The Ellis &amp; Baldwin formula provides a theoretical link between the intrinsic dipole anisotropy in the sky distribution of extragalactic light sources and the observer's velocity relative to the cosmic rest frame, under the assumptions that the sources follow a power-law luminosity function and exhibit power-law spectral energy distributions. In this work, we demonstrate that this relation can be generalized to arbitrary luminosity distributions and spectral profiles. We derive the corresponding expression for the effective spectral index and apply it to a sample of quasars observed in the W1 band of the CatWISE survey. We show that the anomalous cosmic dipole persists beyond the power-law assumption. These results provide a more general and robust framework to interpret measurements of the cosmic dipole in future large-scale surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05700v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Albert Bonnefous</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microlensing constraint on Primordial Black Hole abundance with Subaru Hyper Suprime-Cam observations of Andromeda</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05840</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05840v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present updated microlensing analysis results based on high-cadence ($\sim$2~min) Subaru Hyper Suprime-Cam (HSC) observations of the Andromeda Galaxy (M31) in 2014, 2017, and 2020, yielding a total of 39.3 hours of data. We use a point-lens finite-source model for the microlensing light curve model and employ multi-stage selection procedures to identify microlensing candidates. From more than 25,000 variable candidates detected across all nights, we identify 12 microlensing candidates with light-curve timescales shorter than 5~hours, and among them, 4 secure candidates with high-significance detections. We estimate detection efficiencies using light-curve-level simulations that account for observational conditions and finite-source effects. Using a hierarchical Bayesian framework that combines the light-curve fitting information for each candidate with the Poisson statistics of the number of candidates, we derive constraints on parameters that characterize the abundance and mass scale of primordial black hole (PBH) dark matter. First, we derive upper limits on the PBH abundance under the null hypothesis that all events are assumed to be false detections. Next, employing the PBH hypothesis in which all (or only secure) candidates are assumed to be due to PBH microlensing, we derive the allowed region of the PBH parameters; the inferred mass scale is $M_{\rm PBH}\sim10^{-7}$--$10^{-6}M_\odot$, and the PBH abundance to the total dark matter is $f_{\rm PBH}\sim \mathcal{O}(10^{-2}{\rm -}10^{-1})$. Our results demonstrate that HSC-M31 monitoring remains a uniquely powerful probe of PBHs, and highlight the need for further studies for example, using Rubin Observatory LSST observations of the Large Magellanic Cloud.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05840v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sunao Sugiyama, Masahiro Takada, Naoki Yasuda, Nozomu Tominaga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting galaxy bias using machine learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05881</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05881v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding how galaxies trace the underlying matter density field is essential for characterizing the influence of the large-scale structure on galaxy formation, being therefore a key ingredient in observational cosmology. This connection, commonly described through the galaxy bias, $b$, can be studied effectively using machine learning (ML) techniques, which offer strong predictive capabilities and can capture non-linear relationships. We aim to incorporate the linear bias parameter assigned to individual galaxies into a ML framework, quantify its dependence on various halo and environmental properties, and evaluate whether different algorithms can accurately predict this parameter and reproduce the scatter in several bias relations. We use data from the IllustrisTNG300 simulation, including the distance to different cosmic-web structures computed with DisPerSE. These data are complemented with an object-by-object estimator of the large-scale linear bias ($b_i$), providing the individual contribution of each galaxy to the bias of the entire population. Our ML framework uses three models to predict $b_i$: a Random Forest Regressor, a Neural Network and a probabilistic method (Normalizing Flows). We recover the full hierarchy of galaxy bias dependencies, showing that the most informative features are the overdensities, particularly $\delta_8$, followed by the distances to cosmic-web structures and selected internal halo properties, most notably $z_{1/2}$. We also demonstrate that Normalizing Flows clearly outperform deterministic methods in predicting galaxy bias, including its joint distributions with galaxy properties, owing to their ability to capture the intrinsic variance associated with the stochastic nature of the matter-halo-galaxy connection. Our ML framework provides a foundation for future efforts to measure individual bias with upcoming spectroscopic surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05881v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Catalina Riveros-Jara, Antonio D. Montero-Dorta, Nat\'alia V. N. Rodrigues, P\'ia Amigo, Natal\'i S. M. de Santi, Andr\'es Balaguera-Antol\'inez, Raul Abramo, Neill Guzm\'an, M. Celeste Artale</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Early growth of massive black holes in dynamical dark energy models with negative cosmological constant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05921v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent results from combined cosmological probes indicate that the Dark Energy component of the Universe could be dynamical. The simplest explanation envisages the presence of a quintessence field rolling into a potential, where the Dark Energy energy density parameter $\Omega_{DE}=\Omega_{\Lambda}+\Omega_{x}$ results from the contribution of the ground state energy $\Omega_{\Lambda}$ and the scalar field energy $\Omega_{x}$. Provided that $\Omega_{DE}\approx 0.7$, negative values of $\Omega_{\Lambda}$ can be consistent with current measurements from cosmological probes, and could help in explaining the large abundance of bright galaxies observed by JWST at $z&gt; 10$, largely exceeding the pre-JWST expectations in a $\Lambda CDM$ Universe. Here we explore to what extent such a scenario can account also for the early presence of massive Black Holes (BHs) with masses $M_{BH}\gtrsim 10^7\,M_{\odot}$ observed at $z\gtrsim 8$, and for the large over-abundance of AGN with respect to pre-JWST expectations. Our aim is not to provide a detailed description of BH growth, but rather to compute the maximal BH growth that can occur in cosmological models with negative $\Omega_{\Lambda}$ under the simple assumption of Eddington-limited accretion onto initial light Black Hole seeds with mass $M_{seed}\sim 10^2\,M_{\odot}$ originated from PopIII stars. To this aim we develop a simple analytic framework to connect the growth of dark matter halos to the maximal growth of BHs within the above assumptions. We show such models can account for present observations assuming values of $\Omega_{\Lambda}\approx -1$, simultaneously boosting both galaxy and AGN number counts without invoking any additional physics. This would allow us to trace the observed excess of bright and massive galaxies and the early formation of massive Black Holes and the abundance of AGN to the same cosmological origin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05921v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. Menci, M. Castellano, P. Mukherjee, D. Roberts, P. Santini, A. A. Sen, F. Shankar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmographic parameters from current and next-generation gravitational wave detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05969v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We evaluate the capability of current and next-generation gravitational wave detectors, such as Advanced LIGO, Einstein Telescope and DECIGO, to constrain cosmographic parameters using electromagnetically bright standard sirens. By adopting a third-order Taylor expansion, we analyze how signal-to-noise ratios and the number of events impact the estimates of the Hubble constant ($H_0$), the deceleration ($q_0$) and jerk ($j_0$) parameters. Our results show that while Advanced LIGO provides a calibration-free measurement of $H_0$ at the few-percent level, it remains insensitive to higher-order parameters. In contrast, the Einstein Telescope and DECIGO reach sub-percent accuracy for $H_0$. Notably, DECIGO achieves a precision better than 10\% for the deceleration parameter $q_0$ and a few tens of percent for the jerk parameter $j_0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05969v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Morais, Rodrigo Gon\c{c}alves, Jailson Alcaniz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does Cosmology require Hermiticity in Quantum Mechanics?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05973</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05973v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the consequences of allowing non-Hermitian structures in quantum cosmology by extending the Wheeler DeWitt framework beyond strictly Hermitian dynamics. Using a controlled semiclassical reduction, we show how anti Hermitian contributions propagate into both early universe primordial fluctuations and late-time structure growth as effective damping or gain terms. Confronting this framework with inflationary observables, growth of structure and the observed near flatness of the universe, we derive strong infrared constraints that suppress non Hermiticity across cosmic history. We demonstrate that these bounds are mutually consistent between early and late-time probes and can be partially relaxed in theories beyond General Relativity. Our results establish cosmology as a novel arena for testing foundational aspects of quantum mechanics and suggest that Hermiticity may emerge dynamically along the semiclassical branch describing our universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05973v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oem Trivedi, Alfredo Gurrola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing cosmic anisotropy with cluster scaling relations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06007</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06007v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We test claims of large-scale anisotropy in the local expansion rate using cluster scaling relations as distance indicators. Using a Bayesian forward model, we jointly fit the X-ray luminosity--temperature (LT) and thermal Sunyaev-Zel'dovich--temperature (YT) relations, marginalising over the latent cluster distances and modelling selection effects as well as peculiar velocities. The latter are modelled using reconstructions of the local peculiar velocity field where we self-consistently account for possible anisotropic redshift--distance relations via an approximate scheme. This treatment proves crucial to the inferred anisotropy and breaks the degeneracy between anisotropy in scaling relation normalisations and underlying cosmological anisotropy. We apply our method to 312 clusters at $z \lesssim 0.2$, testing dipolar, quadrupolar and general (pixelised) anisotropy models. Bayesian model selection finds no more than weak evidence for any anisotropic model. For dipole models, we obtain upper limits of $\delta H_0 / H_0 &lt; 3.2\%$ and bulk flow magnitude $&lt; 1300\,\mathrm{km\,s^{-1}}$. Our results contrast with previous claims of statistically significant anisotropy from the same data, which we attribute to our principled forward modelling of both redshifts and scaling relation observables through latent distances and our treatment of the impact of anisotropic redshift--distance relations when modelling the local peculiar velocity field. Our work highlights the importance of accurately modelling peculiar velocities when testing isotropy with distance indicators, and motivates the further development of reconstructions that self-consistently treat large-scale deviations from the Hubble flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06007v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tariq Yasin, Richard Stiskalek, Harry Desmond, Sebastian von Hausegger, Pedro G. Ferreira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ACT DR6+Planck impact on inflation with non-zero vacuum expectation value and the post-inflationary behavior</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06027v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The impact of the most recent cosmic microwave background (CMB) data from the Atacama Cosmology Telescope (ACT) is studied for a model of cosmic inflation which predicts a non-zero vacuum expectation value (VEV) $M$ for a large-field regime. Since lower values of $M$ are compatible with the higher spectral index $n_s$ provided by the ACT+Planck joint analysis, we establish new limits on this parameter while also considering further CMB data from the latest BICEP/Keck Array release for CMB polarization modes. We find $\log_{10}M/M_{Pl}=-2.5^{+1.1}_{-1.3}$ at 68\% confidence level, compatible with $M/M_{Pl}\simeq 0.003$, which is interesting for post-inflationary processes, such as preheating. We conduct a lattice simulation for the inflaton field for the first few e-folds, as the model is compatible with the production of relics such as oscillons, which are possible candidates as sources of gravitational waves and primordial black holes. We find that the model indeed produces localized, quasi-spherical structures compatible with oscillons, which might lead to signatures detectable by future experiments. However, in agreement with recent works, we find that although the abundance of gravitational waves that could be generated in this regime has an amplitude well within the sensitivities of these detectors, the frequency range is on the GHz limit, away from the expected frequencies. Finally, we estimate the impact of a coupling of the type $y\phi\sigma^2$ to the inflaton, in the realization of perturbative reheating, directly impacting the predictions of the model, as lower values of $M$ are consistent with both the entire allowed temperature range, and the limits imposed by BICEP/Keck Array+Planck+ACT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06027v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. B. M. dos Santos, J. G. Rodrigues, G. Rodrigues, C. Siqueira, J. S. Alcaniz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Do Disk Galaxies Form?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04950</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.04950v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In both observed and simulated galaxies, disk morphologies become more prevalent at higher masses and lower redshifts. To elucidate the physical origin of this trend, we develop a simple analytical model in which galaxy morphology is governed by the competition between rotational support and turbulence in a gravitational potential of a dark matter halo and the galaxy itself, and a disk forms when the potential steepens due to the accumulation of baryons in the halo center. The minimum galaxy mass required for this transition decreases with an increasing dark matter contribution within the galaxy, making more concentrated halos more prone to forming disks. Our model predicts that galaxy sizes behave qualitatively differently before and after disk formation: after disks form, sizes are governed by the halo spin, in agreement with classical models, whereas before disk formation, sizes are larger and set by the scale on which turbulent motions, which dominate over rotation, can be contained. We validate our model against the results of the TNG50 cosmological simulation and, despite the simplicity of the model, find remarkable agreement. In particular, our model explains the increase with redshift in the critical halo mass for disk formation, reported in both simulations and observations, as a consequence of the evolution of the halo mass-concentration and baryonic mass-halo mass relations. This redshift trend therefore supports the recent proposal that it is the steepening of the gravitational potential that causes disk formation, while other effects discussed in the literature, such as potential deepening and hot gaseous halo formation, can still play important roles in the transition from early turbulent to dynamically cold disks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.04950v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vadim A. Semenov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Abundant hydrocarbons in a buried galactic nucleus with signs of carbonaceous grain and polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon processing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04967</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.04967v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hydrocarbons play a key role in shaping the chemistry of the interstellar medium (ISM), but their enrichment and relationship with carbonaceous grains and polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) still lack clear observational constraints. We report JWST NIRSpec+MIRI/MRS infrared (IR; 3-28 micron) observations of the local ultra-luminous IR galaxy (ULIRG) IRAS 07251-0248, revealing the extragalactic detection of small gas-phase hydrocarbons such as benzene (C$_6$H$_6$), triacetylene (C$_6$H$_2$), diacetylene (C$_4$H$_2$), acetylene (C$_2$H$_2$), methane (CH$_4$), and methyl radical (CH$_3$) as well as deep amorphous C-H absorptions in the solid phase. The unexpectedly high abundance of these molecules indicates an extremely rich hydrocarbon chemistry, not explained by high-temperature gas-phase chemistry, ice desorption or oxygen depletion. Instead, the most plausible explanation is the erosion and fragmentation of carbonaceous grains and PAHs. This scenario is supported by the correlation between the abundance of one of their main fragmentation products, C$_2$H$_2$, and cosmic ray (CR) ionization rate for a sample of local ULIRGs. These hydrocarbons are outflowing at $\sim$160 km/s, which may represent a potential formation pathway for hydrogenated amorphous grains. Our results suggest that IRAS 07251-0248 might not be unique but represents an extreme example of the commonly rich hydrocarbon chemistry prevalent in deeply obscured galactic nuclei.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.04967v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41550-025-02750-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>I. Garc\'ia-Bernete (Centro de Astrobiolog\'ia), M. Pereira-Santaella (Instituto de F\'isica Fundamental), E. Gonz\'alez-Alfonso (Departamento de F\'isica y Matem\'aticas, Universidad de Alcal\'a), M. Ag\'undez (Instituto de F\'isica Fundamental), D. Rigopoulou (Department of Physics, University of Oxford, School of Sciences, European University Cyprus), F. R. Donnan (Department of Physics, University of Oxford), G. Speranza (Instituto de F\'isica Fundamental), N. Thatte (Department of Physics, University of Oxford)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ASPIRE: The Environments and Dark Matter Halos of Luminous Quasars in the Epoch of Reionization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.04979v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a systematic study of the environments of 25 luminous quasars at $z &gt; 6.5$ from the ASPIRE program. Using JWST/NIRCam WFSS data, we identified 487 galaxies at $5.3 \lesssim z \lesssim 7.0$ exhibiting [OIII] emission. Among these, 122 [OIII] emitters lie within $|\Delta v_{\rm los}| &lt; 1000~{\rm km~s^{-1}}$ of the quasars, corresponding to a $\sim9.4$-fold enhancement relative to the average galaxy density at other redshifts. Furthermore, we identified 16 [CII]-emitting galaxies at the quasar redshifts from ALMA mosaic observations. A cross-correlation function (CCF) analysis between quasars and [OIII]+[CII] emitters yields a cross-correlation length of $r_0^{\rm QG} = 8.68^{+0.51}_{-0.55}~h^{-1}~\mathrm{cMpc}$ and a auto-correlation of $r_0^{\rm{QQ}}=15.76^{+2.48}_{-2.70}~h^{-1}~{\rm cMpc}$, indicating that $z \sim 7$ quasars reside in dark matter halos with $M_{\rm halo} = 10^{12.27^{+0.21}_{-0.26}}~M_\odot$. Notably, the number of [OIII]-emitting galaxies at quasar redshifts varies significantly from field to field, ranging from zero to twenty, highlighting a diverse quasar environment. Remarkably, seven quasars trace significant galaxy overdensities (i.e., protoclusters), with $\delta_{\rm gal} &gt; 5$ within a volume of $V \sim 500~{\rm cMpc^3}$. We also find that $|\Delta v_{\rm los}|$ increases rapidly toward smaller galaxy-quasar separations in protocluster fields, consistent with galaxy kinematics around extremely massive halos in cosmological simulations. By combining JWST and ALMA data, we reveal the complex and diverse environments of these early quasars, providing robust evidence that the earliest luminous quasars are effective tracers of galaxy overdensities, albeit with substantial field-to-field variation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.04979v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Feige Wang, Jaclyn B. Champagne, Jiamu Huang, Jinyi Yang, Joseph F. Hennawi, Xiaohui Fan, Haowen Zhang, Tiago Costa, Roberto Decarli, Melanie Habouzit, Fengwu Sun, Eduardo Banados, Xiangyu Jin, Koki Kakiichi, Romain A. Meyer, Yunjing Wu, Silvia Belladitta, Laura Blecha, Sarah E. I. Bosman, Zheng Cai, Thomas Connor, Frederick B. Davies, Anna-Christina Eilers, Zoltan Haiman, Hyunsung D. Jun, Mingyu Li, Zihao Li, Weizhe Liu, Alessandro Lupi, Jianwei Lyu, Chiara Mazzucchelli, Masafusa Onoue, Maria Pudoka, Sofia Rojas-Ruiz, Jan-Torge Schindler, Yue Shen, Wei Leong Tee, Benny Trakhtenbrot, Maxime Trebitsch, Marianne Vestergaard, Marta Volonteri, Fabian Walter, Huanian Zhang, Siwei Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suppression of Gravitational-Wave Echoes in Diffeomorphism-Invariant Nonlocal Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.04996v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Searches for late--time gravitational--wave echoes following compact binary mergers are often interpreted as probes of exotic near--horizon or horizonless physics. We show that a well--motivated class of ultraviolet--finite quantum gravity and modified gravity theories, those based on diffeomorphism--invariant, analytic, entire--function nonlocality, generically suppress observable echo signals. The suppression follows from Paley--Wiener bounds associated with the analyticity of the nonlocal regulator, which enforce exponential damping of high--frequency reflection amplitudes and smear sharp effective potentials in the black--hole interior. We demonstrate that for regular black holes with horizons, the standard ingoing boundary condition eliminates the cavity required for echoes, while for regular horizonless compact objects the nonlocal kernel strongly attenuates both inner and photon--sphere reflections. As a result, repeated reflections during the ringdown phase are exponentially suppressed in frequency space and washed out in the time domain. Our results imply that the absence of echoes in current gravitational--wave data is consistent with covariant nonlocal gravity theories and does not, by itself, favor classical horizons over regular or horizonless ultraviolet completions. The analyticity and Paley--Wiener bounds that enforce echo suppression are required to ensure unitarity, ghost freedom, and ultraviolet finiteness of the underlying quantum theory. As a result, the classical ringdown phenomenology already encodes quantum--gravity consistency conditions. We emphasize that the absence of echoes in such theories does not rely on quantum decoherence or stochastic effects, but instead reflects the analytic structure imposed by quantum gravity on the classical limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.04996v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. W. Moffat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating first-order phase transition during inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05501v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ending the inflation by vacuum decay is considered infeasible due to the graceful exit problem. Even if considering an alternative field other than the inflaton to realize a first-order phase transition (FoPT) during inflation, it is usually challenging for concrete model building, as bubble nucleations might not be fast and dense enough to successfully end the inflation. In this work, we propose a FoPT at the grand-unification-theory (GUT) scale within the Starobinsky inflation. The key construction is an exponentially evolving potential barrier dynamically controlled by the rolling inflaton, so that almost no bubble is nucleated during the early inflationary era, but with massive bubble nucleations near the end of inflation. With lattice numerical simulations, we have successfully tested this GUT-FoPT during Starobinsky inflation, and the resulting gravitational-wave energy density spectrum reproduces previous analytical estimation with a distinctive oscillation feature at high frequencies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05501v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jintao Zou, Ligong Bian, Shao-Jiang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Induced-Gravity Higgs Inflation in Palatini Supergravity Confronts ACT DR6</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05623</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05623v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We formulate within Palatini Supergravity a model of induced-gravity inflation excellently consistent with ACT DR6. The inflaton belongs in the decomposition of a conjugate pair of Higgs superfields which lead to the spontaneous breaking of a U(1)B-L symmetry at a scale close to the range (0.102-5.85)x10^16 GeV. The inflaton field is canonically normalized thanks to a real and shift-symmetric contribution into the Kaehler potential. It also includes two separate holomorphic and antiholomorphic logarithmic terms, the argument of which can be interpreted as the coupling of the inflaton to the Ricci scalar. The attainment of inflation allows for subplanckian inflaton values and energy scales below the cut-off scale of the corresponding effective theory. Embedding the model in a B-L extension of the MSSM we show how the mu parameter can be generated and non-thermal leptogenesis can be successfully realized. An outcome of our scheme is split SUSY with gravitino mass in the range (40-60) PeV, which is consistent with the results of LHC on the Higgs boson mass.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05623v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Pallis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting gravitational wave background with equivalent configurations in the network of space based optical lattice clocks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05714</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05714v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The network of space based optical lattice clocks (OLCs) has been proposed to detect the stochastic gravitational wave background. We investigate the overlap reduction function (ORF) of the OLC detector network and analytically derive a transformation that leaves the ORF invariant. This transformation is applicable to configurations with two OLC detectors, each equipped with a one-way link. It can map a configuration with small separation and high noise correlation to another configuration with larger separation and reduced noise correlation. Using this transformation, we obtain a favourable OLC detector network configuration with high cross-correlation response, and compare its sensitivity to that of space-based laser interferometer gravitational wave detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05714v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingzhi Lou, Hong Su, Tao Yang, Yun-Long Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Early-universe constraints on the electron mass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05720v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the impact of a nonstandard electron mass $m_e$ on early-Universe thermal history, focusing on neutrino decoupling and Big Bang Nucleosynthesis (BBN). In the standard cosmology, neutrino--electron interactions keep neutrinos in thermal contact with the electromagnetic plasma until shortly before $e^\pm$ annihilation. Varying $m_e$ shifts the decoupling epoch and the entropy transfer from $e^\pm$ annihilation, thereby modifying the neutrino energy density and the inferred effective number of relativistic species, $N_{\mathrm{eff}}$. Independently, during BBN the rates of charged-current weak processes, and hence the neutron-to-proton ratio, depend on $m_e$. By confronting BBN predictions for the primordial light-element abundances with observations and imposing cosmological constraints on $N_{\mathrm{eff}}$, we obtain a bound on $m_e$ in the early Universe of $m_e = 0.504^{+0.007}_{-0.006}$ MeV or $m_e=0.510\pm0.007$ MeV ($1\sigma$), depending on the considered nuclear reaction network (NACRE II or PRIMAT, respectively). The allowed range is close to the present laboratory value at the level of 1.4\%, thus supporting the constancy of the electron mass over cosmological timescales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05720v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michela Garramone, Stefano Gariazzo, Nicolao Fornengo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Foreground removal and 21 cm signal estimates: comparing different blind methods for the BINGO Telescope</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.11701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.11701v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The BINGO radiotelescope will observe hydrogen distribution using Intensity Mapping (IM) to analyze the Dark Energy paradigm through Baryon Acoustic Oscillations. The target signal is contaminated by unwanted signals and instrumental noise, making accurate estimations essential for characterizing the 21 cm signal. In this study, we evaluated the performance of three blind foreground-removing algorithms - FastICA, GNILC, and GMCA - on the BINGO pipeline. Each method used different approaches to estimate foreground contributions, and we also investigated how the number of simulations for debiasing affects estimation quality. Our findings indicate that using 50 or 400 simulations yields equivalent results at this stage of analysis. All algorithms produced statistically consistent estimates of the 21 cm signal. We used FastICA for estimating and debiasing the HI spectra from five years of observations, which yielded reliable results, although the first channel was affected by edge effects from the mixing matrix. The overall signal-to-noise ratio was 204, and the chi-squared value was 1.8.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.11701v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Marins, Filipe B. Abdalla, Elcio Abdalla, Chang Feng, Luiza O. Ponte, Giancarlo de Gasperis, Luiz H. F. Assis, Mathieu Remazeilles, Carlos A. Wuensche, Luciano Barosi, Edmar C. Gurjao, Thyrso Villela, Bin Wang, Jiajun Zhang, Ricardo Landim, Vincenzo Liccardo, Camila P. Novaes, Amilcar R. Queiroz, Larissa Santos, Marcelo V. dos Santos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of Interacting Dark Energy on the Growth of Matter Density Perturbations: Observational Constraints from DESI and Multi-Probe Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05208v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the impact of a non-gravitational interaction between dark matter and dark energy on the growth rate of matter density perturbations within the framework of a $w$CDM scenario, where the coupling is proportional to the dark energy density. To incorporate the effects of this interaction in cosmological analysis, we develop a parameterization for the growth rate based on a second-order approximation for the growth index $\gamma$ that explicitly includes the coupling constant $\alpha$. This formalism reveals a theoretical degeneracy: the coupling induces a correction $\Delta\gamma \simeq 1.1\alpha$, allowing an interacting dark energy model to mimic the growth index predicted by certain modified gravity theories. We confront the model with the latest multi-probe observations, including the Pantheon+ sample of Type~Ia supernovae, Baryon Acoustic Oscillation (BAO) data from the Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS) and the second data release (DR2) of the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI), Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) measurements, Hubble parameter $H(z)$ data, and redshift-space distortion (RSD) measurements, to simultaneously constrain the coupling strength $\alpha$ and the dark energy equation of state $w$. Our analysis finds $\alpha$ consistent with zero and $w$ with $-1$ at the $1\sigma$ confidence level, showing no statistical evidence for a departure from the standard $\Lambda$CDM cosmology. The observational constraints effectively break the theoretical degeneracy with modified gravity, limiting the possible interaction-induced shift in the growth index to $|\Delta\gamma|\lesssim 0.03$ ($3\sigma$). This establishes the growth index as a robust diagnostic for distinguishing between a non-minimal interaction in the dark sector and a genuine modification of gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05208v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fan Yang, Rongrong Zhai, Xiangyun Fu, Bing Xu, Kaiwen Liu, Chikun Ding, Yang Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stabilizing simulation-based cosmological Fisher forecasts: a case study using the Voronoi volume function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16408</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16408v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Forecasting cosmological constraints from halo-based statistics often suffers from instability in derivative estimates, especially when the number of simulations is limited. This instability reduces the reliability of Fisher forecasts and machine learning based approaches that use derivatives. We introduce a general framework that addresses this challenge by stabilizing the input statistic and then systematically identifying the optimal subset of summary statistics that maximizes cosmological information while simultaneously minimizing the instability of predicted constraints. We demonstrate this framework using the halo mass function as well as the Voronoi volume function (VVF), a summary statistic that captures beyond two-point clustering information. Applying our two-step procedure -- random sub-sampling followed by optimization -- improves the constraining power by up to a factor of 4, while also enhancing the stability of the forecasts across realizations. As surveys like Euclid, DESI, and LSST push toward tighter constraints, the ability to produce stable and accurate theoretical predictions is essential. Our results suggest that new summary statistics such as the VVF, combined with careful data curation and stabilization strategies, can play a key role in next-generation precision cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16408v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saee Dhawalikar (IUCAA), Aseem Paranjape (IUCAA), Shadab Alam (TIFR)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phantom crossing or dark interaction?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18274v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent results from DESI BAO measurements, together with Planck CMB and Pantheon+ data, suggest that there may be a `phantom' phase ($w_{\rm de}&lt;-1$) in the expansion of the Universe. This inference follows when the $w_0, w_a$ parametrization for the dark energy equation of state $w_{\rm de}$ is used to fit the data. Since phantom dark energy in general relativity is unphysical, we investigate the possibility that the phantom behaviour is not intrinsic, but effective -- due to a non-gravitational interaction between dark matter and non-phantom dark energy. To this end, we assume a physically motivated thawing quintessence-like form of the intrinsic dark energy equation of state $w_{\rm de}$. Then we use a $w_0, w_a$ model for the \emph{effective} equation of state of dark energy. We find that the data favours a phantom crossing for the effective dark energy, but only at low significance. The intrinsic equation of state of dark energy is non-phantom, without imposing any non-phantom priors. A nonzero interaction is favoured at more than $3\sigma$ at $z\sim0.3$. The energy flows from dark matter to dark energy at early times and reverses at later times.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18274v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2026/01/062</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP01(2026)062</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>S\^ecloka L. Guedezounme, Bikash R. Dinda, Roy Maartens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Wave Spectral Shapes as a probe of Long Lived Right-handed Neutrinos, Leptogenesis and Dark Matter: Global versus Local B-L Cosmic Strings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01779</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01779v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The scale of the seesaw mechanism is typically much larger than the electroweak scale. This hierarchy can be naturally explained by $U(1)_{B-L}$ symmetry, which after spontaneous symmetry breaking, simultaneously generates Majorana masses for neutrinos and produces a network of cosmic strings. Such strings generate a gravitational wave (GW) spectrum which is expected to be almost uniform in frequency unless there is a departure from the usual early radiation domination. We explore this possibility in Type I, II and III seesaw frameworks, finding that only for Type-I, long-lived right-handed neutrinos (RHN) may provide a period of early matter domination for parts of the parameter space, even if they are thermally produced. Such a period leaves distinctive imprints in the GW spectrum in the form of characteristic breaks and a knee feature, arising due to the end and start of the periods of RHN domination. These features, if detected, directly determine the mass $M$, and effective neutrino mass $\tilde m$ of the dominating RHN. We find that GW detectors like LISA and ET could probe RHN masses in the range $M\in[0.1,10^{9}]$ GeV and effective neutrino masses in the $\tilde m\in[10^{-10},10^{-8}]$ eV range. We investigate the phenomenological implications of long-lived right-handed neutrinos for both local and global $U(1)_{B-L}$ strings, focusing on dark matter production and leptogenesis. We map the viable and detectable parameter space for successful baryogenesis and asymmetric dark matter production from right-handed neutrino decays. We derive analytical and semi-analytical relations correlating the characteristic gravitational-wave frequencies to the neutrino parameters $\tilde m$ and $M$, as well as to the relic abundances of dark matter and baryons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01779v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Satyabrata Datta, Anish Ghoshal, Angus Spalding, Graham White</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large-Scale Galaxy Correlations from the DESI First Data Release</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21585</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21585v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We quantify galaxy correlations using two distinct three-dimensional samples from the first data release of the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI): the Bright Galaxy Sample (BGS) and the Luminous Red Galaxy Sample (LRGS). Specifically, we measure the conditional average density, defined as the average density of galaxies observed around a typical galaxy in the sample. To minimize boundary effects, we adopt a conservative criterion: only galaxies for which a spherical volume of radius $r$, centered on them, is fully contained within the survey footprint are included in the computation. For the BGS, we construct four volume-limited subsamples in order to eliminate biases arising from luminosity-dependent selection effects. By contrast, the LRGS is approximately volume-limited by design. The resulting samples span different depths, providing an opportunity to test the stability of statistical measurements across survey volumes of increasing size. Our results show that the conditional average density follows a power-law decay, $\langle n(r) \rangle \propto r^{-0.8}$, without exhibiting any transition to homogeneity within the survey volume. The large statistics of the DESI samples also allow us to demonstrate that finite-size effects become significant as $r$ approaches the boundaries of the sample volumes. Consistently, we find that the distribution of density fluctuations follows a Gumbel distribution - characteristic of extreme-value statistics - rather than a Gaussian distribution, which would be expected for a spatially homogeneous field. These findings confirm and extend the trends previously observed in smaller redshift surveys, supporting the conclusion that the galaxy distribution does not undergo a transition to spatial homogeneity within the probed scales, up to $r \sim 400$~\text{Mpc}/$h$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21585v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Sylos Labini, Tibor Antal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The spectrum of $n_s$ constraints from DESI and CMB data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05108</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05108v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the spectrum of $n_s$ constraints from current CMB data (Planck, ACT, SPT-3G) combined with DESI BAO data, and highlight the interplay of $n_s$ with the optical depth to reionization $\tau$. The spectral index $n_s$ of the primordial power spectrum provides a window into early universe, and constraints on $n_s$ play an important role in discriminating early universe models such as models of cosmic inflation. Historically constrained by cosmic microwave background (CMB) experiments, the constraints on $n_s$ shift upward when CMB data is combined with the latest baryon acoustic oscillation (BAO) data from the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI). Recent work explained the origin of this and the relation to the BAO-CMB tension between CMB experiments and DESI BAO, and as a case study presented constraints on $n_s$ from the combination of Atacama Cosmology Telescope (ACT) DR6 data and DESI DR2 data. Here we present constraints from Planck (PR3 and PR4), ACT, the South Pole Telescope (SPT), and the combination of all three CMB experiments, CMB-SPA, with and without DESI DR2 BAO data, and with and without CMB lensing data. In all cases the constraint on $n_s$ is shifted upwards when DESI is included, with the largest shift exhibited by ACT. This is accompanied by a commensurate shift in the constraint on the optical depth to reionization $\tau$, which is again greatest for ACT. When CMB data are combined into CMB-SPA and combined with DESI the $n_s$ constraint disfavors at more than $2\sigma$ the inflation models preferred by Planck alone, such as Higgs, Starobinsky, and exponential $\alpha$-attractors, in favor of other models, such as polynomial $\alpha$-attractors. This work motivates the further study of the tension between CMB and DESI BAO data, and of the rich interplay between $n_s$ and $\tau$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05108v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evan McDonough, Elisa G. M. Ferreira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The FLAMINGO Project: Exploring the X-ray--cosmic-shear cross-correlation as a probe of large-scale structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.02484</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.02484v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Baryonic feedback processes associated with galaxy formation directly influence the large-scale structure by redistributing gas. Recent measurements of the kinetic Sunyaev-Zel'dovich effect and stacks of X-ray emission from optically selected galaxy clusters suggest that feedback from Active Galactic Nuclei (AGN) is more efficient at expelling gas from low-mass clusters than previously thought. The measurement of the cross-correlation between cosmic shear and diffuse X-ray emission provides a new probe of the distribution of gas in groups and clusters. We use the FLAMINGO cosmological, hydrodynamical simulations to examine the X-ray--cosmic-shear cross-correlation. The cross-correlation is most sensitive to the distribution of gas in haloes with masses $10^{14}\leq M_{200\mathrm{c}}/\mathrm{M}_{\odot}\leq10^{15}$. It is sensitive to the strength of feedback, but the effects of variations in cosmology and baryonic physics are largely degenerate. We compare the FLAMINGO predictions with the cross-correlation between cosmic shear from the Dark Energy Survey and ROSAT all-sky X-ray maps. We find that, if we neglect the X-ray emission from AGN that would remain unresolved by ROSAT, then the fiducial FLAMINGO model is in excellent agreement with the data, while models with stronger or weaker feedback are ruled out. However, if we account for unresolved AGN, either using the direct FLAMINGO predictions or by abundance matching to the observed (extrapolated) AGN luminosity function, then models with stronger feedback are preferred. We conclude that to exploit the potential of the X-ray--lensing cross-correlation, it will be necessary to resolve fainter AGN, and to use external constraints to break the degeneracy between baryonic feedback and cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.02484v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William McDonald, Joop Schaye, Konrad Kuijken, John Helly, Joey Braspenning, Matthieu Schaller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An emulator for the ionizing photon mean free path in ultra-high resolution simulations: the implications of mean free path measurements for the reionization history</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.03923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.03923v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Measurements of the mean free path of ionizing photons from high-redshift quasar spectra at $z \sim 5$-$6$ constrain the reionization history, but interpreting them requires modeling the kiloparsec-scale clumping that large-volume reionization simulations cannot resolve. We present a deep learning emulator for the mean free path (MFP) trained on high-resolution cosmological radiative transfer simulations of ionization fronts sweeping through small 2 comoving~Mpc/h volumes. Using a residual multi-layer perceptron neural network, we predict the MFP at a given redshift as a function of the reionization redshift, photoionization rate, wavelength, and box-scale density, achieving a median relative error of 1.6\% across nearly four orders of magnitude in MFP. Integrating its predictions over box-scale overdensity and an extended reionization history allows the emulator to predict the global MFP. We apply the emulator to extended reionization histories constrained by observed photoionization rates, finding that models prefer late reionization with substantial neutral fractions persisting at $z \lesssim 6$. Fitting a parametric ionization history yields a midpoint of reionization of $z_{\rm re} = 6.8\pm 1.2$ for reionization durations consistent with Planck and kinetic Sunyaev-Zeldovich constraints, and the universe being $10\%$ neutral still at $z_{\rm re} &lt; 5.8 ~(6.3)$ at 1~(2)$\sigma$. Global ionizing emissivity inferences using measurements of the photoionization rate and MFP plus our emulator, which avoids common power-law assumptions, suggest a factor of $2-3$ decline between $z = 6$ and $4.8$, in agreement with previous studies. Our method provides an efficient (and more converged) alternative to large-volume radiative-hydrodynamic simulations of reionization for interpreting MFP measurements, and can also serve as a subgrid prescription for the ionizing opacity within such simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.03923v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hurum Maksora Tohfa, Christopher Cain, Matthew McQuinn, Anson D'Aloisio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Waves from Feebly Interacting Particles in a First Order Phase Transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.06405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.06405v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: First order phase transitions are well-motivated and extensively studied sources of gravitational waves (GWs) from the early Universe. The vacuum energy released during such transitions is assumed to be transferred primarily either to the expanding bubble walls, whose collisions source GWs, or to the surrounding plasma, producing sound waves and turbulence, which source GWs. In this Letter, we study an alternative possibility that has not yet been considered: the released energy gets transferred primarily to feebly interacting particles that do not form a coherent interacting plasma but simply free-stream individually. We develop the formalism to study the production of GWs from such configurations, and demonstrate that such GW signals have qualitatively distinct characteristics compared to conventional sources and are potentially observable with near-future GW detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.06405v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryusuke Jinno, Bibhushan Shakya, Jorinde van de Vis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital eccentricity in a neutron star - black hole binary merger</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15393</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15393v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The observation of gravitational waves from merging black holes and neutron stars provides a unique opportunity to discern information about their astrophysical environment. Two signatures that are considered powerful tracers to distinguish between different binary formation channels are general-relativistic spin-induced orbital precession and orbital eccentricity. Both effects leave characteristic imprints in the gravitational-wave signal that can be extracted from observations. To date, neither precession nor eccentricity have been confidently discerned in merging neutron star -- black hole binaries. Here we report the measurement of orbital eccentricity in a neutron star -- black hole merger. Using, for the first time, a waveform model that incorporates precession and eccentricity, we perform Bayesian inference on the gravitational-wave event GW200105 (R. Abbott et al. 2021a) and infer a median orbital eccentricity of $e_{20}\sim 0.145$ at an orbital period of 0.1s, ruling out eccentricities smaller than 0.028 with 99.5% confidence. We find inconclusive evidence for the presence of precession, consistent with previous, non-eccentric results, but a more unequal mass ratio. Our result implies a fraction of these binaries will exhibit orbital eccentricity even at small separations, suggesting formation through mechanisms involving dynamical interactions beyond isolated binary evolution. Future observations will reveal the contribution of eccentric neutron star -- black hole binaries to the total merger rate across cosmic time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15393v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gonzalo Morras, Geraint Pratten, Patricia Schmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Importance of Shot Noise in the Search for an Isotropic Stochastic Gravitational-Wave Background with Next Generation Detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.15014v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the impact of shot noise on the stochastic gravitational wave background generated by binary neutron star mergers, and confirm that the overall background can be significantly influenced by relatively few neighboring, loud events. To mitigate the shot noise, we propose a procedure to remove nearby events by notching them out in the time-frequency domain. Additionally, we quantify the cosmic/sample variance of the resulting background after notching, and we study the deviation between the cross-correlation measurement and the theoretical prediction of the background. Taking both effects into account, we find that the resulting sensitivity loss in the search for an isotropic background formed by binary neutron star mergers is minimal, and is limited to $\lesssim 4\%$ below 40 Hz, and to $\lesssim 1\%$ above 40 Hz.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.15014v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haowen Zhong, Vuk Mandic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gauge Dependence of Scalar-Induced Gravitational Waves from Isocurvature Perturbations: Analytical Results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07252v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We analytically study the gauge dependence of scalar-induced gravitational waves (SIGWs) sourced by primordial isocurvature perturbations during radiation domination (RD), working across nine gauges. Through analytical integrations of the kernels supported by graphical comparison we identify a clear dichotomy. We find that in some gauges viz. the uniform-density (UD), total-matter (TM), uniform-curvature (UC), comoving-orthogonal (CO) and transverse-traceless (TT) gauges the energy density grows polynomially in conformal time $\eta^n$, where $n$ varies from $2$ to $8$. While in rest of the gauges viz. the longitudinal (Long.), uniform-expansion (UE), Newtonian-motion (Nm), and N-body (Nb) gauges the late-time energy spectrum converges, and SIGWs behave as radiation. For subhorizon modes ($ k\eta \gg 1 $), the divergence becomes severe, showing that SIGWs are gauge-dependent observables in this regime. We resolve it through a kernel projection that isolates the luminal, freely propagating gravitational wave components (oscillating as $\sin(k\eta)$ and $\cos(k\eta)$), eliminating spurious contributions. The resulting kernel decays as $ (k\eta)^{-1} $ and yields a finite, gauge-independent late-time spectrum, confirming that only luminal modes represent physical SIGWs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07252v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/tby4-thbh</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Arshad Ali, Yang Lei, Mudassar Sabir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WIMP Freeze-out dynamics under Tsallis statistics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16487</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16487v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We generalize thermal WIMP (Weakly Interacting Massive Particle) freeze-out within Tsallis nonextensive statistics. Using Curado-Tsallis $q$-distributions $f_q(E;\mu,T)$ we compute $q$-deformed number and energy densities, pressure, entropy density and Hubble rate, $\{n_q,\rho_q,P_q,s_q,H_q\}$. The Boltzmann equation is generalized accordingly to obtain the comoving abundance $Y_{\chi,q}(x)$ and relic density $\Omega_{\chi,q}h^2$ for a dark-matter candidate $\chi$ in a model-independent setup. The thermally averaged cross section is expanded as $\langle\sigma v\rangle_q \approx a + b\,\langle v_{\rm rel}^2\rangle_q$ up to $p$-wave. The freeze-out parameter $x_f(q)$ is determined from $\Gamma_{{\rm ann},q}(T_f)\simeq H_q(T_f)$ using a $q$-logarithmic inversion, with the expansion rate modified through ultra-relativistic rescalings $R_\rho(q)$ of the effective relativistic degrees of freedom $g_*$ and $g_{*s}$. We show that $x_f$ increases with $q$ and that QCD-threshold features propagate into $Y_{\chi,q}(x)$ and $\Omega_{\chi,q}h^2$. We then perform two $q$-grid scans: fixing $\langle\sigma v\rangle_q$ while varying the dark-matter mass $m_\chi$, and fixing $m_\chi$ while varying the $s$-wave coefficient $a$. For an $s$-wave dominated scenario we construct $\chi^2$ profiles in these planes by comparing $\Omega_{\chi,q}h^2$ with the Planck benchmark $\Omega_c h^2 = 0.120\pm 0.001$. In both cases we find a clear degeneracy in the preferred nonextensive parameter $q_{\rm best}$ along valleys in parameter space. However, fixed-mass scans (varying $\langle\sigma v\rangle_q$) are significantly more constraining than fixed-cross-section scans, reflecting that $\Omega_{\chi,q}h^2$ is mainly controlled by $\langle\sigma v\rangle_q$, so that for realistic cross sections the best-fit $q_{\rm best}$ remains close to the extensive limit $q\to 1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16487v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.dark.2026.102241</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physics of the Dark Universe Volume 52, June 2026, 102241</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Matias P. Gonzalez, Roberto A. Lineros</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Misalignment dynamics of Scalar Condensates with Yukawa coupling: Particle and Entropy Production</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22465</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22465v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Misalignment dynamics, the non-equilibrium evolution of a scalar (or pseudoscalar) condensate in a potential landscape, broadly describes a solution to the strong CP problem, a mechanism for cold dark matter production and (pre) reheating post inflation. Often, radiative corrections are included phenomenologically by replacing the potential by the effective potential which is a \emph{static quantity}, its usefulness is restricted to (near) equilibrium situations. We study the misalignment dynamics of a scalar condensate Yukawa coupled to $N_f$ fermions in a manifestly energy conserving, fully renormalized Hamiltonian framework. A large $N_f$ limit allows us to focus on the fermion degrees of freedom, which yield a negative contribution to the effective potential, a radiatively induced instability and ultraviolet divergent field renormalization. We introduce an adiabatic basis and an adiabatic expansion that embodies the derivative expansion in the effective action, the zeroth order is identified with the effective potential, higher orders account for the derivative expansion including field renormalization and describe profuse particle production. Energy conserving dynamics leads to the conjecture of emergent asymptotic highly excited stationary states with a distribution function $n_k(\infty)\propto 1/k^6$ and an extensive entropy which is identified with an entanglement entropy. Subtle aspects of renormalization associated with the initial value problem are analyzed and resolved. Possible new manifestations of asymptotic spontaneous symmetry breaking (SSB) as a consequence of the dynamics even in absence of tree level (SSB), and cosmological inferences are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22465v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/hrhp-kcwj</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 113, 043503 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nathan Herring, Daniel Boyanovsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Active Galaxy Cluster Merger at Cosmic Noon Revealed by JWST Weak Lensing and Multiwavelength Probes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.11022v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The galaxy cluster XLSSC~122 is a rare system at $z = 1.98$, hosting surprisingly evolved member galaxies when the Universe was only one-third of its present age. Leveraging deep JWST/NIRCam imaging, we perform a weak-lensing analysis and reconstruct the cluster's mass distribution, finding a mass peak that coincides with both the X-ray peak and the position of the brightest cluster galaxy. We obtain a mass estimate of $M_{200\rm c}=1.6 \pm 0.3\times 10^{14}~M_{\odot}$ and a concentration of $c_{200 \rm c}=6.3 \pm 0.3$ implied by the preferred concentration--mass relation, in agreement with recent strong-lensing estimates. The high concentration in particular motivates tests against empirical and simulation-derived concentration--mass relations. Placing our weak-lensing mass map in the context of Chandra X-ray data, MeerKAT radio imaging, ALMA+ACA/ACT Sunyaev-Zel'dovich (SZ) mapping, and new JWST intracluster light measurements, we identify consistent NE--SW elongation across datasets and a pronounced offset along the same axis between the SZ and mass/X-ray peaks, pointing to significant merger activity. XLSSC~122 thus serves as a JWST pilot study for high-$z$ lensing, demonstrating the telescope's unique ability to map cluster mass distributions at $z\sim 2$ and motivating a uniform sample of analogous systems with joint lensing, X-ray, SZ, and radio data to probe cluster assembly at cosmic noon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.11022v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zachary P. Scofield, Kyle Finner, Hyungjin Joo, M. James Jee, Wonki Lee, Sangjun Cha, Jinhyub Kim, Yu-Heng Lin, Ranga-Ram Chary, Andreas Faisst, Bomee Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast rotations in galaxies at cosmic noon indicate central concentration of stars, dark matter or massive black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.03338v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The rotation curves of regularly rotating disc galaxies are a unique probe of the gravitational potential and dark matter distribution. Until recently, matter decomposition of rotation curves at $z&gt;0.5$ was challenging, not only due to the lack of high resolution kinematic data but also of both suitable photometry to accurately trace the stellar surface density and spatially-resolved sub-mm observations to trace the cold gas distribution. In this paper, we analyse three galaxies from the Archival Large Program to Advance Kinematic Analysis (ALPAKA) sample, combining highly resolved cold gas observations from ALMA with rest-frame near-infrared imaging from JWST to investigate their dynamical properties and constrain their dark matter halos. The galaxies, initially classified as regularly rotating discs based on ALMA observations alone, appear in JWST as extended and symmetric stellar discs with spiral arms. Our dynamical models reproduce the rotation of the discs in the outer parts well, but they systematically underpredict the inner rotation velocities, revealing a deficit of central mass relative to the data. This discrepancy indicates either an underestimation of the bulge masses due to variations in the stellar mass-to-light ratio or dust attenuation or the presence of overmassive black holes. Alternatively, it may suggest departures from standard dark-matter halo profiles, including enhanced central concentrations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.03338v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fernanda Roman-Oliveira, Francesca Rizzo, Filippo Fraternali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prompt cusps in hierarchical dark matter halos: Implications for annihilation boost</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19863</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.19863v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent simulations have identified long-lived ``prompt cusps'' --  compact remnants of early density peaks with inner profiles $\rho\propto r^{-3/2}$. They can survive hierarchical assembly and potentially enhance signals of dark matter annihilation. In this work, we incorporate prompt cusps into the semi-analytic substructure framework SASHIMI, enabling a fully hierarchical, environment-dependent calculation of the annihilation luminosity that consistently tracks subhalos, sub-subhalos, and tidal stripping. We assign prompt cusps to first-generation microhalos and propagate their survival through the merger history, including an explicit treatment of cusps associated with stripped substructure. We find that the substructure hierarchy converges rapidly once a few levels are included, and that prompt cusps can raise the total annihilation boost of Milky-Way--size hosts at $z=0$ to $B\sim 50$ for fiducial cusp-occupation assumptions, compared to a subhalo-only baseline of $B_{\rm sh}\sim\mathrm{few}$. Across a wide range of host masses and redshifts, prompt cusps increase the normalization of $B(M_{\rm host},z)$ while largely preserving its mass and redshift trends. Compared to universal-average, peak-based estimates, our fiducial boosts are lower by about a factor of a few, primarily reflecting a correspondingly smaller inferred cusp abundance in host halos, highlighting the importance of unifying peak-based cusp formation with merger-tree evolution and environmental dependence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.19863v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shin'ichiro Ando, Martin Moro, Youyou Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
