<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO</link>
    <description>astro-ph.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 03:09:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>AMICO galaxy clusters in KiDS-1000: Splashback radius from weak lensing and cluster-galaxy correlation function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07114v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the splashback radius analysis of the Adaptive Matched Identifier of Clustered Objects (AMICO) galaxy cluster sample in the fourth data release of the Kilo Degree Survey (KiDS). The sample contains 9049 rich galaxy clusters within $z\in[0.1,0.8]$, with shear measurements available for 8730 of them. We measure and model the stacked reduced shear, $g_{\rm t}$, and the cluster-galaxy correlation function, $w_{\rm cg}$, in bins of observed intrinsic richness, $\lambda^*$, and redshift, $z$. Building on the methods employed in recent cosmological analyses, we model the average splashback radius, $r_{\rm sp}$, of the underlying dark matter halo distribution, accounting for the known systematic uncertainties affecting measurements and theoretical models. By modelling $g_{\rm t}$ and $w_{\rm cg}$ separately, in the cluster-centric radial range $R\in[0.4,5]$ $h^{-1}$Mpc, we constrain $r_{\rm sp}$, the mass accretion rate, $\Gamma$, and the relation between $\mathcal{R}_{\rm sp}\equiv r_{\rm sp}/r_{200\rm m}$ and the peak height, $\nu_{200\rm m}$, over the mass range $M_{200\rm m}\in[0.4,20]$ $10^{14}h^{-1}$M$_\odot$. The two probes provide consistent results that also agree with $\Lambda$-cold dark matter model predictions. Our $\mathcal{R}_{\rm sp}$ constraints are consistent with those from previous observations. For $g_{\rm t}$ and $w_{\rm cg}$, we achieve a precision of 14% and 10% per cluster stack, respectively. The higher precision of $w_{\rm cg}$, enabled by its combination with weak-lensing constraints on the mass-richness relation, highlights the complementarity of lensing and clustering in measuring $r_{\rm sp}$ and constraining the properties of the infalling material region.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07114v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. F. Lesci, C. Giocoli, F. Marulli, M. Romanello, L. Moscardini, M. Sereno, M. Maturi, M. Radovich, G. Castignani, H. Hildebrandt, L. Ingoglia, E. Puddu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A General Formulation of the Kinematic Dipole as a Functional of Selection and Source Properties: Beyond the Ellis--Baldwin Approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07389</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07389v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The dipole anisotropy in galaxy and QSO number counts induced by the motion of the observer (the kinematic dipole) provides an important test of cosmological isotropy and a comparison with the Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) dipole. Traditionally, the Ellis \&amp; Baldwin expression,$\mathcal{A}=2+x(1+\alpha)$, has been widely adopted, assuming power-law number counts and a single power-law spectral energy distribution (SED). Realistic surveys, however, involve a range of non-ideal effects, including diverse SEDs, finite instrumental bandpasses, non-power-law number counts, multi-band photometry and photo-$z$ selections, and direction-dependent or stochastic detection limits. In this paper, we incorporate these effects explicitly at the theoretical level and present a unified formulation of the kinematic dipole for a general parent population and a general multi-dimensional selection function. We show that the dipole amplitude is not described by a single index, but is instead given by a functional, $\mathcal{A}[\mathcal{W},f]$, defined as the Doppler response of the selection function acting on the underlying population. We demonstrate that the classical Ellis--Baldwin result is recovered as a special limiting case of this formalism, and clarify the relation between the theoretical coefficient $\mathcal{A}$ and the dipole vector estimated from finite catalogs, separating theoretical response from statistical uncertainty. This framework provides a basis for reinterpreting reported discrepancies in kinematic dipole measurements across surveys and is directly applicable to future wide-area, multi-band observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07389v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tsutomu T. Takeuchi (Nagoya University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prospective bounds on f(Q) gravity with pulsar timing arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07557</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07557v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Pulsar timing arrays (PTAs) have recently provided compelling evidence for a stochastic gravitational wave background (SGWB) in the nanohertz frequency band, offering a unique window into fundamental physics. Here, we explore implications for symmetric teleparallel $f(Q)$ gravity, a theory in which deviations from General Relativity (GR) arise through the non-metricity scalar $f(Q)$. Crucially, tensor modes propagate at the speed of light in this framework. However, their amplitude undergoes a modified damping during their evolution. We adopt a model-independent parameterization and derive an analytic approximation to the tensor mode transfer function to obtain the spectral energy density of primordial inflationary gravitational waves. Comparison with the NANOGrav 15-year and IPTA second data releases show that the inferred damping parameter $n$ remains consistent with GR, yet allows small deviations that could be observable. We then conduct a Fisher information matrix forecasts which demonstrate that the Square Kilometre Array (SKA) observatory will improve these constraints by several orders of magnitude, offering the potential to distinguish $f(Q)$ gravity from GR with high precision. These results highlight PTAs as powerful probes of non-metricity-based modifications to gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07557v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammadreza Davari, Alireza Allahyari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Wave Informed Inference of 21-cm Global Signal Parameters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07631v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding how and when the first stars and galaxies formed remains one of the central challenges in modern cosmology. These structures emerged during the transition from the Dark Ages to the Cosmic Dawn, a period that remains observationally unconstrained despite strong theoretical progress. During this epoch, neutral hydrogen absorbed a fraction of cosmic microwave background photons through its 21-cm hyperfine transition, producing a 21-cm absorption signal whose evolution encodes the early Universe's thermal and ionization history. However, extracting the underlying astrophysical parameters from this signal is limited by severe parameter degeneracies, which cannot be resolved without independent observational probes. The next-generation gravitational wave (GW) detectors, such as Cosmic Explorer (CE), will observe binary black hole (BBH) mergers up to very large redshifts and hence will detect a fraction of them formed within the redshift range $\sim 13-25$. The merger rate of these BBHs will depend on the star formation rate density (SFRD) at these redshifts, together with the BBH formation efficiency and a time delay distribution. Therefore, the merger rate of these BBHs can work as a tracer of the SFRD in the redshift range $\sim 13-25$. In this Letter, we establish a novel multi-messenger framework and present a proof-of-principle concept of how the observations of BBH mergers form next-generation GW detectors can improve the inference of parameters generating the 21-cm cosmic hydrogen signal, and help break degeneracies between them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07631v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Avinash Tiwari, Sajad A. Bhat, Tirthankar Roy Choudhury, Susmita Adhikari, Mukesh Kumar Singh, Shasvath J. Kapadia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmology with one galaxy: An analytic formula relating $\Omega_{\rm m}$ with galaxy properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07651</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07651v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Standard cosmological analyses typically treat galaxy formation and cosmological parameter inference as decoupled problems, relying on population-level statistics such as clustering, lensing, or halo abundances. However, classical studies of baryon fractions in massive galaxy clusters have long suggested that gravitationally bound systems may retain cosmological information through their baryonic content. Building on this insight, we present the first analytic and physically interpretable cosmological tracer that links the matter density parameter, $\Omega_m$, directly to intrinsic galaxy-scale observables, demonstrating that cosmological information can be extracted from individual galaxies. Using symbolic regression applied to state-of-the-art hydrodynamical simulations from the CAMELS project, we identify a compact functional form that robustly recovers $\Omega_m$ across multiple simulation suites (IllustrisTNG, ASTRID, SIMBA, and Swift-EAGLE), requiring only modest recalibration of a small number of coefficients. The resulting expression admits a transparent physical interpretation in terms of baryonic retention and enrichment efficiency regulated by gravitational potential depth, providing a clear explanation for why $\Omega_m$ is locally encoded in galaxy properties. Our work establishes a direct, interpretable bridge between small-scale galaxy physics and large-scale cosmology, opening a complementary pathway to cosmological inference that bypasses traditional clustering-based statistics and enables new synergies between galaxy formation theory and precision cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07651v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kito Liao, Francisco Villaescusa-Navarro, Romain Teysser, Natal\'i S. M. de Santi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalar-Induced Gravitational Waves and Primordial Black Holes from a Localized Bump or Dip Feature in a Single-Field Inflationary Potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07951v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the production of scalar-induced gravitational waves and primordial black holes in a single-field inflation model with a localized bump or dip feature in the potential. Introducing such a localized feature temporarily decelerates the slow-roll inflaton, amplifying the primordial curvature power spectrum into a sharp peak. Consequently, this enhancement sources a significant stochastic background of gravitational waves and leads to abundant formation of primordial black holes. Through eight benchmark cases, we show that the predicted abundances of primordial black holes can remain compatible with current observational limits, while the corresponding gravitational wave spectra peaking across a wide range of frequencies are accessible to future gravitational wave experiments in multiple observational bands.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07951v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiang Zhang, Zhao-Huan Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-resonance preheating in deformed attractor models: oscillon formation and evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07972v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is well known that, in potentials that are quadratic near the minimum but shallower away, such as small-$\alpha$ ($\ll M_P^2$) attractors, the inflaton condensate fragments into localized compact objects known as oscillons during self-resonance preheating. In this work we investigate the self-resonance in deformed $\alpha$-attractor T-model with a Gaussian feature near the minimum, distant from inflation's end. Linear analysis reveals altered resonance bands and deformed Floquet charts dependent on feature parameters. In fully nonlinear lattice simulations, we find that the gradient energy transfer is largely independent of the potential feature parameter $h$. In contrast, after resonance terminates, the subsequent evolution of gradient energy becomes strongly dependent on $h$. Statistical analysis reveals that models with the potential feature produce larger number of smaller oscillons, with a reduced energy stored in these objects, increasingly suppressed as the magnitude of $h$ grows. By tracking the total energy and the gradient energy contained in oscillons, we find that in models with nonzero $h$ oscillons are systematically shorter-lived, with this effect strengthening for larger $h$. The gravitational wave emission is dominated by the resonance stage and is strongly suppressed once oscillons form. Potential features leave the low-frequency spectrum largely unchanged but significantly modify the high-frequency tail. Although a complete reheating description requires external couplings and higher-resolution simulations, clear qualitative differences of cosmic expansion history already emerge within our simulated time window. These results highlight the important role of potential features in shaping reheating dynamics and their cosmological implications, and provide a deeper understanding of preheating dynamics and the properties of oscillons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07972v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bao-Min Gu, Yu-Peng Zhang, Fu-Wen Shu, Yu-Xiao Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complementary Roles of Distance and Growth Probes in Testing Time-Varying Dark Energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08207v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Distance measurements have long provided the primary observational constraints on the expansion history of the Universe and the properties of dark energy. However, because such observables depend on cumulative line-of-sight integrals over the Hubble rate, their sensitivity to time-dependent features of the dark energy equation of state is intrinsically limited. In this work, we examine this limitation from an information-based perspective using the eigenvalue structure of the Fisher information matrix constructed from distance, expansion rate, and growth observables. We show that distance and expansion-rate data generically produce a strongly hierarchical Fisher spectrum dominated by a single information mode, reflecting an irreducible loss of sensitivity to temporal variations in dark energy. This behavior can be traced directly to the integrated kernel structure of geometric observables. Growth measurements, by contrast, respond through differential dynamics and can introduce additional independent information directions. Using both controlled mock data and survey-like configurations representative of next-generation experiments, we find that the impact of growth information depends not only on its nominal precision but also on the structure of the data covariance. In simplified mock setups, growth measurements can partially activate a second information direction even at moderate precision. In Euclid-like configurations, however, the information remains effectively one-dimensional until growth precision reaches the percent level, below which a second mode emerges rapidly. These results clarify the complementary roles of distance and growth probes and provide a model-independent criterion for assessing the physical content of cosmological constraints on dynamical dark energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08207v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seokcheon Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter from Eternity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08338v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose that the totality of dark matter in the universe might ascribe its origin to one of the key properties of cosmological inflation, that it may be eternal: regions that at the end of the primordial accelerated expansion of the universe never reheated, but keep eternally inflating, manifest themselves as primordial black holes in our observable universe. This mechanism can provide a primordial black hole abundance which is larger than the standard one due to the gravitational collapse of sizeable overdensities in the radiation phase. It also predicts a broad spectrum for the curvature perturbation and a flat stochastic gravitational wave background at a level of $\Omega_\text{GW} h^2 \simeq 10^{-10}$ up to the mHz.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08338v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Franciolini, M. Peloso, A. Riotto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kosmulator: A Python framework for cosmological inference with MCMC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08424v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present Kosmulator, a modular and vectorised Python framework designed to accelerate the statistical testing of cosmological models. As the theoretical landscape expands beyond standard $\Lambda$CDM, implementing new expansion histories into traditional Einstein--Boltzmann solvers becomes a significant computational bottleneck. Kosmulator addresses this by leveraging array-native execution and efficient ensemble slice sampling (via Zeus) to perform rapid Bayesian inference. We validate the framework against the industry-standard Cobaya code using a combination of Type Ia Supernovae, Cosmic Chronometers, and Baryon Acoustic Oscillation (BAO) data. Our results demonstrate that Kosmulator reproduces Cobaya's posterior constraints to within $\leq0.3\sigma$ statistical agreement on $H_{0}$ and $\Omega_{m}$ and $&lt;0.6\%$ precision on $\chi^{2}$, while achieving a $\sim 4.5\times$ reduction in wall-clock time on a single CPU core compared to a standard MPI-parallelised baseline. Furthermore, we showcase the framework's utility by constraining the implicit power-law $f(Q)$ "$f_1$CDM" model and demonstrating its automated model selection capabilities (AIC/BIC). Kosmulator is introduced as a "scientific sieve" for rapid hypothesis testing, allowing researchers to efficiently filter theoretical candidates before deploying high-precision resources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08424v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renier T. Hough, Robert Rugg, Shambel Sahlu, Amare Abebe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synchrotron Self-Compton Process for Constraining sub-GeV Dark Matter in Omega Centauri via SKA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08731v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The search for the particle identity of dark matter (DM) continues to be a primary objective in modern physics. In this field, the sub-GeV mass range of DM detection remains a crucial yet challenging window. We investigate synchrotron self-Compton (SSC) emission from electrons and positrons produced by MeV-scale DM annihilation as a novel indirect detection channel. Focusing on the globular cluster Omega Centauri and the sensitivity of the Square Kilometre Array, we derive constraints on the annihilation cross section reaching $\langle\sigma v\rangle \sim 10^{-30}\,\rm{cm}^{3}\,\rm{s}^{-1}$ in the tens-of-MeV range. Furthermore, constraints could even reach below $\langle\sigma v\rangle \sim 10^{-32}\,\rm{cm}^{3}\,\rm{s}^{-1}$ for extreme parameter choices. Remarkably, even under deliberately conservative astrophysical assumptions, this channel outperforms existing indirect limits, establishing SSC emission as a robust probe of sub-GeV DM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08731v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guan-Sen Wang, Bing-Yu Su, Yang Yu, Bo Zhang, Lei Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hints of sign-changing scalar field energy density and a transient acceleration phase at $z\sim 2$ from model-agnostic reconstructions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08928v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a data-driven reconstruction of the late-time expansion history and its implications for dark-energy dynamics. Modeling the reduced Hubble rate with a node-based Gaussian-process-kernel interpolant, we constrain the reconstruction using CC, Pantheon+ SNIa, BAO data from SDSS and DESI, transversal BAO data, and external $H_0$ priors (SH0ES and H0DN). Assuming GR at the background level, we map the reconstructed kinematics onto a dark-energy fluid and a scalar-field description, yielding the total potential and kinetic contributions that reproduce the inferred $H(z)$. To interpret the reconstruction, we consider both a minimal single-field model (canonical or phantom) and a two-field (quintom) system consisting of one canonical and one phantom scalar field (or families). Within the GR-based effective-fluid mapping, the inferred dark-energy density changes sign for all dataset combinations explored, transitioning from $\rho_{\rm DE}&lt;0$ at higher redshift to $\rho_{\rm DE}&gt;0$ toward the present, and defining a transition redshift $z_\dagger$ by $\rho_{\rm DE}(z_\dagger)=0$. A single canonical scalar cannot realize such a smooth evolution during expansion, whereas a phantom field or a two-field quintom framework can accommodate the required behavior; in particular, the two-field system permits smooth phantom-divide crossings at finite $\rho_{\rm DE}&gt;0$ and distinguishes them from the separate notion of a density zero crossing. The reconstructed kinematics admit intermediate-redshift structure in some combinations, including hints of an additional accelerated-expansion interval around $z\sim 1.7$--$2.3$. The present-day equation of state remains close to a cosmological constant: combinations including supernovae give $w_0\simeq -1$, while combinations without supernovae but with an external $H_0$ prior show only a mild preference for $w_0&lt;-1$ at the $\sim1.5$--$1.7\sigma$ level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08928v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\"Ozg\"ur Akarsu, Maria Caruana, Konstantinos F. Dialektopoulos, Luis A. Escamilla, Emre O. Kahya, Jackson Levi Said</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The stellar velocity anisotropy of strong lensing massive elliptical galaxies and its role in the inference of the Hubble parameter $H_0$ using spatially resolved kinematics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07159v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: One of the biggest challenges in cosmology, the Hubble Tension, requires independent measurements of $H_0$, and strong lensing with time-delay cosmography is a promising avenue. The inclusion of spatially resolved kinematic data helps break the mass--sheet degeneracy, a key limitation in strong lensing. Kinematics, however, suffers from its own degeneracy due to unknown stellar velocity anisotropy, which can bias galaxy mass profile inferences. We investigate the bias in $H_0$ using a sample of ten massive elliptical galaxies at $z=0.2$ from the Illustris $TNG100$ simulations. We generate mock line-of-sight velocity-dispersion maps resembling JWST NIRSpec observations and test four anisotropy models: Osipkov--Merritt (OM), Mamon--Lokas (ML), constant $\beta$, and a generalized--OM (gOM) profile, under both kinematics-only and joint kinematics plus strong lensing analyses. We find a sub-percent average bias in $H_{0}$ across ten galaxies with joint modeling for three models: $+0.2 \pm 1.6\%$ (ML), $-0.9 \pm 1.9\%$ (constant) and $-0.9 \pm 1.6\%$ (gOM), with $\sim 5\%$ scatter. Joint modeling reduces bias, improves precision, and mitigates outlier results. Overall, the gOM model best recovers galaxy parameters and delivers the most accurate $H_{0}$ relative to posterior uncertainties considering both analyses. However, the single-parameter OM model produces large systematic biases: with kinematics only data, $H_{0}$ errors can exceed $20\%$, and even with joint modeling, produces an overall bias of $+11.5 \pm 1.3\%$ (OM). The higher bias in OM is unlikely to average out across an ensemble of galaxies. Our findings highlight the impact of anisotropy assumptions on $H_{0}$ inference and, more broadly, in galaxy dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07159v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vishal Verma, Quinn Minor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Dirac neutrinos destabilize $\mathcal{Z}_2$ domain wall network?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07380v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In particle physics model building, a discrete $\mathcal{Z}_2$ symmetry is often spontaneously broken for phenomenological reasons. When this breaking occurs dynamically in the early Universe, stable domain wall networks are formed, which can eventually dominate the cosmic energy density. To avoid this problem, explicit $\mathcal{Z}_2$-breaking terms in the scalar potential are usually introduced in an ad hoc manner. In this Letter, we show that if the same $\mathcal{Z}_2$ symmetry is also responsible for generating light Dirac neutrino masses, such explicit breaking terms can instead arise radiatively from the particles involved in the Dirac mass generation. We find that the resulting bias term scales inversely with the cube of the Dirac neutrino mass, leading to a gravitational wave spectrum proportional to the sixth power of the Dirac neutrino mass. This establishes a nontrivial connection between the Dirac seesaw scale, the domain wall annihilation epoch, and the resulting stochastic gravitational wave signal. We further demonstrate that a wide range of Dirac seesaw scales can be probed by upcoming gravitational wave and cosmic microwave background experiments, while part of the parameter space simultaneously explains the observed baryon asymmetry via Dirac leptogenesis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07380v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debasish Borah, Partha Kumar Paul, Narendra Sahu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Viscosity on Sloshing Cold Fronts in Galaxy Clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07661v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The viscous properties of the intracluster medium (ICM) remain poorly constrained. Cold fronts-sharp discontinuities formed during cluster mergers-offer a potential avenue to probe the effective viscosity of the ICM. Velocity shear across these fronts should generate Kelvin-Helmholtz instabilities (KHI), unless viscosity or magnetic tension suppresses them. We perform cluster merger simulations incorporating four ICM viscosity models: (A) inviscid, (B) isotropic Spitzer viscosity, (C) anisotropic Braginskii viscosity, and (D) Braginskii viscosity limited by microinstabilities. The isotropic Spitzer viscosity (case B) strongly suppresses KHI, producing smooth cold front surfaces, while the inviscid (A) and microinstability-limited (D) cases show prominent ripples. The Braginskii case (C) yields intermediate suppression. We also vary the plasma $\beta$ parameter ($\beta \approx$ 100 and 1600) to examine how a changing magnetic field strength affects the results. Stronger magnetic fields further suppress KHI, leading to smoother fronts and reduced differences between different viscosity models, while also widening the range of permitted pressure anisotropies when microinstability-based limiters are present. These results indicate that both viscosity and magnetic fields play crucial roles in stabilising sloshing cold fronts in galaxy clusters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07661v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ming-Hsueh Hsieh, H. -Y. Karen Yang, John ZuHone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DerivKit: stable numerical derivatives bridging Fisher forecasts and MCMC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08078v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: DerivKit is a Python package for derivative-based statistical inference. It implements stable numerical differentiation and derivative assembly utilities for Fisher-matrix forecasting and higher-order likelihood approximations in scientific applications, supporting scalar- and vector-valued models including black-box or tabulated functions where automatic differentiation is impractical or unavailable. These derivatives are used to construct Fisher forecasts, Fisher bias estimates, and non-Gaussian likelihood expansions based on the Derivative Approximation for Likelihoods (DALI). By extending derivative-based inference beyond the Gaussian approximation, DerivKit forms a practical bridge between fast Fisher forecasts and more computationally intensive sampling-based methods such as Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08078v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikolina \v{S}ar\v{c}evi\'c, Matthijs van der Wild, Cynthia Trendafilova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CFHT MegaCam Two Deep Fields Imaging Survey (2DFIS) II: Decoding the Lensing Profile of a "Rotating" Cluster with Deep CFHT Imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08360v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a multi-wavelength analysis of the galaxy cluster RXCJ0110.0+1358 ($z=0.058$), a rotating cluster candidate, combining deep CFHT imaging, SDSS photometry, spectroscopic redshifts, and XMM-Newton X-ray observations. We find a notable discrepancy between the optical and X-ray views: while optical data reveal a pronounced bimodal galaxy distribution with significant kinematic substructure signatures, the X-ray emission exhibits a single, smoothly extended component centered on the BCG. Our weak lensing analysis resolves this discrepancy by revealing that the mass is predominantly concentrated in the southeast ($\log M_{200}/M_\odot = 14.04_{-0.40}^{+0.24}$), while the northwestern substructure has a negligible mass ($\sim 10^{13} M_\odot$). This immense mass disparity rules out the dynamical possibility of a rotating system. We demonstrate that the apparent optical bimodality arises from the projection of a filament, which led optical group-finding algorithms to misclassify these galaxies as cluster members. This contamination creates a spurious substructure that mimics a rotation signal and leads to an overestimation of the luminosity-based halo mass, resolving the observed inconsistencies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08360v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yicheng Li, Liping Fu, Wentao Luo, Binyang Liu, Wei Du, Martin Kilbinger, Calum Murray, Christopher J. Miller, Ray Wang, David Turner, Lance Miller, Dezi Liu, Mario Radovich, Jean-Paul Kneib, Huanyuan Shan, Kaiwen Mai, Zicheng Wang, Haoran Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Host Galaxies of Binary Black Hole Mergers with Next-Generation Gravitational Wave Detector Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08459v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Identifying the host galaxy of a binary black hole (BBH) merger detected via gravitational waves (GWs) remains a challenge due to the absence of electromagnetic counterparts and the large localization volumes produced by current-generation detectors. A confident host association would provide stellar population properties to constrain BBH formation channels and enable measurements of cosmological parameters such as the Hubble constant, H0. We simulate BBH mergers in nearby (z&lt;0.25) host galaxies to evaluate the feasibility of host identification with future GW detector networks, including configurations with the planned LIGO-India detector and third-generation detectors such as the Einstein Telescope (ET) and Cosmic Explorer (CE). We construct two injection grids to explore variations in BBH mass, distance, and directional sensitivity, and infer localization volumes using the Fisher Information Matrix (FIM)-based parameter estimation implemented through BILBY. To assess the prospects for unique host identification, we introduce a set of diagnostics: theoretical comoving volume thresholds for galaxies of a given stellar mass, derived from galaxy stellar mass functions, a metallicity-based volume threshold motivated by progenitor environment models, stellar mass fractions to quantify candidate host prominence, and the probability of chance alignment (p_c). These metrics provide ways to evaluate host associations and constrain BBH formation channels. We find that future networks that include ET and CE localize BBH mergers to volumes smaller than those theoretical thresholds, implying potentially unique host identification, out to ~1000 Mpc at a rate of ~100 yr^{-1}. While associations for individual events may remain uncertain, our framework is well-suited to population-level analyses, enabling constraints on BBH formation scenarios in the era of next-generation GW detector networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08459v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sumedha Biswas, Andrew Levan, Peter G. Jonker, Kendall Ackley, Gregory Ashton, Nikhil Sarin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can UV meet IR in the Swiss cheese?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08487</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08487v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the embedding of regular black holes in an expanding universe and study how the ultraviolet modifications to the Schwarzschild geometry that regularize the black hole singularity affect the exterior universe's expansion rate. We consider several proposals for the regular black hole geometry and obtain the corresponding Friedmann equations for a universe filled only with dust and black holes. We show that different proposals have different implications which may be distinguished. We then test the hypothesis that the UV corrections to the black hole geometry may be responsible for the current phase of accelerated expansion. To this aim we constrain the value of the regular black hole UV cutoff parameter from observations. Interestingly we find that the best fit is obtained by values of the parameter corresponding to regular horizonless compact objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08487v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Madina Abilmazhinova, Diana Kulubayeva, Hrishikesh Chakrabarty, Daniele Malafarina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal Vacuum Cosmology Explains Hubble Tension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08522v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It is argued that the previously proposed modification of the standard (flat) inflationary $\Lambda CDM$ model in which cosmological constant is replaced by thermal energy of expanding vacum, characterized by the Gibbons-Hawking temperature, explains the origin of notorious ``Hubble tension''.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08522v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert Alicki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial features as probes of baryogenesis from supersymmetric flat directions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08781v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Affleck-Dine mechanism is a leading baryogenesis scenario in which scalar condensates form coherently during inflation along supersymmetric flat directions that are lifted by supersymmetry-breaking effects. We update the viable parameter space for baryogenesis using recent Cosmic Microwave Background constraints on baryon-density isocurvature perturbations, taking the quantum fluctuations of the scalar condensate generated during inflation as initial conditions. We then show that primordial features arising from the inflaton sector can serve as a unique probe of baryogenesis models, whose mechanisms are otherwise difficult to access directly due to their high energy scales. These primordial features leave correlated imprints, such as sharp feature signals and clock signals, on both the curvature and baryon-density isocurvature perturbations, providing direct evidence for the existence of both light and heavy modes involved in the Affleck-Dine mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08781v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi-Peng Wu, Xingang Chen, Nino Ephremidze, Lingfeng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on the primordial curvature power spectrum at small scales between $3\times 10^{18}$ and $4.5\times 10^{21}~\rm Mpc^{-1}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18887v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The primordial curvature power spectrum $\mathcal{P}_\mathcal{R}$ has been measured with high precision on large scales $10^{-4}\lesssim k\lesssim 3~\rm Mpc^{-1}$ based on observations of the cosmic microwave background, Lyman-$\alpha$ forest and large scale structure. On small scales $3\lesssim k \lesssim 10^{23}~\rm Mpc^{-1}$, constraints are primarily derived from studies on primordial black holes (PBHs). In particular, for very small scales $10^{17}\lesssim k\lesssim 10^{23}~{\rm Mpc^{-1}}$, current limits come exclusively from investigations of the lightest supersymmetric particles produced by PBH radiation and the stable Planck-mass relics after their evaporation. Recent findings also indicate that the evaporation of light PBHs ($M_{\rm PBH}\lesssim 10^{9}~\rm g$) can modify the expansion rate of the Universe and the baryon-to-photon ratio, thereby affecting the primordial abundance of light nuclei. Moreover, it has been proposed that the ``memory burden'' effect can slow down the mass loss rate of black holes, allowing light PBHs to survive until the present day. Based on recent theoretical advancements in black hole physics and existing constraints on the initial mass fraction of light PBHs with masses $10^{3}\lesssim M_{\rm PBH}\lesssim 2\times 10^{9}~\rm g$, we derive new constraints on $\mathcal{P}_\mathcal{R}$ on small scales $3\times 10^{18}\lesssim k\lesssim 4.5\times 10^{21}~\rm Mpc^{-1}$, a regime that has been underexplored in previous literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18887v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yupeng Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpreting Cosmological Information from Neural Networks in the Hydrodynamic Universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17839v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: What happens when a black box (neural network) meets a black box (simulation of the Universe)? Recent work has shown that convolutional neural networks (CNNs) can infer cosmological parameters from the matter density field in the presence of complex baryonic processes. A key question that arises is, which parts of the cosmic web is the neural network obtaining information from? We shed light on the matter by identifying the Fourier scales, density scales, and morphological features of the cosmic web that CNNs pay most attention to. We find that CNNs extract cosmological information from both high and low density regions: overdense regions provide the most information per pixel, while underdense regions -- particularly deep voids and their surroundings -- contribute significantly due to their large spatial extent and coherent spatial features. Remarkably, we demonstrate that there is negligible degradation in cosmological constraining power after aggressive cutting in both maximum Fourier scale and density. Furthermore, we find similar results when considering both hydrodynamic and gravity-only simulations, implying that neural networks can marginalize over baryonic effects with minimal loss in cosmological constraining power. Our findings point to practical strategies for optimal and robust field-level cosmological inference in the presence of uncertainly modeled astrophysics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17839v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ae0b5a</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Astrophys. J. 994 129 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Arnab Lahiry, Adrian E. Bayer, Francisco Villaescusa-Navarro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective Field Theory of Chiral Gravitational Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19059v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: When a (non-)Abelian gauge field acquires an isotropic background configuration during inflation, strong gravitational waves (GWs) with parity-violating polarization, known as chiral GWs, can be produced in addition to the intrinsic unpolarized GWs. However, previous studies have analyzed individual models, leaving the generality of this phenomenon unclear. To perform a model-independent analysis, we construct an effective field theory (EFT) of chiral GWs by extending the EFT of inflation and incorporating gauge fields. The resulting action unifies inflationary models with a $SU(2)$ gauge field, such as chromo-natural inflation and gauge-flation, and ones with a triplet of $U(1)$ gauge fields, systematically encompassing all possible GW production mechanisms consistent with the symmetry breaking induced by the gauge field background. We find that chiral GWs are generically and inevitably produced, provided that the effective energy density of the background gauge field is positive and the gauge kinetic function is not fine-tuned to a specific time dependence. This EFT offers a useful foundation for future phenomenological studies as well as for deepening our theoretical understanding of chiral GWs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19059v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2026/02/018</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP02(2026)018</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Katsuki Aoki, Tomohiro Fujita, Ryodai Kawaguchi, Kazuki Yanagihara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for a sign change of the ISW effect in the very recent universe: hot voids and cold overdensities at $z&lt;0.03$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08832v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We find a significant CMB temperature excess in the direction of local underdensities within $z&lt;0.03$. By contrast, less than $0.2\%$ of simulated CMB maps show a similarly significant temperature excess in nearby voids. Combined with earlier findings showing a $&gt;5\sigma$ cooling of CMB photons in galactic filaments in the same redshift range, we now have possible evidence for a negative Integrated Sachs-Wolfe (ISW) effect in the very recent Universe. In addition to having opposite sign, the observed amplitude is an order of magnitude larger than the predicted Rees-Sciama and ISW effects for the nearby Universe and similar to the expectation of some dark energy and modified gravity models predicting altered growth of gravitational potentials at very low redshift. We discuss the results in light of the latest Data Release 2 results of the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) showing evidence for dynamical dark energy. Removing the quadrupole, we find the CMB temperatures measured in nearby voids to a large degree uncorrelated with the temperature measured around nearby galaxies and the observed mean difference between these temperatures is almost $6.5\sigma$ larger than found in simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08832v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Frode K. Hansen, Diego Garcia Lambas, Andr\'es N. Ruiz, Facundo Toscano, Luis A. Pereyra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Interacting Dark-Matter Spikes and the Final-Parsec Problem: Bayesian constraints from the NANOGrav 15-Year Gravitational-Wave Background</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18153</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18153v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A self-interacting dark-matter (SIDM) density spike around merging supermassive black holes (SMBHs) may be able to supply the dynamical friction needed to shrink binaries from $\sim 1\, \mathrm{pc}$ to $\sim 10^{-2} \,\mathrm{pc}$, thereby resolving the long-standing "final-parsec problem". Embedding the binary-halo system in a cosmological population model, we evolve the inspiral under the combined influence of gravitational-wave (GW) emission and SIDM drag, compute the resulting nanohertz GW background, and confront it with the NANOGrav 15-year pulsar-timing data. A six-parameter Bayesian analysis, performed with a Gaussian-process-accelerated Markov chain Monte Carlo, yields posterior constraints on the cross-section per unit mass and maximum circular velocity values that were consistent with independent galaxy-rotation and cluster-lensing limits. Within this parameter space, the SIDM spike remains intact, supplies sufficient friction to overcome the stellar depletion barrier, and produces a characteristic-strain spectrum that matches the NANOGrav signal as well as phenomenological astrophysical models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18153v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/2hqm-qv99</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 113 (2026) 4, 043501</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shreyas Tiruvaskar, Chris Gordon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid cosmological inference with the two-loop matter power spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00611</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00611v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We compute the two-loop effective field theory (EFT) power spectrum of dark matter density fluctuations in $\Lambda$CDM using the recently proposed COBRA method (Bakx. et al, 2025). With COBRA, we are able to evaluate the two-loop matter power spectrum in $\sim 1$ millisecond at $ \sim 0.1 \%$ precision on one CPU for arbitrary redshifts and on scales where perturbation theory applies. As an application, we use the nonlinear matter power spectrum from the Dark Sky simulation to assess the performance of the two-loop EFT power spectrum compared to the one-loop EFT power spectrum at $z=0$. We find that, for volumes typical for Stage IV galaxy surveys, $V = 25 \,(\text{Gpc}/h)^3$, the two-loop EFT can provide unbiased cosmological constraints on $\Omega_m,H_0$ and $A_s$ using scales up to $k_\text{max}=0.26\, h/\text{Mpc}$, thereby outperforming the constraints from the one-loop EFT ($k_\text{max}=0.11\, h/\text{Mpc}$). The Figure of Merit on these three parameters increases by a factor $\sim 2.6$ and the one-dimensional marginalized constraints improve by $\sim35\%$ for $\Omega_m$, $\sim20\%$ for $H_0$ and $\sim 15\%$ for $A_s$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00611v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.33232/001c.157501</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Bakx, Henrique Rubira, Nora Elisa Chisari, Zvonimir Vlah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DESI DR1 Ly$\alpha$ 1D power spectrum: Validation of estimators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13593v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Data Release 1 (DR1) of the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) is the largest sample to date for small-scale Ly$\alpha$ forest cosmology, accessed through its one-dimensional power spectrum ($P_{\mathrm{1D}}$). The Ly$\alpha$ forest $P_{\mathrm{1D}}$ is extracted from quasar spectra that are highly inhomogeneous (both in wavelength and between quasars) in noise properties due to intrinsic properties of the quasar, atmospheric and astrophysical contamination, and also sensitive to low-level details of the spectral extraction pipeline. We employ two estimators in DR1 analysis to measure $P_{\mathrm{1D}}$: the optimal estimator and the fast Fourier transform (FFT) estimator. To ensure robustness of our DR1 measurements, we validate these two power spectrum and covariance matrix estimation methodologies against the challenging aspects of the data. First, using a set of 20 synthetic 1D realizations of DR1, we derive the masking bias corrections needed for the FFT estimator and the continuum fitting bias needed for both estimators. We demonstrate that both estimators, including their covariances, are unbiased with these corrections using the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. Second, we substantially extend our previous suite of CCD image simulations to include 675,000 quasars, allowing us to accurately quantify the pipeline's performance. This set of simulations reveals biases at the highest $k$ values, corresponding to a resolution error of a few percent. We base the resolution systematics error budget of DR1 $P_{\mathrm{1D}}$ on these values, but do not derive corrections from them since the simulation fidelity is insufficient for precise corrections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13593v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. G. Kara\c{c}ayl{\i}, C. Ravoux, P. Martini, J. M. Le Goff, E. Armengaud, M. Abdul-Karim, J. Aguilar, S. Ahlen, A. Anand, S. BenZvi, D. Bianchi, D. Brooks, T. Claybaugh, A. Cuceu, A. de la Macorra, Biprateep Dey, P. Doel, S. Ferraro, A. Font-Ribera, J. E. Forero-Romero, E. Gazta\~naga, S. Gontcho A Gontcho, G. Gutierrez, H. K. Herrera-Alcantar, K. Honscheid, M. Ishak, J. Jimenez, R. Joyce, D. Kirkby, T. Kisner, A. Kremin, O. Lahav, M. Landriau, L. Le Guillou, M. Manera, A. Meisner, R. Miquel, S. Nadathur, G. Niz, N. Palanque-Delabrouille, W. J. Percival, C. Poppett, F. Prada, I. P\'erez-R\`afols, G. Rossi, E. Sanchez, D. Schlegel, M. Schubnell, H. Seo, J. Silber, D. Sprayberry, T. Tan, G. Tarl\'e, M. Walther, B. A. Weaver, H. Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faraday Depolarization Study of a Radio Galaxy Using LOFAR Two-metre Sky Survey: Data Release 2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00440v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a detailed depolarization analysis of the radio galaxy \texttt{ILTJ012215.21+254334.8} using polarimetric data from the \textit{LOFAR Two-metre Sky Survey} (LoTSS) Data Release 2 (DR2) catalogue. This source, with \textit{RM} $\sim$ 47 rad m$^{-2}$ and projected linear size $\sim$ 335 kpc at $z \approx 0.05$, serves as a pilot for systematic QU-fitting of unresolved LoTSS sources, building on prior single-target studies that established the need for multi-component Faraday models in complex magneto-ionic media.
  Fitting five depolarization models to the LoTSS HBA (120-168 MHz) fractional polarization spectra reveals a decisively preferred three-component model (one Faraday-thin instrumental leakage, plus two external Faraday dispersions), demonstrating that LoTSS data alone can constrain moderate Faraday complexity in typical DR2 galaxies. Our results highlight turbulence and inhomogeneity in the foreground magneto-ionic medium and outline a path for population studies of LoTSS FR-I sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00440v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.33232/001c.157500</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Samantha Sneha Paul, Abhik Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BaBy Cosmic Tension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03118v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that the recently released B-mode polarisation data from the South Pole Telescope (SPT) favour a non-vanishing contribution of primordial gravitational waves of inflationary origin which is in tension with the previous BICEP-Keck (BK) measurements. Our analysis uses the third-order slow-roll primordial power spectra, with theoretically motivated priors, on the multifrequency SPT likelihoods complemented by the latest Planck satellite data products. The SPT measurements provide 1.0 bit of information gain on the first slow-roll parameter, which is higher than the 0.9 bit provided by BK even though the SPT sensitivity is five times lower. Moreover, the Bayesian dimensionality on the same parameter exceeds 1.5 for SPT versus 0.3 for BK showing that it is overconstrained by the SPT data. Even if this BB-tension could be the result of a yet to be understood foreground, our findings should motivate for a closer analysis of this unexpected B-modes excess.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03118v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1209/0295-5075/ae37a0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>EPL 153, 29001 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Christophe Ringeval</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phantom Mirage from Axion Dark Energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14957</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14957v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Supernova (SN) and baryon acoustic oscillation (BAO) distance measures have recently provided hints that the dark energy is not only dynamical but apparently evolves from normal to phantom dark energy between redshifts $0&lt;z&lt;1$. A normal axion dark energy component in the mass range just below the Hubble scale can mimic a phantom component by appearing as dark energy at $z=1$ and dark matter at $z=0$, raising the possibility of a phantom mirage. We show that there is a wide range of axion dark energy contributions that can resolve the SN-BAO tension as well as thawing quintessence does, leaving BAO tension with the cosmic microwave background (CMB) for the distance measures from $z\sim 1$ to recombination to be resolved at high redshifts. With axions, raising the optical depth to reionization to $\tau \approx 0.1$ works essentially as well as $w_0-w_a$ phantom dark energy for all but the lowE CMB data, with a remaining $\Delta\chi^2\sim -16$ compared with $\Lambda$CDM, whereas a small spatial curvature of $\Omega_K \sim 0.003$ can largely relax the full SN-BAO-CMB tension with a total $\Delta\chi^2 \sim -12$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14957v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rayne Liu, Yijie Zhu, Wayne Hu, Vivian Miranda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining baryonic feedback and cosmology from DES Y3 and Planck PR4 6$\times$2pt data. I. $\Lambda$CDM models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25596</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25596v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We combine weak lensing, galaxy clustering, cosmic microwave background (CMB) lensing, and their cross-correlations (so-called 6$\times$2pt) to constrain cosmology and baryonic feedback scenarios using data from the Dark Energy Survey (DES) Y3 Maglim catalog and the Planck satellite PR4 data release. We include all data points in the DES Y3 cosmic shear two-point correlation function (2PCF) down to 2.$^\prime$5 and model baryonic feedback processes via principal components (PCs) that are constructed from the ANTILLES simulations. We find a tight correlation between the amplitude of the first PC $Q_1$ and mean normalized baryon mass fraction $\bar{Y_\mathrm{b}}=\bar{f}_\mathrm{b}/(\Omega_\mathrm{b}/\Omega_\mathrm{m})$ from the ANTILLES simulations and employ an independent $\bar{Y_\mathrm{b}}$ measurement from Akino et al. (2022) as a prior of $Q_1$. We train a neural network $6\times2$pt emulator to boost the analysis speed by $\mathcal{O}(10^3)$, which enables us to run an impressive number of simulated analyses to validate our analysis against various systematics. For our 6$\times$2pt analysis, we find $S_8=0.8073\pm0.0094$ when including a $Q_1$ prior from $\bar{Y_\mathrm{b}}$ observations. This level of cosmological constraining power allows us to put tight constraints on the strength of baryonic feedback. We find $Q_1=0.025^{+0.024}_{-0.029}$ for our 6$\times$2pt analysis and $Q_1=0.043\pm{0.016}$ when combining with external information from Planck, ACT, DESI. All these results indicate weak feedback, e.g., the tensions to Illustris ($Q_1=0.095$) and OWLS AGN T8.7 ($Q_1=0.137$) are 2.9$\sigma$-3.3$\sigma$ and 4.7$\sigma$-5.9$\sigma$, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25596v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiachuan Xu, Tim Eifler, Elisabeth Krause, Vivian Miranda, Jaime Salcido, Ian McCarthy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Turnover detection using the power spectrum and bispectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06962v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The turnover at the peak of the Fourier matter power spectrum encodes a fundamental signature of matter-radiation equality in the early Universe. This delivers a potential standard ruler, independent of baryon acoustic oscillations and therefore able to break parameter degeneracies and improve precision. Furthermore, the turnover scale is independent of redshift and clustering bias, allowing for stacking of the signals from redshift bins. In practice, the very large scale of the turnover means that sample variance and systematics are serious impediments to its detection. Detections of the turnover and measurements of its scale have been made in the WiggleZ, eBOSS, Quaia, and DESI surveys. Upcoming surveys should improve the detection significance and reduce errors on the turnover scale. We use MCMC forecasts for turnover detection in a spectroscopic Euclid-like survey and a futuristic MegaMapper-like survey. In addition to the power spectrum, we include the signal from the bispectrum in equilateral configurations. These surveys are forecast to detect the turnover at $\sim\! 6\sigma$ (Euclid-like) and $\sim\! 15\sigma$ (MegaMapper-like), with precision on the turnover scale of $\sim\! 4\%$ and $\sim\! 2\%$. The inclusion of the bispectrum delivers a modest improvement of $\sim\! 10-17\%$ in the constraints on the turnover scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06962v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yolanda Dube, Bikash R. Dinda, Sheean Jolicoeur, Roy Maartens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter from Holography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10617v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Previous studies have examined the holographic principle as a means of producing dark energy. Here we propose instead the possibility of holographic dark matter. In this case, dark matter does not arise in the framework of particle physics but is derived from the infrared cutoff set by the horizon scale. Using the Ricci cutoff, and a universe containing only baryons and radiation, we can account for the dark matter and naturally explain the coincidence between baryonic and nonbaryonic contributions to the density. In the presence of a pre-existing vacuum energy density our model reverses the sign of this density, thus accounting for the fact that certain string theories generically predict a negative vacuum energy, but observations require a positive value.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10617v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oem Trivedi, Robert J. Scherrer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hidden pattern of self-invariant cosmic expansion: Empirical evidence from Hubble diagram of supernovae</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.05512v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present empirical evidence extracted directly from the Pantheon Catalog of SNeIa demonstrating that the speed of light varies as the universe expands. Moreover, the speed of light must vary in a specific quantifiable manner. To show this, we reformulate the kinematics of late-time acceleration using Dolgov's power-law cosmology $a=(t/t_0)^\mu$ [Phys. Rev. D 55, 5881 (1997)] and Barrow's varying speed of light $c=c_0a^{-\zeta}$ [Phys. Rev. D 59, 043515 (1999)]. In this cosmology, light traveling through an expanding universe undergoes an additional refraction caused by the varying c along its path, resulting in a modified Lemaitre redshift formula $1+z=a^{-(1+\zeta)}$. The new model achieves a high-quality fit to the Pantheon Catalog of SNeIa and exhibits a strong degeneracy along the locus $(1+\zeta)\,\mu=1$. This empirical relation indicates a self-invariant cosmic evolution: at all instants during the late-time epoch, the speed of light is exactly proportional to the rate of cosmic expansion, viz. $c=\mu^{-1}c_0t_0\,da/dt$, a characteristic that is absent in the $\Lambda$CDM model. This synchronous behavior between $c$ and $da/dt$ carries profound cosmological implications that we will discuss, regarding (i) the nature of late-time acceleration; (ii) a resolution to the horizon problem; (iii) Kolb's coasting universe model [Astrophys. J. 344, 543 (1989)]; (iv) a generalized cosmological principle into the time domain; and (v) a novel conformally flat metric applicable to cosmology. This newfound kinematic $c\propto da/dt$ relation represents a stringent requirement that any viable dynamical model of cosmology must satisfy, a requirement that the $\Lambda$CDM model does not fulfill. Thus, our paper delivers the clearest and most decisive evidence to date that challenges the standard $\Lambda$CDM paradigm of cosmology and calls for variable-$c$ modifications to General Relativity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.05512v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hoang Ky Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Variable-Slope Smooth-$k$ Filter for Modeling Halo Abundances with Damped and Oscillatory Power Spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.01320v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a variable-slope smooth-$k$ (VSMK) filter within the Press-Schechter formalism to model halo mass functions derived from damped and oscillatory matter power spectra. While the standard smooth-$k$ approach successfully captures small-scale suppression effects, it intrinsically couples these to oscillatory features at intermediate scales. The VSMK filter generalizes this framework by allowing the effective logarithmic slope of the $k$-space window function to vary smoothly between two asymptotic regimes, thereby decoupling the small-scale suppression of halo abundances from the intermediate-scale oscillatory features characteristic of dark acoustic oscillations. We compare the analytic predictions obtained with the VSMK filter to $N$-body simulations for warm dark matter and ETHOS-based models, showing that a single parameter set reproduces both regimes simultaneously. The VSMK filter thus provides a unified and flexible analytic framework for modeling halo abundances in non-cold dark matter scenarios with damped and oscillatory power spectra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.01320v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreu Rocamora Martorell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulation-based cosmological inference from optically-selected galaxy clusters with $\texttt{Capish}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.01911v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Galaxy clusters are powerful probes of the growth of cosmic structure through measurements of their abundance as a function of mass and redshift. Extracting precise cosmological constraints from cluster surveys is challenging, as we must contend the complex relationship between richness and the underlying halo mass, selection function biases, super-sample covariance, and correlated measurement noise between mass proxies. As upcoming photometric surveys are expected to detect tens to hundreds of thousands of galaxy clusters, controlling these systematics becomes essential. In this paper, we present a forward-modelling approach using Simulation-Based Inference (SBI), which provides a natural framework for jointly modelling cluster abundance and lensing mass observables while capturing systematic uncertainties at higher fidelity than analytic likelihood methods - which rely on simplifying assumptions such as fixed covariances and Gaussianity - without requiring an explicit likelihood formulation. We introduce $\texttt{Capish}$, a Python code for generating forward-modelled galaxy cluster catalogues using halo mass functions and incorporating observational effects. We perform SBI using neural density estimation with normalizing flows, trained on abundance and mean lensing mass measurements in observed redshift-richness bins. Our forward model accounts for realistic noise, redshift uncertainties, selection functions, and correlated scatter between lensing mass and observed richness. We find good agreement with likelihood-based analyses, with broader SBI posteriors reflecting the increased realism of the forward model. We also test $\texttt{Capish}$ on cluster catalogues built from a large cosmological simulation, finding a good fit to cosmological parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.01911v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Constantin Payerne, Calum Murray, Hugo Simon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microlensing constraints on Primordial Black Hole abundance with Subaru Hyper Suprime-Cam observations of Andromeda</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05840</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05840v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present updated microlensing analysis results based on high-cadence ($\sim$2~min) Subaru Hyper Suprime-Cam (HSC) observations of the Andromeda Galaxy (M31) in 2014, 2017, and 2020, yielding a total of 39.3 hours of data. We use a point-lens finite-source model for the microlensing light curve model and employ multi-stage selection procedures to identify microlensing candidates. From more than 25,000 variable candidates detected across all nights, we identify 12 microlensing candidates with light-curve timescales shorter than 5~hours, and among them, 4 secure candidates with high-significance detections. We estimate detection efficiencies using light-curve-level simulations that account for observational conditions and finite-source effects. Using a hierarchical Bayesian framework that combines the light-curve fitting information for each candidate with the Poisson statistics of the number of candidates, we derive constraints on parameters that characterize the abundance and mass scale of primordial black hole (PBH) dark matter. First, we derive upper limits on the PBH abundance under the null hypothesis that all events are assumed to be false detections. Next, employing the PBH hypothesis in which all (or only secure) candidates are assumed to be due to PBH microlensing, we derive the allowed region of the PBH parameters; the inferred mass scale is $M_{\rm PBH}\sim10^{-7}$--$10^{-6}M_\odot$, and the PBH abundance to the total dark matter is $f_{\rm PBH}\sim 10^{-1}$. Our results demonstrate that HSC-M31 monitoring remains a uniquely powerful probe of PBHs, and highlight the need for further studies for example, using Rubin Observatory LSST observations of the Large Magellanic Cloud.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05840v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sunao Sugiyama, Masahiro Takada, Naoki Yasuda, Nozomu Tominaga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting stochastic inflation with perturbation theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.17644</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.17644v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A long-standing problem in primordial cosmology is to understand the precise relation between the stochastic formalism and standard perturbation theory for light scalar fields in inflationary spacetimes. A complete correspondence between the two frameworks has remained elusive, even for a single self-interacting spectator field on a fixed de Sitter background. In this Letter, we revisit the assumptions underlying the derivation of the Langevin and Fokker-Planck equations that form the basis of the stochastic approach. We show that the standard stochastic treatment is effectively equivalent to neglecting super-long-wavelength modes beyond the observable range described by these equations. Using perturbation theory, we quantify how these modes enter through virtual loop effects and demonstrate that, once treated consistently, they induce definite corrections to both the Langevin and Fokker-Planck equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.17644v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gonzalo A. Palma, Spyros Sypsas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Berry phase in axion physics, SM global structure, and generalized symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04749v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the Berry phase arising from axion-photon and axion-fermion interactions. The effective Hamiltonians in both systems share the same form, enabling a unified description of the Berry phase and providing a novel perspective on axion experiments. We conceptually propose a new photon-ring experiment for axion detection. Furthermore, we demonstrate that measuring the axion-induced Berry phase offers a unique method for probing the global structure of the Standard Model gauge group and axion-related generalized symmetries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04749v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2026.140218</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Lett. B 874 (2026) 140218</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Qing-Hong Cao, Shuailiang Ge, Yandong Liu, Jun-Chen Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No-scale Brans-Dicke Gravity -- ultralight scalar boson &amp; heavy inflaton</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18648</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18648v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It is very much intriguing if the Planck scale $M_{\rm{Pl}}$ is not a fundamental parameter. The Brans-Dicke gravity is nothing but the theory where the Planck scale $M_{\rm{Pl}}$ is indeed an illusional parameter. The theory predicts a massless scalar boson whose exchanges between matters induce unwanted long range forces. We solve this problem imposing there is no dimensionful parameter in the theory, even at the quantum level. We further extend the theory by including a $R^2$ term and a non-minimal coupling of the Standard Model Higgs to gravity, as their coefficients are dimensionless. This extension provides a heavy inflaton field that is consistent with all cosmological observations, with a potential very similar to that of the Starobinsky model. The inflaton necessarily decays into the massless scalar bosons, resulting in a non-negligible amount of dark radiation in the present universe. We demonstrate that the inflation model yields a sufficiently high reheating temperature for successful leptogenesis, and we also discuss a possible candidate for dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18648v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/10/032</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP10(2025)032</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Muzi Hong, Kyohei Mukaida, Tsutomu T. Yanagida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Millimeter-wave observations of Euclid Deep Field South using the South Pole Telescope: A data release of temperature maps and catalogs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00298v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Context. The South Pole Telescope third-generation camera (SPT-3G) has observed over 10,000 square degrees of sky at 95, 150, and 220 GHz (3.3, 2.0, 1.4 mm, respectively) and will significantly overlap the ongoing 14,000 square-degree Euclid Wide Survey. The Euclid collaboration recently released Euclid Deep Field South (EDF-S) observations of 23 square degrees at wide field depths in the first quick data release (Q1). Aims. With the goal of releasing complementary millimeter-wave data and encouraging legacy science, we performed dedicated observations of a 57-square-degree field overlapping the EDF-S. Methods. The observing time totaled 20 days, and we reached noise depths of 4.3, 3.8, and 13.2 $\mu$K-arcmin at 95, 150, and 220 GHz, respectively. Results. In this work we present the temperature maps and two catalogs constructed from these data. The emissive source catalog contains 601 objects (334 inside EDF-S) with 54% synchrotron-dominated sources and 46% thermal dust emission-dominated sources. The 5$\sigma$ detection thresholds are 1.7, 2.0, and 6.5 mJy in the three bands. The cluster catalog contains 217 cluster candidates (121 inside EDF-S) with median mass $M_{500c}=2.12 \times 10^{14} M_{\odot}/h_{70}$ and median redshift $z$ = 0.70, corresponding to an order-of-magnitude improvement in cluster density over previous tSZ-selected catalogs in this region (3.81 clusters per square degree). Conclusions. The overlap between SPT and Euclid data will enable a range of multiwavelength studies of the aforementioned source populations. This work serves as the first step toward joint projects between SPT and Euclid and provides a rich dataset containing information on galaxies, clusters, and their environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00298v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202555798</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A, 706, A17 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M. Archipley, A. Hryciuk, L. E. Bleem, K. Kornoelje, M. Klein, A. J. Anderson, B. Ansarinejad, M. Aravena, L. Balkenhol, P. S. Barry, K. Benabed, A. N. Bender, B. A. Benson, F. Bianchini, S. Bocquet, F. R. Bouchet, E. Camphuis, M. G. Campitiello, J. E. Carlstrom, J. Cathey, C. L. Chang, S. C. Chapman, P. Chaubal, P. M. Chichura, A. Chokshi, T. -L. Chou, A. Coerver, T. M. Crawford, C. Daley, T. de Haan, R. P. Deane, K. R. Dibert, M. A. Dobbs, M. Doohan, A. Doussot, D. Dutcher, W. Everett, C. Feng, K. R. Ferguson, K. Fichman, B. Floyd, A. Foster, S. Galli, A. E. Gambrel, R. W. Gardner, F. Ge, N. Goeckner-Wald, A. Gonzalez, S. Grandis, T. R. Greve, R. Gualtieri, F. Guidi, S. Guns, N. W. Halverson, R. Hill, E. Hivon, G. P. Holder, W. L. Holzapfel, J. C. Hood, N. Huang, F. K\'eruzor\'e, A. R. Khalife, L. Knox, M. Korman, C. -L. Kuo, K. Levy, A. E. Lowitz, C. Lu, G. P. Lynch, A. Maniyar, E. S. Martsen, F. Menanteau, M. Millea, J. Montgomery, Y. Nakato, T. Natoli, G. I. Noble, Y. Omori, A. Ouellette, Z. Pan, K. A. Phadke, A. W. Pollak, K. Prabhu, W. Quan, S. Raghunathan, M. Rahimi, A. Rahlin, C. L. Reichardt, C. Reuter, M. Rouble, J. E. Ruhl, E. Schiappucci, A. Simpson, J. A. Sobrin, B. Stalder, A. A. Stark, N. Sulzenauer, C. Tandoi, B. Thorne, C. Trendafilova, C. Umilta, J. D. Vieira, A. Vitrier, D. Vizgan, Y. Wan, A. Wei{\ss}, N. Whitehorn, W. L. K. Wu, M. R. Young, J. A. Zebrowski, D. Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational radiation reaction around a static black hole surrounded by a Dehnen type dark matter halo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08569</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08569v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the motion of a particle in the geometry of a Schwarzschild-like black hole embedded in a dark matter (DM) halo with Dehnen type density profile and calculate the orbital periods along with the evolution of the semi-latus rectum and eccentricity for extreme mass ratio inspirals (EMRIs). Such a system emits gravitational waves (GWs), and the particle's orbit evolves under radiation reaction. We also consider the effects of dynamical friction and accretion of DM on the orbital parameters. We find that the eccentricity and semi-latus rectum decrease faster with respect to the case in which EMRI is in empty spacetime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08569v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2026/02/007</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 02 (2026) 007</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Amjad Ashoorioon, Roberto Casadio, Khadije Jafarzade, Mohammad B. Jahani Poshteh, Orlando Luongo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intergalactic magnetic field lower limits up to the redshift $z\approx3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.11397v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Large-scale intergalactic magnetic fields may contain a mixture of galactic and cosmogenic contributions, that can be probed via observations of $\gamma$-ray "echo" - a delayed emission from electromagnetic cascades initiated by the highest energy photons from the sources at cosmological distances. While these fields contributions may be disentangled based on the difference in their redshift evolution, thus far indications of non-negligible magnetic field have been found only at low redshifts. This work aims at extending the intergalactic magnetic field constraints to redshifts $z\gtrsim 1$ using 17-year long all-sky observations of high-redshift active galactic nuclei with Fermi/LAT $\gamma$-ray telescope. Combing the Fermi/LAT measurements in the 0.1 GeV - 1 TeV energy range with the Monte Carlo simulations of the $\gamma$-ray "echo", it is shown that the zero field strength hypothesis at $z = [0.5; 3]$ is disfavoured at the $\approx 8.6\sigma$ significance level, yielding the lower limit of $B \gtrsim 1\times10^{-18}$ cG for the magnetic field correlation length above 1 Mpc. It is further shown that the same data put a lower limit on the volume-filling fraction of this field of $f\gtrsim 90\%$ in the redshift range considered. It is also demonstrated that the derived limits are not substantially affected by either source flux variability or the assumed $\gamma$-ray emission attenuation model. Implications of these limits for intergalactic magnetic field origin are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.11397v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jheap.2026.100577</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ievgen Vovk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Viable f(R) Scenarios Unifying Inflation with Realistic Dynamical Dark Energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.06949</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.06949v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Two $F(R)$ gravity models are tested on the basis of their viability during all stages of cosmological evolution. It is shown that these models can describe both the early-time inflationary epoch and the dark energy epoch. The models are confronted with the latest observational data, including the Pantheon+ catalogue with Type Ia supernovae, the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument measurements of baryon acoustic oscillations, the Hubble parameter estimations and data from cosmic microwave background radiation. Investigation of the viability conditions for these models, in particular, the condition $\frac{dF}{dR}&gt;0$ required a deep analysis. Both models appeared to be viable during the early-time era, but for the late-time evolution the viability conditions are not fulfilled in definite domains in the parameter spaces of these models. However the best fitted parameters, determined in confrontation with the mentioned observational data, lie far from the forbidden domains for both models. These $F(R)$ gravity models describe the observations with the large advantage over the $\Lambda$-Cold-Dark-Matter model, not only in $\chi^2$ statistics, but also with Akaike and Bayesian information criteria. This success of the two $F(R)$ gravity scenarios is connected with their capability to mimic dynamical dark energy, similarly to models with variable equation of state, that is necessary for describing the latest Pantheon+ and DESI observational data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.06949v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. D. Odintsov, V. K. Oikonomou, G. S. Sharov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of Gravitational Anomaly at Low Acceleration from a Highest-quality Sample of 36 Wide Binaries with Accurate 3D Velocities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21728</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21728v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We set out to accurately measure gravity in the low-acceleration range $(10^{-11},10^{-9})$ m s$^{-2}$ from 3D motions of isolated wide binary stars. Gaia DR3 provides precise measurements of the four sky-plane components of the 3D relative displacement and velocity ($\mathbf{r}, \mathbf{v}$) for a wide binary, but not comparably precise line-of-sight (radial) separation and relative velocity $v_{r}$. Based on our new observations and the public databases/publications, we assemble a sample of 36 nearby (distance $&lt;150$pc) wide binaries in the low-acceleration regime with accurate values of $v_{r}$ (uncertainty $&lt; 100$ m s$^{-1}$). Kinematic contaminants such as undetected stellar companions are well under control using various observational diagnostics such as Gaia's ruwe parameter, the color-magnitude diagram, multi-epoch observations of radial velocities, Speckle interferometric follow-up observations, and requiring Hipparcos-Gaia proper motion consistency. For the parameter $\Gamma \equiv \log_{10}\sqrt{\gamma}$ with $\gamma \equiv G/G_{\rm N}$ (where $G$ is a parameter generalizing Newton's constant $G_{\rm N}$ in elliptical orbits), we find $\Gamma=0.102_{-0.021}^{+0.023}$, inconsistent with standard gravity at $4.9\sigma$, giving a gravity boost factor of $\gamma=1.600_{-0.141}^{+0.171}$. Four wide binaries have 3D relative velocities exceeding their estimated Newtonian escape velocities with $1&lt;v_{\rm obs}/v_{\rm escN}\le1.2$. These systems are unlikely to be chance associations and are expected in a nonstandard paradigm such as Milgromian dynamics (MOND). The hypothesis that Newtonian gravity can be extrapolated to the low-acceleration limit is falsified by this independent study with accurate 3D velocities. Future radial velocity monitoring and Speckle interferometric imaging for larger samples will be useful to refine the present result.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21728v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. -H. Chae, B. -C. Lee, X. Hernandez, V. G. Orlov, D. Lim, D. A. Turnshek, Y. -W. Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
