<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.CO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO</link>
    <description>astro-ph.CO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.CO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 05:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>ABCMB: A Python+JAX Package for the Cosmic Microwave Background Power Spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15104v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present ABCMB, a differentiable Einstein-Boltzmann solver for the cosmic microwave background (CMB). ABCMB is a complete code capturing important effects to linear order in $\Lambda{\rm CDM}$ cosmology. It computes the CMB power spectrum and includes effects like lensing, polarization, massive neutrinos, and a state-of-the-art treatment of BBN and recombination. ABCMB has sub-percent-level agreement with CLASS and can be run on a GPU with competitive, and sometimes even faster, run times. It is refactored compared to previous codes and takes advantage of object-oriented programming to improve extensibility, meaning new physics can be added to it without the need for modifying source files. ABCMB provides accurate and stable gradients to the user, making Fisher analyses straightforward, and enabling the use of efficient gradient-based sampling methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15104v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zilu Zhou, Cara Giovanetti, Hongwan Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mimicking the large-scale structure of the Local Universe. Synthetic pre-labelled galaxies in large-scale structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15141v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Current observational and simulated large-scale structure (LSS) catalogues often lack consistency in assigning galaxies to specific structures, due to the absence of a universally accepted classification criterion. With the aim to generate synthetic empirical data for fine-tuning LSS classification algorithms, as well as to train machine learning (ML)/deep learning (DL) models for the same purpose, this work presents a purely geometrical simulation based on statistical spatial properties found in LSS surveys, using the spectroscopic main galaxy sample of the Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS) catalogue up to a redshift of z~0.1 as a specific use case. A parallelism between the LSS and the Voronoi tessellation was utilised, in which the nodes, links, surfaces, and cells of the diagram correspond to clusters, filaments, walls, and voids, respectively. The simulation used random positions within voids as seeds for tessellating the 3D space. The resulting structures were randomly populated with galaxies that adhere to the statistical properties of their observational respective structures. As the galaxies were generated, they were tagged with their corresponding structure. In each simulation, six LSS mock catalogues were generated, following the statistical behaviour observed in the SDSS catalogue, depending on the structure they belong to. The Malmquist bias and the Fingers of God effect were simulated as well. We present a novel geometrical LSS simulator, where generated galaxies mimic the statistical properties of their observational belonging structure. The simulator was tuned to mimic the SDSS catalogue, although any other catalogue can be considered. With the generated catalogue, it is possible to adjust the LSS classification algorithms, train and test ML/DL models, and benchmark several LSS classification methods using this pre-labelled data to contrast their results and performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15141v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Alc\'azar-Laynez, S. Duarte Puertas, S. Verley, G. Bl\'azquez-Calero, A. Jim\'enez, A. Lorenzo-Guti\'errez, D. Espada, M. Argudo-Fern\'andez, I. P\'erez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological Averaging in Nonminimally Coupled Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15448v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We address the challenge, commonly referred to as the cosmological averaging problem, of relating the large-scale evolution of an inhomogeneous Universe to that predicted by a homogeneous matter distribution in theories of gravity with nonminimal matter-gravity couplings. To this end, we focus on the class of $f(R,T)$ models defined by $f(R,T)=R+F(T)$, which provide a simple yet theoretically consistent realization of nonminimal matter-gravity interactions and can be reformulated as general relativity minimally coupled to a modified matter Lagrangian. Using nonstandard global monopole solutions as a toy model for realistic particles, we show that the spatial average of $F$ typically differs significantly from $F$ evaluated at the spatially averaged trace of $T$, implying that homogeneous cosmological models generally fail to capture the correct large-scale dynamics of the Universe. We further show that dust in these theories generally exhibits a non-vanishing proper pressure. Our results underscore the necessity of properly accounting for spatial averaging when modeling cosmology in theories with nonminimal matter-gravity couplings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15448v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. R. Pinto, P. P. Avelino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Quantum Genetic Algorithm with application to Cosmological Parameters Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15459v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An Amplitude-Encoded Quantum Genetic Algorithm (AEQGA) has been developed to minimize $\chi^2$ functions of different cosmological probes (Supernovae Type Ia, Baryon Acoustic Oscillations, Cosmic Microwave Background Radiation), to find the best-fit value for two cosmological parameters, namely the Hubble Constant and the density matter content of the Universe today. Our main aim is to pave the way to testing the adoption of quantum optimization in the inference of the cosmological parameters that describe the universe evolution. AEQGA computes the merit function classically, and then uses a quantum circuit to entangle the population and perform crossover and mutation operations. The results show consistency with the isocontours of the objective functions. We then tested the general behavior of AEQGA as a function of its hyperparameters and compared it with a second quantum genetic algorithm found in the literature as well as with classical algorithms, finding consistent results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15459v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.ascom.2026.101078</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Astronomy and Computing 101078, 2026</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Sarracino, Vincenzo Fabrizio Cardone, Roberto Scaramella, Giuseppe Riccio, Andrea Bulgarelli, Carlo Burigana, Luca Cappelli, Stefano Cavuoti, Farida Farsian, Irene Graziotti, Massimo Meneghetti, Giuseppe Murante, Niccol\`o Parmiggiani, Alessandro Rizzo, Francesco Schillir\`o, Vincenzo Testa, Tiziana Trombetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling solutions in three-form cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15498v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A hybrid three-form model of dark energy is developed in order to identify scaling solutions, a long-sought feature in three-form cosmology. Exploiting Hodge dualities, the theory is formulated in terms of two scalar functions that are associated with the conjugate momentum, and the three-form dual vector in an isotropic background. The resulting Lagrangian yields a stable scaling attractor where the three-form energy density tracks the dominant background fluid. A dynamical mechanism is also identified that naturally drives the system out of this regime toward a late-time accelerated phase distinguishable from a cosmological constant. This constitutes the first realization of scaling behavior within a three-form dark energy framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15498v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vitor da Fonseca, Bruno J. Barros, Tiago Barreiro, Nelson J. Nunes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmic topology. Part IIc. Detectability with non-standard primordial power spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15527v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Non-trivial spatial topology of the Universe can imprint potentially observable signatures on the cosmic microwave background (CMB). In this study, we investigate how deviations from the standard nearly-scale-free primordial power spectrum impact observables for the fully compact, orientable Euclidean topologies ($E_1$--$E_6$). We examine how such deviations modify the detectability of the underlying topology, depending on whether they are an intrinsic consequence of non-trivial topology or independent of it. We compute CMB temperature correlation matrices across a range of topologies, fundamental domain sizes, and observer locations for both standard and modified primordial power spectra. The impact of these modifications on the detectability of topology is quantified using the Kullback-Leibler divergence, providing an estimate of the distinguishability of non-trivial and simply-connected topologies based solely on CMB temperature observations. In addition, we employ the CatBoost machine learning algorithm to classify harmonic-space realizations of CMB temperature maps and thereby assess the observational prospects for topology detection. Signatures of non-trivial topology are encoded in the off-diagonal structure of the CMB temperature correlation matrices and are most prominent on the largest angular scales. Deviations from the simple power-law primordial spectrum at these scales can substantially alter the detectability of topology, either enhancing its characteristic CMB imprints or suppressing them below observational sensitivity. Our results demonstrate that uncertainties in the primordial power spectrum must be carefully accounted for in robust searches for cosmic topology using the CMB.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15527v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joline Noltmann (COMPACT Collaboration), Andrius Tamosiunas (COMPACT Collaboration), Deyan P. Mihaylov (COMPACT Collaboration), Yashar Akrami (COMPACT Collaboration), Javier Carr\'on Duque (COMPACT Collaboration), Thiago S. Pereira (COMPACT Collaboration), Glenn D. Starkman (COMPACT Collaboration), George Alestas (COMPACT Collaboration), Stefano Anselmi (COMPACT Collaboration), Craig J. Copi (COMPACT Collaboration), Fernando Cornet-Gomez (COMPACT Collaboration), Andrew H. Jaffe (COMPACT Collaboration), Arthur Kosowsky (COMPACT Collaboration), Mikel Martin Barandiaran (COMPACT Collaboration), Anna Negro (COMPACT Collaboration), Amirhossein Samandar (COMPACT Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An observational test of the plasma lensing effect using QSOs with and without MgII absorption</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15558v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Radio wave propagation can be perturbed by compact ionized gas clumps through plasma lensing, which induces frequency dependent magnification and may distort the observed number counts of background sources. The quasar (QSO) number densities are a powerful probe for understanding the effects of intervening material. Absorption lines in QSO spectra reveal the presence of interstellar and intergalactic gas, which can change observed fluxes through dust extinction and plasma lensing. By combining observations from radio (VLASS), infrared (WISE), and optical bands (DESI), we assembled a sample of QSOs: ~4000 sources with MgII absorbers, and ~12, 000 non-absorbers. In the radio band, the MgII sample shows a moderate excess at the bright end of the flux distribution, which is broadly consistent with plasma lensing predications. In the optical, the MgII sample turns over at higher g-band fluxes and exhibits a steeper decline at the faint end than the non-MgII sample. Control samples were constructed by matching in redshift, infrared (W1), and optical (g) luminosities. In these comparisons, the radio excess becomes less prominent, suggesting that the apparent magnification may not be robust evidence for plasma lensing. Nevertheless, a weak contribution cannot be ruled out, especially given residual excess observed at the bright end relative to the non-MgII sample. Dust extinction along the line-of-sight remains a plausible alternative. Regardless of the dominant mechanism, the multi-wavelength differences offer a valuable probe of the physical state of the intervening medium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15558v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinzhong Er, Yiping Shu, Chenxu Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast computation of temperature and polarization coupling matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15605</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15605v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a fast and exact method for computing CMB mode-coupling matrices based on an optimised evaluation of Wigner-3j symbols. The method exploits analytic structure in the relevant Wigner-3j symbol configurations appearing in temperature and polarization coupling matrices, expressing all required quantities in terms of a small set of recurrence-generated values which are precomputed and stored in lookup tables. This approach reduces the computational cost of constructing the full coupling matrices whilst maintaining numerical accuracy.
  We demonstrate the performance of the threej_cosmo implementation using realistic survey masks from current CMB experiments. Relative to standard recursion-based approaches used in existing pseudo-C_l pipelines, the method achieves speedups of 6-25x in practical coupling-matrix constructions, with the largest gains occurring at high multipoles. The algorithm admits efficient parallelisation on both CPUs and GPUs, the latter providing additional acceleration, up to a further order of 50 on modern hardware, without altering the underlying formalism.
  Beyond full matrix construction, the approach is naturally suited to applications in which only a restricted set of l3 modes is required for each (l1,l2) pair, such as in the computation of band-limited coupling matrices and analytic covariance terms. These features make threej_cosmo a practical backend for pseudo-C_l estimation and related calculations in next-generation CMB analysis pipelines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15605v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georgia Kiddier, Steven Gratton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for Axion-like particle Dark Matter with Time-domain Polarization: Constraints from a protoplanetary disk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15611</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15611v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Axion-like particles (ALPs) can induce a birefringence effect that rotates the polarization angle of light, offering a probe of ultralight dark matter. We analyze archival near-infrared polarimetric data of the protoplanetary disk (PPD) around HD 163296. Whereas previous studies considered only single-epoch snapshots, we perform a consistent multi-epoch time-series analysis, extracting the polarization angle and its uncertainty from the polarized images. The resulting six-epoch time series is consistent with a constant polarization angle within the measurement uncertainties, while being sensitive to timescales of $\sim 170-400$ days. The typical polarization angle uncertainties are $1.6$--$6.4$ degrees, partly driven by multiple scattering in the optically thick disk, which broadens the intrinsic polarization angle distribution and introduces additional dispersion in the representative polarization angle. Based on these data, we derive the first upper limits on the ALP-photon coupling from PPD polarization variability, $g_{a\gamma} \lesssim 7.5 \times 10^{-12} (m_a / 10^{-22}\,{\rm eV})\,{\rm GeV}^{-1}$. Furthermore, we forecast that achieving a polarization angle uncertainty of $\sigma \sim 0.1$ degrees would enable world-leading sensitivity to ALP-induced birefringence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15611v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kanako Narita, Tomohiro Fujita, Ryo Tazaki, Bunyo Hatsukade</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting the neutrino mass via the cross-correlation between matter tracers and the ISWRS effect?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15688</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15688v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work explores the potential to detect the nonlinear Integrated Sachs Wolfe effect, namely the Rees-Sciama effect (ISWRS), by cross-correlating current and future Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) experiments -- Simons Observatory, CMB-S4, CMB-HD, and PICO -- with ongoing Large Scale Structure (LSS) surveys, such as Euclid and the Vera Rubin Observatory (LSST). We model the cross-correlation of the ISWRS effect with gravitational potential tracers like galaxy clustering, cosmic shear, and CMB-lensing potential, to forecast results from these experiments. Our analysis also accounts for the presence of massive neutrinos to assess the feasibility of identifying the $\nu$$\Lambda$CDM model and constraining the neutrino mass sum, M$\nu$. Our findings indicate that the CMB-lensing potential reconstructed by CMB-HD is expected to provide the most promising results, achieving $\gtrsim$ 5$\sigma$ detections even under conservative assumptions for detector noise and foregrounds, thereby allowing differentiation between $\nu$$\Lambda$CDM models. Galaxy clustering can also yield significant detections, whereas cosmic shear can provide valuable results only if non-linearities are accurately modelled, beyond the capabilities of currently available analytical approaches. These latter LSS probes do not provide strong constraining power on M$\nu$. While our findings suggest that future CMB experiments and LSS surveys will enable the detection of the ISWRS effect, they do not imply significant prospects for imposing new constraints on neutrino masses in the near future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15688v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viviana Cuozzo, Marina Migliaccio, Matteo Calabrese, Carmelita Carbone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nearest Neighbour-Based Statistics for 21cm-Galaxy Cross-Correlations in the Epoch of Reionization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15803v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: 21cm radiation from neutral hydrogen serves as a direct probe of the Epoch of Reionization. However, both its detection and physical interpretation are severely hindered by contamination from astrophysical foreground emission and instrumental noise that are several orders of magnitude brighter than the signal of interest. A promising way to tackle these challenges is to cross-correlate the 21cm signal with other independent tracers of large-scale structure, most notably high-redshift galaxies. Besides validating putative 21cm detections, such joint analyses are expected to provide independent insights into the properties of ionizing sources and the evolving morphology of ionized regions during reionization. The 21cm signal, however, is intrinsically highly non-Gaussian, limiting the effectiveness of conventional two-point cross-correlation statistics, which capture information only up to the second order. In this work, we therefore investigate the utility of k-nearest-neighbour cumulative distribution functions (kNN CDF), which encode information from the joint clustering at all orders, as an alternative framework for probing 21cm-galaxy cross-correlations. Using self-consistently simulated mock 21cm fields and a catalog of line-emitting galaxies at z = 7, we conducted a proof-of-concept study comparing the kNN CDF formalism and the two-point cross-correlation approach. We find that the kNN CDF statistics outperform the two-point statistics in detecting 21cm-galaxy cross-correlations, even in the presence of instrumental noise and aggressive foreground filtering. Moreover, at a fixed global ionized fraction, it is even able to differentiate between reionization models that remain indistinguishable using two-point statistics. These results demonstrate the power and unexplored potential of exploiting higher-order statistics for extracting maximal information from 21cm-galaxy synergies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15803v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anirban Chakraborty, Kwanit Gangopadhyay, Arka Banerjee, Tirthankar Roy Choudhury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model selection with the Pantheon+ Type Ia SN sample</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15047v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent discoveries, e.g., by JWST and DESI, have elevated the level of tension with inflationary $\Lambda$CDM. For example, the empirical evidence now suggests that the standard model violates at least one of the energy conditions from general relativity, which were designed to ensure that systems have positive energy, attractive gravity and non-superluminal energy flows. In this Letter, we use a recently compiled Type Ia supernova sample to examine whether $\Lambda$CDM violates the energy conditions in the local Universe, and carry out model selection with its principal competitor, the $R_{\rm h}=ct$ universe. We derive model-independent constraints on the distance modulus based on the energy conditions and compare these with the Hubble diagram predicted by both $\Lambda$CDM and $R_{\rm h}=ct$, using the Pantheon+ Type Ia supernova catalog. We find that $\Lambda$CDM violates the strong energy condition over the redshift range $z \subset (0, 2)$, whereas $R_{\rm h}=ct$ satisfies all four energy constraints. At the same time, $R_{\rm h}=ct$ is favored by these data over $\Lambda$CDM with a likelihood of $\sim 89.5\%$ versus $\sim 10.5\%$. The $R_{\rm h}=ct$ model without inflation is strongly favored by the Type Ia supernova data over the currrent standard model, while simultaneously adhering to the general relativistic energy conditions at both high and low redshifts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15047v1</guid>
      <category>physics.gen-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Namit Chandak, Fulvio Melia, Junjie Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>May Negative Mass Objects exist in the sky?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15058</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15058v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We conjecture the possibility of negative mass objects (NMOs) existing in the sky. It is shown that they may not be so exotic as usually expected. We show that NMOs appear as solutions of standard gravitational equations if we consider the system of a compact positive mass object, cosmological fluid and negative cosmological constant. We also construct models which generate such NMOs as solutions within the two-scalar theory and scalar-Einstein-Gauss-Bonnet gravity inspired by string theory. The orbits of the photon and massive particles are investigated in the background, where there is a negative mass object which realises a kind of effective anti-gravity. It is explicitly found that the bound system consisting of a positive mass object and a negative mass object can be formed in spite that a positive mass object suffers the repulsive force from the NMO. The possibility that such exotic objects might be observed is discussed. A simple conjecture about their possible masses is made, too. As an even more exotic object, we consider a non-trivial object with vanishing mass and investigate its properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15058v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shin'ichi Nojiri, S. D. Odintsov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intracluster globular clusters as tracers of the mass assembly of the Hydra I galaxy cluster</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15099v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In galaxy clusters, hierarchical assembly predicts the formation of stellar substructures and intracluster light (ICL), a diffuse stellar component tracing the global cluster potential. Because these features are extremely faint, alternative tracers such as globular clusters (GCs) provide a powerful tool to study cluster assembly. We use deep VLT/FORS $V$- and $I$-band imaging to investigate the GC population in the nearby Hydra I galaxy cluster ($\sim 45.7$ Mpc). GC candidates were selected from the $VI$ colour-magnitude diagram and divided into blue and red subpopulations. We find a clear spatial dichotomy: red GCs are concentrated around the massive central galaxies NGC 3311 and NGC 3309, while blue GCs are more extended and offset from the centre, coinciding with a secondary peak of X-ray-emitting gas. In the central regions, GC spatial distributions further depend on stellar population properties: young metal-rich GCs are more extended and may be linked to ram-pressure stripping, whereas old metal-poor GCs are more centrally concentrated, possibly originating from disrupted dwarf galaxies. Comparing the GC number density profiles to the surface brightness profile of NGC 3311, we find that the red GCs closely follow the galaxy light, while the blue population significantly deviates from it and traces the global gravitational potential of the cluster. This is also reflected in the specific frequency of blue GCs, which is approximately $\sim 5\times$ higher in the ICL-dominated outskirts than in the inner regions dominated by red GCs. Finally, we present a novel method to constrain the evolution of the galaxy luminosity function of the cluster using GC specific frequencies and colour distributions, yielding a past faint-end slope of $\alpha=-1.81^{+0.16}_{-0.16}$ compared to $\alpha=-1.41^{+0.08}_{-0.05}$ today, consistent with high-redshift observations and cosmological simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15099v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felipe S. Lohmann, Magda Arnaboldi, Michael Hilker, Andreas Burkert, Marilena Spavone, Ortwin Gerhard, Marina Rejkuba, Marco Mirabile, Michele Cantiello, Enrichetta Iodice</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The diverse nature of spiral arms in the Auriga Superstars cosmological hydrodynamic simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15108</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15108v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The dynamical nature and formation mechanism(s) of galactic spiral arms remain long-standing problems in astrophysics. Most theoretical work is based on analytic calculations or idealised simulations, which has yielded several theories of spiral structure. The radial profile of the spiral arm rotation speed - the pattern speed - is a key observable prediction of these theories. However, observations that infer spiral pattern speeds reveal a mixed picture with no clear consensus. Here, we expand on theoretical efforts by examining the pattern speed profiles in the Auriga Superstars set of high-resolution cosmological magnetohydrodynamic simulatons of Milky Way-mass spiral disc galaxies. These simulations combine galaxy formation in a cosmological environment with the high dynamical fidelity afforded by an $\sim 800$ $\rm M_{\odot}$ star particle resolution, giving $\sim 100$ million star particles in the disc. We show that several different spiral arm theories are realised among our simulations, including large-scale kinematic density waves, manifold spirals, dynamic (co-rotating) spirals, and overlapping modes. In particular, we demonstrate that a strong tidal interaction leads to clear kinematic density waves, and that manifold spirals are present in a strongly-barred galaxy. Interestingly, we find that the same galaxy may show qualitative evolution of their spiral pattern speed profiles, indicating that the nature of spiral arms can evolve on potentially sub-Gigayear timescales. Our results demonstrate that in the absence of a strong external encounter or a strong bar, galactic spiral structure is highly transitional and complex with no clear long-lived underlying wave.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15108v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert J J Grand, Francesca Fragkoudi, R\"udiger Pakmor, Facundo A G\'omez, Freeke van de Voort, Rebekka Bieri, Sophie Townson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring Pulsar Distances from Chirping Orbital Periods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15110v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The observed orbital period time derivative (or orbital "chirp") of a millisecond binary pulsar (MSP) encodes information about both the intrinsic properties of the binary system and its environment. Orbital chirp has contributions from intrinsic energy loss due to gravitational wave emission, kinematic effects due to motion in the plane of the sky, and dynamical effects due to galactic acceleration, with the latter two contributions depending on the MSP distance. We use orbital chirp data to infer distances to 21 MSPs; and for four of which we obtain smaller uncertainties than those reported in previous distance measurements. We incorporate multiple realistic galactic acceleration models to assess the sensitivity of the inferred distances to the choice of galactic gravitational potential, finding a significant dependence for four MSPs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15110v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brady Egleston, Reza Ebadi, Ronald Walsworth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calibrating the Tip of the Red Giant Branch and measuring Magellanic Cloud distances to 2% exclusively with Gaia</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15421v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We have calibrated the Tip of the Red Giant Branch (TRGB) using our recent catalog of homogeneous, high-accuracy Globular Cluster (GC) distances. The GC distances were determined by a global joint fit to optical period-Wesenheit relations of their member RR Lyrae stars and type-II Cepheids, anchored by trigonometric parallaxes; all data taken from the ESA Gaia mission's (early) third data release (GDR3). Using I-band measurements in 48 GCs from P. Stetson's database, we determined $M_{I,0} = -3.948^{+0.037}_{-0.034}$ mag (1.6% in distance). Calibrating the TRGB using Gaia's homogeneous, space-based RP photometry of 53 GCs, we found $M_{RP,0} = -3.807^{+0.041}_{-0.035}$ mag (1.8%). The stated uncertainties include statistical and systematic effects, including the correlated nature of the GC distances. The robustness of our calibrations is demonstrated via tests against small-number statistics and analysis choices. Specifically, we found no significant metallicity effect for our sample of old, low-metallicity GCs. We measured $\sim 2\%$ distances to the Large (LMC) and Small Magellanic Clouds (SMC), $18.447^{+0.036}_{-0.042}$ mag ($48.9 \pm 0.9$ kpc) and $18.898^{+0.049}_{-0.054}$ mag ($60.2 \pm 1.4$ kpc), respectively, using a single well calibrated photometric system: RP (spectro-)photometry from GDR3. Our new TRGB distances, whose absolute scale derives from Gaia parallaxes, are fully independent of the well-known detached eclipsing binary (DEB) distances and agree with them to within the uncertainties. Combining our new TRGB and existing DEB distances, we illustrate how additional constraints may be incorporated in the Local Distance Network and obtain $H_0 = 73.52 \pm 0.80$ km/s/Mpc. Expected improvements due to the upcoming fourth Gaia data release are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15421v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mauricio Cruz Reyes, Richard I. Anderson, Bastian Lengen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primordial black hole evaporation in a thermal bath and gravitational waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15441</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15441v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Primordial black holes (PBHs) formed in the early Universe evaporate via Hawking radiation and constitute a generic source of stochastic gravitational waves. Existing studies of gravitational wave production from evaporating PBHs typically assume vacuum evaporation, neglecting the fact that PBHs in the early Universe are embedded in a hot thermal plasma. In this work, we investigate gravitational wave production from primordial black holes whose evaporation is thermally influenced by their surrounding environment. We adopt a thermal evaporation framework in which interactions with the ambient plasma modify the effective decay rate of the black hole, leading to enhanced mass loss at early times and a redistribution of the evaporation history compared to the standard non-thermal vacuum case. Since graviton emission is intrinsically tied to the evaporation history of PBHs, these thermal effects play a crucial role in determining the timing and spectral properties of the resulting stochastic gravitational wave background. Our results provide a consistent framework for incorporating thermal effects into gravitational wave production from evaporating primordial black holes and set the stage for a detailed analysis of their observational signatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15441v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arnab Chaudhuri, Kousik Loho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning for Point Spread Function Modeling in Cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15780</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15780v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the development of a data-driven, AI-based model of the Point Spread Function (PSF) that achieves higher accuracy than the current state-of-the-art approach, "PSF in the Full Field-of-View'' (PIFF). PIFF is widely used in leading weak-lensing surveys, including the Dark Energy Survey (DES), the Hyper Suprime-Cam (HSC) Survey, and the Vera C. Rubin Observatory Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST). The PSF characterizes how a point source, such as a star, is imaged after its light traverses the atmosphere and telescope optics, effectively representing the "blurred fingerprint'' of the entire imaging system. Accurate PSF modeling is essential for weak gravitational lensing analyses, as biases in its estimation propagate directly into cosmic shear measurements -- one of the primary cosmological probes of the expansion history of the Universe and the growth of large-scale structure for dark energy studies. To address the limitations of PIFF, which constructs PSF models independently for each CCD and therefore loses spatial coherence across the focal plane, we introduce a deep-learning-based framework for PSF reconstruction. In this approach, an autoencoder is trained on stellar images obtained with the Hyper Suprime-Cam (HSC) of the Subaru Telescope and combined with a Gaussian process to interpolate the PSF across the telescope's full field of view. This hybrid model captures systematic variations across the focal plane and achieves a reconstruction error of $3.4 \times 10^{-6}$ compared to PIFF's $3.7 \times 10^{-6}$, laying the foundation for integration into the LSST Science Pipelines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15780v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Revista eSpectra, Vol. 4, Num. 1, 2026</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Dayana Andrea Henao Arbel\'aez, Pierre-Fran\c{c}ois L\'eget, Andr\'es Alejandro Plazas Malag\'on</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hubble-Scale Tachyonic Shocks from Low-Scale Inflation -- A New Gravitational-Wave Window on Inflation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15825v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Current bounds on the tensor-to-scalar ratio imply that the energy scale of inflation may lie below the grand-unified scale. In this paper, we show that in a broad class of single-field inflation models with sufficiently small energy scales, an extremely efficient tachyonic instability develops at the end of inflation. This instability rapidly drives the system into a nonlinear regime before coherent oscillations can be established, leading to a first-order phase-transition--like phenomenon without tunneling or barrier crossing. The resulting ultra-relativistic shock fronts surrounding the bubble interiors expand to near the Hubble scale, corresponding to the most strongly enhanced tachyonic modes, and collide with one another, producing energetic inflaton particles and gravitational waves. As a result, the post-inflationary dynamics can differ significantly from the conventional high-scale inflationary scenario. Interestingly, inflation at MeV--EeV energy scales can be probed via gravitational-wave observations, including pulsar timing arrays, ground-based detectors, and future space-based experiments. Recent limits from the LIGO--KAGRA--Virgo collaboration already constrain EeV-scale inflation, while pulsar timing array results may be interpreted as evidence for gravitational waves generated by GeV-scale inflation. We also briefly discuss further implications of the resulting tachyonic shocks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15825v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haruto Masubuchi, Yuma Narita, Wen Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Astrometric constraints on stochastic gravitational wave background with neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15879v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Astrometric measurements provide a unique avenue for constraining the stochastic gravitational wave background (SGWB). In this work, we investigate the application of two neural network architectures, a fully connected network and a graph neural network, for analyzing astrometric data to detect the SGWB. Specifically, we generate mock Gaia astrometric measurements of the proper motions of sources and train two networks to predict the energy density of the SGWB, $\Omega_\text{GW}$. We evaluate the performance of both models under varying input datasets to assess their robustness across different configurations. We also perform a direct comparison with a likelihood-based approach using Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) methods, finding out that the neural-network-based approach is significantly faster, taking on the order of minutes, compared to MCMC's order of days, while still capturing the same features in the data. Our results demonstrate that neural networks can effectively constrain the SGWB, showing promise as tools for addressing systematic uncertainties and modeling limitations that pose challenges for traditional likelihood-based methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15879v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/b6n8-gjwk</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 113, 043522 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Marienza Caldarola, Gonzalo Morr\'as, Santiago Jaraba, Sachiko Kuroyanagi, Savvas Nesseris, Juan Garc\'ia-Bellido</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational waves from cosmic strings for pedestrians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20907v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Cosmic strings represent an attractive source of gravitational waves (GWs) from the early Universe. However, numerical computation of the GW signal from cosmic strings requires the evaluation of complicated integral and sum expressions, which can become computationally costly in large parameter scans. This motivates us to rederive the GW signal from a network of local stable cosmic strings in the Nambu-Goto approximation and based on the velocity-dependent one-scale model from a ``pedestrian'' perspective. That is, we derive purely analytical expressions for the total GW spectrum, which remain exact wherever possible and whose error can be tracked and reduced in a controlled way in crucial situations in which we are forced to introduce approximations. In this way, we obtain powerful formulas that, unlike existing results in the literature, are valid across the entire frequency spectrum and across the entire conceivable range of cosmic-string tensions. We provide an in-depth discussion of the GW spectra thus obtained, including their characteristic break frequencies and approximate power-law behaviors, comment on the effect of changes in the effective number of degrees of freedom during radiation domination, and conclude with a concise summary of our main formulas that can readily be used in future studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20907v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2026/01/025</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP01(2026)025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kai Schmitz, Tobias Schroeder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Influence of finite-temperature effects on CMB power spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07469</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07469v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore the implications of finite-temperature quantum field theory effects on cosmological parameters within the framework of the $\L$CDM model and its modification. By incorporating temperature-dependent corrections to the cosmological constant, we extend the standard cosmological model to include additional density parameters, $\Omega_{\L_2}$ and $\Omega_{\L_3}$, which arise from finite-T quantum gravitational effects. Using the Cosmic Linear Anisotropy Solving System (CLASS), we analyze the impact of these corrections on the cosmic microwave background power spectrum and compare the results with the Planck 2018 data. Through brute-force parameter scans and advanced machine learning techniques, including quartic regression, we demonstrate that the inclusion of $\Omega_{\L_2}$ and $\Omega_{\L_3}$ improves the model's predictive accuracy, achieving higher $R^2$ values, lower mean squared error, and lower AIC/BIC scores than those of the $\L$CDM model. Despite identified methodological limitations, these findings establish an exploratory framework for incorporating finite-temperature quantum corrections into precision cosmology and open new avenues for data-driven parameter inference.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07469v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. Y. Park, P. Y. Wui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic analysis of finite-temperature effects on cosmological parameters by artificial neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02223v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore the impact of finite-temperature quantum gravity effects on cosmological parameters, particularly the cosmological constant $\Lambda$, by incorporating temperature-dependent quantum corrections into the Hubble parameter. For that purpose, we modify the Cosmic Linear Anisotropy Solving System. We introduce new density parameters, $\Omega_{\Lambda_2}$ and $\Omega_{\Lambda_3}$, arising from finite-temperature quantum gravity contributions, and analyze their influence on the cosmic microwave background power spectrum using advanced machine learning techniques, including artificial neural networks and stochastic optimization. Our results reveal that $\Omega_{\Lambda_2}$ assumes a negative value, consistent with dimensional regularization in renormalization and that the presence of $\Omega_{\Lambda_2}$ as well as $\Omega_{\Lambda_3}$ enhances model accuracy. Numerical analyses demonstrate that the inclusion of these parameters improves the fit to 2018 Planck data. Although further work is required, our results suggest that finite-temperature quantum gravity effects may play a non-negligible role in cosmological evolution. Although the Hubble tension persists, our findings highlight the potential of quantum gravitational corrections in refining cosmological models and motivate further investigation into higher-order thermal effects and polarization data constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02223v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Armin Hatefi, Ehsan Hatefi, I. Y. Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Carnegie Supernova Project: Fast-Declining Type Ia Supernovae as Cosmological Distance Indicators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07093v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, the suitability of fast-declining Type Ia supernovae (SNe Ia) as cosmological standard candles is examined utilizing a Hubble Flow sample of 43 of these objects observed by the Carnegie Supernova Project (CSP). We confirm previous suggestions that fast-declining SNe Ia offer a viable method for estimating distances to early-type galaxies when the color-stretch parameter, $s_{BV}$, is used as a measure of the light curve shape. As a test, we employ the Tripp method, which models the absolute magnitude at maximum as a function of light curve shape and color. We calibrate the sample using 12 distance moduli based on published Infrared Surface Brightness Fluctuations to derive a value of the Hubble constant that is in close agreement with the value obtained for the full sample of CSP SNe Ia using the same methodology. We also develop a new and simple method of estimating the distances of fast decliners based only on their colors at maximum (and not light curve shape) and find that it leads to similar results as with using the Tripp method. This "Color" technique is a powerful tool that is unique to fast-declining SNe Ia. We show that the colors of the fast decliners at maximum light are strongly affected by photospheric temperature differences and not solely due to dust extinction, and provide a physical rationale for this effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07093v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. M. Phillips, Syed A. Uddin, Christopher R. Burns, Nicholas B. Suntzeff, C. Ashall, E. Baron, L. Galbany, P. Hoeflich, E. Y. Hsiao, Nidia Morrell, S. E. Persson, Maximilian Stritzinger, Carlos Contreras, Wendy L. Freedman, Kevin Krisciunas, S. Kumar, J. Lu, Anthony L. Piro, M. Shahbandeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark-to-black super accretion as a mechanism for early supermassive black hole growth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00644</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00644v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The discovery of supermassive black holes with masses $\gtrsim 10^9 M_\odot$ at redshifts $z\gtrsim 10$ challenges conventional formation scenarios based on baryonic accretion and mergers within the first few hundred million years. We propose an alternative channel in which ultralight scalar dark matter undergoes dark-to-black conversion via quasi-bound state depletion around black hole seeds. We estimate the accretion rate of the scalar field as a function of the boson mass parameter $\mu$ and the black hole mass $M_{\rm BH}$, and integrate this rate over cosmological timescales. Our results show that once a critical value of $\mu M_{\rm BH}$ is reached, scalar field accretion becomes highly efficient, enabling substantial black hole growth even from relatively small initial seed masses. For boson masses $\mu \sim 10^{-19}-10^{-16}\,\mathrm{eV}$, black hole seeds of $10^2-10^5 M_\odot$ can reach $10^6-10^8 M_\odot$ within $\sim 10^8$ yr. This dark-to-black mechanism provides a natural pathway for the rapid formation of massive black holes in the early universe, offering a potential probe of the microphysical nature of dark matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00644v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Sanchis-Gual, Juan Barranco, Juan Carlos Degollado, Dar\'io Nu\~nez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond CPL: Evidence for dynamical dark energy in three-parameter models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03779</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03779v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce two three-parameter extensions of the minimal Akhtar-Hossain (mAH) dark energy parametrization, termed modified minimal AH (MmAH1 and MmAH2), which provide a smooth and bounded evolution of the dark energy equation of state while retaining $\Lambda$CDM as a limiting case. Using a joint analysis of the CMB compressed likelihood, DESI DR2 BAO, $H(z)$, redshift space distortions, and three SNeIa samples (PantheonPlus, Union3, and DESY5), we compare these models with $\Lambda$CDM, $w$CDM, mAH, CPL, and the three-parameter CPL-$w_{\rm b}$ extension. The standard cosmological parameters remain stable across all models, while CPL, MmAH1 and MmAH2 parametrizations yield modest but consistent improvements in fit ($\Delta\chi^2\simeq-6$ to $-12$ for PantheonPlus and Union3, and $\simeq-38$ for DESY5). Statistical consistency with $\Lambda$CDM, quantified via the Mahalanobis distance in one, two, and three dimensional parameter subspaces, reveals mild to moderate deviations, $\sim2$--$2.5\sigma$ for $+$PantheonPlus, $2$--$3\sigma$ for $+$Union3, and up to $4$--$5\sigma$ for $+$DESY5 combination, depending on model complexity. Among all extensions CPL, MmAH1 and MmAH2 provide the most stable and physically coherent representations of dynamical dark energy, maintaining moderate tensions with $\Lambda$CDM and well behaved parameter correlations. Overall, these results indicate consistent evidence for departures from $\Lambda$CDM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03779v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sonej Alam, Md. Wali Hossain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crosschecking Cosmic Distances from DESI BAO and DES SNe Points to Systematics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04179</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04179v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We perform a consistency check of DESI DR2 BAO constraints ($D_M/r_d, D_H/r_d)$ by reconstructing the same quantities from DES supernovae (SNe) in bins with the same effective redshift $z_{\textrm{eff}}$. We find that the ratio of $D_M/r_d$ values are consistent with a horizontal, thus confirming that the distance duality relation holds up to calibration. However, the $D_H/r_d$ ratio shows a decreasing trend with $z_{\textrm{eff}}$ at $2.3 \sigma$ to $2.5 \sigma$ that cannot be explained by physics. We demonstrate that the result does not depend on the choice of late Universe cosmological model, but the radius of the sound horizon $r_d$ has a much greater influence. Studying ratios of $D_H/r_d$ is a stronger test than the distance duality relation, and the rejection of a horizontal confirms systematics in either DESI BAO or DES SNe. Underscoring the potential for systematics, in the appendix we show that replacing DES with DES-Dovekie SNe reduces the significance to at most $1.7 \sigma$. Claims of new physics based on combined data still have rudimentary hurdles to clear.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04179v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mauricio Lopez-Hernandez, Eoin \'O Colg\'ain, Saeed Pourojaghi, M. M. Sheikh-Jabbari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Gaussianity in SMICA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22641v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a new formalism for the component separation method Spectral Matching Independent Component Analysis (SMICA) in order to include the information contained in the foregrounds beyond second-order statistics. We also develop a binned bispectrum estimator that works directly using maps of different frequency channels, capable of determining the bispectrum of multiple components at the same time, shifting the traditional approach to non-Gaussianity estimation from a cleaned map to the component separation step, for a better handling of foreground uncertainty. We test our method on 400 E and B polarization simulations based on the LiteBIRD experiment, containing the two main sources of contamination for CMB polarization experiments: polarized dust and synchrotron emission. We show that the bispectrum does not improve the precision of the power spectrum estimation or of the spectral parameters. However, we are capable of recovering the correct 3-point correlator of the foregrounds and standard constraints on primordial non-Gaussianity in a coherent multi-frequency and multi-component framework. The advantage of our approach is that it combines data in an optimal way accounting for the power spectrum and the bispectrum of the various components, which is not true for the standard approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22641v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Citran, H. V. Tran, G. Patanchon, B. van Tent</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is cosmic birefringence due to dark energy or dark matter? Simulation-based inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.12019v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Simulation-based inference (SBI) is a powerful inference technique for cases where the exact functional form of the likelihood is not known. A prime example is the likelihood of cross-correlation power spectra of the cosmic microwave background (CMB) fields at low multipoles, $\ell\lesssim 10$. In this paper, we investigate a parity-violating cross-correlation between $E$- and $B$- mode polarization fields using SBI. The $EB$ correlation at low $\ell$ is essential to distinguish between possible axion dark energy and dark matter interpretations of `cosmic birefringence', a rotation of the plane of linear polarization of the CMB, recently reported from WMAP, Planck, and Atacama Cosmology Telescope data. We use neural likelihood estimation to infer the likelihood of the $EB$ correlation at low $\ell$ and show that it is highly non-Gaussian. We then employ neural posterior estimation to constrain the scalar field mass ($m_\phi$), the cosmic birefringence amplitude ($g\phi_\mathrm{in}/2$), and the instrumental miscalibration angle ($\alpha$), from simulated datasets. We find that the posterior on $m_{\phi}$ shows two regimes, with a transition marked by $10^{-32}$ eV, highlighting a strong sensitivity to the scale dependence of cosmic birefringence. To quantify this behavior, we compute the probability $p(m_{\phi} &lt; 10^{-32}$ eV) for various fiducial values of $m_{\phi}$. We find that $\alpha$ and the contribution of lensed $B$ modes ultimately limit our ability to exclude the dark energy scenario fully.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.12019v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Florie Carralot, Patricia Diego-Palazuelos, Adriaan J. Duivenvoorden, Eiichiro Komatsu, Nicoletta Krachmalnicoff, Carlo Baccigalupi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explaining the PeV Neutrino Fluxes at KM3NeT and IceCube with Quasi-Extremal Primordial Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22722v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The KM3NeT experiment has recently observed a neutrino with an energy around 100PeV, and IceCube has detected five neutrinos with energies above 1PeV. While there are no known astrophysical sources, exploding primordial black holes could have produced these high-energy neutrinos. For Schwarzschild black holes this interpretation results in tensions between the burst rates inferred from the KM3NeT and IceCube observations, with indirect constraints from the extragalactic gamma ray background and with the non-observation of an associated gamma ray signal at LHAASO. In this letter we show that if there is a population of primordial black holes charged under a new dark $u(1)$ symmetry which spend most of their time in a quasi-extremal state, the neutrino emission at 1PeV may be more suppressed than at 100PeV. The burst rates implied by the KM3NeT and IceCube observations and the indirect constraints can then all be consistent at $1\sigma$, and no associated gamma-ray signal was expected at LHAASO. Furthermore, these black holes could constitute all of the observed dark matter in the universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22722v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/r793-p7ct</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Michael J. Baker, Joaquim Iguaz Juan, Aidan Symons, Andrea Thamm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secluded Dark Composites and Remnant Binding Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04331v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dark matter may freeze-out and undergo composite assembly while decoupled from the Standard Model. In this secluded composite scenario, while individual dark matter particles may be too weakly-coupled to detect, the assembled composite can potentially be detected since its effective coupling scales with number of constituents. We examine models and observables for secluded composites, and in particular we investigate the cosmological abundance of the composite binding field, which is generated during freeze-out annihilation and secluded composite assembly. This binding field could be discovered as a new relativistic species in the early universe or through later interactions as a subdominant dark component.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04331v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/12/034</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 12 (2025) 034</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Katarina Bleau, Yilda Boukhtouchen, Joseph Bramante, Rohan Kulkarni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravothermal Pile-Up of Collisional Dark Matter Around Compact Objects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11601v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The dark matter may consist of multiple species that interact differently. We show that a species that is cosmologically subdominant but highly collisional can pile up and become dominant in deep gravitational wells, such as those of white dwarfs and neutron stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11601v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reza Ebadi, Erwin H. Tanin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing Real WIMPs with CTAO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15937</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15937v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We forecast the reach of the upcoming Cherenkov Telescope Array Observatory (CTAO) to the full set of real representations within the paradigm of minimal dark matter. We employ effective field theory techniques to compute the annihilation cross section and photon spectrum that results when fermionic dark matter is the neutral component of an arbitrary odd and real representation of SU(2), including the Sommerfeld enhancement, next-to-leading log resummation of the relevant electroweak effects, and the contribution from bound states. We also compute the corresponding signals for scalar dark matter, with the exception of the bound state contribution. Results are presented for all real representations from the $\sim$3 TeV triplet (or wino), a $\mathbf{3}$ of SU(2), to the $\sim$300 TeV tredecuplet, a $\mathbf{13}$ of SU(2) that is at the threshold of the unitarity bound. Using these results, we forecast that with 500 hrs of Galactic Center observations and assuming background systematics are controlled at the level of ${\cal O}(1\%)$, then should no signal emerge, CTAO could exclude all representations up to the $\mathbf{11}$ of SU(2) in even the most conservative models for the dark-matter density in the inner galaxy, in both the fermionic and scalar dark matter cases. Assuming the default CTAO configuration, the tredecuplet will marginally escape exclusion, although we outline steps that CTAO could take to test even this scenario. In summary, CTAO appears poised to make a definitive statement on whether real WIMPs constitute the dark matter of our universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15937v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Baumgart, Salvatore Bottaro, Diego Redigolo, Nicholas L. Rodd, Tracy R. Slatyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
