<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.ST updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.ST</link>
    <description>q-fin.ST updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.ST" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 02:37:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-Informed Singular-Value Learning for Cross-Covariances Forecasting in Financial Markets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07687</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.07687v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A new wave of work on covariance cleaning and nonlinear shrinkage has delivered asymptotically optimal analytical solutions for large covariance matrices. The same framework has been generalized to empirical cross-covariance matrices, whose singular value decomposition identifies canonical comovement modes between two asset sets, with singular values quantifying the strength of each mode and providing natural targets for shrinkage. Existing analytical cross-covariance cleaners are derived under strong stationarity and large-sample assumptions, and they typically rely on mesoscopic regularity conditions such as bounded spectra; macroscopic common modes (e.g., a global market factor) violate these conditions. When applied to real equity returns, where dependence structures drift over time and global modes are prominent, we find that these theoretically optimal formulas do not translate into robust out-of-sample performance. We address this gap by designing a random-matrix-inspired neural architecture that operates in the empirical singular-vector basis and learns a nonlinear mapping from empirical singular values to their corresponding cleaned values. By construction, the network can recover the analytical solution as a special case, yet it remains flexible enough to adapt to non-stationary dynamics and mode-driven distortions. Trained on a long history of equity returns, the proposed method achieves a more favorable bias-variance trade-off than purely analytical cleaners and delivers systematically lower out-of-sample cross-covariance prediction errors. Our results demonstrate that combining random-matrix theory with machine learning makes asymptotic theories practically effective in realistic time-varying markets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07687v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.ST</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Efstratios Manolakis, Christian Bongiorno, Rosario Nunzio Mantegna</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Target search optimization by threshold resetting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13501v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a new class of first passage time optimization driven by threshold resetting, inspired by many natural processes where crossing a critical limit triggers failure, degradation or transition. In here, search agents are collectively reset when a threshold is reached, creating event-driven, system-coupled simultaneous resets that induce long-range interactions. We develop a unified framework to compute search times for these correlated stochastic processes, with ballistic- and diffusive searchers as key examples uncovering diverse optimization behaviors. A cost function, akin to breakdown penalties, reveals that optimal resetting can forestall larger losses. This formalism generalizes to broader stochastic systems with multiple degrees of freedom.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13501v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-fin.ST</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/752c-wqly</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 227101 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Arup Biswas, Satya N Majumdar, Arnab Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
