<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.OS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.OS</link>
    <description>cs.OS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.OS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 02:33:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Getting the MOST out of your Storage Hierarchy with Mirror-Optimized Storage Tiering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.03279v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present Mirror-Optimized Storage Tiering (MOST), a novel tiering-based approach optimized for modern storage hierarchies. The key idea of MOST is to combine the load balancing advantages of mirroring with the space-efficiency advantages of tiering. Specifically, MOST dynamically mirrors a small amount of hot data across storage tiers to efficiently balance load, avoiding costly migrations. As a result, MOST is as space-efficient as classic tiering while achieving better bandwidth utilization under I/O-intensive workloads. We implement MOST in Cerberus, a user-level storage management layer based on CacheLib. We show the efficacy of Cerberus through a comprehensive empirical study: across a range of static and dynamic workloads, Cerberus achieves better throughput than competing approaches on modern storage hierarchies especially under I/O-intensive and dynamic workloads.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.03279v1</guid>
      <category>cs.OS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaiwei Tu, Kan Wu, Andrea C. Arpaci-Dusseau, Remzi H. Arpaci-Dusseau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Talyxion: From Speculation to Optimization in Risk Managed Crypto Portfolio Allocation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13239v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Cryptocurrency trading has attracted tremendous attention from both retail and institutional investors. However, most traders fail to scale their assets under management due to fragile strategies that collapse during adverse markets. The primary causes are oversized leverage, speculative position sizing, and the absence of robust risk management or hedging mechanisms. This paper introduces Talyxion, an end to end framework for crypto portfolio allocation that shifts the paradigm from speculation to optimization. The proposed pipeline consists of four stages: universe selection, alpha backtesting, volatility aware portfolio optimization, and dynamic drawdown based risk management. By combining operations research techniques with practical risk controls, Talyxion enables scalable crypto portfolios that can withstand market downturns. In live 30 day trading on Binance Futures, the framework achieved a return on investment (ROI) of +16.68%, with the Sharpe ratio reaching 5.72 and the maximum drawdown contained at just 4.56%, demonstrating strong downside risk control. The system executed 227 trades, of which 131 were profitable, resulting in a win rate of 57.71% and a PnL of +1,137.49 USDT. Importantly, these results outperformed the buy and hold baseline (Sharpe 1.79, ROI 4.36%, MDD 4.96%) as well as several top leader copy trading bots on Binance, highlighting both the competitiveness and scalability of Talyxion in real world trading environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13239v2</guid>
      <category>cs.OS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thanh Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
