<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.OS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.OS</link>
    <description>cs.OS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.OS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 04:28:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Continuum: Efficient and Robust Multi-Turn LLM Agent Scheduling with KV Cache Time-to-Live</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02230v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: KV cache management is essential for efficient LLM inference. To maximize utilization, existing inference engines evict finished requests' KV cache if new requests are waiting. This policy breaks for agentic workloads, which interleave LLM calls with tools, introducing pauses that prevent effective KV reuse across turns. Since some tool calls have much shorter durations than human response multi-turn chatbot, it would be promising to retain the KV cache in during these tools. However, there are many challenges. First, we need to consider both the potential cost of recomputation or reloading (if CPU offloading enabled) and the increasing queueing delays after eviction from GPU. Second, due to the internal variance of tool call durations, we need the method to remain robust under limited predictability of tool call durations.
  We present Continuum, a serving system to optimize job completion time for multi-turn agent workloads by introducing time-to-live mechanism for KV cache retaining. For LLM request that generates a tool call, Continuum selectively pins the KV cache in GPU memory with a time-to-live value determined by considering both the reload cost and ordering preserve benefit of retaining KV cache. Moreover, when the TTL expires, the KV cache can be automatically evicted to free up GPU memory, providing robust performance under edge cases. When combined with program-level first-come-first-serve, Continuum preserves multi-turn continuity, and reduces delay for complex agentic workflows. Our evaluation on real-world agentic workloads (SWE-Bench and BFCL) with Llama-3.1 8B/70B shows that Continuum significantly improves the average job completion times and its improvement scales with turn number increase. We release a preview version at: https://github.com/Hanchenli/vllm-continuum</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02230v3</guid>
      <category>cs.OS</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanchen Li, Qiuyang Mang, Runyuan He, Qizheng Zhang, Huanzhi Mao, Xiaokun Chen, Hangrui Zhou, Alvin Cheung, Joseph Gonzalez, Ion Stoica</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
