<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.OS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.OS</link>
    <description>cs.OS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.OS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 03:05:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A Flower-Inspired Solution for Computer Memory Wear-Leveling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.19902v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Lengthening a computer memory's lifespan is important for e-waste and sustainability. Uneven wear of memory is a major barrier. The problem is becoming even more urgent as emerging memory such as phase-change memory is subject to even shorter lifespan. Various solutions have been proposed, but they either require complicated hardware extensions or apply only to certain program constructs such as loops. This research proposes a new method, dual-ring wear leveling. It takes inspiration from the natural law known as the ``golden ratio" and how it helps flower petals evenly receive sun lights. By modeling memory as two rings and combines the idea with existing memory management, garbage collection, the new solution offers an effective way to reduce memory wear and hence lengthen memory lifespan. It is deterministic, able to automatically adapt to memory size, requiring no hardware changes, and adding no slowdown to program executions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.19902v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <category>cs.OS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elizabeth Shen, Huiyang Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rethinking Thread Scheduling under Oversubscription: A User-Space Framework for Coordinating Multi-runtime and Multi-process Workloads</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.20435</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.20435v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The convergence of high-performance computing (HPC) and artificial intelligence (AI) is driving the emergence of increasingly complex parallel applications and workloads. These workloads often combine multiple parallel runtimes within the same application or across co-located jobs, creating scheduling demands that place significant stress on traditional OS schedulers. When oversubscribed (there are more ready threads than cores), OS schedulers rely on periodic preemptions to multiplex cores, often introducing interference that may degrade performance. In this paper, we present: (1) The User-space Scheduling Framework (USF), a novel seamless process scheduling framework completely implemented in user-space. USF enables users to implement their own process scheduling algorithms without requiring special permissions. We evaluate USF with its default cooperative policy, (2) SCHED_COOP, designed to reduce interference by switching threads only upon blocking. This approach mitigates well-known issues such as Lock-Holder Preemption (LHP), Lock-Waiter Preemption (LWP), and scalability collapse. We implement USF and SCHED_COOP by extending the GNU C library with the nOS-V runtime, enabling seamless coordination across multiple runtimes (e.g., OpenMP) without requiring invasive application changes. Evaluations show gains up to 2.4x in oversubscribed multi-process scenarios, including nested BLAS workloads, multi-process PyTorch inference with LLaMA-3, and Molecular Dynamics (MD) simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.20435v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.OS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3774934.3786451</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Aleix Roca, Vicen\c{c} Beltran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>/dev/SDB: Software Defined Boot -- A novel standard for diskless booting anywhere and everywhere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.20629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.20629v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A computer is nothing but a device that processes the instructions supplied to it. However, as computers evolved, the instructions or codes started to be more complicated. As computers started to be used by non-technical people, it became imperative that the users be able to use the machine without having underlying knowledge of the code or the hardware. And operating system became the backbone for translating the inputs from the user to actual operation on the hardware. With the increasing complexity and the choices of operating system, it became clear that different groups of people, especially in an enterprise scenario, required different operating systems. Installing them all on a single machine, for shared computers became a difficult task, giving rise to network-based booting. But network-based booting was confined to only wired connectivity, keeping it restricted to very small geographical areas. The proposed system, /dev/SDB, is aimed at creating a standard where any user, anyone on the globe, can access the operating system authorized to them without having to be on the corporate network. It aims to offer the same over Wi-Fi as well as cellular connectivity, ensuring employees can truly work from anywhere, while following the policies for operating systems and without redundant hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.20629v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.OS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aditya Mitra, Hamza Haroon, Amaan Rais Shah, Mohammad Elham Rasooli, Bogdan Itsam Dorantes Nikolaev, Tu\u{g}\c{c}e Ball{\i}</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
