<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.IT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.IT</link>
    <description>math.IT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.IT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 04:00:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Mini-Batch Gradient-Based MCMC for Decentralized Massive MIMO Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18489v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Massive multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) technology has significantly enhanced spectral and power efficiency in cellular communications and is expected to further evolve towards extra-large-scale MIMO. However, centralized processing for massive MIMO faces practical obstacles, including excessive computational complexity and a substantial volume of baseband data to be exchanged. To address these challenges, decentralized baseband processing has emerged as a promising solution. This approach involves partitioning the antenna array into clusters with dedicated computing hardware for parallel processing. In this paper, we investigate the gradient-based Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) method -- an advanced MIMO detection technique known for its near-optimal performance in centralized implementation -- within the context of a decentralized baseband processing architecture. This decentralized design mitigates the computation burden at a single processing unit by utilizing computational resources in a distributed and parallel manner. Additionally, we integrate the mini-batch stochastic gradient descent method into the proposed decentralized detector, achieving remarkable performance with high efficiency. Simulation results demonstrate substantial performance gains of the proposed method over existing decentralized detectors across various scenarios. Moreover, complexity analysis reveals the advantages of the proposed decentralized strategy in terms of computation delay and interconnection bandwidth when compared to conventional centralized detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18489v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xingyu Zhou, Le Liang, Jing Zhang, Chao-Kai Wen, Shi Jin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signalling and Control in Nonlinear Stochastic Systems: An Information State Approach with Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18588</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18588v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider optimal signalling and control of discrete-time nonlinear partially observable stochastic systems in state space form. In the first part of the paper, we characterize the operational {\it control-coding capacity}, $C_{FB}$ in bits/second, by an information theoretic optimization problem of encoding signals or messages into randomized controller-encoder strategies, and reproducing the messages at the output of the system using a decoder or estimator with arbitrary small asymptotic error probability. Our analysis of $C_{FB}$ is based on realizations of randomized strategies (controller-encoders), in terms of information states of nonlinear filtering theory, and either uniform or arbitrary distributed random variables (RVs). In the second part of the paper, we analyze the linear-quadratic Gaussian partially observable stochastic system (LQG-POSS). We show that simultaneous signalling and control leads to randomized strategies described by finite-dimensional sufficient statistics, that involve two Kalman-filters, and consist of control, estimation and signalling strategies. We apply decentralized optimization techniques to prove a separation principle, and to derive the optimal control part of randomized strategies explicitly in terms of a control matrix difference Riccati equation (DRE).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18588v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charalambos D. Charalambous, Stelios Louka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secrecy Performance Analysis of Integrated RF-UWOC IoT Networks Enabled by UAV and Underwater-RIS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18766</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18766v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the sixth-generation (6G) Internet of Things (IoT) networks, the use of UAV-mounted base stations and reconfigurable intelligent surfaces (RIS) has been considered to enhance coverage, flexibility, and security in non-terrestrial networks (NTNs). In addition to aerial networks enabled by NTN technologies, the integration of underwater networks with 6G IoT can be considered one of the most innovative challenges in future IoT. Along with such trends in IoT, this study investigates the secrecy performance of IoT networks that integrate radio frequency (RF) UAV-based NTNs and underwater optical wireless communication (UOWC) links with an RIS. Considering three potential eavesdropping scenarios (RF signal, UOWC signal, and both), we derive closed-form expressions for secrecy performance metrics, including average secrecy capacity, secrecy outage probability, probability of strictly positive secrecy capacity, and effective secrecy throughput. Extensive numerical analyses and Monte Carlo simulations elucidate the impact of system parameters such as fading severity, the number of RIS reflecting elements, underwater turbulence, pointing errors, and detection techniques on system security. The findings offer comprehensive design guidelines for developing such a network aiming to enhance secrecy performance and ensure secure communication in diverse and challenging environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18766v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abrar Bin Sarawar, A. S. M. Badrudduza, Md. Ibrahim, Imran Shafique Ansari, Heejung Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploiting Device Heterogeneity in Grant-Free Random Access: A Data-Driven Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18806v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Grant-free random access (GFRA) is now a popular protocol for large-scale wireless multiple access systems in order to reduce control signaling. Resource allocation in GFRA can be viewed as a form of frame slotted ALOHA, where a ubiquitous design assumption is device homogeneity. In particular, the probability that a device seeks to transmit data is common to all devices. Recently, there has been an interest in designing frame slotted ALOHA algorithms for networks with heterogeneous activity probabilities. These works have established that the throughput can be significantly improved over the standard uniform allocation. However, the algorithms for optimizing the probability a device accesses each slot require perfect knowledge of the active devices within each frame. In practice, this assumption is limiting as device identification algorithms in GFRA rarely provide activity estimates with zero errors. In this paper, we develop a new algorithm based on stochastic gradient descent for optimizing slot allocation probabilities in the presence of activity estimation errors. Our algorithm exploits importance weighted bias mitigation for stochastic gradient estimates, which is shown to provably converge to a stationary point of the throughput optimization problem. In moderate size systems, our simulations show that the performance of our algorithm depends on the type of error distribution. We study symmetric bit flipping, asymmetric bit flipping and errors resulting from a generalized approximate message passing (GAMP) algorithm. In these scenarios, we observe gains up to 40\%, 66\%, and 19\%, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18806v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TVT.2024.3396825</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Transactions on Vehicular Technology, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alix Jeannerot, Malcolm Egan, Jean-Marie Gorce</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint Slot and Power Optimization for Grant Free Random Access with Unknown and Heterogeneous Device Activity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18809v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Grant Free Random Access (GFRA) is a popular protocol in the Internet of Things (IoT) to reduce the control signaling. GFRA is a framed protocol where each frame is split into two parts: device identification; and data transmission part which can be viewed as a form of Frame Slotted ALOHA (FSA). A common assumption in FSA is device homogeneity; that is the probability that a device seeks to transmit data in a particular frame is common for all devices and independent of the other devices. Recent work has investigated the possibility of tuning the FSA protocol to the statistics of the network by changing the probability for a particular device to access a particular slot. However, power control with a successive interference cancellation (SIC) receiver has not yet been considered to further increase the performance of the tuned FSA protocols. In this paper, we propose algorithms to jointly optimize both the slot selection and the transmit power of the devices to minimize the outage of the devices in the network. We show via a simulation study that our algorithms can outperform baselines (including slotted ALOHA) in terms of expected number of devices transmitting without outage and in term of transmit power.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18809v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alix Jeannerot, Malcolm Egan, Jean-Marie Gorce</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conversational Dueling Bandits in Generalized Linear Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18488v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Conversational recommendation systems elicit user preferences by interacting with users to obtain their feedback on recommended commodities. Such systems utilize a multi-armed bandit framework to learn user preferences in an online manner and have received great success in recent years. However, existing conversational bandit methods have several limitations. First, they only enable users to provide explicit binary feedback on the recommended items or categories, leading to ambiguity in interpretation. In practice, users are usually faced with more than one choice. Relative feedback, known for its informativeness, has gained increasing popularity in recommendation system design. Moreover, current contextual bandit methods mainly work under linear reward assumptions, ignoring practical non-linear reward structures in generalized linear models. Therefore, in this paper, we introduce relative feedback-based conversations into conversational recommendation systems through the integration of dueling bandits in generalized linear models (GLM) and propose a novel conversational dueling bandit algorithm called ConDuel. Theoretical analyses of regret upper bounds and empirical validations on synthetic and real-world data underscore ConDuel's efficacy. We also demonstrate the potential to extend our algorithm to multinomial logit bandits with theoretical and experimental guarantees, which further proves the applicability of the proposed framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18488v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3637528.3671892</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Shuhua Yang, Hui Yuan, Xiaoying Zhang, Mengdi Wang, Hong Zhang, Huazheng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Bilinear Equalizer for Cell-Free Massive MIMO Systems over Correlated Rician Channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18531</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18531v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we explore the low-complexity optimal bilinear equalizer (OBE) combining scheme design for cell-free massive multiple-input multiple-output networks with spatially correlated Rician fading channels. We provide a spectral efficiency (SE) performance analysis framework for both the centralized and distributed processing schemes with bilinear equalizer (BE)-structure combining schemes applied. The BE-structured combining is a set of schemes that are constructed by the multiplications of channel statistics-based BE matrices and instantaneous channel estimates. Notably, we derive closed-form achievable SE expressions for centralized and distributed BE-structured combining schemes. We propose one centralized and two distributed OBE schemes: Centralized OBE (C-OBE), Distributed OBE based on Global channel statistics (DG-OBE), and Distributed OBE based on Local channel statistics (DL-OBE), which maximize their respective SE expressions. OBE matrices in these schemes are tailored based on varying levels of channel statistics. Notably, we obtain new and insightful closed-form results for the C-OBE, DG-OBE, and DL-OBE combining schemes. Numerical results demonstrate that the proposed OBE schemes can achieve excellent SE, even in scenarios with severe pilot contamination.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18531v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhe Wang, Jiayi Zhang, Emil Bj\"ornson, Dusit Niyato, Bo Ai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new family of binary sequences with a low correlation via elliptic curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18570v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the realm of modern digital communication, cryptography, and signal processing, binary sequences with a low correlation properties play a pivotal role. In the literature, considerable efforts have been dedicated to constructing good binary sequences of various lengths. As a consequence, numerous constructions of good binary sequences have been put forward. However, the majority of known constructions leverage the multiplicative cyclic group structure of finite fields $\mathbb{F}_{p^n}$, where $p$ is a prime and $n$ is a positive integer. Recently, the authors made use of the cyclic group structure of all rational places of the rational function field over the finite field $\mathbb{F}_{p^n}$, and firstly constructed good binary sequences of length $p^n+1$ via cyclotomic function fields over $\mathbb{F}_{p^n}$ for any prime $p$ \cite{HJMX24,JMX22}. This approach has paved a new way for constructing good binary sequences. Motivated by the above constructions, we exploit the cyclic group structure on rational points of elliptic curves to design a family of binary sequences of length $2^n+1+t$ with a low correlation for many given integers $|t|\le 2^{(n+2)/2}$. Specifically, for any positive integer $d$ with $\gcd(d,2^n+1+t)=1$, we introduce a novel family of binary sequences of length $2^n+1+t$, size $q^{d-1}-1$, correlation bounded by $(2d+1) \cdot 2^{(n+2)/2}+ |t|$, and a large linear complexity via elliptic curves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18570v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lingfei Jin, Liming Ma, Chaoping Xing, Runtian Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Log-Concave Coupling for Sampling Neural Net Posteriors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18802v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we present a sampling algorithm for single hidden layer neural networks. This algorithm is built upon a recursive series of Bayesian posteriors using a method we call Greedy Bayes. Sampling of the Bayesian posterior for neuron weight vectors $w$ of dimension $d$ is challenging because of its multimodality. Our algorithm to tackle this problem is based on a coupling of the posterior density for $w$ with an auxiliary random variable $\xi$.
  The resulting reverse conditional $w|\xi$ of neuron weights given auxiliary random variable is shown to be log concave. In the construction of the posterior distributions we provide some freedom in the choice of the prior. In particular, for Gaussian priors on $w$ with suitably small variance, the resulting marginal density of the auxiliary variable $\xi$ is proven to be strictly log concave for all dimensions $d$. For a uniform prior on the unit $\ell_1$ ball, evidence is given that the density of $\xi$ is again strictly log concave for sufficiently large $d$.
  The score of the marginal density of the auxiliary random variable $\xi$ is determined by an expectation over $w|\xi$ and thus can be computed by various rapidly mixing Markov Chain Monte Carlo methods. Moreover, the computation of the score of $\xi$ permits methods of sampling $\xi$ by a stochastic diffusion (Langevin dynamics) with drift function built from this score. With such dynamics, information-theoretic methods pioneered by Bakry and Emery show that accurate sampling of $\xi$ is obtained rapidly when its density is indeed strictly log-concave. After which, one more draw from $w|\xi$, produces neuron weights $w$ whose marginal distribution is from the desired posterior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18802v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Curtis McDonald, Andrew R Barron</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Scalable Quantum Non-local Neural Network for Image Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18906v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Non-local operations play a crucial role in computer vision enabling the capture of long-range dependencies through weighted sums of features across the input, surpassing the constraints of traditional convolution operations that focus solely on local neighborhoods. Non-local operations typically require computing pairwise relationships between all elements in a set, leading to quadratic complexity in terms of time and memory. Due to the high computational and memory demands, scaling non-local neural networks to large-scale problems can be challenging. This article introduces a hybrid quantum-classical scalable non-local neural network, referred to as Quantum Non-Local Neural Network (QNL-Net), to enhance pattern recognition. The proposed QNL-Net relies on inherent quantum parallelism to allow the simultaneous processing of a large number of input features enabling more efficient computations in quantum-enhanced feature space and involving pairwise relationships through quantum entanglement. We benchmark our proposed QNL-Net with other quantum counterparts to binary classification with datasets MNIST and CIFAR-10. The simulation findings showcase our QNL-Net achieves cutting-edge accuracy levels in binary image classification among quantum classifiers while utilizing fewer qubits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18906v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sparsh Gupta, Debanjan Konar, Vaneet Aggarwal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intelligent Reflecting Surface vs. Decode-and-Forward: How Large Surfaces Are Needed to Beat Relaying?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1906.03949</link>
      <description>arXiv:1906.03949v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The rate and energy efficiency of wireless channels can be improved by deploying software-controlled metasurfaces to reflect signals from the source to the destination, especially when the direct path is weak. While previous works mainly optimized the reflections, this letter compares the new technology with classic decode-and-forward (DF) relaying. The main observation is that very high rates and/or large metasurfaces are needed to outperform DF relaying, both in terms of minimizing the total transmit power and maximizing the energy efficiency, which also includes the dissipation in the transceiver hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1906.03949v4</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LWC.2019.2950624</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Emil Bj\"ornson, \"Ozgecan \"Ozdogan, Erik G. Larsson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Physical-Layer Orchestration Framework for Open System Models of Autonomous RISs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.10858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.10858v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: To obviate the control of reconfigurable intelligent surfaces (RISs) and related overhead, recent works envisioned the concept of autonomous RISs: Intelligent devices capable of autonomously deciding their reflection states. This paradigm is enabled by hybrid RIS (HRIS), a hardware solution that integrates sensing and channel estimation (CHEST) capabilities, enabling autonomous operation. Autonomous RISs operate independently alongside other network entities, promoting open communication system models for RISs. However, this autonomy introduces a significant challenge: How to schedule the operation of the autonomous RIS over time and frequency to minimize its impact on the network? This paper introduces a physical layer (PHY) orchestration framework within a massive multiple-input multiple-output (mMIMO) network to address this challenge. Our framework highlights an engineering trade-off termed the "autonomous RIS trade-off," which examines the performance implications of autonomy. Through mathematical analysis and numerical results, we describe the HRIS feasibility region, illustrating the conditions under which autonomous RISs are viable when properly deployed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.10858v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Croisfelt, Francesco Devoti, Fabio Saggese, Vincenzo Sciancalepore, Xavier Costa-P\'erez, Petar Popovski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Near-field Integrated Sensing and Communication: Opportunities and Challenges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.01342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.01342v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: With the extremely large-scale array XL-array deployed in future wireless systems, wireless communication and sensing are expected to operate in the radiative near-field region, which needs to be characterized by the spherical rather than planar wavefronts. Unlike most existing works that considered far-field integrated sensing and communication (ISAC), we study in this article the new near-field ISAC, which integrates both functions of sensing and communication in the near-field region. To this end, we first discuss the appealing advantages of near-field communication and sensing over their far-field counterparts, respectively. Then, we introduce three approaches for near-field ISAC, including joint near-field communication and sensing, sensing-assisted near-field communication, and communication-assisted near-field sensing. We discuss their individual research opportunities, new design issues, as well as propose promising solutions. Finally, several important directions in near-field ISAC are also highlighted to motivate future work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.01342v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiayi Cong, Changsheng You, Jiapeng Li, Li Chen, Beixiong Zheng, Yuanwei Liu, Wen Wu, Yi Gong, Shi Jin, Rui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Break-Resilient Codes for Forensic 3D Fingerprinting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.03897</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.03897v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: 3D printing brings about a revolution in consumption and distribution of goods, but poses a significant risk to public safety. Any individual with internet access and a commodity printer can now produce untraceable firearms, keys, and dangerous counterfeit products. To aid government authorities in combating these new security threats, objects are often tagged with identifying information. This information, also known as fingerprints, is written into the object using various bit embedding techniques, such as varying the width of the molten thermoplastic layers. Yet, due to the adversarial nature of the problem, it is important to devise tamper resilient fingerprinting techniques, so that the fingerprint could be extracted even if the object was damaged. While fingerprinting various forms of digital media (such as videos, images, etc.) has been studied extensively in the past, 3D printing is a relatively new medium which is exposed to different types of adversarial physical tampering that do not exist in the digital world. This paper focuses on one such type of adversarial tampering, where the adversary breaks the object to at most a certain number of parts. This gives rise to a new adversarial coding problem, which is formulated and investigated herein. We survey the existing technology, present an abstract problem definition, provide lower bounds for the required redundancy, and construct a code which attains it up to asymptotically small factors. Notably, the problem bears some resemblance to the torn paper channel, which was recently studied for applications in DNA storage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.03897v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Canran Wang, Jin Sima, Netanel Raviv</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>User Clustering for Coexistence between Near-field and Far-field Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.15707</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.15707v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This letter investigates the coexistence between near-field (NF) and far-field (FF) communications, where multiple FF users are clustered to be served on the beams of legacy NF users, via non-orthogonal multiple access (NOMA). Three different successive interference cancellation (SIC) decoding strategies are proposed and a sum rate maximization problem is formulated to optimize the beam assignment and decoding order. The beam assignment problem is further reformulated as an overlapping coalitional game, which facilitates the design of the proposed clustering algorithm. The optimal decoding order in each cluster is also derived, which can be integrated into the proposed clustering. Simulation results demonstrate that the proposed clustering algorithm is able to significantly improve the sum rate of the considered system, and the developed strategies achieve different trade-offs between sum rate and fairness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.15707v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaidi Wang, Zhiguo Ding, George K. Karagiannidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Repairing Schemes for Tamo-Barg Codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.12803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.12803v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, the repair problem for erasures beyond locality in locally repairable codes is explored under a practical system setting, where a rack-aware storage system consists of racks, each containing a few parity checks. This is referred to as a rack-aware system with locality. Two repair schemes are devised to reduce the repair bandwidth for Tamo-Barg codes under the rack-aware model by setting each repair set as a rack. Additionally, a cut-set bound for locally repairable codes under the rack-aware model with locality is introduced. Using this bound, the second repair scheme is proven to be optimal. Furthermore, the partial-repair problem is considered for locally repairable codes under the rack-aware model with locality, and both repair schemes and bounds are introduced for this scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.12803v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Han Cai, Ying Miao, Moshe Schwartz, Xiaohu Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Transmission Design for RIS-Assisted Integrated Sensing and Communication Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.13882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.13882v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: As a critical technology for next-generation communication networks, integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) aims to achieve the harmonious coexistence of communication and sensing. The degrees-of-freedom (DoF) of ISAC is limited due to multiple performance metrics used for communication and sensing. Reconfigurable Intelligent Surfaces (RIS) composed of metamaterials can enhance the DoF in the spatial domain of ISAC systems. However, the availability of perfect Channel State Information (CSI) is a prerequisite for the gain brought by RIS, which is not realistic in practical environments. Therefore, under the imperfect CSI condition, we propose a decomposition-based large deviation inequality approach to eliminate the impact of CSI error on communication rate and sensing Cram\'er-Rao bound (CRB). Then, an alternating optimization (AO) algorithm based on semi-definite relaxation (SDR) and gradient extrapolated majorization-maximization (GEMM) is proposed to solve the transmit beamforming and discrete RIS beamforming problems. We also analyze the complexity and convergence of the proposed algorithm. Simulation results show that the proposed algorithms can effectively eliminate the influence of CSI error and have good convergence performance. Notably, when CSI error exists, the gain brought by RIS will decrease with the increase of the number of RIS elements. Finally, we summarize and outline future research directions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.13882v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TVT.2024.3426042</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yongqing Xu, Yong Li, Tony Q. S. Quek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RIS-Assisted Physical Layer Security in Emerging RF and Optical Wireless Communication Systems: A Comprehensive Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10412v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Physical layer security (PLS) has received a growing interest from the research community for its ability to safeguard data confidentiality without relying on key distribution or encryption/decryption. However, the evolution towards the 5G technology and beyond poses new security challenges that must be addressed in order to fulfill the unprecedented performance requirements of future wireless networks. Among the potential enabling technologies, RIS has attracted extensive attention due to its ability to proactively and intelligently reconfigure the wireless propagation environment to combat dynamic wireless channel impairments. Consequently, the RIS technology can be adopted to improve the information-theoretic security of both RF and OWC systems. This survey paper provides a comprehensive overview of the information-theoretic security of RIS-based RF and optical systems. The article first discusses the fundamental concepts of PLS and RIS technologies, followed by their combination in both RF and OWC systems. Subsequently, some optimization techniques are presented in the context of the underlying system model, followed by an assessment of the impact of RIS-assisted PLS through a comprehensive performance analysis. Given that the computational complexity of future communication systems that adopt RIS-assisted PLS is likely to increase rapidly as the number of interactions between the users and infrastructure grows, ML is seen as a promising approach to address this complexity issue while sustaining or improving the network performance. A discussion of recent research studies on RIS-assisted PLS-based systems embedded with ML is presented. Furthermore, some important open research challenges are proposed and discussed to provide insightful future research directions, with the aim of moving a step closer towards the development and implementation of the forthcoming 6G wireless technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10412v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Majid H. Khoshafa, Omar Maraqa, Jules M. Moualeu, Sylvester Aboagye, Telex M. N. Ngatched, Mohamed H. Ahmed, Yasser Gadallah, Marco Di Renzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Refined-Deep Reinforcement Learning for MIMO Bistatic Backscatter Resource Allocation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14046</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14046v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Bistatic backscatter communication facilitates ubiquitous, massive connectivity of passive tags for future Internet-of-Things (IoT) networks. The tags communicate with readers by reflecting carrier emitter (CE) signals. This work addresses the joint design of the transmit/receive beamformers at the CE/reader and the reflection coefficient of the tag. A throughput maximization problem is formulated to satisfy the tag requirements. A joint design is developed through a series of trial-and-error interactions within the environment, driven by a predefined reward system in a continuous state and action context. By leveraging recent advances in deep reinforcement learning (DRL), the underlying optimization problem is addressed. Capitalizing on deep deterministic policy gradient (DDPG) and soft actor-critic (SAC), we proposed two new algorithms, namely refined-DDPG for MIMO BiBC (RDMB) and refined-SAC for MIMO BiBC (RSMB). Simulation results show that the proposed algorithms can effectively learn from the environment and progressively improve their performance. They achieve results comparable to two leading benchmarks: alternating optimization (AO) and several DRL methods, including deep Q-network (DQN), double deep Q-network (DDQN), and dueling DQN (DuelDQN). For a system with twelve antennas, RSMB leads with a %26.76 gain over DQN, followed by AO and RSMB at 23.02% and 19.16%, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14046v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Zargari, D. Galappaththige, C. Tellambura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Reinforcement Learning for Wireless Scheduling in Distributed Networked Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.12562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2109.12562v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a joint uplink and downlink scheduling problem of a fully distributed wireless networked control system (WNCS) with a limited number of frequency channels. Using elements of stochastic systems theory, we derive a sufficient stability condition of the WNCS, which is stated in terms of both the control and communication system parameters. Once the condition is satisfied, there exists a stationary and deterministic scheduling policy that can stabilize all plants of the WNCS. By analyzing and representing the per-step cost function of the WNCS in terms of a finite-length countable vector state, we formulate the optimal transmission scheduling problem into a Markov decision process and develop a deep reinforcement learning (DRL) based framework for solving it. To tackle the challenges of a large action space in DRL, we propose novel action space reduction and action embedding methods for the DRL framework that can be applied to various algorithms, including Deep Q-Network (DQN), Deep Deterministic Policy Gradient (DDPG), and Twin Delayed Deep Deterministic Policy Gradient (TD3). Numerical results show that the proposed algorithm significantly outperforms benchmark policies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2109.12562v4</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaoyang Pang, Kang Huang, Daniel E. Quevedo, Branka Vucetic, Yonghui Li, Wanchun Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>R\'enyi--Sobolev Inequalities and Connections to Spectral Graph Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.12288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.12288v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we generalize the log-Sobolev inequalities to R\'enyi--Sobolev inequalities by replacing the entropy with the two-parameter entropy, which is a generalized version of entropy and closely related to R\'enyi divergences. We derive the sharp nonlinear dimension-free version of this kind of inequalities. Interestingly, the resultant inequalities show a transition phenomenon depending on the parameters. We then connect R\'enyi--Sobolev inequalities to contractive and data-processing inequalities, concentration inequalities, and spectral graph theory. Our proofs in this paper are based on the information-theoretic characterization of the R\'enyi--Sobolev inequalities, as well as the method of types.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.12288v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Yu, Hao Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
