<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.IT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.IT</link>
    <description>math.IT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.IT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 05:01:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>From Raw Data to Structural Semantics: Trade-offs among Distortion, Rate, and Inference Accuracy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19825v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work explores the advantages of using persistence diagrams (PDs), topological signatures of raw point cloud data, in a point-to-point communication setting. PD is a structural semantics in the sense that it carries information about the shape and structure of the data. Instead of transmitting raw data, the transmitter communicates its PD semantics, and the receiver carries out inference using the received semantics. We propose novel qualitative definitions for distortion and rate of PD semantics while quantitatively characterizing the trade-offs among the distortion, rate, and inference accuracy. Simulations demonstrate that unlike raw data or autoencoder (AE)-based latent representations, PD semantics leads to more effective use of transmission channels, enhanced degrees of freedom for incorporating error detection/correction capabilities, and improved robustness to channel imperfections. For instance, in a binary symmetric channel with nonzero crossover probability settings, the minimum rate required for Bose, Chaudhuri, and Hocquenghem (BCH)-coded PD semantics to achieve an inference accuracy over 80% is approximately 15 times lower than the rate required for the coded AE-latent representations. Moreover, results suggest that the gains of PD semantics are even more pronounced when compared with the rate requirements of raw data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19825v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charmin Asirimath, Chathuranga Weeraddana, Sumudu Samarakoon, Jayampathy Ratnayake, Mehdi Bennis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Overview of Cellular ISAC for Low-Altitude UAV: New Opportunities and Challenges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19973</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19973v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Low-altitude unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs) are expected to play an important role in future wireless networks, either as aerial base stations (BSs) or aerial users connected to the cellular network. In addition, integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) has been identified as one of the six usage scenarios for the forthcoming sixth-generation (6G) mobile networks, aimed at improving network functionalities and realizing situational awareness of the physical world. While most existing research efforts focus on terrestrial two-dimensional (2D) communication and sensing, UAV as an aerial platform offers a new degree of freedom for designing three-dimensional (3D) air-ground (AG) ISAC networks. In this article, we provide an overview of cellular-connected UAV ISAC, by elaborating the UAV's roles as a target to be sensed and as an aerial anchor to provide sensing functionality, respectively. In particular, we pay attention to the network coverage issue and topics specific to UAV networking, emphasizing the new opportunities as well as unique challenges to be addressed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19973v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxuan Song (Southeast University, China), Yong Zeng (Southeast University, China, Purple Mountain Laboratories, China), Yuhang Yang (Southeast University, China), Zixiang Ren (The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Shenzhen, China), Gaoyuan Cheng (The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Shenzhen, China), Xiaoli Xu (Southeast University, China), Jie Xu (The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Shenzhen, China), Shi Jin (Southeast University, China), Rui Zhang (The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Shenzhen, China, National University of Singapore)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Achieving Full-Bandwidth Sensing Performance with Partial Bandwidth Allocation for ISAC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20083</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20083v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This letter studies an uplink integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) system using discrete Fourier transform spread orthogonal frequency division multiplexing (DFT-s-OFDM) transmission. We try to answer the following fundamental question: With only a fractional bandwidth allocated to the user with sensing task, can the same delay resolution and unambiguous range be achieved as if all bandwidth were allocated to it? We affirmatively answer the question by proposing a novel two-stage delay estimation (TSDE) method that exploits the following facts: without increasing the allocated bandwidth, higher delay resolution can be achieved via distributed subcarrier allocation compared to its collocated counterpart, while there is a trade-off between delay resolution and unambiguous range by varying the decimation factor of subcarriers. Therefore, the key idea of the proposed TSDE method is to first perform coarse delay estimation with collocated subcarriers to achieve a large unambiguous range, and then use distributed subcarriers with optimized decimation factor to enhance delay resolution while avoiding delay ambiguity. Our analysis shows that the proposed TSDE method can achieve the full-bandwidth delay resolution and unambiguous range, by using only at most half of the full bandwidth, provided that the channel delay spread is less than half of the unambiguous range. Numerical results show the superiority of the proposed method over the conventional method with collocated subcarriers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20083v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiqiang Xiao, Zhiwen Zhou, Qianglong Dai, Yong Zeng, Fei Yang, Yan Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Hybrid Quantum-Classical Autoencoder Framework for End-to-End Communication Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20241</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20241v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the application of quantum machine learning to End-to-End (E2E) communication systems in wireless fading scenarios. We introduce a novel hybrid quantum-classical autoencoder architecture that combines parameterized quantum circuits with classical deep neural networks (DNNs). Specifically, we propose a hybrid quantum-classical autoencoder (QAE) framework to optimize the E2E communication system. Our results demonstrate the feasibility of the proposed hybrid system, and reveal that it is the first work that can achieve comparable block error rate (BLER) performance to classical DNN-based and conventional channel coding schemes, while significantly reducing the number of trainable parameters. Additionally, the proposed QAE exhibits steady and superior BLER convergence over the classical autoencoder baseline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20241v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bolun Zhang, Gan Zheng, Nguyen Van Huynh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Movable Antenna Array Aided Ultra Reliable Covert Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20417</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20417v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we construct a framework of the movable antenna (MA) aided covert communication shielded by the general noise uncertainty for the first time. According to the analysis performance on the derived closed-form expressions of the sum of the probabilities of the detection errors and the communication outage probability, the perfect covertness and the ultra reliability can be achieved by adjusting the antenna position in the MA array. Then, we formulate the communication covertness maximization problem with the constraints of the ultra reliability and the independent discrete movable position to optimize the transmitter's parameter. With the maximal ratio transmitting (MRT) design for the beamforming, we solve the closed-form optimal information transmit power and design a lightweight discrete projected gradient descent (DPGD) algorithm to determine the optimal antenna position. The numerical results show that the optimal achievable covertness and the feasible region of the steering angle with the MA array is significant larger than the one with the fixed-position antenna (FPA) array.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20417v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yida Wang, Guojie Hu, Xiaoling Hu, Xingbo Lu, Yuzhen Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graph Neural Networks for Next-Generation-IoT: Recent Advances and Open Challenges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20634v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) have emerged as a critical tool for optimizing and managing the complexities of the Internet of Things (IoT) in next-generation networks. This survey presents a comprehensive exploration of how GNNs may be harnessed in 6G IoT environments, focusing on key challenges and opportunities through a series of open questions. We commence with an exploration of GNN paradigms and the roles of node, edge, and graph-level tasks in solving wireless networking problems and highlight GNNs' ability to overcome the limitations of traditional optimization methods. This guidance enhances problem-solving efficiency across various next-generation (NG) IoT scenarios. Next, we provide a detailed discussion of the application of GNN in advanced NG enabling technologies, including massive MIMO, reconfigurable intelligent surfaces, satellites, THz, mobile edge computing (MEC), and ultra-reliable low latency communication (URLLC). We then delve into the challenges posed by adversarial attacks, offering insights into defense mechanisms to secure GNN-based NG-IoT networks. Next, we examine how GNNs can be integrated with future technologies like integrated sensing and communication (ISAC), satellite-air-ground-sea integrated networks (SAGSIN), and quantum computing. Our findings highlight the transformative potential of GNNs in improving efficiency, scalability, and security within NG-IoT systems, paving the way for future advances. Finally, we propose a set of design guidelines to facilitate the development of efficient, scalable, and secure GNN models tailored for NG IoT applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20634v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nguyen Xuan Tung, Le Tung Giang, Bui Duc Son, Seon Geun Jeong, Trinh Van Chien, Won Joo Hwang, Lajos Hanzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beam Codebook Refinement for mmWave Devices with Random Orientations: Concept and Experimental Validation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20726v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: There is a growing interest in codebook-based beam-steering for millimeter-wave (mmWave) systems due to its potential for low complexity and rapid beam search. A key focus of recent research has been the design of codebooks that strike a trade-off between achievable gain and codebook size, which directly impacts beam search time. Statistical approaches have shown promise by leveraging the likelihood that certain beam directions (equivalently, sets of phase-shifter configurations) are more probable than others. Such approaches are shown to be valid for static, non-rotating transmission stations such as base stations. However, for the case of user terminals that are constantly changing orientation, the possible phase-shifter configurations become equally probable, rendering statistical methods less relevant. On the other hand, user terminals come with a large number of possible steering vector configurations, which can span up to six orders of magnitude. Therefore, efficient solutions to reduce the codebook size (set of possible steering vectors) without compromising array gain are needed. We address this challenge by proposing a novel and practical codebook refinement technique, aiming to reduce the codebook size while maintaining array gain within $\gamma$ dB of the maximum achievable gain at any random orientation of the user terminal. We project that a steering vector at a given angle could effectively cover adjacent angles with a small gain loss compared to the maximum achievable gain. We demonstrate experimentally that it is possible to reduce the codebook size from $1024^{16}$ to just a few configurations (e.g., less than ten), covering all angles while maintaining the gain within $\gamma=3$ dB of the maximum achievable gain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20726v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bora Bozkurt, Ahmet Muaz Aktas, Hasan Atalay Gunel, Mohaned Chraiti, Ali Gorcin, Ibrahim Hokelek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimally Decoding Two-Dimensional Reed-Solomon Codes up to the Half-Singleton Bound</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20771v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Constructing Reed-Solomon (RS) codes capable of correcting insertion and deletion errors (ins-del errors) has been the focus of numerous recent studies. However, the development of efficient decoding algorithms for such RS codes has not garnered significant attention and remains an important and intriguing open problem. In this work, we take a first step toward addressing this problem by designing an optimal-time decoding algorithm for the special case of two-dimensional RS codes, capable of decoding up to the half-Singleton bound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20771v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shubhransh Singhvi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Language Model Enabled Multi-Task Physical Layer Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20772v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The recent advance of Artificial Intelligence (AI) is continuously reshaping the future 6G wireless communications. Recently, the development of Large Language Models (LLMs) offers a promising approach to effectively improve the performance and generalization for different physical layer tasks. However, most existing works finetune dedicated LLM networks for a single wireless communication task separately. Thus performing diverse physical layer tasks introduces extremely high training resources, memory usage, and deployment costs. To solve the problem, we propose a LLM-enabled multi-task physical layer network to unify multiple tasks with a single LLM. Specifically, we first propose a multi-task LLM framework, which finetunes LLM to perform multi-user precoding, signal detection and channel prediction simultaneously. Besides, multi-task instruction module, input encoders, as well as output decoders, are elaborately designed to distinguish multiple tasks and adapted the features of different formats of wireless data for the features of LLM. Numerical simulations are also displayed to verify the effectiveness of the proposed method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20772v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianyue Zheng, Linglong Dai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LEO Satellite-Enabled Random Access with Large Differential Delay and Doppler Shift</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20806v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates joint device identification, channel estimation, and symbol detection for LEO satellite-enabled grant-free random access systems, specifically targeting scenarios where remote Internet-of-Things (IoT) devices operate without global navigation satellite system (GNSS) assistance. Considering the constrained power consumption of these devices, the large differential delay and Doppler shift are handled at the satellite receiver. We firstly propose a spreading-based multi-frame transmission scheme with orthogonal time-frequency space (OTFS) modulation to mitigate the doubly dispersive effect in time and frequency, and then analyze the input-output relationship of the system. Next, we propose a receiver structure based on three modules: a linear module for identifying active devices that leverages the generalized approximate message passing algorithm to eliminate inter-user and inter-carrier interference; a non-linear module that employs the message passing algorithm to jointly estimate the channel and detect the transmitted symbols; and a third module that aims to exploit the three dimensional block channel sparsity in the delay-Doppler-angle domain. Soft information is exchanged among the three modules by careful message scheduling. Furthermore, the expectation-maximization algorithm is integrated to adjust phase rotation caused by the fractional Doppler and to learn the hyperparameters in the priors. Finally, the convolutional neural network is incorporated to enhance the symbol detection. Simulation results demonstrate that the proposed transmission scheme boosts the system performance, and the designed algorithms outperform the conventional methods significantly in terms of the device identification, channel estimation, and symbol detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20806v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boxiao Shen, Yongpeng Wu, Wenjun Zhang, Symeon Chatzinotas, Bj\"orn Ottersten</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective Application of Normalized Min-Sum Decoding for BCH Codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20828</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20828v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High-throughput decoding of BCH codes necessitates efficient and parallelizable decoders. However, the algebraic rigidity of BCH codes poses significant challenges to applying parallel belief propagation variants. To address this, we propose a systematic design scheme for constructing parity-check matrices using a heuristic approach. This involves a sequence of binary sum operations and row cyclic shifts on the standard parity-check matrix, aiming to generate a redundant, low-density, and quasi-regular matrix with significantly fewer length-4 cycles. The relationships between frame error rate, rank deficiency of minimum-weight dual-code codewords, and row redundancy are empirically analyzed. For the revised normalized min-sum decoder, we introduce three types of random automorphisms applied to decoder inputs. These are unpacked and aggregated by summing messages after each iteration, achieving a 1-2dB improvement in bit error rate compared to parallelizable counterparts and two orders of magnitude faster convergence in iterations than iterative rivals. Additionally, undetected errors are highlighted as a non-negligible issue for very short BCH codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20828v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guangwen Li, Xiao Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CF-CGN: Channel Fingerprints Extrapolation for Multi-band Massive MIMO Transmission based on Cycle-Consistent Generative Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20885</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20885v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multi-band massive multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) communication can promote the cooperation of licensed and unlicensed spectra, effectively enhancing spectrum efficiency for Wi-Fi and other wireless systems. As an enabler for multi-band transmission, channel fingerprints (CF), also known as the channel knowledge map or radio environment map, are used to assist channel state information (CSI) acquisition and reduce computational complexity. In this paper, we propose CF-CGN (Channel Fingerprints with Cycle-consistent Generative Networks) to extrapolate CF for multi-band massive MIMO transmission where licensed and unlicensed spectra cooperate to provide ubiquitous connectivity. Specifically, we first model CF as a multichannel image and transform the extrapolation problem into an image translation task, which converts CF from one frequency to another by exploring the shared characteristics of statistical CSI in the beam domain. Then, paired generative networks are designed and coupled by variable-weight cycle consistency losses to fit the reciprocal relationship at different bands. Matched with the coupled networks, a joint training strategy is developed accordingly, supporting synchronous optimization of all trainable parameters. During the inference process, we also introduce a refining scheme to improve the extrapolation accuracy based on the resolution of CF. Numerical results illustrate that our proposed CF-CGN can achieve bidirectional extrapolation with an error of 5-17 dB lower than the benchmarks in different communication scenarios, demonstrating its excellent generalization ability. We further show that the sum rate performance assisted by CF-CGN-based CF is close to that with perfect CSI for multi-band massive MIMO transmission.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20885v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenjie Xie, Li You, Zhenzhou Jin, Jinke Tang, Xiqi Gao, Xiang-Gen Xia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Channel Charting-assisted Non-orthogonal Pilot Allocation for Uplink XL-MIMO Transmission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20920</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20920v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Extremely large-scale multiple-input multiple-output (XL-MIMO) is critical to future wireless networks. The substantial increase in the number of base station (BS) antennas introduces near-field propagation effects in the wireless channels, complicating channel parameter estimation and increasing pilot overhead. Channel charting (CC) has emerged as a potent unsupervised technique to effectively harness varying high-dimensional channel statistics to enable non-orthogonal pilot assignment and reduce pilot overhead. In this paper, we investigate near-field channel estimation with reduced pilot overhead by developing a CC-assisted pilot scheduling. To this end, we introduce a polar-domain codebook to capture the power distribution of near-field XL-MIMO channels. The CC-assisted approach uses such features as inputs to enable an effective low-dimensional mapping of the inherent correlation patterns in near-field user terminal (UT) channels. Building upon the mapped channel correlations, we further propose a near-field CC-assisted pilot allocation (NCC-PA) algorithm, which efficiently enhances channel orthogonality among pilot-reusing UTs. Numerical results confirm that the NCC-PA algorithm substantially elevates the wireless transmission performance, offering a marked improvement over the conventional far-field CC-PA approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20920v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haohong Che, Li You, Jue Wang, Zhenzhou Jin, Chenjie Xie, Xiqi Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cluster-Based Time-Variant Channel Characterization and Modeling for 5G-Railways</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20943v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With the development of high-speed railways, 5G for Railways (5G-R) is gradually replacing Global System for the Mobile Communications for Railway (GSM-R) worldwide to meet increasing demands. The large bandwidth, array antennas, and non-stationarity caused by high mobility has made 5G-R channel characterization more complex. Therefore, it is essential to develop an accurate channel model for 5G-R. However, researches on channel characterization and time-variant models specific to 5G-R frequency bands and scenarios is scarce. There are virtually no cluster-based time-variant channel models that capture statistical properties of 5G-R channel. In this paper, we propose a cluster-based time-variant channel model for 5G-R within an enhanced 3GPP framework, which incorporates time evolution features. Extensive channel measurements are conducted on 5G-R private network test line in China. We then extract and analyze typical channel fading characteristics and multipath cluster characteristics. Furthermore, birth-death process of the clusters is modeled by using a four-state Markov chain. Finally, a generalized clustered delay line (CDL) model is established in accordance with 3GPP standard and validated by comparing the results of measurements and simulations. This work enhances the understanding of 5G-R channels and presents a flexible cluster-based time-variant channel model. The results can be used in the design, deployment, and optimization of 5G-R networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20943v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuejian Zhang, Ruisi He, Bo Ai, Mi Yang, Jianwen Ding, Shuaiqi Gao, Ziyi Qi, Zhengyu Zhang, Zhangdui Zhong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Mixture-of-Agents for Edge Inference with Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21200v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mixture-of-Agents (MoA) has recently been proposed as a method to enhance performance of large language models (LLMs), enabling multiple individual LLMs to work together for collaborative inference. This collaborative approach results in improved responses to user prompts compared to relying on a single LLM. In this paper, we consider such an MoA architecture in a distributed setting, where LLMs operate on individual edge devices, each uniquely associated with a user and equipped with its own distributed computing power. These devices exchange information using decentralized gossip algorithms, allowing different device nodes to talk without the supervision of a centralized server. In the considered setup, different users have their own LLM models to address user prompts. Additionally, the devices gossip either their own user-specific prompts or augmented prompts to generate more refined answers to certain queries. User prompts are temporarily stored in the device queues when their corresponding LLMs are busy. Given the memory limitations of edge devices, it is crucial to ensure that the average queue sizes in the system remain bounded. In this paper, we address this by theoretically calculating the queuing stability conditions for the device queues under reasonable assumptions, which we validate experimentally as well. Further, we demonstrate through experiments, leveraging open-source LLMs for the implementation of distributed MoA, that certain MoA configurations produce higher-quality responses compared to others, as evaluated on AlpacaEval 2.0 benchmark. The implementation is available at: https://github.com/purbeshmitra/distributed_moa.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21200v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Purbesh Mitra, Priyanka Kaswan, Sennur Ulukus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal MIMO Jammer Mitigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19804v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multi-antenna processing enables jammer mitigation through spatial filtering, provided that the receiver knows the spatial signature of the jammer interference. Estimating this signature is easy for barrage jammers that transmit continuously and with static signature, but difficult for more sophisticated jammers. Smart jammers may deliberately suspend transmission when the receiver tries to estimate their spatial signature, or they may use time-varying beamforming to continuously change their spatial signature. To deal with such smart jammers, we propose MASH, the first method that indiscriminately mitigates all types of jammers. Assume that the transmitter and receiver share a common secret. Based on this secret, the transmitter embeds (with a time-domain transform) its signal in a secret subspace of a higher-dimensional space. The receiver applies a reciprocal transform to the receive signal, which (i) raises the legitimate transmit signal from its secret subspace and (ii) provably transforms any jammer into a barrage jammer, making estimation and mitigation via multi-antenna processing straightforward. Focusing on the massive multi-user MIMO uplink, we present three MASH-based data detectors and show their jammer-resilience via extensive simulations. We also introduce strategies for multi-user communication without a global secret as well as methods that use computationally efficient embedding and raising transforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19804v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gian Marti, Christoph Studer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explainable Semantic Federated Learning Enabled Industrial Edge Network for Fire Surveillance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19979v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In fire surveillance, Industrial Internet of Things (IIoT) devices require transmitting large monitoring data frequently, which leads to huge consumption of spectrum resources. Hence, we propose an Industrial Edge Semantic Network (IESN) to allow IIoT devices to send warnings through Semantic communication (SC). Thus, we should consider (1) Data privacy and security. (2) SC model adaptation for heterogeneous devices. (3) Explainability of semantics. Therefore, first, we present an eXplainable Semantic Federated Learning (XSFL) to train the SC model, thus ensuring data privacy and security. Then, we present an Adaptive Client Training (ACT) strategy to provide a specific SC model for each device according to its Fisher information matrix, thus overcoming the heterogeneity. Next, an Explainable SC (ESC) mechanism is designed, which introduces a leakyReLU-based activation mapping to explain the relationship between the extracted semantics and monitoring data. Finally, simulation results demonstrate the effectiveness of XSFL.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19979v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TII.2024.3441626</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Transactions on Industrial Informatics, vol. 20, no. 12, pp. 14053-14061, Dec. 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Li Dong, Yubo Peng, Feibo Jiang, Kezhi Wang, Kun Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Hybrid Sketching for $\ell_2$-Embeddings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20301v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Linear algebraic operations are ubiquitous in engineering applications, and arise often in a variety of fields including statistical signal processing and machine learning. With contemporary large datasets, to perform linear algebraic methods and regression tasks, it is necessary to resort to both distributed computations as well as data compression. In this paper, we study \textit{distributed} $\ell_2$-subspace embeddings, a common technique used to efficiently perform linear regression. In our setting, data is distributed across multiple computing nodes and a goal is to minimize communication between the nodes and the coordinator in the distributed centralized network, while maintaining the geometry of the dataset. Furthermore, there is also the concern of keeping the data private and secure from potential adversaries. In this work, we address these issues through randomized sketching, where the key idea is to apply distinct sketching matrices on the local datasets. A novelty of this work is that we also consider \textit{hybrid sketching}, \textit{i.e.} a second sketch is applied on the aggregated locally sketched datasets, for enhanced embedding results. One of the main takeaways of this work is that by hybrid sketching, we can interpolate between the trade-offs that arise in off-the-shelf sketching matrices. That is, we can obtain gains in terms of embedding dimension or multiplication time. Our embedding arguments are also justified numerically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20301v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Neophytos Charalambides, Arya Mazumdar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal Variational Autoencoder: a Barycentric View</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20487</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20487v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multiple signal modalities, such as vision and sounds, are naturally present in real-world phenomena. Recently, there has been growing interest in learning generative models, in particular variational autoencoder (VAE), to for multimodal representation learning especially in the case of missing modalities. The primary goal of these models is to learn a modality-invariant and modality-specific representation that characterizes information across multiple modalities. Previous attempts at multimodal VAEs approach this mainly through the lens of experts, aggregating unimodal inference distributions with a product of experts (PoE), a mixture of experts (MoE), or a combination of both. In this paper, we provide an alternative generic and theoretical formulation of multimodal VAE through the lens of barycenter. We first show that PoE and MoE are specific instances of barycenters, derived by minimizing the asymmetric weighted KL divergence to unimodal inference distributions. Our novel formulation extends these two barycenters to a more flexible choice by considering different types of divergences. In particular, we explore the Wasserstein barycenter defined by the 2-Wasserstein distance, which better preserves the geometry of unimodal distributions by capturing both modality-specific and modality-invariant representations compared to KL divergence. Empirical studies on three multimodal benchmarks demonstrated the effectiveness of the proposed method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20487v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peijie Qiu, Wenhui Zhu, Sayantan Kumar, Xiwen Chen, Xiaotong Sun, Jin Yang, Abolfazl Razi, Yalin Wang, Aristeidis Sotiras</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Diffusion Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20934</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20934v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Of stochastic differential equations, diffusion processes have been adopted in numerous applications, as more relevant and flexible models. This paper studies diffusion processes in a different setting, where for a given stationary distribution and average variance, it seeks the diffusion process with optimal convergence rate. It is shown that the optimal drift function is a linear function and the convergence rate of the stochastic process is bounded by the ratio of the average variance to the variance of the stationary distribution. Furthermore, the concavity of the optimal relaxation time as a function of the stationary distribution has been proven, and it is shown that all Pearson diffusion processes of the Hypergeometric type with polynomial functions of at most degree two as the variance functions are optimal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20934v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LCSYS.2018.2843172</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Control Systems Letters, vol. 2, no. 3, pp. 465-470, July 2018</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Saber Jafarizadeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Approximate Degenerate Ordered Statistics Decoding for Quantum Codes via Reliable Subset Reduction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21118v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Efficient decoding of quantum codes is crucial for achieving high-performance quantum error correction. In this paper, we introduce the concept of approximate degenerate decoding and integrate it with ordered statistics decoding (OSD). Previously, we proposed a reliability metric that leverages both hard and soft decisions from the output of belief propagation (BP), which is particularly useful for identifying highly reliable subsets of variables. Using the approach of reliable subset reduction, we reduce the effective problem size. Additionally, we identify a degeneracy condition that allows high-order OSD to be simplified to order-0 OSD. By integrating these techniques, we present an ADOSD algorithm that significantly improves OSD efficiency in the code capacity noise model. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our BP+ADOSD approach through extensive simulations on a varity of quantum codes, including generalized hypergraph-product codes, topological codes, lift-connected surface codes, and bivariate bicycle codes. The results indicate that the BP+ADOSD decoder outperforms existing methods, achieving higher error thresholds and enhanced performance at low error rates. Additionally, we validate the efficiency of our approach in terms of computational time, demonstrating that ADOSD requires, on average, the same amount of time as two to three BP iterations on surface codes at a depolarizing error rate of around $1\%$. All the proposed algorithms are compared using single-threaded CPU implementations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21118v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ching-Feng Kung, Kao-Yueh Kuo, Ching-Yi Lai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Error Correction near the Coding Theoretical Bound</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21171</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21171v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent advancements in quantum computing have led to the realization of systems comprising tens of reliable logical qubits, constructed from thousands of noisy physical qubits. However, many of the critical applications that quantum computers aim to solve require quantum computations involving millions or more logical qubits. This necessitates highly efficient quantum error correction capable of handling large numbers of logical qubits. Classical error correction theory is well-developed, with low-density parity-check (LDPC) codes achieving performance limits by encoding large classical bits. Despite more than two decades of effort, no efficiently decodable quantum error-correcting code that approaches the hashing bound, which is a fundamental lower bound on quantum capacity, had been discovered. Here, we present quantum error-correcting codes constructed from classical LDPC codes that approach the hashing bound while maintaining linear computational complexity in the number of physical qubits. This result establishes a pathway toward realizing large-scale, fault-tolerant quantum computers. By integrating our quantum error correction scheme with devices capable of managing vast numbers of qubits, the prospect of solving critical real-world problems through quantum computation is brought significantly closer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21171v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daiki Komoto, Kenta Kasai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causal Hangover Effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.21181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.21181v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It's not unreasonable to think that in-game sporting performance can be affected partly by what takes place off the court. We can't observe what happens between games directly. Instead, we proxy for the possibility of athletes partying by looking at play following games in party cities. We are interested to see if teams exhibit a decline in performance the day following a game in a city with active nightlife; we call this a "hangover effect". Part of the question is determining a reasonable way to measure levels of nightlife, and correspondingly which cities are notorious for it; we colloquially refer to such cities as "party cities". To carry out this study, we exploit data on bookmaker spreads: the expected score differential between two teams after conditioning on observable performance in past games and expectations about the upcoming game. We expect a team to meet the spread half the time, since this is one of the easiest ways for bookmakers to guarantee a profit. We construct a model which attempts to estimate the causal effect of visiting a "party city" on subsequent day performance as measured by the odds of beating the spread. In particular, we only consider the hangover effect on games played back-to-back within 24 hours of each other. To the extent that odds of beating the spread against next day opponent is uncorrelated with playing in a party city the day before, which should be the case under an efficient betting market, we have identification in our variable of interest. We find that visiting a city with active nightlife the day prior to a game does have a statistically significant negative effect on a team's likelihood of meeting bookmakers' expectations for both NBA and MLB.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.21181v1</guid>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Santucci, Eric Lax</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>6G: The Intelligent Network of Everything</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09398v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The global 6G vision has taken its shape after years of international research and development efforts. This work culminated in ITU-R Recommendation on "IMT-2030 Framework". While the definition phase of technological requirements is currently ongoing, 3GPP standardization process on 6G networks is expected to start in 2025 and worldwide commercialization around 2029-2030. This article serves as a comprehensive guide to 6G by providing an overall vision, a contemporary survey of the main literature, and an informative tutorial-type presentation style. In our vision, 6G will be based on three fundamental elements: wireless, artificial intelligence, and Internet of Everything. Consequently, 6G can ultimately become the Intelligent Network of Everything while serving as an enabling platform for the next major disruption in mobile communication, called mobile intelligence. The potential of mobile intelligence is that anything can be made connected, intelligent, and aware of its environment. This will revolutionize the way how devices, systems, and applications are designed; how they operate and interact with humans and each other; and how they can be used for the benefit of people, society, and the world in general. After high-level visioning, the main details of 6G are discussed, including fundamental elements, disruptive applications, key use cases, main performance requirements, potential technologies, and defining features. A special focus is given to a comprehensive set of potential 6G technologies, each of which is introduced in a tutorial manner. Finally, we speculate on what comes after 6G and sketch the first high-level vision of 7G. All in all, the objective of this article is to provide a thorough guide to 6G in order to serve as a source of knowledge and inspiration for further research and development work in academia, industry, and standardization bodies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09398v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/ACCESS.2024.3521579</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Harri Pennanen, Tuomo H\"anninen, Oskari Tervo, Antti T\"olli, Matti Latva-aho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fluid Antenna Index Modulation for MIMO Systems: Robust Transmission and Low-Complexity Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04877v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The fluid antenna (FA) index modulation (IM)-enabled multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) system, referred to as FA-IM, significantly enhances spectral efficiency (SE) compared to the conventional FA-assisted MIMO system. To improve robustness against the high spatial correlation among multiple activated ports of the fluid antenna, this paper proposes an innovative FA grouping-based IM (FAG-IM) system. A block grouping scheme is employed based on the spatial correlation model and the distribution structure of the ports. Then, a closed-form expression for the average bit error probability (ABEP) upper bound of the FAG-IM system is derived. To reduce the complexity of the receiver, the message passing architecture is incorporated into the FAG-IM system. Building on this, an efficient approximate message passing (AMP) detector, named structured AMP (S-AMP) detector, is proposed by exploiting the structural characteristics of the transmitted signals. Simulation results confirm that the proposed FAG-IM system significantly outperforms the existing FA-IM system in the presence of spatial correlation, achieving more robust transmission. Furthermore, it is demonstrated that the proposed low-complexity S-AMP detector not only reduces time complexity to a linear scale but also substantially improves bit error rate (BER) performance compared to the minimum mean square error (MMSE) detector, thereby enhancing the practical feasibility of the FAG-IM system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04877v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinghao Guo, Yin Xu, Dazhi He, Cixiao Zhang, Hanjiang Hong, Kai-Kit Wong, Wenjun Zhang, Yiyan Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impossibility of Local State Transformation via Hypercontractivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1307.2747</link>
      <description>arXiv:1307.2747v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Local state transformation is the problem of transforming an arbitrary number of copies of a bipartite resource state to a bipartite target state under local operations. That is, given two bipartite states, is it possible to transform an arbitrary number of copies of one of them to one copy of the other state under local operations only? This problem is a hard one in general since we assume that the number of copies of the resource state is arbitrarily large. In this paper we prove some bounds on this problem using the hypercontractivity properties of some super-operators corresponding to bipartite states. We measure hypercontractivity in terms of both the usual super-operator norms as well as completely bounded norms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1307.2747v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00220-014-2105-y</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Communications in Mathematical Physics 332(1), 449-476 (2014)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Payam Delgosha, Salman Beigi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoding quantum information via the Petz recovery map</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1504.04449</link>
      <description>arXiv:1504.04449v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We obtain a lower bound on the maximum number of qubits, $Q^{n, \epsilon}(\mathcal{N})$, which can be transmitted over $n$ uses of a quantum channel $\mathcal{N}$, for a given non-zero error threshold $\epsilon$. To obtain our result, we first derive a bound on the one-shot entanglement transmission capacity of the channel, and then compute its asymptotic expansion up to the second order. In our method to prove this achievability bound, the decoding map, used by the receiver on the output of the channel, is chosen to be the \emph{Petz recovery map} (also known as the \emph{transpose channel}). Our result, in particular, shows that this choice of the decoder can be used to establish the coherent information as an achievable rate for quantum information transmission. Applying our achievability bound to the 50-50 erasure channel (which has zero quantum capacity), we find that there is a sharp error threshold above which $Q^{n, \epsilon}(\mathcal{N})$ scales as $\sqrt{n}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1504.04449v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/1.4961515</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Math. Phys. 57(8), 082203 (2016)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Salman Beigi, Nilanjana Datta, Felix Leditzky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Unified Analysis of Federated Learning with Arbitrary Client Participation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.13648</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.13648v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Federated learning (FL) faces challenges of intermittent client availability and computation/communication efficiency. As a result, only a small subset of clients can participate in FL at a given time. It is important to understand how partial client participation affects convergence, but most existing works have either considered idealized participation patterns or obtained results with non-zero optimality error for generic patterns. In this paper, we provide a unified convergence analysis for FL with arbitrary client participation. We first introduce a generalized version of federated averaging (FedAvg) that amplifies parameter updates at an interval of multiple FL rounds. Then, we present a novel analysis that captures the effect of client participation in a single term. By analyzing this term, we obtain convergence upper bounds for a wide range of participation patterns, including both non-stochastic and stochastic cases, which match either the lower bound of stochastic gradient descent (SGD) or the state-of-the-art results in specific settings. We also discuss various insights, recommendations, and experimental results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.13648v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiqiang Wang, Mingyue Ji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum state testing beyond the polarizing regime and quantum triangular discrimination</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.01952</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.01952v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The complexity class Quantum Statistical Zero-Knowledge ($\mathsf{QSZK}$) captures computational difficulties of the time-bounded quantum state testing problem with respect to the trace distance, known as the Quantum State Distinguishability Problem (QSDP) introduced by Watrous (FOCS 2002). However, QSDP is in $\mathsf{QSZK}$ merely within the constant polarizing regime, similar to its classical counterpart shown by Sahai and Vadhan (JACM 2003) due to the polarization lemma (error reduction for SDP).
  Recently, Berman, Degwekar, Rothblum, and Vasudevan (TCC 2019) extended the $\mathsf{SZK}$ containment for SDP beyond the polarizing regime via the time-bounded distribution testing problems with respect to the triangular discrimination and the Jensen-Shannon divergence. Our work introduces proper quantum analogs for these problems by defining quantum counterparts for triangular discrimination. We investigate whether the quantum analogs behave similarly to their classical counterparts and examine the limitations of existing approaches to polarization regarding quantum distances. These new $\mathsf{QSZK}$-complete problems improve $\mathsf{QSZK}$ containments for QSDP beyond the polarizing regime and establish a simple $\mathsf{QSZK}$-hardness for the quantum entropy difference problem (QEDP) defined by Ben-Aroya, Schwartz, and Ta-Shma (ToC 2010). Furthermore, we prove that QSDP with some exponentially small errors is in $\mathsf{PP}$, while the same problem without error is in $\mathsf{NQP}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.01952v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yupan Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-Overhead Channel Estimation via 3D Extrapolation for TDD mmWave Massive MIMO Systems Under High-Mobility Scenarios</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.08887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.08887v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In time division duplexing (TDD) millimeter wave (mmWave) massive multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) systems, downlink channel state information (CSI) can be obtained from uplink channel estimation thanks to channel reciprocity. However, under high-mobility scenarios, frequent uplink channel estimation is needed due to channel aging. Additionally, large amounts of antennas and subcarriers result in high-dimensional CSI matrices, aggravating pilot training overhead. To address this, we propose a three-domain (3D) channel extrapolation framework across spatial, frequency, and temporal domains. First, considering the effectiveness of traditional knowledge-driven channel estimation methods and the marginal effects of pilots in the spatial and frequency domains, a knowledge-and-data driven spatial-frequency channel extrapolation network (KDD-SFCEN) is proposed for uplink channel estimation via joint spatial-frequency channel extrapolation to reduce spatial-frequency domain pilot overhead. Then, leveraging channel reciprocity and temporal dependencies, we propose a temporal uplink-downlink channel extrapolation network (TUDCEN) powered by generative artificial intelligence for slot-level channel extrapolation, aiming to reduce the tremendous temporal domain pilot overhead caused by high mobility. Numerical results demonstrate the superiority of the proposed framework in significantly reducing the pilot training overhead by 16 times and improving the system's spectral efficiency under high-mobility scenarios compared with state-of-the-art channel estimation/extrapolation methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.08887v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Binggui Zhou, Xi Yang, Shaodan Ma, Feifei Gao, Guanghua Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear Complementary dual codes and Linear Complementary pairs of AG codes in function fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05845v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In recent years, linear complementary pairs (LCP) of codes and linear complementary dual (LCD) codes have gained significant attention due to their applications in coding theory and cryptography. In this work, we construct explicit LCPs of codes and LCD codes from function fields of genus $g \geq 1$. To accomplish this, we present pairs of suitable divisors giving rise to non-special divisors of degree $g-1$ in the function field. The results are applied in constructing LCPs of algebraic geometry codes and LCD algebraic geometry (AG) codes in Kummer extensions, hyperelliptic function fields, and elliptic curves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05845v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alonso S. Castellanos, Adler V. Marques, Luciane Quoos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zak-OTFS with Interleaved Pilots to Extend the Region of Predictable Operation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.09379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.09379v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: When the delay period of the Zak-OTFS carrier is greater than the delay spread of the channel, and the Doppler period of the carrier is greater than the Doppler spread of the channel, the effective channel filter taps can simply be read off from the response to a single pilot carrier waveform. The input-output (I/O) relation can then be reconstructed for a sampled system that operates under finite duration and bandwidth constraints. We introduce a framework for pilot design in the delay-Doppler (DD) domain which makes it possible to support users with very different delay-Doppler characteristics when it is not possible to choose a single delay and Doppler period to support all users. The method is to interleave single pilots in the DD domain, and to choose the pilot spacing so that the I/O relation can be reconstructed by solving a small linear system of equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.09379v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinu Jayachandran, Imran Ali Khan, Saif Khan Mohammed, Ronny Hadani, Ananthanarayanan Chockalingam, Robert Calderbank</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coprime Bivariate Bicycle Codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10001</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10001v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This work (1) proposes a novel numerical algorithm to accelerate the search process for good Bivariate Bicycle (BB) codes and (2) defines a new subclass of BB codes suitable for quantum error correction. The proposed acceleration search algorithm reduces the search space by excluding some equivalent codes from the search space, as well as setting thresholds to drop bad codes at an early stage. A number of new BB codes found by this algorithm are reported. The proposed subclass of BB codes employs coprimes to construct groups via polynomials as the basis for the BB code, rather than using the standard BB codes with unconstrained constructors. In contrast to vanilla BB codes, where parameters remain unknown prior to code discovery, the rate of the proposed code can be determined beforehand by specifying a factor polynomial as an input to the numerical search algorithm. Using this coprime BB construction, we found a number of surprisingly short to medium-length codes that were previously unknown.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10001v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ming Wang, Frank Mueller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A physics-compliant diagonal representation for wireless channels parametrized by beyond-diagonal reconfigurable intelligent surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.20509</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.20509v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The parametrization of wireless channels by so-called "beyond-diagonal reconfigurable intelligent surfaces" (BD-RIS) is mathematically characterized by a matrix whose off-diagonal entries are partially or fully populated. Physically, this corresponds to tunable coupling mechanisms between the RIS elements that originate from the RIS control circuit. Here, we derive a physics-compliant diagonal representation for BD-RIS-parametrized channels. We recognize that any RIS control circuit can always be separated into its static parts (SLC) and a set of tunable individual loads (IL). Therefore, a BD-RIS-parametrized channel results from the chain cascade of three systems: i) radio environment (RE), ii) SLC, and iii) IL. RE and SLC are static non-diagonal systems whose cascade K is terminated by the tunable diagonal system IL. This physics-compliant representation in terms of K and IL is directly analogous to that for conventional ("diagonal") RIS (D-RIS). Therefore, scenarios with BD-RIS can also readily be captured by the physics-compliant coupled-dipole model PhysFad, as we show. In addition, physics-compliant algorithms for system-level optimization with D-RIS can be directly applied to scenarios with BD-RIS. We demonstrate this important implication of our conceptual finding in a case study on end-to-end channel estimation and optimization in a BD-RIS-parametrized rich-scattering environment. Our case study is the first experimentally grounded system-level optimization for BD-RIS: We obtain the characteristics of RE and IL from experimental measurements and a commercial PIN diode, respectively. Altogether, our physics-compliant diagonal representation for BD-RIS enables a paradigm shift in how practitioners in wireless communications and signal processing implement system-level optimizations for BD-RIS because it enables them to directly apply existing physics-compliant D-RIS algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.20509v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philipp del Hougne</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InfAlign: Inference-aware language model alignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19792v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Language model alignment has become a critical step in training modern generative language models. The goal of alignment is to finetune a reference model such that the win rate of a sample from the aligned model over a sample from the reference model is high, subject to a KL divergence constraint. Today, we are increasingly using inference-time algorithms (e.g., Best-of-N, controlled decoding, tree search) to decode from language models rather than standard sampling. However, the alignment objective does not capture such inference-time decoding procedures. We show that the existing alignment framework is sub-optimal in view of such inference-time methods. We then modify the alignment objective and propose a framework for inference-aware alignment (IAPO). We prove that for any inference-time decoding algorithm, the optimal solution that optimizes the inference-time win rate of the aligned policy against the reference policy is the solution to the typical RLHF problem with a transformation of the reward. This motivates us to provide the KL-regularized calibrate-and-transform RL (CTRL) algorithm to solve this problem, which involves a reward calibration step and a KL-regularized reward maximization step with a transformation of the calibrated reward. We particularize our study to two important inference-time strategies: best-of-N sampling and best-of-N jailbreaking, where N responses are sampled from the model and the one with the highest or lowest reward is selected. We propose specific transformations for these strategies and demonstrate that our framework offers significant improvements over existing state-of-the-art methods for language model alignment. Empirically, we outperform baselines that are designed without taking inference-time decoding into consideration by 8-12% and 4-9% on inference-time win rates over the Anthropic helpfulness and harmlessness dialog benchmark datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19792v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ananth Balashankar, Ziteng Sun, Jonathan Berant, Jacob Eisenstein, Michael Collins, Adrian Hutter, Jong Lee, Chirag Nagpal, Flavien Prost, Aradhana Sinha, Ananda Theertha Suresh, Ahmad Beirami</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
