<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.IT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.IT</link>
    <description>math.IT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.IT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 04:00:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Polarized 6D Movable Antenna for Wireless Communication: Channel Modeling and Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04471v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a novel polarized six-dimensional movable antenna (P-6DMA) to enhance the performance of wireless communication cost-effectively. Specifically, the P-6DMA enables polarforming by adaptively tuning the antenna's polarization electrically as well as controls the antenna's rotation mechanically, thereby exploiting both polarization and spatial diversity to reconfigure wireless channels for improving communication performance. First, we model the P-6DMA channel in terms of transceiver antenna polarforming vectors and antenna rotations. We then propose a new two-timescale transmission protocol to maximize the weighted sum-rate for a P-6DMA-enhanced multiuser system. Specifically, antenna rotations at the base station (BS) are first optimized based on the statistical channel state information (CSI) of all users, which varies at a much slower rate compared to their instantaneous CSI. Then, transceiver polarforming vectors are designed to cater to the instantaneous CSI under the optimized BS antennas' rotations. Under the polarforming phase shift and amplitude constraints, a new polarforming and rotation joint design problem is efficiently addressed by a low-complexity algorithm based on penalty dual decomposition, where the polarforming coefficients are updated in parallel to reduce computational time. Simulation results demonstrate the significant performance advantages of polarforming, antenna rotation, and their joint design in comparison with various benchmarks without polarforming or antenna rotation adaptation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04471v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaodan Shao, Qijun Jiang, Derrick Wing Kwan Ng, Naofal Al-Dhahir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sparse Phase Retrieval with Redundant Dictionary via $\ell_q (0&lt;q\le 1)$-Analysis Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04576v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Sparse phase retrieval with redundant dictionary is to reconstruct the signals of interest that are (nearly) sparse in a redundant dictionary or frame from the phaseless measurements via the optimization models. Gao [7] presented conditions on the measurement matrix, called null space property (NSP) and strong dictionary restricted isometry property (S-DRIP), for exact and stable recovery of dictionary-$k$-sparse signals via the $\ell_1$-analysis model for sparse phase retrieval with redundant dictionary, respectively, where, in particularly, the S-DRIP of order $tk$ with $t&gt;1$ was derived. In this paper, motivated by many advantages of the $\ell_q$ minimization with $0&lt;q\leq1$, e.g., reduction of the number of measurements required, we generalize these two conditions to the $\ell_q$-analysis model. Specifically, we first present two NSP variants for exact recovery of dictionary-$k$-sparse signals via the $\ell_q$-analysis model in the noiseless scenario. Moreover, we investigate the S-DRIP of order $tk$ with $0&lt;t&lt;\frac{4}{3}$ for stable recovery of dictionary-$k$-sparse signals via the $\ell_q$-analysis model in the noisy scenario, which will complement the existing result of the S-DRIP of order $tk$ with $t\geq2$ obtained in [4].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04576v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haiye Huo, Li Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Role of Early-Termination for Age of Information in Tree-Based Random Access Protocols</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04793v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Age of Information (AoI) has emerged as a key metric for assessing data freshness in IoT applications, where a large number of devices report time-stamped updates to a monitor. Such systems often rely on random access protocols based on variations of ALOHA at the link layer, where collision resolution algorithms play a fundamental role to enable reliable delivery of packets. In this context, we provide the first analytical characterization of average AoI for the classical Capetanakis tree-based algorithm with gated access under exogenous traffic, capturing the protocol's dynamics, driven by sporadic packet generation and variable collision resolution times. We also explore a variant with early termination, where contention is truncated after a maximum number of slots even if not all users are resolved. The approach introduces a fundamental trade-off between reliability and timeliness, allowing stale packets to be dropped to improve freshness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04793v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Munari, Cedomir Stefanovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatio-Temporal Information Freshness for Remote Source Monitoring in IoT Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04804v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The widespread adoption of age of information (AoI) as a meaningful and analytically tractable information freshness metric has led to a wide body of work on the timing performance of Internet of things (IoT) systems. However, the spatial correlation inherent to environmental monitoring has been mostly neglected in the recent literature, due to the significant modeling complexity it introduces. In this work, we address this gap by presenting a model of spatio-temporal information freshness, considering the conditional entropy of the system state in a remote monitoring scenario, such as a low-orbit satellite collecting information from a wide geographical area. Our analytical results show that purely age-oriented schemes tend to select an overly broad communication range, leading to inaccurate estimates and energy inefficiency, both of which can be mitigated by adopting a spatio-temporal approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04804v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Munari, Federico Chiariotti, Leonardo Badia, Petar Popovski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Iterative Neural Rollback Chase-Pyndiah Decoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04839v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Iterative decoding is essential in modern communication systems, especially optical communications, where error-correcting codes such as turbo product codes (TPC) and staircase codes are widely employed. A key factor in achieving high error correction performance is the use of soft-decision decoding for component codes. However, implementing optimal maximum a posteriori (MAP) probability decoding for commonly used component codes, such as BCH and Polar codes, is computationally prohibitive. Instead, practical systems rely on approximations, with the Chase-Pyndiah algorithm being a widely used suboptimal method. TPC are more powerful than their component codes and begin to function effectively at low signal-to-noise ratios. Consequently, during the initial iterations, the component codes do not perform well and introduce errors in the extrinsic information updates. This phenomenon limits the performance of TPC. This paper proposes a neural network-aided rollback Chase-Pyndiah decoding method to address this issue. A transformer-based neural network identifies cases where extrinsic updates are likely to introduce errors, triggering a rollback mechanism which prevents the update and keeps the component code message intact. Our results demonstrate that a neural network with a relatively small number of parameters can effectively distinguish destructive updates and improve decoding performance. We evaluate the proposed approach using TPC with (256, 239) extended BCH component codes. We show that the proposed method enhances the bit error rate performance of Chase-Pyndiah p=6 decoding, achieving a gain of approximately 0.145 dB in a TPC scheme with four full iterations, significantly outperforming conventional Chase p=7 decoding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04839v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dmitry Artemasov, Oleg Nesterenkov, Kirill Andreev, Pavel Rybin, Alexey Frolov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Goal-Oriented Semantic Resource Allocation with Cumulative Prospect Theoretic Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04947v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a resource allocation framework for goal-oriented semantic networks, where participating agents assess system quality through subjective (e.g., context-dependent) perceptions. To accommodate this, our model accounts for agents whose preferences deviate from traditional expected utility theory (EUT), specifically incorporating cumulative prospect theory (CPT) preferences. We develop a comprehensive analytical framework that captures human-centric aspects of decision-making and risky choices under uncertainty, such as risk perception, loss aversion, and perceptual distortions in probability metrics. By identifying essential modifications in traditional resource allocation design principles required for agents with CPT preferences, we showcase the framework's relevance through its application to the problem of power allocation in multi-channel wireless communication systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04947v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Symeon Vaidanis, Photios A. Stavrou, Marios Kountouris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimization for Semantic-Aware Resource Allocation under CPT-based Utilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04952</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04952v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The problem of resource allocation in goal-oriented semantic communication with semantic-aware utilities and subjective risk perception is studied here. By linking information importance to risk aversion, we model agent behavior using Cumulative Prospect Theory (CPT), which incorporates risk-sensitive utility functions and nonlinear transformations of distributions, reflecting subjective perceptions of gains and losses. The objective is to maximize the aggregate utility across multiple CPT-modeled agents, which leads to a nonconvex, nonsmooth optimization problem. To efficiently solve this challenging problem, we propose a new algorithmic framework that combines successive convex approximation (SCA) with the projected subgradient method and Lagrangian relaxation, Our approach enables tractable optimization while preserving solution quality, offering both theoretical rigor and practical effectiveness in semantics-aware resource allocation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04952v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Symeon Vaidanis, Photios A. Stavrou, Marios Kountouris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CSI2Vec: Towards a Universal CSI Feature Representation for Positioning and Channel Charting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05237v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Natural language processing techniques, such as Word2Vec, have demonstrated exceptional capabilities in capturing semantic and syntactic relationships of text through vector embeddings. Inspired by this technique, we propose CSI2Vec, a self-supervised framework for generating universal and robust channel state information (CSI) representations tailored to CSI-based positioning (POS) and channel charting (CC). CSI2Vec learns compact vector embeddings across various wireless scenarios, capturing spatial relationships between user equipment positions without relying on CSI reconstruction or ground-truth position information. We implement CSI2Vec as a neural network that is trained across various deployment setups (i.e., the spatial arrangement of radio equipment and scatterers) and radio setups (RSs) (i.e., the specific hardware used), ensuring robustness to aspects such as differences in the environment, the number of used antennas, or allocated set of subcarriers. CSI2Vec abstracts the RS by generating compact vector embeddings that capture essential spatial information, avoiding the need for full CSI transmission or reconstruction while also reducing complexity and improving processing efficiency of downstream tasks. Simulations with ray-tracing and real-world CSI datasets demonstrate CSI2Vec's effectiveness in maintaining excellent POS and CC performance while reducing computational demands and storage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05237v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victoria Palhares, Sueda Taner, Christoph Studer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling Voices: A Co-Hashtag Analysis of TikTok Discourse on the 2023 Israel-Palestine Crisis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07182</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07182v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: TikTok has gradually become one of the most pervasive social media platforms in our daily lives. While much can be said about the merits of platforms such as TikTok, there is a different kind of attention paid towards the political affect of social media today compared to its impact on other aspects of modern networked reality. I explored how users on TikTok discussed the crisis in Palestine that worsened in 2023. Using network analysis, I situate keywords representing the conflict and categorize them thematically based on a coding schema derived from politically and ideologically differentiable stances. I conclude that activism and propaganda are contending amongst themselves in the thriving space afforded by TikTok today.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07182v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rozin Hasin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimating the Euclidean distortion of an orbit space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04425v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given a finite-dimensional inner product space $V$ and a group $G$ of isometries, we consider the problem of embedding the orbit space $V/G$ into a Hilbert space in a way that preserves the quotient metric as well as possible. This inquiry is motivated by applications to invariant machine learning. We introduce several new theoretical tools before using them to tackle various fundamental instances of this problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04425v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Blum-Smith, Harm Derksen, Dustin G. Mixon, Yousef Qaddura, Brantley Vose</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved Regret Bounds for Linear Bandits with Heavy-Tailed Rewards</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04775</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04775v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study stochastic linear bandits with heavy-tailed rewards, where the rewards have a finite $(1+\epsilon)$-absolute central moment bounded by $\upsilon$ for some $\epsilon \in (0,1]$. We improve both upper and lower bounds on the minimax regret compared to prior work. When $\upsilon = \mathcal{O}(1)$, the best prior known regret upper bound is $\tilde{\mathcal{O}}(d T^{\frac{1}{1+\epsilon}})$. While a lower with the same scaling has been given, it relies on a construction using $\upsilon = \mathcal{O}(d)$, and adapting the construction to the bounded-moment regime with $\upsilon = \mathcal{O}(1)$ yields only a $\Omega(d^{\frac{\epsilon}{1+\epsilon}} T^{\frac{1}{1+\epsilon}})$ lower bound. This matches the known rate for multi-armed bandits and is generally loose for linear bandits, in particular being $\sqrt{d}$ below the optimal rate in the finite-variance case ($\epsilon = 1$). We propose a new elimination-based algorithm guided by experimental design, which achieves regret $\tilde{\mathcal{O}}(d^{\frac{1+3\epsilon}{2(1+\epsilon)}} T^{\frac{1}{1+\epsilon}})$, thus improving the dependence on $d$ for all $\epsilon \in (0,1)$ and recovering a known optimal result for $\epsilon = 1$. We also establish a lower bound of $\Omega(d^{\frac{2\epsilon}{1+\epsilon}} T^{\frac{1}{1+\epsilon}})$, which strictly improves upon the multi-armed bandit rate and highlights the hardness of heavy-tailed linear bandit problems. For finite action sets, we derive similarly improved upper and lower bounds for regret. Finally, we provide action set dependent regret upper bounds showing that for some geometries, such as $l_p$-norm balls for $p \le 1 + \epsilon$, we can further reduce the dependence on $d$, and we can handle infinite-dimensional settings via the kernel trick, in particular establishing new regret bounds for the Mat\'ern kernel that are the first to be sublinear for all $\epsilon \in (0, 1]$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04775v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Artin Tajdini, Jonathan Scarlett, Kevin Jamieson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information-Optimal Sensing and Control in High-Intensity Laser Experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04946v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: High-intensity laser systems present unique measurement and optimization challenges due to their high complexity, low repetition rates, and shot-to-shot variations. We discuss recent developments towards a unified framework based on information theory and Bayesian inference that addresses these challenges. Starting from fundamental constraints on the physical field structure, we recently demonstrated how to capture complete spatio-temporal information about individual petawatt laser pulses. Building on this foundation, we demonstrate how Bayesian frameworks can leverage temporal correlations between consecutive pulses to improve measurement precision. We then extend these concepts to active sensing strategies that adaptively select measurements to maximize information gain, exemplified through Bayesian autocorrelation spectroscopy. Finally, we show how these information-optimal measurement principles naturally extend to Bayesian optimization. This progression represents a paradigm shift where measurement devices transition from passive data collectors to active participants in complex experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04946v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. D\"opp, C. Eberle, J. Esslinger, S. Howard, F. Irshad, J. Schroeder, N. Weisse, S. Karsch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Norming Sets for Tensor and Polynomial Sketching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05174v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper develops the sketching (i.e., randomized dimension reduction) theory for real algebraic varieties and images of polynomial maps, including, e.g., the set of low rank tensors and tensor networks. Through the lens of norming sets, we provide a framework for controlling the sketching dimension for \textit{any} sketch operator used to embed said sets, including sub-Gaussian, fast Johnson-Lindenstrauss, and tensor structured sketch operators. Leveraging norming set theory, we propose a new sketching method called the median sketch. It embeds such a set $V$ using only $\widetilde{\mathcal{O}}(\dim V)$ tensor structured or sparse linear measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05174v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Zhang, Joe Kileel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Upper bound for the Holevo quantity arising from the fundamental entropic inequality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05335v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show how the fundamental entropic inequality proved recently in [arXiv:2408.15306] can be used to obtain a quite accurate upper bound on the Holevo quantity of a discrete ensemble of quantum states expressed via the probabilities and the metric characteristics of this ensembles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05335v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. E. Shirokov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>R\'enyi divergence guarantees for hashing with linear codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04406v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the problem of distilling uniform random bits from an unknown source with a given $p$-entropy using linear hashing. As our main result, we estimate the expected $p$-divergence from the uniform distribution over the ensemble of random linear codes for all integer $p\ge 2$. The proof relies on analyzing how additive noise, determined by a random element of the code from the ensemble, acts on the source distribution. This action leads to the transformation of the source distribution into an approximately uniform one, a process commonly referred to as distribution smoothing. We also show that hashing with Reed-Muller matrices reaches intrinsic randomness of memoryless Bernoulli sources in the $l_p$ sense for all integer $p\ge 2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04406v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TIT.2025.3577765</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Madhura Pathegama, Alexander Barg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Deviation Analysis for the Reverse Shannon Theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07984v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Channel simulation is to simulate a noisy channel using noiseless channels with unlimited shared randomness. This can be interpreted as the reverse problem to Shannon's noisy coding theorem. In contrast to previous works, our approach employs R\'enyi divergence (with the parameter $\alpha\in(0,\infty)$) to measure the level of approximation. Specifically, we obtain the reverse Shannon theorem under the R\'enyi divergence, which characterizes the R\'enyi simulation rate, the minimum communication cost rate required for the R\'enyi divergence vanishing asymptotically. We also investigate the behaviors of the R\'enyi divergence when the communication cost rate is above or below the R\'enyi simulation rate. When the communication cost rate is above the R\'enyi simulation rate, we provide a complete characterization of the convergence exponent, called the reliability function. When the communication cost rate is below the R\'enyi simulation rate, we determine the linear increasing rate for the R\'enyi divergence with parameter $\alpha\in(0,\infty]$, which implies the strong converse exponent for the $\alpha$-order fidelity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07984v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shi-Bing Li, Ke Li, Lei Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information Limits of Joint Community Detection and Finite Group Synchronization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16387</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16387v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The emerging problem of joint community detection and group synchronization, with applications in signal processing and machine learning, has been extensively studied in recent years. Previous research has predominantly focused on a statistical model that extends the stochastic block model~(SBM) by incorporating additional group transformations. In its simplest form, the model randomly generates a network of size $n$ that consists of two equal-sized communities, where each node $i$ is associated with an unknown group element $g_i^* \in G_M$ for some finite group $G_M$ of order $M$. The connectivity between nodes follows a probability $p$ if they belong to the same community, and a probability $q$ otherwise. Moreover, a group transformation $g_{ij} \in G_M$ is observed on each edge $(i,j)$, where $g_{ij} = g_i^* - g_j^*$ if nodes $i$ and $j$ are within the same community, and $g_{ij} \sim \text{Uniform}(G_M)$ otherwise. The goal of the problem is to recover both the underlying communities and group elements. Under this setting, when $p = a\log n /n$ and $q = b\log n /n $ with $a, b &gt; 0$, we establish the following sharp information-theoretic threshold for exact recovery by maximum likelihood estimation~(MLE): $$ (i):\enspace \frac{a + b}{2} -\sqrt{\frac{ab}{M}} &gt; 1 \quad \text{and} \quad (ii):\enspace a &gt; 2$$ where the exact recovery of communities is possible only if $(i)$ is satisfied, and the recovery of group elements is achieved only if both $(i)$ and $(ii)$ are satisfied. Our theory indicates the recovery of communities greatly benefits from the extra group transformations. Also, it demonstrates a significant performance gap exists between the MLE and all the existing approaches, including algorithms based on semidefinite programming and spectral methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16387v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifeng Fan, Zhizhen Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-terminal Strong Coordination over Noisy Channels with Encoder Co-operation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12227</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12227v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the problem of strong coordination over a multiple-access channel (MAC) with cribbing encoders. In this configuration, two encoders observe independent and identically distributed (i.i.d.) samples of a source random variable each and encode the inputs to the MAC. The decoder which observes the output of the MAC together with side-information, must generate approximately i.i.d. samples of another random variable which is jointly distributed with the two sources and the side information. We also allow for possible encoder cooperation, where one of the encoders can non-causally crib from the other encoders input. Independent pairwise shared randomness is assumed between each encoder and the decoder at limited rates. Firstly, in the presence of cribbing, we derive an achievable region based on joint source-channel coding. We also prove that in the absence of cribbing, our inner bound is tight for the special case when the MAC is composed of deterministic links, and the sources are conditionally independent given the side information. We then explicitly compute the regions for an example both with and without cribbing between the encoders, and demonstrate that cribbing strictly improves upon the achievable region.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12227v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viswanathan Ramachandran, Tobias J. Oechtering, Mikael Skoglund</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simultaneous Rational Number Codes: Decoding Beyond Half the Minimum Distance with Multiplicities and Bad Primes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08472v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we extend the work of (Abbondati et al., 2024) on decoding simultaneous rational number codes by addressing two important scenarios: multiplicities and the presence of bad primes (divisors of denominators). First, we generalize previous results to multiplicity rational codes by considering modular reductions with respect to prime power moduli. Then, using hybrid analysis techniques, we extend our approach to vectors of fractions that may present bad primes. Our contributions include: a decoding algorithm for simultaneous rational number reconstruction with multiplicities, a rigorous analysis of the algorithm's failure probability that generalizes several previous results, an extension to a hybrid model handling situations where not all errors can be assumed random, and a unified approach to handle bad primes within multiplicities. The theoretical results provide a comprehensive probabilistic analysis of reconstruction failure in these more complex scenarios, advancing the state of the art in error correction for rational number codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08472v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.SC</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Abbondati (LIRMM | ECO), Eleonora Guerrini (LIRMM | ECO), Romain Lebreton (LIRMM | ECO)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Divisible minimal codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.00885</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.00885v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Minimal codes are linear codes where all non-zero codewords are minimal, i.e., whose support is not properly contained in the support of another codeword. The minimum possible length of such a $k$-dimensional linear code over $\mathbb{F}_q$ is denoted by $m(k,q)$. Here we determine $m(7,2)$, $m(8,2)$, and $m(9,2)$, as well as full classifications of all codes attaining $m(k,2)$ for $k\le 7$ and those attaining $m(9,2)$. We give improved upper bounds for $m(k,2)$ for all $10\le k\le 17$. It turns out that in many cases the attaining extremal codes have the property that the weights of all codewords are divisible by some constant $\Delta&gt;1$. So, here we study the minimum lengths of minimal codes where we additionally assume that the weights of the codewords are divisible by $\Delta$. As a byproduct we also give a few binary linear codes improving the best known lower bound for the minimum distance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.00885v3</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Chubenko, Sascha Kurz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial Network Calculus: Toward Deterministic Wireless Networking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02556v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper extends the classical network calculus to spatial scenarios, focusing on wireless networks with differentiated services and varying transmit power levels. Building on a spatial network calculus, a prior extension of network calculus to spatial settings, we propose a generalized framework by introducing regulations for stationary marked point processes. The regulations correspond to two key constraints: the total transmit power of all transmitters within a spatial region and the cumulative received power at a receiver, which we refer to as ball regulation and shot-noise regulation, respectively. Then we prove the equivalence of ball regulation and shot-noise regulation for stationary marked point processes and establish a universal lower bound on the performance of all network links under these constraints. This framework is applicable to diverse network scenarios, as demonstrated by the analysis of performance guarantees for networks with multi-class users. In addition, we propose an SINR-based power control scheme adapted to user traffic, which ensures differentiated quality of service (QoS) for different user classes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02556v4</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi Zhong, Xiaohang Zhou, Ke Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing hypergraph product codes with random walks, simulated annealing and reinforcement learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09622v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Hypergraph products are quantum low-density parity-check (LDPC) codes constructed from two classical LDPC codes. Although their dimension and distance depend only on the parameters of the underlying classical codes, optimizing their performance against various noise channels remains challenging. This difficulty partly stems from the complexity of decoding in the quantum setting. The standard, ad hoc approach typically involves selecting classical LDPC codes with large girth. In this work, we focus on optimizing performance against the quantum erasure channel. A key advantage of this channel is the existence of an efficient maximum-likelihood decoder, which enables us to employ optimization techniques based on sampling random codes, such as Reinforcement Learning (RL) and Simulated Annealing (SA). Our results indicate that these techniques improve performance relative to the state-of-the-art.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09622v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruno C. A. Freire, Nicolas Delfosse, Anthony Leverrier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adversarial Combinatorial Semi-bandits with Graph Feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18826v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In combinatorial semi-bandits, a learner repeatedly selects from a combinatorial decision set of arms, receives the realized sum of rewards, and observes the rewards of the individual selected arms as feedback. In this paper, we extend this framework to include \emph{graph feedback}, where the learner observes the rewards of all neighboring arms of the selected arms in a feedback graph $G$. We establish that the optimal regret over a time horizon $T$ scales as $\widetilde{\Theta}(S\sqrt{T}+\sqrt{\alpha ST})$, where $S$ is the size of the combinatorial decisions and $\alpha$ is the independence number of $G$. This result interpolates between the known regrets $\widetilde\Theta(S\sqrt{T})$ under full information (i.e., $G$ is complete) and $\widetilde\Theta(\sqrt{KST})$ under the semi-bandit feedback (i.e., $G$ has only self-loops), where $K$ is the total number of arms. A key technical ingredient is to realize a convexified action using a random decision vector with negative correlations. We also show that online stochastic mirror descent (OSMD) that only realizes convexified actions in expectation is suboptimal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18826v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxiao Wen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bottlenecked Transformers: Periodic KV Cache Abstraction for Generalised Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16950</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16950v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Despite their impressive capabilities, Large Language Models struggle with generalisation beyond their training distribution, often exhibiting sophisticated pattern interpolation rather than true abstract reasoning (extrapolation). In this work, we approach this limitation through the lens of Information Bottleneck (IB) theory, which posits that model generalisation emerges from an optimal balance between input compression and retention of predictive information in latent representations. We prove using IB theory that decoder-only Transformers are inherently constrained in their ability to form task-optimal sequence representations. We then use this result to demonstrate that periodic global transformation of the internal sequence-level representations (KV cache) is a necessary computational step for improving Transformer generalisation in reasoning tasks. Based on these theoretical insights, we propose a modification to the Transformer architecture, in the form of an additional module that globally rewrites the KV cache at periodic intervals, shifting its capacity away from memorising input prefixes and toward encoding features most useful for predicting future tokens. Our model delivers substantial gains on mathematical reasoning benchmarks, outperforming both vanilla Transformers with up to 3.5x more parameters, as well as heuristic-driven pruning mechanisms for cache compression. Our approach can be seen as a principled generalisation of existing KV-cache compression methods; whereas such methods focus solely on compressing input representations, they often do so at the expense of retaining predictive information, and thus their capabilities are inherently bounded by those of an unconstrained model. This establishes a principled framework to manipulate Transformer memory using information theory, addressing fundamental reasoning limitations that scaling alone cannot overcome.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16950v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adnan Oomerjee, Zafeirios Fountas, Zhongwei Yu, Haitham Bou-Ammar, Jun Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
