<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.IT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.IT</link>
    <description>math.IT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.IT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 04:04:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Asymmetric graph alignment and the phase transition for asymmetric tree correlation testing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02299</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02299v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Graph alignment - identifying node correspondences between two graphs - is a fundamental problem with applications in network analysis, biology, and privacy research. While substantial progress has been made in aligning correlated Erd\H{o}s-R\'enyi graphs under symmetric settings, real-world networks often exhibit asymmetry in both node numbers and edge densities. In this work, we introduce a novel framework for asymmetric correlated Erd\H{o}s-R\'enyi graphs, generalizing existing models to account for these asymmetries. We conduct a rigorous theoretical analysis of graph alignment in the sparse regime, where local neighborhoods exhibit tree-like structures. Our approach leverages tree correlation testing as the central tool in our polynomial-time algorithm, MPAlign, which achieves one-sided partial alignment under certain conditions.
  A key contribution of our work is characterizing these conditions under which asymmetric tree correlation testing is feasible: If two correlated graphs $G$ and $G'$ have average degrees $\lambda s$ and $\lambda s'$ respectively, where $\lambda$ is their common density and $s,s'$ are marginal correlation parameters, their tree neighborhoods can be aligned if $ss' &gt; \alpha$, where $\alpha$ denotes Otter's constant and $\lambda$ is supposed large enough. The feasibility of this tree comparison problem undergoes a sharp phase transition since $ss' \leq \alpha$ implies its impossibility. These new results on tree correlation testing allow us to solve a class of random subgraph isomorphism problems, resolving an open problem in the field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02299v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jakob Maier, Laurent Massouli\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Liquid Neural Networks: Next-Generation AI for Telecom from First Principles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02352</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02352v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Artificial intelligence (AI) has emerged as a transformative technology with immense potential to reshape the next-generation of wireless networks. By leveraging advanced algorithms and machine learning techniques, AI offers unprecedented capabilities in optimizing network performance, enhancing data processing efficiency, and enabling smarter decision-making processes. However, existing AI solutions face significant challenges in terms of robustness and interpretability. Specifically, current AI models exhibit substantial performance degradation in dynamic environments with varying data distributions, and the black-box nature of these algorithms raises concerns regarding safety, transparency, and fairness. This presents a major challenge in integrating AI into practical communication systems. Recently, a novel type of neural network, known as the liquid neural networks (LNNs), has been designed from first principles to address these issues. In this paper, we explore the potential of LNNs in telecommunications. First, we illustrate the mechanisms of LNNs and highlight their unique advantages over traditional networks. Then we unveil the opportunities that LNNs bring to future wireless networks. Furthermore, we discuss the challenges and design directions for the implementation of LNNs. Finally, we summarize the performance of LNNs in two case studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02352v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fenghao Zhu, Xinquan Wang, Chen Zhu, Chongwen Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Efficient Reservation Protocol for Medium Access: When Tree Splitting Meets Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02376v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As an enhanced version of massive machine-type communication in 5G, massive communication has emerged as one of the six usage scenarios anticipated for 6G, owing to its potential in industrial internet-of-things and smart metering. Driven by the need for random multiple-access (RMA) in massive communication, as well as, next-generation Wi-Fi, medium access control has attracted considerable recent attention. Holding the promise of attaining bandwidth-efficient collision resolution, multiaccess reservation no doubt plays a central role in RMA, e.g., the distributed coordination function (DCF) in IEEE 802.11. In this paper, we are interested in maximizing the bandwidth efficiency of reservation protocols for RMA under quality-of-service constraints. Particularly, we present a tree splitting based reservation scheme, in which the attempting probability is dynamically optimized by partially observable Markov decision process or reinforcement learning (RL). The RL-empowered tree-splitting algorithm guarantees that all these terminals with backlogged packets at the beginning of a contention cycle can be scheduled, thereby providing a first-in-first-out service. More importantly, it substantially reduces the reservation bandwidth determined by the communication complexity of DCF, through judiciously conceived coding and interaction for exchanging information required by distributed ordering. Simulations demonstrate that the proposed algorithm outperforms the CSMA/CA based DCF in IEEE 802.11.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02376v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yutao Chen, Wei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revolutionizing Medical Data Transmission with IoMT: A Comprehensive Survey of Wireless Communication Solutions and Future Directions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02446v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Traditional hospital-based medical examination methods face unprecedented challenges due to the aging global population. The Internet of Medical Things (IoMT), an advanced extension of the Internet of Things (IoT) tailored for the medical field, offers a transformative solution for delivering medical care. IoMT consists of interconnected medical devices that collect and transmit patients' vital signs online. This data can be analyzed to identify potential health issues, support medical decision-making, enhance patient outcomes, and streamline healthcare operations. Additionally, IoMT helps individuals make informed decisions about their health and fitness. There is a natural synergy with emerging communication technologies to ensure the secure and timely transmission of medical data. This paper presents the first comprehensive tutorial on cutting-edge IoMT research focusing on wireless communication-based solutions. It introduces a systematic three-tier framework to analyze IoMT networks and identify application scenarios. The paper examines the medical data transmission process, including intra-wireless Body Area Networks (WBAN), inter-WBAN, and beyond-WBAN communications. It also discusses the challenges of implementing IoMT applications, such as the longevity of biosensors, co-channel interference management, information security, and data processing delays. Proposed solutions to these challenges are explored from a wireless communication perspective, and future research directions are outlined. The survey concludes with a summary of key findings and insights.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02446v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiasi Zhou, Yanjing Sun, Chintha Tellambura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-Driven Design of 3GPP Handover Parameters with Bayesian Optimization and Transfer Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02633v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mobility management in dense cellular networks is challenging due to varying user speeds and deployment conditions. Traditional 3GPP handover (HO) schemes, relying on fixed A3-offset and time-to-trigger (TTT) parameters, struggle to balance radio link failures (RLFs) and ping-pongs. We propose a data-driven HO optimization framework based on high-dimensional Bayesian optimization (HD-BO) and enhanced with transfer learning to reduce training time and improve generalization across different user speeds. Evaluations on a real-world deployment show that HD-BO outperforms 3GPP set-1 and set-5 benchmarks, while transfer learning enables rapid adaptation without loss in performance. This highlights the potential of data-driven, site-specific mobility management in large-scale networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02633v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed Benzaghta, Sahar Ammar, David L\'opez-P\'erez, Basem Shihada, Giovanni Geraci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TeleMoM: Consensus-Driven Telecom Intelligence via Mixture of Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02712v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Large language models (LLMs) face significant challenges in specialized domains like telecommunication (Telecom) due to technical complexity, specialized terminology, and rapidly evolving knowledge. Traditional methods, such as scaling model parameters or retraining on domain-specific corpora, are computationally expensive and yield diminishing returns, while existing approaches like retrieval-augmented generation, mixture of experts, and fine-tuning struggle with accuracy, efficiency, and coordination. To address this issue, we propose Telecom mixture of models (TeleMoM), a consensus-driven ensemble framework that integrates multiple LLMs for enhanced decision-making in Telecom. TeleMoM employs a two-stage process: proponent models generate justified responses, and an adjudicator finalizes decisions, supported by a quality-checking mechanism. This approach leverages strengths of diverse models to improve accuracy, reduce biases, and handle domain-specific complexities effectively. Evaluation results demonstrate that TeleMoM achieves a 9.7\% increase in answer accuracy, highlighting its effectiveness in Telecom applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02712v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinquan Wang, Fenghao Zhu, Chongwen Huang, Zhaohui Yang, Zhaoyang Zhang, Sami Muhaidat, Chau Yuen, M\'erouane Debbah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved universal approximation with neural networks studied via affine-invariant subspaces of $L_2(\mathbb{R}^n)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02445v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that there are no non-trivial closed subspaces of $L_2(\mathbb{R}^n)$ that are invariant under invertible affine transformations. We apply this result to neural networks showing that any nonzero $L_2(\mathbb{R})$ function is an adequate activation function in a one hidden layer neural network in order to approximate every function in $L_2(\mathbb{R})$ with any desired accuracy. This generalizes the universal approximation properties of neural networks in $L_2(\mathbb{R})$ related to Wiener's Tauberian Theorems. Our results extend to the spaces $L_p(\mathbb{R})$ with $p&gt;1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02445v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cornelia Schneider, Samuel Probst</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VISTA: Unsupervised 2D Temporal Dependency Representations for Time Series Anomaly Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02498v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Time Series Anomaly Detection (TSAD) is essential for uncovering rare and potentially harmful events in unlabeled time series data. Existing methods are highly dependent on clean, high-quality inputs, making them susceptible to noise and real-world imperfections. Additionally, intricate temporal relationships in time series data are often inadequately captured in traditional 1D representations, leading to suboptimal modeling of dependencies. We introduce VISTA, a training-free, unsupervised TSAD algorithm designed to overcome these challenges. VISTA features three core modules: 1) Time Series Decomposition using Seasonal and Trend Decomposition via Loess (STL) to decompose noisy time series into trend, seasonal, and residual components; 2) Temporal Self-Attention, which transforms 1D time series into 2D temporal correlation matrices for richer dependency modeling and anomaly detection; and 3) Multivariate Temporal Aggregation, which uses a pretrained feature extractor to integrate cross-variable information into a unified, memory-efficient representation. VISTA's training-free approach enables rapid deployment and easy hyperparameter tuning, making it suitable for industrial applications. It achieves state-of-the-art performance on five multivariate TSAD benchmarks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02498v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sinchee Chin, Fan Zhang, Xiaochen Yang, Jing-Hao Xue, Wenming Yang, Peng Jia, Guijin Wang, Luo Yingqun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Average Distance, Level-1 Fourier Weight, and Chang's Lemma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02593v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we improve the well-known level-1 weight bound, also known as Chang's lemma, by using an induction method. Our bounds are close to optimal no matter when the set is large or small. Our bounds can be seen as bounds on the minimum average distance problem, since maximizing the level-1 weight is equivalent to minimizing the average distance. We apply our new bounds to improve the Friedgut--Kalai--Naor theorem. We also derive the sharp version for Chang's original lemma for $\mathbb{F}_{2}^{n}$. That is, we show that in $\mathbb{F}_{2}^{n}$, Hamming balls maximize the dimension of the space spanned by large Fourier coefficients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02593v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bacon-Shor Board Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02749v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We identify a period-4 measurement schedule for the checks of the Bacon-Shor code that fully covers spacetime with constant-weight detectors, and is numerically observed to provide the code with a threshold. Unlike previous approaches, our method does not rely on code concatenation and instead arises as the solution to a coloring game on a square grid. Under a uniform circuit-level noise model, we observe a threshold of approximately $0.3\%$ when decoding with minimum weight perfect matching, and we conjecture that this could be improved using a more tailored decoder.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02749v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Sohaib Alam, Jiajun Chen, Thomas R. Scruby</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Twist on Low-Complexity Digital Backpropagation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14489v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work proposes a novel low-complexity digital backpropagation (DBP) method, with the goal of optimizing the trade-off between backpropagation accuracy and complexity. The method combines a split step Fourier method (SSFM)-like structure with a simplified logarithmic perturbation method to obtain a high accuracy with a small number of DBP steps. Subband processing and asymmetric steps with optimized splitting ratio are also employed to further reduce the number of steps required to achieve a prescribed performance. The first part of the manuscript is dedicated to the derivation of a simplified logarithmic-perturbation model for the propagation of signal in an optical fiber, which serves for the development of the proposed coupled-band enhanced split step Fourier method (CB-ESSFM) and for the analytical calculation of the model coefficients. Next, the manuscript presents a DSP algorithm for the implementation of DBP based on a discrete-time version of the model and an overlap-and-save processing strategy. Practical approaches for the optimization of the coefficients used in the algorithm and of the splitting ratio of the asymmetric steps are also discussed. A detailed analysis of the computational complexity is presented. Finally, the performance and complexity of the proposed DBP method are investigated through simulations. In a five-channel 100 GHz-spaced wavelength division multiplexing system over a 15x80 km single-mode-fiber link, the proposed CB-ESSFM achieves a gain of about 1dB over simple dispersion compensation with only 15 steps (corresponding to 681 real multiplications per 2D symbol), with an improvement of 0.9 dB over conventional SSFM and almost 0.4dB over our previously proposed ESSFM. Significant gains and improvements are obtained also at lower complexity. A similar analysis is performed also for longer links, confirming the good performance of the proposed method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14489v4</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stella Civelli, Debi Pada Jana, Enrico Forestieri, Marco Secondini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Framework for Uplink ISAC Receiver Designs: Performance Analysis and Algorithm Development</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02647</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02647v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Uplink integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) systems have recently emerged as a promising research direction, enabling simultaneous uplink signal detection and target sensing. In this paper, we propose the flexible projection (FP)-type receiver that unify the projection-type receiver and the successive interference cancellation (SIC)-type receiver by using a flexible tradeoff factor to adapt to dynamically changing uplink ISAC scenarios. The FP-type receiver addresses the joint signal detection and target response estimation problem through two coordinated phases: 1) Communication signal detection using a reconstructed signal whose composition is controlled by the tradeoff factor, followed by 2) Target response estimation performed through subtraction of the detected communication signal from the received signal. With adjustable tradeoff factors, the FP-type receiver can balance the enhancement of the signal-to-interference-plus-noise ratio (SINR) with the reduction of correlation in the reconstructed signal for communication signal detection. The pairwise error probabilities (PEPs) are analyzed for both the maximum likelihood (ML) and the zero-forcing (ZF) detectors, revealing that the optimal tradeoff factor should be determined based on the adopted detection algorithm and the relative power of the sensing and communication (S\&amp;C) signal. A homotopy optimization framework is first applied for the FP-type receiver with a fixed trade-off factor. This framework is then extended to develop the dynamic FP (DFP)-type receiver, which iteratively adjust the trade-off factor for improved algorithm performance and environmental adaptability. Subsequently, two extensions are explored to further enhance the receiver's performance: parallel DFP (PDFP)-type receiver and a block-structured receiver design. Finally, the effectiveness of the proposed receiver designs is verified via simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02647v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyuan Yu, Hong Ren, Cunhua Pan, Gui Zhou, Dongming Wang, Chau Yuen, Jiangzhou Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TinyML NLP Scheme for Semantic Wireless Sentiment Classification with Privacy Preservation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06291v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Natural Language Processing (NLP) operations, such as semantic sentiment analysis and text synthesis, often raise privacy concerns and demand significant on-device computational resources. Centralized Learning (CL) on the edge provides an energy-efficient alternative but requires collecting raw data, compromising user privacy. While Federated Learning (FL) enhances privacy, it imposes high computational energy demands on resource-constrained devices. We introduce Split Learning (SL) as an energy-efficient, privacy-preserving Tiny Machine Learning (TinyML) framework and compare it to FL and CL in the presence of Rayleigh fading and additive noise. Our results show that SL significantly reduces computational power and CO2 emissions while enhancing privacy, as evidenced by a fourfold increase in reconstruction error compared to FL and nearly eighteen times that of CL. In contrast, FL offers a balanced trade-off between privacy and efficiency. This study provides insights into deploying privacy-preserving, energy-efficient NLP models on edge devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06291v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmed Y. Radwan, Mohammad Shehab, Mohamed-Slim Alouini</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
