<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.IT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.IT</link>
    <description>math.IT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.IT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 02:37:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Equivalence of Informations Characterizes Bregman Divergences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02104v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bregman divergences are a class of distance-like comparison functions which play fundamental roles in optimization, statistics, and information theory. One important property of Bregman divergences is that they cause two useful formulations of information content (in the sense of variability or non-uniformity) in a weighted collection of vectors to agree. In this note, we show that this agreement in fact characterizes the class of Bregman divergences; they are the only divergences which generate this agreement for arbitrary collections of weighted vectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02104v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philip S. Chodrow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fastest mixing reversible Markov chain on friendship graph: Trade-off between transition probabilities among friends and convergence rate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02117v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A long-standing goal of social network research has been to alter the properties of network to achieve the desired outcome. In doing so, DeGroot's consensus model has served as the popular choice for modeling the information diffusion and opinion formation in social networks. Achieving a trade-off between the cost associated with modifications made to the network and the speed of convergence to the desired state has shown to be a critical factor. This has been treated as the Fastest Mixing Markov Chain (FMMC) problem over a graph with given transition probabilities over a subset of edges. Addressing this multi-objective optimization problem over the friendship graph, this paper has provided the corresponding Pareto optimal points or the Pareto frontier. In the case of friendship graph with at least three blades, it is shown that the Pareto frontier is reduced to a global minimum point which is same as the optimal point corresponding to the minimum spanning tree of the friendship graph, i.e., the star topology. Furthermore, a lower limit for transition probabilities among friends has been provided, where values higher than this limit do not have any impact on the convergence rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02117v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.sysconle.2019.07.001</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Systems &amp; Control Letters 130 (2019) 13-22</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Saber Jafarizadeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Securing Integrated Sensing and Communication Against a Mobile Adversary: A Stackelberg Game with Deep Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02271v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study a secure integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) system employing a full-duplex base station with sensing capabilities against a mobile proactive adversarial target$\unicode{x2014}$a malicious unmanned aerial vehicle (M-UAV). We develop a game-theoretic model to enhance communication security, radar sensing accuracy, and power efficiency. The interaction between the legitimate network and the mobile adversary is formulated as a non-cooperative Stackelberg game (NSG), where the M-UAV acts as the leader and strategically adjusts its trajectory to improve its eavesdropping ability while conserving power and avoiding obstacles. In response, the legitimate network, acting as the follower, dynamically allocates resources to minimize network power usage while ensuring required secrecy rates and sensing performance. To address this challenging problem, we propose a low-complexity successive convex approximation (SCA) method for network resource optimization combined with a deep reinforcement learning (DRL) algorithm for adaptive M-UAV trajectory planning through sequential interactions and learning. Simulation results demonstrate the efficacy of the proposed method in addressing security challenges of dynamic ISAC systems in 6G, i.e., achieving a Stackelberg equilibrium with robust performance while mitigating the adversary's ability to intercept network signals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02271v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Milad Tatar Mamaghani, Xiangyun Zhou, Nan Yang, A. Lee Swindlehurst</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Connecting the Unconnectable through Feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02335v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Reliable uplink connectivity remains a persistent challenge for IoT devices, particularly those at the cell edge, due to their limited transmit power and single-antenna configurations. This paper introduces a novel framework aimed at connecting the unconnectable, leveraging real-time feedback from access points (APs) to enhance uplink coverage without increasing the energy consumption of IoT devices. At the core of this approach are feedback channel codes, which enable IoT devices to dynamically adapt their transmission strategies based on AP decoding feedback, thereby reducing the critical uplink SNR required for successful communication. Analytical models are developed to quantify the coverage probability and the number of connectable APs, providing a comprehensive understanding of the system's performance. Numerical results validate the proposed method, demonstrating substantial improvements in coverage range and connectivity, particularly for devices at the cell edge, with up to a 51% boost in connectable APs. Our approach offers a robust and energy-efficient solution to overcoming uplink coverage limitations, enabling IoT networks to connect devices in challenging environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02335v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yimeng Li, Yulin Shao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fastest Mixing Reversible Markov Chain: Clique Lifted Graphs and Subgraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02421v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Markov chains are one of the well-known tools for modeling and analyzing stochastic systems. At the same time, they are used for constructing random walks that can achieve a given stationary distribution. This paper is concerned with determining the transition probabilities that optimize the mixing time of the reversible Markov chains towards a given equilibrium distribution. This problem is referred to as the Fastest Mixing Reversible Markov Chain (FMRMC) problem. It is shown that for a given base graph and its clique lifted graph, the FMRMC problem over the clique lifted graph is reducible to the FMRMC problem over the base graph, while the optimal mixing times on both graphs are identical. Based on this result and the solution of the semidefinite programming formulation of the FMRMC problem, the problem has been addressed over a wide variety of topologies with the same base graph. Second, the general form of the FMRMC problem is addressed on stand-alone topologies as well as subgraphs of an arbitrary graph. For subgraphs, it is shown that the optimal transition probabilities over edges of the subgraph can be determined independent of rest of the topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02421v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TSIPN.2020.2964211</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Transactions on Signal and Information Processing over Networks 6 (2020): 88-104</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Saber Jafarizadeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blockage-Aware UAV-Assisted Wireless Data Harvesting With Building Avoidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02453v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs) offer dynamic trajectory control, enabling them to avoid obstacles and establish line-of-sight (LoS) wireless channels with ground nodes (GNs), unlike traditional ground-fixed base stations. This study addresses the joint optimization of scheduling and three-dimensional (3D) trajectory planning for UAV-assisted wireless data harvesting. The objective is to maximize the minimum uplink throughput among GNs while accounting for signal blockages and building avoidance. To achieve this, we first present mathematical models designed to avoid cuboid-shaped buildings and to determine wireless signal blockage by buildings through rigorous mathematical proof. The optimization problem is formulated as nonconvex mixed-integer nonlinear programming and solved using advanced techniques. Specifically, the problem is decomposed into convex subproblems via quadratic transform and successive convex approximation. Building avoidance and signal blockage constraints are incorporated using the separating hyperplane method and an approximated indicator function. These subproblems are then iteratively solved using the block coordinate descent algorithm. Simulation results validate the effectiveness of the proposed approach. The UAV dynamically adjusts its trajectory and scheduling policy to maintain LoS channels with GNs, significantly enhancing network throughput compared to existing schemes. Moreover, the trajectory of the UAV adheres to building avoidance constraints for its continuous trajectory, ensuring uninterrupted operation and compliance with safety requirements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02453v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gitae Park, Kanghyun Heo, Kisong Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rotatable Antenna Enabled Wireless Communication: Modeling and Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02595</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02595v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fluid antenna system (FAS) and movable antenna (MA) have recently emerged as promising technologies to exploit new spatial degrees of freedom (DoFs), which have attracted growing attention in wireless communication. In this paper, we propose a new rotatable antenna (RA) model to improve the performance of wireless communication systems. Different from conventional fixed antennas, the proposed RA system can flexibly alter the three-dimensional (3D) boresight direction of each antenna independently by adjusting its deflection angles to achieve a desired array directional gain pattern. Specifically, we investigate an RA-enabled uplink communication system, where the receive beamforming and the deflection angles of all RAs at the base station (BS) are jointly optimized to maximize the minimum signal-to-interference-plus-noise ratio (SINR) among all the users. In the special single-user and free-space propagation setup, the optimal deflection angles of RAs are derived in closed form with the maximum-ratio combining (MRC) beamformer applied at the BS. Moreover, we analyze the asymptotic performance with an infinite number of antennas based on this solution, which theoretically proves that the RA system can achieve a higher array gain as compared to the fixed-antenna system. In the general multi-user and multi-path channel setup, we first propose an alternating optimization (AO) algorithm to alternately optimize the receive beamforming and the deflection angles of RAs in an iterative manner. Then, a two-stage algorithm that solves the formulated problem without the need for iteration is further proposed to reduce computational complexity. Simulation results are provided to validate our analytical results and demonstrate that the proposed RA system can significantly outperform other benchmark schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02595v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beixiong Zheng, Qingjie Wu, Rui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Independence Assumption in Quasi-Cyclic Code-Based Cryptography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02626v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cryptography based on the presumed hardness of decoding codes -- i.e., code-based cryptography -- has recently seen increased interest due to its plausible security against quantum attackers. Notably, of the four proposals for the NIST post-quantum standardization process that were advanced to their fourth round for further review, two were code-based. The most efficient proposals -- including HQC and BIKE, the NIST submissions alluded to above -- in fact rely on the presumed hardness of decoding structured codes. Of particular relevance to our work, HQC is based on quasi-cyclic codes, which are codes generated by matrices consisting of two cyclic blocks.
  In particular, the security analysis of HQC requires a precise understanding of the Decryption Failure Rate (DFR), whose analysis relies on the following heuristic: given random ``sparse'' vectors $e_1,e_2$ (say, each coordinate is i.i.d. Bernoulli) multiplied by fixed ``sparse'' quasi-cyclic matrices $A_1,A_2$, the weight of resulting vector $e_1A_1+e_2A_2$ is very concentrated around its expectation. In the documentation, the authors model the distribution of $e_1A_1+e_2A_2$ as a vector with independent coordinates (and correct marginal distribution). However, we uncover cases where this modeling fails. While this does not invalidate the (empirically verified) heuristic that the weight of $e_1A_1+e_2A_2$ is concentrated, it does suggest that the behavior of the noise is a bit more subtle than previously predicted. Lastly, we also discuss implications of our result for potential worst-case to average-case reductions for quasi-cyclic codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02626v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxime Bombar, Nicolas Resch, Emiel Wiedijk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SCSC: A Novel Standards-Compatible Semantic Communication Framework for Image Transmission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02738v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Joint source-channel coding (JSCC) is a promising paradigm for next-generation communication systems, particularly in challenging transmission environments. In this paper, we propose a novel standard-compatible JSCC framework for the transmission of images over multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) channels. Different from the existing end-to-end AI-based DeepJSCC schemes, our framework consists of learnable modules that enable communication using conventional separate source and channel codes (SSCC), which makes it amenable for easy deployment on legacy systems. Specifically, the learnable modules involve a preprocessing-empowered network (PPEN) for preserving essential semantic information, and a precoder \&amp; combiner-enhanced network (PCEN) for efficient transmission over a resource-constrained MIMO channel. We treat existing compression and channel coding modules as non-trainable blocks. Since the parameters of these modules are non-differentiable, we employ a proxy network that mimics their operations when training the learnable modules. Numerical results demonstrate that our scheme can save more than 29\% of the channel bandwidth, and requires lower complexity compared to the constrained baselines. We also show its generalization capability to unseen datasets and tasks through extensive experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02738v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xue Han, Yongpeng Wu, Zhen Gao, Biqian Feng, Yuxuan Shi, Deniz G\"und\"uz, Wenjun Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectrum Sharing in 6G Space-Ground Integrated Networks: A Ground Protection Zone-Based Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02870v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Space-ground integrated network (SGIN) has been envisioned as a competitive solution for large scale and wide coverage of future wireless networks. By integrating both the non-terrestrial network (NTN) and the terrestrial network (TN), SGIN can provide high speed and omnipresent wireless network access for the users using the predefined licensed spectrums. Considering the scarcity of the spectrum resource and the low spectrum efficiency of the SGIN, we enable the NTN and TN to share the spectrum to improve overall system performance, i.e., weighted-sum area data rate (WS-ADR). However, mutual interference between NTN and TN is often inevitable and thus causes SGIN performance degradation. In this work, we consider a ground protection zone for the TN base stations, in which the NTN users are only allowed to use the NTN reserved spectrum to mitigate the NTN and TN mutual interference. We analytically derive the coverage probability and area data rate (ADR) of the typical users and study the performance under various protection zone sizes and spectrum allocation parameter settings. Simulation and numerical results demonstrate that the WS-ADR could be maximized by selecting the appropriate radius of protection zone and bandwidth allocation factor in the SGIN.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02870v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bodong Shang, Xiangyu Li, Zheng Wang, Junchao Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Achievable Rates Over Noisy Nanopore Channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02917v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider a recent channel model of a nanopore sequencer proposed by McBain, Viterbo, and Saunderson (2024), termed the noisy nanopore channel (NNC). In essence, an NNC is a noisy duplication channel, whose input source has a specific Markov structure. We present bounds on the channel capacity of selected NNCs, via simple information-theoretic inequalities. In particular, we provide a (tight) lower bound on the capacity of the noiseless NCC and demonstrate that for an NNC with erasure noise, the capacity approaches $1$ for nanopore memories that scale roughly logarithmically in the length of the input sequence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02917v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Arvind Rameshwar, Nir Weinberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification of LCD and self-dual codes over a finite non-unital local ring</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03016v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work explores LCD and self-dual codes over a noncommutative non-unital ring $ E_p= \langle r,s ~|~ pr =ps=0,~ r^2=r,~ s^2=s,~ rs=r,~ sr=s \rangle$ of order $p^2$ where $p$ is a prime. Initially, we study the monomial equivalence of two free $E_p$-linear codes. In addition, a necessary and sufficient condition is derived for a free $E_p$-linear code to be MDS and almost MDS (AMDS). Then, we use these results to classify MDS and AMDS LCD codes over $E_2$ and $E_3$ under monomial equivalence for lengths up to $6$. Subsequently, we study left self-dual codes over the ring $E_p$ and classify MDS and AMDS left self-dual codes over $E_2$ and $E_3$ for lengths up to $12$. Finally, we study self-dual codes over the ring $E_p$ and classify MDS and AMDS self-dual codes over $E_2$ and $E_3$ for smaller lengths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03016v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anup Kushwaha, Indibar Debnath, Om Prakash</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical learning does not always entail knowledge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01963v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study learning and knowledge acquisition (LKA) of an agent about a proposition that is either true or false. We use a Bayesian approach, where the agent receives data to update his beliefs about the proposition according to a posterior distribution. The LKA is formulated in terms of active information, with data representing external or exogenous information that modifies the agent's beliefs. It is assumed that data provide details about a number of features that are relevant to the proposition. We show that this leads to a Gibbs distribution posterior, which is in maximum entropy relative to the prior, conditioned on the side constraints that the data provide in terms of the features. We demonstrate that full learning is sometimes not possible and full knowledge acquisition is never possible when the number of extracted features is too small. We also distinguish between primary learning (receiving data about features of relevance for the proposition) and secondary learning (receiving data about the learning of another agent). We argue that this type of secondary learning does not represent true knowledge acquisition. Our results have implications for statistical learning algorithms, and we claim that such algorithms do not always generate true knowledge. The theory is illustrated with several examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01963v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Andr\'es D\'iaz-Pach\'on, H. Renata Gallegos, Ola H\"ossjer, J. Sunil Rao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General Information Metrics for Improving AI Model Training Efficiency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02004</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02004v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: To address the growing size of AI model training data and the lack of a universal data selection methodology-factors that significantly drive up training costs -- this paper presents the General Information Metrics Evaluation (GIME) method. GIME leverages general information metrics from Objective Information Theory (OIT), including volume, delay, scope, granularity, variety, duration, sampling rate, aggregation, coverage, distortion, and mismatch to optimize dataset selection for training purposes. Comprehensive experiments conducted across diverse domains, such as CTR Prediction, Civil Case Prediction, and Weather Forecasting, demonstrate that GIME effectively preserves model performance while substantially reducing both training time and costs. Additionally, applying GIME within the Judicial AI Program led to a remarkable 39.56% reduction in total model training expenses, underscoring its potential to support efficient and sustainable AI development.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02004v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianfeng Xu, Congcong Liu, Xiaoying Tan, Xiaojie Zhu, Anpeng Wu, Huan Wan, Weijun Kong, Chun Li, Hu Xu, Kun Kuang, Fei Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion Model-Based Data Synthesis Aided Federated Semi-Supervised Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02219</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02219v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Federated semi-supervised learning (FSSL) is primarily challenged by two factors: the scarcity of labeled data across clients and the non-independent and identically distribution (non-IID) nature of data among clients. In this paper, we propose a novel approach, diffusion model-based data synthesis aided FSSL (DDSA-FSSL), which utilizes a diffusion model (DM) to generate synthetic data, bridging the gap between heterogeneous local data distributions and the global data distribution. In DDSA-FSSL, clients address the challenge of the scarcity of labeled data by employing a federated learning-trained classifier to perform pseudo labeling for unlabeled data. The DM is then collaboratively trained using both labeled and precision-optimized pseudo-labeled data, enabling clients to generate synthetic samples for classes that are absent in their labeled datasets. This process allows clients to generate more comprehensive synthetic datasets aligned with the global distribution. Extensive experiments conducted on multiple datasets and varying non-IID distributions demonstrate the effectiveness of DDSA-FSSL, e.g., it improves accuracy from 38.46% to 52.14% on CIFAR-10 datasets with 10% labeled data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02219v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhongwei Wang, Tong Wu, Zhiyong Chen, Liang Qian, Yin Xu, Meixia Tao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital Deep Joint Source-Channel Coding with Blind Training for Adaptive Modulation and Power Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02273v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper proposes a novel digital deep joint source-channel coding (DeepJSCC) framework that achieves robust performance across diverse communication environments without requiring extensive retraining and prior knowledge of communication environments. Traditional digital DeepJSCC techniques often face challenges in adapting to various communication environments, as they require significant training overhead and large amounts of communication data to develop either multiple specialized models or a single generalized model, in pre-defined communication environments. To address this challenge, in our framework, an error-adaptive blind training strategy is devised, which eliminates the need for prior knowledge of communication environments. This is achieved by modeling the relationship between the encoder's output and the decoder's input using binary symmetric channels, and optimizing bit-flip probabilities by treating them as trainable parameters. In our framework, a training-aware communication strategy is also presented, which dynamically selects the optimal encoder-decoder pair and transmission parameters based on current channel conditions. In particular, in this strategy, an adaptive power and modulation control method is developed to minimize the total transmission power, while maintaining high task performance. Simulation results demonstrate that our framework outperforms existing DeepJSCC methods, achieving higher peak signal-to-noise ratio, lower power consumption, and requiring significantly fewer encoder-decoder pairs for adaptation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02273v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongjeong Oh, Joohyuk Park, Jinho Choi, Jihong Park, Yo-Seb Jeon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The parenthood effect in urban mobility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02299</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02299v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The modelling of human mobility is vital for the understanding of the complexity of urban dynamics and guiding effective interventions to improve quality of life. Traditional modelling approaches focus on `average citizens,' which overlook the multitude of experiences from distinct sociodemographic groups. Recent studies have unveiled significant variations in mobility patterns related to gender and socioeconomic status, yet the impact of parenthood remains under-explored. Parenthood brings profound changes to daily routines, influenced by factors such as increased caregiving responsibilities, altered work-life balance, and the need for family-friendly environments. Parents often prioritise considerations such as cost of living, social wellbeing, environmental quality, and safety. Quantifying how `friendly' a city is becomes more and more important for parents, especially in the context of rising remote work opportunities which, in turn, reverberate on the choices on where to settle. This work investigates whether these considerations lead to distinct mobility patterns between parents and non-parents, also accounting for the impact of partnership. Using extensive census data across American cities, we analyse how parenthood and partnership reshape their urban experiences. Our findings indicate that cities can indeed be classified by their level of friendliness towards parents and partners. For example, Dallas and Nashville can be more suited for single individuals, New York and Chicago can be more accommodating to parents, while Washington and Baltimore favour married people. These insights contribute to the growing body of research advocating for more nuanced and equitable urban planning. By recognising the diverse needs of different demographic groups, particularly parents, our study underscores the importance of tailored urban design strategies over universal solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02299v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mariana Macedo, Ronaldo Menezes, Alessio Cardillo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revelio: A Real-World Screen-Camera Communication System with Visually Imperceptible Data Embedding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02349v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present `Revelio', a real-world screen-camera communication system leveraging temporal flicker fusion in the OKLAB color space. Using spatially-adaptive flickering and encoding information in pixel region shapes, Revelio achieves visually imperceptible data embedding while remaining robust against noise, asynchronicity, and distortions in screen-camera channels, ensuring reliable decoding by standard smartphone cameras. The decoder, driven by a two-stage neural network, uses a weighted differential accumulator for precise frame detection and symbol recognition. Initial experiments demonstrate Revelio's effectiveness in interactive television, offering an unobtrusive method for meta-information transmission.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02349v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abbaas Alif Mohamed Nishar, Shrinivas Kudekar, Bernard Kintzing, Ashwin Ashok</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Who Wrote This? Zero-Shot Statistical Tests for LLM-Generated Text Detection using Finite Sample Concentration Inequalities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02406v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Verifying the provenance of content is crucial to the function of many organizations, e.g., educational institutions, social media platforms, firms, etc. This problem is becoming increasingly difficult as text generated by Large Language Models (LLMs) becomes almost indistinguishable from human-generated content. In addition, many institutions utilize in-house LLMs and want to ensure that external, non-sanctioned LLMs do not produce content within the institution. In this paper, we answer the following question: Given a piece of text, can we identify whether it was produced by LLM $A$ or $B$ (where $B$ can be a human)? We model LLM-generated text as a sequential stochastic process with complete dependence on history and design zero-shot statistical tests to distinguish between (i) the text generated by two different sets of LLMs $A$ (in-house) and $B$ (non-sanctioned) and also (ii) LLM-generated and human-generated texts. We prove that the type I and type II errors for our tests decrease exponentially in the text length. In designing our tests, we derive concentration inequalities on the difference between log-perplexity and the average entropy of the string under $A$. Specifically, for a given string, we demonstrate that if the string is generated by $A$, the log-perplexity of the string under $A$ converges to the average entropy of the string under $A$, except with an exponentially small probability in string length. We also show that if $B$ generates the text, except with an exponentially small probability in string length, the log-perplexity of the string under $A$ converges to the average cross-entropy of $B$ and $A$. Lastly, we present preliminary experimental results to support our theoretical results. By enabling guaranteed (with high probability) finding of the origin of harmful LLM-generated text with arbitrary size, we can help fight misinformation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02406v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tara Radvand, Mojtaba Abdolmaleki, Mohamed Mostagir, Ambuj Tewari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial Network Calculus: Toward Deterministic Wireless Networking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02556v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper extends the classical network calculus to spatial scenarios, focusing on wireless networks with heterogeneous traffic and varying transmit power levels. Building on spatial network calculus, a prior extension of network calculus to spatial settings, we propose a generalized framework by introducing spatial regulations for stationary marked point processes. The regulations correspond to two key constraints: the total transmit power within a spatial region and the cumulative received power at a receiver. Then we prove the equivalence of ball regulation and shot-noise regulation for stationary marked point processes and establish a universal lower bound on the performance of all network links under these constraints. This framework is applicable to diverse network scenarios, as demonstrated by the analysis of performance guarantees for networks with multi-class users. In addition, we propose an SINR-based power control scheme adapted to user traffic, which ensures differentiated quality of service (QoS) for different user classes. We derive deterministic performance guarantees for all links in complex and heterogeneous wireless networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02556v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi Zhong, Xiaohang Zhou, Ke Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collision-resistant hash-shuffles on the reals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02604</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02604v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Oneway real functions are effective maps on positive-measure sets of reals that preserve randomness and have no effective probabilistic inversions. We construct a oneway real function which is collision-resistant: the probability of effectively producing distinct reals with the same image is zero, and each real has uncountable inverse image.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02604v1</guid>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George Barmpalias, Xiaoyan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parsings of Stationary Processes, Stopping Times and the Fundamental Pointwise Convergence Theorems of Ergodic Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02615v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The idea of a parsing of a stationary process according to a collection of words is introduced, and the basic framework required for the asymptotic analysis of these parsings is presented. We demonstrate how the pointwise ergodic theorem and the Shannon-McMillan-Breiman theorem can be deduced from their respective weaker convergence in probability versions combined with our observations regarding parsings, where the parsings are done according to collections that originate in stopping times tailored for that purpose.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02615v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matan Tal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectrum Sharing in Satellite-Terrestrial Integrated Networks: Frameworks, Approaches, and Opportunities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02750</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02750v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: To accommodate the increasing communication needs in non-terrestrial networks (NTNs), wireless users in remote areas may require access to more spectrum than is currently allocated. Terrestrial networks (TNs), such as cellular networks, are deployed in specific areas, but many underused licensed spectrum bands remain in remote areas. Therefore, bringing NTNs to a shared spectrum with TNs can improve network capacity under reasonable interference management. However, in satellite-terrestrial integrated networks (STINs), the comprehensive coverage of a satellite and the unbalanced communication resources of STINs make it challenging to effectively manage mutual interference between NTN and TN. This article presents the fundamentals and prospects of spectrum sharing (SS) in STINs by introducing four SS frameworks, their potential application scenarios, and technical challenges. Furthermore, advanced SS approaches related to interference management in STINs and performance metrics of SS in STINs are introduced. Moreover, a preliminary performance evaluation showcases the potential for sharing the spectrum between NTN and TN. Finally, future research opportunities for SS in STINs are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02750v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bodong Shang, Zheng Wang, Xiangyu Li, Chungang Yang, Chao Ren, Haijun Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital Twin Aided Channel Estimation: Zone-Specific Subspace Prediction and Calibration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02758</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02758v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Effective channel estimation in sparse and high-dimensional environments is essential for next-generation wireless systems, particularly in large-scale MIMO deployments. This paper introduces a novel framework that leverages digital twins (DTs) as priors to enable efficient zone-specific subspace-based channel estimation (CE). Subspace-based CE significantly reduces feedback overhead by focusing on the dominant channel components, exploiting sparsity in the angular domain while preserving estimation accuracy. While DT channels may exhibit inaccuracies, their coarse-grained subspaces provide a powerful starting point, reducing the search space and accelerating convergence. The framework employs a two-step clustering process on the Grassmann manifold, combined with reinforcement learning (RL), to iteratively calibrate subspaces and align them with real-world counterparts. Simulations show that digital twins not only enable near-optimal performance but also enhance the accuracy of subspace calibration through RL, highlighting their potential as a step towards learnable digital twins.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02758v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sadjad Alikhani, Ahmed Alkhateeb</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rydberg Atomic Quantum Receivers for Multi-Target DOA Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02820v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum sensing technologies have experienced rapid progresses since entering the `second quantum revolution'. Among various candidates, schemes relying on Rydberg atoms exhibit compelling advantages for detecting radio frequency signals. Based on this, Rydberg atomic quantum receivers (RAQRs) have emerged as a promising solution to classical wireless communication and sensing. To harness the advantages and exploit the potential of RAQRs in wireless sensing, we investigate the realization of the direction of arrival (DOA) estimation by RAQRs. Specifically, we first conceive a Rydberg atomic quantum uniform linear array (RAQ-ULA) aided receiver for multi-target detection and propose the corresponding signal model of this sensing system. Furthermore, we propose the Rydberg atomic quantum estimation of signal parameters by designing a rotational invariance based technique termed as RAQ-ESPRIT relying on our model. The proposed algorithm solves the sensor gain mismatch problem, which is due to the presence of the RF local oscillator in the RAQ-ULA and cannot be well addressed by using the conventional ESPRIT. Lastly, we characterize our scheme through numerical simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02820v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tierui Gong, Chau Yuen, Chong Meng Samson See, M\'erouane Debbah, Lajos Hanzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact Matching in Correlated Networks with Node Attributes for Improved Community Recovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02851v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study community detection in multiple networks whose nodes and edges are jointly correlated. This setting arises naturally in applications such as social platforms, where a shared set of users may exhibit both correlated friendship patterns and correlated attributes across different platforms. Extending the classical Stochastic Block Model (SBM) and its contextual counterpart (CSBM), we introduce the correlated CSBM, which incorporates structural and attribute correlations across graphs. To build intuition, we first analyze correlated Gaussian Mixture Models, wherein only correlated node attributes are available without edges, and identify the conditions under which an estimator minimizing the distance between attributes achieves exact matching of nodes across the two databases. For correlated CSBMs, we develop a two-step procedure that first applies $k$-core matching to most nodes using edge information, then refines the matching for the remaining unmatched nodes by leveraging their attributes with a distance-based estimator. We identify the conditions under which the algorithm recovers the exact node correspondence, enabling us to merge the correlated edges and average the correlated attributes for enhanced community detection. Crucially, by aligning and combining graphs, we identify regimes in which community detection is impossible in a single graph but becomes feasible when side information from correlated graphs is incorporated. Our results illustrate how the interplay between graph matching and community recovery can boost performance, broadening the scope of multi-graph, attribute-based community detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02851v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joonhyuk Yang, Hye Won Chung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Counting H-Intersecting Families and Graph Homomorphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02894v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work leverages Shearer's inequalities to derive a new upper bound on the maximum cardinality of a family of graphs on a fixed number of vertices, in which every pair of graphs shares a fixed common subgraph. The derived bound is expressed in terms of the chromatic number of the shared subgraph. Additionally, Shearer's inequalities, in conjunction with properties of the Shannon entropy, are employed to establish bounds related to the enumeration of graph homomorphisms, providing further insights into the interplay between combinatorial structures and information-theoretic principles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02894v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igal Sason</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing the Accuracy-Communication-Privacy Trade-off in Distributed Stochastic Convex Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03222v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the problem of differentially private stochastic convex optimization (DP-SCO) in a distributed setting with $M$ clients, where each of them has a local dataset of $N$ i.i.d. data samples from an underlying data distribution. The objective is to design an algorithm to minimize a convex population loss using a collaborative effort across $M$ clients, while ensuring the privacy of the local datasets. In this work, we investigate the accuracy-communication-privacy trade-off for this problem. We establish matching converse and achievability results using a novel lower bound and a new algorithm for distributed DP-SCO based on Vaidya's plane cutting method. Thus, our results provide a complete characterization of the accuracy-communication-privacy trade-off for DP-SCO in the distributed setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03222v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sudeep Salgia, Nikola Pavlovic, Yuejie Chi, Qing Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Should Selfish Miners Double-Spend?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03227</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03227v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Although, both double-spending and selfish-mining attacks have been extensively studied since the ``Bitcoin'' whitepaper of Nakamoto and the ``majority is not enough'' paper of Eyal and Sirer, there has been no rigorous stochastic analysis of an attack that combines the two, except for the complicated MDP models. In this paper, we first combine stubborn and selfish mining attacks, i.e., construct a strategy where the attacker acts stubborn until its private branch reaches a certain length and then switches to act selfish. We provide the optimal stubbornness for each parameter regime. Next, we provide the maximum stubbornness that is still more profitable than honest mining and argue a connection between the level of stubbornness and the $k$-confirmation rule. We show that, at each attack cycle, if the level of stubbornness is higher than $k$, there is a risk of double-spending which comes at no-cost to the adversary. The result can be seen as a guide for picking $k$ in the $k$-confirmation rule in a blockchain design. At each cycle, for a given stubbornness level, we rigorously formulate how great the risk of double-spending is. We provide the minimum double-spend value needed for an attack to be profitable in the regimes where the scheme is less profitable than honest mining. We further modify the attack in the stubborn regime in order to conceal the attack and increase the double-spending probability. Finally, we evaluate the results and provide the optimal and the maximum stubbornness levels for each parameter regime as well as the revenue. As a case study, with Bitcoin's $k=6$ block confirmation rule, we evaluate the revenue and double-spending risk of the attacks for each pool parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03227v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mustafa Doger, Sennur Ulukus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skew Generalized Polycyclic Codes with Derivations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.06086</link>
      <description>arXiv:1907.06086v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we first consider the iterated skew polynomial ring $\mathscr{R}[z_1;\tau_1,\delta_{\tau_1}]$\\$[z_2;\tau_2,\delta_{\tau_2}]$, where $\mathscr{R}$ is a finite ring with unity. Then we use this structure for the construction of skew generalized polycyclic codes over the ring $\mathscr{R}$ and finite field $\mathbb{F}_q$, where $q=p^m$ for some positive integer $m$. Further, we derive the structure of the generator and parity check matrices for skew generalized polycyclic codes. Furthermore, we improve the Bose-Chaudhuri-Hocquenghem (BCH) lower bound for a minimum distance of skew generalized polycyclic codes with non-zero derivations over a finite field. Moreover, we find a sufficient condition for a code to be a maximum-distance-separable (MDS) code. In addition, we provide examples of MDS codes to show the importance of our results. A comparative summary of our work with other linear codes is also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1907.06086v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shikha Patel, Om Prakash</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sequences with identical autocorrelation functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.07467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.07467v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Aperiodic autocorrelation is an important indicator of performance of sequences used in communications, remote sensing, and scientific instrumentation. Knowing a sequence's autocorrelation function, which reports the autocorrelation at every possible translation, is equivalent to knowing the magnitude of the sequence's Fourier transform. The phase problem is the difficulty in resolving this lack of phase information. We say that two sequences are equicorrelational to mean that they have the same aperiodic autocorrelation function. Sequences used in technological applications often have restrictions on their terms: they are not arbitrary complex numbers, but come from a more restricted alphabet. For example, binary sequences involve terms equal to only $+1$ and $-1$. We investigate the necessary and sufficient conditions for two sequences to be equicorrelational, where we take their alphabet into consideration. There are trivial forms of equicorrelationality arising from modifications that predictably preserve the autocorrelation, for example, negating a binary sequence or reversing the order of its terms. By a search of binary sequences up to length $44$, we find that nontrivial equicorrelationality among binary sequences does occur, but is rare. An integer $n$ is said to be equivocal when there are binary sequences of length $n$ that are nontrivially equicorrelational; otherwise $n$ is unequivocal. For $n \leq 44$, we found that the unequivocal lengths are $1$--$8$, $10$, $11$, $13$, $14$, $19$, $22$, $23$, $26$, $29$, $37$, and $38$. We pose open questions about the finitude of unequivocal numbers and the probability of nontrivial equicorrelationality occurring among binary sequences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.07467v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel J. Katz, Adeebur Rahman, Michael J Ward</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meta-Learning for Resource Allocation in Uplink Multi-Active STAR-RIS-aided NOMA System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.07100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.07100v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Simultaneously transmitting and reflecting reconfigurable intelligent surface (STAR-RIS) is a novel technology which enables the full-space coverage. In this letter, a multi-active STAR-RIS-aided system using non-orthogonal multiple access in an uplink transmission is considered, where the second-order reflections among multiple active STAR-RISs assist the transmission from the single-antenna users to the multi-antenna base station. Specifically, the total sum rate maximization problem is solved by jointly optimizing the active beamforming, power allocation, transmission and reflection beamforming at the active STAR-RISs, and user-active STAR-RIS assignment. To solve the non-convex optimization problem, a novel deep reinforcement learning algorithm is proposed which integrates Meta-learning and deep deterministic policy gradient (DDPG), denoted by Meta-DDPG. Numerical results reveal that our proposed Meta-DDPG algorithm outperforms the DDPG algorithm with $19\%$ improvement, while second-order reflections among multi-active STAR-RISs provide $74.1\%$ enhancement in the total data rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.07100v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sepideh Javadi, Armin Farhadi, Mohammad Robat Mili, Eduard Jorswieck, Naofal Al-Dhahir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Unified Study on Sequentiality in Universal Classification with Empirically Observed Statistics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.16213</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.16213v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the binary hypothesis testing problem, it is well known that sequentiality in taking samples eradicates the trade-off between two error exponents, yet implementing the optimal test requires the knowledge of the underlying distributions, say $P_0$ and $P_1$. In the scenario where the knowledge of distributions is replaced by empirically observed statistics from the respective distributions, the gain of sequentiality is less understood when subject to universality constraints over all possible $P_0,P_1$. In this work, the gap is mended by a unified study on sequentiality in the universal binary classification problem, where the universality constraints are set on the expected stopping time as well as the type-I error exponent. The type-I error exponent is required to achieve a pre-set distribution-dependent constraint $\lambda(P_0,P_1)$ for all $P_0,P_1$. Under the proposed framework, different sequential setups are investigated so that fair comparisons can be made with the fixed-length counterpart. By viewing these sequential classification problems as special cases of a general sequential composite hypothesis testing problem, the optimal type-II error exponents are characterized. Specifically, in the general sequential composite hypothesis testing problem subject to universality constraints, upper and lower bounds on the type-II error exponent are proved, and a sufficient condition for which the bounds coincide is given. The results for sequential classification problems are then obtained accordingly. With the characterization of the optimal error exponents, the benefit of sequentiality is shown both analytically and numerically by comparing the sequential and the fixed-length cases in representative examples of type-I exponent constraint $\lambda$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.16213v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ching-Fang Li, I-Hsiang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intent-Aware DRL-Based NOMA Uplink Dynamic Scheduler for IIoT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18364v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the problem of supporting Industrial Internet of Things user equipment (IIoT UEs) with intent (i.e., requested quality of service (QoS)) and random traffic arrival. A deep reinforcement learning (DRL) based centralized dynamic scheduler for time-frequency resources is proposed to learn how to schedule the available communication resources among the IIoT UEs. The proposed scheduler leverages an RL framework to adapt to the dynamic changes in the wireless communication system and traffic arrivals. Moreover, a graph-based reduction scheme is proposed to reduce the state and action space of the RL framework to allow fast convergence and a better learning strategy. Simulation results demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed intelligent scheduler in guaranteeing the expressed intent of IIoT UEs compared to several traditional scheduling schemes, such as round-robin, semi-static, and heuristic approaches. The proposed scheduler also outperforms the contention-free and contention-based schemes in maximizing the number of successfully computed tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18364v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Salwa Mostafa, Mateus P. Mota, Alvaro Valcarce, Mehdi Bennis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supplementary File: Coded Cooperative Networks for Semi-Decentralized Federated Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19002v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: To enhance straggler resilience in federated learning (FL) systems, a semi-decentralized approach has been recently proposed, enabling collaboration between clients. Unlike the existing semi-decentralized schemes, which adaptively adjust the collaboration weight according to the network topology, this letter proposes a deterministic coded network that leverages wireless diversity for semi-decentralized FL without requiring prior information about the entire network. Furthermore, the theoretical analyses of the outage and the convergence rate of the proposed scheme are provided. Finally, the superiority of our proposed method over benchmark methods is demonstrated through comprehensive simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19002v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shudi Weng, Ming Xiao, Chao Ren, Mikael Skoglund</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gumbel-Softmax Discretization Constraint, Differentiable IDS Channel, and an IDS-Correcting Code for DNA Storage</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18929v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Insertion, deletion, and substitution (IDS) error-correcting codes have garnered increased attention with recent advancements in DNA storage technology. However, a universal method for designing IDS-correcting codes across varying channel settings remains underexplored. We present an autoencoder-based method, THEA-code, aimed at efficiently generating IDS-correcting codes for complex IDS channels. In the work, a Gumbel-Softmax discretization constraint is proposed to discretize the features of the autoencoder, and a simulated differentiable IDS channel is developed as a differentiable alternative for IDS operations. These innovations facilitate the successful convergence of the autoencoder, resulting in channel-customized IDS-correcting codes with commendable performance across complex IDS channels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18929v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alan J. X. Guo, Mengyi Wei, Yufan Dai, Yali Wei, Pengchen Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meta-Learning for Hybrid Precoding in Millimeter Wave MIMO System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09427v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The hybrid analog/digital architecture that connects a limited number of RF chains to multiple antennas through phase shifters could effectively address the energy consumption issues in massive multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) systems. However, the main challenges in hybrid precoding lie in the coupling between analog and digital precoders and the constant modulus constraint. Generally, traditional optimization algorithms for this problem typically suffer from high computational complexity or suboptimal performance, while deep learning based solutions exhibit poor scalability and robustness. This paper proposes a plug and play, free of pre-training solution that leverages gradient guided meta learning (GGML) framework to maximize the spectral efficiency of MIMO systems through hybrid precoding. Specifically, GGML utilizes gradient information as network input to facilitate the sharing of gradient information flow. We retain the iterative process of traditional algorithms and leverage meta learning to alternately optimize the precoder. Simulation results show that this method outperforms existing methods, demonstrates robustness to variations in system parameters, and can even exceed the performance of fully digital weighted minimum mean square error (WMMSE) precoding with the same number of antennas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09427v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$(\Theta, \Delta_\Theta, \mathbf{a})$-cyclic codes over $\mathbb{F}_q^l$ and their applications in the construction of quantum codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01708v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article, for a finite field $\mathbb{F}_q$ and a natural number $l,$ let $\mathcal{R}:=\mathbb{F}_q^l.$ Firstly, for an automorphism $\Theta$ of $\mathcal{R},$ a $\Theta$-derivation $\Delta_\Theta$ of $\mathcal{R}$ and $\mathbf{a}\in \mathcal{R}^\times,$ we study $(\Theta, \Delta_\Theta, \mathbf{a})$-cyclic codes over the skew polynomial ring $\mathcal{R}.$ In this direction, we give an algebraic characterization of a $(\Theta, \Delta_\Theta, \mathbf{a})$-cyclic code over $\mathcal{R},$ determine its generator polynomial, and find its decomposition over $\mathbb{F}_q$. Secondly, we give a necessary and sufficient condition for a $(\Theta, 0, \mathbf{a})$-cyclic code to be Euclidean dual-containing over $\mathcal{R}.$ Thirdly, we study Gray maps and obtain several MDS and optimal linear codes over $\mathbb{F}_q$ as Gray images of $(\Theta, \Delta_\Theta, \mathbf{a})$-cyclic codes over $\mathcal{R}.$ Moreover, we determine orthogonality preserving Gray maps and construct Euclidean dual-containing codes with good parameters. Lastly, as an application, we construct MDS and almost MDS quantum codes by employing the Euclidean dual-containing and annihilator dual-containing CSS constructions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01708v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Akanksha, Anuj Kumar Bhagat, Ritumoni Sarma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Propagation of chaos in path spaces via information theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.00339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.00339v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Propagation of chaos for interacting particle systems has been an active research topic over decades. We propose an alternative approach to study the mean-field limit of the stochastic interacting particle systems via tools from information theory. In our framework, the propagation of chaos is reduced to the space for driving processes with possible lower dimension. Indeed, after applying the data processing inequality, one only needs to estimate the difference between the drifts of the particle system and the mean-field Mckean stochastic differential equation. This point is particularly useful in situations where the discrepancy in the driving processes is more apparent than the investigated processes. We will take the second order system as well as other examples for the illustration of how our framework could be used. This approach allows us to focus on probability measures in path spaces for the driving processes, avoiding using the usual hypocoercivity technique or taking the pseudo-inverse of the diffusion matrix, which might be more stable for numerical computation. Our framework is different from current approaches in literature and could provide new insight into the study of interacting particle systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.00339v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Li, Yuelin Wang, Yuliang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random unitaries in extremely low depth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07754v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that random quantum circuits on any geometry, including a 1D line, can form approximate unitary designs over $n$ qubits in $\log n$ depth. In a similar manner, we construct pseudorandom unitaries (PRUs) in 1D circuits in $\text{poly}(\log n)$ depth, and in all-to-all-connected circuits in $\text{poly}(\log \log n)$ depth. In all three cases, the $n$ dependence is optimal and improves exponentially over known results. These shallow quantum circuits have low complexity and create only short-range entanglement, yet are indistinguishable from unitaries with exponential complexity. Our construction glues local random unitaries on $\log n$-sized or $\text{poly}(\log n)$-sized patches of qubits to form a global random unitary on all $n$ qubits. In the case of designs, the local unitaries are drawn from existing constructions of approximate unitary $k$-designs, and hence also inherit an optimal scaling in $k$. In the case of PRUs, the local unitaries are drawn from existing PRU constructions. Applications of our results include proving that classical shadows with 1D log-depth Clifford circuits are as powerful as those with deep circuits, demonstrating superpolynomial quantum advantage in learning low-complexity physical systems, and establishing quantum hardness for recognizing phases of matter with topological order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07754v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Schuster, Jonas Haferkamp, Hsin-Yuan Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Near-Field Signal Processing: Unleashing the Power of Proximity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11434</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11434v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: After nearly a century of specialized applications in optics, remote sensing, and acoustics, the near-field (NF) electromagnetic propagation zone is experiencing a resurgence in research interest. This renewed attention is fueled by the emergence of promising applications in various fields such as wireless communications, holography, medical imaging, and quantum-inspired systems. Signal processing within NF sensing and wireless communications environments entails addressing issues related to extended scatterers, range-dependent beampatterns, spherical wavefronts, mutual coupling effects, and the presence of both reactive and radiative fields. Recent investigations have focused on these aspects in the context of extremely large arrays and wide bandwidths, giving rise to novel challenges in channel estimation, beamforming, beam training, sensing, and localization. While NF optics has a longstanding history, advancements in NF phase retrieval techniques and their applications have lately garnered significant research attention. Similarly, utilizing NF localization with acoustic arrays represents a contemporary extension of established principles in NF acoustic array signal processing. This article aims to provide an overview of state-of-the-art signal processing techniques within the NF domain, offering a comprehensive perspective on recent advances in diverse applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11434v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmet M. Elbir, \"Ozlem Tu\u{g}fe Demir, Kumar Vijay Mishra, Symeon Chatzinotas, Martin Haardt</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
