<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.IT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.IT</link>
    <description>math.IT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.IT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 04:03:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Amortized Locally Decodable Codes for Insertions and Deletions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03141v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Locally Decodable Codes (LDCs) are error correcting codes which permit the recovery of any single message symbol with a low number of queries to the codeword (the locality). Traditional LDC tradeoffs between the rate, locality, and error tolerance are undesirable even in relaxed settings where the encoder/decoder share randomness or where the channel is resource-bounded. Recent work by Blocki and Zhang initiated the study of Hamming amortized Locally Decodable Codes (aLDCs), which allow the local decoder to amortize their number of queries over the recovery of a small subset of message symbols. Surprisingly, Blocki and Zhang construct asymptotically ideal (constant rate, constant amortized locality, and constant error tolerance) Hamming aLDCs in private-key and resource-bounded settings. While this result overcame previous barriers and impossibility results for Hamming LDCs, it is not clear whether the techniques extend to Insdel LDCs. Constructing Insdel LDCs which are resilient to insertion and/or deletion errors is known to be even more challenging.
  Our first contribution is to provide a Hamming-to-Insdel compiler which transforms any amortized Hamming LDC that satisfies a particular property to amortized Insdel LDC while asymptotically preserving the rate, error tolerance and amortized locality. Prior Hamming-to-Insdel compilers worked for arbitrary Hamming LDCs, but incurred an undesirable polylogarithmic blow-up in the locality. Our second contribution is a construction of an ideal amortized Hamming LDC which satisfies our special property in the relaxed settings where the sender/receiver share randomness or where the channel is resource bounded. Taken together, we obtain ideal Insdel aLDCs in private-key and resource-bounded settings with constant amortized locality, constant rate and constant error tolerance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03141v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeremiah Blocki, Justin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Theta Series of a Lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03178</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03178v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mimicking the idea of the generalized Hamming weight of linear codes, we introduce a new lattice invariant, the generalized theta series. Applications range from identifying stable lattices to the lattice isomorphism problem. Moreover, we provide counterexamples for the secrecy gain conjecture on isodual lattices, which claims that the ratio of the theta series of an isodual (and more generally, formally unimodular) lattice by the theta series of the integer lattice $\mathbb{Z}^n$ is minimized at a (unique) symmetry point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03178v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maiara F. Bollauf, Hsuan-Yin Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Function-Correcting Codes with Homogeneous Distance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03332v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Function-correcting codes are designed to reduce redundancy of codes when protecting function values of information against errors. As generalizations of Hamming weights and Lee weights over $ \mathbb{Z}_{4} $, homogeneous weights are used in codes over finite rings. In this paper, we introduce function-correcting codes with homogeneous distance denoted by FCCHDs, which extend function-correcting codes with Hamming distance. We first define $ D $-homogeneous distance codes. We use $ D $-homogenous distance codes to characterize connections between the optimal redundancy of FCCHDs and lengths of these codes for some matrices $ D $. By these connections, we obtain several bounds of the optimal redundancy of FCCHDs for some functions. In addition, we also construct FCCHDs for homogeneous weight functions and homogeneous weight distribution functions. Specially, redundancies of some codes we construct in this paper reach the optimal redundancy bounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03332v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huiying Liu, Hongwei Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Set Shaping Theory and the Foundations of Redundancy-Free Testable Codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03444v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To render a sequence testable, namely capable of identifying and detecting errors, it is necessary to apply a transformation that increases its length by introducing statistical dependence among symbols, as commonly exemplified by the addition of parity bits. However, since the decoder does not have prior knowledge of the original symbols, it must treat the artificially introduced symbols as if they were independent. Consequently, these additional symbols must be transmitted, even though their conditional probability, under ideal and error free conditions, would be zero. This sequence extension implies that not all symbol combinations of the new length are practically realizable: if an error modifies a sequence, making it inadmissible such an error becomes detectable. Recent developments in Set Shaping Theory have revealed a surprising result: it is always possible to transform a sequence into a longer version by carefully selecting which longer sequences are allowed, in such a way that the overall set of sequences becomes more structured and less complex than the original. This means that even though the sequence is extended and dependencies are introduced between symbols, the total amount of information contained in the new set does not increase proportionally on the contrary, it can be slightly reduced. In other words, one can construct a new set of longer sequences where each one corresponds uniquely to an original sequence, but the entire set is designed in such a way that it can be treated as if the symbols were independent, making encoding simpler. This allows sequence to become testable capable of detecting errors without adding visible redundancy or increasing the informational content.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03444v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aida Koch, Alix Petit</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Movable-Antenna-Enhanced Physical-Layer Service Integration: Performance Analysis and Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03449</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03449v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Movable antennas (MAs) have drawn increasing attention in wireless communications due to their capability to create favorable channel conditions via local movement within a confined region. In this letter, we investigate its application in physical-layer service integration (PHY-SI), where a multi-MA base station (BS) simultaneously transmits both confidential and multicast messages to two users. The multicast message is intended for both users, while the confidential message is intended only for one user and must remain perfectly secure from the other. Our goal is to jointly optimize the secrecy and multicast beamforming, as well as the MAs' positions at the BS to maximize the secrecy rate for one user while satisfying the multicast rate requirement for both users. To gain insights, we first conduct performance analysis of this MA-enhanced PHY-SI system in two special cases, revealing its unique characteristics compared to conventional PHY-SI with fixed-position antennas (FPAs). To address the secrecy rate maximization problem, we propose a two-layer optimization framework that integrates the semidefinite relaxation (SDR) technique and a discrete sampling algorithm. Numerical results demonstrate that MAs can greatly enhance the achievable secrecy rate region for PHY-SI compared to FPAs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03449v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuanlin Shen, Xin Wei, Weidong Mei, Zhi Chen, Jun Fang, Boyu Ning</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Variable Node Selection for Improved Multi-Round Belief Propagation Decoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03461v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Error correction at short blocklengths remains a challenge for low-density parity-check (LDPC) codes, as belief propagation (BP) decoding is suboptimal compared to maximum-likelihood decoding (MLD). While BP rarely makes errors, it often fails to converge due to a small number of problematic, erroneous variable nodes (VNs). Multi-round BP (MRBP) decoding improves performance by identifying and perturbing these VNs, enabling BP to succeed in subsequent decoding attempts. However, existing heuristic approaches for VN identification may require a large number of decoding rounds to approach ML performance. In this work, we draw a connection between identifying candidate VNs to perturb in MRBP and estimating channel output errors, a problem previously addressed by syndrome-based neural decoders (SBND). Leveraging this insight, we propose an SBND-inspired neural network architecture that learns to predict which VNs MRBP needs to focus on. Experimental results demonstrate that the proposed learning approach outperforms expert rules from the literature, requiring fewer MRBP decoding attempts to reach near-MLD performance. This makes it a promising lead for improving the decoding of short LDPC codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03461v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmad Ismail, Rapha\"el Le Bidan, Elsa Dupraz, Charbel Abdel Nour</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Class-Based Expurgation Attains Csisz\'ar's Expurgated Source-Channel Exponent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03481</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03481v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper studies expurgated error exponents for joint source-channel coding for discrete memoryless sources and channels. We consider a partition of the source messages into classes, where the codeword distributions depend on the class. We show that two carefully chosen classes suffice to achieve Csisz\'ar's expurgated exponent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03481v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>AmirPouya Moeini, Albert Guill\'en i F\`abregas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Near-Field Codebook-Based 3D Spherical Channel Estimation for UCA XL-MIMO Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03507</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03507v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Extremely large-scale multiple input multiple output (XL-MIMO), a key technology for 6G communications, faces challenges in near-field channel estimation due to spherical wavefronts and the need for three-dimensional (3D) spatial characterization, particularly with uniform circular arrays (UCAs). This letter proposes a spherical-domain simultaneous orthogonal matching pursuit (S-SOMP) based scheme tailored for near-field 3D channel estimation in UCA-equipped XL-MIMO systems. We establish a sparse channel representation based on the near-field spherical wave model. Then, a novel spherical-domain transform matrix codebook is designed via joint discrete sampling of distance, azimuth, and elevation parameters, leveraging analytical approximations to ensure low correlation between steering vectors. This structured codebook enables accurate sparse signal recovery using the S-SOMP algorithm for efficient joint estimation of channel path gains, spatial angles, and distances. Simulation results demonstrate significant channel estimation accuracy improvements compared to existing benchmarks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03507v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenliang Yang, Guangchi Zhang, Miao Cui, Qingqing Wu, Yong Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>You May Use the Same Channel Knowledge Map for Environment-Aware NLoS Sensing and Communication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03589v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As one of the key usage scenarios for the sixth generation (6G) wireless networks, integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) provides an efficient framework to achieve simultaneous wireless sensing and communication. However, traditional wireless sensing techniques mainly rely on the line-of-sight (LoS) assumptions, i.e., the sensing targets are directly visible to both the sensing transmitter and receiver. This hinders ISAC systems to be applied in complex environments such as the urban low-altitude airspace, which usually suffers from signal blockage and non-line-of-sight (NLoS) multi-path propagation. To address this challenge, in this paper, we propose a novel approach to enable environment-aware NLoS ISAC by leveraging the new technique called channel knowledge map (CKM), which was originally proposed for environment-aware wireless communications. One major novelty of our proposed method is that the same CKM built for wireless communication can be directly used to enable NLoS wireless sensing, thus enjoying the benefits of ``killing two birds with one stone''. To this end, the sensing targets are treated as virtual user equipment (UE), and the wireless communication channel priors are transformed into the sensing channel priors, allowing one single CKM to serve dual purposes. We illustrate our proposed framework by a specific CKM called \emph{channel angle-delay map} (CADM). Specifically, the proposed framework utilizes CADM to derive angle-delay priors of the sensing channel by exploiting the relationship between communication and sensing angle-delay distributions, enabling sensing target localization in the challenging NLoS environment. Extensive simulation results demonstrate significant performance improvements over classic geometry-based sensing methods, which is further validated by Cram\'er-Rao Lower Bound (CRLB) analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03589v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Di Wu, Zhuoyin Dai, Yong Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Distribution of Age of Information in Time-varying Updating Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03799</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03799v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Age of Information (AoI) is a crucial metric for quantifying information freshness in real-time systems where the sampling rate of data packets is time-varying. Evaluating AoI under such conditions is challenging, as system states become temporally correlated and traditional stationary analysis is inapplicable. We investigate an $M_{t}/G/1/1$ queueing system with a time-varying sampling rate and probabilistic preemption, proposing a novel analytical framework based on multi-dimensional partial differential equations (PDEs) to capture the time evolution of the system's status distribution. To solve the PDEs, we develop a decomposition technique that breaks the high-dimensional PDE into lower-dimensional subsystems. Solving these subsystems allows us to derive the Aol distribution at arbitrary time instances. We show AoI does not exhibit a memoryless property, even with negligible processing times, due to its dependence on the historical sampling process. Our framework extends to the stationary setting, where we derive a closed-form expression for the Laplace-Stieltjes Transform (LST) of the steady-state AoI. Numerical experiments reveal AoI exhibits a non-trivial lag in response to sampling rate changes. Our results also show that no single preemption probability or processing time distribution can minimize Aol violation probability across all thresholds in either time-varying or stationary scenarios. Finally, we formulate an optimization problem and propose a heuristic method to find sampling rates that reduce costs while satisfying AoI constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03799v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin Xu, Weiqi Wang, Natarajan Gautam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study of AP Association and Users and Power Allocation for Cell-Free Massive MIMO Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03848v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces an access point-user (AP-UE) association strategy combined with pilot power allocation to mitigate multiuser interference and enhance spectral efficiency (SE) in clustered cell-free massive MIMO (CCF-mMIMO) networks. We propose a dynamic channel-based clustering method that groups APs according to their channel correlation, ensuring users are associated with APs exhibiting similar channel characteristics. The proposed approach exploits hierarchical clustering, enabling flexible cluster sizing to improve interference management and overall SE. Moreover, we present a power control (PC) technique that is based on a weighted sum-rate maximization (WSRM) algorithm to ensure consistent service quality across users. Numerical results demonstrate that the proposed method achieves superior SE and robust performance in high-density multi-user environments as compared to competing approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03848v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Mohammadzadeh, S. Mashdour, R. C. de Lamare, K. Cumanan, C. Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Difference Imaging-Based Parking Lot Surveillance in Multi-RIS-Aided Collaborative ISAC System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03851v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Parking lot surveillance with integrated sensing and communication (ISAC) system is one of the potential application scenarios defined by 3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP). Traditional surveillance systems using cameras or magnetic sensors face limitations such as light dependence, high costs, and constrained scalability. Wireless sensing with reconfigurable intelligent surfaces (RISs) has the ability to address the above limitations due to its light independence and lower deployment overhead. In this study, we propose a difference imaging-based multi-RIS-aided collaborative ISAC system to achieve parking lot surveillance. In a parking lot, the presence of vehicles induces impacts on wireless environments due to scattering characteristic variation. By delineating the parking lot into a two-dimensional image with several grid units, the proposed system can capture the variation of their scattering coefficients in free and occupied states. The variation between these two states is sparse, which can be captured through compressed sensing (CS)-based imaging algorithms. Additionally, we collaboratively employ multiple RISs to enable higher surveillance performance. Experimental results demonstrate that our method can achieve high-accuracy parking occupancy detection, and the employment of collaborative RISs further enhances the detection rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03851v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhengze Ji, Yixuan Huang, Zhixin Chen, Jie Yang, Shi Jin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resource Allocation for Multi-waveguide Pinching Antenna-assisted Broadcast Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03915v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the resource allocation for multi-dielectric waveguide-assisted broadcast systems, where each waveguide employs multiple pinching antennas (PAs), aiming to maximize the minimum achievable rate among multiple users. To capture realistic propagation effects, we propose a novel generalized frequency-dependent power attenuation model for dielectric waveguides PA system. We jointly optimize waveguide beamforming, PA power allocation, and antenna positions via a block coordinate descent scheme that capitalizes on majorization minimization and penalty methods, circumventing the inherent non-convexity of the formulated optimization problem and obtaining a computationally efficient sub-optimal solution. Simulation results demonstrate that our proposed framework substantially outperforms both conventional antenna systems and single-PA-per-waveguide configurations, clearly illustrating the intricate trade-offs between waveguide propagation loss, path loss, and resource allocation among multiple PAs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03915v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruotong Zhao, Shaokang Hu, Deepak Mishra, Derrick Wing Kwan Ng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FollowSpot: Enhancing Wireless Communications via Movable Ceiling-Mounted Metasurfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03918</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03918v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper studies the optimal placement of ceiling-mounted metasurfaces (MTSs) to help focus the wireless signal beam onto the target receiver, as inspired by the theatre spotlight. We assume that a total of $M$ MTSs are deployed, and that there are $L$ possible positions for each MTS. The resulting signal-to-noise (SNR) maximization problem is difficult to tackle directly because of the coupling between the placement decisions of the different MTSs. Mathematically, we are faced with a nonlinear discrete optimization problem with $L^M$ possible solutions. A remarkable result shown in this paper is that the above challenging problem can be efficiently solved within $O(ML^2\log(ML))$ time. There are two key steps in developing the proposed algorithm. First, we successfully decouple the placement variables of different MTSs by introducing a continuous auxiliary variable $\mu$; the discrete primal variables are now easy to optimize when $\mu$ is held fixed, but the optimization problem of $\mu$ is nonconvex. Second, we show that the optimization of continuous $\mu$ can be recast into a discrete optimization problem with only $LM$ possible solutions, so the optimal $\mu$ can now be readily obtained. Numerical results show that the proposed algorithm can not only guarantee a global optimum but also reach the optimal solution efficiently.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03918v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenhai Lai, Kaiming Shen, Rui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Invariants for sum-rank metric codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04158v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The code equivalence problem is central in coding theory and cryptography. While classical invariants are effective for Hamming and rank metrics, the sum-rank metric, which unifies both, introduces new challenges. This paper introduces new invariants for sum-rank metric codes: generalised idealisers, the centraliser, the center, and a refined notion of linearity. These lead to the definition of nuclear parameters, inspired by those used in division algebra theory, where they are crucial for proving inequivalence. We also develop a computational framework based on skew polynomials, which is isometric to the classical matrix setting but enables explicit computation of nuclear parameters for known MSRD (Maximum Sum-Rank Distance) codes. This yields a new and effective method to study the code equivalence problem where traditional tools fall short. In fact, using nuclear parameters, we can study the equivalence among the largest families of known MSRD codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04158v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Santonastaso, Ferdinando Zullo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Efficient Max-Min Fair Resource Optimization Algorithm for Rate-Splitting Multiple Access</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04201v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The max-min fairness (MMF) problem in rate-splitting multiple access (RSMA) is known to be challenging due to its non-convex and non-smooth nature, as well as the coupled beamforming and common rate variables. Conventional algorithms to address this problem often incur high computational complexity or degraded MMF rate performance. To address these challenges, in this work, we propose a novel optimization algorithm named extragradient-fractional programming (EG-FP) to address the MMF problem of downlink RSMA. The proposed algorithm first leverages FP to transform the original problem into a block-wise convex problem. For the subproblem of precoding block, we show that its Lagrangian dual is equivalent to a variational inequality problem, which is then solved using an extragradient-based algorithm. Additionally, we discover the optimal beamforming structure of the problem and based on which, we introduce a low-dimensional EG-FP algorithm with computational complexity independent of the number of transmit antennas. This feature is especially beneficial in scenarios with a large number of transmit antennas. The proposed algorithms are then extended to handle imperfect channel state information at the transmitter (CSIT). Numerical results demonstrate that the MMF rate achieved by our proposed algorithms closely matches that of the conventional successive convex approximation (SCA) algorithm and significantly outperforms other baseline schemes. Remarkably, the average CPU time of the proposed algorithms is less than 10\% of the runtime required by the SCA algorithm, showing the efficiency and scalability of the proposed algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04201v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Facheng Luo, Yijie Mao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mutual Information Bounds for Lossy Common Information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04209v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show the mutual information between the targets in a Gray-Wyner Network as a bound that separates Wyner's lossy common information and G\'acs-K\"orner lossy common information. The results are a generalization of the lossless case presented by Wyner (1975).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04209v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anderson de Andrade</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital-Twin Empowered Site-Specific Radio Resource Management in 5G Aerial Corridor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04566v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Base station (BS) association and beam selection in multi-cell drone corridor networks present unique challenges due to the high altitude, mobility and three-dimensional movement of drones. These factors lead to frequent handovers and complex beam alignment issues, especially in environments with dense BS deployments and varying signal conditions. To address these challenges, this paper proposes a channel-twin (CT) enabled resource-allocation framework for drone-corridor communications, where the CT constitutes the radio-channel component of a broader digital-twin (DT) environment. The CT supplies high-fidelity channel-state information (CSI), which drives a two-stage optimization procedure. In Stage 1, array-level beamforming weights at each BS are selected to maximize antenna gain. In Stage 2, the framework jointly optimizes drone-BS-beam associations at discrete corridor way-points to maximize end-to-end throughput. Simulation results confirm that the CT-driven strategy delivers significant throughput gains over baseline methods across diverse operating scenarios, validating the effectiveness of integrating precise digital-twin channel models with cross-layer resource optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04566v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pulok Tarafder, Imtiaz Ahmed, Danda B. Rawat, Md. Zoheb Hassan, Kamrul Hasan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On subcodes of the generalized Reed-Solomon codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04689v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study a class of subcodes of codimension $1$ in the $[n,k+1]_q$ generalized Reed-Solomon (GRS) codes, whose generator matrix is derived by removing the row of degree $k-r$ from the generator matrix of the $[n,k+1]_q$ GRS codes, where $1 \le r \le k-1$. We show equivalent characterizations for this class of subcodes of the GRS codes being self-dual or near-MDS, which extends the results for $r=1$ in the literature. Along with these characterizations, families of self-dual near-MDS subcodes of the GRS codes are also proposed. Finally, for $r = 1,2$, the dual codes of the subcodes of the GRS codes are found out. In some cases, the subcodes of the GRS codes can be closed under taking dual codes. In other cases, the dual codes turn out to be the twisted GRS codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04689v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Ning</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correcting Bursty/Localized Deletions: A New Error-Position-Estimation Code</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04797</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04797v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Codes correcting bursts of deletions and localized deletions have garnered significant research interest in recent years. One of the primary objectives is to construct codes with minimal redundancy. Currently, the best known constructions of $q$-ary codes correcting a burst of at most $t$ deletions ($(\le t)$-burst-deletion correcting codes) achieve redundancy $\log n+8\log\log n+o(\log\log n)$ (for any $q$ and $t$) or $\log n+t\log\log n+O(1)$ (for even $q$). For codes correcting single $t$-localized-deletion ($t$-localized-deletion correcting codes), state-of-the-art constructions attain redundancy $\log n+O\parenv{t(\log\log n)^2}$ (for any $q$ and $t$) or $\log n+2t\log\log n+O(1)$ (for even $q$). Here, $n$ denotes the code-length, and $q$ and $t$ are fixed. These codes employ a position-estimation component to approximate error positions, augmented by additional constraints that enable error-correction given the information about error positions.
  In this work, we select codewords from the set of sequences whose differential sequences are strong-$(\ell,\epsilon)$-locally-balanced. By imposing a VT-type constraint and an $L_1$-weight constraint on the differential sequences of codewords, we construct novel position-estimation codes. When $q\ge 2$ and $t&lt;q$, or $q$ is even and $t&lt;2q$, this approach gives a $q$-ary $(\le t)$-burst-deletion correcting code and a $t$-localized-deletion correcting code with redundancy $\log n+(t-1)\log\log n+O(1)$. In addition to improving previous redundancy, the method is new and our position-estimation codes are simpler than those in previous works. Finally, we give an efficient encoder to encode an arbitrary input sequence into a sequence whose differential sequence is strong-$(\ell,\epsilon)$-locally-balanced. To our knowledge, no prior algorithm for this specific task has been reported.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04797v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zuo Ye, Yubo Sun, Gennian Ge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Maximum Size of Codes Under the Damerau-Levenshtein Metric</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04806v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Damerau-Levenshtein distance between two sequences is the minimum number of operations (deletions, insertions, substitutions, and adjacent transpositions) required to convert one sequence into another. Notwithstanding a long history of this metric, research on error-correcting codes under this distance has remained limited. Recently, motivated by applications in DNA-based storage systems, Gabrys \textit{et al} and Wang \texit{et al} reinvigorated interest in this metric. In their works, some codes correcting both deletions and adjacent transpositions were constructed. However, theoretical upper bounds on code sizes under this metric have not yet been established. This paper seeks to establish upper bounds for code sizes in the Damerau-Levenshtein metric. Our results show that the code correcting one deletion and asymmetric adjacent transpositions proposed by Wang \textit{et al} achieves optimal redundancy up to an additive constant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04806v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zuo Ye, Gennian Ge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kalman Filter Aided Federated Koopman Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04808v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Real-time control and estimation are pivotal for applications such as industrial automation and future healthcare. The realization of this vision relies heavily on efficient interactions with nonlinear systems. Therefore, Koopman learning, which leverages the power of deep learning to linearize nonlinear systems, has been one of the most successful examples of mitigating the complexity inherent in nonlinearity. However, the existing literature assumes access to accurate system states and abundant high-quality data for Koopman analysis, which is usually impractical in real-world scenarios. To fill this void, this paper considers the case where only observations of the system are available and where the observation data is insufficient to accomplish an independent Koopman analysis. To this end, we propose Kalman Filter aided Federated Koopman Learning (KF-FedKL), which pioneers the combination of Kalman filtering and federated learning with Koopman analysis. By doing so, we can achieve collaborative linearization with privacy guarantees. Specifically, we employ a straightforward yet efficient loss function to drive the training of a deep Koopman network for linearization. To obtain system information devoid of individual information from observation data, we leverage the unscented Kalman filter and the unscented Rauch-Tung-Striebel smoother. To achieve collaboration between clients, we adopt the federated learning framework and develop a modified FedAvg algorithm to orchestrate the collaboration. A convergence analysis of the proposed framework is also presented. Finally, through extensive numerical simulations, we showcase the performance of KF-FedKL under various situations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04808v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yutao Chen, Wei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast and Provable Hankel Tensor Completion for Multi-measurement Spectral Compressed Sensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04847</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04847v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce a novel low-rank Hankel tensor completion approach to address the problem of multi-measurement spectral compressed sensing. By lifting the multiple signals to a Hankel tensor, we reformulate this problem into a low-rank Hankel tensor completion task, exploiting the spectral sparsity via the low multilinear rankness of the tensor. Furthermore, we design a scaled gradient descent algorithm for Hankel tensor completion (ScalHT), which integrates the low-rank Tucker decomposition with the Hankel structure. Crucially, we derive novel fast computational formulations that leverage the interaction between these two structures, achieving up to an $O(\min\{s,n\})$-fold improvement in storage and computational efficiency compared to the existing algorithms, where $n$ is the length of signal, $s$ is the number of measurement vectors. Beyond its practical efficiency, ScalHT is backed by rigorous theoretical guarantees: we establish both recovery and linear convergence guarantees, which, to the best of our knowledge, are the first of their kind for low-rank Hankel tensor completion. Numerical simulations show that our method exhibits significantly lower computational and storage costs while delivering superior recovery performance compared to prior arts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04847v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinsheng Li, Xu Zhang, Shuang Wu, Wei Cui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Age-Aware CSI Acquisition of a Finite-State Markovian Channel</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05042</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05042v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Age of Information (AoI) has emerged as a critical metric for quantifying information freshness; however, its interplay with channel estimation in partially observable wireless systems remains underexplored. This work considers a transmitter-receiver pair communicating over an unreliable channel with time-varying reliability levels. The transmitter observes the instantaneous link reliability through a channel state information acquisition procedure, during which the data transmission is interrupted. This leads to a fundamental trade-off between utilizing limited network resources for either data transmission or channel state information acquisition to combat the channel aging effect. Assuming the wireless channel is modeled as a finite-state Markovian channel, we formulate an optimization problem as a partially observable Markov decision process (POMDP), obtain the optimal policy through the relative value iteration algorithm, and demonstrate the efficiency of our solution through simulations. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first work to aim for an optimal scheduling policy for data transmissions while considering the effect of channel state information aging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05042v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Onur Ayan, Jiping Luo, Xueli An, Nikolaos Pappas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Circular Holographic MIMO Beamforming for Integrated Data and Energy Multicast Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05057</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05057v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Thanks to the application of metamaterials, holographic multiple-input multiple-output (H-MIMO) is expected to achieve a higher spatial diversity gain with lower hardware complexity. With the aid of a circular antenna arrangement of H-MIMO, integrated data and energy multicast (IDEM) can fully exploit the near-field channel to realize wider range of energy focusing and higher achievable rate. In this paper, we derive the closed-form near-field resolution function in 3D space and show the asymptotic spatial orthogonality of near-field channel for circular antenna array. We then investigate the beamforming designs for IDEM systems, where the minimum rate of data users (DUs) are maximized while guaranteeing the energy harvesting requirements for energy users (EUs). Specifically, the asymptotically optimal fully-digital beamformer is first obtained based on the spatial orthogonality. Then, the alternating optimization is adopted for the H-MIMO beamforming, where the digital beamformer is obtained in closed form and the analog beamformers of three different control modes are then obtained, respectively. Scaling schemes are also investigated to further improve the IDEM performance. Numerical results verify the correctness of the resolution function and asymptotic orthogonality. Moreover, the proposed beamforming schemes with very low complexity outperform benchmark schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05057v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qingxiao Huang, Yizhe Zhao, Jie Hu, Kun Yang, Yuguang Fang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LVM4CSI: Enabling Direct Application of Pre-Trained Large Vision Models for Wireless Channel Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05121</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05121v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate channel state information (CSI) is critical to the performance of wireless communication systems, especially with the increasing scale and complexity introduced by 5G and future 6G technologies. While artificial intelligence (AI) offers a promising approach to CSI acquisition and utilization, existing methods largely depend on task-specific neural networks (NNs) that require expert-driven design and large training datasets, limiting their generalizability and practicality. To address these challenges, we propose LVM4CSI, a general and efficient framework that leverages the structural similarity between CSI and computer vision (CV) data to directly apply large vision models (LVMs) pre-trained on extensive CV datasets to wireless tasks without any fine-tuning, in contrast to large language model-based methods that generally necessitate fine-tuning. LVM4CSI maps CSI tasks to analogous CV tasks, transforms complex-valued CSI into visual formats compatible with LVMs, and integrates lightweight trainable layers to adapt extracted features to specific communication objectives. We validate LVM4CSI through three representative case studies, including channel estimation, human activity recognition, and user localization. Results demonstrate that LVM4CSI achieves comparable or superior performance to task-specific NNs, including an improvement exceeding 9.61 dB in channel estimation and approximately 40% reduction in localization error. Furthermore, it significantly reduces the number of trainable parameters and eliminates the need for task-specific NN design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05121v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiajia Guo, Peiwen Jiang, Chao-Kai Wen, Shi Jin, Jun Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deterministic Cryptographic Seed Generation via Cyclic Modular Inversion over $\mathbb{Z}/3^p\mathbb{Z}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03000v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a deterministic framework for cryptographic seed generation based on cyclic modular inversion over $\mathbb{Z}/3^p\mathbb{Z}$. The method enforces algebraic admissibility on seed inputs via the identity $d_k \equiv -\left(2^{k-1}\right)^{-1} \bmod 3^p$, thereby producing structured and invertible residue sequences. This mapping yields entropy-rich, cycle-complete seeds well-suited for cryptographic primitives such as DRBGs, KDFs, and post-quantum schemes. To assess the quality of randomness, we introduce the Entropy Confidence Score (ECS), a composite metric reflecting coverage, uniformity, and modular bias. Although not a cryptographic PRNG in itself, the framework serves as a deterministic entropy filter that conditions and validates seed inputs prior to their use by conventional generators. Empirical and hardware-based results confirm constant-time execution, minimal side-channel leakage, and lightweight feasibility for embedded applications. The framework complements existing cryptographic stacks by acting as an algebraically verifiable entropy filter, thereby enhancing structural soundness and auditability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03000v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael A. Idowu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error correction, authentication, and false acceptance, probabilities for communication over noisy quantum channels: converse upper bounds on the bit transmission rate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03035v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We obtain strict upper bounds on the bit transmission rate for communication of Classical bit codewords over Quantum channels. Albeit previous arguments in arXiv: 1804.01797 which have demonstrated that lower bounds can be shown to hold for the bit transmission rate without the presence of significant noise over the channel shared by Alice and Bob for the purposes of encoding, decoding, transmission and authentication, the author suggests that upper bounding the bit transmission rate could be of use towards classifying paradoxical aspects of communication protocols, as well as constructing error correcting codes which are resilient to noise. The upper bound that is obtained in this work for the bit transmission rate, as a converse result, is dependent upon the natural logarithm of the size of each player's alphabet, as well as smaller alphabets, which can be leveraged for simultaneously realizing Quantum advantage for maximizing error correction and minimizing false acceptance. Crucially, the upper bound to the bit transmission rate is dependent upon a pruning procedure, which seeks to determine whether letters from player's alphabets can be removed so that prospective Quantum advantage, in order for Alice and Bob to implement error correction protocols with high probability, despite the fact that there is more noise over the channel between Alice and Bob in comparison to that between Bob and Eve.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03035v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pete Rigas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Specific Absorption Rate-Aware Multiuser MIMO Assisted by Fluid Antenna System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03351</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03351v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: With the development of the upcoming sixth-generation (6G) wireless networks, there is a pressing need for innovative technologies capable of satisfying heightened performance indicators. Fluid antenna system (FAS) is proposed recently as a promising technique to achieve higher data rates and more diversity gains by dynamically changing the positions of the antennas to form a more desirable channel. However, worries regarding the possibly harmful effects of electromagnetic (EM) radiation emitted by devices have arisen as a result of the rapid evolution of advanced techniques in wireless communication systems. Specific absorption rate (SAR) is a widely adopted metric to quantify EM radiation worldwide. In this paper, we investigate the SAR-aware multiuser multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) communications assisted by FAS. In particular, a two-layer iterative algorithm is proposed to minimize the SAR value under signal-to-interference-plus-noise ratio (SINR) and FAS constraints. Moreover, the minimum weighted SINR maximization problem under SAR and FAS constraints is studied by finding its relationship with the SAR minimization problem. Simulation results verify that the proposed SAR-aware FAS design outperforms the adaptive backoff and fixed-position antenna designs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03351v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuqi Ye, Li You, Hao Xu, Ahmed Elzanaty, Kai-Kit Wong, Xiqi Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Early Termination of Low-Density Parity-Check Codes for Continuous-Variable Quantum Key Distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03509</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03509v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyse the impact of log a-posteriori early termination on the decoding throughput of reconciliation for continuous-variable quantum key distribution. Increases in decoded secret key rate throughput of up to 182% are reported in both simulations and experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03509v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kadir G\"um\"u\c{s}, Jo\~ao dos Reis Fraz\~ao, Vincent van Vliet, Menno van den Hout, Aaron Albores-Mejia, Thomas Bradley, Chigo Okonkwo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Short Blocklength Error Correction Codes for Continuous-Variable Quantum Key Distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03529v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a two-step error correction scheme for reconciliation in continuous-variable quantum key distribution systems. Using this scheme, it is possible to use error correction codes with small blocklengths (1000 bits), increasing secret key rates at a distance of 140km by up to 7.3 times.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03529v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kadir G\"um\"u\c{s}, Jo\~ao dos Reis Fraz\~ao, Boris \v{S}kori\'c, Gabriele Liga, Aaron Albores-Mejia, Thomas Bradley, Chigo Okonkwo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Affine Frequency Division Multiplexing Over Wideband Doubly-Dispersive Channels With Time-Scaling Effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03537v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The recently proposed affine frequency division multiplexing (AFDM) modulation has been considered as a promising technology for narrowband doubly-dispersive channels. However, the time-scaling effects, i.e., pulse widening and pulse shortening phenomena, in extreme wideband doubly-dispersive channels have not been considered in the literatures. In this paper, we investigate such wideband transmission and develop an efficient transmission structure with chirp-periodic prefix (CPP) and chirp-periodic suffix (CPS) for AFDM system. We derive the input-output relationship of AFDM system under time-scaled wideband doubly-dispersive channels and demonstrate the sparsity in discrete affine Fourier (DAF) domain equivalent channels. We further optimize the AFDM chirp parameters to accommodate the time-scaling characteristics in wideband doubly-dispersive channels and verify the superiority of the derived chirp parameters by pairwise error probability (PEP) analysis. We also develop an efficient cross domain distributed orthogonal approximate message passing (CD-D-OAMP) algorithm for AFDM symbol detection and analyze its corresponding state evolution. By analyzing the detection complexity of CD-D-OAMP detector and evaluating the error performance of AFDM systems based on simulations, we demonstrate that the AFDM system with our optimized chirp parameters outperforms the existing competitive modulation schemes in time-scaled wideband doubly-dispersive channels. Moreover, our proposed CD-D-OAMP detector can achieve the desirable trade-off between the complexity and performance, while supporting parallel computing to significantly reduce the computational latency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03537v1</guid>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiangxiang Li, Haiyan Wang, Yao Ge, Xiaohong Shen, Yong Liang Guan, Miaowen Wen, Chau Yuen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Street Form to Spatial Justice: Explaining Urban Exercise Inequality via a Triadic SHAP-Informed Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03570v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Urban streets are essential public spaces that facilitate everyday physical activity and promote health equity. Drawing on Henri Lefebvre's spatial triad, this study proposes a conceptual and methodological framework to quantify street-level exercise deprivation through the dimensions of conceived (planning and structure), perceived (visual and sensory), and lived (practice and experiential) urban spaces. We integrate multi-source spatial data-including street networks, street-view imagery, and social media-using explainable machine learning (SHAP analysis) to classify streets by their dominant deprivation modes, forming a novel typology of spatial inequity. Results highlight significant differences across urban contexts: older city cores predominantly experience infrastructural constraints (conceived space), whereas new development areas suffer from experiential disengagement (lived space). Furthermore, by identifying spatial mismatches between population distribution and exercise intensity, our study reveals localized clusters of latent deprivation. Simulation experiments demonstrate that targeted improvements across spatial dimensions can yield up to 14% increases in exercise supportiveness. This research not only operationalizes Lefebvre's spatial theory at the street scale but also provides actionable insights and intervention guidelines, contributing to the broader goals of spatial justice and urban health equity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03570v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minwei Zhao, Guosheng Yang, Zhuoni Zhang, Cai Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Security proof for parallel DIQKD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03991v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a parallel device independent quantum key distribution (DIQKD) protocol based on the CHSH game and prove its security. Using techniques developed for analysing the parallel repetition of anchored non-local games, we show that the answers on a small random linear subset of the games in the DIQKD protocol can be simulated as the output of a single-round strategy for playing the CHSH game. Then, we use the recently developed unstructured approximate entropy accumulation theorem to establish the smooth min-entropy lower bound required for the security proof. Our approach yields a more information-theoretic and general proof for parallel DIQKD compared to previous proofs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03991v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashutosh Marwah, Fr\'ed\'eric Dupuis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LCD and self-orthogonal twisted group codes over finite commutative chain rings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04013v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we shall study k-Galois LCD constacyclic group codes over finite commutative chain rings with identity. In particular, we shall characterize Galois LCD constacyclic codes over finite commutative chain ring with identity in terms of its idempotent generators and the classical involution using the twisted group ring structures and find some good LCD codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04013v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samir Assuena, Andr\'e Luiz Martins Pereira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Availability Integrity Monitoring for Multi-Constellation GNSS Navigation with Non-Gaussian Errors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04284v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Global navigation satellite systems (GNSS) are essential for aviation, requiring strict integrity monitoring to alert users to hazardously misleading information. Conventional receiver autonomous integrity monitoring (RAIM) and advanced RAIM (ARAIM) rely heavily on Gaussian models in bounding nominal errors, which can be overly conservative with real-world non-Gaussian errors with heavy tails, such as the satellite clock and orbit errors. This paper proposes an extended jackknife detector capable of detecting multiple simultaneous faults with non-Gaussian nominal errors. Furthermore, an integrity monitoring algorithm, jackknife ARAIM, is developed by systematically exploiting the properties of the jackknife detector in the range domain. A tight bound of the integrity risk is derived by quantifying the impacts of hypothetical fault vectors on the position solution. The proposed method is examined in worldwide simulations, with the nominal measurement error simulated based on authentic experimental data, which reveals different findings in existing research. In a setting of a single Global Positioning System (GPS) constellation, the proposed method reduces the 99.5 percentile vertical protection level (VPL) 45m, where the VPL of the baseline ARAIM is larger than 50m in most user locations. For dual-constellation (GPS-Galileo) settings, baseline ARAIM suffers VPL inflation over 60m due to the over-conservatism induced by the heavy-tailed Galileo signal-in-space range errors, whereas the proposed jackknife ARAIM retains VPL below 40m, achieving over 92% normal operations for a 35m Vertical Alert Limit. These improvements have promising potential to support localizer performance with vertical guidance (LPV) with a decision height of 200 ft, enhancing integrity and availability for multi-constellation GNSS applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04284v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Penggao Yan, Ronghe Jin, Junyi Zhang, Cheng-Wei Wang, Li-Ta Hsu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconstructing Biological Pathways by Applying Selective Incremental Learning to (Very) Small Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04432v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The use of generative artificial intelligence (AI) models is becoming ubiquitous in many fields. Though progress continues to be made, general purpose large language AI models (LLM) show a tendency to deliver creative answers, often called "hallucinations", which have slowed their application in the medical and biomedical fields where accuracy is paramount. We propose that the design and use of much smaller, domain and even task-specific LM may be a more rational and appropriate use of this technology in biomedical research. In this work we apply a very small LM by today's standards to the specialized task of predicting regulatory interactions between molecular components to fill gaps in our current understanding of intracellular pathways. Toward this we attempt to correctly posit known pathway-informed interactions recovered from manually curated pathway databases by selecting and using only the most informative examples as part of an active learning scheme. With this example we show that a small (~110 million parameters) LM based on a Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers (BERT) architecture can propose molecular interactions relevant to tuberculosis persistence and transmission with over 80% accuracy using less than 25% of the ~520 regulatory relationships in question. Using information entropy as a metric for the iterative selection of new tuning examples, we also find that increased accuracy is driven by favoring the use of the incorrectly assigned statements with the highest certainty (lowest entropy). In contrast, the concurrent use of correct but least certain examples contributed little and may have even been detrimental to the learning rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04432v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.MN</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pranta Saha, Joyce Reimer, Brook Byrns, Connor Burbridge, Neeraj Dhar, Jeffrey Chen, Steven Rayan, Gordon Broderick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropy measures as indicators of connectivity paths in the human brain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04442v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: How does the information flow between different brain regions during various stimuli? This is the question we aim to address by studying complex cognitive paradigms in terms of Information Theory. To assess creativity and the emergence of patterns from a Shannon perspective, we applied a range of tools, including Entropy Density, Effective Measure Complexity, and the Lempel-Ziv distance. These entropic tools enable the detection of both linear and non-linear dynamics without relying on pre-established parameters, models, or prior assumptions about the data. To identify connections between different brain regions, we analyse task-based fMRI data from subjects during motor, working memory, emotion recognition, and language stimuli to gain insight into these complex cognitive processes. Since this method does not rely on prior knowledge, it is particularly well-suited for exploratory research, facilitating the discovery of previously unidentified connections or patterns in the brain. The capacity to identify non-linear dynamics is especially important for studying brain connectivity, as the brain exhibits significant non-linear interactions across multiple functional levels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04442v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ania Mesa-Rodr\'iguez, Ernesto Estevez-Rams, Holger Kantz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LINE: Public-key encryption</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04501v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a public key encryption cryptosystem based on solutions of linear equation systems with predefinition of input parameters through shared secret computation for factorizable substitutions. The existence of multiple equivalent solutions for an underdetermined system of linear equations determines the impossibility of its resolution by a cryptanalyst in polynomial time. The completion of input parameters of the equation system is implemented through secret homomorphic matrix transformation for substitutions factorized over the basis of a vector space of dimension m over the field F2. Encryption is implemented through computation of substitutions that are one-way functions on an elementary abelian 2-group of order 2"m. Decryption is implemented through completion of input parameters of the equation system. Homomorphic transformations are constructed based on matrix computations. Matrix computations enable the implementation of high security and low computational overhead for homomorphic transformations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04501v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gennady Khalimov, Yevgen Kotukh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information-Guided Diffusion Sampling for Dataset Distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04619v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Dataset distillation aims to create a compact dataset that retains essential information while maintaining model performance. Diffusion models (DMs) have shown promise for this task but struggle in low images-per-class (IPC) settings, where generated samples lack diversity. In this paper, we address this issue from an information-theoretic perspective by identifying two key types of information that a distilled dataset must preserve: ($i$) prototype information $\mathrm{I}(X;Y)$, which captures label-relevant features; and ($ii$) contextual information $\mathrm{H}(X | Y)$, which preserves intra-class variability. Here, $(X,Y)$ represents the pair of random variables corresponding to the input data and its ground truth label, respectively. Observing that the required contextual information scales with IPC, we propose maximizing $\mathrm{I}(X;Y) + \beta \mathrm{H}(X | Y)$ during the DM sampling process, where $\beta$ is IPC-dependent. Since directly computing $\mathrm{I}(X;Y)$ and $\mathrm{H}(X | Y)$ is intractable, we develop variational estimations to tightly lower-bound these quantities via a data-driven approach. Our approach, information-guided diffusion sampling (IGDS), seamlessly integrates with diffusion models and improves dataset distillation across all IPC settings. Experiments on Tiny ImageNet and ImageNet subsets show that IGDS significantly outperforms existing methods, particularly in low-IPC regimes. The code will be released upon acceptance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04619v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linfeng Ye, Shayan Mohajer Hamidi, Guang Li, Takahiro Ogawa, Miki Haseyama, Konstantinos N. Plataniotis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intuitive dissection of the Gaussian information bottleneck method with an application to optimal prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05183v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Efficient signal representation is essential for the functioning of living and artificial systems operating under resource constraints. A widely recognized framework for deriving such representations is the information bottleneck method, which yields the optimal strategy for encoding a random variable, such as the signal, in a way that preserves maximal information about a functionally relevant variable, subject to an explicit constraint on the amount of information encoded. While in its general formulation the method is numerical, it admits an analytical solution in an important special case where the variables involved are jointly Gaussian. In this setting, the solution predicts discrete transitions in the dimensionality of the optimal representation as the encoding capacity is increased. Although these signature transitions, along with other features of the optimal strategy, can be derived from a constrained optimization problem, a clear and intuitive understanding of their emergence is still lacking. In our work, we advance our understanding of the Gaussian information bottleneck method through multiple mutually enriching perspectives, including geometric and information-theoretic ones. These perspectives offer novel intuition about the set of optimal encoding directions, the nature of the critical points where the optimal number of encoding components changes, and about the way the optimal strategy navigates between these critical points. We then apply our treatment of the method to a previously studied signal prediction problem, obtaining new insights on how different features of the signal are encoded across multiple components to enable optimal prediction of future signals. Altogether, our work deepens the foundational understanding of the information bottleneck method in the Gaussian setting, motivating the exploration of analogous perspectives in broader, non-Gaussian contexts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05183v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.MN</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vahe Galstyan, Age Tjalma, Pieter Rein ten Wolde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alternating minimization for computing doubly minimized Petz Renyi mutual information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05205</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05205v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The doubly minimized Petz Renyi mutual information (PRMI) of order $\alpha$ is defined as the minimization of the Petz divergence of order $\alpha$ of a fixed bipartite quantum state $\rho_{AB}$ relative to any product state $\sigma_A\otimes \tau_B$. To date, no closed-form expression for this measure has been found, necessitating the development of numerical methods for its computation. In this work, we show that alternating minimization over $\sigma_A$ and $\tau_B$ asymptotically converges to the doubly minimized PRMI for any $\alpha\in (\frac{1}{2},1)\cup (1,2]$, by proving linear convergence of the objective function values with respect to the number of iterations for $\alpha\in (1,2]$ and sublinear convergence for $\alpha\in (\frac{1}{2},1)$. Previous studies have only addressed the specific case where $\rho_{AB}$ is a classical-classical state, while our results hold for any quantum state $\rho_{AB}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05205v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laura Burri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metrization of powers of the Jensen-Shannon divergence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.10070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.10070v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Metrization of statistical divergences is valuable in both theoretical and practical aspects. One approach to obtaining metrics associated with divergences is to consider their fractional powers. Motivated by this idea, Os\'an, Bussandri, and Lamberti (2018) studied the metrization of fractional powers of the Jensen-Shannon divergence between multinomial distributions and posed an open problem. In this short note, we provide an affirmative answer to their conjecture. Moreover, our method is also applicable to fractional powers of $f$-divergences between Cauchy distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.10070v4</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuki Okamura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving Numerical Stability of Normalized Mutual Information Estimator on High Dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07642v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Mutual information provides a powerful, general-purpose metric for quantifying the amount of shared information between variables. Estimating normalized mutual information using a k-Nearest Neighbor (k-NN) based approach involves the calculation of the scaling-invariant k-NN radius. Calculation of the radius suffers from numerical overflow when the joint dimensionality of the data becomes high, typically in the range of several hundred dimensions. To address this issue, we propose a logarithmic transformation technique that improves the numerical stability of the radius calculation in high-dimensional spaces. By applying the proposed transformation during the calculation of the radius, numerical overflow is avoided, and precision is maintained. Proposed transformation is validated through both theoretical analysis and empirical evaluation, demonstrating its ability to stabilize the calculation without compromising precision, increasing bias, or adding significant computational overhead, while also helping to maintain estimator variance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07642v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marko Tuononen, Ville Hautam\"aki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Massive MIMO over Correlated Fading Channels: Multi-Cell MMSE Processing, Pilot Assignment and Power Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02061v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a multi-cell massive multiple-input-multiple-output (MIMO) system with correlated Rayleigh fading channels, where pilot reuse is permitted within each cell (to reduce pilot overhead), and each base station (BS) utilizes multi-cell minimum mean square (M-MMSE) precoders and combining. We derive a large-scale approximation of the uplink signal-to-interference-and-noise ratio (SINR) that is asymptotically tight in the large system limit. By leveraging the derived SINR approximation, we (i) develop a low-complexity multi-cell pilot assignment (PA) scheme aimed at minimizing pilot contamination from pilot-sharing users, via effectively exploiting the channel spatial correlation matrices of all users in the network, (ii) design pilot and data power allocation schemes, using both the weighted sum and max-min spectral efficiency (SE) metrics. Simulations demonstrate the superiority of our multi-cell PA scheme, requiring significantly less pilot overhead. The proposed power allocation schemes also achieve substantial sum SE gains with good fairness among users compared to equal power allocation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02061v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TWC.2025.3581057</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Masoud Elyasi, Azadeh Vosoughi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Informational Parsimony Perspective on Probabilistic Symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08954v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Extraction of structure, in particular of group symmetries, is increasingly crucial to understanding and building intelligent models. In particular, some information-theoretic models of parsimonious learning have been argued to induce invariance extraction. Here, we formalise these arguments from a group-theoretic perspective. We then extend them to the study of more general probabilistic symmetries, through compressions preserving geometric measures of complexity. More precisely, our framework implements a trade-off between compression and preservation of the divergence from a given hierarchical model, yielding a novel generalisation of the Information Bottleneck framework. Through appropriate choices of hierarchical models, we fully characterise (in the discrete and full support case) channel invariance, channel equivariance and distribution invariance under permutation. Allowing imperfect divergence preservation then leads to principled definitions of "soft symmetries", where the "coarseness" corresponds to the degree of compression of the system. In simple synthetic experiments, we demonstrate that our method successively recovers, at increasingly compressed "resolutions", nested but increasingly perturbed equivariances, where new equivariances emerge at bifurcation points of the trade-off parameter. Our framework suggests a new path for the extraction of generalised probabilistic symmetries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08954v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hippolyte Charvin, Nicola Catenacci Volpi, Daniel Polani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decision Feedback In-Context Learning for Wireless Symbol Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16594v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Pre-trained Transformers, through in-context learning (ICL), have demonstrated exceptional capabilities to adapt to new tasks using example prompts without model update. Transformer-based wireless receivers, where prompts consist of the pilot data in the form of transmitted and received signal pairs, have shown high detection accuracy when pilot data are abundant. However, pilot information is often costly and limited in practice. In this work, we propose DEcision Feedback IN-ContExt Detection (DEFINED) as a new wireless receiver design, which bypasses channel estimation and directly performs symbol detection using the (sometimes extremely) limited pilot data. The key innovation in DEFINED is the proposed decision feedback mechanism in ICL, where we sequentially incorporate the detected symbols into the prompts as pseudo-labels to improve the detection for subsequent symbols. We further establish an error lower bound and provide theoretical insights into the model's generalization under channel distribution mismatch. Extensive experiments across a broad range of wireless settings demonstrate that a small Transformer trained with DEFINED achieves significant performance improvements over conventional methods, in some cases only needing a single pilot pair to achieve similar performance to the latter with more than 4 pilot pairs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16594v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Li Fan, Wei Shen, Jing Yang, Cong Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-Complexity Detection of Permutational Index Modulation for Noncoherent Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02946v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work presents a massive SIMO scheme for wireless communications with one-shot noncoherent detection. It is based on permutational index modulation over OFDM. Its core principle is to convey information on the ordering in which a fixed collection of values is mapped onto a set of OFDM subcarriers. A spherical code is obtained which provides improved robustness against channel impairments. A simple detector based on the sorting of quadratic metrics of data is proposed. By exploiting statistical channel state information and hardening, it reaches near-ML error performance with a low-complexity implementation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02946v3</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LWC.2025.3585351</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Marc Vil\`a-Insa, Aniol Mart\'i, Meritxell Lamarca, Jaume Riba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint Source-Channel Noise Adding with Adaptive Denoising for Diffusion-Based Semantic Communications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09644</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09644v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Semantic communication (SemCom) aims to convey the intended meaning of messages rather than merely transmitting bits, thereby offering greater efficiency and robustness, particularly in resource-constrained or noisy environments. In this paper, we propose a novel framework which is referred to as joint source-channel noise adding with adaptive denoising (JSCNA-AD) for SemCom based on a diffusion model (DM). Unlike conventional encoder-decoder designs, our approach intentionally incorporates the channel noise during transmission, effectively transforming the harmful channel noise into a constructive component of the diffusion-based semantic reconstruction process. Besides, we introduce an attention-based adaptive denoising mechanism, in which transmitted images are divided into multiple regions, and the number of denoising steps is dynamically allocated based on the semantic importance of each region. This design effectively balances the reception quality and the inference latency by prioritizing the critical semantic information. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our method significantly outperforms existing SemCom schemes under various noise conditions, underscoring the potential of diffusion-based models in next-generation communication systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09644v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengyang Liang, Dong Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Last-Pair Swapping Polar Codes: A Structure to Improve Polarization under Finite-State Modulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.11535v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A novel structure of polar codes is proposed for finite-state modulation (FSM), in order to improve polarization under it, and approach the polarization efficiency that conventional polar codes achieve under memoryless channels. We choose a particular class of FSM for research, termed bijective FSM, and observe an explicit polarization loss under bijective FSM. To eliminate the loss, we propose a novel polar coding structure by substituting the last kernel of each layer in polar coding structure with a swapping matrix, thereby termed last-pair swapping structure. We prove that under bijective FSM the proposed structure achieves identical polarization efficiency with that of conventional one on memoryless channels, and exceeds that of conventional one under bijective FSM. Furthermore, we give a plausible generalization of last-pair swapping polar code: on a broader class termed sub-injective FSM. Simulation corroborates that under sub-injective FSM polarization efficiency of the proposed polar code exceeds that of conventional one. And simulation results of error rate are given on continuous phase modulation (CPM) with additional white Gaussian noise (AWGN) channels, showing a considerable signal-to-noise power ratio (snr) gain of last-pair swapping polar code over conventional one, and identical performances between the proposed polar code under bijective FSM and conventional one on memoryless channels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.11535v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yinuo Mei, Yangyong Zhang, Daiming Qu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A proof of P != NP (New symmetric encryption algorithm against any linear attacks and differential attacks)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.05022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2203.05022v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: P vs NP problem is the most important unresolved problem in the field of computational complexity. Its impact has penetrated into all aspects of algorithm design, especially in the field of cryptography. The security of cryptographic algorithms based on short keys depends on whether P is equal to NP. In fact, Shannon[1] strictly proved that the one-time-pad system meets unconditional security, but because the one-time-pad system requires the length of key to be at least the length of plaintext, how to transfer the key is a troublesome problem that restricts the use of the one-time-pad system in practice. Cryptography algorithms used in practice are all based on short key, and the security of the short key mechanism is ultimately based on "one-way" assumption, that is, it is assumed that a one-way function exists. In fact, the existence of one-way function can directly lead to the important conclusion P != NP. In this paper, we originally constructed a short-key block cipher algorithm. The core feature of this algorithm is that for any block, when a plaintext-ciphertext pair is known, any key in the key space can satisfy the plaintext-ciphertext pair, that is, for each block, the plaintext-ciphertext pair and the key are independence, and the independence between blocks is also easy to construct. This feature is completely different from all existing short-key cipher algorithms. Based on the above feature, we construct a problem and theoretically prove that the problem satisfies the properties of one-way functions, thereby solving the problem of the existence of one-way functions, that is, directly proving that P != NP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2203.05022v5</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gao Ming</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shapley-Based Data Valuation with Mutual Information: A Key to Modified K-Nearest Neighbors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.01991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.01991v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The K-Nearest Neighbors (KNN) algorithm is widely used for classification and regression; however, it suffers from limitations, including the equal treatment of all samples. We propose Information-Modified KNN (IM-KNN), a novel approach that leverages Mutual Information ($\mathcal{I}$) and Shapley values to assign weighted values to neighbors, thereby bridging the gap in treating all samples with the same value and weight. On average, IM-KNN improves the accuracy, precision, and recall of traditional KNN by 16.80\%, 17.08\%, and 16.98\%, respectively, across 12 benchmark datasets. Experiments on four large-scale datasets further highlight IM-KNN's robustness to noise, imbalanced data, and skewed distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.01991v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Ali Vahedifar, Azim Akhtarshenas, Mohammad Mohammadi Rafatpanah, Maryam Sabbaghian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast and Scalable Beamforming for RIS-Assisted Downlink Multi-group Multicasting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.00594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.00594v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper considers downlink multi-group multicasting via beamforming facilitated by a reconfigurable intelligent surface (RIS). We develop a fast and scalable algorithm for the joint base station (BS) and RIS beamforming optimization to minimize the transmit power while meeting user quality-of-service (QoS) targets. By analyzing the structure of the QoS constraints, we reformulate the problem and show that the joint beamforming optimization inherently consists of a multicast beamforming QoS problem for the BS and a passive multicast beamforming max-min-fair (MMF) problem for the RIS. We propose a fast alternating multicast beamforming (AMBF) algorithm to effectively solve the two subproblems alternatingly. For the BS multicast subproblem, we utilize the optimal multicast beamforming structure to efficiently determine the BS beamformers. For the RIS multicast subproblem, we reformulate the MMF problem and apply a first-order projected subgradient algorithm (PSA), which yields simple closed-form updates. The computational complexity of the AMBF algorithm grows linearly with the number of RIS elements and BS antennas. We further consider joint BS and RIS beamforming for the weighted MMF design objective, subject to the BS transmit power budget. We propose an alternating PSA (APSA) fast algorithm to compute the beamforming solutions for the BS and RIS. APSA consists of only closed-form updates per iteration, yielding linear computational complexity in the number of RIS elements and BS antennas. Simulation results show the efficacy of our proposed algorithms in terms of performance and computational cost compared to alternative methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.00594v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Ebrahimi, Min Dong, Mitra Hekmat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matrix Majorization in Large Samples with Varying Support Restrictions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16581v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We say that a matrix $P$ with non-negative entries majorizes another such matrix $Q$ if there is a stochastic matrix $T$ such that $Q=TP$. We study matrix majorization in large samples and in the catalytic regime in the case where the columns of the matrices need not have equal support, as has been assumed in earlier works. We focus on two cases: either there are no support restrictions (except for requiring a non-empty intersection for the supports) or the final column dominates the others. Using real-algebraic methods, we identify sufficient and almost necessary conditions for majorization in large samples or when using catalytic states under these support conditions. These conditions are given in terms of multivariate divergences that generalize the R\'enyi divergences. We notice that varying support conditions dramatically affect the relevant set of divergences. Our results find an application in the theory of catalytic state transformation in quantum thermodynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16581v2</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TIT.2025.3585062</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Frits Verhagen, Marco Tomamichel, Erkka Haapasalo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous-variable designs and design-based shadow tomography from random lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17909v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate state designs for continuous-variable quantum systems using the aid of lattice-like quantum states. These are code states of Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill (GKP) codes. We show that for an n-mode system, the set of all GKP states forms a rigged continuous-variable state 2-design. We use these lattice state designs to construct a continuous variable shadow tomography protocol, derive sample complexity bounds for both global- and local GKP shadows under reasonable physical assumptions, and provide the physical gadgets needed to implement this protocol.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17909v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Conrad, Joseph T. Iosue, Ansgar G. Burchards, Victor V. Albert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Doeblin Coefficients: Interpretations and Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.22823v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In classical information theory, the Doeblin coefficient of a classical channel provides an efficiently computable upper bound on the total-variation contraction coefficient of the channel, leading to what is known as a strong data-processing inequality. Here, we investigate quantum Doeblin coefficients as a generalization of the classical concept. In particular, we define various new quantum Doeblin coefficients, one of which has several desirable properties, including concatenation and multiplicativity, in addition to being efficiently computable. We also develop various interpretations of two of the quantum Doeblin coefficients, including representations as minimal singlet fractions, exclusion values, reverse max-mutual and oveloH informations, reverse robustnesses, and hypothesis testing reverse mutual and oveloH informations. Our interpretations of quantum Doeblin coefficients as either entanglement-assisted or unassisted exclusion values are particularly appealing, indicating that they are proportional to the best possible error probabilities one could achieve in state-exclusion tasks by making use of the channel. We also outline various applications of quantum Doeblin coefficients, ranging from limitations on quantum machine learning algorithms that use parameterized quantum circuits (noise-induced barren plateaus), on error mitigation protocols, on the sample complexity of noisy quantum hypothesis testing, and on mixing, distinguishability, and decoupling times of time-varying channels. All of these applications make use of the fact that quantum Doeblin coefficients appear in upper bounds on various trace-distance contraction coefficients of a channel. Furthermore, in all of these applications, our analysis using Doeblin coefficients provides improvements of various kinds over contributions from prior literature, both in terms of generality and being efficiently computable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.22823v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian George, Christoph Hirche, Theshani Nuradha, Mark M. Wilde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-Complexity Frequency Domain Equalization of Zak-OTFS in Doubly-Spread Channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23045</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.23045v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We communicate over wireless channels by first estimating and then equalizing the effective channel. In Zak-OTFS (orthogonal time frequency space) modulation the carrier waveform is a pulse in the delay-Doppler (DD) domain, formally a quasi-periodic localized function with specific periods along delay and Doppler. When the channel delay spread is less than the delay period, and the channel Doppler spread is less than the Doppler period, the response to a single Zak-OTFS carrier provides an image of the scattering environment and can be used to predict the effective channel at all other carriers. This makes DD domain channel estimation straightforward, and there is no loss in spectral efficiency since it is possible to design data and pilot signals that are mutually unbiased. However, equalization in the DD domain has high complexity ${\mathcal O}(M^3N^3)$ where $M$, $N$ are respectively the number of delay and Doppler bins in an OTFS frame, and $MN$ is the number of information symbols.
  We demonstrate that equalization in the frequency domain (FD) reduces complexity to only ${\mathcal O}(M^2 N^2)$ by taking advantage of the banded structure of the effective FD channel. We also derive a low-complexity method to reconstruct the effective FD channel from the estimated DD domain effective channel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.23045v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saif Khan Mohammed, Sandesh Rao Mattu, Nishant Mehrotra, Venkatesh Khammammetti, Robert Calderbank</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A hierarchical invariant for line bundles and its applications in algebraic geometry codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01859</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.01859v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce the notion of hierarchical depth for line bundles on smooth projective surfaces, defined via filtrations by line subbundles with successive quotients supported on effective divisors. This invariant helps to investigate both the algebraic and geometric complexity of line bundles through discrete stepwise constructions. We study some of its basic properties, including functorial behavior under restriction to curves and compatibility with ampleness and base-point freeness. Applying this framework to algebraic geometry (AG) codes, we show that hierarchical filtrations yield natural code families whose combinatorial parameters (dimension, minimum distance) evolve predictably across the filtration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.01859v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rahim Rahmati-asghar</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
