<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.IT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.IT</link>
    <description>math.IT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.IT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 05:01:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Physical Layer Security in FAS-aided Wireless Powered NOMA Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09106v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The rapid evolution of communication technologies and the emergence of sixth-generation (6G) networks have introduced unprecedented opportunities for ultra-reliable, low-latency, and energy-efficient communication. However, the integration of advanced technologies like non-orthogonal multiple access (NOMA) and wireless powered communication networks (WPCNs) brings significant challenges, particularly in terms of energy constraints and security vulnerabilities. Traditional antenna systems and orthogonal multiple access schemes struggle to meet the increasing demands for performance and security in such environments. To address this gap, this paper investigates the impact of emerging fluid antenna systems (FAS) on the performance of physical layer security (PLS) in WPCNs. Specifically, we consider a scenario in which a transmitter, powered by a power beacon via an energy link, transmits confidential messages to legitimate FAS-aided users over information links while an external eavesdropper attempts to decode the transmitted signals. Additionally, users leverage the NOMA scheme, where the far user may also act as an internal eavesdropper. For the proposed model, we first derive the distributions of the equivalent channels at each node and subsequently obtain compact expressions for the secrecy outage probability (SOP) and average secrecy capacity (ASC), using the Gaussian quadrature methods. Our results reveal that incorporating the FAS for NOMA users, instead of the TAS, enhances the performance of the proposed secure WPCN.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09106v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Farshad Rostami Ghadi, Masoud Kaveh, Kai-Kit Wong, Diego Martin, Riku Jantti, Zheng Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Short-time Variational Mode Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09174v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Variational mode decomposition (VMD) and its extensions like Multivariate VMD (MVMD) decompose signals into ensembles of band-limited modes with narrow central frequencies. These methods utilize Fourier transformations to shift signals between time and frequency domains. However, since Fourier transformations span the entire time-domain signal, they are suboptimal for non-stationary time series.
  We introduce Short-Time Variational Mode Decomposition (STVMD), an innovative extension of the VMD algorithm that incorporates the Short-Time Fourier transform (STFT) to minimize the impact of local disturbances. STVMD segments signals into short time windows, converting these segments into the frequency domain. It then formulates a variational optimization problem to extract band-limited modes representing the windowed data. The optimization aims to minimize the sum of the bandwidths of these modes across the windowed data, extending the cost functions used in VMD and MVMD. Solutions are derived using the alternating direction method of multipliers, ensuring the extraction of modes with narrow bandwidths.
  STVMD is divided into dynamic and non-dynamic types, depending on whether the central frequencies vary with time. Our experiments show that non-dynamic STVMD is comparable to VMD with properly sized time windows, while dynamic STVMD better accommodates non-stationary signals, evidenced by reduced mode function errors and tracking of dynamic central frequencies. This effectiveness is validated by steady-state visual-evoked potentials in electroencephalogram signals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09174v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Jia, Pengfei Cao, Tong Liang, Cesar F. Caiafa, Zhe Sun, Yasuhiro Kushihashi, Grau A, Bolea Y, Feng Duan, Jordi Sole-Casals</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RIS-Aided Fluid Antenna Array-Mounted UAV Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09351</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09351v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates reconfigurable intelligent surface (RIS)-assisted unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV) downlink networks with fluid antennas (FA), where RIS enables non-line-of-sight (NLoS) transmissions. Moreover, the FA is equipped on the UAV offering dynamic antenna position adjustment, enhancing spatial diversity besides UAV deployment. We aim at total downlink rate maximization while ensuring minimum user rate requirement. We consider joint optimization of active UAV beamforming, passive RIS beamforming, UAV deployment and FA position adjustment. To address the complex problem, we propose beamfomring for RIS/UAV and FA-UAV deployment (BRAUD) scheme by employing alternative optimization, successive convex approximation (SCA) and sequential rank-one constraint relaxation (SROCR) method for the decomposed subproblems. Simulation results demonstrate the effectiveness of RIS-FA-UAV, achieving the highest rate among existing architectures without FA/UAV/RIS deployment and without proper beamforming. Moreover, BRAUD achieves the highest rate among benchmarks of drop-rank method, heuristic optimizations and conventional zero-forcing beamforming as well as random method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09351v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Li-Hsiang Shen, Yi-Hsuan Chiu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Revisit to Rate-distortion Problems via Optimal Weak Transport Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09362v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper revisits the rate-distortion theory from the perspective of optimal weak transport theory, as recently introduced by Gozlan et al. While the conditions for optimality and the existence of solutions are well-understood in the case of discrete alphabets, the extension to abstract alphabets requires more intricate analysis. Within the framework of weak transport problems, we derive a parametric representation of the rate-distortion function, thereby connecting the rate-distortion function with the Schr\"odinger bridge problem, and establish necessary conditions for its optimality. As a byproduct of our analysis, we reproduce K. Rose's conclusions regarding the achievability of Shannon lower bound concisely, without reliance on variational calculus.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09362v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiayang Zou, Luyao Fan, Jiayang Gao, Jia Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint Antenna Selection and Beamforming Design for Active RIS-aided ISAC Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09400v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Active reconfigurable intelligent surface (A-RIS) aided integrated sensing and communications (ISAC) system has been considered as a promising paradigm to improve spectrum efficiency. However, massive energy-hungry radio frequency (RF) chains hinder its large-scale deployment. To address this issue, an A-RIS-aided ISAC system with antenna selection (AS) is proposed in this work, where a target is sensed while multiple communication users are served with specifically selected antennas. Specifically, a cuckoo search-based scheme is first utilized to select the antennas associated with high-gain channels. Subsequently, with the properly selected antennas, the weighted sum-rate (WSR) of the system is optimized under the condition of radar probing power level, power budget for the A-RIS and transmitter. To solve the highly non-convex optimization problem, we develop an efficient algorithm based on weighted minimum mean square error (WMMSE) and fractional programming (FP). Simulation results show that the proposed AS scheme and the algorithm are effective, which reduce the number of RF chains without significant performance degradation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09400v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Ma, Peichang Zhang, Junjie Ye, Rouyang Guan, Xiao-Peng Li, Lei Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the distribution of the statistical sum related to BSC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09408</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09408v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The distribution function of the sum of i.i.d. random variables of the special form is considered. Such sum describes messages posterior probabilities for random coding in binary symmetric channel. Close non-asymptotic lower and upper bounds for that function are derived.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09408v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. V. Burnashev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RWZC: A Model-Driven Approach for Learning-based Robust Wyner-Ziv Coding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09520</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09520v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, a novel learning-based Wyner-Ziv coding framework is considered under a distributed image transmission scenario, where the correlated source is only available at the receiver. Unlike other learnable frameworks, our approach demonstrates robustness to non-stationary source correlation, where the overlapping information between image pairs varies. Specifically, we first model the affine relationship between correlated images and leverage this model for learnable mask generation and rate-adaptive joint source-channel coding. Moreover, we also provide a warping-prediction network to remove the distortion from channel interference and affine transform. Intuitively, the observed performance improvement is largely due to focusing on the simple geometric relationship, rather than the complex joint distribution between the sources. Numerical results show that our framework achieves a 1.5 dB gain in PSNR and a 0.2 improvement in MS-SSIM, along with a significant superiority in perceptual metrics, compared to state-of-the-art methods when applied to real-world samples with non-stationary correlations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09520v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxuan Shi, Shuo Shao, Yongpeng Wu, Wenjun Zhang, Merouane Debbah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On equidistant single-orbit cyclic and quasi-cyclic subspace codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09710v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A code is said to be equidistant if the distance between any two distinct codewords of the code is the same. In this paper, we have studied equidistant single-orbit cyclic and quasi-cyclic subspace codes. The orbit code generated by a subspace $U$ in $\mathbb{F}_{q^n}$ such that the dimension of $U$ over $\mathbb{F}_q$ is $t$ or $n-t$, $\mbox{where}~t=\dim_{\mathbb{F}_q}(\mbox{Stab}(U)\cup\{0\})$, is equidistant and is termed a trivial equidistant orbit code. Using the concept of cyclic difference sets, we have proved that only the trivial equidistant single-orbit cyclic subspace codes exist. Further, we have explored equidistant single-orbit quasi-cyclic subspace codes, focusing specifically on those which are sunflowers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09710v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Mahak, Maheshanand Bhaintwal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative Models with ELBOs Converging to Entropy Sums</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09022v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The evidence lower bound (ELBO) is one of the most central objectives for probabilistic unsupervised learning. For the ELBOs of several generative models and model classes, we here prove convergence to entropy sums. As one result, we provide a list of generative models for which entropy convergence has been shown, so far, along with the corresponding expressions for entropy sums. Our considerations include very prominent generative models such as probabilistic PCA, sigmoid belief nets or Gaussian mixture models. However, we treat more models and entire model classes such as general mixtures of exponential family distributions. Our main contributions are the proofs for the individual models. For each given model we show that the conditions stated in Theorem 1 or Theorem 2 of [arXiv:2209.03077] are fulfilled such that by virtue of the theorems the given model's ELBO is equal to an entropy sum at all stationary points. The equality of the ELBO at stationary points applies under realistic conditions: for finite numbers of data points, for model/data mismatches, at any stationary point including saddle points etc, and it applies for any well behaved family of variational distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09022v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Warnken, Dmytro Velychko, Simon Damm, Asja Fischer, J\"org L\"ucke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comprehensive Survey of QML: From Data Analysis to Algorithmic Advancements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09528v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum Machine Learning represents a paradigm shift at the intersection of Quantum Computing and Machine Learning, leveraging quantum phenomena such as superposition, entanglement, and quantum parallelism to address the limitations of classical approaches in processing high-dimensional and large-scale datasets. This survey provides a comprehensive analysis of Quantum Machine Learning, detailing foundational concepts, algorithmic advancements, and their applications across domains such as healthcare, finance, and quantum chemistry. Key techniques, including Quantum Support Vector Machine, Quantum Neural Network, Quantum Decision Trees, and hybrid quantum-classical models, are explored with a focus on their theoretical foundations, computational benefits, and comparative performance against classical counterparts. While the potential for exponential speedups and enhanced efficiency is evident, the field faces significant challenges, including hardware constraints, noise, and limited qubit coherence in the current era of Noisy Intermediate-Scale Quantum devices. Emerging solutions, such as error mitigation techniques, hybrid frameworks, and advancements in quantum hardware, are discussed as critical enablers for scalable and fault-tolerant Quantum Machine Learning systems. By synthesizing state-of-the-art developments and identifying research gaps, this survey aims to provide a foundational resource for advancing Quantum Machine Learning toward practical, real-world applications in tackling computationally intensive problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09528v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sahil Tomar, Rajeshwar Tripathi, Sandeep Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing hypergraph product codes with random walks, simulated annealing and reinforcement learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09622v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hypergraph products are quantum low-density parity-check (LDPC) codes constructed from two classical LDPC codes. Although their dimension and distance depend only on the parameters of the underlying classical codes, optimizing their performance against various noise channels remains challenging. This difficulty partly stems from the complexity of decoding in the quantum setting. The standard, ad hoc approach typically involves selecting classical LDPC codes with large girth. In this work, we focus on optimizing performance against the quantum erasure channel. A key advantage of this channel is the existence of an efficient maximum-likelihood decoder, which enables us to employ optimization techniques based on sampling random codes, such as Reinforcement Learning (RL) and Simulated Annealing (SA). Our results indicate that these techniques improve performance relative to the state-of-the-art.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09622v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruno C. A. Freire, Nicolas Delfosse, Anthony Leverrier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Converse bounds for quantum hypothesis exclusion: A divergence-radius approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09712v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hypothesis exclusion is an information-theoretic task in which an experimenter aims at ruling out a false hypothesis from a finite set of known candidates, and an error occurs if and only if the hypothesis being ruled out is the ground truth. For the tasks of quantum state exclusion and quantum channel exclusion -- where hypotheses are represented by quantum states and quantum channels, respectively -- efficiently computable upper bounds on the asymptotic error exponents were established in a recent work of the current authors [Ji et al., arXiv:2407.13728 (2024)], where the derivation was based on nonasymptotic analysis. In this companion paper of our previous work, we provide alternative proofs for the same upper bounds on the asymptotic error exponents of quantum state and channel exclusion, but using a conceptually different approach from the one adopted in the previous work. Specifically, we apply strong converse results for asymmetric binary hypothesis testing to distinguishing an arbitrary ``dummy'' hypothesis from each of the concerned candidates. This leads to the desired upper bounds in terms of divergence radii via a geometrically inspired argument.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09712v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaiyuan Ji, Hemant K. Mishra, Mil\'an Mosonyi, Mark M. Wilde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semantic Security with Infinite Dimensional Quantum Eavesdropping Channel</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.07663</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.07663v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a new proof method for direct coding theorems for wiretap channels where the eavesdropper has access to a quantum version of the transmitted signal on an infinite-dimensional Hilbert space and the legitimate parties communicate through a classical channel or a classical input, quantum output (cq) channel. The transmitter input can be subject to an additive cost constraint, which specializes to the case of an average energy constraint. This method yields errors that decay exponentially with increasing block lengths. Moreover, it provides a guarantee of a quantum version of semantic security, which is an established concept in classical cryptography and physical layer security. Therefore, it complements existing works which either do not prove the exponential error decay or use weaker notions of security. The main part of this proof method is a direct coding result on channel resolvability which states that there is only a doubly exponentially small probability that a standard random codebook does not solve the channel resolvability problem for the cq channel. Semantic security has strong operational implications meaning essentially that the eavesdropper cannot use its quantum observation to gather any meaningful information about the transmitted signal. We also discuss the connections between semantic security and various other established notions of secrecy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.07663v4</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthias Frey, Igor Bjelakovi\'c, Janis N\"otzel, S{\l}awomir Sta\'nczak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric Characteristics and Stable Guarantees for Phaseless Operators and Structured Matrix Restoration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17946v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we first propose a unified framework for analyzing the stability of the phaseless operators for both amplitude and intensity measurement on an arbitrary geometric set, thereby characterizing the robust performance of phase retrieval via the empirical minimization method. We introduce the random embedding of concave lifting operators to characterize the unified analysis of any geometric set. Similarly, we investigate the robust performance of structured matrix restoration problem through the robust injectivity of a linear rank one measurement operator on an arbitrary matrix set. The core of our analysis is to establish unified empirical chaos processes characterization for various matrix sets. Talagrand's $\gamma_{\alpha}$-functionals are employed to characterize the connection between the geometric constraints and the number of measurements required for stability or robust injectivity. We also construct adversarial noise to demonstrate the sharpness of the recovery bounds derived through the empirical minimization method in the both scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17946v5</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gao Huang, Song Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Latent Space Characterization of Autoencoder Variants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04755v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Understanding the latent spaces learned by deep learning models is crucial in exploring how they represent and generate complex data. Autoencoders (AEs) have played a key role in the area of representation learning, with numerous regularization techniques and training principles developed not only to enhance their ability to learn compact and robust representations, but also to reveal how different architectures influence the structure and smoothness of the lower-dimensional non-linear manifold. We strive to characterize the structure of the latent spaces learned by different autoencoders including convolutional autoencoders (CAEs), denoising autoencoders (DAEs), and variational autoencoders (VAEs) and how they change with the perturbations in the input. By characterizing the matrix manifolds corresponding to the latent spaces, we provide an explanation for the well-known observation that the latent spaces of CAE and DAE form non-smooth manifolds, while that of VAE forms a smooth manifold. We also map the points of the matrix manifold to a Hilbert space using distance preserving transforms and provide an alternate view in terms of the subspaces generated in the Hilbert space as a function of the distortion in the input. The results show that the latent manifolds of CAE and DAE are stratified with each stratum being a smooth product manifold, while the manifold of VAE is a smooth product manifold of two symmetric positive definite matrices and a symmetric positive semi-definite matrix.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04755v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anika Shrivastava, Renu Rameshan, Samar Agnihotri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information Sifting Funnel: Privacy-preserving Collaborative Inference Against Model Inversion Attacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00824v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The complexity of neural networks and inference tasks, coupled with demands for computational efficiency and real-time feedback, poses significant challenges for resource-constrained edge devices. Collaborative inference mitigates this by assigning shallow feature extraction to edge devices and offloading features to the cloud for further inference, reducing computational load. However, transmitted features remain susceptible to model inversion attacks (MIAs), which can reconstruct original input data. Current defenses, such as perturbation and information bottleneck techniques, offer explainable protection but face limitations, including the lack of standardized criteria for assessing MIA difficulty, challenges in mutual information estimation, and trade-offs among usability, privacy, and deployability.
  To address these challenges, we introduce the first criterion to evaluate MIA difficulty in collaborative inference, supported by theoretical analysis of existing attacks and defenses, validated using experiments with the Mutual Information Neural Estimator (MINE). Based on these findings, we propose SiftFunnel, a privacy-preserving framework for collaborative inference. The edge model is trained with linear and non-linear correlation constraints to reduce redundant information in transmitted features, enhancing privacy protection. Label smoothing and a cloud-based upsampling module are added to balance usability and privacy. To improve deployability, the edge model incorporates a funnel-shaped structure and attention mechanisms, preserving both privacy and usability. Extensive experiments demonstrate that SiftFunnel outperforms state-of-the-art defenses against MIAs, achieving superior privacy protection with less than 3% accuracy loss and striking an optimal balance among usability, privacy, and practicality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00824v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rongke Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
