<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 04:00:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Threshold (Q, P) Quantum Distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15274v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum distillation is the task of concentrating quantum correlations present in 'N' imperfect copies using free operations by involving all 'P' parties sharing the quantum correlations. We present a threshold quantum distillation task where the same objective is achieved but using fewer parties 'Q'. In particular, we give exact local filtering operations by the participating parties sharing a high-dimension multipartite GHZ or W state to distil the perfect quantum correlation. Specifically, an arbitrary GHZ state can be distilled using just one party in the network, as both the success probability of the distillation protocol and the fidelity after the distillation are independent of the number of parties. However, for a general W-state, at least 'P-1' parties are required for the distillation, indicating a strong relationship between the distillation and the separability of such states. Further, we connect threshold entanglement distillation and quantum steering distillation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15274v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shashank Gupta, William John Munro, Carlos Cid</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Initial Correlations and Time-Retarded Noise in Dynamical Decoupling Schemes for Superconducting Qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15277v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One of the simplest and least resource-intensive methods to suppress decoherence for superconducting qubit operations, namely, dynamical decoupling (DD), is investigated for a broad range of realistic noise sources with time-retarded feedback. By way of example, the Carr-Purcell-Meiboom-Gill (CPMG) sequence is analyzed in a numerically rigorous manner accounting also for correlations between qubit and environment. Since experimentally noise sources are characterized through spectral densities, we adopt the spin-boson model as a suitable platform to describe the qubit dynamics under DD for a given spectral density $J(\omega) \propto \omega^s$. To cover a broad range of noise sources, the spectral exponent $s$ is varied from $s=1$ (Ohmic bath) to a substantially small value $0 &lt; s \ll 1$ (deep sub-Ohmic bath), in order to investigate the impact of time-nonlocal back action on DD performances for enhanced coherence times. As reference to the DD schemes, dynamics of a single qubit subject to Ramsey sequences without any pules and Hahn echo (HE) sequences are also investigated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15277v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kiyoto Nakamura, Joachim Ankerhold</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-Powered Personalized Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15287</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15287v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper explores the transformative potential of quantum computing in the realm of personalized learning. Traditional machine learning models and GPU-based approaches have long been utilized to tailor educational experiences to individual student needs. However, these methods face significant challenges in terms of scalability, computational efficiency, and real-time adaptation to the dynamic nature of educational data. This study proposes leveraging quantum computing to address these limitations. We review existing personalized learning systems, classical machine learning methods, and emerging quantum computing applications in education. We then outline a protocol for data collection, privacy preservation using quantum techniques, and preprocessing, followed by the development and implementation of quantum algorithms specifically designed for personalized learning. Our findings indicate that quantum algorithms offer substantial improvements in efficiency, scalability, and personalization quality compared to classical methods. This paper discusses the implications of integrating quantum computing into educational systems, highlighting the potential for enhanced teaching methodologies, curriculum design, and overall student experiences. We conclude by summarizing the advantages of quantum computing in education and suggesting future research directions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15287v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Zhou, Chong Cheng Xu, Mingi Song, Yew Kee Wong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solution of Relativistic Feshbach-Villars Spin-1/2 Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15288v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose method for studying relativistic spin-$1/2$ particles by solving the corresponding Feshbach-Villars equation. We have found that the Feshbach-Villars spin-$1/2$ equations can be formulated as spin-coupled Feshbach-Villars spin-$0$ equations, that results in a Hamiltonian eigenvalue problem. We adopted an integral equation formalism. The potential operators are represented in a discrete Hilbert space basis and the relevant Green's operator has been calculated by a matrix continued fraction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15288v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Few-Body Systems, 65, 30 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>D. Wingard, A. Garcia Vallejo, Z. Papp</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-photon description of the lossless optical Y coupler</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15304v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using symmetry considerations, we derive a unitary scattering matrix for a three-port optical Y-coupler or Y-branch. The result is shown to be unique up to external phase shifts. Unlike traditional passive linear-optical one-way splitters, coupling light into the conventional output ports of the Y-coupler results in strong coherent back-reflections, making the device a hybrid between feed-forward devices like the beam splitter, which do not reverse the direction of light, and a recently considered class of directionally unbiased multiport scatterers (with dimension greater than two) which do. While the device could immediately find use as a novel scattering vertex for the implementation of quantum walks, we also design a few simple but nonetheless useful optical systems that can be constructed by taking advantage of the symmetry of the scattering process. This includes an interference-free, resource-efficient implementation of the Grover four-port and a higher-dimensional Fabry-Perot interferometer with tunable finesse. Symmetry-breaking generalizations are also considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15304v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.110.023527</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A, 110(2), 023527 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Christopher R. Schwarze, Anthony D. Manni, David S. Simon, Alexander V. Sergienko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuity bounds for quantum entropies arising from a fundamental entropic inequality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15306</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15306v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish a tight upper bound for the difference in von Neumann entropies between two quantum states, $\rho_1$ and $\rho_2$. This bound is expressed in terms of the von Neumann entropies of the mutually orthogonal states derived from the Jordan-Hahn decomposition of the difference operator $(\rho_1 - \rho_2)$. This yields a novel entropic inequality that implies the well-known Audenaert-Fannes inequality. We employ this inequality to obtain a uniform continuity bound for the quantum conditional entropy of two states whose marginals on the conditioning system coincide. We additionally use it to derive a continuity bound for the quantum relative entropy in both variables. Our proofs are largely based on majorization theory and convex optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15306v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koenraad Audenaert, Bjarne Bergh, Nilanjana Datta, Michael G. Jabbour, \'Angela Capel, Paul Gondolf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review: Quantum Metrology and Sensing with Many-Body Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15323</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15323v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The main power of quantum sensors is achieved when the probe is composed of several particles. In this situation, quantum features such as entanglement contribute in enhancing the precision of quantum sensors beyond the capacity of classical sensors. Originally, quantum sensing was formulated for non-interacting particles which are prepared in a special form of maximally entangled states. These probes are extremely sensitive to decoherence and any interaction between particles is detrimental to their performance. An alternative framework for quantum sensing has been developed exploiting quantum many-body systems, where the interaction between particles plays a crucial role. In this review, we investigate different aspects of the latter approach for quantum metrology and sensing. Many-body probes have been used in both equilibrium and non-equilibrium scenarios. Quantum criticality has been identified as a resource for achieving quantum enhanced sensitivity in both scenarios. In equilibrium, various types of criticalities, such as first order, second order, topological, and localization phase transitions have been exploited for sensing purposes. In non-equilibrium scenarios, quantum enhanced sensitivity has been discovered for Floquet, dissipative, and time crystal phase transitions. While each type of these criticalities has its own characteristics, the presence of one feature is crucial for achieving quantum enhanced sensitivity: the energy/quasi-energy gap closing. In non-equilibrium quantum sensing, time is another parameter which can affect the sensitivity of the probe. Typically, the sensitivity enhances as the probe evolves in time. In general, a more complete understanding of resources for non-equilibrium quantum sensors is now rapidly evolving. In this review, we provide an overview of recent progress in quantum metrology and sensing using many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15323v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Montenegro, Chiranjib Mukhopadhyay, Rozhin Yousefjani, Saubhik Sarkar, Utkarsh Mishra, Matteo G. A. Paris, Abolfazl Bayat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep thermalization under charge-conserving quantum dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15325v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: ``Deep thermalization'' describes the emergence of universal wavefunction distributions in quantum many-body dynamics, appearing on a local subsystem upon measurement of its environment. In this work, we study in detail the effect of continuous internal symmetries and associated conservation laws on deep thermalization. Concretely, we consider quantum spin systems with a $U(1)$ symmetry associated with the conservation of magnetization (or `charge'), and analyze how the choice of initial states (specifically, their degree of charge fluctuations) and the choice of measurement basis (specifically, whether or not it can reveal information about the local charge density) determine the ensuing universal wavefunction distributions. We find a rich set of possibilities. First we focus on the case of a random state of well-defined charge subjected to charge-revealing masurements, and rigorously prove that the projected ensemble approaches a direct sum of Haar ensembles in the charge sectors of the subsystem of interest. We then analytically derive the limiting wavefunction distributions for more general initial states and measurement bases, finding results that include the Haar ensemble, the ``Scrooge ensemble'' (a distortion of the Haar ensemble by a density matrix), and the ``generalized Scrooge ensemble'' (a stochastic mixture of multiple Scrooge ensembles). These represent nontrivial higher-moment generalizations of the Gibbs state, and notably can depend on the entire charge distribution of the initial state, not just its average. Our findings demonstrate a rich interplay between symmetries and the information extracted by measurements, which allows deep thermalization to exhibit a range of universal behaviors far beyond regular thermalization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15325v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rui-An Chang, Harshank Shrotriya, Wen Wei Ho, Matteo Ippoliti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Artificially intelligent Maxwell's demon for optimal control of open quantum systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15328</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15328v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Feedback control of open quantum systems is of fundamental importance for practical applications in various contexts, ranging from quantum computation to quantum error correction and quantum metrology. Its use in the context of thermodynamics further enables the study of the interplay between information and energy. However, deriving optimal feedback control strategies is highly challenging, as it involves the optimal control of open quantum systems, the stochastic nature of quantum measurement, and the inclusion of policies that maximize a long-term time- and trajectory-averaged goal. In this work, we employ a reinforcement learning approach to automate and capture the role of a quantum Maxwell's demon: the agent takes the literal role of discovering optimal feedback control strategies in qubit-based systems that maximize a trade-off between measurement-powered cooling and measurement efficiency. Considering weak or projective quantum measurements, we explore different regimes based on the ordering between the thermalization, the measurement, and the unitary feedback timescales, finding different and highly non-intuitive, yet interpretable, strategies. In the thermalization-dominated regime, we find strategies with elaborate finite-time thermalization protocols conditioned on measurement outcomes. In the measurement-dominated regime, we find that optimal strategies involve adaptively measuring different qubit observables reflecting the acquired information, and repeating multiple weak measurements until the quantum state is "sufficiently pure", leading to random walks in state space. Finally, we study the case when all timescales are comparable, finding new feedback control strategies that considerably outperform more intuitive ones. We discuss a two-qubit example where we explore the role of entanglement and conclude discussing the scaling of our results to quantum many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15328v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Andrea Erdman, Robert Czupryniak, Bibek Bhandari, Andrew N. Jordan, Frank No\'e, Jens Eisert, Giacomo Guarnieri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Site-selective cavity readout and classical error correction of a 5-bit atomic register</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15329v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optical cavities can provide fast and non-destructive readout of individual atomic qubits; however, scaling up to many qubits remains a challenge. Using locally addressed excited-state Stark shifts to tune atoms out of resonance, we realize site-selective hyperfine-state cavity readout across a 10-site array. The state discrimination fidelity is 0.994(1) for one atom and 0.989(2) averaged over the entire array at a survival probability of 0.975(1). To further speed up array readout, we demonstrate adaptive search strategies utilizing global/subset checks. Finally, we demonstrate repeated rounds of classical error correction, showing exponential suppression of logical error and extending logical memory fivefold beyond the single-bit idling lifetime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15329v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beili Hu, Josiah Sinclair, Edita Bytyqi, Michelle Chong, Alyssa Rudelis, Joshua Ramette, Zachary Vendeiro, Vladan Vuleti\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alternatives of entanglement depth and metrological entanglement criteria</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15350v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We work out the general theory of one-parameter families of partial entanglement properties and the resulting entanglement depth-like quantities. Special cases of these are the depth of partitionability, the depth of producibility (or simply entanglement depth) and the depth of stretchability, which are based on one-parameter families of partial entanglement properties known earlier. We also construct some further physically meaningful properties, for instance the squareability, the toughness, the degree of freedom, and also several ones of entropic motivation. Metrological multipartite entanglement criteria with the quantum Fisher information fit naturally into this framework. Here we formulate these for the depth of squareability, which therefore turns out to be the natural choice, leading to stronger bounds than the usual entanglement depth. Namely, the quantum Fisher information turns out to provide a lower bound not only on the maximal size of entangled subsystems, but also on the average size of entangled subsystems for a random choice of elementary subsystems. We also formulate convex criteria for both cases, which are much stronger than the original ones. This means that the aforementioned bounds hold also for the average in every decomposition of the quantum state. We also argue for that one-parameter partial entanglement properties bearing entropic meaning are more suitable for the purpose of defining metrological bounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15350v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Szil\'ard Szalay, G\'eza T\'oth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comprehensive explanation of ZZ coupling in superconducting qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15402v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A major challenge for scaling up superconducting quantum computers is unwanted couplings between qubits, which lead to always-on ZZ couplings that impact gate fidelities by shifting energy levels conditional on qubit states. To tackle this challenge, we introduce analytical and numerical techniques, including a diagrammatic perturbation theory and a state-assignment algorithm, as well as a refined intuitive picture for the workings of the ZZ coupling. Together, these tools enable a deeper understanding of the mechanisms behind the ZZ coupling and facilitate finding parameter regions of weak and strong ZZ coupling. We showcase these techniques for a system consisting of two fixed-frequency transmon qubits connected by a flux-tunable transmon coupler. There, we find three types of parameter regions with zero or near-zero ZZ coupling, all of which are accessible with current technology. We furthermore find regions of strong ZZ coupling nearby, which may be used to implement adiabatic controlled-phase gates. Our methods are applicable to many types of qubits and open up for the design of large-scale quantum computers with improved gate fidelities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15402v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Pettersson Fors, Jorge Fern\'andez-Pend\'as, Anton Frisk Kockum</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Effects of Small Graph Perturbations in the MaxCut Problem by QAOA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15413v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the Maximum Cut (MaxCut) problem on different graph classes with the Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) using symmetries. In particular, heuristics on the relationship between graph symmetries and the approximation ratio achieved by a QAOA simulation are considered. To do so, we first solve the MaxCut problem on well-known graphs, then we consider a simple and controllable perturbation of the graph and find again the approximate MaxCut with the QAOA. Through an analysis of the spectrum of the graphs and their perturbations, as well as a careful study of the associated automorphism groups, we aim to extract valuable insights into how symmetry impacts the performance of QAOA. These insights can then be leveraged to heuristically reduce the quantum circuit complexity, the number of training steps, or the number of parameters involved, thus enhancing the efficiency and effectiveness of QAOA-based solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15413v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonardo Lavagna, Simone Piperno, Andrea Ceschini, Massimo Panella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recent Advances in Semiclassical Methods Inspired by Supersymmetric Quantum Mechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15424v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Semiclassical methods are essential in analyzing quantum mechanical systems. Although they generally produce approximate results, relatively rare potentials exist for which these methods are exact. Such intriguing potentials serve as crucial test cases for semiclassical approximations. Recent research has demonstrated a deep connection between supersymmetric quantum mechanics and the exactness of semiclassical methods. Specifically, the mathematical form of conventional shape-invariant potentials guarantees exactness in several related situations. In this manuscript, we review these recent results and discuss their significance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15424v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Asim Gangopadhaya, Jonathan Bougie, Constantin Rasinariu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoherence and Brownian motion of a polarizable particle near a surface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15433</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15433v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We analyze the classical and quantized center-of-mass motion of a polarizable particle interacting with the fluctuations of the electromagnetic (EM) field in the presence of a medium. As a polarizable particle is immersed in a thermal environment, the momentum impulses imparted by the field fluctuations lead to momentum diffusion and drag for the particle's classical center of mass. When considering the quantized center-of-mass motion of the particle, these very fluctuations gain information about its position, leading to decoherence in the position basis. We derive a position localization master equation for the particle's quantized center of mass, and examine its classical center-of-mass momentum diffusion, elucidating correspondences between classical and quantum Brownian motion of polarizable particles near media.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15433v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Clemens Jakubec, Christopher Jarzynski, Kanu Sinha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Games and Synchronicity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15444v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the flavour of categorical quantum mechanics, we extend nonlocal games to allow quantum questions and answers, using quantum sets (special symmetric dagger Frobenius algebras) and the quantum functions of arXiv:1711.07945. Equations are presented using a diagrammatic calculus for tensor categories. To this quantum question and answer setting, we extend the standard definitions, including strategies, correlations, and synchronicity, and we use these definitions to extend results about synchronicity. We extend the graph homomorphism (isomorphism) game to quantum graphs, and show it is synchronous (bisynchronous) and that its perfect quantum-commuting (bi)strategies are quantum graph homomorphisms (isomorphisms). Our extended definitions agree with the existing quantum games literature, except in the case of synchronicity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15444v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adina Goldberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimating QSVT angles for matrix inversion with large condition numbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15453v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum Singular Value Transformation (QSVT) is a state-of-the-art, near-optimal quantum algorithm that can be used for matrix inversion. The QSVT circuit is parameterized by a sequence of angles that must be pre-calculated classically, with the number of angles increasing as the matrix condition number grows. Computing QSVT angles for ill-conditioned problems is a numerically challenging task. We propose a numerical technique for estimating QSVT angles for large condition numbers. This technique allows one to avoid expensive numerical computations of QSVT angles and to emulate QSVT circuits for solving ill-conditioned problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15453v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. Novikau, I. Joseph</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy conservation and quantum backreaction in Bose-Einstein condensates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15455</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15455v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bose-Einstein condensates are suitable systems for studying fundamental aspects of quantum backreaction. Here the backreaction problem in 1D condensates is considered from the perspective of energy and momentum conservation. By assuming the validity of Bogoliubov theory, the backreaction equations are used to identify the contributions to the system energy and momentum coming from quantum fluctuations and condensate corrections. The backreaction is solved for a condensate trapped in a ring configuration and such that particle interactions are continuously switched on. It is shown that the energy in the condensate cannot be addressed without taking into account how the system entered the interacting regime, and even for homogeneous condensates the power transferred to the condensate by quantum fluctuations showcases an intricate non-monotonic pattern.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15455v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Caio C. Holanda Ribeiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical modeling of quantum error propagation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15459v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, I design a new statistical abstract model for studying quantum error propagation. For each circuit, I give the algorithm to construct the Error propagation space-time graph(\textbf{EPSTG}) graph as well as the bipartite reverse spanning graph (\textbf{RSG}). Then I prove that the problem of finding an error pattern is $\mathcal{P}$ while calculate the error number distribution is $\textit{NP-complete}$. I invent the new measure for error propagation and show that for widely used transversal $CNOT$ circuit in parallel, the shift of distribution is bounded by $\frac{n}{27}$, where $n$ is the number of physical qubits. The consistency between the result of qiskit simulation and my algorithm justify the correctness of my model. Applying the framework to random circuit, I show that there is severe unbounded error propagation when circuit has global connection. We also apply my framework on parallel transversal logical $CNOT$ gate in surface code, and demonstrate that the error threshold will decrease from $0.231$ to $0.134$ per cycle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15459v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhuoyang Ye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CTRQNets &amp; LQNets: Continuous Time Recurrent and Liquid Quantum Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15462v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Neural networks have continued to gain prevalence in the modern era for their ability to model complex data through pattern recognition and behavior remodeling. However, the static construction of traditional neural networks inhibits dynamic intelligence. This makes them inflexible to temporal changes in data and unfit to capture complex dependencies. With the advent of quantum technology, there has been significant progress in creating quantum algorithms. In recent years, researchers have developed quantum neural networks that leverage the capabilities of qubits to outperform classical networks. However, their current formulation exhibits a static construction limiting the system's dynamic intelligence. To address these weaknesses, we develop a Liquid Quantum Neural Network (LQNet) and a Continuous Time Recurrent Quantum Neural Network (CTRQNet). Both models demonstrate a significant improvement in accuracy compared to existing quantum neural networks (QNNs), achieving accuracy increases as high as 40\% on CIFAR 10 through binary classification. We propose LQNets and CTRQNets might shine a light on quantum machine learning's black box.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15462v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alejandro Mayorga, Alexander Yuan, Andrew Yuan, Tyler Wooldridge, Xiaodi Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Casimir Effects: The Need for Nonlocality in Time-Varying Dispersive Nanophotonics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15504</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15504v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Both real and virtual photons can be involved in light-matter interactions. A famous example of the observable implications of virtual photons -- vacuum fluctuations of the quantum electromagnetic field -- is the Casimir effect. Since quantum vacuum effects are weak, various mechanisms have been proposed to enhance and engineer them, ranging from static, e.g., strong optical resonances, to dynamic, e.g., systems with moving boundaries or time-varying optical properties, or a combination of them. In this Letter, we discuss the role of material nonlocality (spatial dispersion) in dynamical Casimir effects in time-varying frequency-dispersive nanophotonic systems. We first show that local models may lead to nonphysical predictions, such as diverging emission rates of entangled polariton pairs. We then theoretically demonstrate that nonlocality regularizes this behavior by correcting the asymptotic response of the system for large wavevectors and reveals physical effects missed by local models, including a significant broadening of the emission rate distribution, which are relevant for future experimental observations. Our work sheds light on the importance of nonlocal effects in this new frontier of nanophotonics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15504v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Ali Hassani Gangaraj, George Hanson, Francesco Monticone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Purity and construction of arbitrary dimensional $k$-uniform mixed states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15515v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: k-uniform mixed states are a significant class of states characterized by all k-party reduced states being maximally mixed. Novel methodologies are constructed for constructing k-uniform mixed states with the highest possible purity. By using the orthogonal partition of orthogonal arrays, a series of new $k$-uniform mixed states is derived. Consequently, an infinite number of higher-dimensional k-uniform mixed states, including those with highest purity, can be generated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15515v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/qute.202400245</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Adv. Quantum Technol. 2024, 2400245</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiao Zhang, Shanqi Pang, Shao-Ming Fei, Zhu-Jun Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rabi oscillations and entanglement between two atoms interacting by the Rydberg blockade and with a quantized radiation field studied by the Jaynes-Cummings Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15523v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The interaction between atoms and a quantized radiation field is fundamentally important in quantum optics and quantum information science. Due to their unusual properties, Rydberg atoms are promising building blocks for two-qubit gates and atom-light quantum interfaces, exploiting the Rydberg blockade interaction which prevents two atoms at close distance from being simultaneously excited to Rydberg states. Recently, this effect was used to engineer quantum processors based on arrays of interacting Rydberg atoms illuminated by Raman lasers. Motivated by these experiments, we extend the Jaynes-Cummings model to study the interaction between two Rydberg atoms interacting by the Rydberg blockade and a quantized radiation field. We find a rich variety of Rabi oscillations and entanglement between the atoms and the radiation field as a function of initial conditions and interaction time, which may be used to obtain atom-light quantum interfaces as components for future long-distance quantum communication.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15523v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francisco D. Santillan, Andreas Hanke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-Lindblad pseudomode theory for open quantum systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15529v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a new framework to study the dynamics of open quantum systems with linearly coupled Gaussian baths. Our approach replaces the continuous bath with an auxiliary discrete set of pseudomodes with dissipative dynamics, but we further relax the complete positivity requirement in the Lindblad master equation and formulate a quasi-Lindblad pseudomode theory. We show that this quasi-Lindblad pseudomode formulation directly leads to a representation of the bath correlation function in terms of a complex weighted sum of complex exponentials, an expansion that is known to be rapidly convergent in practice and thus leads to a compact set of pseudomodes. The pseudomode representation is not unique and can differ by a gauge choice. When the global dynamics can be simulated exactly, the system dynamics is unique and independent of the specific pseudomode representation. However, the gauge choice may affect the stability of the global dynamics, and we provide an analysis of why and when the global dynamics can retain stability despite losing positivity. We showcase the performance of this formulation across various spectral densities in both bosonic and fermionic problems, finding significant improvements over conventional pseudomode formulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15529v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gunhee Park, Zhen Huang, Yuanran Zhu, Chao Yang, Garnet Kin-Lic Chan, Lin Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Assemblage Tomography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15576v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A central requirement in asymmetric quantum nonlocality protocols, such as quantum steering, is the precise reconstruction of state assemblages -- statistical ensembles of quantum states correlated with remote classical signals. Here we introduce a generalized loss model for assemblage tomography that uses conical optimization techniques combined with maximum likelihood estimation. Using an evidence-based framework based on Akaike's Information Criterion, we demonstrate that our approach excels in the accuracy of reconstructions while accounting for model complexity. In comparison, standard tomographic methods fall short when applied to experimentally relevant data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15576v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luis Villegas-Aguilar, Yuanlong Wang, Alex Pepper, Travis J. Baker, Geoff J. Pryde, Sergei Slussarenko, Nora Tischler, Howard M. Wiseman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipation-driven quantum generative adversarial networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15597v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum machine learning holds the promise of harnessing quantum advantage to achieve speedup beyond classical algorithms. Concurrently, research indicates that dissipation can serve as an effective resource in quantum computation. In this paper, we introduce a novel dissipation-driven quantum generative adversarial network (DQGAN) architecture specifically tailored for generating classical data. Our DQGAN comprises two interacting networks: a generative network and a discriminative network, both constructed from qubits. The classical data is encoded into the input qubits of the input layer via strong tailored dissipation processes. This encoding scheme enables us to extract both the generated data and the classification results by measuring the observables of the steady state of the output qubits. The network coupling weight, i.e., the strength of the interaction Hamiltonian between layers, is iteratively updated during the training process. This training procedure closely resembles the training of conventional generative adversarial networks (GANs). By alternately updating the two networks, we foster adversarial learning until the equilibrium point is reached. Our preliminary numerical test on a simplified instance of the task substantiate the feasibility of our DQGAN model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15597v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>He Wang, Jin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Circuit Implementation of Discrete-Time Quantum Walks on Complex Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15653</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15653v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a circuit design for implementing quantum walks on complex networks. Quantum walks are powerful tools for various graph-based applications such as spatial search, community detection, and node classification. Although many quantum-walk-based graph algorithms have been extensively studied, specific quantum circuits for implementing these algorithms have not yet been provided. To address this issue, we present a circuit design for implementing the discrete-time quantum walk on complex networks. We investigate the functionality of our circuit using the small-sized Watts-and-Strogatz model as the complex network model, comparing it with theoretical calculations. This work offers a new approach to constructing quantum circuits for implementing quantum walks on arbitrary complex networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15653v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rei Sato, Kazuhiro Saito</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluation of Quantum Annealing-based algorithms for flexible job shop scheduling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15671v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A flexible job shop scheduling problem (FJSSP) poses a complex optimization task in modeling real-world process scheduling tasks with conflicting objectives. To tackle FJSSPs, approximation methods are employed to ensure solutions are within acceptable timeframes. Quantum Annealing, a metaheuristic leveraging quantum mechanical effects, demonstrates superior solution quality in a shorter time compared to classical algorithms. However, due to hardware limitations of quantum annealers, hybrid algorithms become essential for solving larger FJSSPs. This paper investigates the threshold problem sizes up to which quantum annealers are sufficient and when hybrid algorithms are required, highlighting the distribution of computing power in hybrid methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15671v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philipp Schworm, Xiangqian Wu, Matthias Klar, Jan C. Aurich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strongly interacting fermions are non-trivial yet non-glassy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15699</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15699v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Random spin systems at low temperatures are glassy and feature computational hardness in finding low-energy states. We study the random all-to-all interacting fermionic Sachdev--Ye--Kitaev (SYK) model and prove that, in contrast, (I) the low-energy states have polynomial circuit depth, yet (II) the annealed and quenched free energies agree to inverse-polynomially low temperatures, ruling out a glassy phase transition in this sense. These results are derived by showing that fermionic and spin systems significantly differ in their \emph{commutation index}, which quantifies the non-commutativity of Hamiltonian terms. Our results suggest that low-temperature strongly interacting fermions, unlike spins, belong in a classically nontrivial yet quantumly easy phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15699v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric R. Anshuetz, Chi-Fang Chen, Bobak T. Kiani, Robbie King</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance of Cascade and LDPC-codes for Information Reconciliation on Industrial Quantum Key Distribution Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15758</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15758v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Information Reconciliation is a critical component of Quantum Key Distribution, ensuring that mismatches between Alice's and Bob's keys are corrected. In this study, we analyze, simulate, optimize, and compare the performance of two prevalent algorithms used for Information Reconciliation: Cascade and LDPC codes in combination with the Blind protocol. We focus on their applicability in practical and industrial settings, operating in realistic and application-close conditions. The results are further validated through evaluation on a live industrial QKD system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15758v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ronny M\"uller, Claudia De Lazzari, Fernando Chirici, Ilaria Vagniluca, Leif Katsuo Oxenl{\o}we, S{\o}ren Forchhammer, Alessandro Zavatta, Davide Bacco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Determining non-Hermitian parent Hamiltonian from a single eigenstate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15781v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A quantum state for being an eigenstate of some local Hamiltonian should be constraint by zero energy variance and consequently, the constraint is rather strong that a single eigenstate may uniquely determine the Hamiltonian. For non-Hermitian systems, it is natural to expect that determining the Hamiltonian requires a pair of both left and right eigenstates. Here, we observe that it can be sufficient to determine a non-Hermitian Hamiltonian from a single right or left eigenstate. Our approach is based on the quantum covariance matrix, where the solution of Hamiltonian corresponds to the complex null vector. Our scheme favours non-Hermitian Hamiltonian learning on experimental quantum systems, as only the right eigenstates there can be accessed. Furthermore, we use numerical simulations to examine the effects of measurement errors and show the stability of our scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15781v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xu-Dan Xie, Zheng-Yuan Xue, Dan-Bo Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Certifying high-dimensional quantum channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15880</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15880v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The use of high-dimensional systems for quantum communication opens interesting perspectives, such as increased information capacity and noise resilience. In this context, it is crucial to certify that a given quantum channel can reliably transmit high-dimensional quantum information. Here we develop efficient methods for the characterization of high-dimensional quantum channels. We first present a notion of dimensionality of quantum channels, and develop efficient certification methods for this quantity. We consider a simple prepare-and-measure setup, and provide witnesses for both a fully and a partially trusted scenario. In turn we apply these methods to a photonic experiment and certify dimensionalities up to 59 for a commercial graded-index multi-mode optical fiber. Moreover, we present extensive numerical simulations of the experiment, providing an accurate noise model for the fiber and exploring the potential of more sophisticated witnesses. Our work demonstrates the efficient characterization of high-dimensional quantum channels, a key ingredient for future quantum communication technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15880v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sophie Engineer, Suraj Goel, Sophie Egelhaaf, Will McCutcheon, Vatshal Srivastav, Saroch Leedumrongwatthanakun, Sabine Wollmann, Ben Jones, Thomas Cope, Nicolas Brunner, Roope Uola, Mehul Malik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymmetry Amplification by a Nonadiabatic Passage through a Critical Point</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15897</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15897v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose and solve a minimal model of dynamic passage through a quantum second order phase transition in the presence of weak symmetry breaking interactions and no dissipation. The evolution eventually leads to a highly asymmetric state, no matter how weak the symmetry breaking term is. This suggests a potential mechanism for strong asymmetry in the production of particles with almost identical characteristics. The model's integrability also allows us to obtain exact Kibble-Zurek exponents for the scaling of the number of nonadiabatic excitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15897v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bhavay Tyagi, Fumika Suzuki, Vladimir A. Chernyak, Nikolai A. Sinitsyn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beating the Ramsey limit on sensing with deterministic qubit control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15926</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15926v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum sensors promise revolutionary advances in medical imaging, energy production, mass detection, geodesy, foundational physics research, and a host of other fields. In many sensors, the signal takes the form of a changing qubit frequency, which is detected with an interference measurement. Unfortunately, environmental noise decoheres the qubit state, reducing signal-to-noise ratio (SNR). Here we introduce a protocol for enhancing the sensitivity of a measurement of a qubit's frequency in the presence of decoherence. We use a continuous drive to stabilize one component of the qubit's Bloch vector, enhancing the effect of a small static frequency shift. We demonstrate our protocol on a superconducting qubit, enhancing SNR per measurement shot by 1.65$\times$ and SNR per qubit evolution time by 1.09$\times$ compared to standard Ramsey interferometry. We explore the protocol theoretically and numerically, finding maximum enhancements of 1.96$\times$ and 1.18$\times$, respectively. We also show that the protocol is robust to parameter miscalibrations. Our protocol provides an unconditional enhancement in signal-to-noise ratio compared to standard Ramsey interferometry. It requires no feedback and no extra control or measurement resources, and can be immediately applied in a wide variety of quantum computing and quantum sensor technologies to enhance their sensitivities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15926v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. O. Hecht, Kumar Saurav, Evangelos Vlachos, Daniel A. Lidar, Eli M. Levenson-Falk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observing Time-Dependent Energy Level Renormalisation in an Ultrastrongly Coupled Open System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15928v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding how strong coupling and memory effects influence the energy levels of open quantum systems is a complex and challenging problem. Here, we show these effects by probing the transition frequency of an open two-level system within the Jaynes-Cummings model, experimentally realised using Ramsey interferometry in a single trapped 25Mg+ ion. Measurements of the system, coupled to a single-mode environment, reveal a time-dependent shift in the system's energy levels of up to 15% of the bare system frequency. This shift, accurately predicted using an open system ansatz of minimal dissipation, results purely from ultra-strong system-mode interactions and the buildup of correlations. Time-averaged measurements converge to the dispersive Lamb shift predictions and match dressed-state energies, indicating that this observed shift represents a generalised Lamb shift applicable across all coupling and detuning regimes. Our findings provide direct evidence of dynamic energy level renormalisation in strongly coupled open quantum systems, although the total system-environment Hamiltonian is static; this underscores the significance of memory effects in shaping the reduced system's energy landscape. These results offer more profound insights into Hamiltonian renormalisation, essential for strong-coupling quantum thermodynamics and advancements in all quantum platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15928v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandra Colla, Florian Hasse, Deviprasath Palani, Tobias Schaetz, Heinz-Peter Breuer, Ulrich Warring</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flow of non-classical correlations in cluster states due to projective measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15930</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15930v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the flow of quantum correlations in cluster states defined on ladder type graphs as measurements are done on qubits located on the nodes of the cluster. We focus on three qubits at the end of the ladder and compute the non-classical correlations between two of the three qubits as measurements are done on the remaining qubits. We compute both the entanglement between the two qubits as well as the quantum discord between them after the measurements. We see that after all but three qubits are measured, the non-classical correlations developed between two of them show a trend of being stronger with the length of the ladder. It is also seen that measurements on to the basis states of operators belonging to the Clifford group do not produce such correlations or entanglement. The non-classical correlations produced depend only on the number, location and nature of preceding non-Clifford measurements. Our results not only throw light on the dynamics of quantum correlations while an algorithm proceeds step-by-step in the Measurement-based Based Quantum Computing (MBQC) model but it also reveals how the last two qubits, treated as an open quantum system, can have increasing entanglement or other non-classical correlations as its immediate environment is interrogated through random measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15930v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chandan Mahto, Anil Shaji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast quantum interconnects via constant-rate entanglement distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15936</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15936v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Distributed quantum computing allows the modular construction of large-scale quantum computers and enables new protocols for blind quantum computation. However, such applications in the large-scale, fault-tolerant regime place stringent demands on the fidelity and rate of entanglement generation which are not met by existing methods for quantum interconnects. In this work, we develop constant-rate entanglement distillation methods to address this bottleneck in the setting of noisy local operations. By using a sequence of two-way entanglement distillation protocols based on quantum error detecting codes with increasing rate, and combining with standard fault tolerance techniques, we achieve constant-rate entanglement distillation. We prove the scheme has constant-rate in expectation and further numerically optimize to achieve low practical overhead subject to memory constraints. We find our optimized schemes outperform existing computationally efficient quantum interconnect schemes by an order of magnitude in relevant regimes, leading to a direct speed-up in the execution of distributed quantum algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15936v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher A. Pattison, Gefen Baranes, J. Pablo Bonilla Ataides, Mikhail D. Lukin, Hengyun Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase kickback in quantum Recursive Fourier Sampling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15938v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recursive Fourier Sampling (RFS) is one of the earliest problems demonstrating a quantum advantage, and is known to lie outside the Merlin-Arthur complexity class. This paper contains a description of the phenomenon of phase kickback and its use in RFS, and how and why this is the enabling quantum computational property for the quantum advantage in RFS. Most importantly, describing the computational process of quantum computation in the terminology of phase kickback gives a much better understanding of why uncomputation is necessary when solving RFS, pointing to the underlying reason for the limitations of the quantum advantage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15938v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christoffer Hindlycke, Niklas Johansson, Jan-{\AA}ke Larsson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mid-infrared characterization of NbTiN superconducting nanowire single-photon detectors on silicon-on-insulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15959v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Superconducting nanowire single-photon detectors are widely used for detecting individual photons across various wavelengths from ultraviolet to near-infrared range. Recently, there has been increasing interest in enhancing their sensitivity to single photons in the mid-infrared spectrum, driven by applications in quantum communication, spectroscopy and astrophysics. Here, we present our efforts to expand the spectral detection capabilities of U-shaped NbTiN-based superconducting nanowire single-photon detectors, fabricated in a 2-wire configuration on a silicon-on-insulator substrate, into the mid-infrared range. We demonstrate saturated internal detection efficiency extending up to a wavelength of 3.5 {\mu}m for a 5 nm thick and 50 nm wide NbTiN nanowire with a dark count rate less than 10 counts per second at 0.9 K and a rapid recovery time of 4.3 ns. The detectors are engineered for integration on waveguides in a silicon-on-insulator platform for compact, multi-channel device applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15959v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adan Azem, Dmitry V. Morozov, Daniel Kuznesof, Ciro Bruscino, Robert H. Hadfield, Lukas Chrostowski, Jeff F. Young</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic Foliations: Self-Similar Quasicrystals from Hyperbolic Honeycombs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15316v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Discrete geometries in hyperbolic space are of longstanding interest in pure mathematics and have come to recent attention in holography, quantum information, and condensed matter physics. Working at a purely geometric level, we describe how any regular tessellation of ($d+1$)-dimensional hyperbolic space naturally admits a $d$-dimensional boundary geometry with self-similar ''quasicrystalline'' properties. In particular, the boundary geometry is described by a local, invertible, self-similar substitution tiling, that discretizes conformal geometry. We greatly refine an earlier description of these local substitution rules that appear in the 1D/2D example and use the refinement to give the first extension to higher dimensional bulks; including a detailed account for all regular 3D hyperbolic tessellations. We comment on global issues, including the reconstruction of bulk geometries from boundary data, and introduce the notion of a ''holographic foliation'': a foliation by a stack of self-similar quasicrystals, where the full geometry of the bulk (and of the foliation itself) is encoded in any single leaf in a local invertible way. In the $\{3,5,3\}$ tessellation of 3D hyperbolic space by regular icosahedra, we find a 2D boundary quasicrystal admitting points of 5-fold symmetry which is not the Penrose tiling, and record and comment on a related conjecture of William Thurston. We end with a large list of open questions for future analytic and numerical studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15316v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Latham Boyle, Justin Kulp</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Models of interacting bosons with exact ground states: a unified approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15319v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We define an infinite class of ``frustration-free'' interacting lattice quantum Hamiltonians for number-conserving bosons, constructed such that their exact ground states have a density distribution specified by the Boltzmann weight of a corresponding classical lattice gas problem. By appropriately choosing the classical weights, we obtain boson representations of various known solvable models, including quantum dimer models and certain Levin-Wen string-net models, and we also systematically construct solvable models with other interesting ground states, including ``quantum spin liquids,'' supersolids, ``Bose-Einstein insulators,'' Bose liquids with ``Bose surfaces'', and Bose-Einstein condensates that permit adiabatic evolution from a non-interacting limit to a Gutzwiller-projected limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15319v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhaoyu Han, Steven A. Kivelson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultralight dark matter detection with levitated ferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15330v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Levitated ferromagnets act as ultraprecise magnetometers, which can exhibit high quality factors due to their excellent isolation from the environment. These instruments can be utilized in searches for ultralight dark matter candidates, such as axionlike dark matter or dark-photon dark matter. In addition to being sensitive to an axion-photon coupling or kinetic mixing, which produce physical magnetic fields, ferromagnets are also sensitive to the effective magnetic field (or ``axion wind") produced by an axion-electron coupling. While the dynamics of a levitated ferromagnet in response to a DC magnetic field have been well studied, all of these couplings would produce AC fields. In this work, we study the response of a ferromagnet to an applied AC magnetic field and use these results to project their sensitivity to axion and dark-photon dark matter. We pay special attention to the direction of motion induced by an applied AC field, in particular, whether it precesses around the applied field (similar to an electron spin) or librates in the plane of the field (similar to a compass needle). We show that existing levitated ferromagnet setups can already have comparable sensitivity to an axion-electron coupling as comagnetometer or torsion balance experiments. In addition, future setups can become sensitive probes of axion-electron coupling, dark-photon kinetic mixing, and axion-photon coupling, for ultralight dark matter masses $m_\mathrm{DM}\lesssim\mathrm{feV}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15330v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saarik Kalia, Dmitry Budker, Derek F. Jackson Kimball, Wei Ji, Zhen Liu, Alexander O. Sushkov, Chris Timberlake, Hendrik Ulbricht, Andrea Vinante, Tao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying Light-assisted Collisions in Optical Tweezers Across the Hyperfine Spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15359v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the role of hyperfine structure in resonant-dipole interactions between two atoms co-trapped in an optical tweezer. Two-body loss rates from light-assisted collisions (LACs) are measured across the $^{87}$Rb hyperfine spectrum and connected to properties of molecular photoassociation potentials via a semi-classical model. To obtain our results, we introduce an imaging technique that leverages repulsive LACs to detect two atoms in a trap, thereby circumventing parity constraints in tweezers. Our findings offer key insights for exploiting hyperfine structure in laser-induced collisions to control cold atoms and molecules in a broad range of quantum science applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15359v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steven K. Pampel, Matteo Marinelli, Mark O. Brown, Jos\'e P. D'Incao, Cindy A. Regal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-shot latched readout of a quantum dot qubit using barrier gate pulsing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15380v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Latching techniques are widely used to enhance readout of qubits. These methods require precise tuning of multiple tunnel rates, which can be challenging to achieve under realistic experimental conditions, such as when a qubit is coupled to a single reservoir. Here, we present a method for single-shot measurement of a quantum dot qubit with a single reservoir using a latched-readout scheme. Our approach involves pulsing a barrier gate to dynamically control qubit-to-reservoir tunnel rates, a method that is readily applicable to the latched readout of various spin-based qubits. We use this method to enable qubit state latching and to reduce the qubit reset time in measurements of coherent Larmor oscillations of a Si/SiGe quantum dot hybrid qubit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15380v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanghyeok Park, Jared Benson, J. Corrigan, J. P. Dodson, S. N. Coppersmith, Mark Friesen, M. A. Eriksson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct sum theorems beyond query complexity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15570v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A fundamental question in computer science is: \emph{Is it harder to solve $n$ instances independently than to solve them simultaneously?} This question, known as the direct sum question or direct sum theorem, has been paid much attention in several research fields. Despite its importance, however, little has been discovered in many other research fields.
  In this paper, we introduce a novel framework that extends to classical/quantum query complexity, PAC-learning for machine learning, statistical estimation theory, and more. Within this framework, we establish several fundamental direct sum theorems. The main contributions of this paper include: (i) establishing a complete characterization of the amortized query/oracle complexities, and (ii) proving tight direct sum theorems when the error is small. Note that in our framework, every oracle access needs to be performed \emph{classically} even in the quantum setting. This can be thought of one limitation of this work.
  As a direct consequence of our results, we obtain the following: (A) The first known asymptotic separation of the randomized query complexity. Specifically, we show that there is a function $f: \{0, 1\}^k \to \{0, 1\}$ and small error $\varepsilon &gt; 0$ such that solving $n$ instances simultaneously requires the query complexity $\tilde{O}(n\sqrt{k})$ but solving one instance with the same error has the complexity $\tilde{\Omega}(k)$. In communication complexity this type of separation was previously given in~Feder, Kushilevitz, Naor and Nisan (1995). (B) The query complexity counterpart of the ``information = amortized communication" relation, one of the most influential results in communication complexity shown by Braverman and Rao (2011) and further investigated by Braverman (2015).
  We hope that our results will provide further interesting applications in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15570v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daiki Suruga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-dependent exotic interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15691v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Novel interactions beyond the four known fundamental forces in nature (electromagnetic, gravitational, strong and weak interactions), may arise due to "new physics" beyond the standard model, manifesting as a "fifth force". This review is focused on spin-dependent fifth forces mediated by exotic bosons such as spin-0 axions and axionlike particles and spin-1 Z' bosons, dark photons, or paraphotons. Many of these exotic bosons are candidates to explain the nature of dark matter and dark energy, and their interactions may violate fundamental symmetries. Spin-dependent interactions between fermions mediated by the exchange of exotic bosons have been investigated in a variety of experiments, particularly at the low-energy frontier. Experimental methods and tools used to search for exotic spin-dependent interactions, such as atomic comagnetometers, torsion balances, nitrogen-vacancy spin sensors, and precision atomic and molecular spectroscopy, are described. A complete set of interaction potentials, derived based on quantum field theory with minimal assumptions and characterized in terms of reduced coupling constants, are presented. A comprehensive summary of existing experimental and observational constraints on exotic spin-dependent interactions is given, illustrating the current research landscape and promising directions of further research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15691v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Cong, Wei Ji, Pavel Fadeev, Filip Ficek, Min Jiang, Victor V. Flambaum, Haosen Guan, Derek F. Jackson Kimball, Mikhail G. Kozlov, Yevgeny V. Stadnik, Dmitry Budker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum tunneling in a quintessence background and the role of GUP</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15711v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we studied quantum tunneling of massless and massive particles pertaining to a Schwarzschild black hole in a quintessence background, and explored the consequences emerging from a generalized uncertainty principle (GUP). For the quintessence scenario, we considered two specific cases of $w$, which is the ratio of the pressure and energy density, namely $w=-1/3$ and $w=-2/3$. For the GUP, we used a modified Schwarzschild metric and employed a unique choice of contour integration to compute the tunneling amplitudes. An analysis and comparative study of the respective temperature profiles have been made.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15711v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sauvik Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric interpretation of timelike entanglement entropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15752</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15752v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Analytic continuations of holographic entanglement entropy in which the boundary subregion extends along a timelike direction have brought a promise of a novel, time-centric probe of the emergence of spacetime. We propose that the bulk carriers of this holographic timelike entanglement entropy are boundary-anchored extremal surfaces probing analytic continuation of holographic spacetimes into complex coordinates. This proposal not only provides a geometric interpretation of all the known cases obtained by direct analytic continuation of closed-form expressions of holographic entanglement entropy of a strip subregion but crucially also opens a window to study holographic timelike entanglement entropy in full generality. We initialize the investigation of complex extremal surfaces anchored on a timelike strip at the boundary of anti-de Sitter black branes. We find multiple complex extremal surfaces and discuss possible principles singling out the physical contribution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15752v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michal P. Heller, Fabio Ori, Alexandre Serantes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Macroscopic Thermalization for Highly Degenerate Hamiltonians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15832v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We say of an isolated macroscopic quantum system in a pure state $\psi$ that it is in macroscopic thermal equilibrium if $\psi$ lies in or close to a suitable subspace $\mathcal{H}_{eq}$ of Hilbert space. It is known that every initial state $\psi_0$ will eventually reach macroscopic thermal equilibrium and stay there most of the time (``thermalize'') if the Hamiltonian is non-degenerate and satisfies the appropriate version of the eigenstate thermalization hypothesis (ETH), i.e., that every eigenvector is in macroscopic thermal equilibrium. Shiraishi and Tasaki recently proved the ETH for a certain perturbation $H_\theta$ of the Hamiltonian $H_0$ of $N\gg 1$ free fermions on a one-dimensional lattice. The perturbation is needed to remove the high degeneracies of $H_0$. Here, we point out that also for degenerate Hamiltonians, all $\psi_0$ thermalize if the ETH holds for every eigenbasis, and we prove that this is the case for $H_0$. On top of that and more generally, we develop another strategy of proving thermalization, inspired by the fact that there is one eigenbasis of $H_0$ for which ETH can be proven more easily and with smaller error bounds than for the others. This strategy applies to arbitrarily small generic perturbations $H$ of $H_0$, which seem no less realistic than $H_\theta$, and to arbitrary spatial dimensions. In fact, we consider any given $H_0$, suppose that the ETH holds for some but not necessarily every eigenbasis of $H_0$, and add a small generic perturbation, $H=H_0+\lambda V$ with $\lambda\ll 1$. Then, although $H$ (which is non-degenerate) may still not satisfy the ETH, we show that nevertheless (i) every $\psi_0$ thermalizes for most perturbations $V$, and more generally, (ii) for any subspace $\mathcal{H}_\nu$ (such as corresponding to a non-equilibrium macro state), most perturbations $V$ are such that most $\psi_0$ from $\mathcal{H}_\nu$ thermalize.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15832v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Barbara Roos, Stefan Teufel, Roderich Tumulka, Cornelia Vogel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>1+1d SPT phases with fusion category symmetry: interface modes and non-abelian Thouless pump</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15960v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider symmetry protected topological (SPT) phases with finite non-invertible symmetry $\mathcal{C}$ in 1+1d. In particular, we investigate interfaces and parameterized families of them within the framework of matrix product states. After revealing how to extract the $\mathcal{C}$-SPT invariant, we identify the algebraic structure of symmetry operators acting on the interface of two $\mathcal{C}$-SPT phases. By studying the representation theory of this algebra, we show that there must be a degenerate interface mode between different $\mathcal{C}$-SPT phases. This result generalizes the bulk-boundary correspondence for ordinary SPT phases. We then propose the classification of one-parameter families of $\mathcal{C}$-SPT states based on the explicit construction of invariants of such families. Our invariant is identified with a non-abelian generalization of the Thouless charge pump, which is the pump of a local excitation within a $\mathcal{C}$-SPT phase. Finally, by generalizing the results for one-parameter families of SPT phases, we conjecture the classification of general parameterized families of general gapped phases with finite non-invertible symmetries in both 1+1d and higher dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15960v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kansei Inamura, Shuhei Ohyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Novel ground states and emergent quantum many-body scars in a two-species Rydberg atom array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15965v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Rydberg atom array has been established as one appealing platform for quantum simulation and quantum computation. Recent experimental development of trapping and controlling two-species atoms using optical tweezer arrays has brought more complex interactions in this game, enabling much versatile novel quantum states and phenomena to emerge and thus leading to a growing need for both theoretical and numerical investigations in this regard. In this paper we systematically calculate the ground state phase diagram of alternating two-species atom array and find some novel quantum states that cannot exist in traditional cold-atom platforms, for instance the period $4$ product state $|1100\rangle^{\otimes m}$, the period $6$ product state $|111000\rangle^{\otimes m}$ and order-disorder separation phase. We also confirm the existence of floating phase, however, in this system it has to be described by two interacting bosonic fields whereas that in the single species Rydberg atom array can be understood as free bosons. More interestingly, in the quench dynamics we discover a type of new quantum many-body scar distinct from that previous found in single species atoms which is explained by low-energy effective theory of the PXP model. Instead, the underlying physics of the newly found quantum many-body scar can be described by a perturbation theory spanning the whole energy spectrum. Detailed analysis on how to experimentally prepare these states and observe the phenomena is provided. Numerical evidence shows that the proposed scheme is robust against typical experimentally relevent imperfections and thus it is implementable. Our work opens new avenue for quantum simulating novel quantum many-body states both in and out of equilibrium arising from the interplay of competing interactions of different atom species and quantum fluctuations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15965v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei-Yi-Nan Liu, Shun-Yao Yu, Shi-Rong Peng, Jie Sheng, Su Yi, Peng Xu, Shou-Shu Gong, Tao Shi, Jian Cui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum thermodynamics with fast driving and strong coupling via the mesoscopic leads approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.01090</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.01090v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding the thermodynamics of driven quantum systems strongly coupled to thermal baths is a central focus of quantum thermodynamics and mesoscopic physics. A variety of different methodological approaches exist in the literature, all with their own advantages and disadvantages. The mesoscopic leads approach was recently generalised to steady state thermal machines and has the ability to replicate Landauer B\"uttiker theory in the non-interacting limit. In this approach a set of discretised lead modes, each locally damped, provide a markovian embedding for the baths. In this work we further generalise this approach to incorporate an arbitrary time dependence in the system Hamiltonian. Following a careful discussion of the calculation of thermodynamic quantities we illustrate the power of our approach by studying several driven mesoscopic examples coupled to finite temperature fermionic baths, replicating known results in various limits. In the case of a driven non interacting quantum dot we show how fast driving can be used to induce heat rectification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.01090v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.107.195117</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 107, 195117 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Artur M. Lacerda, Archak Purkayastha, Michael Kewming, Gabriel T. Landi, John Goold</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New constructive counterexamples to additivity of minimum output R\'enyi p-entropy of quantum channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.07428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.07428v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we present new families of quantum channels for which corresponding minimum output R\'enyi $p$-entropy is not additive. Our manuscript is motivated by the results of Grudka et al., J. Phys. A: Math. Theor. 43 425304 and we focus on channels characterized by both extensions and subspaces of the antisymmetric subspace in $\mathbb{C}^d \otimes \mathbb{C}^d$, which exhibit additivity breaking for $p&gt;2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.07428v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TIT.2024.3446191</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Krzysztof Szczygielski, Micha{\l} Studzi\'nski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the possibility of a complex-valued non-Gaussianity measure for quantum states of light</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.00880</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.00880v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a quantity that is the differential relative entropy between a generic Wigner function and a Gaussian one. We prove that said quantity is minimized with respect to its Gaussian argument, if both Wigner functions in the argument of the Wigner differential entropy have the same first and second moments, i.e., if the Gaussian argument is the Gaussian associate of the other, generic Wigner function. Therefore, we introduce the differential relative entropy between any Wigner function and its Gaussian associate and we examine its potential as a non-Gaussianity measure. We prove that said quantity is faithful, invariant under Gaussian unitary operations, and find a sufficient condition on its monotonic behavior under Gaussian channels. We provide numerical results supporting aforesaid condition. The proposed, phase-space based non-Gaussianity measure is complex-valued, with its imaginary part possessing the physical meaning of the negative volume of the Wigner function. At the same time, the real part of this measure provides an extra layer of information, rendering the complex-valued quantity a measure of non-Gaussianity, instead of a quantity pertaining only to the negativity of the Wigner function. We examine the usefulness of our measure to non-Gaussian quantum state engineering with partial measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.00880v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0219011</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>APL Quantum 1 September 2024; 1 (3): 036117</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andrew J. Pizzimenti, Prajit Dhara, Zacharie Van Herstraeten, Sijie Cheng, Christos N. Gagatsos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Influence of noise in entanglement-based quantum networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.03759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.03759v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider entanglement-based quantum networks, where multipartite entangled resource states are distributed and stored among the nodes and locally manipulated upon request to establish the desired target configuration. Separating the generation process from the requests enables a pre-preparation of resources, hence a reduced network latency. It also allows for an optimization of the entanglement topology, which is independent of the underlying network geometry. We concentrate on establishing Bell pairs or tripartite GHZ states between arbitrary parties. We study the influence of noise in this process, where we consider imperfections in state preparation, memories, and measurements - all of which can be modeled by local depolarizing noise. We compare different resource states corresponding to linear chains, trees, or multi-dimensional rectangular clusters, as well as centralized topologies using bipartite or tripartite entangled states. We compute the fidelity of the target states using a recently established efficient method, the noisy stabilizer formalism, and identify the best resource states within these classes. This allows us to treat networks of large size containing millions of nodes. We find that in large networks, high-dimensional cluster states are favorable and lead to a significantly higher target state fidelity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.03759v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/JSAC.2024.3380089</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Communications, vol. 42, no. 7, pp. 1793-1807, July 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Maria Flors Mor-Ruiz, Wolfgang D\"ur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tutorial: projector approach to master equations for open quantum systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.19704</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.19704v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Most quantum theorists are familiar with different ways of describing the effective quantum dynamics of a system coupled to external degrees of freedom, such as the Born-Markov master equation or the adiabatic elimination. Understanding the deep connection between these -- sometimes apparently unrelated -- methods can be a powerful tool, allowing us to derive effective dynamics in unconventional systems or regimes. This tutorial aims at providing quantum theorists across multiple fields (e.g., quantum and atom optics, optomechanics, or hybrid quantum systems) with a self-contained practical toolbox to derive effective quantum dynamics, applicable to systems ranging from N-level emitters to mechanical resonators. First, we summarize the projector approach to open quantum systems and the derivation of the fundamental Nakajima-Zwanzig equation. Then, we show how three common effective equations, namely the Brownian master equation, the Born-Markov master equation, and the adiabatic elimination used in atom and molecular optics, can be derived from different perturbative expansions of the Nakajima-Zwanzig equation. We also solve in detail four specific examples using this formalism, namely a harmonic oscillator subject to displacement noise, the effective equations of a mechanical resonator cooled by an optical cavity, the Purcell effect for a qubit coupled to an optical cavity, and the adiabatic elimination in a Lambda system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.19704v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Gonzalez-Ballestero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-Shot Quantum Error Correction in Intertwined Toric Codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.08118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.08118v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct a new subsystem code in three dimensions that exhibits single-shot error correction in a user-friendly and transparent way. As this code is a subsystem version of coupled toric codes, we call it the intertwined toric code (ITC). Although previous codes share the property of single-shot error correction, the ITC is distinguished by its physically motivated origin, geometrically straightforward logical operators and errors, and a simple phase diagram. The code arises from 3d stabilizer toric codes in a way that emphasizes the physical origin of the single-shot property. In particular, starting with two copies of the 3d toric code, we add check operators that provide for the confinement of pointlike excitations without condensing the loop excitations. Geometrically, the bare and dressed logical operators in the ITC derive from logical operators in the underlying toric codes, creating a clear relationship between errors and measurement outcomes. The syndromes of the ITC resemble the syndromes of the single-shot code by Kubica and Vasmer, allowing us to use their decoding schemes. We also extract the phase diagram corresponding to ITC and show that it contains the phases found in the Kubica-Vasmer code. Finally, we suggest various connections to Walker-Wang models and measurement-based quantum computation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.08118v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.075143</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 075143 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Charles Stahl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Designs via Free Probability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.06200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.06200v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Unitary Designs have become a vital tool for investigating pseudorandomness since they approximate the statistics of the uniform Haar ensemble. Despite their central role in quantum information, their relation to quantum chaotic evolution and in particular to the Eigenstate Thermalization Hypothesis (ETH) are still largely debated issues. This work provides a bridge between the latter and $k$-designs through Free Probability theory. First, by introducing the more general notion of $k$-freeness, we show that it can be used as an alternative probe to designs. In turn, free probability theory comes with several tools, useful for instance for the calculation of mixed moments or the so-called $k$-fold quantum channels. Our second result is the connection to quantum dynamics. Quantum ergodicity, and correspondingly ETH, apply to a restricted class of physical observables, as already discussed in the literature. In this spirit, we show that unitary evolution with generic Hamiltonians always leads to freeness at sufficiently long times, but only when the operators considered are restricted within the ETH class. Our results provide a direct link between unitary designs, quantum chaos and the Eigenstate Thermalization Hypothesis, and shed new light on the universality of late-time quantum dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.06200v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michele Fava, Jorge Kurchan, Silvia Pappalardi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evanescent Electron Wave Spin</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.17325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.17325v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study demonstrates the existence of an evanescent electron wave outside both finite and infinite quantum wells by solving the Dirac equation and ensuring continuity of the spinor wavefunction at the boundaries. We show that this evanescent wave shares spin characteristics with the wave confined within the well, as supported by analytical expressions for the current density across the all regions. Our findings suggest that the electron wave cannot be confined to a mathematical singularity, which allows quantum information, or quantum entropy, to leak through the quantum confinement. The results emphasize that the electron wave, fully characterized by Lorentz-invariant charge and current densities, should be regarded as the true and sole entity of the electron.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.17325v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ju Gao, Fang Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A graduate laboratory experiment to set up a photon-counting detector using MKIDs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.08295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.08295v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a new laboratory activity aimed at developing knowledge and expertise in microwave applications at cryogenic temperatures. The experience focuses on the detection of infrared photons through Microwave Kinetic Inductance Detectors (MKIDs). The experimental setup, theoretical concepts, and activities involved are detailed, highlighting the skills and knowledge gained through the experience. This experiment is designed for graduate students in the field of quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.08295v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ed-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6404/ad4e1e</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>European Journal of Physics (2024), Volume 45, Number 4</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pietro Campana, Rodolfo Carobene, Eleonora Cipelli, Marco Gobbo, Aurora Perego, Davide Vertemati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropy production in the mesoscopic-leads formulation of quantum thermodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.12513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.12513v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding the entropy production of systems strongly coupled to thermal baths is a core problem of both quantum thermodynamics and mesoscopic physics. While there exist many techniques to accurately study entropy production in such systems, they typically require a microscopic description of the baths, which can become numerically intractable to study for large systems. Alternatively an open-systems approach can be employed with all the nuances associated with various levels of approximation. Recently, the mesoscopic leads approach has emerged as a powerful method for studying such quantum systems strongly coupled to multiple thermal baths. In this method, a set of discretised lead modes, each locally damped, provide a Markovian embedding. Here we show that this method proves extremely useful to describe entropy production of a strongly coupled open quantum system. We show numerically, for both non-interacting and interacting setups, that a system coupled to a single bath exhibits a thermal fixed point at the level of the embedding. This allows us to use various results from the thermodynamics of quantum dynamical semi-groups to infer the non-equilibrium thermodynamics of the strongly coupled, non-Markovian central systems. In particular, we show that the entropy production in the transient regime recovers the well established microscopic definitions of entropy production with a correction that can be computed explicitly for both the single- and multiple-lead cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.12513v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevE.110.014125</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. E 110, 014125 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Artur M. Lacerda, Michael J. Kewming, Marlon Brenes, Conor Jackson, Stephen R. Clark, Mark T. Mitchison, John Goold</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of dark states on the stationary properties of quantum particles with off-centered interactions in one dimension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10078v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a generalization of the two-body contact interaction for non-relativistic particles trapped in one dimension. The particles interact only when they are a distance c apart. The competition of the interaction length scale with the oscillator length leads to three regimes identified from the energy spectra. When c is less than the oscillator length, particles avoid each other, whereas in the opposite case bunching occurs. In the intermediate region where the oscillator length is comparable to c, both exclusion and bunching are manifested. All of these regions are separated by dark states, i.e. bosonic or fermionic states which are not affected by the interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10078v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.110.023327</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>G. Bougas, N. L. Harshman, P. Schmelcher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Many-hypercube codes: High-rate quantum error-correcting codes for high-performance fault-tolerant quantum computing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16054</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16054v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Standard approaches to quantum error correction for fault-tolerant quantum computing are based on encoding a single logical qubit into many physical ones, resulting in asymptotically zero encoding rates and therefore huge resource overheads. To overcome this issue, high-rate quantum codes, such as quantum low-density parity-check codes, have been studied over the past decade. In this case, however, it is difficult to perform logical gates in parallel while maintaining low overheads. Here we propose concatenated high-rate small-size quantum error-detecting codes as a new family of high-rate quantum codes. Their simple structure allows for a geometrical interpretation using hypercubes corresponding to logical qubits. We thus call them many-hypercube codes. They can realize both high rates, e.g., 30% (64 logical qubits are encoded into 216 physical ones), and parallelizability of logical gates. Developing dedicated decoder and encoders, we achieve high error thresholds even in a circuit-level noise model. Thus, the many-hypercube codes will pave the way to high-performance fault-tolerant quantum computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16054v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hayato Goto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Quantum Metrology with Non-Phase-Covariant Noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.08436v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The detrimental impact of noise on sensing performance in quantum metrology has been widely recognized by researchers in the field. However, there are no explicit fundamental laws of physics stating that noise invariably weakens quantum metrology. We reveal that phase-covariant (PC) noise either degrades or remains neutral to sensing precision, whereas non-phase-covariant (NPC) noise can potentially enhance parameter estimation, surpassing even the ultimate precision limit achievable in the absence of noise. This implies that a non-Hermitian quantum sensor may outperform its Hermitian counterpart in terms of sensing performance. To illustrate and validate our theory, we present several paradigmatic examples of magnetic field metrology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.08436v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.090801</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review Letters 133, 090801 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Xin Peng, Baiqiang Zhu, Weiping Zhang, Keye Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum delocalization on correlation landscape: The key to exponentially fast multipartite entanglement generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10973</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10973v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Entanglement, a hallmark of quantum mechanics, is a vital resource for quantum technologies. Generating highly entangled multipartite states is a key goal in current quantum experiments. We unveil a novel framework for understanding entanglement generation dynamics in Hamiltonian systems by quantum delocalization of an effective operator wavefunction on a correlation landscape. Our framework establishes a profound connection between the exponentially fast generation of multipartite entanglement, witnessed by the quantum Fisher information, and the linearly increasing asymptotics of hopping amplitudes governing the delocalization dynamics in Krylov space. We illustrate this connection using the paradigmatic Lipkin-Meshkov-Glick model and highlight potential signatures in chaotic Feingold-Peres tops. Our results provide a transformative tool for understanding and harnessing rapid entanglement production in complex quantum systems, providing a pathway for quantum enhanced technologies by large-scale entanglement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10973v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yaoming Chu, Xiangbei Li, Jianming Cai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constant-depth preparation of matrix product states with adaptive quantum circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16083</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16083v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Adaptive quantum circuits, which combine local unitary gates, midcircuit measurements, and feedforward operations, have recently emerged as a promising avenue for efficient state preparation, particularly on near-term quantum devices limited to shallow-depth circuits. Matrix product states (MPS) comprise a significant class of many-body entangled states, efficiently describing the ground states of one-dimensional gapped local Hamiltonians and finding applications in a number of recent quantum algorithms. Recently, it was shown that the AKLT state -- a paradigmatic example of an MPS -- can be exactly prepared with an adaptive quantum circuit of constant-depth, an impossible feat with local unitary gates due to its nonzero correlation length [Smith et al., PRX Quantum 4, 020315 (2023)]. In this work, we broaden the scope of this approach and demonstrate that a diverse class of MPS can be exactly prepared using constant-depth adaptive quantum circuits, outperforming optimal preparation protocols that rely on unitary circuits alone. We show that this class includes short- and long-ranged entangled MPS, symmetry-protected topological (SPT) and symmetry-broken states, MPS with finite Abelian, non-Abelian, and continuous symmetries, resource states for MBQC, and families of states with tunable correlation length. Moreover, we illustrate the utility of our framework for designing constant-depth sampling protocols, such as for random MPS or for generating MPS in a particular SPT phase. We present sufficient conditions for particular MPS to be preparable in constant time, with global on-site symmetry playing a pivotal role. Altogether, this work demonstrates the immense promise of adaptive quantum circuits for efficiently preparing many-body entangled states and provides explicit algorithms that outperform known protocols to prepare an essential class of states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16083v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin C. Smith, Abid Khan, Bryan K. Clark, S. M. Girvin, Tzu-Chieh Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Unitary Matrix Representation of Lattice Boltzmann Method for Fluid Flow Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.08669</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.08669v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the present contribution, we propose a quantum unitary matrix representation for the Lattice Boltzmann Method (LBM) to simulate fluid flows in the low Reynolds number ($Re$) regime. Since the particle distribution functions are encoded as probability amplitudes of the quantum state, we show that the state of the ancilla qubit must be controlled during the initial state preparation. In contrast to methods such as the linear combination of unitaries to implement non-unitary operators, we utilize the classical singular value decomposition (SVD) to decompose the collision and streaming operators into a product of unitaries. Our approach has been tested using benchmark problems such as advection-diffusion of a Gaussian hill, Poiseuille flow, Couette flow, and the lid-driven cavity problem. We report the two-qubit controlled-NOT (CNOT) and single-qubit U gate counts for test cases involving 9 to 12 qubits and grid sizes ranging from 24 to 216 points. While the gate count closely aligns with the theoretical limit, the high number of two-qubit gates on the order of $10^7$ requires special attention as it relates to circuit synthesis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.08669v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Dinesh Kumar, Steven H. Frankel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generation of quantum phases of matter and finding a maximum-weight independent set of unit-disk graphs using Rydberg atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09803v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent progress in quantum computing and quantum simulation of many-body systems with arrays of neutral atoms using Rydberg excitation has provided unforeseen opportunities towards computational advantage in solving various optimization problems. The problem of a maximum-weight independent set of unit-disk graphs is an example of an NP-hard optimization problem. It involves finding the largest set of vertices with the maximum sum of their weights for a graph which has edges connecting all pairs of vertices within a unit distance. This problem can be solved using quantum annealing with an array of interacting Rydberg atoms. For a particular graph, a spatial arrangement of atoms represents vertices of the graph, while the detuning from resonance at Rydberg excitation defines the weights of these vertices. The edges of the graph can be drawn according to the unit disk criterion. Maximum-weight independent sets can be obtained by applying a variational quantum adiabatic algorithm. We consider driving the quantum system of interacting atoms to the many-body ground state using a non-linear quasi-adiabatic profile for sweeping the Rydberg detuning. We also propose using a quantum wire which is a set of auxiliary atoms of a different chemical element to mediate strong coupling between the remote vertices of the graph. We investigate this effect for different lengths of the quantum wire. We also investigate the quantum phases of matter realizing commensurate and incommensurate phases in one- and two-dimensional spatial arrangements of the atomic array.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09803v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.110.022442</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 110, 022442 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ahmed M. Farouk, I. I. Beterov, Peng Xu, I. I. Ryabtsev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational-Cartan Quantum Dynamics Simulations of Excitation Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14127v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum dynamics simulations (QDSs) are one of the most highly anticipated applications of quantum computing. Quantum circuit depth for implementing Hamiltonian simulation algorithms is commonly time dependent so that long time dynamics simulations become impratical on near-term quantum processors. The Hamiltonian simulation algorithm based on Cartan decomposition (CD) provides an appealing scheme for QDSs with fixed-depth circuits while limited to time-independent case. In this work, we generalize this CD-based Hamiltonian simulation algorithm for studying time-dependent systems by combining it with variational Hamiltonian simulation. The time-dependent and time-independent parts of the Hamiltonian are treated with the variational approach and the CD-based Hamiltonian simulation algorithms, respectively. As such, only fixed-depth quantum circuits are required in this hybrid Hamiltonian simulation algorithm while still maintaining high accuracy. We apply this new algorithm to study the response of spin and molecular systems to $\delta$-kick electric fields and obtain accurate spectra for these excitation processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14127v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linyun Wan, Jie Liu, Zhenyu Li, Jinlong Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trade-off between Gradient Measurement Efficiency and Expressivity in Deep Quantum Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18316v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum neural networks (QNNs) require an efficient training algorithm to achieve practical quantum advantages. A promising approach is the use of gradient-based optimization algorithms, where gradients are estimated through quantum measurements. However, general QNNs lack an efficient gradient measurement algorithm, which poses a fundamental and practical challenge to realizing scalable QNNs. In this work, we rigorously prove a trade-off between gradient measurement efficiency, defined as the mean number of simultaneously measurable gradient components, and expressivity in a wide class of deep QNNs, elucidating the theoretical limits and possibilities of efficient gradient estimation. This trade-off implies that a more expressive QNN requires a higher measurement cost in gradient estimation, whereas we can increase gradient measurement efficiency by reducing the QNN expressivity to suit a given task. We further propose a general QNN ansatz called the stabilizer-logical product ansatz (SLPA), which can reach the upper limit of the trade-off inequality by leveraging the symmetric structure of the quantum circuit. In learning an unknown symmetric function, the SLPA drastically reduces the quantum resources required for training while maintaining accuracy and trainability compared to a well-designed symmetric circuit based on the parameter-shift method. Our results not only reveal a theoretical understanding of efficient training in QNNs but also provide a standard and broadly applicable efficient QNN design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18316v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koki Chinzei, Shinichiro Yamano, Quoc Hoan Tran, Yasuhiro Endo, Hirotaka Oshima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parallel Segment Entanglement Swapping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06598v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the noisy intermediate-scale quantum era, scientists are trying to improve the entanglement swapping success rate by researching anti-noise technology on the physical level, thereby obtaining a higher generation rate of long-distance entanglement. However, we may improve the generation rate from another perspective, which is studying an efficient entanglement swapping strategy. This paper analyzes the challenges faced by existing entanglement swapping strategies, including the node allocation principle, time synchronization, and processing of entanglement swapping failure. We present Parallel Segment Entanglement Swapping (PSES) to solve these problems. The core idea of PSES is to segment the path and perform parallel entanglement swapping between segments to improve the generation rate of long-distance entanglement. We construct a tree-like model as the carrier of PSES and propose heuristic algorithms called Layer Greedy and Segment Greedy to transform the path into a tree-like model. Moreover, we realize the time synchronization and design the on-demand retransmission mechanism to process entanglement swapping failure. The experiments show that PSES performs superiorly to other entanglement swapping strategies, and the on-demand retransmission mechanism can reduce the average entanglement swapping time by 80% and the average entanglement consumption by 80%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06598v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/QCNC62729.2024.00050</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2024 International Conference on Quantum Communications, Networking, and Computing (QCNC), Kanazawa, Japan, 2024, pp. 271-279</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Binjie He, Seng W. Loke, Dong Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Tree Tensor Network Operators for Tensor Network Simulations: Applications to Open Quantum Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13098</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13098v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Tree tensor network states (TTNS) decompose the system wavefunction to the product of low-rank tensors based on the tree topology, serving as the foundation of the multi-layer multi-configuration time-dependent Hartree (ML-MCTDH) method. In this work, we present an algorithm that automatically constructs the optimal and exact tree tensor network operators (TTNO) for any sum-of-product symbolic quantum operator.The construction is based on the minimum vertex cover of a bipartite graph. With the optimal TTNO, we simulate open quantum systems such as spin relaxation dynamics in the spin-boson model and charge transport in molecular junctions. In these simulations, the environment is treated as discrete modes and its wavefunction is evolved on equal footing with the system. We employ the Cole-Davidson spectral density to model the glassy phonon environment, and incorporate temperature effects via thermo field dynamics. Our results show that the computational cost scales linearly with the number of discretized modes, demonstrating the efficiency of our approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13098v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0218773</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Weitang Li, Jiajun Ren, Hengrui Yang, Haobin Wang, Zhigang Shuai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tensor Network enhanced Dynamic Multiproduct Formulas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17405v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Tensor networks and quantum computation are two of the most powerful tools for the simulation of quantum many-body systems. Rather than viewing them as competing approaches, here we consider how these two methods can work in tandem. We introduce a novel algorithm that combines tensor networks and quantum computation to produce results that are more accurate than what could be achieved by either method used in isolation. Our algorithm is based on multiproduct formulas (MPF) - a technique that linearly combines Trotter product formulas to reduce algorithmic error. Our algorithm uses a quantum computer to calculate the expectation values and tensor networks to calculate the coefficients used in the linear combination. We present a detailed error analysis of the algorithm and demonstrate the full workflow on a one-dimensional quantum simulation problem on $50$ qubits using two IBM quantum computers: $ibm\_torino$ and $ibm\_kyiv$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17405v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niall F. Robertson, Bibek Pokharel, Bryce Fuller, Eric Switzer, Oles Shtanko, Mirko Amico, Adam Byrne, Andrea D'Urbano, Salome Hayes-Shuptar, Albert Akhriev, Nathan Keenan, Sergey Bravyi, Sergiy Zhuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimally generating $\mathfrak{su}(2^N)$ using Pauli strings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03294</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03294v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Any quantum computation consists of a sequence of unitary evolutions described by a finite set of Hamiltonians. When this set is taken to consist of only products of Pauli operators, we show that the minimal such set generating $\mathfrak{su}(2^{N})$ contains $2N+1$ elements. We provide a number of examples of such generating sets and furthermore provide an algorithm for producing a sequence of rotations corresponding to any given Pauli rotation, which is shown to have optimal complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03294v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Isaac D. Smith, Maxime Cautr\`es, David T. Stephen, Hendrik Poulsen Nautrup</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coprime Bivariate Bicycle Codes and their Properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10001</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10001v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work (1) proposes a novel numerical algorithm to accelerate the search process for good Bivariate Bicycle (BB) codes and (2) defines a new subclass of BB codes suitable for quantum error correction. The proposed acceleration search algorithm reduces the search space by excluding some equivalent codes from the search space, as well as setting thresholds to drop bad codes at an early stage. A number of new BB codes found by this algorithm are reported. The proposed subclass of BB codes employs coprimes to construct groups via polynomials as the basis for the BB code, rather than using the standard BB codes with unconstrained constructors. In contrast to vanilla BB codes, where parameters remain unknown prior to code discovery, the rate of the proposed code can be determined beforehand by specifying a factor polynomial as an input to the numerical search algorithm. Using this coprime BB construction, we found a number of surprisingly short to medium-length codes that were previously unknown.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10001v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ming Wang, Frank Mueller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-machine-assisted Drug Discovery: Survey and Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13479v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Drug discovery and development is a highly complex and costly endeavor, typically requiring over a decade and substantial financial investment to bring a new drug to market. Traditional computer-aided drug design (CADD) has made significant progress in accelerating this process, but the development of quantum computing offers potential due to its unique capabilities. This paper discusses the integration of quantum computing into drug discovery and development, focusing on how quantum technologies might accelerate and enhance various stages of the drug development cycle. Specifically, we explore the application of quantum computing in addressing challenges related to drug discovery, such as molecular simulation and the prediction of drug-target interactions, as well as the optimization of clinical trial outcomes. By leveraging the inherent capabilities of quantum computing, we might be able to reduce the time and cost associated with bringing new drugs to market, ultimately benefiting public health.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13479v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yidong Zhou, Jintai Chen, Jinglei Cheng, Gopal Karemore, Marinka Zitnik, Frederic T. Chong, Junyu Liu, Tianfan Fu, Zhiding Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic compensation for pump-induced frequency shift in Kerr-cat qubit initialization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14112v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The noise-biased Kerr-cat qubit is an attractive candidate for fault-tolerant quantum computation; however, its initialization faces challenges due to the squeezing pump-induced frequency shift (PIFS). Here, we propose and demonstrate a dynamic compensation method to mitigate the effect of PIFS during the Kerr-cat qubit initialization. Utilizing a novel nonlinearity-engineered triple-loop SQUID device, we realize a stabilized Kerr-cat qubit and validate the advantages of the dynamic compensation method by improving the initialization fidelity from 57% to 78%, with a projected fidelity of 91% after excluding state preparation and measurement errors. Our results not only advance the practical implementation of Kerr-cat qubits, but also provide valuable insights into the fundamental adiabatic dynamics of these systems. This work paves the way for scalable quantum processors that leverage the bias-preserving properties of Kerr-cat qubits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14112v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifang Xu, Ziyue Hua, Weiting Wang, Yuwei Ma, Ming Li, Jiajun Chen, Jie Zhou, Xiaoxuan Pan, Lintao Xiao, Hongwei Huang, Weizhou Cai, Hao Ai, Yu-xi Liu, Chang-Ling Zou, Luyan Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modelling of planar germanium hole qubits in electric and magnetic fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.04795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.04795v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Hole-based spin qubits in strained planar germanium quantum wells have received considerable attention due to their favourable properties and remarkable experimental progress. The sizeable spin-orbit interaction in this structure allows for efficient qubit operations with electric fields. However, it also couples the qubit to electrical noise. In this work, we perform simulations of a heterostructure hosting these hole spin qubits. We solve the effective mass equations for a realistic heterostructure, provide a set of analytical basis wave functions, and compute the effective g-factor of the heavy-hole ground-state. Our investigations reveal a strong impact of highly excited light-hole states located outside the quantum well on the g-factor. We find that sweet spots, points of operations that are least susceptible to charge noise, for out-of-plane magnetic fields are shifted to impractically large electric fields. However, for magnetic fields close to in-plane alignment, partial sweet spots at low electric fields are recovered. Furthermore, sweet spots with respect to multiple fluctuating charge traps can be found under certain circumstances for different magnetic field alignments. This work will be helpful in understanding and improving coherence of germanium hole spin qubits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.04795v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chien-An Wang, Ercan Ekmel, Mark Gyure, Giordano Scappucci, Menno Veldhorst, Maximilian Rimbach-Russ</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconstructing the spatial structure of quantum correlations in materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.11723</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.11723v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum correlations are a fundamental property of quantum many-body states. Yet they remain experimentally elusive, hindering certification of genuine quantum behavior, especially in quantum materials. Here we show that the momentum-dependent dynamical susceptibility measured via inelastic neutron scattering enables the systematic reconstruction of a general family of quantum correlation functions, which express the degree of quantum coherence in the fluctuations of two spins at arbitrary mutual distance. Using neutron scattering data on the compound KCuF$_3$ $\unicode{x2014}$ a system of weakly coupled $S=1/2$ Heisenberg chains $\unicode{x2014}$ and of numerically exact quantum Monte Carlo data, we show that quantum correlations possess a radically different spatial structure with respect to conventional correlations. Indeed, they exhibit a new emergent length scale $\unicode{x2014}$ the quantum coherence length $\unicode{x2014}$ which is finite at any finite temperature (including when long-range magnetic order develops). Moreover, we show theoretically that coupled Heisenberg spin chains exhibit a form of quantum monogamy, with a trade-off between quantum correlations along and transverse to the spin chains. These results highlight real-space quantum correlators as an informative, model-independent means of probing the underlying quantum state of real quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.11723v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.6.033183</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 6, 033183 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Allen Scheie, Pontus Laurell, Elbio Dagotto, D. Alan Tennant, Tommaso Roscilde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eigenstate Thermalization in 2+1 dimensional SU(2) Lattice Gauge Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.16202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.16202v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present preliminary numerical evidence for the hypothesis that the Hamiltonian SU(2) gauge theory discretized on a lattice obeys the Eigenstate Thermalization Hypothesis (ETH). To do so we study three approximations: (a) a linear plaquette chain in a reduced Hilbert space limiting the electric field basis to $j=0,\frac{1}{2}$ , (b) a two-dimensional honeycomb lattice with periodic or closed boundary condition and the same Hilbert space constraint, and (c) a chain of only three plaquettes but such a sufficiently large electric field Hilbert space ($j \leq \frac{7}{2})$ that convergence of all energy eigenvalues in the analyzed energy window is observed. While an unconstrained Hilbert space is required to reach the continuum limit of SU(2) gauge theory, numerical resource constraints do not permit us to realize this requirement for all values of the coupling constant and large lattices. In each of the three studied cases we check first for random matrix theory (RMT) behavior in the eigenenergy spectrum and then analyze the diagonal as well as the off-diagonal matrix elements between energy eigenstates for a few operators. Within current uncertainties all results for (a), (b) and (c) agree with ETH predictions. Furthermore, we find the off-diagonal matrix elements of the electric energy operator exhibit RMT behavior in frequency windows that are small enough in (b) and (c). To unambiguously establish ETH behavior and determine for which class of operators it applies, an extension of our investigations is necessary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.16202v3</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.014504</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109, 014504 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Ebner, Berndt M\"uller, Andreas Sch\"afer, Clemens Seidl, Xiaojun Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical analysis of multiple reentrant localization in an antiferromagnetic helix with transverse electric field: Hopping dimerization-free scenario</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.02778v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Reentrant localization (RL), a recently prominent phenomenon, traditionally links to the interplay of staggered correlated disorder and hopping dimerization, as indicated by prior research. Contrary to this paradigm, our present study demonstrates that hopping dimerization is not a pivotal factor in realizing RL. Considering a helical magnetic system with antiferromagnetic ordering, we uncover spin-dependent RL at multiple energy regions, in the {\em absence} of hopping dimerization. This phenomenon persists even in the thermodynamic limit. The correlated disorder in the form of Aubry-Andr\'{e}-Harper model is introduced by applying a transverse electric field to the helical system, circumventing the use of traditional substitutional disorder. We conduct a finite-size scaling analysis on the observed reentrant phases to identify critical points, determine associated critical exponents, and examine the scaling behavior linked to localization transitions. Additionally, we explore the parameter space to identify the conditions under which the reentrant phases occur. Described within a tight-binding framework, present work provides a novel outlook on RL, highlighting the crucial role of electric field, antiferromagnetic ordering, and the helicity of the geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.02778v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sudin Ganguly, Sourav Chattopadhyay, Kallol Mondal, Santanu K. Maiti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement Entropy of ($\mathbf{2+1}$)-Dimensional SU(2) Lattice Gauge Theory on Plaquette Chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.15184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.15184v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the entanglement entropy of Hamiltonian SU(2) lattice gauge theory in $2+1$ dimensions on linear plaquette chains and show that the entanglement entropies of both ground and excited states follow Page curves. The transition of the subsystem size dependence of the entanglement entropy from the area law for the ground state to the volume law for highly excited states is found to be described by a universal crossover function. Quantum many-body scars in the middle of the spectrum, which are present in the electric flux truncated Hilbert space, where the gauge theory can be mapped onto an Ising model, disappear when higher electric field representations are included in the Hilbert space basis. This suggests the continuum $(2+1)$-dimensional SU(2) gauge theory does not have such scarred states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.15184v4</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.014505</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 014505 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Ebner, Andreas Sch\"afer, Clemens Seidl, Berndt M\"uller, Xiaojun Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantized Thouless pumps protected by interactions in dimerized Rydberg tweezer arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.09311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.09311v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study Thouless pumps, i.e., adiabatic topological transport, in an interacting spin chain described by the dimerized XXZ Hamiltonian. In the noninteracting case, quantized Thouless pumps can only occur when a topological singularity is encircled adiabatically. In contrast, here we show that, in the presence of interactions, such topological transport can even persist for exotic paths in which the system gets arbitrarily close to the noninteracting singularity. We illustrate the robustness of these exotic Thouless pumps through the behavior of the noninteracting singularity, which for sufficiently strong interactions splits into two singularities separated by a spontaneous antiferromagnetic insulator. We perform a numerical benchmark of these phenomena by means of tensor network simulations of ground-state physics and real-time adiabatic dynamics. Finally, we propose an experimental protocol with Floquet-driven Rydberg tweezer arrays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.09311v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.110.023328</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 110, 023328 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sergi Juli\`a-Farr\'e, Javier Arg\"uello-Luengo, Lo\"ic Henriet, Alexandre Dauphin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extracting Universal Corner Entanglement Entropy during the Quantum Monte Carlo Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.13876v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The subleading corner logarithmic corrections in entanglement entropy (EE) are crucial for revealing universal characteristics of the quantum critical points (QCPs), but they are challenging to detect. Motivated by recent developments in the stable computation of EE in (2+1)D quantum many-body systems, we have developed a new method for directly measuring the corner contribution in EE with less computational cost. The cornerstone of our approach is to measure the subtracted corner entanglement entropy (SCEE) defined as the difference between the EEs of subregions with the same boundary length for smooth and cornered boundaries during the sign-problem free quantum Monte Carlo simulation. Our improved method inherently eliminates not only the area law term of EE but also the subleading log-corrections arising from Goldstone modes, leaving the universal corner contribution as the leading term of SCEE with greatly improved data quality. Utilizing this advanced approach, we calculate the SCEE of the bilayer Heisenberg model on both square and honeycomb lattices across their (2+1)D O(3) QCPs with different opening angles on entanglement boundary, and obtain the accurate values of the corresponding universal corner log-coefficients. These findings will encourage further theoretical investigations to access controlled universal information for interacting CFTs at (2+1)D.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.13876v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuan Da Liao, Menghan Song, Jiarui Zhao, Zi Yang Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>All-fiber microendoscopic polarization sensing at single-photon level aided by deep-learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02172v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The polarization of light conveys crucial information about the spatial ordering and optical properties of a specimen. However, precise polarization measurement in challenging conditions, including constrained spaces, low light levels, and high-speed scenarios, remains a severe challenge. Addressing this problem, we introduce a real-time polarization measurement method accurate down to a single-photon level that provides complete information about the polarization state. Free of moving components, the polarization sensor utilizes a few-mode fiber followed by a fiber array and a detector array. The calibration of the sensor relies on a neural network yielding unprecedented accuracy across all polarization states, including partially polarized light. We validate the approach by visualizing the polarization structure of a biological specimen. Our method offers an efficient and reliable solution for real-time polarization sensing and microendoscopy under low-light conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02172v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Bielak, Dominik Va\v{s}inka, Miroslav Je\v{z}ek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The two-spin enigma: from the helium atom to quantum ontology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05169v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The purpose of this article is to provide a novel approach and justification of the idea that classical physics and quantum physics can neither function nor even be conceived one without the other - in line with ideas attributed to e.g. Niels Bohr or Lev Landau. Though this point of view may go against current common wisdom, we will show that it perfectly fits with empirical evidence, and can be maintained without giving up physical realism. In order to place our arguments in a convenient historical perspective, we will proceed as if we were following the path of a police investigation, about the demise, or vanishing, of some valuable properties of the two electrons in the helium atom. We will start from experimentally based evidence in order to analyse and explain physical facts, moving cautiously from a classical to a quantum description, without mixing them up. The overall picture will be that the physical properties of microscopic systems are quantized, as initially shown by Planck and Einstein, and they are also contextual, i.e. that they can be given a physical sense only by embedding a microscopic system within a macroscopic measurement context.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05169v2</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philippe Grangier, Alexia Auffeves, Nayla Farouki, Mathias Van Den Bossche, Olivier Ezratty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear Quantum Optics at a Topological Interface Enabled by Defect Engineering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08750</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08750v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The integration of topology into photonics has generated a new design framework for constructing robust and unidirectional waveguides, which are not feasible with traditional photonic devices. Here, we overcome current barriers to the successful integration of quantum emitters such as quantum dots (QDs) into valley-Hall (VH) topological waveguides, utilising photonic defects at the topological interface to stabilise the local charge environment and inverse design for efficient topological-conventional mode conversion. By incorporating QDs within defects of VH-photonic crystals, we demonstrate the first instances of single-photon resonant fluorescence and resonant transmission spectroscopy of a quantum emitter at a topological waveguide interface. Our results bring together topological photonics with optical nonlinear effects at the single-photon level, offering a new avenue to investigate the interaction between topology and quantum nonlinear systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08750v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Hallacy, N. J. Martin, M. Jalali Mehrabad, D. Hallett, X. Chen, R. Dost, A. Foster, L. Brunswick, A. Fenzl, E. Clarke, P. K. Patil, A. M Fox, M. S. Skolnick, L. R. Wilson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Potential Enabling Technologies for 7G Networks: Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11072v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Every new generation of mobile networks brings significant advances in two segments, enhancement of the network parameters within the legacy technologies and introduction of new technologies enabling new paradigms in designing the networks. In the first class of enhancements the effort is to increase data rates, improve energy efficiency, enhance connectivity, reduce data transmission latency etc. In the second class of innovations for 6G and 7G, we anticipate focus on optimum integration of advanced ML and AI in general, and quantum computing with the continuous interest in the satellite networks for optimal quantum key distribution . By introducing quantum technology 7G will be able to speed up computing processes in the net, enhance network security as well as to enable distributed QC, which is a new paradigm in computer sciences.
  Using advanced networks as a basic ingredient of inter system integration, here we focus only on the second segment of anticipated innovations in networking and present a survey of the subset of potential technology enablers for the above concept with special emphasis on the inter dependency of the solutions chosen in different segments of the network. In Section II, we present several anticipated 6G/7G (system of systems type) network optimization examples resulting in a new paradigm of network optimization indicating a need for quantum computing and quantum computing based optimization algorithms. In Section III we survey work on quantum cryptography and QKD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11072v2</guid>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Savo Glisic</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
