<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 05:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Vacuum polarization in a one-dimensional effective quantum-electrodynamics model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07246v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With the aim of progressing toward a practical implementation of an effective quantum-electrodynamics (QED) theory of atoms and molecules, which includes the effects of vacuum polarization through the creation of virtual electron-positron pairs but without the explicit photon degrees of freedom, we study a one-dimensional effective QED model of the hydrogen-like atom with delta-potential interactions. This model resembles the three-dimensional effective QED theory with Coulomb interactions while being substantially simpler. We provide some mathematical details about the definition of this model, calculate the vacuum-polarization density, and the Lamb-type shift of the bound-state energy, correcting and extending results of previous works. We also study the approximation of the model in a finite plane-wave basis, and in particular we discuss the basis convergence of the bound-state energy and eigenfunction, of the vacuum-polarization density, and of the Lamb-type shift of the bound-state energy. We highlight the difficulty of converging the vacuum-polarization density in a finite basis and we propose a way to improve it. The present work could give hints on how to perform similar calculations for the three-dimensional effective QED theory of atoms and molecules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07246v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timoth\'ee Audinet (LCT), Umberto Morellini (CEREMADE), Antoine Levitt (LMO), Julien Toulouse (LCT, IUF)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalization of the exact Eriksen and exponential operators of the Foldy-Wouthuysen transformation to arbitrary-spin particles in nonstationary fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07251v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Time-dependent terms in Hamiltonians and equations of motion can be rather important for a quantum-mechanical description of a particle in nonstationary fields. We use the Foldy-Wouthuysen transformation which allows one to obtain the Schr\"{o}dinger picture of relativistic quantum mechanics. We consider particles with arbitrary spins in nonstationary fields. Unlike previous publications, we determine exact Eriksen and exponential operators of the Foldy-Wouthuysen transformation in this general case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07251v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander J. Silenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Empirical Quantum Advantage Analysis of Quantum Kernel in Gene Expression Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07276</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07276v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The incorporation of quantum ansatz with machine learning classification models demonstrates the ability to extract patterns from data for classification tasks. However, taking advantage of the enhanced computational power of quantum machine learning necessitates dealing with various constraints. In this paper, we focus on constraints like finding suitable datasets where quantum advantage is achievable and evaluating the relevance of features chosen by classical and quantum methods. Additionally, we compare quantum and classical approaches using benchmarks and estimate the computational complexity of quantum circuits to assess real-world usability. For our experimental validation, we selected the gene expression dataset, given the critical role of genetic variations in regulating physiological behavior and disease susceptibility. Through this study, we aim to contribute to the advancement of quantum machine learning methodologies, offering valuable insights into their potential for addressing complex classification challenges in various domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07276v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arpita Ghosh, MD Muhtasim Fuad, Seemanta Bhattacharjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chaos in Time: A Dissipative Continuous Quasi Time Crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07297</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07297v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: While a generic open quantum system decays to its steady state, continuous time crystals (CTCs) develop spontaneous oscillation and never converge to a stationary state. Just as crystals develop correlations in space, CTCs do so in time. Here, we introduce a Continuous Quasi Time Crystals (CQTC). Despite being characterized by the presence of non-decaying oscillations, this phase does not retain its long-range order, making it the time analogous of quasi-crystal structures. We investigate the emergence of this phase in a system made of two coupled collective spin sub-systems, each developing a CTC phase upon the action of a strong enough drive. The addition of a coupling enables the emergence of different synchronized phases, where both sub-systems oscillate at the same frequency. In the transition between different CTC orders, the system develops chaotic dynamics with aperiodic oscillations. These chaotic features differ from those of closed quantum systems, as the dynamics is not characterized by a unitary evolution. At the same time, the presence of non-decaying oscillations makes this phenomenon distinct from other form of chaos in open quantum system, where the system decays instead. We investigate the connection between chaos and this quasi-crystalline phase using mean-field techniques, and we confirm these results including quantum fluctuations at the lowest order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07297v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Parvinder Solanki, Fabrizio Minganti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-stage relaxation of operators through domain wall and magnon dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07298v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The out-of-time ordered correlator (OTOC) has become a popular probe for quantum information spreading and thermalization. In systems with local interactions, the OTOC defines a characteristic butterfly lightcone that separates a regime not yet disturbed by chaos from one where time-evolved operators and the OTOC approach their equilibrium value. This relaxation has been shown to proceed in two stages, with the first stage exhibiting an extensive timescale and a decay rate slower than the gap of the transfer matrix -- known as the ``phantom eigenvalue". In this work, we investigate the two-stage relaxation of the OTOC towards its equilibrium value in various local quantum circuits. We apply a systematic framework based on an emergent statistical model, where the dynamics of two single-particle modes -- a domain wall and a magnon -- govern the decay rates. Specifically, a configuration with coexisting domain wall and magnon modes generates the phantom rate in the first stage, and competition between these modes determines the second stage. We also examine this relaxation within the operator cluster picture. The magnon modes translates into a bound state of clusters and domain wall into a random operator, giving consistent rates. Finally, we extend our findings from random in time circuits to a broad class of Floquet models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07298v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheryne Jonay, Cathy Li, Tianci Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strategies for entanglement distribution in optical fiber networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07306</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07306v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Distributing entanglement over long distances remains a challenge due to its fragility when exposed to environmental effects. In this work, we compare various entanglement distribution protocols in a realistic noisy fiber network. We focus specifically on two schemes that only require the sending of a non-entangled carrier photon to remote nodes of the network. These protocols rely on optical CNOT gates and we vary the probability with which they can be successfully performed. Encoding our entangled states in photon polarization, we analyse the effect of depolarizing noise on the photonic states as the carrier passes through the fibers. Building a robust model of photon loss and calculating the distillable entanglement of the noisy states, we find the entanglement distribution rate. We discover that methods involving a separable carrier can reach a higher rate than the standard entanglement distribution protocol, provided that the success probability of the optical CNOT gates is sufficiently high.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07306v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hannah McAleese, Anuj Agrawal, Vivek Vasan, Conall J. Campbell, Adam G. Hawkins, Daniel C. Kilper, Mauro Paternostro, Marco Ruffini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Metrology for Gravitational Wave Astronomy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07313v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Einstein's General Theory of Relativity predicts that accelerating mass distributions produce gravitational radiation, analogous to electromagnetic radiation from accelerating charges. These gravitational waves have not been directly detected to date, but are expected to open a new window to the Universe in the near future. Suitable telescopes are kilometre-scale laser interferometers measuring the distance between quasi free-falling mirrors. Recent advances in quantum metrology may now provide the required sensitivity boost. So-called squeezed light is able to quantum entangle the high-power laser fields in the interferometer arms, and could play a key role in the realization of gravitational wave astronomy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07313v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/ncomms1122</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature communications 1 121 (2010)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Roman Schnabel, Nergis Mavalvala, David E. McClelland, Ping Koy Lam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A finite-resource description of a measurement process and its implications for the "Wigner's Friend" scenario</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07327v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum mechanics started out as a theory to describe the smallest scales of energy in Nature. After hundred years of development it is now routinely employed to describe, for example, quantum computers with thousands of qubits. This tremendous progress turns the debate of foundational questions into a technological imperative. In what follows we introduce a model of a quantum measurement process that consistently includes the impact of having access only to finite resources when describing a macroscopic system, like a measurement apparatus. Leveraging modern tools from equilibration of closed systems and typicality, we show how the collapse can be seen as an effective description of a closed dynamics, of which we do not know all its details. Our model is then exploited to address the ``Wigner Friend Scenario'', and we observe that an agreement is reached when both Wigner and his friend acknowledge their finite resources perspective and describe the measurement process accordingly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07327v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fernando de Melo, Gabriel Dias Carvalho, Pedro S. Correia, Paola Concha Obando, Thiago R. de Oliveira, Ra\'ul O. Vallejos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subtle Nuances between Quantum and Classical regimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07373v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study explores the semiclassical limit of an integrable-chaotic bosonic many-body quantum system, providing nuanced insights into its behavior. We examine classical-quantum correspondences across different interaction regimes of bosons in a triple-well potential, ranging from the integrable to the self-trapping regime, and including the chaotic one. The close resemblance between the phase-space mean projections of classical trajectories and those of Husimi distributions evokes the Principle of Uniform Semiclassical Condensation (PUSC) of Wigner functions of eigenstates. Notably, the resulting figures also exhibit patterns reminiscent of Jason Gallas's "shrimp" shapes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07373v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karin Wittmann Wilsmann, Erick R. Castro, Itzhak Roditi, Angela Foerster, Jorge G. Hirsch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of 15 dB Squeezed States of Light and their Application for the Absolute Calibration of Photoelectric Quantum Efficiency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07379v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Squeezed states of light belong to the most prominent nonclassical resources. They have compelling applications in metrology, which has been demonstrated by their routine exploitation for improving the sensitivity of a gravitational-wave detector since 2010. Here, we report on the direct measurement of 15 dB squeezed vacuum states of light and their application to calibrate the quantum efficiency of photoelectric detection. The object of calibration is a customized InGaAs positive intrinsic negative (p-i-n) photodiode optimized for high external quantum efficiency. The calibration yields a value of 99.5% with a 0.5% (k = 2) uncertainty for a photon flux of the order 10^17/s at a wavelength of 1064 nm. The calibration neither requires any standard nor knowledge of the incident light power and thus represents a valuable application of squeezed states of light in quantum metrology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07379v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.117.110801</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 117, 110801 (2016)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Henning Vahlbruch, Moritz Mehmet, Karsten Danzmann, Roman Schnabel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Density matrix renormalization group in the discrete variable representation basis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07477</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07477v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a numerical implementation of the density matrix renormalization group (DMRG) using the discrete variable representation (DVR) basis set. One main advantage of using the local DVR basis sets is that the computations of one-electron integral and two-electron repulsion integrals are drastically simplified. For comparison, we further implemented DVR complete active space configuration interaction (CASCI) using canonical molecular orbitals. These methods are applied to a one-dimensional pseudo-hydrogen chain under screened Coulomb potential. The DMRG ground state energy agrees with CASCI up to 0.1 mEh with a very small number of bond dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07477v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bing Gu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generation of Tunable Three-Photon Entanglement in Cubic Nonlinear Coupled Waveguides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07491v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically investigate the generation of three-photon states with spatial entanglement in cubic nonlinear coupled waveguides using third-order spontaneous parametric down-conversion and quantum walks. Our approach involves independently pumping two coupled waveguides to generate a path-encoded three-photon Greenberger Horne Zeilinger (GHZ) state, which then evolves with complex spatial dynamics governed by coupling coefficients and phase mismatch. By appropriate parameter tuning, we demonstrate the generation of robust heralded Bell states, uniform states, and GHZ-like states at the chip output. This work demonstrates an integrated source of three-photon spatial entanglement on a simple chip, offering additional reconfigurability for advanced multiphoton quantum applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07491v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Bacaoco, Max Galettis, James Huang, Denis Ilin, Alexander Solntsev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\mathscr{H}_2$ Model Reduction for Linear Quantum Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07603v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, an $\mathscr{H}_2$ norm-based model reduction method for linear quantum systems is presented, which can obtain a physically realizable model with a reduced order for closely approximating the original system. The model reduction problem is described as an optimization problem, whose objective is taken as an $\mathscr{H}_2$ norm of the difference between the transfer function of the original system and that of the reduced one. Different from classical model reduction problems, physical realizability conditions for guaranteeing that the reduced-order system is also a quantum system should be taken as nonlinear constraints in the optimization. To solve the optimization problem with such nonlinear constraints, we employ a matrix inequality approach to transform nonlinear inequality constraints into readily solvable linear matrix inequalities (LMIs) and nonlinear equality constraints, so that the optimization problem can be solved by a lifting variables approach. We emphasize that different from existing work, which only introduces a criterion to evaluate the performance after model reduction, we guide our method to obtain an optimal reduced model with respect to the $\mathscr{H}_2$ norm. In addition, the above approach for model reduction is extended to passive linear quantum systems. Finally, examples of active and passive linear quantum systems validate the efficacy of the proposed method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07603v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. P. Wu, S. Xue, G. F. Zhang, I. R. Petersen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Almost-quantum correlations violate the isotropy and homogeneity principles in flat space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07631v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One of fascinating phenomena of nature is quantum nonlocality, which is observed upon measurements on spacelike entangled systems. However, there are sets of post-quantum models which have stronger correlations than quantum mechanics, wherein instantaneous communication remains impossible. The set of almost quantum correlations is one of post-quantum models which satisfies all kinematic axioms of standard quantum correlations except one, meanwhile they contain correlations slightly stronger than quantum correlations. There arises the natural question whether there is some fundamental principle of nature which can genuinely characterizes quantum correlations. Here, we provide an answer and close this gap by invoking the isotropy and homogeneity principles of the flat space as a conclusive and distinguishing criterion to rule out the almost-quantum correlations model. In particular, to characterize quantum correlations we impose the isotropy and homogeneity symmetry group structure on the almost quantum correlations model and request that the joint probability distributions corresponding to the Born rule remain invariant. We prove that this condition is sufficient (and necessary) to reduce the almost quantum correlations model to quantum mechanics in both bipartite and multipartite systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07631v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akbar Fahmi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum combinatorial optimization beyond the variational paradigm: simple schedules for hard problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07646</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07646v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Advances in quantum algorithms suggest a tentative scaling advantage on certain combinatorial optimization problems. Recent work, however, has also reinforced the idea that barren plateaus render variational algorithms ineffective on large Hilbert spaces. Hence, finding annealing protocols by variation ultimately appears to be difficult. Similarly, the adiabatic theorem fails on hard problem instances with first-order quantum phase transitions. Here, we show how to use the spin coherent-state path integral to shape the geometry of quantum adiabatic evolution, leading to annealing protocols at polynomial overhead that provide orders-of-magnitude improvements in the probability to measure optimal solutions, relative to linear protocols. These improvements are not obtained on a controllable toy problem but on randomly generated hard instances (Sherrington-Kirkpatrick and Maximum 2-Satisfiability), making them generic and robust. Our method works for large systems and may thus be used to improve the performance of state-of-the-art quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07646v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tim Bode, Krish Ramesh, Tobias Stollenwerk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital reconstruction of squeezed light for quantum information processing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07666v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Squeezed light plays a vital role in quantum information processing. By nature, it is highly sensitive, which presents significant practical challenges, particularly in remote detection, traditionally requiring complex systems such as active phase locking, clock synchronization, and polarization control. Here, we propose and demonstrate an asynchronous detection method for squeezed light that eliminates the need for these complex systems. By employing radio-frequency heterodyne detection with a locally generated local oscillator and applying a series of digital unitary transformations, we successfully reconstruct squeezed states of light. We validate the feasibility of our approach in two key applications: the distribution of squeezed light over a 10 km fiber channel, and secure quantum key distribution between two labs connected via deployed fiber based on continuous variables using squeezed vacuum states without active modulation. This demonstrates a practical digital reconstruction method for squeezed light, opening new avenues for practical distributed quantum sensing networks and high-performance and long-distance quantum communication using squeezed states and standard telecom technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07666v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huy Q. Nguyen, Ivan Derkach, Adnan A. E. Hajomer, Hou-Man Chin, Akash nag Oruganti, Ulrik L. Andersen, Vladyslav Usenko, Tobias Gehring</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collective multimode strong coupling in plasmonic nanocavities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07694</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07694v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Plasmonic nanocavities enable access to the quantum properties of matter, but are often simplified to single mode models despite their complex multimode structure. Here, we show that off-resonant plasmonic modes in fact play a crucial role in strong coupling, and determine the onset of a novel collective interaction. Our analysis reveals that $n$ strongly coupled plasmonic modes, introduce up to $n(n+1)/2$ oscillation frequencies that depend on their coupling strengths and detunings from the quantum emitter. Furthermore, we identify three distinct regions as the coupling strength increases: (1) single mode, (2) multimode, and (3) collective multimode strong coupling. Our findings enhance the understanding of quantum dynamics in realistic plasmonic environments and demonstrate their potential to achieve ultra-fast energy transfer in light-driven quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07694v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Angus Crookes, Ben Yuen, Angela Demetriadou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generating and analyzing small-size datasets to explore physical observables in quantum Ising systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07701v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a detailed analysis of datasets generated from simulations of two-dimensional quantum spin systems using the quantum Ising model at absolute zero temperature. Our focus is on examining how fundamental physical properties, energy, magnetization, and entanglement entropy, evolve under varying external transverse magnetic fields and system sizes. From the Quantum Toolbox in Python (QuTiP), we simulate systems with 4, 8, and 16 spins arranged in square lattices, generating extensive datasets with 5000 samples per magnetic field value. The Hamiltonian operator incorporates quantum mechanical effects such as superposition and tunneling, challenging classical interpretations of spin states. We compute extended Pauli operators and construct the Hamiltonian to include spin-spin interactions and transverse field terms. Our analysis reveals that as the system size increases, fluctuations in energy and entanglement entropy become more evident, indicating lifted sensitivity to external perturbations and suggesting the onset of quantum phase transitions. Spin-spin correlation functions demonstrate that interactions are predominantly local, but larger systems exhibit more complex and fluctuating correlations. These findings provide valuable insights into the behavior of quantum spin systems and lay the groundwork for future machine learning applications aimed at predicting physical quantities and identifying phase transitions from a quantum perspective.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07701v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rodrigo Carmo Terin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum master equation from the eigenstate thermalization hypothesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07706</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07706v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We use the eigenstate thermalization hypothesis to derive a quantum master equation for a system weakly coupled to a chaotic finite-sized bath prepared in a pure state. We show that the emergence of Markovianity is controlled by the spectral function of the ETH and that local detailed balance emerges in the Markovian regime for a broad class of pure bath states. We numerically verify this result by comparing the master equation to dynamics computed using exact diagonalization of a chaotic Hamiltonian. We also compare the master equation to exact dynamics for an integrable bath and find that at finite size they strongly disagree. Our work puts forward eigenstate thermalization as a foundation for open quantum systems theory, thus extending it beyond ensemble bath preparations to chaotic many-body environments in generic pure states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07706v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter O'Donovan, Philipp Strasberg, Kavan Modi, John Goold, Mark T. Mitchison</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlated Rydberg Electromagnetically Induced Transparencys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07726v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the regime of Rydberg electromagnetically induced transparency, we study the correlated behaviors between the transmission spectra of a pair of probe fields passing through respective parallel one-dimensional cold Rydberg ensembles. Due to the van der Waals (vdW) interactions between Rydberg atoms, each ensemble exhibits a local optical nonlinearity, where the output EIT spectra are sensitive to both the input probe intensity and the photonic statistics. More interestingly, a nonlocal optical nonlinearity emerges between two spatially separated ensembles, as the probe transmissivity and probe correlation at the exit of one Rydberg ensemble can be manipulated by the probe field at the input of the other Rydberg ensemble. Realizing correlated Rydberg EITs holds great potential for applications in quantum control, quantum network, quantum walk and so on.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07726v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Huang, Peng-fei Wang, Han-xiao Zhang, Yu Zhu, Hong Yang, Dong Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trapped-ion quantum simulation of the Fermi-Hubbard model as a lattice gauge theory using hardware-aware native gates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07778v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Fermi-Hubbard model (FHM) is a simple yet rich model of strongly interacting electrons with complex dynamics and a variety of emerging quantum phases. These properties make it a compelling target for digital quantum simulation. Trotterization-based quantum simulations have shown promise, but implementations on current hardware are limited by noise, necessitating error mitigation techniques like circuit optimization and post-selection. A mapping of the FHM to a Z2 LGT was recently proposed that restricts the dynamics to a subspace protected by additional symmetries, and its ability for post-selection error mitigation was verified through noisy classical simulations. In this work, we propose and demonstrate a suite of algorithm-hardware co-design strategies on a trapped-ion quantum computer, targeting two key aspects of NISQ-era quantum simulation: circuit compilation and error mitigation. In particular, a novel combination of iteratively preconditioned gradient descent (IPG) and subsystem von Neumann Entropy compression reduces the 2-qubit gate count of FHM quantum simulation by 35%, consequently doubling the number of simulatable Trotter steps when used in tandem with error mitigation based on conserved symmetries, debiasing and sharpening techniques. Our work demonstrates the value of algorithm-hardware co-design to operate digital quantum simulators at the threshold of maximum circuit depths allowed by current hardware, and is broadly generalizable to strongly correlated systems in quantum chemistry and materials science.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07778v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dhruv Srinivasan, Alex Beyer, Daiwei Zhu, Spencer Churchill, Kushagra Mehta, Sashank Kaushik Sridhar, Kushal Chakrabarti, David W. Steuerman, Nikhil Chopra, Avik Dutt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric constructions of generalized dual-unitary circuits from biunitarity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07783v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a general framework for constructing solvable lattice models of chaotic many-body quantum dynamics with multiple unitary directions using biunitary connections. We show that a network of biunitary connections on the Kagome lattice naturally defines a multi-unitary circuit, where three `arrows of time' directly reflect the lattice symmetry. These models unify various constructions of hierarchical dual-unitary and triunitary gates and present new families of models with solvable correlations and entanglement dynamics. Using multilayer constructions of biunitary connections, we additionally introduce multilayer circuits with monoclinic symmetry and higher level hierarchical dual-unitary solvability and discuss their (non-)ergodicity. Our work demonstrates how different classes of solvable models can be understood as arising from different geometric structures in spacetime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07783v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael A. Rampp, Suhail A. Rather, Pieter W. Claeys</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonclassicality and sub-Planck structures of photon subtracted compass states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07793v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss the nonclassical properties of photon subtracted compass states (PSCS). Nonclassical behavior is studied using various parameters like the Wigner function, squeezing, and photon statistical parameters like Mandels Q function, secondorder correlation function, Agarwal Tara $A_3$ criterion, and photon number distribution. Further analysis is being done to investigate the subPlanck structures in the Wigner functions of these PSCS. We also show that the photon subtraction causes the loss of sensitivity due to displacement of the states in phase space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07793v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amit Das, Sobhan Sounda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tighter superadditivity relations for $l_{1}$-norm coherence measure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07803v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum coherence serves as a crucial physical resource, with its quantification emerging as a focal point in contemporary research. Superadditivity constitutes one of the most fundamental attributes in characterizing the coherence distribution in multipartite quantum systems. In this paper, we provide a way to derive tighter superadditivity inequalities of $l_1$-norm coherence measure for arbitrary multiqubit states. We present a category of superadditivity relations related to the $\alpha$-th ($\alpha\geqslant 2$) power of $l_{1}$-norm coherence $C_{l_{1}}$ under certain conditions. Our results are better than existing ones and are illustrated in detail with examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07803v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1142/S0219749924500266</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Int. J. Quant. Inform. 22(7)(2024), 2450026</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kang-Kang Yang, Zhong-Xi Shen, Zhi-Xi Wang, Shao-Ming Fei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Routing algorithm within the multiple non-overlapping paths approach for quantum key distribution networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07810</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07810v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a novel key routing algorithm for quantum key distribution (QKD) networks that utilizes a distribution of keys between remote, i.e., not directly connected by a QKD link, nodes through multiple non-overlapping paths. This approach enchases the security of QKD network by minimizing potential vulnerabilities associated with individual trusted nodes. The algorithm ensures a balanced allocation of the workload across the QKD network links, while aiming for the target key generation rate between directly connected and remote nodes. We present the results of testing the algorithm on two QKD network models consisting of 6 and 10 nodes. The testing demonstrates the ability of the algorithm to distribute secure keys among the nodes of the network in an all-to-all manner, ensuring that the information-theoretic security of the keys between remote nodes is maintained even when one of the trusted nodes is compromised. These results highlight the potential of the algorithm to improve the performance of QKD networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07810v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evgeniy O. Kiktenko, Andrey Tayduganov, Aleksey K. Fedorov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherence and entropy complementarity relations of generalized wave-particle duality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07818v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The concept of wave-particle duality holds significant importance in the field of quantum mechanics, as it elucidates the dual nature encompassing both wave-like and particle-like properties exhibited by microscopic particles. In this paper, we construct generalized measures for the predictability and visibility of $n$-path interference fringes to quantify the wave and particle properties in quantum high-dimensional systems. By employing the Morozova-Chentsov function, we ascertain that the wave-particle relationship can be delineated by the average coherence. This function exhibits a close correlation with the metric-adjusted skew information, thereby we establish complementary relations between visibility, predictability, and quantum $f$ entropy, which reveals deep connections between wave-particle duality and other physical quantities. Through our methodology, diverse functions can be selected to yield corresponding complementary relationships.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07818v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.110.042413</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 110(2024), 042413</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kang-Kang Yang, Zhi-Xi Wang, Shao-Ming Fei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frequency-bin entanglement-based quantum key distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07884v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Entanglement is an essential ingredient in many quantum communication protocols. In particular, entanglement can be exploited in quantum key distribution (QKD) to generate two correlated random bit strings whose randomness is guaranteed by the nonlocal property of quantum mechanics. Most of QKD protocols tested to date rely on polarization and/or time-bin encoding. Despite compatibility with existing fiber-optic infrastructure and ease of manipulation with standard components, frequency-bin QKD have not yet been fully explored. Here we report the first demonstration of entanglement-based QKD using frequency-bin encoding. We implement the BBM92 protocol using photon pairs generated by two independent, high-finesse, ring resonators on a silicon photonic chip. We perform a passive basis selection scheme and simultaneously record sixteen projective measurements. A key finding is that frequency-bin encoding is sensitive to the random phase noise induced by thermal fluctuations of the environment. To correct for this effect, we developed a real-time adaptive phase rotation of the measurement basis, achieving stable transmission over a 26 km fiber spool with a secure key rate &gt;= 4.5 bit/s. Our work introduces a new degree of freedom for the realization of entangled based QKD protocols in telecom networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07884v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noemi Tagliavacche, Massimo Borghi, Giulia Guarda, Domenico Ribezzo, Marco Liscidini, Davide Bacco, Matteo Galli, Daniele Bajoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating Quantum Many-Body States with Neural-Network Exponential Ansatz</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07886v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Preparing quantum many-body states on classical or quantum devices is a very challenging task that requires accounting for exponentially large Hilbert spaces. Although this complexity can be managed with exponential ans\"atze (such as in the coupled-cluster method), these approaches are often tailored to specific systems, which limits their universality. Recent work has shown that the contracted Schr\"odinger equation enables the construction of universal, formally exact exponential ans\"atze for quantum many-body physics. However, while the ansatz is capable of resolving arbitrary quantum systems, it still requires a full calculation of its parameters whenever the underlying Hamiltonian changes, even slightly. Here, inspired by recent progress in operator learning, we develop a surrogate neural network solver that generates the exponential ansatz parameters using the Hamiltonian parameters as inputs, eliminating the need for repetitive computations. We illustrate the effectiveness of this approach by training neural networks of several quantum many-body systems, including the Fermi-Hubbard model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07886v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weillei Zeng, Jiaji Zhang, Lipeng Chen, Carlos L. Benavides-Riveros</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal coarse geometry of spin systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07912v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The prospect of realizating highly entangled states on quantum processors with fundamentally different hardware geometries raises the question: to what extent does a state of a quantum spin system have an intrinic geometry? In this paper, we propose that both states and dynamics of a spin system have a canonically associated coarse geometry in the sense of Roe on the set of sites in the thermodynamic limit. For a state $\phi$ on an (abstract) spin system with an infinite collection of sites $X$, we define a universal coarse structure $\mathcal{E}_{\phi}$ on the set $X$ with the property that a state has decay of correlations with respect to a coarse structure $\mathcal{E}$ on $X$ if and only if $\mathcal{E}_{\phi}\subseteq \mathcal{E}$. We show that under mild assumptions, the coarsely connected completion $(\mathcal{E}_{\phi})_{con}$ is stable under quasi-local perturbations of the state $\phi$. We also develop in parallel a dynamical coarse structure for arbitrary quantum channels, and prove a similar stability result. We show that several order parameters of the state only depend on the coarse structure of the metric, and we establish a basic compatibility between the dynamical coarse structure associated to a quantum circuit $\alpha$ and the coarse structure of the state $\psi\circ \alpha$ where $\psi$ is any product state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07912v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Elokl, Corey Jones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Note on the Relativistic Transformation Properties of Quantum Stochastic Calculus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07915v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give a simple argument to derive the transformation of quantum stochastic calculus formalism between inertial observers, and derive the quantum open system dynamics for a system moving in a vacuum (more generally coherent) quantum field under the usual Markov approximation. We argue that for uniformly accelerated open systems, however, the formalism must breakdown as we move from a Fock representation of the quantum noise to a unitarily inequivalent non-Fock representation - in particular, the latter is a thermal representation at the Unruh temperature. The unitary inequivalence ultimately being a consequence of the underlying flat noise spectrum approximation for the fundamental quantum stochastic processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07915v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. E. Gough</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable General Error Mitigation for Quantum Circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07916v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In quantum computing, error mitigation is a method to improve the results of an error-prone quantum processor by post-processing them on a classical computer. In this work, we improve the General Error Mitigation (GEM) method for scalability. GEM relies on the use of a matrix to represent the device error, which requires the execution of $2^{n+1}$ calibration circuits on the quantum hardware, where $n$ is the number of qubits. With our improved method, the number of calibration runs is independent of the number of qubits and depends only on the number of non-zero states in the output distribution. We run 1853 randomly generated circuits with widths between 2-7 qubits and depths between 10-140 gates on IBMQ superconducting devices. The experiments show that the mitigation works comparably well to GEM, while requiring a fraction of the calibration runs. Finally, an experiment to mitigate errors in a 100 qubit circuit demonstrates the scalable features of our method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07916v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philip D\"obler, Jannik Pflieger, Fengping Jin, Hans De Raedt, Kristel Michielsen, Thomas Lippert, Manpreet Singh Jattana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classical Pre-optimization Approach for ADAPT-VQE: Maximizing the Potential of High-Performance Computing Resources to Improve Quantum Simulation of Chemical Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07920</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07920v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ADAPT-VQE algorithm is a promising method for generating a compact ansatz based on derivatives of the underlying cost function, and it yields accurate predictions of electronic energies for molecules. In this work we report the implementation and performance of ADAPT-VQE with our recently developed sparse wavefunction circuit solver (SWCS) in terms of accuracy and efficiency for molecular systems with up to 52 spin-orbitals. The SWCS can be tuned to balance computational cost and accuracy, which extends the application of ADAPT-VQE for molecular electronic structure calculations to larger basis sets and larger number of qubits. Using this tunable feature of the SWCS, we propose an alternative optimization procedure for ADAPT-VQE to reduce the computational cost of the optimization. By pre-optimizing a quantum simulation with a parameterized ansatz generated with ADAPT-VQE/SWCS, we aim to utilize the power of classical high-performance computing in order to minimize the work required on noisy intermediate-scale quantum hardware, which offers a promising path toward demonstrating quantum advantage for chemical applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07920v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Wayne Mullinax, Panagiotis G. Anastasiou, Jeffrey Larson, Sophia E. Economou, Norm M. Tubman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noise-Resilient Quantum Random Access Codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07924v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A $n^d \xrightarrow{p} 1$ Quantum Random Access Code (QRAC) is a communication task where Alice encodes $n$ classical bits into quantum states of dimension $d$ and transmits them to Bob, who performs appropriate measurements to recover the required bit with probability $p$. In the presence of a noisy environment, the performance of a QRAC is degraded, losing the advantage over classical strategies. We propose a practical technique that enables noise tolerance in such scenarios, recovering the quantum advantage in retrieving the required bit. We perform a photonic implementation of a $2^2 \xrightarrow {\text{p}} 1$ QRAC using polarization-encoded qubits under an amplitude-damping channel, where simple operations allow for noise robustness showing the revival of the quantum advantage when the noisy channel degrades the performance of the QRAC. This revival can be observed by violating a suitable dimension witness, which is closely related to the average success probability of the QRAC. This technique can be extended to other applications in the so-called prepare-and-measure scenario, enhancing the semi-device-independent protocol implementations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07924v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. S. Karthik, S. G\'omez, F. M. Quinteros, Akshata Shenoy H., M. Paw{\l}owski, S. P. Walborn, G. Lima, E. S. G\'omez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving quantum metrology protocols with programmable photonic circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07929v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Photonic quantum metrology enables the measurement of physical parameters with precision surpassing classical limits by using quantum states of light. However, generating states providing a large metrological advantage is hard because standard probabilistic methods suffer from low generation rates. Deterministic protocols using non-linear interactions offer a path to overcome this problem, but they are currently limited by the errors introduced during the interaction time. Thus, finding strategies to minimize the interaction time of these non-linearities is still a relevant question. In this work, we introduce and compare different deterministic strategies based on continuous and programmable Jaynes-Cummings and Kerr-type interactions, aiming to maximize the metrological advantage while minimizing the interaction time. We find that programmable interactions provide a larger metrological advantage than continuous operations at the expense of slightly larger interaction times. We show that while for Jaynes-Cummings non-linearities the interaction time grows with the photon number, for Kerr-type ones it decreases, favoring the scalability to big photon numbers. Finally, we also optimize different measurement strategies for the deterministically generated states based on photon-counting and homodyne detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07929v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Mu\~noz de las Heras, D. Porras, A. Gonz\'alez-Tudela</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-dependent radiative heat flux due to started thermal radiation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07931v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a theoretical formalism for time-dependent radiative heat flux from one object to another in the case where the former starts to radiate at a certain time. The time dependence is demonstrated for the heat flux between two isolated nanoparticles. After one particle starts to radiate, the emitted energy first reaches the other one with a delay according to electromagnetic retardation, and afterwards the flux shows oscillatory exponential relaxation to its stationary value. For the room or higher temperature radiation, the oscillation period and relaxation time are determined by the resonance frequency and damping rate of the particle polarizability, respectively, being equal to dozens of femtoseconds and one picosecond for silicon carbide particles. At cryogenic temperatures, the relaxation time depends on the thermal wavelength.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07931v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kiryl Asheichyk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-isometry, State-Dependence and Holography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07296v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We establish an equivalence between non-isometry of quantum codes and state-dependence of operator reconstruction, and discuss implications of this equivalence for holographic duality. Specifically, we define quantitative measures of non-isometry and state-dependence and describe bounds relating these quantities. In the context of holography we show that, assuming known gravitational path integral results for overlaps between semiclassical states, non-isometric bulk-to-boundary maps with a trivial kernel are approximately isometric and bulk reconstruction approximately state-independent. In contrast, non-isometric maps with a non-empty kernel always lead to state-dependent reconstruction. We also show that if a global bulk-to-boundary map is non-isometric, then there exists a region in the bulk which is causally disconnected from the boundary. Finally, we conjecture that, under certain physical assumptions for the definition of the Hilbert space of effective field theory in AdS space, the presence of a global horizon implies a non-isometric global bulk-to-boundary map.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07296v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Antonini, Vijay Balasubramanian, Ning Bao, ChunJun Cao, Wissam Chemissany</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Commentary on Peierls's "In defence of measurement" in Physics World, January 1991</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07359v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper is a commentary on Rudolph Peierls's "In defence of measurement" Physics World 19-20, January 1991 to accompany the reprint of this paper for the special volume dedicated to the celebration of the centenary of the discovery of quantum mechanics by Werner Heisenberg, to be published by World Scientific in July 2025.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07359v1</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tuck C Choy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Thouless Pumping in the Generalized Creutz Model: A Graphical Method and Modulation Schemes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07610v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Thouless pumping with nontrivial topological phases provides a powerful means for the manipulation of matter waves in one-dimensional lattice systems. The band topology is revealed by the quantization of pumped charge. In the context of Thouless pumping, we present a graphical representation for the topological phases characterized by the Chern number of an effective two-dimensional band. We illustrate how the two topological phases with distinct Zak phase is connected in the pumping process. Such a visual depiction exhibits typical patterns that is directly related to a linking number and to the Chern number, allowing for the construction of Thouless pumping schemes in a practical way. As a demonstration, we present a generalized Creutz model with tunable Peierls phase, inter-leg imbalance and diagonal hopping. Various modulation schemes for Thouless pumping are studied, focusing on their graphical representations in Bloch space, as well as the quantized pumping phenomenon in real space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07610v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan-Jue Lv, Yang Peng, Yong-Kai Liu, Yi Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-time propagation of adaptive sampling selected configuration interaction wave function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07615v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We have developed a new time propagation method, time-dependent adaptive sampling configuration interaction (TD-ASCI), to describe the dynamics of a strongly correlated system. We employ the short iterative Lanczos (SIL) method as the time-integrator, which provides a unitary, norm-conserving, and stable long-time propagation scheme. We used the TD-ASCI method to evaluate the time-domain correlation functions of molecular systems. The accuracy of the correlation function was assessed by Fourier transforming (FT) into the frequency domain to compute the dipole-allowed absorption spectra. The FT has been carried out with a short-time signal of the correlation function to reduce the computation time, using an efficient alternative FT scheme based on the ESPRIT signal processing algorithm. We have applied the {TD-ASCI} method to prototypical strongly correlated molecular systems and compared the absorption spectra to spectra evaluated using the equation of motion coupled cluster (EOMCC) method with a truncation at single-doubles-triples (SDT) level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07615v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Avijit Shee, Zhen Huang, Martin Head-Gordon, K. Birgitta Whaley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic resonance in vibrational polariton chemistry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07616v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we systematically investigate the impact of ambient noise intensity on the rate modifications of ground-state chemical reactions in an optical cavity under vibrational strong-coupling conditions. To achieve this, we utilize a numerically exact open quantum system approach--the hierarchical equations of motion in twin space, combined with a flexible tree tensor network state solver. Our findings reveal a stochastic resonance phenomenon in cavity-modified chemical reactivities: an optimal reaction rate enhancement occurs at an intermediate noise level. In other words, this enhancement diminishes if ambient noise, sensed by the cavity-molecule system through cavity leakage, is either too weak or excessively strong. In the collective coupling regime, when the cavity is weakly damped, rate enhancement strengthens as more molecules couple to the cavity. In contrast, under strong cavity damping, reaction rates decline as the number of molecules grows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07616v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yaling Ke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin entanglement in antiferromagnetic spin-1 Bose-Einstein condensates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07637v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the spin entanglement in a spin-1 Bose-Einstein condensate with antiferromagnetic atomic interactions using the Hartree-Fock approach. Based on the isomorphism between symmetric $N$-qubit states and spin-$j=N/2$ states, we analyze the negativity of the spin-1 ground state of the condensate viewed as a two spins $1/2$, and explore its dependence with the temperature and external Zeeman fields. The scope of this type of entanglement is highlighted and contrasted with other types of entanglement, as the mode and particle entanglement. It is shown that, at finite temperatures, there is a strong dependence of the negativity with respect to the strengths of quadratic Zeeman fields and the spin-spin interactions of the condensate. Interestingly, in the antiferromagnetic ground-state phase, the negativity and the linear Zeeman field are connected quadratically through the equation of a simple circle, in which its radius depends on the temperature. On the other hand, for the polar phase, being the phase that exhibits the highest degree of entanglement, we were able to identify a clear dependency on the spin-spin interactions and the Zeeman fields that can be expressed analytically in a closed form as a function of the temperature. This results might be relevant for applications in quantum information and metrology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07637v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Santiago, F. Mireles, E. Serrano-Ens\'astiga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$2$-R\'enyi CCNR Negativity of Compact Boson for multiple disjoint intervals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07698v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate mixed-state bipartite entanglement between multiple disjoint intervals using the computable cross-norm criterion (CCNR). We consider entanglement between a single interval and the union of remaining disjoint intervals, and compute $2$-R\'enyi CCNR negativity for $2$d massless compact boson. The expression for $2$-R\'enyi CCNR negativity is given in terms of cross-ratios and Riemann period matrices of Riemann surfaces involved in the calculation. In general, the Riemann surfaces involved in the calculation of $n$-R\'enyi CCNR negativity do not possess a $Z_n$ symmetry. We also evaluate the Reflected R\'enyi entropy related to the $2$-R\'enyi CCNR negativity. This Reflected R\'enyi entropy is a universal quantity. We extend these calculations to the $2$d massless Dirac fermions as well. Finally, the analytical results are checked against the numerical evaluations in the tight-binding model and are found to be in good agreement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07698v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Himanshu Gaur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological resilience of optical skyrmions in local decoherence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07775</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07775v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The concept of skyrmions was introduced as early as the 1960s by Tony Skyrme. The topologically protected configuration embedded in skyrmions has prompted some investigations into their fundamental properties and versatile applications, sparking interest and guiding ongoing development. The topological protection associated with skyrmions was initially observed in systems with interactions. It is widely believed that skyrmions are stable yet relevant confirmation and empirical research remains limited. A pertinent question is whether skyrmion configurations formed by single-particle wave functions also exhibit topological stability. In this study, we affirm this hypothesis by investigating the effects of local decoherence. We analytically and numerically demonstrate the topological resilience of skyrmions and occurrence of transition points of skyrmion numbers in local decoherence of three typical decoherence channels. On the other hand, we show that these qualities are independent of the initial state. From the numerical results, we verify that inhomogeneous but continuous decoherence channels also adhere to the same behaviors and hold topological stability of skyrmions as homogeneous decoherence channels. These properties of skyrmions contribute to further applications in various areas including communication and imaging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07775v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Li-Wen Wang, Sheng Liu, Cheng-Jie Zhang, Geng Chen, Yong-Sheng Zhang, Chuan-Feng Li, Guang-Can Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Casimir stresses of the dielectric ball: inhomogeneity and divergences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07911v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Puzzles are still preventing people from further understanding and manipulating the Casimir interaction in spherical systems. Here we investigate the behaviors of Casimir stresses in the system consisting of a ball immersed in the background, emphasising the roles of spherical geometry and inhomogeneity. Spherical modes are employed to evaluate the Green's dyadic and thus the Casimir stresses. The inhomogeneity of the media essentially modifies the wave form of the spherical mode, leading to significant impacts on the Casimir stresses, especially when far away from the surface of the ball. As the surface approached, the divergence (surface divergence) in Casimir stresses is seen. For both homogeneous and inhomogeneous cases, the leading behaviors (zero for the radial component, and inverse quantic order of distance for the transverse components) of Casimir stresses are exactly the same as those for the corresponding planar homogeneous wall, involving only properties of media at the surface and reflecting no information about the spherical geometry and the inhomogeneity, which implies the local nature. The other surface divergences are influenced by the spherical geometry, and for the transverse component always weaker than the planar contribution. The general impacts from the inhomogeneity of media to the surface divergences are also shown. The inhomogeneity will further soften the surface divergence. For two touching media with permittivities and permeabilities equal up to high enough order of their expansion over the distance to the surface, surface divergences may disappear together with the interaction Casimir stresses. Other factors, such as the refractivity and anisotropy, are also included, which may rise considerable complexities, but typically not related to divergences. Perspectives on the renormalization of the surface divergence are briefly outlined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07911v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Mechanics from General Relativity and the Quantum Friedmann Equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07961v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we demonstrate that the recently introduced linear form of the Friedmann equations corresponds to the first-order WKB expansion of a quantum cosmological equation, indicating that both General Relativity (GR) contains aspects of Quantum Mechanics (QM) and that GR itself is part of a more general theory. Solutions of this quantum Friedmann equation are built in terms of a quantum scale factor that encapsulates the quantum effects on a free-falling particle. The quantum-modified scale factor reshapes the dynamics of the universe, removing the singularity due to the vanishing of the scale factor. A detailed example within the radiation-dominated context illustrates how these quantum solutions connect to Seiberg-Witten theory, recently applied to black holes, and incorporate resurgence phenomena and complex metrics as developed by Kontsevich, Segal, and Witten. As a result, this reveals an invariance of time parametrization under $\Gamma(2)$ transformations of the wave function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07961v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Matone, Nikolaos Dimakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunneling Spectroscopy in Superconducting Circuit Lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07997</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07997v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate tunneling spectroscopy of synthetic quantum matter in superconducting circuit lattices. We measure site-resolved excitation spectra by coupling the lattice to engineered driven-dissipative particle baths that serve as local tunneling probes. Using incoherent particle source and drain, we independently extract quasi-particle and quasi-hole spectra and reconstruct the spatial structure of collective excitations. We perform spectroscopy of a strongly interacting Bose-Hubbard lattice at different densities, observing changes in energy gaps across the superfluid to Mott-insulator transition and the effects of three-body interactions. Our results provide a new toolset for characterizing many-body states in analog quantum simulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07997v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Botao Du, Qihao Guo, Santiago L\'opez, Ruichao Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection Time Distribution for Several Quantum Particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1601.03871</link>
      <description>arXiv:1601.03871v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We address the question of how to compute the probability distribution of the time at which a detector clicks, in the situation of $n$ non-relativistic quantum particles in a volume $\Omega\subset \mathbb{R}^3$ in physical space and detectors placed along the boundary $\partial \Omega$ of $\Omega$. We have previously [arXiv:1601.03715] argued in favor of a rule for the 1-particle case that involves a Schr\"odinger equation with an absorbing boundary condition on $\partial \Omega$ introduced by Werner; we call this rule the "absorbing boundary rule." Here, we describe the natural extension of the absorbing boundary rule to the $n$-particle case. A key element of this extension is that, upon a detection event, the wave function gets collapsed by inserting the detected position, at the time of detection, into the wave function, thus yielding a wave function of $n-1$ particles. We also describe an extension of the absorbing boundary rule to the case of moving detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1601.03871v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.106.042220</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review A 106: 042220 (2022)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Roderich Tumulka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Certifying Temporal Correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.06092</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.06092v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Self-testing has been established as a major approach for quantum device certification based on experimental statistics under minimal assumptions. However, despite more than 20 years of research effort most of the self-testing protocols are restricted to spatial scenarios (Bell scenarios), without any temporal generalisations known. Under the scenario of sequential measurements performed on a single quantum system, we build upon previous works which used semi-definite programming (SDP) based methods to bound sequential measurement inequalities. For such SDPs, we show that the optimiser matrix is unique and moreover this uniqueness is robust to small deviations from the quantum bound. Further, we consider a generalised scenario in presence of quantum channels and draw analogies in the structure of Bell and sequential inequalities using the pseudo-density matrix formalism. These analogies allow us to show a practical use of maximal violations of sequential inequalities in the form of certification of quantum channels up to isometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.06092v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harshank Shrotriya, Leong-Chuan Kwek, Kishor Bharti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grothendieck inequalities characterize converses to the polynomial method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.08559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.08559v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A surprising 'converse to the polynomial method' of Aaronson et al. (CCC'16) shows that any bounded quadratic polynomial can be computed exactly in expectation by a 1-query algorithm up to a universal multiplicative factor related to the famous Grothendieck constant. Here we show that such a result does not generalize to quartic polynomials and 2-query algorithms, even when we allow for additive approximations. We also show that the additive approximation implied by their result is tight for bounded bilinear forms, which gives a new characterization of the Grothendieck constant in terms of 1-query quantum algorithms. Along the way we provide reformulations of the completely bounded norm of a form, and its dual norm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.08559v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jop Bri\"et, Francisco Escudero Guti\'errez, Sander Gribling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipatons as generalized Brownian particles for open quantum systems: Dissipaton-embedded quantum master equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.10666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.10666v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dissipaton theory had been proposed as an exact and nonperturbative approach to deal with open quantum system dynamics, where the influence of Gaussian environment is characterized by statistical quasi-particles named as dissipatons. In this work, we revisit the dissipaton equation of motion theory and establish an equivalent dissipatons-embedded quantum master equation (DQME), which gives rise to dissipatons as generalized Brownian particles. As explained in this work, the DQME supplies a direct approach to investigate the statistical characteristics of dissipatons and thus the physically supporting hybrid bath modes. Numerical demonstrations are carried out on the electron transfer model, exhibiting the transient statistical properties of the solvation coordinate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.10666v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0151239</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Chem. Phys. 158, 214110 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiang Li, Yu Su, Zi-Hao Chen, Yao Wang, Rui-Xue Xu, Xiao Zheng, YiJing Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combinatorial NLTS From the Overlap Gap Property</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.00643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.00643v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In an important recent development, Anshu, Breuckmann, and Nirkhe [ABN22] resolved positively the so-called No Low-Energy Trivial State (NLTS) conjecture by Freedman and Hastings. The conjecture postulated the existence of linear-size local Hamiltonians on n qubit systems for which no near-ground state can be prepared by a shallow (sublogarithmic depth) circuit. The construction in [ABN22] is based on recently developed good quantum codes. Earlier results in this direction included the constructions of the so-called Combinatorial NLTS -- a weaker version of NLTS -- where a state is defined to have low energy if it violates at most a vanishing fraction of the Hamiltonian terms [AB22]. These constructions were also based on codes.
  In this paper we provide a "non-code" construction of a class of Hamiltonians satisfying the Combinatorial NLTS. The construction is inspired by one in [AB22], but our proof uses the complex solution space geometry of random K-SAT instead of properties of codes. Specifically, it is known that above a certain clause-to-variables density the set of satisfying assignments of random K-SAT exhibits an overlap gap property, which implies that it can be partitioned into exponentially many clusters each constituting at most an exponentially small fraction of the total set of satisfying solutions. We establish a certain robust version of this clustering property for the space of near-satisfying assignments and show that for our constructed Hamiltonians every combinatorial near-ground state induces a near-uniform distribution supported by this set. Standard arguments then are used to show that such distributions cannot be prepared by quantum circuits with depth o(log n). Since the clustering property is exhibited by many random structures, including proper coloring and maximum cut, we anticipate that our approach is extendable to these models as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.00643v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric R. Anschuetz, David Gamarnik, Bobak Kiani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral and flavor oscillations in a hyperentangled neutrino state</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.14574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.14574v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In addition to flavor oscillations, Dirac neutrinos also undergo the so-called chiral oscillations, a consequence of the free-particle dynamics under the Dirac equation. Such a transition between different chiralities affect the flavor transitions, but also can generate non-trivial correlations between the internal degrees of freedom of the particle. In this paper, we show that the state of a massive oscillating neutrino produced by weak interaction process, is an hyperentangled state, in which flavor, chirality, and spin exhibit non-trivial correlations. Using complete complementarity relations, we show that both chiral and flavor oscillations redistribute correlations and coherence in time among different partitions of the system. In a similar way, we consider a spin entangled lepton-antineutrino pair and show that there is a dynamical redistribution of spin-spin entanglement into correlations and coherence between the other degrees-of-freedom. Our analysis provides a complete characterization of the quantum correlations involved in lepton-antineutrino pairs and in single particle neutrino evolution, and provides a further insight on possible routes to interpret and measure chiral oscillations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.14574v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Bittencourt, Massimo Blasone, Gennaro Zanfardino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Construction of perfect tensors using biunimodular vectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.01504</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.01504v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dual unitary gates are highly non-local two-qudit unitary gates that have been studied extensively in quantum many-body physics and quantum information in the recent past. A special class of dual unitary gates consists of rank-four perfect tensors that are equivalent to highly entangled multipartite pure states called absolutely maximally entangled (AME) states. In this work, numerical and analytical constructions of dual unitary gates and perfect tensors that are diagonal in a special maximally entangled basis are presented. The main ingredient in our construction is a phase-valued (unimodular) two-dimensional array whose discrete Fourier transform is also unimodular. We obtain perfect tensors for several local Hilbert space dimensions, particularly, in dimension six. A perfect tensor in local dimension six is equivalent to an AME state of four qudits, denoted as AME(4,6). Such a state cannot be constructed from existing constructions of AME states based on error-correcting codes and graph states. An explicit construction of AME(4,6) states is provided in this work using two-qudit controlled and single-qudit gates making it feasible to generate such states experimentally.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.01504v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suhail Ahmad Rather</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncertainty relations from state polynomial optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.00612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.00612v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Uncertainty relations are a fundamental feature of quantum mechanics. How can these relations be found systematically? Here we develop a semidefinite programming hierarchy for additive uncertainty relations in the variances of non-commuting observables. Our hierarchy is built on the state polynomial optimization framework, also known as scalar extension. The hierarchy is complete, in the sense that it converges to tight uncertainty relations. We improve upon upper bounds for all 1292 additive uncertainty relations on up to nine operators for which a tight bound is not known. The bounds are dimension-free and depend entirely on the algebraic relations among the operators. The techniques apply to a range of scenarios, including Pauli, Heisenberg-Weyl, and fermionic operators, and generalize to higher order moments and multiplicative uncertainty relations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.00612v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.132.200202</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review Letters 132, 200202 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mois\'es Bermejo Mor\'an, Felix Huber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VQC-Based Reinforcement Learning with Data Re-uploading: Performance and Trainability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.11555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.11555v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Reinforcement Learning (RL) consists of designing agents that make intelligent decisions without human supervision. When used alongside function approximators such as Neural Networks (NNs), RL is capable of solving extremely complex problems. Deep Q-Learning, a RL algorithm that uses Deep NNs, achieved super-human performance in some specific tasks. Nonetheless, it is also possible to use Variational Quantum Circuits (VQCs) as function approximators in RL algorithms. This work empirically studies the performance and trainability of such VQC-based Deep Q-Learning models in classic control benchmark environments. More specifically, we research how data re-uploading affects both these metrics. We show that the magnitude and the variance of the gradients of these models remain substantial throughout training due to the moving targets of Deep Q-Learning. Moreover, we empirically show that increasing the number of qubits does not lead to an exponential vanishing behavior of the magnitude and variance of the gradients for a PQC approximating a 2-design, unlike what was expected due to the Barren Plateau Phenomenon. This hints at the possibility of VQCs being specially adequate for being used as function approximators in such a context.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.11555v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s42484-024-00190-z</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Quantum Mach. Intell. 6, 53 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Rodrigo Coelho, Andr\'e Sequeira, Lu\'is Paulo Santos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arithmeticity, thinness and efficiency of qutrit Clifford+T gates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.16120</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.16120v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Clifford+T gate set is a topological generating set for PU(2), which has been well-studied from the perspective of quantum computation on a single qubit. The discovery that it generates a full S-arithmetic subgroup of PU(2) has led to a fruitful interaction between quantum computation and number theory, resulting in a proof that words in these gates cover PU(2) in an almost-optimal manner.
  In this paper we study the analogue gate set for PU(3). We show that in PU(3) the group generated by the Clifford+T gates is not arithmetic - in fact, it is a thin matrix group, namely a Zariski-dense group of infinite index in its ambient S-arithmetic group. On the other hand, we study a recently proposed extension of the Clifford+T gates, called Clifford+D, and show that these do generate a full S-arithmetic subgroup of PU(3), and satisfy a slightly weaker almost-optimal covering property than that of Clifford+T in PU(2). The proofs are different from those for PU(2): while both gate sets act naturally on a (Bruhat-Tits) tree, in PU(2) the generated group acts transitively on the vertices of the tree, and this is a main ingredient in proving both arithmeticity and efficiency. In the PU(3) Clifford+D case the action on the tree is far from being transitive. This makes the proof of arithmeticity considerably harder, and the study of efficiency by automorphic representation theory becomes more involved, and results in a covering rate which differs from the optimal one by a factor of $log_3(105)\approx 4.236$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.16120v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shai Evra, Ori Parzanchevski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fundamental limits of metrology at thermal equilibrium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.06582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.06582v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the estimation of an unknown parameter $\theta$ through a quantum probe at thermal equilibrium. The probe is assumed to be in a Gibbs state according to its Hamiltonian $H_\theta$, which is divided in a parameter-encoding term $H^{\rm P}_\theta$ and an additional, parameter-independent, control $H^{\rm C}$. Given a fixed encoding, we find the maximal Quantum Fisher Information attainable via arbitrary $H^{\rm C}$, which provides a fundamental bound on the measurement precision. We elucidate the role of quantum coherence between encoding and control in different temperature regimes, which include ground state metrology as a limiting case. In the case of locally-encoded parameters, the optimal sensitivity presents a $N^2$-scaling in terms of the number of particles of the probe, which can be reached, at finite temperature, with local measurements and no entanglement. We apply our results to paradigmatic spin chain models, showing that these fundamental limits can be approached using local two-body interactions. Our results set the fundamental limits and optimal control for metrology with thermal and ground state probes, including probes at the verge of criticality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.06582v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Abiuso, Pavel Sekatski, John Calsamiglia, Mart\'i Perarnau-Llobet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calculating the expected value function of a two-stage stochastic optimization program with a quantum algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.15029</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.15029v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Two-stage stochastic programming is a problem formulation for decision-making under uncertainty. In the first stage, the actor makes a best "here and now" decision in the presence of uncertain quantities that will be resolved in the future, represented in the objective function as the expected value function. This function is a multi-dimensional integral of the second stage optimization problem, which must be solved over all possible future scenarios. This work uses a quantum algorithm to estimate the expected value function with a polynomial speedup. Our algorithm gains its advantage through the two following observations. First, by encoding the probability distribution as a quantum wavefunction in an auxilliary register, and using this register as control logic for a phase-separation unitary, Digitized Quantum Annealing (DQA) can converge to the minimium of each scenario in the random variable in parallel. Second, Quantum Amplitude Estimation (QAE) on DQA can calculate the expected value of this per-scenario optimized wavefunction, producing an estimate for the expected value function. Quantum optimization is theorized to have a polynomial speedup for combinatorial optimization problems, and estimation error from QAE is known to converge inverse-linear in the number of samples (as opposed to the best case inverse of a square root in classical Monte Carlo). Therefore, assuming the probability distribution wavefunction can be prepared efficiently, we conclude our method has a polynomial speedup (of varying degree, depending on the optimization problem) over classical methods for estimating the expected value function. We conclude by demonstrating this algorithm on a stochastic programming problem inspired by operating the power grid under weather uncertainty.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.15029v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Caleb Rotello, Peter Graf, Matthew Reynolds, Eric B. Jones, Cody James Winkleblack, Wesley Jones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement-assisted classical capacities of some channels acting as radial multipliers on fermion algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.15440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.15440v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate a new class of unital quantum channels on $\mathrm{M}_{2^k}$, acting as radial multipliers when we identify the matrix algebra $\mathrm{M}_{2^k}$ with a finite-dimensional fermion algebra. Our primary contribution lies in the precise computation of the (optimal) rate at which classical information can be transmitted through these channels from a sender to a receiver when they share an unlimited amount of entanglement. Our approach relies on new connections between fermion algebras with the $n$-dimensional discrete hypercube $\{-1,1\}^n$. Significantly, our calculations yield exact values applicable to the operators of the fermionic Ornstein-Uhlenbeck semigroup. This advancement not only provides deeper insights into the structure and behaviour of these channels but also enhances our understanding of Quantum Information Theory in a dimension-independent context.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.15440v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\'edric Arhancet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modified Six State Cryptographic Protocol with Entangled Ancilla Component States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17046</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17046v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In a realistic situation, it is very difficult to communicate securely between two distant parties without introducing any disturbances. These disturbances might occur either due to external noise or may be due to the interference of an eavesdropper sitting in between the sender and the receiver. In this work, we probe here the existence of the possibility of the situation of generation of a secret key even if the eavesdropper is able to construct an entangled ancilla state in such a way that she can extract information from the intercepted qubit. To achieve this task, we consider and modify the six-state QKD protocol in which Eve can construct the unitary transformation that may make all ancilla components entangled at the output. Then, we calculate the mutual information between Alice and Bob and Alice and Eve, and identify the region where the secret key is generated even in the presence of Eve. We find that, in general, the mutual information of Alice and Eve depends not only on the disturbance D, but here we have shown that it also depends on the concurrence of the ancilla component states. We have further shown that it is possible to derive the disturbance-free mutual information of Alice and Eve, if Eve manipulates her entangled ancilla state in a particular manner. Thus, in this way, we are able to show that a secret key can be generated between Alice and Bob even if the disturbance is large enough. Moreover, we show that Bruss's six state QKD protocol failed to generate the secret key in the region where the modified six-state QKD protocol can generate the secret key.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17046v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rashi Jain, Satyabrata Adhikari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Operator Space Entangling Power of Quantum Dynamics and Local Operator Entanglement Growth in Dual-Unitary Circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10206v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Operator entanglement is a well-established measure of operator complexity across a system bipartition. In this work, we introduce a measure for the ability of a unitary channel to generate operator entanglement, representing an operator-level generalization of the state-space entangling power. This operator space entangling power is demonstrated to be linked to the scrambling properties of the unitary channel via the recently introduced concept of mutual averaged non-commutativity of quantum operator algebras. An upper bound for the operator space entangling power is identified, corresponding to unitary channels with scrambling properties akin to those of typical unitaries. Additionally, for Hamiltonian dynamics, we find that the short-time growth rate of the operator space entangling power matches the Gaussian scrambling rate of the bipartite out-of-time-order-correlator, establishing a direct link between information scrambling and operator entanglement generation for short time scales. Finally, we examine the average growth of local operator entanglement across a symmetric bipartition of a spin-chain. For dual-unitary circuits, a combination of analytical and numerical investigations demonstrates that the average growth of local operator entanglement exhibits two distinct regimes in relation to the operator space entangling power of the building-block gate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10206v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.110.052416</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 110, 052416 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Faidon Andreadakis, Emanuel Dallas, Paolo Zanardi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the effectiveness of the collapse in the Di\'osi-Penrose model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18494v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The possibility that gravity plays a role in the collapse of the quantum wave function has been considered in the literature, and it is of relevance not only because it would provide a solution to the measurement problem in quantum theory, but also because it would give a new and unexpected twist to the search for a unified theory of quantum and gravitational phenomena, possibly overcoming the current impasse. The Di\'osi-Penrose model is the most popular incarnation of this idea. It predicts a progressive breakdown of quantum superpositions when the mass of the system increases; as such, it is susceptible to experimental verification. Current experiments set a lower bound $R_0\gtrsim 4 \times 10^{-10}$ m for the free parameter of the model, excluding some versions of it. In this work we search for an upper bound, coming from the request that the collapse is effective enough to guarantee classicality at the macroscopic scale: we find out that not all macroscopic systems collapse effectively. If one relaxes this request, a reasonable (although to some degree arbitrary) bound is found to be: $R_0\lesssim 10^{-4}$ m. This will serve to better direct future experiments to further test the model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18494v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laria Figurato, Marco Dirindin, Jos\'e Luis Gaona-Reyes, Matteo Carlesso, Angelo Bassi, Sandro Donadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbative approach to time-dependent quantum systems and applications to one-crossing multistate Landau-Zener models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06832v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We formulate a perturbative approach for studying a class of multi-level time-dependent quantum systems with constant off-diagonal couplings and diabatic energies being odd functions of time. Applying this approach to a general multistate Landau-Zener (MLZ) model with all diabatic levels crossing at one point (named the one-crossing MLZ model), we derive analytical formulas of all its transition probabilities up to $4$th order in the couplings. For one-crossing MLZ models it is difficult to obtain such analytical results by other kinds of approximation methods; thus, these perturbative results can serve as reliable benchmarks for future studies of any one-crossing MLZ models that have not been exactly solved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06832v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rongyu Hu, Chen Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Landau-Zener-St\"uckelberg interference in edge state pumping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01629v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The adiabatic edge state pumping (ESP) in one dimensional model, which has important applications in topological phase transition and quantum simulation, has been widely performed in both theories and experiments. This phenomenon has been observed in some systems with sizes $L = 9 - 100$, and it seems that due to the topological protection, the ESP can be survived even in the presence of weak random potential. Yet the fundamental issues of adiabaticity for this process have not been clarified. In this paper, we revisit this problem and show that this process involves two non-adiabatic points during the transition between the edge state and bulk state, yielding non-abadiatic physics. As a result, the ESP can be described by the Landau-Zener-St\"{u}ckelberg (LZS) interference process, in which the relative phase between the edge state and the bulk state determine the fate of the edge state during pumping. Furthermore, in a relatively long chain with weak disorder, the ESP can break down due to the anti-crossing of the edge state and the bulk edge states. We unveil these physics in terms of non-adiabaticity. The new mechanisms for ESP unveiled in this work is readily accessible in experiment, and shall therefore offer a down-to-earth platform for the intriguing LZS dynamics in terms of edge states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01629v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. Liu, Xiaoshui Lin, Ming Gong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polynomial-time tolerant testing stabilizer states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06289</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.06289v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the following task: suppose an algorithm is given copies of an unknown $n$-qubit quantum state $|\psi\rangle$ promised $(i)$ $|\psi\rangle$ is $\varepsilon_1$-close to a stabilizer state in fidelity or $(ii)$ $|\psi\rangle$ is $\varepsilon_2$-far from all stabilizer states, decide which is the case. We show that for every $\varepsilon_1&gt;0$ and $\varepsilon_2\leq \varepsilon_1^C$, there is a $\textsf{poly}(1/\varepsilon_1)$-sample and $n\cdot \textsf{poly}(1/\varepsilon_1)$-time algorithm that decides which is the case (where $C&gt;1$ is a universal constant). Our proof includes a new definition of Gowers norm for quantum states, an inverse theorem for the Gowers-$3$ norm of quantum states and new bounds on stabilizer covering for structured subsets of Paulis using results in additive combinatorics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.06289v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Srinivasan Arunachalam, Arkopal Dutt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum information with quantum-like bits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06485</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.06485v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In previous work we have proposed a construction of quantum-like bits that could endow a large, complex classical system, for example of oscillators, with quantum-like function that is not compromised by decoherence. In the present paper we investigate further this platform of quantum-like states. Firstly, we discuss a general protocol on how to construct synchronizing networks that allow for emergent states. We then study how gates can be implemented on those states. This suggests the possibility of quantum-like computing on specially-constructed classical networks. Finally, we define a notion of measurement that allows for non-Kolmogorov interference, a feature that separates our model from a classical probabilistic system. This paper aims to explore the mathematical structure of quantum-like resources, and shows how arbitrary gates can be implemented by manipulating emergent states in those systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.06485v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Graziano Amati, Gregory D. Scholes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The role of gaps in digitized counterdiabatic QAOA for fully-connected spin models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.03503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.03503v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, digitized-counterdiabatic (CD) corrections to the quantum approximate optimization algorithm (QAOA) have been proposed, yielding faster convergence within the desired accuracy than standard QAOA. In this manuscript, we apply this approach to a fully-connected spin model with random couplings. We show that the performances of the algorithm are related to the spectral properties of the instances analyzed. In particular, the larger the gap between the ground state and the first excited states, the better the convergence to the exact solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.03503v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mara Vizzuso, Gianluca Passarelli, Giovanni Cantele, Procolo Lucignano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Memory-Augmented Hybrid Quantum Reservoir Computing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09886v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Reservoir computing (RC) is an effective method for predicting chaotic systems by using a high-dimensional dynamic reservoir with fixed internal weights, while keeping the learning phase linear, which simplifies training and reduces computational complexity compared to fully trained recurrent neural networks (RNNs). Quantum reservoir computing (QRC) uses the exponential growth of Hilbert spaces in quantum systems, allowing for greater information processing, memory capacity, and computational power. However, the original QRC proposal requires coherent injection of inputs multiple times, complicating practical implementation. We present a hybrid quantum-classical approach that implements memory through classical post-processing of quantum measurements. This approach avoids the need for multiple coherent input injections and is evaluated on benchmark tasks, including the chaotic Mackey-Glass time series prediction. We tested our model on two physical platforms: a fully connected Ising model and a Rydberg atom array. The optimized model demonstrates promising predictive capabilities, achieving a higher number of steps compared to previously reported approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09886v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Settino, L. Salatino, L. Mariani, M. Channab, L. Bozzolo, S. Vallisa, P. Barill\`a, A. Policicchio, N. Lo Gullo, A. Giordano, C. Mastroianni, F. Plastina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying nonclassical correlation via the generalized Wigner-Yanase skew information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11198v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Nonclassical correlation is an important concept in quantum information theory, referring to a special type of correlation that exists between quantum systems, which surpasses the scope of classical physics. In this paper, we introduce the concept of a family of information with important properties, namely the generalized Wigner-Yanase skew information, of which the famous quantum Fisher information and Wigner-Yanase skew information are special cases. We classify the local observables in the generalized Wigner-Yanase skew information into two categories (i.e., orthonormal bases and a Hermitian operator with a fixed nondegenerate spectrum), and based on this, we propose two different forms of indicators to quantify nonclassical correlation of bipartite quantum states. We have not only investigated some important properties of these two kinds of indicators but also illustrated through specific examples that they can indeed capture some nonclassical correlation. Furthermore, we find that these two types of indicators reduce to entanglement measure for bipartite pure states. Specifically, we also derive the relationship between these two indicators and the entanglement measure $I$-concurrence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11198v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan Hong, Xinlan Hao, Limin Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An exact analytical solution for Dicke superradiance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19040</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.19040v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We revisit the Dicke superradiance problem, namely finding the time evolution of the density operator for an initially inverted ensemble of $N$ identical two-level systems (spins), undergoing collective spontaneous decay. We derive a compactly written, easily computable and fully analytical solution, valid for any time during the evolution and for any $N$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.19040v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raphael Holzinger, Claudiu Genes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal bounds for quantum metrology in the presence of correlated noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01881</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01881v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We derive fundamental bounds for general quantum metrological models involving both temporal or spatial correlations (mathematically described by quantum combs), which may be effectively computed in the limit of a large number of probes or sensing channels involved. Although the bounds are not guaranteed to be tight in general, their tightness may be systematically increased by increasing numerical complexity of the procedure. Interestingly, this approach yields bounds tighter than the state of the art also for uncorrelated channels. We apply the bound to study the limits for the most general adaptive phase estimation models in the presence of temporally correlated dephasing. We consider dephasing both parallel (no Heisenberg scaling) and perpendicular (Heisenberg scaling possible) to the signal. In the former case our new bounds show that negative correlations are beneficial, for the latter we show evidence that the bounds are tight.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01881v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stanislaw Kurdzialek, Francesco Albarelli, Rafal Demkowicz-Dobrzanski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entangling power of symmetric multiqubit systems: a geometrical approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.03361v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Unitary gates with high entangling capabilities are relevant for several quantum-enhanced technologies. For symmetric multiqubit systems, such as spin states or bosonic systems, the particle exchange symmetry restricts these gates and also the set of not-entangled states. In this work, we analyze the entangling power of unitary gates in these systems by reformulating it as an inner product between vectors with components given by SU$(2)$ invariants. For small number of qubits, this approach allows us to study analytically the entangling power including the detection of the unitary gate that maximizes it. We observe that extremal unitary gates exhibit entanglement distributions with high rotational symmetry, same that are linked to a convex combination of Husimi functions of certain states. Furthermore, we explore the connection between entangling power and the Schmidt numbers admissible in some quantum state subspaces. Thus, the geometrical approach presented here suggests new paths for studying entangling power linked to other concepts in quantum information theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.03361v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eduardo Serrano-Ens\'astiga, Diego Morachis Galindo, Jes\'us A. Maytorena, Chryssomalis Chryssomalakos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-enhanced sensing of spin-orbit coupling without fine-tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00598v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Spin-orbit coupling plays an important role in both fundamental physics and technological applications. Precise estimation of the spin-orbit coupling is necessary for accurate designing across various physical setups such as solid state devices and quantum hardware. Here, we exploit quantum features in a 1D quantum wire for estimating the Rashba spin-orbit coupling with enhanced sensitivity beyond the capability of classical probes. The Heisenberg limited enhanced precision is achieved across a wide range of parameters and does not require fine tuning. Such advantage is directly related to the gap-closing nature of the probe across the entire relevant range of parameters. This provides clear advantage over conventional criticality-based quantum sensors in which quantum enhanced sensitivity can only be achieved through fine-tuning around the phase transition point. We have demonstrated quantum enhanced sensitivity for both single particle and interacting many-body probes. In addition to extending our results to thermal states and the multi-parameter scenario, we have provided an measurement basis to perform close to the ultimate precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00598v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bin Yi, Abolfazl Bayat, Saubhik Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Hamiltonian, structure and trace distance learning of Gaussian states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03163</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03163v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we initiate the study of Hamiltonian learning for positive temperature bosonic Gaussian states, the quantum generalization of the widely studied problem of learning Gaussian graphical models. We obtain efficient protocols, both in sample and computational complexity, for the task of inferring the parameters of their underlying quadratic Hamiltonian under the assumption of bounded temperature, squeezing, displacement and maximal degree of the interaction graph. Our protocol only requires heterodyne measurements, which are often experimentally feasible, and has a sample complexity that scales logarithmically with the number of modes. Furthermore, we show that it is possible to learn the underlying interaction graph in a similar setting and sample complexity. Taken together, our results put the status of the quantum Hamiltonian learning problem for continuous variable systems in a much more advanced state when compared to spins, where state-of-the-art results are either unavailable or quantitatively inferior to ours. In addition, we use our techniques to obtain the first results on learning Gaussian states in trace distance with a quadratic scaling in precision and polynomial in the number of modes, albeit imposing certain restrictions on the Gaussian states. Our main technical innovations are several continuity bounds for the covariance and Hamiltonian matrix of a Gaussian state, which are of independent interest, combined with what we call the local inversion technique. In essence, the local inversion technique allows us to reliably infer the Hamiltonian of a Gaussian state by only estimating in parallel submatrices of the covariance matrix whose size scales with the desired precision, but not the number of modes. This way we bypass the need to obtain precise global estimates of the covariance matrix, controlling the sample complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03163v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Fanizza, Cambyse Rouz\'e, Daniel Stilck Fran\c{c}a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning the closest product state</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04283v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the problem of finding a product state with optimal fidelity to an unknown $n$-qubit quantum state $\rho$, given copies of $\rho$. This is a basic instance of a fundamental question in quantum learning: is it possible to efficiently learn a simple approximation to an arbitrary state? We give an algorithm which finds a product state with fidelity $\varepsilon$-close to optimal, using $N = n^{\text{poly}(1/\varepsilon)}$ copies of $\rho$ and $\text{poly}(N)$ classical overhead. We further show that estimating the optimal fidelity is NP-hard for error $\varepsilon = 1/\text{poly}(n)$, showing that the error dependence cannot be significantly improved.
  For our algorithm, we build a carefully-defined cover over candidate product states, qubit by qubit, and then demonstrate that extending the cover can be reduced to approximate constrained polynomial optimization. For our proof of hardness, we give a formal reduction from polynomial optimization to finding the closest product state. Together, these results demonstrate a fundamental connection between these two seemingly unrelated questions. Building on our general approach, we also develop more efficient algorithms in three simpler settings: when the optimal fidelity exceeds $5/6$; when we restrict ourselves to a discrete class of product states; and when we are allowed to output a matrix product state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04283v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ainesh Bakshi, John Bostanci, William Kretschmer, Zeph Landau, Jerry Li, Allen Liu, Ryan O'Donnell, Ewin Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic parameterized quantum circuits: expressive and barren-plateau free</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05760v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Classical optimization of parameterized quantum circuits is a widely studied methodology for the preparation of complex quantum states, as well as the solution of machine learning and optimization problems. However, it is well known that many proposed parameterized quantum circuit architectures suffer from drawbacks which limit their utility, such as their classical simulability or the hardness of optimization due to a problem known as "barren plateaus". We propose and study a class of dynamic parameterized quantum circuit architectures. These are parameterized circuits containing intermediate measurements and feedforward operations. In particular, we show that these architectures: 1. Provably do not suffer from barren plateaus. 2. Are expressive enough to describe arbitrarily deep unitary quantum circuits. 3. Are competitive with state of the art methods for the preparation of ground states and facilitate the representation of nontrivial thermal states. These features make the proposed architectures promising candidates for a variety of applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05760v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhinav Deshpande, Marcel Hinsche, Sona Najafi, Kunal Sharma, Ryan Sweke, Christa Zoufal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement incompatibility under loss</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05920</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05920v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Measurement incompatibility plays a critical role in quantum information processing, as it is essential for the violation of Bell and steering inequalities. Identifying sets of incompatible measurements is thus a key task in this field. However, practical implementations of quantum systems are inherently noisy, making it crucial to understand how noise affects measurement incompatibility. While it is known that noise can destroy incompatibility, it cannot create it. Despite extensive research on measurement incompatibility in finite-dimensional systems -- often tackled using semi-definite programming -- there has been limited progress in understanding this phenomenon in infinite-dimensional continuous-variable (CV) systems, which are highly relevant for quantum information applications. In this work, we investigate the measurement incompatibility of CV systems under the influence of pure losses, a fundamental noise source in quantum optics and a significant challenge for long-distance quantum communication. We first establish a quantitative relationship between the degree of loss and the minimum number of measurements required to maintain incompatibility. Furthermore, we design a set of measurements that remains incompatible even under extreme losses, where the number of measurements in the set increases with the amount of loss. Importantly, these measurements rely on on-off photo-detection and linear optics, making them feasible for implementation in realistic laboratory conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05920v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Mehboudi, Fatemeh Rezaeinia, Saleh Rahimi-Keshari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jacobi matrices that realize perfect quantum state transfer and early state exclusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06047v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we show how to construct 1D Hamiltonians, that is, Jacobi matrices, that realize perfect quantum state transfer and also have the property that the overlap of the time evolved state with the initial state is zero for some time before the transfer time. If the latter takes place we call it an early exclusion state. We also show that in some case early state exclusion is impossible. The proofs rely on properties of Krawtchouk and Chebyshev polynomials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06047v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rachel Bailey, Sara Costa, Maxim Derevyagin, Caleb Findley, Kai Zuang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universe as Klein-Gordon Eigenstates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01557</link>
      <description>arXiv:2110.01557v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We formulate Friedmann's equations as second-order linear differential equations. This is done using techniques related to the Schwarzian derivative that selects the $\beta$-times $t_\beta:=\int^t a^{-2\beta}$, where $a$ is the scale factor. In particular, it turns out that Friedmann's equations are equivalent to the eigenvalue problems $$ O_{1/2} \Psi=\frac{\Lambda}{12}\Psi \ , \qquad O_1 a =\frac{\Lambda}{3} a \ , $$ which is suggestive of a measurement problem. $O_{\beta}(\rho,p)$ are space-independent Klein-Gordon operators, depending only on energy density and pressure, and related to the Klein-Gordon Hamilton-Jacobi equations. The $O_\beta$'s are also independent of the spatial curvature, labeled by $k$, and absorbed in $$ \Psi=\sqrt a e^{\frac{i}{2}\sqrt{k}\eta} \ . $$ The above pair of equations is the unique possible linear form of Friedmann's equations unless $k=0$, in which case there are infinitely many pairs of linear equations. Such a uniqueness just selects the conformal time $\eta\equiv t_{1/2}$ among the $t_\beta$'s, which is the key to absorb the curvature term. An immediate consequence of the linear form is that it reveals a new symmetry of Friedmann's equations in flat space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2110.01557v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-021-09865-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur.Phys.J.C 81 (2021) 12, 1052</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Marco Matone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fragmented superconductivity in the Hubbard model as solitons in Ginzburg-Landau theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.11820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.11820v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The phenomena of superconductivity and charge density waves are observed in close vicinity in many strongly correlated materials. Increasing evidence from experiments and numerical simulations suggests both phenomena can also occur in an intertwined manner, where the superconducting order parameter is coupled to the electronic density. Employing density matrix renormalization group simulations, we investigate the nature of such an intertwined state of matter stabilized in the phase diagram of the elementary $t$-$t^\prime$-$U$ Hubbard model in the strong coupling regime. Remarkably, the condensate of Cooper pairs is shown to be fragmented in the presence of a charge density wave where more than one pairing wave function is macroscopically occupied. Moreover, we provide conclusive evidence that the macroscopic wave functions of the superconducting fragments are well-described by soliton solutions of a Ginzburg-Landau equation in a periodic potential constituted by the charge density wave. In the presence of an orbital magnetic field, the order parameters are gauge invariant, and superconducting vortices are pinned between the stripes. This intertwined Ginzburg-Landau theory is proposed as an effective low-energy description of the stripe fragmented superconductor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.11820v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niccol\`o Baldelli, Hannes Karlsson, Benedikt Kloss, Matthew Fishman, Alexander Wietek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the relativistic quantum mechanics of a photon between two electrons in 1+1 dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.06019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.06019v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A Lorentz-covariant system of wave equations is formulated for a quantum-mechanical three-body system in one space dimension, comprised of one photon and two identical massive spin one-half Dirac particles, which can be thought of as two electrons (or alternatively, two positrons). Manifest covariance is achieved using Dirac's formalism of multi-time wave functions, i.e, wave functions $\Psi(\textbf{x}_{\text{ph}},\textbf{x}_{\text{e}_1},\textbf{x}_{\text{e}_2})$ where $\textbf{x}_{\text{ph}},\textbf{x}_{\text{e}_1},\textbf{x}_{\text{e}_2}$ are generic spacetime events of the photon and two electrons respectively. Their interaction is implemented via a Lorentz-invariant no-crossing-of-paths boundary condition at the coincidence submanifolds $\{\textbf{x}_{\text{ph}}=\textbf{x}_{\text{e}_1}\}$ and $\{\textbf{x}_{\text{ph}}=\textbf{x}_{\text{e}_2}\}$ compatible with conservation of probability current. The corresponding initial-boundary value problem is shown to be well-posed, and it is shown that the unique solution can be represented by a convergent infinite sum of Feynman-like diagrams, each one corresponding to the photon bouncing between the two electrons a fixed number of times.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.06019v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lawrence Frolov, Samuel E. Leigh, A. Shadi Tahvildar-Zadeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A quantum picture of light-suppressed photosynthetic charge transfer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13873v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a dynamic mechanism for the reversible regulation of photosynthesis in varying light environments. We employ a three-level quantum model to take into account the correlations between charge donors and charge acceptors immediately before photoexcitation, and show that under continuous illumination, the transfer efficiency of a single charge is inversely proportional to the intensity of light, which can be suppressed so severely that it becomes a limiting factor on linear electron transport. This result is used to derive a set of analytical expressions that characterize the light response curves of photosynthetic parameters, including that of gross photosynthetic rate which saturates in high light and has long been assumed to obey a Michaelis-Menten function. We discuss the implications of thermal fluctuation in the light source, and argue that at a given intensity of light, the quantum yields measured with an incandescent lamp may be higher than those measured with a laser, a manifestation of thermal fluctuation in lamp illumination. Our new picture helps understand the observed plastocyanin-dependent electron transport in photosystem I and provides a donor-side scheme for the onset of irreversible damage to photosystem II by visible light.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13873v2</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.cplett.2024.141727</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chem. Phys. Lett. 858, 141727 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Guang Yang, Gen Tatara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The relevance of degenerate states in chiral polaritonics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16695</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16695v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work we explore theoretically whether a parity-violating/chiral light-matter interaction is required to capture all relevant aspects of chiral polaritonics or if a parity-conserving/achiral theory is sufficient (e.g. long-wavelength/dipole approximation). This question is non-trivial to answer, since achiral theories (Hamiltonians) still possess chiral solutions. To elucidate this fundamental theoretical question, a simple GaAs quantum ring model is coupled to an effective chiral mode of a single-handedness optical cavity in dipole approximation. The bare matter GaAs quantum ring possesses a non-degenerate ground state and a doubly degenerate first excited state. The chiral or achiral nature (superpositions) of the degenerate excited states remains undetermined for an isolated matter system. However, inside our parity-conserving description of a chiral cavity, we find that the dressed eigenstates automatically (ab-initio) attain chiral character and become energetically discriminated based on the handedness of the cavity. In contrast, the non-degenerate bare matter state (ground state) does not show an energetic discrimination inside a chiral cavity within dipole approximation. Nevertheless, our results suggest that the handedness of the cavity can still be imprinted onto these states (e.g. angular momentum and chiral current densities). Overall, above findings highlight the relevance of degenerate states in chiral polaritonics. In particular, because recent theoretical results for linearly polarized cavities indicate the formation of a frustrated and highly-degenerate electronic ground-state under collective strong coupling conditions, which, likewise, is expected to form in chiral polaritonics and thus could be prone to chiral symmetry breaking effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16695v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos M. Bustamante, Dominik Sidler, Michael Ruggenthaler, Angel Rubio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reflected entropy in random tensor networks III: triway cuts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17218</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17218v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For general random tensor network states at large bond dimension, we prove that the integer R\'enyi reflected entropies (away from phase transitions) are determined by minimal triway cuts through the network. This generalizes the minimal cut description of bipartite entanglement for these states. A natural extrapolation away from integer R\'enyi parameters, suggested by the triway cut problem, implies the holographic conjecture $S_R=2EW$, where $S_R$ is the reflected entropy and $EW$ is the entanglement wedge cross-section. Minimal triway cuts can be formulated as integer programs which cannot be relaxed to find a dual maximal flow/bit-thread description. This sheds light on the gap between the existence of tripartite entanglement in holographic states and the bipartite entanglement structure motivated by bit-threads. In particular, we prove that the Markov gap that measures tripartite entanglement is lower bounded by the integrality gap of the integer program that computes the triway cut.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17218v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chris Akers, Thomas Faulkner, Simon Lin, Pratik Rath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The (1+3)-dimensional 'quantum principle of relativity' is Einstein's principle of relativity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07017</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07017v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that the $(1+3)$-dimensional `superboost' operators, proposed in Dragan and Ekert's most recent work on superluminal reference frames \cite{Dragan:2022txt}, are simply the canonical Lorentz boosts, expressed in nonstandard notation. Their $(1+3)$-dimensional `superflip', which is claimed to interchange time and space dimensions for a superluminal observer, travelling with infinite speed, is equivalent to applying the identity operator together with an arbitrary relabeling. Physically, it corresponds to staying put within the canonical rest frame, then renaming space as `time' and time as `space'. We conclude that their extension of the `quantum principle of relativity', proposed in earlier work on $(1+1)$-dimensional spacetimes \cite{Dragan:2019grn}, to ordinary Minkowski space \cite{Dragan:2022txt}, is simply Einstein's principle of relativity, proposed in 1905.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07017v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew J. Lake</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-shot readout of the nuclear spin of an on-surface atom</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08704</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08704v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Nuclear spins owe their long-lived magnetic states to their excellent isolation from the environment. At the same time, a finite degree of interaction with their surroundings is necessary for reading and writing the spin state. Therefore, detailed knowledge of and control over the atomic environment of a nuclear spin is key to optimizing conditions for quantum information applications. While various platforms enabled single-shot readout of nuclear spins, their direct environments were either unknown or impossible to controllably modify on the atomic scale. Scanning tunnelling microscopy (STM), combined with electron spin resonance (ESR), provides atomic-scale information of individual nuclear spins via the hyperfine interaction. Here, we demonstrate single-shot readout of an individual $^{\text{49}}$Ti nuclear spin with an STM. Employing a pulsed measurement scheme, we find its lifetime to be in the order of seconds. Furthermore, we shed light on the pumping and relaxation mechanisms of the nuclear spin by investigating its response to both ESR driving and tunnelling current, which is supported by model calculations. These findings give an atomic-scale insight into the nature of nuclear spin relaxation and are relevant for the development of atomically assembled qubit platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08704v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evert W. Stolte, Jinwon Lee, Hester G. Vennema, Rik Broekhoven, Esther Teng, Allard J. Katan, Lukas M. Veldman, Philip Willke, Sander Otte</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stabilizing nanoparticles in the intensity minimum: feedback levitation on an inverted potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17253v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate the stable trapping of a levitated nanoparticle on top of an inverted potential using a combination of optical readout and electrostatic control. The feedback levitation on an inverted potential (FLIP) method stabilizes the particle at an intensity minimum. By using a Kalman-filter-based linear-quadratic-Gaussian (LQG) control method, we confine a particle to within $\sigma_x = (9.0 \pm 0.5) nm$ of the potential maximum at an effective temperature of $(16 \pm 1) K$ in a room-temperature environment. Despite drifts in the absolute position of the potential maximum, we can keep the nanoparticle at the apex by estimating the drift from the particle dynamics using the Kalman filter. Our approach may enable new levitation-based sensing schemes with enhanced bandwidth. It also paves the way for optical levitation at zero intensity of an optical potential, which alleviates decoherence effects due to material-dependent absorption and is hence relevant for macroscopic quantum experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17253v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Salamb\^o Dago, Jakob Rieser, Mario A. Ciampini, Vojtech Mlyn\'a\v{r}, Andreas Kugi, Markus Aspelmeyer, Andreas Deutshmann-Olek, Nikolai Kiesel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ramsey Approach to Quantum Mechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02082v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Ramsey theory enables re-shaping of the basic ideas of quantum mechanics. Quantum observables represented by linear Hermitian operators are seen as the vertices of a graph. Relations of commutation define the coloring of edges linking the vertices: if the operators commute, they are connected with a red link; if they do not commute, they are connected with a green link. Thus, a bi-colored complete Ramsey graph emerges. According to Ramsey's theorem, a complete bi-colored graph built of six vertices will inevitably contain at least one monochromatic triangle; in other words, the Ramsey number \( R(3,3) = 6 \). In our interpretation, this triangle represents the triad of observables that could or could not be established simultaneously in a given quantum system. The Ramsey approach to quantum mechanics is illustrated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02082v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Edward Bormashenko, Nir Shvalb</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trapping of Single Atoms in Metasurface Optical Tweezer Arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05321v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Optical tweezer arrays have emerged as a key experimental platform for quantum computation, quantum simulation, and quantum metrology, enabling unprecedented levels of control over single atoms and molecules. Existing methods to generate tweezer arrays mostly rely on active beam-shaping devices, such as acousto-optic deflectors or liquid-crystal spatial light modulators. However, these approaches have fundamental limitations in array geometry, size, and scalability. Here we demonstrate the trapping of single atoms in optical tweezer arrays generated via holographic metasurfaces. We realize two-dimensional arrays with more than 250 tweezer traps, arranged in arbitrary geometries with trap spacings as small as 1.5 um. The arrays have a high uniformity in terms of trap depth, trap frequency, and positional accuracy, rivaling or exceeding existing approaches. Owing to sub-micrometer pixel sizes and high pixel densities, holographic metasurfaces open a path towards optical tweezer arrays with &gt;100,000 traps, facilitating tweezer-array based quantum applications that require large system sizes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05321v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aaron Holman, Yuan Xu, Ximo Sun, Jiahao Wu, Mingxuan Wang, Bojeong Seo, Nanfang Yu, Sebastian Will</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An atomic Fabry-Perot interferometer-based acceleration sensor for microgravity environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05352</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05352v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the use of an atomic Fabry-Perot interferometer (FPI) with a pulsed non-interacting Bose-Einstein condensate (BEC) source as a space-based acceleration sensor. We derive an analytic approximation for the device's transmission under a uniform acceleration, which we use to compute the device's attainable acceleration sensitivity using the classical Fisher information. In the ideal case of a high-finesse FPI and an infinitely narrow momentum width atomic source, we find that when the total length of the device is constrained to small values, the atomic FPI can achieve greater acceleration sensitivity than a Mach-Zender (MZ) interferometer of equivalent total device length. Under the more realistic case of a finite momentum width atomic source, We identify the ideal cavity length that gives the best sensitivity. Although the MZ interferometer now offers enhanced sensitivity within currently-achievable experimental parameter regimes, our analysis demonstrates that the atomic FPI holds potential as a promising alternative in the future, provided that narrow momentum width atomic sources can be engineered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05352v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manju Perumbil, Matthew J. Blacker, Stuart S. Szigeti, Simon A. Haine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-Varying Strong Coupling and It Induced Time Diffraction of Magnon Modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06801v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Time-varying media break the temporal translation symmetry of wave propagation in materials, enabling advanced wave manipulations. However, this novel phenomenon has been rarely explored in magnonic systems due to the significant challenge of achieving a sudden and prominent change in magnon dispersion within materials. Here, we drive a ferrimagnet with periodic pump pulses to construct time-varying strong coupling between two magnon modes. We observe a change in the beats of Rabi-like oscillations near the pulse edges, indicating the time-varying strong magnon coupling and the formation of time interfaces. Using a frequency comb spectroscopy technique developed in this work, we characterize the frequency conversion of magnon modes induced by the time-varying strong coupling effect. Moreover, we construct time slits with adjacent time interfaces and demonstrate, for the first time, the double-slit time diffraction of magnon modes. The frequency spacing of the multiplied magnon modes inversely correlates with the separation between two time slits, analogous to the well-known Yang's double-slit experiment. These findings rely solely on the time-varying strong magnon coupling, independent of device reconfiguration. Our results open avenues for applications such as all-magnetic mixers or on-chip GHz sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06801v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinwei Rao, Yi-Pu Wang, Zhijian Chen, Bimu Yao, Kaixin Zhao, Chunke Wei, Congyi Wang, Runze Li, Li-Hui Bai, Wei Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
