<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of Complex Particle without Extra Dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03378v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Complex particle is a kind of bilocal particle having unexpected symmetry, which was proposed by the authour. In the present paper, we show that critical dimension of the complex particle in Minkowski spacetime is $D = 4$, while $D = 2, 4$ or $6$ are permitted in Euclid spacetime. The origin of the restriction to the dimension is the existence of tertiary constraint in the canonical theory, quantization of which leads to an eigenvalue equation having single-valued and bounded solutions only in particular dimension of spacetime. The derivation is based on a detailed analysis of Laplace-Beltrami operator on $S^{1,D-2}$ or $S^{D-1}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03378v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takayuki Hori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black box work extraction and composite hypothesis testing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03400v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Work extraction is one of the most central processes in quantum thermodynamics. However, the prior analysis of optimal extractable work has been restricted to a limited operational scenario where complete information about the initial state is given. Here, we introduce a general framework of black box work extraction, which addresses the inaccessibility of information on the initial state. We show that the optimal extractable work in the black box setting is completely characterized by the performance of a composite hypothesis testing task, a fundamental problem in information theory.We employ this general relation to reduce the asymptotic black box work extraction to the quantum Stein's lemma in composite hypothesis testing, allowing us to provide their exact characterization in terms of the Helmholtz free energy. We also show a new quantum Stein's lemma motivated in this physical setting, where a composite hypothesis contains a certain correlation. Our work exhibits the importance of information about the initial state and gives a new interpretation of the quantities in the composite quantum hypothesis testing, encouraging the interplay between the physical settings and the information theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03400v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaito Watanabe, Ryuji Takagi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct Estimation of the Density of States for Fermionic Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03414v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Simulating time evolution is one of the most natural applications of quantum computers and is thus one of the most promising prospects for achieving practical quantum advantage. Here we develop quantum algorithms to extract thermodynamic properties by estimating the density of states (DOS), a central object in quantum statistical mechanics. We introduce key innovations that significantly improve the practicality and extend the generality of previous techniques. First, our approach allows one to estimate the DOS for a specific subspace of the full Hilbert space. This is crucial for fermionic systems, since fermion-to-qubit mappings partition the full Hilbert space into subspaces of fixed number, on which both canonical and grand canonical ensemble properties depend. Second, in our approach, by time evolving very simple, random initial states (e.g. random computational basis states), we can exactly recover the DOS on average. Third, due to circuit-depth limitations, we only reconstruct the DOS up to a convolution with a Gaussian window - thus all imperfections that shift the energy levels by less than the width of the convolution window will not significantly affect the estimated DOS. For these reasons we find the approach is a promising candidate for early quantum advantage as even short-time, noisy dynamics yield a semi-quantitative reconstruction of the DOS (convolution with a broad Gaussian window), while early fault tolerant devices will likely enable higher resolution DOS reconstruction through longer time evolution. We demonstrate the practicality of our approach in representative Fermi-Hubbard and spin models and find that our approach is highly robust to algorithmic errors in the time evolution and to gate noise. We show that our approach is compatible with NISQ-friendly variational methods, introducing a new technique for variational time evolution in noisy DOS computations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03414v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew L. Goh, B\'alint Koczor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unifying Floquet theory of longitudinal and dispersive readout</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03417</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03417v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We devise a Floquet theory of longitudinal and dispersive readout in circuit QED. By studying qubits coupled to cavity photons and driven at the resonance frequency of the cavity $\omega_{\rm r}$, we establish a universal connection between the qubit AC Stark shift and the longitudinal and dispersive coupling to photons. We find that the longitudinal coupling $g_\parallel$ is controlled by the slope of the AC Stark shift as function of the driving strength $A_{\rm q}$, while the dispersive shift $\chi$ depends on its curvature. The two quantities become proportional to each other in the weak drive limit ($A_{\rm q}\rightarrow 0$). Our approach unifies the adiabatic limit ($\omega_{\rm r}\rightarrow 0$) -- where $g_\parallel$ is generated by the static spectrum curvature (or quantum capacitance) -- with the diabatic one, where the static spectrum plays no role. We derive analytical results supported by exact numerical simulations. We apply them to superconducting and spin-hybrid cQED systems, showcasing the flexibility of faster-than-dispersive longitudinal readout.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03417v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Chessari, Esteban A. Rodr\'iguez-Mena, Jos\'e Carlos Abadillo-Uriel, Victor Champain, Simon Zihlmann, Romain Maurand, Yann-Michel Niquet, Michele Filippone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analog Quantum Simulator of a Quantum Field Theory with Fermion-Spin Systems in Silicon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03419</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03419v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Simulating fermions coupled to spin degrees of freedom, relevant for a range of quantum field theories, represents a promising application for quantum simulators. Mapping fermions to qubits is challenging in $2+1$ and higher spacetime dimensions, and mapping bosons demands substantial quantum-computational overhead. These features complicate the realization of mixed fermion-boson quantum systems in digital quantum computers. We propose a native fermion-(large-)spin analog quantum simulator by utilizing dopant arrays in silicon. Specifically, we show how to use a dynamical lattice of coupled nuclear spins and conduction-band electrons to realize a quantum field theory: an extended Jackiw-Rebbi model involving coupled fermions and quantum rotors. We demonstrate the feasibility of observing dynamical mass generation and a confinement-deconfinement quantum phase transition in 1+1 dimensions on this platform, even in the presence of strong long-range Coulomb interactions. Furthermore, we employ finite-temperature Hartree-Fock-Bogoliubov simulations to investigate the dynamics of mass generation in two-dimensional square and honeycomb arrays, showing that this phenomenon can be simulated with realistic experimental parameters. Our findings reveal two distinct phases, and demonstrate robustness against the addition of Coulomb interactions. Finally, we discuss experimental signatures of the phases through transport and local charge sensing in dopant arrays. This study lays the foundation for quantum simulations of quantum field theories exhibiting fermions coupled to spin degrees of freedom using donors in silicon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03419v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Rad, Alexander Schuckert, Eleanor Crane, Gautam Nambiar, Fan Fei, Jonathan Wyrick, Richard M. Silver, Mohammad Hafezi, Zohreh Davoudi, Michael J. Gullans</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Qudit-native measurement protocol for dynamical correlations using Hadamard tests</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03421v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dynamical correlations reveal important out-of-equilibrium properties of the underlying quantum many-body system, yet they are notoriously difficult to measure in experiments. While measurement protocols for dynamical correlations based on Hadamard tests for qubit quantum devices exist, they do not straightforwardly extend to qudits. Here, we propose a modified protocol to overcome this limitation by decomposing qudit observables into unitary operations that can be implemented and probed in a quantum circuit. We benchmark our algorithm numerically at the example of quench dynamics in a spin-1 XXZ chain with finite shot noise and demonstrate advantages in terms of signal-to-noise ratio over established protocols based on linear response. Our scheme can readily be implemented on various platforms and offers a wide range of applications like variational quantum optimization or probing thermalization in many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03421v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pavel P. Popov, Kevin T. Geier, Valentin Kasper, Maciej Lewenstein, Philipp Hauke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing symmetries in quantum computing for many-body systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03452v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a method to deduce the symmetry properties of many-body Hamiltonians when they are prepared in Jordan-Wigner form for evaluation on quantum computers. Symmetries, such as point-group symmetries in molecules, are apparent in the standard second quantized form of the Hamiltonian. They are, however, masked when the Hamiltonian is translated into a Pauli matrix representation required for its operation on qubits. To reveal these symmetries we prove a general theorem that provides a straightforward method to calculate the transformation of Pauli tensor strings under symmetry operations. They are a subgroup of the Clifford group transformations and induce a corresponding group representation inside the symplectic matrices. We finally give a simplified derivation of an affine qubit encoding scheme which allows for the removal of qubits due to Boolean symmetries and thus reduces computational effort in quantum computing applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03452v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert van Leeuwen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Application of Magnus expansion for the quantum dynamics of $\Lambda$-systems under periodic driving and assessment of the rotating wave approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03576v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Employing a sixth order expression for the differential time evolution operator based on the Magnus expansion (ME), we conducted quantum dynamics calculations of a $\Lambda$-system driven by two sinusoidal time dependent fields. For a closed system dynamics, we confirmed the equivalence of the dynamics in the Hilbert space and the Liouville space numerically. We also conducted open system quantum dynamics calculation by generalizing the ME to the non-Hermitian dynamics in the Liouville space for the case where the effects of photonic bath are represented by Lindblad operators. In both cases, the accuracy of the rotating wave approximation (RWA) was assessed. We found significant errors of RWA during initial stages of the dynamics for representative cases where electromagnetically induced transparency or coherent population trapping can be observed. The presence of bath for open system quantum dynamics reduces the errors of RWA, but significant errors for off-diagonal elements of the density operator can still be seen. We also found that approaches to steady state limits of exact dynamics are slower than those for RWA. These results demonstrate the utility of the ME as a general and reliable tool for closed and open system quantum dynamics for time dependent Hamiltonians, and expose potential issues of drawing conclusions based solely on RWA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03576v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taner M. Ture, Changbong Hyeon, Seogjoo J. Jang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The role of initial system-environment correlations in the accuracies of parameters within spin-spin model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03584v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the effect of initial system-environment correlations to improve the estimation of environment parameters. By employing various physical situations of interest, we present results for the environment temperature and system-environment coupling strength. We consider the spin-spin model whereby a probe (a small controllable quantum system) interacts with a bath of quantum spins and attains a thermal equilibrium state. A projective measurement is then performed to prepare the initial state and allow it to evolve unitarily. The properties of the environment are imprinted upon the dynamics of the probe. The reduced density matrix of the probe state contains a modified decoherence factor and dissipation. This additional factor acts in such a way to improve the estimation of the environment parameters, as quantified by the quantum Fisher information (QFI). In the temperature estimation case, our results are promising as one can improve the precision of the estimates by orders of magnitude by incorporating the effect of initial correlations. The precision increases in the strong coupling regime even if the nearest neighbours' interaction is taken into account. In the case of coupling strength, interestingly the accuracy was found to be continuously increasing in both with and without correlations cases. More importantly, one can see the noticeable role of correlations in improving precision, especially at low temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03584v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Raza Mirza, Jim Al-Khalili</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deterministic entanglement swapping of W states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03603v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a deterministic entanglement swapping protocol for generating a shared three-qubit W state between two remote parties. Our method offers a reliable alternative to existing probabilistic protocols for W state entanglement swapping, which is crucial for various quantum information processing tasks. We present a detailed quantum circuit design, implemented using the Qiskit simulator, that outlines the preparation of W states and the execution of joint measurements required for the entanglement swapping process. Furthermore, we analyze the effects of imperfect operations and noisy communication channels on the fidelity of the resulting shared W state. To address these challenges, we introduce a weak measurement-based purification method that enhances fidelity in the presence of amplitude damping. Through mathematical analysis and Qiskit simulations, we demonstrate the effectiveness of our proposed protocol, offering a practical solution for high-fidelity W state generation in real-world quantum communication scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03603v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sajede Harraz, Yueyan Wang, Shuang Cong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous-variable quantum digital signatures against coherent attacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03609</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03609v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum digital signatures (QDS), which utilize correlated bit strings among sender and recipients, guarantee the authenticity, integrity and non-repudiation of classical messages based on quantum laws. Continuous-variable (CV) quantum protocol with heterodyne and homodyne measurement has obvious advantages of low-cost implementation and easy wavelength division multiplexing. However, security analyses in previous researches are limited to the proof against collective attacks in finite-size scenarios. Moreover, existing multi-bit CV QDS schemes have primarily focused on adapting single-bit protocols for simplicity of security proof, often sacrificing signature efficiency. Here, we introduce a CV QDS protocol designed to withstand general coherent attacks through the use of a cutting-edge fidelity test function, while achieving high signature efficiency by employing a refined one-time universal hashing signing technique. Our protocol is proved to be robust against finite-size effects and excess noise in quantum channels. In simulation, results demonstrate a significant reduction of over 6 orders of magnitude in signature length for a megabit message signing task compared to existing CV QDS protocols and this advantage expands as the message size grows. Our work offers a solution with enhanced security and efficiency, paving the way for large-scale deployment of CV QDS in future quantum networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03609v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi-Fan Zhang, Wen-Bo Liu, Bing-Hong Li, Hua-Lei Yin, Zeng-Bing Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum phase transition in a quantum Rabi square with next-nearest-neighbor hopping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03612v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a quantum Rabi square model where both the nearest-neighbor and the next-nearest-neighbor photon hopping are allowed among four quantum Rabi systems located at the vertices of a square. By tuning the next-nearest hopping strength, we realize a first-order phase transition between the antiferromagnetic superradiant phase and the frustrated superradiant phase, as well as a second-order phase transition between the normal and the superradiant phases. To understand the emergence of such phases, we show analytically that the effect induced by next-nearest hopping is equivalent to that of an artificial gauge phase. Our findings suggest that the next-nearest-neighbor hopping can serve as an alternative for the gauge phase to realize quantum control in applications of quantum simulation and quantum materials, and that our model represents a basic building block for the frustrated $J_1$-$J_2$ quantum spin model on square lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03612v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yilun Xu, Feng-Xao Sun, Qiongyi He, Han Pu, Wei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Quantum-Classical Machine Learning with String Diagrams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03673</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03673v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Central to near-term quantum machine learning is the use of hybrid quantum-classical algorithms. This paper develops a formal framework for describing these algorithms in terms of string diagrams: a key step towards integrating these hybrid algorithms into existing work using string diagrams for machine learning and differentiable programming. A notable feature of our string diagrams is the use of functor boxes, which correspond to a quantum-classical interfaces. The functor used is a lax monoidal functor embedding the quantum systems into classical, and the lax monoidality imposes restrictions on the string diagrams when extracting classical data from quantum systems via measurement. In this way, our framework provides initial steps toward a denotational semantics for hybrid quantum machine learning algorithms that captures important features of quantum-classical interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03673v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Koziell-Pipe, Aleks Kissinger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental demonstration of the equivalence of entropic uncertainty with wave-particle duality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03797</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03797v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Wave-particle duality is one of the most striking and counter-intuitive features of quantum mechanics, illustrating that two incompatible observables cannot be measured simultaneously with arbitrary precision. In this work, we experimentally demonstrate the equivalence of wave-particle duality and entropic uncertainty relations using orbital angular momentum (OAM) states of light. Our experiment utilizes an innovative and reconfigurable platform composed of few-mode optical fibers and photonic lanterns, showcasing the versatility of this technology for quantum information processing. Our results provide fundamental insights into the complementarity principle from an informational perspective, with implications for the broader field of quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03797v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Spegel-Lexne, Santiago G\'omez, Joakim Argillander, Marcin Paw{\l}owski, Pedro R. Dieguez, Alvaro Alarc\'on, Guilherme B. Xavier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-quality entangled photons source by symmetric beam displacement design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03806v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Entangled photon sources (EPSs) are pivotal in advancing quantum communication, computing and sensing. The demand for deploying efficient, robust EPSs in the field, characterized by exceptional (phase) stability, has become increasingly apparent. This work introduces a polarization-entangled photon source, leveraging type-0 spontaneous parametric down-conversion, and constructed using commercial bulk optomechanical components. Our system is versatile, enabling the generation of N00N states for sensing applications or Bell states for quantum key distribution protocols. We attained a maximal Bell inequality violation, with the average entanglement visibility exceeding 99% . The potential for further performance enhancements is also explored.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03806v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giacomo Paganini, Alvaro Cuevas, Robin Camphausen, Alexander Demuth, Valerio Pruneri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum spectral method for gradient and Hessian estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03833v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Gradient descent is one of the most basic algorithms for solving continuous optimization problems. In [Jordan, PRL, 95(5):050501, 2005], Jordan proposed the first quantum algorithm for estimating gradients of functions close to linear, with exponential speedup in the black-box model. This quantum algorithm was greatly enhanced and developed by [Gily\'en, Arunachalam, and Wiebe, SODA, pp. 1425-1444, 2019], providing a quantum algorithm with optimal query complexity $\widetilde{\Theta}(\sqrt{d}/\varepsilon)$ for a class of smooth functions of $d$ variables, where $\varepsilon$ is the accuracy. This is quadratically faster than classical algorithms for the same problem.
  In this work, we continue this research by proposing a new quantum algorithm for another class of functions, namely, analytic functions $f(\boldsymbol{x})$ which are well-defined over the complex field. Given phase oracles to query the real and imaginary parts of $f(\boldsymbol{x})$ respectively, we propose a quantum algorithm that returns an $\varepsilon$-approximation of its gradient with query complexity $\widetilde{O}(1/\varepsilon)$. This achieves exponential speedup over classical algorithms in terms of the dimension $d$. As an extension, we also propose two quantum algorithms for Hessian estimation, aiming to improve quantum analogs of Newton's method. The two algorithms have query complexity $\widetilde{O}(d/\varepsilon)$ and $\widetilde{O}(d^{1.5}/\varepsilon)$, respectively, under different assumptions. Moreover, if the Hessian is promised to be $s$-sparse, we then have two new quantum algorithms with query complexity $\widetilde{O}(s/\varepsilon)$ and $\widetilde{O}(sd/\varepsilon)$, respectively. The former achieves exponential speedup over classical algorithms. We also prove a lower bound of $\widetilde{\Omega}(d)$ for Hessian estimation in the general case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03833v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxin Zhang, Changpeng Shao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noise analysis of a quasi-phase-matched quantum frequency converter and higher-order counter-propagating SPDC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03845v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum frequency conversion (QFC) will be an indispensable ingredient in future quantum technologies. For example, large-scale fibre-based quantum networks will require QFC to interconnect heterogeneous building blocks like emitters, channels, memories and detectors. The performance of existing QFC devices - typically realised in periodically-poled nonlinear crystals - is often severely limited by parasitic noise that arises when the pump wavelength lies between the wavelengths which are inter-converted. Here we investigate the noise spectrum of a frequency converter pumped by a CW 1064 nm laser. The converter was realised as a monolithic bulk pump enhancement cavity made from a periodically-poled potassium titanyl phosphate (ppKTP) crystal - quasi-phase-matched for the conversion of 637 nm to 1587 nm. In the range from 1140 nm to 1330 nm (up to 60 THz from the pump) Stokes-Raman resonances can be identified as the dominant noise source while the noise in the range from 1330 nm to 1650 nm can be attributed mainly to parasitic spontaneous parametric down-conversion (SPDC). Further, a succession of narrow-band peaks is observed in the spectrum originating from higher-order counter-propagating SPDC. Both types of counter-propagation, where either the lower-energy idler photon or the higher-energy signal photon counter-propagate relative to the pump beam, are observed, with narrow-band peaks corresponding to 10th to 44th order quasi-phase-matching.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03845v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felix Mann, Helen M. Chrzanowski, Felipe Gewers, Marlon Placke, Sven Ramelow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-latency machine learning FPGA accelerator for multi-qubit state discrimination</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03852v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Measuring a qubit is a fundamental yet error prone operation in quantum computing. These errors can stem from various sources such as crosstalk, spontaneous state-transitions, and excitation caused by the readout pulse. In this work, we utilize an integrated approach to deploy neural networks (NN) on to field programmable gate arrays (FPGA). We demonstrate that it is practical to design and implement a fully connected neural network accelerator for frequency-multiplexed readout balancing computational complexity with low latency requirements without significant loss in accuracy. The neural network is implemented by quantization of weights, activation functions, and inputs. The hardware accelerator performs frequency-multiplexed readout of 5 superconducting qubits in less than 50 ns on RFSoC ZCU111 FPGA which is first of its kind in the literature. These modules can be implemented and integrated in existing Quantum control and readout platforms using a RFSoC ZCU111 ready for experimental deployment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03852v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pradeep Kumar Gautam, Shantharam Kalipatnapu, Shankaranarayanan H, Ujjawal Singhal, Benjamin Lienhard, Vibhor Singh, Chetan Singh Thakur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RobQuNNs: A Methodology for Robust Quanvolutional Neural Networks against Adversarial Attacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03875v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advancements in quantum computing have led to the emergence of hybrid quantum neural networks, such as Quanvolutional Neural Networks (QuNNs), which integrate quantum and classical layers. While the susceptibility of classical neural networks to adversarial attacks is well-documented, the impact on QuNNs remains less understood. This study introduces RobQuNN, a new methodology to enhance the robustness of QuNNs against adversarial attacks, utilizing quantum circuit expressibility and entanglement capability alongside different adversarial strategies. Additionally, the study investigates the transferability of adversarial examples between classical and quantum models using RobQuNN, enhancing our understanding of cross-model vulnerabilities and pointing to new directions in quantum cybersecurity. The findings reveal that QuNNs exhibit up to 60\% higher robustness compared to classical networks for the MNIST dataset, particularly at low levels of perturbation. This underscores the potential of quantum approaches in improving security defenses. In addition, RobQuNN revealed that QuNN does not exhibit enhanced resistance or susceptibility to cross-model adversarial examples regardless of the quantum circuit architecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03875v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2024 IEEE International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Walid El Maouaki, Alberto Marchisio, Taoufik Said, Muhammad Shafique, Mohamed Bennai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous-time quantum optimisation without the adiabatic principle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03910</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03910v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Continuous-time quantum algorithms for combinatorial optimisation problems, such as quantum annealing, have previously been motivated by the adiabatic principle. A number of continuous-time approaches exploit dynamics, however, and therefore are no longer physically motivated by the adiabatic principle. In this work we take Planck's principle as the underlying physical motivation for continuous-time quantum algorithms. Planck's principle states that the energy of an isolated system cannot decrease as the result of a cyclic process. We use this principle to justify monotonic schedules in quantum annealing which are not adiabatic. This approach also highlights the limitations of reverse quantum annealing in an isolated system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03910v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert J. Banks, Georgios S. Raftis, Dan E. Browne, P. A. Warburton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum dynamics of frustrated Josephson junction arrays embedded in a transmission line: an effective XX spin chain with long-range interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03928v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study theoretically a variety of collective quantum phases occurring in frustrated saw-tooth chains of Josephson junctions embedded in a dissipationless transmission line. The basic element of a system, i.e., the triangular superconducting cell, contains two $0$- and one $\pi$- Josephson junctions characterized by $E_J$ and $\alpha E_J$ Josephson energies, accordingly. In the frustrated regime the low energy quantum dynamics of a single cell is determined by anticlockwise or clockwise flowing persistent currents (vortex/antivortex). The direct embedding of $\pi$-Josephson junctions in a transmission line allows to establish a short/long-range interaction between (anti)vortices of well separated cells. By making use of the variational approach, we map the superconducting circuit Hamiltonian to an effective $XX$ spin model with an exchange spin-spin interaction decaying with the distance $x$ as $x^{-\beta}$, and the local $\hat \sigma_{x,n}$-terms corresponding to the coherent quantum beats between vortex and antivortex in a single cell. We obtain that in long arrays as $N \gg \ell_0 \simeq \sqrt{C/C_0}$, where $C$ and $C_0$ are capacitances of $0$-Josephson junction and transmission line, accordingly, the amplitude of quantum beats is strongly suppressed. By means of exact numerical diagonalization, we study the interplay between the coherent quantum beats and the exchange spin-spin interaction leading to the appearance of various collective quantum phases such as the paramagnetic ($P$), compressible superfluid ($CS$) and weakly compressible superfluid ($w$-$CS$) states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03928v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benedikt J. P. Pernack, Mikhail V. Fistul, Ilya M. Eremin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magic spreading in random quantum circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03929v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magic state resources or non-stabilizerness quantify the beyond-Clifford operations necessary for universal quantum computing. How rapidly are magic resources generated by generic many-body dynamics under constraints of locality? We address this problem by exploring magic spreading in brick-wall random unitary circuits. Inspired by the algebraic structure of the Clifford group, we propose a scalable measure of non-stabilizerness, the Calderbank-Shor-Steane entropy, which generalizes the notion of stabilizer entropy and mirrors its qualitative behavior. This metric enables the investigation of non-stabilizerness dynamics for systems of up to N = 1024 qudits. Our main finding is that magic resources equilibrate on timescales logarithmic in system size N, akin to anticoncentration and Hilbert space delocalization measures, but differently from entanglement entropy. We conjecture that our findings describe the phenomenology of non-stabilizerness growth in a broad class of chaotic many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03929v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xhek Turkeshi, Emanuele Tirrito, Piotr Sierant</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Markovian environment induced anomaly in steady state quantum coherence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03943v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Environment induced steady state quantum coherence (SSQC) is a captivating phenomenon that challenges conventional understandings of decoherence. In this letter, we delve into the foundational aspects of environment-induced SSQC, shedding light on its emergence within the framework of system-bath interactions. Starting from a microscopic system-bath coupled model, we investigate the dependence of SSQC on environmental memory effects, bath temperature, system-bath coupling strength, and squeezing parameters. Our findings reveal that the environment not only acts as a generator but also as a disruptor of SSQC. A peak will exist for a non-Markovian bath, which is a result of competition between these two mechanisms. Interestingly, the peak disappears in Markovian case. Additionally, we observe that the generated SSQC can be further amplified through environment squeezing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03943v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arapat Ablimit, Zhao-Ming Wang, Feng-Hua Ren, Paul Brumer, Lian-Ao Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Overdispersion in gate tomography: Experiments and continuous, two-scale random walk model on the Bloch sphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03970v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Noisy intermediate-scale quantum computers (NISQ) are in their childhood, but showing high promise. One main concern for NISQ machines is their inherent noisiness, as the qubit states are subject to disturbances with each algorithmic operation applied. In this study, we conduct experiments on quantum noise. Based on our data, we show that existing noise models fail to properly capture the aggregation of noise effects over an algorithm's runtime. They are underdispersed, meaning that observable frequencies scatter much more between repeated experiments than what the standard assumptions of the binomial distribution allow for. We develop noise model for the readout probabilities as a function of the number of gate operations. The model is based on a continuous random walk on the (Bloch) sphere, where the angular diffusion coefficient characterizes the noisiness of gate operations. We superimpose a second random walk at the scale of multiple readouts to account for overdispersion. The interaction of these two random walks predicts theoretical, runtime-dependent bounds for probabilities. Overall, it is a three-parameter distributional model that fits the data better than the corresponding one-scale model (without overdispersion). We demonstrate the fit and the plausibility of the predicted bounds via Bayesian data-model analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03970v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wolfgang Nowak, Tim Br\"unnette, Merel Schalkers, Matthias M\"oller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement Polygon Inequalities for A Class of Mixed States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03972v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The study on the entanglement polygon inequality of multipartite systems has attracted much attention. However, most of the results are on pure states. Here we consider the property for a class of mixed states, which are the reduced density matrices of generalized W-class states in multipartite higher dimensional systems. First we show the class of mixed states satisfies the entanglement polygon inequalities in terms of Tsallis-q entanglement, then we propose a class of tighter inequalities for mixed states in terms of Tsallis-q entanglement. At last, we get an inequality for the mixed states, which can be regarded as a relation for bipartite entanglement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03972v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xian Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Logical Operators and Fold-Transversal Gates of Bivariate Bicycle Codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03973</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03973v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum low-density parity-check (qLDPC) codes offer a promising route to scalable fault-tolerant quantum computation with constant overhead. Recent advancements have shown that qLDPC codes can outperform the quantum memory capability of surface codes even with near-term hardware. The question of how to implement logical gates fault-tolerantly for these codes is still open. We present new examples of high-rate bivariate bicycle (BB) codes with enhanced symmetry properties. These codes feature explicit nice bases of logical operators (similar to toric codes) and support fold-transversal Clifford gates without overhead. As examples, we construct $[[98,6,12]]$ and $[[162, 8, 12]]$ BB codes which admit interesting fault-tolerant Clifford gates. Our work also lays the mathematical foundations for explicit bases of logical operators and fold-transversal gates in quantum two-block and group algebra codes, which might be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03973v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jens Niklas Eberhardt, Vincent Steffan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Practical asynchronous measurement-device-independent quantum key distribution with advantage distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03980v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The advantage distillation (AD) method has proven effective in improving the performance of quantum key distribution (QKD). In this paper, we introduce the AD method into a recently proposed asynchronous measurement-device-independent (AMDI) QKD protocol, taking finite-key effects into account. Simulation results show that the AD method significantly enhances AMDIQKD, e.g., extending the transmission distance by 16 km with a total pulse count of N = 7.24*10^13, and enables AMDI-QKD, previously unable to generate keys, to generate keys with a misalignment error rate of 10%. As the AD method can be directly integrated into the current system through refined post-processing, our results facilitate the practical implementation of AMDI-QKD in various applications, particularly in scenarios with high channel losses and misalignment errors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03980v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Di Luo, Xin Liu, Kaibiao Qin, Zhenrong Zhang, Kejin Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modelling Quantum Transduction for Multipartite Entanglement Distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04015</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04015v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Superconducting and photonic technologies are envisioned to play a key role in the Quantum Internet. However the hybridization of these technologies requires functional quantum transducers for converting superconducting qubits into "flying" qubits able to propagate through the network (and vice-versa). In this paper, quantum transduction is theoretically investigated for a key functionality of the Quantum Internet, namely, multipartite entanglement distribution. Different communication models for quantum transduction are provided, in order to make the entanglement distribution possible. The proposed models departs from the large heterogeneity of hardware solutions available in literature, abstracting from the particulars of the specific solutions with a communication engineering perspective. Then, a performance analysis of the proposed models is conducted through key communication metrics, such as quantum capacity and entanglement generation probability. The analysis reveals that -- although the considered communication metrics depend on transduction hardware parameters for all the proposed models -- the particulars of the considered transduction paradigm play a relevant role in the overall entanglement distribution performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04015v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laura d'Avossa, Angela Sara Cacciapuoti, Marcello Caleffi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-bin entangled Bell state generation and tomography on thin-film lithium niobate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04048</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04048v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optical quantum communication technologies are making the prospect of unconditionally secure and efficient information transfer a reality. The possibility of generating and reliably detecting quantum states of light, with the further need of increasing the private data-rate is where most research efforts are focusing. The physical concept of entanglement is a solution guaranteeing the highest degree of security in device-independent schemes, yet its implementation and preservation over long communication links is hard to achieve. Lithium niobate-on-insulator has emerged as a revolutionising platform for high-speed classical telecommunication and is equally suited for quantum information applications owing to the large second-order nonlinearities that can efficiently produce entangled photon pairs. In this work, we generate maximally entangled quantum states in the time-bin basis using lithium niobate-on-insulator photonics at the fibre optics telecommunication wavelength, and reconstruct the density matrix by quantum tomography on a single photonic integrated circuit. We use on-chip periodically-poled lithium niobate as source of entangled qubits with a brightness of 242 MHz/mW and perform quantum tomography with a fidelity of 91.9+-1.0 %. Our results, combined with the established large electro-optic bandwidth of lithium niobate, showcase the platform as perfect candidate to realise fibre-coupled, high-speed time-bin quantum communication modules that exploit entanglement to achieve information security.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04048v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Finco, Filippo Miserocchi, Andreas Maeder, Jost Kellner, Alessandra Sabatti, Robert J. Chapman, Rachel Grange</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring multipartite quantum correlations by thermodynamic work extraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04058</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04058v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum correlations are at the core of quantum mechanics and play a crucial role in various fields. While bipartite quantum correlations have been extensively studied, multipartite quantum correlations in many-body systems remain elusive due to their complex structure. In particular, a primary challenge lies in the fact that the calculation of multipartite quantum correlation measure often requires exponential cost. In this work, we tackle this problem by adopting a thermodynamic approach; we introduce a measure of multipartite quantum correlations based on the difference in extractable thermodynamic work by global operations and local operations and classical communication (LOCC). This can be regarded as a multipartite generalization of the work deficit, which has attracted attention as a thermodynamic measure of bipartite quantum correlation. A distinguishing feature of the thermodynamic approach to multipartite quantum correlation is that we can compare the degree of quantum correlations with clear operational meaning. Importantly, we develop an efficient calculation method of the multipartite work deficit. This efficient method works for a special class of quantum many-body systems described by matrix product states (MPS), where the numerical cost is shown to be proportional to the system size, significantly reducing the exponential cost required for the direct calculations. We demonstrate this efficient method in the AKLT state and the cluster state, and analytically obtain the exact values of this measure. We further show that a quantum phase transition described by MPS is well captured by the multipartite work deficit. This shows that the multipartite work deficit does not only highlight the fundamental connection between multipartite quantum correlations and quantum thermodynamics, but also serves as an efficiently-computable probe of the structures of quantum many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04058v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Toshihiro Yada, Nobuyuki Yoshioka, Takahiro Sagawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Quantum Information Perspective on Many-Body Dispersive Forces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04111</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04111v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Despite its ubiquity, many-body dispersion remains poorly understood. Here we investigate the distribution of entanglement in quantum Drude oscillator assemblies, minimal models for dispersion bound systems. We analytically determine a relation between entanglement and energy, showing how the entanglement distribution governs dispersive bonding. This suggests that the monogamy of entanglement explains deviations of multipartite dispersive binding energies compared to the commonly used pairwise prediction. We illustrate our findings using examples of a trimer and extended crystal lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04111v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher Willby, Martin Kiffner, Joseph Tindall, Jason Crain, Dieter Jaksch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Convolutional Neural Network for Phase Recognition in Two Dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04114v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum convolutional neural networks (QCNNs) are quantum circuits for recognizing quantum phases of matter at low sampling cost and have been designed for condensed matter systems in one dimension. Here we construct a QCNN that can perform phase recognition in two dimensions and correctly identify the phase transition from a Toric Code phase with $\mathbb{Z}_2$-topological order to the paramagnetic phase. The network also exhibits a noise threshold up to which the topological order is recognized. Our work generalizes phase recognition with QCNNs to higher spatial dimensions and intrinsic topological order, where exploration and characterization via classical numerics become challenging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04114v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leon C. Sander, Nathan A. McMahon, Petr Zapletal, Michael J. Hartmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collective transition quenching in the presence of multiple competing decay channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04129v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a theoretical framework for 'collective transition quenching', a quantum many-body dissipative phenomenon that occurs in systems with multiple collective decay channels. Despite the competition, interactions suppress all but the dominant decay transition, leading to a 'winner takes all' dynamic where the system primarily settles into the dominant ground state. We prove that, in the presence of permutation symmetry, this problem is exactly solvable for any number of competing channels. Additionally, we develop an approximate model for the dynamics by mapping the evolution into a continuity equation for a fluid, and show analytically that the dominant transition ratio converges to unity with increasing system size as a power-law, for any branching ratio. This near-deterministic preparation of the dominant ground state has broad applicability. As an example we discuss a protocol for molecular photoassociation where collective dynamics effectively acts as a catalyst, amplifying the yield in a particular final state. Our results open new avenues for many-body strategies in the preparation and control of quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04129v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wai-Keong Mok, Stuart J. Masson, Dan M. Stamper-Kurn, Tanya Zelevinsky, Ana Asenjo-Garcia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluation of phase shifts for non-relativistic elastic scattering using quantum computers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04155v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Simulations of scattering processes are essential in understanding the physics of our universe. Computing relevant scattering quantities from ab initio methods is extremely difficult on classical devices because of the substantial computational resources needed. This work reports the development of an algorithm that makes it possible to obtain phase shifts for generic non-relativistic elastic scattering processes on a quantum computer. This algorithm is based on extracting phase shifts from the direct implementation of the real-time evolution. The algorithm is improved by a variational procedure, making it more accurate and resistant to the quantum noise. The reliability of the algorithm is first demonstrated by means of classical numerical simulations for different potentials, and later tested on existing quantum hardware, specifically on IBM quantum processors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04155v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Turro, Kyle A. Wendt, Sofia Quaglioni, Francesco Pederiva, Alessandro Roggero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holography of Transmission Lines: Insights of Continuous MERA and AdS/CFT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04171</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04171v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study examines the holographic representation of the quantum theory of transmission lines, which play a crucial role in quantum computing and quantum information. Utilizing Yurke and Denker's quantum circuit network theory within the framework of continuous MERA (cMERA) in AdS space, we analyze the quantization and interactions of transmission lines. The metric is revealed to be described by the inductance of the quantum circuit, which is AdS-space in its 0-limit. These results provide new insights into handling and controlling complex phenomena in quantum circuits, potentially advancing the understanding of quantum computing and quantum communication.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04171v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>So Katagiri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum subspace expansion approach for simulating dynamical response functions of Kitaev spin liquids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04205</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04205v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a quantum simulation-based approach for studying properties of strongly correlated magnetic materials at increasing scale. We consider a paradigmatic example of a quantum spin liquid (QSL) state hosted by the honeycomb Kitaev model, and use a trainable symmetry-guided ansatz for preparing its ground state. Applying the tools of quantum subspace expansion (QSE), Hamiltonian operator approximation, and overlap measurements, we simulate the QSL at zero temperature and finite magnetic field, thus moving outside of the symmetric subspace. Next, we implement a protocol for quantum subspace expansion-based measurement of spin-spin correlation functions. Finally, we perform QSE-based simulation of the dynamical structure factor obtained from Green's functions of the finite field Kitaev model. Our results show that quantum simulators offer an insight to quasiparticle properties of strongly correlated magnets and can become a valuable tool for studying material science.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04205v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chukwudubem Umeano, Fran\c{c}ois Jamet, Lachlan P. Lindoy, Ivan Rungger, Oleksandr Kyriienko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Utilizing classical programming principles in the Intel Quantum SDK: implementation of quantum lattice Boltzmann method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04311v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the use of classical programming techniques in implementing the quantum lattice Boltzmann method in the Intel Quantum SDK -- a software tool for quantum circuit creation and execution on Intel quantum hardware. As hardware access is limited, we use the state vector simulator provided by the SDK. The novelty of this work lies in leveraging classical techniques for the implementation of quantum algorithms. We emphasize the refinement of algorithm implementation and devise strategies to enhance quantum circuits for better control over problem variables. To this end, we adopt classical principles such as modularization, which allows for systematic and controlled execution of complex algorithms. Furthermore, we discuss how the same implementation could be expanded from state vector simulations to execution on quantum hardware with minor adjustments in these configurations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04311v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tejas Shinde, Ljubomir Budinski, Ossi Niemim\"aki, Valtteri Lahtinen, Helena Liebelt, Rui Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement distribution based on quantum walk in arbitrary quantum networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04338v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In large-scale quantum networks, distributing the multi-particle entangled state among selected nodes is crucial for realizing long-distance and complicated quantum communication. Quantum repeaters provides an efficient method to generate entanglement between distant nodes. However, it is difficult to extend quantum repeater protocols to high-dimensional quantum states in existing experiments. Here we develop a series of scheme for generating high-dimensional entangled states via quantum walks with multiple coins or single coin by quantum repeaters, including $d$-dimensional Bell states, multi-particle high dimensional GHZ states etc.. Furthermore, we give entanglement distribution schemes on arbitrary quantum networks according to the above theoretical framework. As applications, we construct quantum fractal networks and multiparty quantum secret sharing protocols based on $d$-dimensional GHZ states. In the end, we give the experiment implementing of various 2-party or 3-party entanglement generation schemes based on repeaters. Our work can serve as a building block for constructing larger and more complex quantum networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04338v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianen Chen, Yun Shang, Chitong Chen, Heng Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulation of Spin Chains with off-diagonal Coupling Using Inchworm Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04365v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the dynamical simulation of open quantum spin chain with nearest neighboring coupling, where each spin in the chain is associated with a harmonic bath. This is an extension of our previous work [G. Wang and Z. Cai, J. Chem. Theory Comput., 19, 8523--8540, 2023] by generalizing the application of the inchworm method and the technique of modular path integrals from diagonally coupled cases to off-diagonally coupled cases. Additionally, to reduce computational and memory cost in long time simulation, we apply tensor-train representation to efficiently represent the reduced density matrix of the spin chains, and employ the transfer tensor method (TTM) to avoid exponential growth of computational cost with respect to time. Abundant numerical experiments are performed to validate our method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04365v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yixiao Sun, Geshuo Wang, Zhenning Cai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploiting the equivalence between quantum neural networks and perceptrons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04371v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum machine learning models based on parametrized quantum circuits, also called quantum neural networks (QNNs), are considered to be among the most promising candidates for applications on near-term quantum devices. Here we explore the expressivity and inductive bias of QNNs by exploiting an exact mapping from QNNs with inputs $x$ to classical perceptrons acting on $x \otimes x$ (generalised to complex inputs). The simplicity of the perceptron architecture allows us to provide clear examples of the shortcomings of current QNN models, and the many barriers they face to becoming useful general-purpose learning algorithms. For example, a QNN with amplitude encoding cannot express the Boolean parity function for $n\geq 3$, which is but one of an exponential number of data structures that such a QNN is unable to express. Mapping a QNN to a classical perceptron simplifies training, allowing us to systematically study the inductive biases of other, more expressive embeddings on Boolean data. Several popular embeddings primarily produce an inductive bias towards functions with low class balance, reducing their generalisation performance compared to deep neural network architectures which exhibit much richer inductive biases. We explore two alternate strategies that move beyond standard QNNs. In the first, we use a QNN to help generate a classical DNN-inspired kernel. In the second we draw an analogy to the hierarchical structure of deep neural networks and construct a layered non-linear QNN that is provably fully expressive on Boolean data, while also exhibiting a richer inductive bias than simple QNNs. Finally, we discuss characteristics of the QNN literature that may obscure how hard it is to achieve quantum advantage over deep learning algorithms on classical data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04371v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chris Mingard, Jessica Pointing, Charles London, Yoonsoo Nam, Ard A. Louis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unitary death of Schr\"odinger's cat</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04389</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04389v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We analyze dynamics of the Rabi model describing interactions of a qubit with a single soft-mode oscillator. We show that the model with a slightly violated parity generates symmetric Schr{\"o}dinger cat states of the oscillator, which suddenly perish in a spontaneous unitary process similar to the measurement-induced wave-function collapse. The effect is sufficiently robust to be tested experimentally, e.g., with trapped ions, macroscopic mechanical oscillators or superconducting circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04389v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pavel Str\'ansk\'y, Pavel Cejnar, Radim Filip</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relational objectivity in presence of finite quantum resources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04391</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04391v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The no-go theorems of Bell and Kochen and Specker could be interpreted as implying that the notions of system and experimental context are fundamentally inseparable. In this interpretation, statements such as "spin is 'up' along direction $x$" are relational statements about the configurations of macroscopic devices which are mediated by the spin and not about any intrinsic properties of the spin. The operational meaning of these statements is provided by the practically infinite resources of macroscopic devices that serve to define the notion of a direction in three-dimensional space. This is the subject of "textbook quantum mechanics": The description of quantum systems in relation to an experimental context.. Can one go beyond that? Relational quantum mechanics endeavors to provide a relational description between any quantum systems without the necessity of involving macroscopic devices. However, by applying "textbook quantum mechanics" in such situations, it implicitly assumes infinite resources, even for simple quantum systems such as spins, which have no capacity to define an experimental context. This leads to conceptual difficulties. We analyse Penrose's spin network proposal as a potential formalisation of quantum theory that goes beyond the textbook framework: A description in presence of finite resources, which is inherently relational and inseparable in the system-context entity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04391v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luis C. Barbado, \v{C}aslav Brukner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Function Smoothing Regularization for Precision Factorization Machine Annealing in Continuous Variable Optimization Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04393</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04393v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Solving continuous variable optimization problems by factorization machine quantum annealing (FMQA) demonstrates the potential of Ising machines to be extended as a solver for integer and real optimization problems. However, the details of the Hamiltonian function surface obtained by factorization machine (FM) have been overlooked. This study shows that in the widely common case where real numbers are represented by a combination of binary variables, the function surface of the Hamiltonian obtained by FM can be very noisy. This noise interferes with the inherent capabilities of quantum annealing and is likely to be a substantial cause of problems previously considered unsolvable due to the limitations of FMQA performance. The origin of the noise is identified and a simple, general method is proposed to prevent its occurrence. The generalization performance of the proposed method and its ability to solve practical problems is demonstrated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04393v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katsuhiro Endo, Kazuaki Z. Takahashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement manipulation through multicore fibres</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04423</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04423v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multicore fibres are recently gaining considerable attention in the context of quantum communication tasks, where their capability to transmit multiple quantum states along different cores of the same channel make them a promising candidate for the implementation of scalable quantum networks. Here, we show that multicore fibres can be effectively used not only for the scope of communication but also for the generation of entangled states. By exploiting the formalism of completely positive trace preserving maps, we describe the action of a multicore fibre as a quantum channel and propose a protocol to implement bound entangled states of two qudits. Notably, the presence of crosstalk among the cores of the fibre is fundamental for the generation of such states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04423v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlo Marconi, Elena Fanella, Davide Bacco, Alessandro Zavatta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controlling Fano resonance and slow/fast light in a magnomechanical system with an optical parametric amplifier</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04430v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the slow-fast light effect and multi-transparency induced by magnomechanical systems. The system incorporates two magnons, which are collective magnetic excitations, placed alongside a degenerate optical parametric amplifier (OPA) within a cavity. The interaction between phonons, magnons, and light inside the cavity leads to two phenomena: magnomechanically induced transparency (MMIT) and magnon induced transparency (MIT). We show how an OPA alters the absorption and dispersion characteristics of the light spectrum. The observation of the Fano resonance through magnon-mechanical coupling with the degenerate OPA is discussed. Through tuning vibration interactions and the OPA, we achieve the improvement of slow light. We hope our findings could pave the way for advancements in quantum information processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04430v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M'bark Amghar, Noura Chabar, Mohamed Amazioug</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient simulation of quantum chemistry problems in an enlarged basis set</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04432v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a quantum algorithm to simulate the dynamics in quantum chemistry problems. It is based on adding fresh qubits at each Trotter step, which enables a simpler implementation of the dynamics in the extended system. After each step, the extra qubits are recycled, so that the whole process accurately approximates the correct unitary evolution. A key ingredient of the approach is an isometry that maps a simple, diagonal Hamiltonian in the extended system to the original one. We give a procedure to compute this isometry, while minimizing the number of extra qubits required. We estimate the error at each time step, as well as the number of gates, which scales as $O(N^2)$, where $N$ is the number of orbitals. We illustrate our results with two examples: the Hydrogen chain and the FeMoCo molecule. In the Hydrogen chain we observe that the error scales in the same way as the Trotter error. For FeMoCo, we estimate the number of gates in a fault-tolerant setup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04432v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxine Luo, J. Ignacio Cirac</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Connecting the Hamiltonian structure to the QAOA performance and energy landscape</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04435</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04435v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum computing holds promise for outperforming classical computing in specialized applications such as optimization. With current Noisy Intermediate Scale Quantum (NISQ) devices, only variational quantum algorithms like the Quantum Alternating Operator Ansatz (QAOA) can be practically run. QAOA is effective for solving Quadratic Unconstrained Binary Optimization (QUBO) problems by approximating Quantum Annealing via Trotterization. Successful implementation on NISQ devices requires shallow circuits, influenced by the number of variables and the sparsity of the augmented interaction matrix. This paper investigates the necessary sparsity levels for augmented interaction matrices to ensure solvability with QAOA. By analyzing the Max-Cut problem with varying sparsity, we provide insights into how the Hamiltonian density affects the QAOA performance. Our findings highlight that, while denser matrices complicate the energy landscape, the performance of QAOA remains largely unaffected by sparsity variations. This study emphasizes the algorithm's robustness and potential for optimization tasks on near-term quantum devices, suggesting avenues for future research in enhancing QAOA for practical applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04435v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel M\"ussig, Markus Wappler, Steve Lenk, J\"org L\"assig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking Variational Quantum Eigensolvers for Entanglement Detection in Many-Body Hamiltonian Ground States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04453v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Variational quantum algorithms (VQAs) have emerged in recent years as a promise to obtain quantum advantage. These task-oriented algorithms work in a hybrid loop combining a quantum processor and classical optimization. Using a specific class of VQA named variational quantum eigensolvers (VQEs), we choose some parameterized quantum circuits to benchmark them at entanglement witnessing and entangled ground state detection for many-body systems described by Heisenberg Hamiltonian, varying the number of qubits and shots. Quantum circuits whose structure is inspired by the Hamiltonian interactions presented better results on cost function estimation than problem-agnostic circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04453v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Drinko, Guilherme I. Correr, Ivan Medina, Pedro C. Azado, Askery Canabarro, Diogo O. Soares-Pinto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimal eigenvalue estimates for self-adjoint trace-class operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04478v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spectral properties of bounded linear operators play a crucial role in several areas of mathematics and physics, and arguably the most important one is being positive semidefinite. For each self-adjoint, trace-class operator $O$ we construct a monotone increasing sequence $q_n$ which tends to the minimal eigenvalue $\lambda_{\min}$ if $O$ is not positive semidefinite, and to $0$ otherwise. This sequence only depends on the moments of $O$ and a concrete upper estimate of its $1$-norm; we also demonstrate that it can be effectively calculated for a large class of physically relevant operators. As a by-product, we obtain computable estimates for the $1$-norm of $O$, too.
  First assume that $O$ is positive semidefinite. Unfortunately, positivity tests fail to prove this in finitely many steps. However, $q_n$ gives a rigorous, monotone increasing lower estimate for all eigenvalues, providing a quantitative way of measuring positivity. In this case the speed of convergence is $q_n\approx -\frac cn$.
  Now suppose that $O$ is not positive semidefinite. Then $q_n$ monotonically converges to $\lambda_{\min}$ with super-exponential speed. Hence if $q_n$ stabilizes at a negative value, we obtain a strong indication that $O$ is in fact not positive semidefinite. We also construct an easier computable sequence $q_{n,0}$ which fails to be monotone, but converges to $\lambda_{\min}&lt;0$ faster, providing an even better indicator of non-positivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04478v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rich\'ard Balka, G\'abor Homa, Andr\'as Csord\'as</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantal phase of extreme nonstatic light waves: Step-phase evolution and its effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04494v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The phases are the main factor that affects the outcome of various optical phenomena, such as quantum superposition, wave interference, and light-matter interaction. As a light wave becomes nonstatic, an additional phase, the so-called geometric phase, takes place in its evolution. Then, due to this phase, the overall phase of the quantum wave function varies in a nonlinear way with time. Interestingly, the phase exhibits a step-like evolution if the measure of nonstaticity is extremely high. Such an abnormal phase variation is analyzed in detail for better understanding of wave nonstaticity in this work. As the wave becomes highly nonstatic, the phase factor of the electromagnetic wave evolves in a rectangular manner. However, the shape of the electromagnetic field is still a sinusoidal form on account of the compensational variation of the wave amplitude. The electromagnetic field in this case very much resembles that of a standing wave. The effects accompanying the step-phase evolution, such as modification of the probability distribution and alteration of the wave-interference profile, are analyzed and their implications are illustrated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04494v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeong Ryeol Choi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry-informed transferability of optimal parameters in the Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04496v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One of the main limitations of variational quantum algorithms is the classical optimization of the highly dimensional non-convex variational parameter landscape. To simplify this optimization, we can reduce the search space using problem symmetries and typical optimal parameters as initial points if they concentrate. In this article, we consider typical values of optimal parameters of the Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm for the MaxCut problem with $d$-regular tree subgraphs and reuse them in different graph instances. We prove symmetries in the optimization landscape of several kinds of weighted and unweighted graphs, which explains the existence of multiple sets of optimal parameters. However, we observe that not all optimal sets can be successfully transferred between problem instances. We find specific transferable domains in the search space and show how to translate an arbitrary set of optimal parameters into the adequate domain using the studied symmetries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04496v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Isak Brundin, Laura Garc\'ia-\'Alvarez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropy Computing: A Paradigm for Optimization in an Open Quantum System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04512v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Modern quantum technologies using matter are designed as closed quantum systems to isolate them from interactions with the environment. This design paradigm greatly constrains the scalability and limits practical implementation of such systems. Here, we introduce a novel computing paradigm, entropy computing, that works by conditioning a quantum reservoir thereby enabling the stabilization of a ground state. In this work, we experimentally demonstrate the feasibility of entropy computing by building a hybrid photonic-electronic computer that uses measurement-based feedback to solve non-convex optimization problems. The system functions by using temporal photonic modes to create qudits in order to encode probability amplitudes in the time-frequency degree of freedom of a photon. This scheme, when coupled with electronic interconnects, allows us to encode an arbitrary Hamiltonian into the system and solve non-convex continuous variables and combinatorial optimization problems. We show that the proposed entropy computing paradigm can act as a scalable and versatile platform for tackling a large range of NP-hard optimization problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04512v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lac Nguyen, Mohammad-Ali Miri, R. Joseph Rupert, Wesley Dyk, Sam Wu, Nick Vrahoretis, Irwin Huang, Milan Begliarbekov, Nicholas Chancellor, Uchenna Chukwu, Pranav Mahamuni, Cesar Martinez-Delgado, David Haycraft, Carrie Spear, Mark Campanelli, Russell Huffman, Yong Meng Sua, Yuping Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Restrictions imposed by quantum mechanics on the results of measuring the momentum of a particle in three-dimensional configuration space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04537v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revised the restrictions imposed by quantum mechanics on the results of particle momentum measurements. Now we consider a three-dimensional case and approach the definition of the field of the kinetic energy operator differently. The quantum mechanical potential that arises in this approach differs from the Bohmian one, and both value fields of particle momentum in the configuration space are always real.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04537v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. L. Chuprikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved algorithms for learning quantum Hamiltonians, via flat polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04540</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04540v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give an improved algorithm for learning a quantum Hamiltonian given copies of its Gibbs state, that can succeed at any temperature. Specifically, we improve over the work of Bakshi, Liu, Moitra, and Tang [BLMT24], by reducing the sample complexity and runtime dependence to singly exponential in the inverse-temperature parameter, as opposed to doubly exponential. Our main technical contribution is a new flat polynomial approximation to the exponential function, with significantly lower degree than the flat polynomial approximation used in [BLMT24].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04540v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shyam Narayanan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Quantum Coherence in Terms of Phase-Sensitive Nonadiabatic Dressed States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04550v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The quantum coherence is considered within phase-sensitive nonadiabatic dressed states. Two types of phase correlations are found: a rapidly changing phase correlation between the real and the virtual components and a stationary phase correlation between different virtual components of these states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04550v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. G. Koprinkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convex roofs witnessing Kirkwood-Dirac nonpositivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04558v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given two observables $A$ and $B$, one can associate to every quantum state a Kirkwood-Dirac (KD) quasiprobability distribution. KD distributions are like joint classical probabilities except that they can have negative or nonreal values, which are associated to nonclassical features of the state. In the last decade, KD distributions have come to the forefront as a versatile tool to investigate and construct quantum advantages and nonclassical phenomena. KD distributions are also used to determine quantum-classical boundaries. To do so, one must have witnesses for when a state is KD nonpositive. Previous works have established a relation between the uncertainty of a pure state with respect to the eigenbases of $A$ and $B$ and KD positivity. If this $\textit{support uncertainty}$ is large, the state cannot be KD positive. Here, we construct two witnesses for KD nonpositivity for general mixed states. Our first witness is the convex roof of the support uncertainty; it is not faithful, but it extends to the convex hull of pure KD-positive states the relation between KD positivity and small support uncertainty. Our other witness is the convex roof of the total KD nonpositivity, which provides a faithful witness for the convex hull of the pure KD-positive states. This implies that the convex roof of the total nonpositivity captures the nonpositive nature of the KD distribution at the underlying pure state level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04558v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher Langrenez, Stephan De Bi\`evre, David R. M. Arvidsson-Shukur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovering Local Hidden-Variable Models for Arbitrary Multipartite Entangled States and Arbitrary Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04673</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04673v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Measurement correlations in quantum systems can exhibit non-local behavior, a fundamental aspect of quantum mechanics with applications such as device-independent quantum information processing. However, the explicit construction of local hidden-variable (LHV) models remains an outstanding challenge in the general setting. To address this, we develop an approach that employs gradient-descent algorithms from machine learning to find LHV models which reproduce the statistics of arbitrary measurements for quantum many-body states. In contrast to previous approaches, our method employs a general ansatz, enabling it to discover an LHV model in all cases where the state is local. Therefore, it provides actual estimates for the critical noise levels at which two-qubit Werner states and three-qubit GHZ and W states become non-local. Furthermore, we find evidence suggesting that two-spin subsystems in the ground states of translationally invariant Hamiltonians are local, while bigger subsystems are in general not. Our method now offers a quantitative tool for determining the regimes of non-locality in any given physical context, including scenarios involving non-equilibrium and decoherence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04673v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nick von Selzam, Florian Marquardt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exceptional Points and Braiding Topology in Non-Hermitian Systems with long-range coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04691v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a study of complex energy braiding in a 1D non-Hermitian system with $n$th order long range asymmetrical coupling. Our work highlights the emergence of novel topological phenomena in such systems beyond the conventional nearest-neighbor interaction. The modified SSH model displays $n$ distinct knots and links combinations in the complex energy-momentum space under periodic boundary conditions (PBC), which can be controlled by varying the coupling strengths. A topological invariant, namely the braiding index, is introduced to characterize the different complex energy braiding profiles, which depends on the zeros and poles of the characteristic polynomials. Furthermore, we demonstrate that the non-Hermitian skin effect can be localized at one or both ends, signifying conventional or bipolar localization, depending on the sign of the braiding index. Phase transitions between different braiding phases with the same (opposite) sign of the topological invariant occur at Type-1 (Type-2) exceptional points, with Type-1 (Type-2) phase transitions accompanied by single (multiple) exceptional points. We propose an experimental set-up to realize the various braiding schemes based on the RLC circuit framework, which provides an accessible avenue for implementation without recourse to high-dimensional momentum space required in most other platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04691v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. M. Rafi-Ul-Islam, Zhuo Bin Siu, Md. Saddam Hossain Razo, Mansoor B. A. Jalil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Loschmidt echo, emerging dual unitarity and scaling of generalized temporal entropies after quenches to the critical point</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14706</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14706v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Loschmidt echo of a product state after a quench to a conformal invariant critical point can be predicted by using conformal field theories (CFT). We check such prediction with tensor networks, finding excellent agreement. In particular, we are able to predict and confirm that the CFT imply an emerging dual-unitarity of the evolution. We show how to extract the universal information of the underlying CFT including, the central charge, the operator content, and the generalized temporal entropies. Our results also imply that, using state-of-the art tensor networks algorithms, such calculations only require resources that increase polynomially with the duration of the quench, thus providing an example of numerically efficiently solvable out-of-equilibrium scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14706v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Carignano, Luca Tagliacozzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singular Excitement Beyond the Horizon of a Rotating Black Hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01673</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01673v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Previous studies have shown that an Unruh-DeWitt (UDW) detector, when coupled linearly to a massless scalar field and permitted to fall radially into certain black holes, will exhibit non-monotonicity in its transition properties near the horizon. Specifically, the transition probability of a detector freely falling into a (3+1)-dimensional Schawrzschild black hole, when considering the Unruh and Hartle-Hawking vacuum states, was shown to possess a local extremum at horizon crossing [K.K. Ng et al., New J. Phys. 24 (2022) 103018]. The transition rate of a detector falling into a static (2+1)-dimensional Ba\~nados-Teitelboim-Zanelli (BTZ) black hole, for the Hartle-Hawking state, was also found to have multiple local extrema near the horizon under certain parameter settings [M.R. Preciado-Rivas et al., arXiv:2402.14908v1]. These discoveries are of interest, as they suggest that the event horizon of a black hole may be distinguishable to a local probe when QFT effects are included. In this paper, we explore the problem of a UDW detector falling freely into a rotating BTZ black hole. We numerically compute the detector's transition rate for different values of black hole mass, black hole angular momentum, detector energy gap, and field boundary conditions at infinity. Our results lead to a more generalized description of the behaviour of particle detectors in BTZ black hole spacetime, from which the previous non-rotating BTZ case can be retrieved in the limit as angular momentum vanishes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01673v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sijia Wang, Mar\'ia Rosa Preciado-Rivas, Massimilano Spadafora, Robert B. Mann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Radical Pair Mechanism Cannot Explain Telecommunication Frequency Effects on Reactive Oxygen Species</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03358</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03358v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In order to investigate whether the radical pair mechanism (RPM) can explain the effects of telecommunication frequency radiation on reactive oxygen species production, we modelled the effects of oscillating magnetic fields on radical pair systems. Our analysis indicates that the RPM cannot account for the biological effects observed under exposure to telecommunication frequencies due to negligible effects under low-amplitude conditions used in experimental setups. Observable effects on radical pairs at these frequencies would require hyperfine coupling constants that are precisely fine-tuned to large values that far exceed those naturally occurring within biological systems. We conclude that some other mechanism must be responsible for the effects of telecommunication frequency fields in biological systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03358v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Owaiss Talbi, Hadi Zadeh-Haghighi, Christoph Simon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meson Mass Sets Onset Time of Anomalous Dynamical Quantum Phase Transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03394</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03394v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Dynamical quantum phase transitions (DQPTs) have been established as a rigorous framework for investigating far-from-equilibrium quantum many-body criticality. Although initially thought to be trivially connected to an order parameter flipping sign, a certain kind of \textit{anomalous} DQPTs have been discovered that exhibit no direct connection to the order parameter and have been shown to arise in the presence of confinement. Here, we show in two paradigmatic models how the onset time of anomalous DQPTs is directly connected, through a power law, to the meson mass in the confined regime of a global symmetry-broken phase. This relation becomes more prominent the closer the initial parameters are to the equilibrium quantum critical point, where a relativistic quantum field theory emerges. Our findings draw a direct connection between mesons and anomalous DQPTs, highlighting the power of the latter to classify exotic far-from-equilibrium criticality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03394v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jesse J. Osborne, Johannes Knaute, Ian P. McCulloch, Jad C. Halimeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2500 vibronic eigenstates of the NO$_3$ radical</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03398v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The nitrate radical NO$_3$ plays an important role in atmospheric chemistry, yet many aspects of its coupled and anharmonic vibronic structure remain elusive. Here, using an accurate, coupled full-dimensional diabatic potential that includes five electronic states, we revisit the vibronic spectrum associated with the electronic $\tilde X ^2A_2'$ state. Using recently developed tensor network state methods, we are able to compute more than 2500 vibronic states, thereby increasing the number of computed full-dimensional states by a factor of 50, compared to previous work. While we obtain good agreement with experiment for most of the assigned vibronic levels, for several others, we observe striking disagreement. Further, for the antisymmetric bending motion we find remarkably large symmetry-induced level splittings that are larger than the zero-order reference. We discuss non-negligible nonadiabatic effects and show that the Born-Oppenheimer approximation leads to significant errors in the spectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03398v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henrik R. Larsson, Alexandra Viel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cheshire qudits from fractional quantum spin Hall states in twisted MoTe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03401v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Twisted MoTe$_2$ homobilayers exhibit transport signatures consistent with a fractional quantum spin Hall (FQSH) state. We describe a route to construct topological quantum memory elements, dubbed Cheshire qudits, formed from punching holes in such a FQSH state and using proximity-induced superconductivity to gap out the resulting helical edge states. Cheshire qudits encode quantum information in states that differ by a fractional topological "Cheshire" charge that is hidden from local detection within a condensate anyons. Control of inter-edge tunneling by gates enables both supercurrent-based readout of a Cheshire qudit, and capacitive measurement of the thermal entropy associated with its topological ground-space degeneracy. Additionally, we systematically classify different types of gapped boundaries, Cheshire qudits, and parafermionic twist defects for various Abelian and non-Abelian candidate FQSH orders that are consistent with the transport data, and describe experimental signatures to distinguish these orders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03401v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rui Wen, Andrew C. Potter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Barium Titanate and Lithium Niobate Permittivity and Pockels Coefficients from MHz to Sub-THz Frequencies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03443v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Pockels effect is essential for controlling optical signals at the highest speeds. We present the first measurements of the Pockels coefficients and permittivity in lithium niobate (LN) and barium titanate (BTO) over a continuous frequency range from 100 MHz to 330 GHz. These properties are constant across this frequency range in LN but have a significant frequency dependence in BTO. Still, our measurements show that BTO ($\varepsilon$ = 1136, $r_{42}$ = 481 pm/V, $r_{33}$ = 125 pm/V at 100 MHz, $\varepsilon$ = 453, $r_{42}$ = 191 pm/V, $r_{33}$ = 60 pm/V at 330 GHz) has remarkably large electro-optic properties compared to LN ($\varepsilon$ = 27, $r_{42}$ = 15 pm/V, $r_{33}$ = 27 pm/V). Furthermore, we show how BTO devices can be designed with a flat electro-optic frequency response despite the Pockels coefficient dispersion. Finally, we expound our method for broadband characterization of these vital electro-optic properties, utilizing specialized integrated electro-optic phase shifters. Altogether, this work is foundational to designing high-speed BTO devices and to developing new electro-optic materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03443v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Chelladurai, Manuel Kohli, Joel Winiger, David Moor, Andreas Messner, Yuriy Fedoryshyn, Mohammed Eleraky, Yuqi Liu, Hua Wang, Juerg Leuthold</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Helicity is a topological invariant of massless particles: C=-2h</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03494v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: There is an elementary but indispensable relationship between the topology and geometry of massive particles. The geometric spin $s$ is related to the topological dimension of the internal space $V$ by $\dim V = 2s + 1$. This breaks down for massless particles, which are characterized by their helicity $h$, but all have 1D internal spaces. We show that a subtler relation exists between the topological and geometry of massless particles. Wave functions of massless particles are sections of nontrivial line bundles over the lightcone whose topology are completely characterized by their first Chern number $C$. We prove that in general $C = -2h$. In doing so, we also exhibit a method of generating all massless bundle representations via an abelian group structure of massless particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03494v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Palmerduca, Hong Qin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological phase transitions via attosecond x-ray absorption spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03737</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03737v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a numerical experiment that demonstrates the possibility to capture topological phase transitions via an x-ray absorption spectroscopy scheme. We consider a Chern insulator whose topological phase is tuned via a second-order hopping. We perform time-dynamics simulations of the out-of-equilibrium laser-driven electron motion that enables us to model a realistic attosecond spectroscopy scheme. In particular, we use an ultrafast scheme with a circularly polarized IR pump pulse and an attosecond x-ray probe pulse. A laser-induced dichroism-type spectrum shows a clear signature of the topological phase transition. We are able to connect these signatures with the Berry structure of the system. This work extend the applications of attosecond absorption spectroscopy to systems presenting a non-trivial topological phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03737v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan F. P. Mosquera, Giovanni Cistaro, Mikhail Malakhov, Emilio Pisanty, Alexandre Dauphin, Luis Plaja, Alexis Chac\'on, Maciej Lewenstein, Antonio Pic\'on</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Krylov Complexity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03866v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This Thesis explores the notion of Krylov complexity as a probe of quantum chaos and as a candidate for holographic complexity. The first Part is devoted to presenting the fundamental notions required to conduct research in this area. Namely, an extensive introduction to the Lanczos algorithm, its properties and associated algebraic structures, as well as technical details related to its practical implementation, is given. Subsequently, an overview of the seminal references and the main debates regarding Krylov complexity and its relation to chaos and holography is provided. The text throughout this first Part combines review material with original analyses which either intend to contextualize, compare and criticize results in the literature, or are the fruit of the investigations leading to the publications on which this Thesis is based. These research projects are the subject of the second Part of the manuscript. In them, methods for the efficient implementation of the Lanczos algorithm in finite many-body systems were developed, allowing to compute numerically the Krylov complexity of models like SYK or the XXZ spin chain up to time scales exponentially large in system size. It was observed that the operator Krylov complexity profile in SYK, a paradigmatic low-dimensional chaotic system with a holographic dual, agrees with holographic expectations, while in the case of integrable models like XXZ complexity is affected by a novel localization effect in the so-called Krylov space which hinders its growth. Finally, an exact, analytical, correspondence between the Krylov complexity of the infinite-temperature thermofield double state in the low-energy regime of the double-scaled SYK model and bulk length in the theory of JT gravity is established.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03866v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. S\'anchez-Garrido</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic Processes: From Classical to Quantum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04005v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The main goal of these notes is to give an introduction to the mathematics of quantum noise and some of its applications in non-equilibrium statistical mechanics. We start with some reminders from the theory of classical stochastic processes. We then provide a brief overview of quantum mechanics and quantum field theory, from the viewpoint of quantum probability and adopting the language of Hudson and Parthasarathy. We introduce quantum stochastic processes on a boson Fock space and their calculus. Whenever possible, we make connections with the relevant concepts in classical probability theory. As an application of the theory, we introduce the theory of open quantum systems, with emphasis on the physics and modeling aspects of these systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04005v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soon Hoe Lim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence rates for the Trotter-Kato splitting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04045</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04045v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study convergence rates of the Trotter-Kato splitting $e^{A+L} = \lim_{n \to \infty} (e^{L/n} e^{A/n})^n$ in the strong operator topology. In the first part, we use complex interpolation theory to treat generators $L$ and $A$ of contraction semigroups on Banach spaces, with $L$ relatively $A$-bounded. In the second part, we study unitary dynamics on Hilbert spaces and develop a new technique based on the concept of energy constraints. Our results provide a complete picture of the convergence rates for the Trotter splitting for all common types of Schr\"odinger and Dirac operators, including singular, confining and magnetic vector potentials, as well as molecular many-body Hamiltonians in dimension $d=3$. Using the Brezis-Mironescu inequality, we derive convergence rates for the Schr\"odinger operator with $V(x)=\pm |x|^{-a}$ potential. In each case, our conditions are fully explicit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04045v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Becker, Niklas Galke, Robert Salzmann, Lauritz van Luijk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal work statistics in long-range interacting quantum systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04101v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We determine the conditions under which the presence of long-range interactions reduce the energy losses due to defect generation during non-adiabatic evolution, crucial for enhancing the power to efficiency ratio of quantum thermal devices. In order to do so, we investigate the response of long-range systems to diverse external drivings, emphasizing their robustness against dynamic excitation in comparison to generic local systems. This phenomenon is demonstrated through the study of the quantum work statistics, revealing insights into energy transfer efficiency and dynamical quantum criticality. Our results demonstrate the benefits of including a long-range interacting medium for quantum thermodynamics application, highlighting the potential to optimize finite-time quantum thermal cycles. Thanks to the effective dimension approach our findings can be drawn in full generality and, then, specified to different experimentally relevant scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04101v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Solfanelli, Nicol\`o Defenu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interacting Circular Rydberg Atoms Trapped in Optical Tweezers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04109</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04109v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Circular Rydberg atoms (CRAs), i.e., Rydberg atoms with maximal orbital momentum, ideally combine long coherence times and strong interactions, a key property of quantum systems, in particular for the development of quantum technologies. However, the dipole-dipole interaction between CRAs has not been observed so far. We report the measurement and characterization of the resonant dipole-dipole interaction between two CRAs, individually trapped in optical tweezers, and find excellent agreement with theoretical predictions. We demonstrate a dynamic control over the strength of the interaction by tuning the orientation of an electric field. We use the interaction between the CRAs as a meter for the interatomic distance, and record the relative motion between two atoms in their traps. This motion, that we induce through the interaction between Rydberg levels with permanent electric dipoles, transiently populated during the preparation of the circular states, is a signature of spin-motion coupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04109v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul M\'ehaignerie, Yohann Machu, Andr\'es Dur\'an Hern\'andez, Gautier Creutzer, David J. Papoular, Jean-Michel Raimond, Cl\'ement Sayrin, Michel Brune</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic Correlations in Multielectron Silicon Quantum Dots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04289</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04289v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Silicon quantum computing has the potential to revolutionize technology with capabilities to solve real-life problems that are computationally complex or even intractable for modern computers [1] by offering sufficient high quality qubits to perform complex error-corrected calculations. Silicon metal-oxide-semiconductor based quantum dots present a promising pathway for realizing practical quantum computers. To improve certain qubit properties, it is a common strategy to incorporate multiple electrons in the same dot in order to form qubits in higher confined orbital states. Theoretical modelling is an essential part of understanding the quantum behaviour of these electrons, providing a basis for validating the physical working of device models as well as providing insights into experimental data.
  Hartree-Fock theory is an imperative tool for the electronic structure modelling of multi-electron quantum dots due to its ability to simulate a large number of electrons with manageable computation load. However, an efficient calculation of the self-consistent field becomes hard because dot formations in silicon are characterized by strong electron-electron interactions and conduction band valleys, besides the relatively high comparative effective mass, which add to create a behaviour dominated by repulsion between electrons rather than a well established shell structure. In this paper, we present a Hartree-Fock-based method that accounts for these complexities for the modelling of silicon quantum dots. With this method, we first establish the significance of including electron-electron interactions and valley degree of freedom and their implications. We then explore a simple case of anisotropic dots and observe the impact of anisotropy on dot formations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04289v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dylan H. Liang, MengKe Feng, Philip Y. Mai, Jesus D. Cifuentes, Andrew S. Dzurak, Andre Saraiva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Quantum Channel Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04406v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The problem of an optimal mapping between Hilbert spaces $IN$ and $OUT$, based on a series of density matrix mapping measurements $\rho^{(l)} \to \varrho^{(l)}$, $l=1\dots M$, is formulated as an optimization problem maximizing the total fidelity $\mathcal{F}=\sum_{l=1}^{M} \omega^{(l)} F\left(\varrho^{(l)},\sum_s B_s \rho^{(l)} B^{\dagger}_s\right)$ subject to probability preservation constraints on Kraus operators $B_s$. For $F(\varrho,\sigma)$ in the form that total fidelity can be represented as a quadratic form with superoperator $\mathcal{F}=\sum_s\left\langle B_s\middle|S\middle| B_s \right\rangle$ (either exactly or as an approximation) an iterative algorithm is developed to find the global maximum. The result comprises in $N_s$ operators $B_s$ that collectively form an $IN$ to $OUT$ quantum channel $A^{OUT}=\sum_s B_s A^{IN} B_s^{\dagger}$. The work introduces two important generalizations of unitary learning: 1. $IN$/$OUT$ states are represented as density matrices. 2. The mapping itself is formulated as a general quantum channel. This marks a crucial advancement from the commonly studied unitary mapping of pure states $\phi_l=\mathcal{U} \psi_l$ to a general quantum channel, what allows us to distinguish probabilistic mixture of states and their superposition. An application of the approach is demonstrated on unitary learning of density matrix mapping $\varrho^{(l)}=\mathcal{U} \rho^{(l)} \mathcal{U}^{\dagger}$, in this case a quadratic on $\mathcal{U}$ fidelity can be constructed by considering $\sqrt{\rho^{(l)}} \to \sqrt{\varrho^{(l)}}$ mapping, and on a general quantum channel of Kraus rank $N_s$, where quadratic on $B_s$ fidelity is an approximation -- a quantum channel is then built as a hierarchy of unitary mappings. The approach can be applied to study decoherence effects, spontaneous coherence, synchronizing, etc.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04406v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail Gennadievich Belov, Victor Victorovich Dubov, Alexey Vladimirovich Filimonov, Vladislav Gennadievich Malyshkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Didactic Journey from Statistical Physics to Thermodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04633v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper offers a pedestrian guide from the fundamental properties of entropy to the axioms of thermodynamics, which are a consequence of the axiom of statistical physics. It also dismantles flawed concepts, such as assigning physical meaning to Lagrange multipliers and numerous others. This work also provides a comprehensive understanding of the Legendre transform via geometrical, mathematical and physical insights, as well as its connection to the experimental setup. The central result of this paper is the comprehensive formalisation of key concepts, including ensembles, variable dependencies, potentials and natural variables. Furthermore, the framework of thermodynamics, the state function and the Euler inequality are rigorously proven from the axiom of statistical physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04633v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mario Graml, Michael Riedl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantized circular dichroism on the edge of quantum Hall systems: The many-body Chern number as seen from the edge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04639v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum Hall states are characterized by a topological invariant, the many-body Chern number, which determines the quantized value of the Hall conductivity. Interestingly, this topological property can also be accessed through a dissipative response, by subjecting the system to a circular drive and comparing excitation rates obtained for opposite orientations of the drive. This quantized circular dichroism assumes that only the bulk contributes to the response. Indeed, in a confined and isolated system, the edge contribution exactly cancels the bulk response. This work explores an important corollary of the latter observation: If properly isolated, the circular dichroic response stemming from the edge of a quantum Hall droplet must be quantized, thus providing an appealing way to probe the many-body Chern number. Importantly, we demonstrate that this quantized edge response is entirely captured by low-energy chiral edge modes, allowing for a universal description of this effect based on Wen's edge theory. Its low-energy nature implies that the quantized edge response can be distinguished from the bulk response in the frequency domain. We illustrate our findings using realistic models of integer and fractional Chern insulators, with different edge geometries, and propose detection schemes suitable for ultracold atoms. Edge dichroic responses emerge as a practical probe for strongly-correlated topological phases, accessible in cold-atom experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04639v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Nur \"Unal, A. Nardin, N. Goldman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Differentiating and Integrating ZX Diagrams with Applications to Quantum Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2201.13250</link>
      <description>arXiv:2201.13250v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: ZX-calculus has proved to be a useful tool for quantum technology with a wide range of successful applications. Most of these applications are of an algebraic nature. However, other tasks that involve differentiation and integration remain unreachable with current ZX techniques. Here we elevate ZX to an analytical perspective by realising differentiation and integration entirely within the framework of ZX-calculus. We explicitly illustrate the new analytic framework of ZX-calculus by applying it in context of quantum machine learning for the analysis of barren plateaus.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2201.13250v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quanlong Wang, Richie Yeung, Mark Koch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Operational Quantum Mereology and Minimal Scrambling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.14340</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.14340v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we will attempt to answer the following question: what are the natural quantum subsystems which emerge out of a system's dynamical laws? To answer this question we first define generalized tensor product structures (gTPS) in terms of observables, as dual pairs of an operator subalgebra $\cal A$ and its commutant. Second, we propose an operational criterion of minimal information scrambling at short time scales to dynamically select gTPS. In this way the emergent subsystems are those which maintain the longest informational identity. This strategy is made quantitative by defining a Gaussian scrambling rate in terms of the short-time expansion of an algebraic version of the Out of Time Order Correlation (OTOC) function i.e., the $\cal A$-OTOC. The Gaussian scrambling rate is computed analytically for physically important cases of general division into subsystems, and is shown to have an intuitive and compelling physical interpretation in terms of minimizing the interaction strength between subsystems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.14340v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Zanardi, Emanuel Dallas, Faidon Andreadakis, Seth Lloyd</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving Performance of Quantum Heat Engines using modified Otto cycle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.07003</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.07003v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The efficiency of a quantum heat engine is maximum when the unitary strokes are adiabatic. On the other hand, this may not be always possible due to small energy gaps in the system, especially at the critical point where the gap vanishes. With the aim to achieve this adiabaticity, we modify one of the unitary strokes of the cycle by allowing the system to evolve freely with a particular Hamiltonian till a time so that the system reaches a less excited state. This will help in increasing the magnitude of the heat absorbed from the hot bath so that the work output and efficiency of the engine can be increased. We demonstrate this method using an integrable model and a non-integrable model as the working medium. In the case of a two spin system, the optimal value for the time till which the system needs to be freely evolved is calculated analytically in the adiabatic limit. The results show that implementing this modified stroke significantly improves the work output and efficiency of the engine, especially when it crosses the critical point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.07003v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1751-8121/ad38ee</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. A: Math. Theor. 57 165302 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Revathy B. S, Harsh Sharma, Uma Divakaran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generation of intraparticle quantum correlations in amplitude damping channel and its robustness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.01238</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.01238v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum correlations between two or more different degrees of freedom of the same particle is sometimes referred to as intraparticle entanglement. In this work, we study these intra-particle correlations between two different degrees of freedom under various decoherence channels viz. amplitude damping, depolarising and phase damping channels. We observe a unique feature of the amplitude damping channel, wherein entanglement is shown to arise starting from separable states. In case of non maximally entangled input states, in addition to entanglement sudden death, the creation of entanglement is also observed, having an asymptotic decay over a long time. These counter-intuitive behaviours arise due to the subtle interplay of channel and input state parameters, and are not seen for interparticle entanglement without consideration of non-Markovian noise. It is also not observed for maximally entangled input states. Furthermore, investigation of entanglement evolution in phase damping and depolarizing channels shows its robustness against decoherence as compared to interparticle entanglement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.01238v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Animesh Sinha Roy, Namitha C. V., Subroto Mukerjee, Prasanta K. Panigrahi, Urbasi Sinha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational Gibbs State Preparation on NISQ devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.11276</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.11276v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The preparation of an equilibrium thermal state of a quantum many-body system on noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices is an important task in order to extend the range of applications of quantum computation. Faithful Gibbs state preparation would pave the way to investigate protocols such as thermalization and out-of-equilibrium thermodynamics, as well as providing useful resources for quantum algorithms, where sampling from Gibbs states constitutes a key subroutine. We propose a variational quantum algorithm (VQA) to prepare Gibbs states of a quantum many-body system. The novelty of our VQA consists in implementing a parameterized quantum circuit acting on two distinct, yet connected (via CNOT gates), quantum registers. The VQA evaluates the Helmholtz free energy, where the von Neumann entropy is obtained via post-processing of computational basis measurements on one register, while the Gibbs state is prepared on the other register, via a unitary rotation in the energy basis. Finally, we benchmark our VQA by preparing Gibbs states of the transverse field Ising and Heisenberg XXZ models and achieve remarkably high fidelities across a broad range of temperatures in statevector simulations. We also assess the performance of the VQA on IBM quantum computers, showcasing its feasibility on current NISQ devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.11276v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mirko Consiglio, Jacopo Settino, Andrea Giordano, Carlo Mastroianni, Francesco Plastina, Salvatore Lorenzo, Sabrina Maniscalco, John Goold, Tony J. G. Apollaro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounds to electron spin qubit variability for scalable CMOS architectures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.14864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.14864v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Spins of electrons in CMOS quantum dots combine exquisite quantum properties and scalable fabrication. In the age of quantum technology, however, the metrics that crowned Si/SiO2 as the microelectronics standard need to be reassessed with respect to their impact upon qubit performance. We chart the spin qubit variability due to the unavoidable atomic-scale roughness of the Si/SiO$_2$ interface, compiling experiments in 12 devices, and developing theoretical tools to analyse these results. Atomistic tight binding and path integral Monte Carlo methods are adapted for describing fluctuations in devices with millions of atoms by directly analysing their wavefunctions and electron paths instead of their energy spectra. We correlate the effect of roughness with the variability in qubit position, deformation, valley splitting, valley phase, spin-orbit coupling and exchange coupling. These variabilities are found to be bounded and lie within the tolerances for scalable architectures for quantum computing as long as robust control methods are incorporated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.14864v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-024-48557-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nat Commun 15, 4299 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jes\'us D. Cifuentes, Tuomo Tanttu, Will Gilbert, Jonathan Y. Huang, Ensar Vahapoglu, Ross C. C. Leon, Santiago Serrano, Dennis Otter, Daniel Dunmore, Philip Y. Mai, Fr\'ed\'eric Schlattner, MengKe Feng, Kohei Itoh, Nikolay Abrosimov, Hans-Joachim Pohl, Michael Thewalt, Arne Laucht, Chih Hwan Yang, Christopher C. Escott, Wee Han Lim, Fay E. Hudson, Rajib Rahman, Andrew S. Dzurak, Andre Saraiva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noise-adapted recovery circuits for quantum error correction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.11093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.11093v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Implementing quantum error correction (QEC) protocols is a challenging task in today's era of noisy intermediate-scale quantum devices. We present quantum circuits for a universal, noise-adapted recovery map, often referred to as the Petz map, which is known to achieve close-to-optimal fidelity for arbitrary codes and noise channels. While two of our circuit constructions draw upon algebraic techniques such as isometric extension and block encoding, the third approach breaks down the recovery map into a sequence of two-outcome POVMs. In each of the three cases we improve upon the resource requirements that currently exist in the literature. Apart from Petz recovery circuits, we also present circuits that can directly estimate the fidelity between the encoded state and the recovered state. As a concrete example of our circuit constructions, we implement Petz recovery circuits corresponding to the $4$-qubit QEC code tailored to protect against amplitude-damping noise. The efficacy of our noise-adapted recovery circuits is then demonstrated through ideal and noisy simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.11093v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debjyoti Biswas, Gaurav M. Vaidya, Prabha Mandayam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precision magnetometry exploiting excited state quantum phase transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.01126</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.01126v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Critical behaviour in phase transitions is a resource for enhanced precision metrology. The reason is that the function, known as Fisher information, is superextensive at critical points, and, at the same time, quantifies performances of metrological protocols. Therefore, preparing metrological probes at phase transitions provides enhanced precision in measuring the transition control parameter. We focus on the Lipkin-Meshkov-Glick model that exhibits excited state quantum phase transitions at different magnetic fields. Resting on the model spectral properties, we show broad peaks of the Fisher information, and propose efficient schemes for precision magnetometry. The Lipkin-Meshkov-Glick model was first introduced for superconductivity and for nuclear systems, and recently realised in several condensed matter platforms. The above metrological schemes can be also exploited to measure microscopic properties of systems able to simulate the Lipkin-Meshkov-Glick model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.01126v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qian Wang, Ugo Marzolino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A proposal to demonstrate non-abelian anyons on a NISQ device</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.13129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.13129v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work we present a proposal for realising non-Abelian anyons on a NISQ device. In particular we explore the feasibility of implementing the quantum double model $D(D_4)$. We propose techniques to drastically simplify the circuits for the manipulation and measurements of anyons. Numerical simulations with realistic noise models suggest that current NISQ technology is capable of probing signatures of non-Abelian anyons far beyond elemental properties such as the non-commutativity of braids. In particular, we conclude that experimentally measuring the full modular data of the model is feasible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.13129v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jovan Jovanovi\'c, Carolin Wille, Daan Timmers, Steven H. Simon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimising surface-code failures using a color-code decoder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.16476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.16476v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The development of practical, high-performance decoding algorithms reduces the resource cost of fault-tolerant quantum computing. Here we propose a decoder for the surface code that finds low-weight correction operators for errors produced by the depolarising noise model. The decoder is obtained by mapping the syndrome of the surface code onto that of the color code, thereby allowing us to adopt more sophisticated color-code decoding algorithms. Analytical arguments and exhaustive testing show that the resulting decoder can find a least-weight correction for all weight $d/2$ depolarising errors for even code distance $d$. This improves the logical error rate by an exponential factor $O(2^{d/2})$ compared with decoders that treat bit-flip and dephasing errors separately. We demonstrate this improvement with analytical arguments and supporting numerical simulations at low error rates. Of independent interest, we also demonstrate an exponential improvement in logical error rate for our decoder used to correct independent and identically distributed bit-flip errors affecting the color code compared with more conventional color-code decoding algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.16476v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Asmae Benhemou, Kaavya Sahay, Lingling Lao, Benjamin J. Brown</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring Trotter error and its application to precision-guaranteed Hamiltonian simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.05406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.05406v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Trotterization is the most common and convenient approximation method for Hamiltonian simulations on digital quantum computers, but estimating its error accurately is computationally difficult for large quantum systems. Here, we develop a method for measuring the Trotter error without ancillary qubits on quantum circuits by combining the $m$th- and $n$th-order ($m&lt;n$) Trotterizations rather than consulting with mathematical error bounds. Using this method, we make Trotterization precision-guaranteed, developing an algorithm named Trotter$(m,n)$, in which the Trotter error at each time step is within an error tolerance $\epsilon$ preset for our purpose. Trotter$(m,n)$ is applicable to both time- independent and dependent Hamiltonians, and it adaptively chooses almost the largest stepsize $\mathrm{d}t$, which keeps quantum circuits shallowest within the error tolerance. Benchmarking it in a quantum spin chain, we find the adaptively chosen $\mathrm{d}t$ to be about ten times larger than that inferred from known upper bounds of Trotter errors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.05406v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tatsuhiko N. Ikeda, Hideki Kono, Keisuke Fujii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The p-Adic Schr\"odinger Equation and the Two-slit Experiment in Quantum Mechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.01283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.01283v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: p-Adic quantum mechanics is constructed from the Dirac-von Neumann axioms identifying quantum states with square-integrable functions on the N-dimensional p-adic space. This choice is equivalent to the hypothesis of the discreteness of the space. The time is assumed to be a real variable. The p-adic quantum mechanics is motivated by the question: what happens with the standard quantum mechanics if the space has a discrete nature? The time evolution of a quantum state is controlled by a nonlocal Schr\"{o}dinger equation obtained from a p-adic heat equation by a temporal Wick rotation. This p-adic heat equation describes a particle performing a random motion in the N-dimensional p-adic space. The Hamiltonian is a nonlocal operator; thus, the Schr\"{o}dinger equation describes the evolution of a quantum state under nonlocal interactions. In this framework, the Schr\"{o}dinger equation admits complex-valued plane wave solutions, which we interpret as p-adic de Broglie waves. These mathematical waves have all wavelength 1/p. In the p-adic framework, the double-slit experiment cannot be explained using the interference of the de Broglie waves. The wavefunctions can be represented as convergent series in the de Broglie waves, but the p-adic de Broglie waves are just mathematical objects. Only the square of the modulus of a wave function has a physical meaning as a time-dependent probability density. These probability densities exhibit interference patterns similar to the ones produced by `quantum waves.' In the p-adic framework, in the double-slit experiment, each particle goes through one slit only.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.01283v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>W. A. Z\'u\~niga-Galindo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What can we learn from quantum convolutional neural networks?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.16664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.16664v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We can learn from analyzing quantum convolutional neural networks (QCNNs) that: 1) working with quantum data can be perceived as embedding physical system parameters through a hidden feature map; 2) their high performance for quantum phase recognition can be attributed to generation of a very suitable basis set during the ground state embedding, where quantum criticality of spin models leads to basis functions with rapidly changing features; 3) pooling layers of QCNNs are responsible for picking those basis functions that can contribute to forming a high-performing decision boundary, and the learning process corresponds to adapting the measurement such that few-qubit operators are mapped to full-register observables; 4) generalization of QCNN models strongly depends on the embedding type, and that rotation-based feature maps with the Fourier basis require careful feature engineering; 5) accuracy and generalization of QCNNs with readout based on a limited number of shots favor the ground state embeddings and associated physics-informed models. We demonstrate these points in simulation, where our results shed light on classification for physical processes, relevant for applications in sensing. Finally, we show that QCNNs with properly chosen ground state embeddings can be used for fluid dynamics problems, expressing shock wave solutions with good generalization and proven trainability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.16664v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chukwudubem Umeano, Annie E. Paine, Vincent E. Elfving, Oleksandr Kyriienko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adiabatic quantum trajectories in engineered reservoirs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.11937</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.11937v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We analyze the efficiency of protocols for adiabatic quantum state transfer assisted by an engineered reservoir. The target dynamics is a quantum trajectory in the Hilbert space and is a fixed point of a time-dependent master equation in the limit of adiabatic dynamics. We specialize to quantum state transfer in a qubit and determine the optimal schedule for a class of time-dependent Lindblad equations. The speed limit on state transfer is extracted from a physical model of a qubit coupled to a reservoir, from which the Lindblad equation is derived in the Born-Markov limit. Our analysis shows that the resulting efficiency is comparable to the efficiency of the optimal unitary dynamics. Numerical studies indicate that reservoir-engineered protocols could outperform unitary protocols outside the regime of the Born-Markov master equation, namely, when correlations between the qubit and reservoir become relevant. Our study contributes to the theory of shortcuts to adiabaticity for open quantum systems and to the toolbox of protocols of the NISQ era.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.11937v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emma C. King, Luigi Giannelli, Rapha\"el Menu, Johannes N. Kriel, Giovanna Morigi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous optimization by quantum adaptive distribution search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.17353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.17353v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce the quantum adaptive distribution search (QuADS), a quantum continuous optimization algorithm that integrates Grover adaptive search (GAS) with the covariance matrix adaptation - evolution strategy (CMA-ES), a classical technique for continuous optimization. QuADS utilizes the quantum-based search capabilities of GAS and enhances them with the principles of CMA-ES for more efficient optimization. It employs a multivariate normal distribution for the initial state of the quantum search and repeatedly updates it throughout the optimization process. Our numerical experiments show that QuADS outperforms both GAS and CMA-ES. This is achieved through adaptive refinement of the initial state distribution rather than consistently using a uniform state, resulting in fewer oracle calls. This study presents an important step toward exploiting the potential of quantum computing for continuous optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.17353v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.6.023191</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Kohei Morimoto, Yusuke Takase, Kosuke Mitarai, Keisuke Fujii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>p-Adic Quantum Mechanics, the Dirac Equation, and the violation of Einstein causality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02744</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.02744v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article studies the breaking of the Lorentz symmetry at the Planck length in quantum mechanics. We use three-dimensional p-adic vectors as position variables, while the time remains a real number. In this setting, the Planck length is 1/p, where p is a prime number, and the Lorentz symmetry is naturally broken. In the framework of the Dirac-von Neumann formalism for quantum mechanics, we introduce a new p-adic Dirac equation that predicts the existence of particles and antiparticles and charge conjugation like the standard one. The discreteness of the p-adic space imposes substantial restrictions on the solutions of the new equation. This equation admits localized solutions, which is impossible in the standard case. We show that an isolated quantum system whose evolution is controlled by the p-adic Dirac equation does not satisfy the Einstein causality, which means that the speed of light is not the upper limit for the speed at which conventional matter or energy can travel through space. The new p-adic Dirac equation is not intended to replace the standard one; it should be understood as a new version (or a limit) of the classical equation at the Planck length scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.02744v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>W. A. Z\'u\~niga-Galindo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>True image construction in quantum-secured single-pixel imaging under spoofing attack</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.03465</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.03465v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce a quantum-secured single-pixel imaging (QS-SPI) technique designed to withstand spoofing attacks, wherein adversaries attempt to deceive imaging systems with fake signals. Unlike previous quantum-secured protocols that impose a threshold error rate limiting their operation, even with the existence of true signals, our approach not only identifies spoofing attacks but also facilitates the reconstruction of a true image. Our method involves the analysis of a specific mode correlation of a photon-pair, which is independent of the mode used for image construction, to check security. Through this analysis, we can identify both the targeted image region by the attack and the type of spoofing attack, enabling reconstruction of the true image. A proof-of-principle demonstration employing polarization-correlation of a photon-pair is provided, showcasing successful image reconstruction even under the condition of spoofing signals 2000 times stronger than the true signals. We expect our approach to be applied to quantum-secured signal processing such as quantum target detection or ranging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.03465v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jaesung Heo, Taek Jeong, Nam Hun Park, Yonggi Jo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A polynomial-time dissipation-based quantum algorithm for solving the ground states of a class of classically hard Hamiltonians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.13946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.13946v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we give a quantum algorithm for solving the ground states of a class of Hamiltonians. The mechanism of the exponential speedup that appeared in our algorithm comes from dissipation in open quantum systems. To utilize the dissipation, the central idea is to treat $n$-qubit density matrices $\rho$ as $2n$-qubit pure states $|\rho\rangle$ by vectorization and normalization. By doing so, the Lindblad master equation (LME) becomes a Schr\"odinger equation with non-Hermitian Hamiltonian $L$. The steady-state $\rho_{ss}$ of the LME, therefore, corresponds to the ground states $|\rho_{ss}\rangle$ of Hamiltonians with the form $L^\dag L$. The runtime of the LME has no dependence on $\zeta$ the overlap between the initial state and the ground state compared with the Heisenberg scaling $\mathcal{O}(\zeta^{-1})$ in other algorithms. For the input part, given a Hamiltonian $H$, under plausible assumptions, we give a polynomial-time classical procedure to judge and solve whether there exists $L$ such that $H-E_0=L^\dag L$. For the output part, we define the mission as estimating expectation values of arbitrary operators with respect to the ground state $|\rho_{ss}\rangle$, which can be done surprisingly by an efficient measurement protocol on $\rho_{ss}$ with no need to prepare $|\rho_{ss}\rangle$. We give several pieces of evidence on the quantum hardness of really preparing $|\rho_{ss}\rangle$, which indicates a potential complexity separation between our algorithm and those projection-based quantum algorithms such as quantum phase estimation. Further, we show that the Hamiltonians that can be efficiently solved by our algorithms contain classically hard instances assuming $\text{P}\neq \text{BQP}$. Later, we discuss and analyze several important aspects of the algorithm including generalizing to other types of Hamiltonians and the "non-linear`` dynamics in the algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.13946v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhong-Xia Shang, Zi-Han Chen, Chao-Yang Lu, Jian-Wei Pan, Ming-Cheng Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Measurement Encoding for Quantum Metrology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.15622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.15622v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Preserving the precision of the parameter of interest in the presence of environmental decoherence is an important yet challenging task in dissipative quantum sensing. In this work, we study quantum metrology when the decoherence effect is unraveled by a set of quantum measurements,dubbed quantum measurement encoding. In our case, the estimation parameter is encoded into a quantum state through a quantum measurement, unlike the parameter encoding through a unitary channel in the decoherence-free case or trace-preserving quantum channels in the case of decoherence. We identify conditions for a precision-preserving measurement encoding. These conditions can be employed to transfer metrological information from one subsystem to another through quantum measurements. Furthermore, postselected non-Hermitian sensing can also be viewed as quantum sensing with measurement encoding. When the precision-preserving conditions are violated in non-Hermitian sensing, we derive a universal formula for the loss of precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.15622v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The relative entropy of coherence quantifies performance in Bayesian metrology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.16020</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.16020v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The ability of quantum states to be in superposition is one of the key features that sets them apart from the classical world. This `coherence' is rigorously quantified by resource theories, which aim to understand how such properties may be exploited in quantum technologies. There has been much research on what the resource theory of coherence can reveal about quantum metrology, almost all of which has been from the viewpoint of Fisher information. We prove however that the relative entropy of coherence, and its recent generalisation to POVMs, naturally quantify the performance of Bayesian metrology. In particular, we show how a coherence measure can be applied to an ensemble of states. We then prove that during parameter estimation, the ensemble relative entropy of coherence is equal to the difference between the information gained, and the optimal Holevo information. We call this relation the CXI equality. The ensemble coherence lets us visualise how much information is locked away in superposition inaccessible with a given measurement scheme, and quantify the advantage that would be gained by using a joint measurement on multiple states. Our results hold regardless of how the parameter is encoded in the state, encompassing unitary, dissipative, and discrete settings. We consider both projective measurements, and general POVMs. This work suggests new directions for research in quantum resource theories, provides a novel operational interpretation for the relative entropy of coherence and its POVM generalisation, and introduces a new tool to study the role of quantum features in metrology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.16020v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PRX Quantum 5, 030303 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ruvi Lecamwasam, Syed M Assad, Joseph J Hope, Ping Koy Lam, Jayne Thompson, Mile Gu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-classical correlations between a quantum probe and complex quantum systems in presence of noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.09618</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.09618v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Non-classical correlations generated within a quantum probe system when it interacts with a large, macroscopic system can signal the presence of quantum features in the latter. Theoretical models have considered how entanglement generated in photosynthetic bacteria can be probed using light that interacts with them. More recently, a tardigrade was entangled to a transmon qubit. We consider a detailed model including noise for such systems wherein a small quantum probe interacts with a large system in order to delineate the regimes with respect to coupling strengths and noise levels in which such signatures of quantumness in macroscopic systems can realistically be detected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.09618v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bijoy John Mathew, Sanchit Srivastava, Anil Shaji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Quantum Approach to Synthetic Minority Oversampling Technique (SMOTE)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.17398v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The paper proposes the Quantum-SMOTE method, a novel solution that uses quantum computing techniques to solve the prevalent problem of class imbalance in machine learning datasets. Quantum-SMOTE, inspired by the Synthetic Minority Oversampling Technique (SMOTE), generates synthetic data points using quantum processes such as swap tests and quantum rotation. The process varies from the conventional SMOTE algorithm's usage of K-Nearest Neighbors (KNN) and Euclidean distances, enabling synthetic instances to be generated from minority class data points without relying on neighbor proximity. The algorithm asserts greater control over the synthetic data generation process by introducing hyperparameters such as rotation angle, minority percentage, and splitting factor, which allow for customization to specific dataset requirements. Due to the use of a compact swap test, the algorithm can accommodate a large number of features. Furthermore, the approach is tested on a public dataset of Telecom Churn and evaluated alongside two prominent classification algorithms, Random Forest and Logistic Regression, to determine its impact along with varying proportions of synthetic data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.17398v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nishikanta Mohanty, Bikash K. Behera, Christopher Ferrie, Pravat Dash</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fault-tolerance of the [[8,1,3]] non-CSS code</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.19389</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.19389v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a fault-tolerant [[8, 1, 3]] non-CSS quantum error correcting code and study its logical error rates. We choose the unitary encoding procedure for stabilizer codes given by Gottesman and modify it to suit the setting of a class of non- CSS codes. Considering two types of noise models for this study, namely the depolarising noise and anisotropic noise, to depict the logical error rates obtained in decoding, we adopt the procedure of the bare ancilla method presented by Brown et al. to reorder the measurement sequence in the syndrome extraction step and upgrade it to obtain higher pseudo-thresholds and lower leading order terms of logical error rates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.19389v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pranav Maheshwari, Ankur Raina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonperturbative cavity quantum electrodynamics: is the Jaynes-Cummings model still relevant?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02402v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this tutorial review, we briefly discuss the role that the Jaynes-Cummings model occupies in present-day research in cavity quantum electrodynamics with a particular focus on the so-called ultrastrong coupling regime. We start by critically analyzing the various approximations required to distill such a simple model from standard quantum electrodynamics. We then discuss how many of those approximations can, and often have been broken in recent experiments. The consequence of these failures has been the need to abandon the Jaynes-Cummings model for more complex models. In this, the quantum Rabi model has the most prominent role and we will rapidly survey its rich and peculiar phenomenology. We conclude the paper by showing how the Jaynes-Cummings model still plays a crucial role even in non-perturbative light-matter coupling regimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02402v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1364/JOSAB.522786</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Opt. Soc. Am. B 41, C206-C221 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Daniele De Bernardis, Alberto Mercurio, Simone De Liberato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extending echo state property for quantum reservoir computing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02686</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02686v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The echo state property (ESP) represents a fundamental concept in the reservoir computing (RC) framework that ensures output-only training of reservoir networks by being agnostic to the initial states and far past inputs. However, the traditional definition of ESP does not describe possible non-stationary systems in which statistical properties evolve. To address this issue, we introduce two new categories of ESP: $\textit{non-stationary ESP}$, designed for potentially non-stationary systems, and $\textit{subspace/subset ESP}$, designed for systems whose subsystems have ESP. Following the definitions, we numerically demonstrate the correspondence between non-stationary ESP in the quantum reservoir computer (QRC) framework with typical Hamiltonian dynamics and input encoding methods using non-linear autoregressive moving-average (NARMA) tasks. We also confirm the correspondence by computing linear/non-linear memory capacities that quantify input-dependent components within reservoir states. Our study presents a new understanding of the practical design of QRC and other possibly non-stationary RC systems in which non-stationary systems and subsystems are exploited.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02686v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shumpei Kobayashi, Quoc Hoan Tran, Kohei Nakajima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent Continuous Time Crystal in Dissipative Quantum Spin System without Driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08476v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Time crystal, a nonequilibrium phenomenon extending spontaneous symmetry breaking into the temporal dimension, holds fundamental significance in understanding quantum many-body physics. In this work, we explore the nonequilibrium phase diagram of a two-dimensional dissipative Heisenberg spin system without explicit coherent or incoherent external driving. We numerically identify the emergence of novel nonstationary oscillatory states by analyzing the spin dynamics. These states are categorized as limit cycle and chaos based on the Lyapunov exponent. Remarkably, the observed limit cycle behavior represents a continuous time crystal (CTC), spontaneously breaking the continuous time translation symmetry of the system. We further confirm those oscillatory behaviors by studying the stability against local perturbations applied to the system. Finally, we investigate the robustness of the emergent CTC by introducing isotropic Gaussian-type white noise into the interactions. This study provides many insights into the intricate interplay between the dissipation-induced spin downwards and anisotropic-interaction-induced spin precession or spin fluctuation, opening a new avenue for realizing dissipation-induced, heating-immune TCs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08476v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shu Yang, Zeqing Wang, Libin Fu, Jianwen Jie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum critical engine at finite temperatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20172v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct a quantum critical Otto engine that is powered by finite temperature baths. We show that the work output of the engine shows universal power law behavior that depends on the critical exponents of the working medium, as well as on the temperature of the cold bath. Furthermore, higher temperatures of the cold bath allows the engine to approach the limit of adiabatic operation for smaller values of the time period, while the corresponding power shows a maximum at an intermediate value of the cold bath temperature. These counterintuitive results stems from thermal excitations dominating the dynamics at higher temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20172v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjb/s10051-024-00721-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. B 97, 76 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Revathy B S, Victor Mukherjee, Uma Divakaran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Piecemeal Quantum Telescope with Super Efficiency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03432v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Detecting remote objects with higher precision takes a crucial role in many scientific tasks, such as astronomical observation. The precision of existing quantum telescopes is improved in the scale of square root of incident single-photons. Here we propose the piecemeal quantum telescope with high efficiency through bit-by-bit iteration. It improves precision exponentially requesting only a small number of incident single-photons in detecting the star angle. As a result, it requests to detect only a few hundreds of photons for a precision breaking classical limit by 4 to 5 magnitude orders. Moreover, our method can be applied to distinguish a general astronomical target consisting of unknown number of stars with high resolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03432v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian Leng, Yi-Xin Shen, Zhou-Kai Cao, Xiang-Bin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational Quantum Crank-Nicolson and Method of Lines for the Solution of Initial Value Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07016v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we use a Variational Quantum Algorithm to solve Initial Value Problems with the Implicit Crank-Nicolson and the Method of Lines (MoL) evolution schemes. The unknown functions use a spectral decomposition with the Fourier basis. The examples developed to illustrate the implementation are the Advection equation, the wave equation written as a system of first order coupled equations and the viscous Burgers equation as a non-linear case. The problems are solved using: i) standard Finite Differences as the solution to compare with, ii) the State Vector Formalism (SVF), and iii) the Sampling Error Formalism (SEF). The contributions of this paper include: 1) cost functions for generic first order in time PDEs using the implicit Crank-Nicholson and the MoL, 2) detailed convergence or self-convergence tests are presented for all the equations solved, 3) a system of three coupled PDEs is solved, 4) solutions using sampling error are presented and 5) a fast version of the SVF and SEF was developed which can be used to test different optimizers faster.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07016v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francisco Guzman-Cajica, Francisco S. Guzman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A quantum annealing approach to the minimum distance problem of quantum codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17703v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum error-correcting codes (QECCs) is at the heart of fault-tolerant quantum computing. As the size of quantum platforms is expected to grow, one of the open questions is to design new optimal codes of ever-increasing size. A related challenge is to ``certify'' the quality of a given code by evaluating its minimum distance, a quantity characterizing code's capacity to preserve quantum information. This problem is known to be NP-hard. Here we propose to harness the power of contemporary quantum platforms to address this question, and in this way help design quantum platforms of the future. Namely, we introduce an approach to compute the minimum distance of quantum stabilizer codes by reformulating the problem as a Quadratic Unconstrained Binary Optimization (QUBO) problem and leveraging established QUBO algorithms and heuristics as well as quantum annealing (QA) to address the latter. The reformulation as a QUBO introduces only a logarithmic multiplicative overhead in the required number of variables. We demonstrate practical viability of our method by comparing the performance of purely classical algorithms with the D-Wave Advantage 4.1 quantum annealer as well as hybrid quantum-classical algorithm Qbsolv. We found that the hybrid approach demonstrates competitive performance, on par with the best available classical algorithms to solve QUBO. In a practical sense, the QUBO-based approach is currently lagging behind the best deterministic minimal distance algorithms, however this advantage may disappear as the size of the platforms grows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17703v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Refat Ismail, Ashish Kakkar, Anatoly Dymarsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized group designs: overcoming the 4-design-barrier and constructing novel unitary 2-designs in arbitrary dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00919v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Unitary designs are essential tools in several quantum information protocols. Similarly to other design concepts, unitary designs are mainly used to facilitate averaging over a relevant space, in this case, the unitary group $\mathrm{U}(d)$. While it is known that exact unitary $t$-designs exist for any degree $t$ and dimension $d$, the most appealing type of designs, group designs (in which the elements of the design form a group), can provide at most $3$-designs. Moreover, even group $2$-designs can only exist in limited dimensions. In this paper, we present novel construction methods for creating exact generalized group designs based on the representation theory of the unitary group and its finite subgroups that overcome the $4$-design-barrier of unitary group designs. Furthermore, a construction is presented for creating generalized group $2$-designs in arbitrary dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00919v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\'Agoston Kaposi, Zolt\'an Kolarovszki, Adri\'an Solymos, Zolt\'an Zimbor\'as</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong-to-Weak Spontaneous Symmetry Breaking in Mixed Quantum States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.03639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.03639v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Symmetry in mixed quantum states can manifest in two distinct forms: \textit{strong symmetry}, where each individual pure state in the quantum ensemble is symmetric with the same charge, and \textit{weak symmetry}, which applies only to the entire ensemble. This paper explores a novel type of spontaneous symmetry breaking (SSB) where a strong symmetry is broken to a weak one. While the SSB of a weak symmetry is measured by the long-ranged two-point correlation function $\mathrm{Tr}(O_xO^{\dagger}_y\rho)$, the strong-to-weak SSB (SW-SSB) is measured by the fidelity $F(\rho, O_xO^{\dagger}_y\rho O_yO^{\dagger}_x)$, dubbed the \textit{fidelity correlator}. We prove that SW-SSB is a universal property of mixed-state quantum phases, in the sense that the phenomenon of SW-SSB is robust against symmetric low-depth local quantum channels. { We also show that the symmetry breaking is "spontaneous
" in the sense that the effect of a local symmetry-breaking measurement cannot be recovered locally.} We argue that a thermal state at a nonzero temperature in the canonical ensemble (with fixed symmetry charge) should have spontaneously broken strong symmetry. Additionally, we study non-thermal scenarios where decoherence induces SW-SSB, leading to phase transitions described by classical statistical models with bond randomness. In particular, the SW-SSB transition of a decohered Ising model can be viewed as the "ungauged" version of the celebrated toric code decodability transition. We confirm that, in the decohered Ising model, the SW-SSB transition defined by the fidelity correlator is the only physical transition in terms of channel recoverability. We also comment on other (inequivalent) definitions of SW-SSB, through correlation functions with higher R\'enyi indices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.03639v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonardo A. Lessa, Ruochen Ma, Jian-Hao Zhang, Zhen Bi, Meng Cheng, Chong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Exact Generalized Grover's Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.06963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.06963v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Distributed quantum computation has garnered immense attention in the noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) era, where each computational node necessitates fewer qubits and quantum gates. In this paper, we focus on a generalized search problem involving multiple targets within an unordered database and propose a Distributed Exact Generalized Grover's Algorithm (DEGGA) to address this challenge by decomposing it into arbitrary $t$ components, where $2 \leq t \leq n$. Specifically, (1) our algorithm ensures accuracy, with a theoretical probability of identifying the target states at $100\%$; (2) if the number of targets is fixed, the pivotal factor influencing the circuit depth of DEGGA is the partitioning strategy, rather than the magnitude of $n$; (3) our method requires a total of $n$ qubits, eliminating the need for auxiliary qubits; (4) we elucidate the resolutions (two-node and three-node) of a particular generalized search issue incorporating two goal strings (000000 and 111111) by applying DEGGA. The feasibility and effectiveness of our suggested approach is further demonstrated by executing the quantum circuits on MindSpore Quantum (a quantum simulation software). Eventually, through the decomposition of multi-qubit gates, DEGGA diminishes the utilization of quantum gates by $90.7\%$ and decreases the circuit depth by $91.3\%$ in comparison to the modified Grover's algorithm by Long. It is increasingly evident that distributed quantum algorithms offer augmented practicality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.06963v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xu Zhou, Xusheng Xu, Shenggen Zheng, Le Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Federated Hierarchical Tensor Networks: a Collaborative Learning Quantum AI-Driven Framework for Healthcare</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.07735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.07735v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Healthcare industries frequently handle sensitive and proprietary data, and due to strict privacy regulations, they are often reluctant to share data directly. In today's context, Federated Learning (FL) stands out as a crucial remedy, facilitating the rapid advancement of distributed machine learning while effectively managing critical concerns regarding data privacy and governance. The fusion of federated learning and quantum computing represents a groundbreaking interdisciplinary approach with immense potential to revolutionize various industries, from healthcare to finance. In this work, we proposed a federated learning framework based on quantum tensor networks, which leverages the principles of many-body quantum physics. Currently, there are no known classical tensor networks implemented in federated settings. Furthermore, we investigated the effectiveness and feasibility of the proposed framework by conducting a differential privacy analysis to ensure the security of sensitive data across healthcare institutions. Experiments on popular medical image datasets show that the federated quantum tensor network model achieved a mean receiver-operator characteristic area under the curve (ROC-AUC) between 0.91-0.98. Experimental results demonstrate that the quantum federated global model, consisting of highly entangled tensor network structures, showed better generalization and robustness and achieved higher testing accuracy, surpassing the performance of locally trained clients under unbalanced data distributions among healthcare institutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.07735v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amandeep Singh Bhatia, David E. Bernal Neira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized cluster states from Hopf algebras: non-invertible symmetry and Hopf tensor network representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09277v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Cluster states are crucial resources for measurement-based quantum computation (MBQC). It exhibits symmetry-protected topological (SPT) order, thus also playing a crucial role in studying topological phases. We present the construction of cluster states based on Hopf algebras. By generalizing the finite group valued qudit to a Hopf algebra valued qudit and introducing the generalized Pauli-X operator based on the regular action of the Hopf algebra, as well as the generalized Pauli-Z operator based on the irreducible representation action on the Hopf algebra, we develop a comprehensive theory of Hopf qudits. We demonstrate that non-invertible symmetry naturally emerges for Hopf qudits. Subsequently, for a bipartite graph termed the cluster graph, we assign the identity state and trivial representation state to even and odd vertices, respectively. Introducing the edge entangler as controlled regular action, we provide a general construction of Hopf cluster states. To ensure the commutativity of the edge entangler, we propose a method to construct a cluster lattice for any triangulable manifold. We use the 1d cluster state as an example to illustrate our construction. As this serves as a promising candidate for SPT phases, we construct the gapped Hamiltonian for this scenario and delve into a detailed discussion of its non-invertible symmetries. We also show that the 1d cluster state model is equivalent to the quasi-1d Hopf quantum double model. We also introduce the Hopf tensor network representation of Hopf cluster states by integrating the tensor representation of structure constants with the string diagrams of the Hopf algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09277v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhian Jia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generation of quantum phases of matter and finding maximum-weight independent set of unit-disk graphs using Rydberg atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09803v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent progress in quantum computing and quantum simulation of many-body systems with arrays of neutral atoms using Rydberg excitation brought unforeseen opportunities towards computational advantage in solving various optimization problems. The problem of maximum-weight independent set (MWIS) of unit-disk graphs is an example of NP-hard optimization problems. It involves finding the largest set of vertices with the maximum sum of their weights for a graph which has edges connecting all pairs of vertices within a unit distance. This problem can be solved using quantum annealing with an array of interacting Rydberg atoms. For a particular graph, a spatial arrangement of atoms represents vertices of the graph, while the detuning from the resonance at Rydberg excitation defines weights of these vertices. The edges of the graph can be drawn according to the unit disk criterion. MWIS can be obtained by applying a variational quantum adiabatic algorithm (VQAA). We consider driving the quantum system of interacting atoms to the many-body ground state using a non-linear quasi-adiabatic profile for sweeping the Rydberg detuning. We also propose using a quantum wire which is a set of auxiliary atoms of a different chemical element to mediate strong coupling between the remote vertices of the graph. We investigate this effect for different lengths of the quantum wire. We also investigate the quantum phases of matter realizing commensurate and incommensurate phases in 1D and 2D spatial arrangement of the atomic array.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09803v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmed M. Farouk, I. I. Beterov, Peng Xu, I. I. Ryabtsev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcement learning-based architecture search for quantum machine learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02717</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02717v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum machine learning models use encoding circuits to map data into a quantum Hilbert space. While it is well known that the architecture of these circuits significantly influences core properties of the resulting model, they are often chosen heuristically. In this work, we present a novel approach using reinforcement learning techniques to generate problem-specific encoding circuits to improve the performance of quantum machine learning models. By specifically using a model-based reinforcement learning algorithm, we reduce the number of necessary circuit evaluations during the search, providing a sample-efficient framework. In contrast to previous search algorithms, our method uses a layered circuit structure that significantly reduces the search space. Additionally, our approach can account for multiple objectives such as solution quality, hardware restrictions and circuit depth. We benchmark our tailored circuits against various reference models, including models with problem-agnostic circuits and classical models. Our results highlight the effectiveness of problem-specific encoding circuits in enhancing QML model performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02717v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Frederic Rapp, David A. Kreplin, Marco Roth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complementarity-based complementarity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11395</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11395v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that the amount of complementarity that a quantum system can exhibit depends on which complementary properties one is considering. Consider a set of mutually unbiased bases (MUBs) which corresponds to the spectral decomposition of some maximally complementary properties: The perfect knowledge of one, i.e. the state of the system is one of the basis states, implies that all the others are completely unknown, namely the measurement of another property will find any of its possible outcomes with uniform probability. We show that, depending on which three of the MUBs we choose, a 5-dimensional system can have different degrees of complementarity, measured using the minimum over all the system states of the sum of the entropies and of the variances of the measurement outcomes related to the three chosen observables. This property was first found experimentally, and demonstrates that an experimental discovery can disclose quantum information effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11395v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laura Serino, Giovanni Chesi, Benjamin Brecht, Lorenzo Maccone, Chiara Macchiavello, Christine Silberhorn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constant search time algorithm via topological quantum walks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18768</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18768v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is well-known that quantum algorithms such as Grover's can provide a quadradic speed-up for unstructured search problems. By adding topological structure to a search problem, we show that it is possible to achieve a constant search-time quantum algorithm with a constant improvement of the search probability over classical search. Specifically, we study the spatial search algorithm implemented by a two-dimensional split-step quantum random walks that realize topologically nontrivial phases and show the asymptotic search behavior is constant with growing system size. Using analytical and numerical calculations, we determine the efficient search regions in the parameter space of the quantum walker. These regions correspond to pairs of trapped states formed near a lattice defect. By studying the spectral properties of the discrete time-evolution-operators, we show that these trapped states have large overlap with the initial state. This correspondence, which is analogous to localization by constructive interference of bound states, makes it possible to reach the best possible search-time asymptotic and produce a disorder-protected fast search in quantum random walks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18768v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. O. Oriekhov, Guliuxin Jin, Eliska Greplova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error mitigation with stabilized noise in superconducting quantum processors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02467v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Pre-fault tolerant quantum computers have already demonstrated the ability to estimate observable values accurately, at a scale beyond brute-force classical computation. This has been enabled by error mitigation techniques that often rely on a representative model on the device noise. However, learning and maintaining these models is complicated by fluctuations in the noise over unpredictable time scales, for instance, arising from resonant interactions between superconducting qubits and defect two-level systems (TLS). Such interactions affect the stability and uniformity of device performance as a whole, but also affect the noise model accuracy, leading to incorrect observable estimation. Here, we experimentally demonstrate that tuning of the qubit-TLS interactions helps reduce noise instabilities and consequently enables more reliable error-mitigation performance. These experiments provide a controlled platform for studying the performance of error mitigation in the presence of quasi-static noise. We anticipate that the capabilities introduced here will be crucial for the exploration of quantum applications on solid-state processors at non-trivial scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02467v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youngseok Kim, Luke C. G. Govia, Andrew Dane, Ewout van den Berg, David M. Zajac, Bradley Mitchell, Yinyu Liu, Karthik Balakrishnan, George Keefe, Adam Stabile, Emily Pritchett, Jiri Stehlik, Abhinav Kandala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A quantum approach for optimal control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02864v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we propose a novel variational quantum approach for solving a class of nonlinear optimal control problems. Our approach integrates Dirac's canonical quantization of dynamical systems with the solution of the ground state of the resulting non-Hermitian Hamiltonian via a variational quantum eigensolver (VQE). We introduce a new perspective on the Dirac bracket formulation for generalized Hamiltonian dynamics in the presence of constraints, providing a clear motivation and illustrative examples. Additionally, we explore the structural properties of Dirac brackets within the context of multidimensional constrained optimization problems.
  Our approach for solving a class of nonlinear optimal control problems employs a VQE-based approach to determine the eigenstate and corresponding eigenvalue associated with the ground state energy of a non-Hermitian Hamiltonian. Assuming access to an ideal VQE, our formulation demonstrates excellent results, as evidenced by selected computational examples. Furthermore, our method performs well when combined with a VQE-based approach for non-Hermitian Hamiltonian systems. Our VQE-based formulation effectively addresses challenges associated with a wide range of optimal control problems, particularly in high-dimensional scenarios. Compared to standard classical approaches, our quantum-based method shows significant promise and offers a compelling alternative for tackling complex, high-dimensional optimization challenges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02864v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hirmay Sandesara, Alok Shukla, Prakash Vedula</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unique continuation for many-body Schr\"odinger operators and the Hohenberg-Kohn theorem. II. The Pauli Hamiltonian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1901.03207</link>
      <description>arXiv:1901.03207v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove the strong unique continuation property for many-body Pauli operators with external potentials, interaction potentials and magnetic fields in $L^p\loc(\R^d)$, and with magnetic potentials in ${L^{q}\loc(\R^d)}$, where ${p &gt; \max(2d/3,2)}$ and ${q &gt; 2d}$. For this purpose, we prove a singular Carleman estimate involving fractional Laplacian operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1901.03207v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.4171/DM/765</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Doc. Math. 25, 869-898 (2020)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Louis Garrigue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum references</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2105.10914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2105.10914v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a theory of "quantum references", similar to lenses in classical functional programming, that allow to point to a subsystem of a larger quantum system, and to mutate/measure that part. Mutable classical variables, quantum registers, and wires in quantum circuits are examples of this, but also references to parts of larger quantum datastructures. Quantum references in our setting can also refer to subparts of other references, or combinations of parts from different references, or quantum references seen in a different basis, etc. Our modeling is intended to be well suited for formalization in theorem provers and as a foundation for modeling variables in quantum programs. We study quantum references in greater detail and cover the infinite-dimensional case as well, but also provide a more general treatment not specific to the quantum case. We implemented a large part of our results (including a small quantum Hoare logic and an analysis of quantum teleportation) in the Isabelle/HOL theorem prover.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2105.10914v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dominique Unruh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the mathematical description of combined PMD PDL effects in optical communications and how their induced impairments can be minimized</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.07855</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.07855v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper it is shown that the correct mathematical framework of combined polarization mode dispersion and polarization dependent losses (combined PMD-PDL effects or impairments) in optical fibers is the irreducible spinor representation of the extended Lorentz Group. Combined PMD-PDL effects are shown to be formally identical to Lorentz Transformations acting on spin 1/2 zero mass particles. Since there are two different irreducible spinor representations of the restricted Lorentz Group, there must also exist two kinds of states of polarizations (SOPs) that are relevant in the description of PMD-PDL effects. The optical process that allows to convert one kind into the other is identified as optical phase conjugation. Optical phase conjugation plays the same role as the time inversion operator in the Lorentz Group representation theory. A practical and extremely important example of utility of these ideas, a technique that significantly reduces the PMD-PDL induced impairments, is presented. This technique allows to cancel the PDL part of the combined PMD-PDL impairments in a very simple and straightforward way.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.07855v5</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos L. Janer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General-relativistic wave$-$particle duality with torsion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.03234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.03234v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose that the four-velocity of a Dirac particle is related to its relativistic wave function by $u^i=\bar{\psi}\gamma^i\psi/\bar{\psi}\psi$. This relativistic wave$-$particle duality relation is demonstrated for a free particle related to a plane wave in a flat spacetime. For a curved spacetime with torsion, the momentum four-vector of a spinor is related to a generator of translation, given by a covariant derivative. The spin angular momentum four-tensor of a spinor is related to a generator of rotation in the Lorentz group. We use the covariant conservation laws for the spin and energy$-$momentum tensors for a spinor field in the presence of the Einstein$-$Cartan torsion to show that if the wave satisfies the curved Dirac equation, then the four-velocity, four-momentum, and spin satisfy the classical Mathisson$-$Papapetrou equations of motion. We show that these equations reduce to the geodesic equation. Consequently, the motion of a particle guided by the four-velocity in the pilot-wave quantum mechanics coincides with the geodesic motion determined by spacetime. We also show how the duality and the operator form of the Mathisson$-$Papapetrou equations arise from the covariant Heisenberg equation of motion in the presence of torsion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.03234v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6382/ad1fcb</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Class. Quantum Grav. 41, 065011 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Francisco Ribeiro Benard Guedes, Nikodem Janusz Pop{\l}awski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>\boldmath $SU(\infty)$ Quantum Gravity: Emergence of Gravity in an Infinitely Divisible Quantum Universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.02813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.02813v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: $SU(\infty)$-QGR is a foundationally quantum approach to gravity. It assumes that the Hilbert space of the Universe as a whole represents the symmetry group $SU(\infty)$, and demonstrates this symmetry for Hilbert spaces of infinite number of subsystems that randomly emerge and represent arbitrary finite rank internal symmetries. It is shown that their states depend on a dimensionful parameter arising due to the breaking of a global $U(1)$ symmetry, and a relative dynamics can be defined by selection of a subsystem as clock. The action has the form of a Yang-Mills quantum field theory defined on the (3+1)-dimensional parameter space for both $SU(\infty)$ - gravity - and internal symmetries. Therefore, $SU(\infty)$-QGR is renormalizable, but predicts a spin-1 mediator for quantum gravity. Nonetheless, it is proved that when quantum gravity effects are not detectable, dynamics is similar to the Einstein-Hilbert action. The aim of present work is in depth study of the foundation and properties of this model. In particular, we show that the global $SU(\infty)$ symmetry manifests itself through the entanglement of subsystems with the rest of the Universe, and demonstrate irrelevance of geometry of the parameter space for observables. Hence, $SU(\infty)$-QGR deviates from gauge-gravity duality models, because the classical spacetime is an emergent effective geometry with negative signature, reflecting relative variation of quantum states of subsystems and quantum uncertainties. We also briefly discuss $SU(\infty)$-QGR specific models for dark energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.02813v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Houri Ziaeepour</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When the Machine Chimes the Bell: Entanglement and Bell Inequalities with Boosted $t\bar{t}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.07075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.07075v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Large Hadron Collider provides a unique opportunity to study quantum entanglement and violation of Bell inequalities at the highest energy available today. In this paper, we will investigate these quantum correlations with top quark pair production, which represents a system of two-qubits. The spacelike separation requirement for the two causally disconnected top quarks requires they fly relativistically away from each other, which motivates the use of the boosted top-tagging with the semi-leptonic top pair channel. Although measuring the spin polarization of the hadronic top quark is known to be challenging, our study indicates that it is feasible to reconstruct the spin density matrix of the two-qubit system using an optimal hadronic polarimeter. This is achieved with the aid of jet substructure techniques and NN-inspired reconstruction methods, which improve the mapping between subjets and quarks. We find that entanglement can already be observed at more than $5\sigma$ level with existing data, and violation of Bell inequalities may be probed above 4$\sigma$ level at the HL-LHC with 3 ab$^{-1}$ of data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.07075v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.115023</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D (Vol. 109, No. 11), 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zhongtian Dong, Dorival Gon\c{c}alves, Kyoungchul Kong, Alberto Navarro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipative time crystal in a strongly interacting Rydberg gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.20070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.20070v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The notion of spontaneous symmetry breaking has been well established to characterize classical and quantum phase transitions of matter, such as in condensation, crystallization or quantum magnetism. Generalizations of this paradigm to the time dimension can lead to a time crystal phase, which spontaneously breaks the time translation symmetry of the system. Whereas the existence of a continuous time crystal at equilibrium has been challenged by no-go theorems, this difficulty can be circumvented by dissipation in an open system. Here, we report the experimental observation of such dissipative time crystalline order in a room-temperature atomic gas, where ground-state atoms are continuously driven to Rydberg states. The emergent time crystal is revealed by persistent oscillations of the photon transmission, and we show that the observed limit cycles arise from the coexistence and competition between distinct Rydberg components. The nondecaying autocorrelation of the oscillation, together with the robustness against temporal noises, indicate the establishment of true long-range temporal order and demonstrates the realization of a continuous time crystal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.20070v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41567-024-02542-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nat. Phys. (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoling Wu, Zhuqing Wang, Fan Yang, Ruochen Gao, Chao Liang, Meng Khoon Tey, Xiangliang Li, Thomas Pohl, Li You</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal duality of the nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation: Theory and applications to parameter estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.17720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.17720v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation (NLSE) is a rich and versatile model, which in one spatial dimension has stationary solutions similar to those of the linear Schr\"odinger equation as well as more exotic solutions such as solitary waves and quantum droplets. Here we present the unified theory of the NLSE, showing that all stationary solutions of the local one-dimensional cubic-quintic NLSE can be classified according to a single number called the cross-ratio. Any two solutions with the same cross-ratio can be converted into one another using a conformal transformation, and the same also holds true for traveling wave solutions. Further, we introduce an optimization afterburner that relies on this conformal symmetry to substantially improve NLSE parameter estimation from noisy empirical data. The new method therefore should have far reaching practical applications for nonlinear physical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.17720v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David B. Reinhardt, Dean Lee, Wolfgang P. Schleich, Matthias Meister</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On temporal entropy and the complexity of computing the expectation value of local operators after a quench</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.11649</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.11649v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the computational complexity of simulating the time-dependent expectation value of a local operator in a one-dimensional quantum system by using temporal matrix product states. We argue that such cost is intimately related to that of encoding temporal transition matrices and their partial traces. In particular, we show that we can upper-bound the rank of these reduced transition matrices by the one of the Heisenberg evolution of local operators, thus making connection between two apparently different quantities, the temporal entanglement and the local operator entanglement. As a result, whenever the local operator entanglement grows slower than linearly in time, we show that computing time-dependent expectation values of local operators using temporal matrix product states is likely advantageous with respect to computing the same quantities using standard matrix product states techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.11649v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.6.033021</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Carignano, Carlos Ramos Marim\'on, Luca Tagliacozzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fano resonances in tilted Weyl semimetals in an oscillating quantum well</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.15928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.15928v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Considering the low-energy model of tilted Weyl semimetal, we study the electronic transmission through a periodically driven quantum well, oriented in the transverse direction with respect to the tilt. We adopt the formalism of Floquet scattering theory and investigate the emergence of Fano resonances as an outcome of matching between the Floquet sidebands and quasi-bound states. The Fano resonance energy changes linearly with the tilt strength suggesting the fact that tilt-mediated part of quasi-bound states energies depends on the above factor. Given a value of momentum parallel (perpendicular) to the tilt, we find that the energy gap between two Fano resonances, appearing for two adjacent values of transverse (collinear) momentum with respect to the tilt direction, is insensitive (sensitive) to the change in the tilt strength. Such a coupled (decoupled) behavior of tilt strength and the collinear (transverse) momentum can be understood from the tilt-mediated and normal parts of the quasi-bound state energies inside the potential well. We vary the other tilt parameters and chirality of the Weyl points to conclusively verify the exact form of the tilt-mediated part of the quasi-bound state energy that is the same as the tilt term in the static dispersion. The tilt orientation can significantly alter the transport in terms of evolution of Fano resoance energy with tilt momentum. We analytically find the explicit form of the bound state energy that further supports all our numerical findings. Our work paves the way to probe the tilt-mediated part of quasi-bound state energy to understand the complex interplay between the tilt and Fano resonance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.15928v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-648X/ad5acd</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 36 395804 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Souvik Das, Arnab Maity, Rajib Sarkar, Anirudha Menon, Tanay Nag, Banasri Basu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homotopy, Symmetry, and Non-Hermitian Band Topology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.14416</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.14416v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Non-Hermitian matrices are ubiquitous in the description of nature ranging from classical dissipative systems, including optical, electrical, and mechanical metamaterials, to scattering of waves and open quantum many-body systems. Seminal line-gap and point-gap classifications of non-Hermitian systems using K-theory have deepened the understanding of many physical phenomena. However, ample systems remain beyond this description; reference points and lines do not in general distinguish whether multiple non-Hermitian bands exhibit intriguing exceptional points, spectral braids and crossings. To address this we consider two different notions: non-Hermitian band gaps and separation gaps that crucially encompass a broad class of multi-band scenarios, enabling the description of generic band structures with symmetries. With these concepts, we provide a unified and comprehensive classification of both gapped and nodal systems in the presence of physically relevant parity-time ($\mathcal{PT}$) and pseudo-Hermitian symmetries using homotopy theory. This uncovers new stable topology stemming from both eigenvalues and wave functions, and remarkably also implies distinct fragile topological phases. In particular, we reveal different Abelian and non-Abelian phases in $\mathcal{PT}$-symmetric systems, described by frame and braid topology. The corresponding invariants are robust to symmetry-preserving perturbations that do not induce (exceptional) degeneracy, and they also predict the deformation rules of nodal phases. We further demonstrate that spontaneous $\mathcal{PT}$ symmetry breaking is captured by Chern-Euler and Chern-Stiefel-Whitney descriptions, a fingerprint of unprecedented non-Hermitian topology previously overlooked. These results open the door for theoretical and experimental exploration of a rich variety of novel topological phenomena in a wide range of physical platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.14416v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6633/ad4e64</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Rep. Prog. Phys. 87 078002 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kang Yang, Zhi Li, J. Lukas K. K\"onig, Lukas R{\o}dland, Marcus St{\aa}lhammar, Emil J. Bergholtz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polariton Fluids as Quantum Field Theory Simulators on Tailored Curved Spacetimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.01392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.01392v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum fields in curved spacetime exhibit a wealth of effects like Hawking radiation from black holes. While quantum field theory in black holes can only be studied theoretically, it can be tested in controlled laboratory experiments. In experiments, a fluid going from sub- to supersonic speed creates an effectively curved spacetime for the acoustic field, with a horizon where the speed of the fluid equals the speed of sound. The challenge to test predictions like the Hawking effect in such systems lies in the control of the spacetime curvature and access to the field spectrum thereon. Here, we create tailored stationary effective curved spacetimes in a polaritonic quantum fluid of light in which either massless or massive excitations can be created, with smooth and steep horizons and various supersonic fluid speeds. Using a recently developed spectroscopy method we measure the spectrum of collective excitations on these spacetimes, crucially observing negative energy modes in the supersonic regions, which signals the formation of a horizon. Control over the horizon curvature and access to the spectrum on either side demonstrates the potential of quantum fluids of light for the study of field theories on curved spacetimes, and we discuss the possibility of investigating emission and spectral instabilities with a horizon or in an effective Exotic Compact Object configuration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.01392v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K\'evin Falque, Adri\`a Delhom, Quentin Glorieux, Elisabeth Giacobino, Alberto Bramati, Maxime J Jacquet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Bell inequalities be tested via scattering cross-section at colliders ?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.01162</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.01162v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In current studies for testing Bell inequalities at colliders, the reconstruction of spin correlations from scattering cross-sections relies on the bilinear form of the spin correlations, but not all local hidden variable models (LHVMs) have such a property. To demonstrate that a general LHVM cannot be rule out via scattering cross-section data, we propose a specific LHVM, which can exactly duplicate the same scattering cross-section for particle production and decay as the standard quantum theory, making it indistinguishable at colliders in principle. Despite of this, we find that reconstructing spin correlations through scattering cross-sections can still exclude a broad class of LHVMs, e.g., those models employing classical spin correlations as a surrogate for quantum spin correlations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.01162v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Song Li, Wei Shen, Jin Min Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controlling Many-Body Quantum Chaos: Bose-Hubbard systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.17744</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.17744v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This work develops a quantum control application of many-body quantum chaos for ultracold bosonic gases trapped in optical lattices. It is long known how to harness exponential sensitivity to changes in initial conditions for control purposes in classically chaotic systems. In the technique known as targeting, instead of a hindrance to control, the instability becomes a resource. Recently, this classical targeting has been generalized to quantum systems either by periodically countering the inevitable quantum state spreading or by introducing a control Hamiltonian, where both enable localized states to be guided along special chaotic trajectories toward any of a broad variety of desired target states. Only strictly unitary dynamics are involved; i.e., it gives a coherent quantum targeting. In this paper, the introduction of a control Hamiltonian is applied to Bose-Hubbard systems in chaotic dynamical regimes. Properly selected unstable mean field solutions can be followed quite rapidly to states possessing precise phase relationships and occupancies. In essence, the method generates a quantum simulation technique that can access rather special states. The protocol reduces to a time-dependent control of the chemical potentials, opening up the possibility for application in optical lattice experiments. Explicit applications to custom state preparation and stabilization of quantum many-body scars are presented in one- and two-dimensional lattices (three-dimensional applications are similarly possible).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.17744v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1367-2630/ad5752</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Beringer, Mathias Steinhuber, Juan Diego Urbina, Klaus Richter, Steven Tomsovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Satisfiability of commutative vs. non-commutative CSPs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11709v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Mermin-Peres magic square is a celebrated example of a system of Boolean linear equations that is not (classically) satisfiable but is satisfiable via linear operators on a Hilbert space of dimension four. A natural question is then, for what kind of problems such a phenomenon occurs? Atserias, Kolaitis, and Severini answered this question for all Boolean Constraint Satisfaction Problems (CSPs): For 0-Valid-SAT, 1-Valid-SAT, 2-SAT, Horn-SAT, and Dual Horn-SAT, classical satisfiability and operator satisfiability is the same and thus there is no gap; for all other Boolean CSPs, these notions differ as there are gaps, i.e., there are unsatisfiable instances that are satisfiable via operators on Hilbert spaces.
  We generalize their result to CSPs on arbitrary finite domains and give an almost complete classification: First, we show that NP-hard CSPs admit a separation between classical satisfiability and satisfiability via operators on finite- and infinite-dimensional Hilbert spaces. Second, we show that tractable CSPs of bounded width have no satisfiability gaps of any kind. Finally, we show that tractable CSPs of unbounded width can simulate, in a satisfiability-gap-preserving fashion, linear equations over an Abelian group of prime order $p$; for such CSPs, we obtain a separation of classical satisfiability and satisfiability via operators on infinite-dimensional Hilbert spaces. Furthermore, if $p=2$, such CSPs also have gaps separating classical satisfiability and satisfiability via operators on finite- and infinite-dimensional Hilbert spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11709v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.LO</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei A. Bulatov, Stanislav \v{Z}ivn\'y</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Optimization Model for Multiple-Control Toffoli Quantum Circuit Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14384</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14384v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: As quantum technology is advancing, the efficient design of quantum circuits has become an important area of research. This paper provides an introduction to the MCT quantum circuit design problem for reversible Boolean functions without assuming a prior background in quantum computing. While this is a well-studied problem, optimization models that minimize the true objective have only been explored recently. This paper introduces a new optimization model and symmetry-breaking constraints that improve solving time by up to two orders of magnitude compared to earlier work when a Constraint Programming solver is used. Experiments with up to seven qubits and using up to 15 quantum gates result in several new best-known circuits, obtained by any method, for well-known benchmarks. Finally, an extensive comparison with other approaches shows that optimization models may require more time but can provide superior circuits with optimality guarantees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14384v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jihye Jung, Kevin Dalmeijer, Pascal Van Hentenryck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breaking and trapping Cooper pairs by Rydberg-molecule spectroscopy in atomic Fermi superfluids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01401v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a spectroscopic probe of the breaking and localization of Cooper pairs in an atomic Fermi superfluid interacting with a Rydberg impurity. This is achieved by monitoring the formation of diatomic and triatomic ultralong-range molecular species in the superfluid across the BCS - Bose Einstein condensation (BEC) crossover. The triatomic Rydberg molecule in the BEC regime heralds the trapping of a tightly-bound Cooper pair, reminiscent of pion capture in nuclear matter, while the breaking of a Cooper pair on the BCS side by a diatomic Rydberg molecule is evocative of binary-star tidal disruption by a black hole. Spectroscopy of the Fermi superfluid and Rydberg molecules allows for an estimation of the Cooper-pair size while the Rydberg molecule binding energies discern many-body pairing effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01401v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chih-Chun Chien, Simeon I. Mistakidis, Hossein R. Sadeghpour</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Super-diffusive transport in two-dimensional Fermionic wires</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15560v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a two-dimensional model of a Fermionic wire which shows a power-law conductance behavior despite the presence of uncorrelated disorder along the direction of the transport. The power-law behavior is attributed to the presence of energy eigenstates of diverging localization length below some energy cutoff, $E_c$. To study transport, we place the wire in contact with electron reservoirs biased around a Fermi level, $E$. We show that the conductance scales super-diffusively for $|E|&lt;E_c$ and decays exponentially for $|E|&gt;E_c$. At $|E|=E_c$, we show that the conductance scales diffusively or with different sub-diffusive power-laws depending on the sign of the expectation value of the disorder and the parameters of the wire.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15560v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junaid Majeed Bhat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Women for Quantum -- Manifesto of Values</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02612v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Data show that the presence of women in quantum science is affected by a number of detriments and their percentage decreases even further for higher positions. Beyond data, from our shared personal experiences as female tenured quantum physics professors, we believe that the current model of scientific leadership, funding, and authority fails to represent many of us. It is time for a real change that calls for a different kind of force and for the participation of everyone. Women for quantum calls for a joint effort and aims with this initiative to contribute to such a transformation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02612v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Almut Beige, Ana Predojevi\'c, Anja Metelmann, Anna Sanpera, Chiara Macchiavello, Christiane P. Koch, Christine Silberhorn, Costanza Toninelli, Dagmar Bru{\ss}, Elisa Ercolessi, Elisabetta Paladino, Francesca Ferlaino, Giulia Ferrini, Gloria Platero, Ivette Fuentes, Kae Nemoto, Leticia Tarruell, Maria Bondani, Marilu Chiofalo, Marisa Pons, Milena D'Angelo, Mio Murao, Nicole Fabbri, Paola Verrucchi, Pascale Senellart-Mardon, Roberta Citro, Roberta Zambrini, Rosario Gonz\'alez-F\'erez, Sabrina Maniscalco, Susana Huelga, Tanja Mehlst\"aubler, Valentina Parigi, Ver\'onica Ahufinger</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
