<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 04:00:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Self-oscillating open quantum systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16300v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Evolution of occupation number is studied for a bosonic oscillator (with one and two degrees of freedom) linearly fully coupled to fermionic and bosonic heat baths. The lack of equilibrium in this oscillator is discussed in the light of the creation of an energy source. The connection of such a system with known nonlinear self-oscillating systems is shown.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16300v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. V. Sargsyan, A. A. Hovhannisyan, G. G. Adamian, N. V. Antonenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does the oscillatory behavior of the Momentum Spectrum depend on the basis in the Post-Transient Stage?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16321v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Pair creation by a spatially homogeneous, time-dependent electric field is studied within the framework of scalar quantum electrodynamics. We employ the standard Bogoliubov transformation approach to compute the single-particle distribution function in an adiabatic basis. We analyzed the distribution function of created particles in two different adiabatic bases (related by a unitary transformation). A novel dynamical scaling is observed while analyzing the oscillatory momentum spectrum of the pairs created by the Sauter pulsed field at intermediate times, calculated using the two adiabatic bases. In these bases, the same oscillatory momentum spectra are observed but at different times. However, when we scale the time by the point marking the end of the transient stage of dynamical evolution for each case of central momentum, the respective momentum spectra overlap. Furthermore, we study the time evolution of the momentum spectrum in the multi-photon regime and find that the spectra show a multi-modal profile structure at finite times for both choices of basis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16321v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Deepak Sah, Manoranjan P. Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Quantum Neural Networks for Demand Forecasting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16331v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Forecasting demand for assets and services can be addressed in various markets, providing a competitive advantage when the predictive models used demonstrate high accuracy. However, the training of machine learning models incurs high computational costs, which may limit the training of prediction models based on available computational capacity. In this context, this paper presents an approach for training demand prediction models using quantum neural networks. For this purpose, a quantum neural network was used to forecast demand for vehicle financing. A classical recurrent neural network was used to compare the results, and they show a similar predictive capacity between the classical and quantum models, with the advantage of using a lower number of training parameters and also converging in fewer steps. Utilizing quantum computing techniques offers a promising solution to overcome the limitations of traditional machine learning approaches in training predictive models for complex market dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16331v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gleydson Fernandes de Jesus, Maria Helo\'isa Fraga da Silva, Otto Menegasso Pires, Lucas Cruz da Silva, Clebson dos Santos Cruz, Val\'eria Loureiro da Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase space distributions in information theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16338v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We use phase space distributions specifically, the Wigner distribution (WD) and Husimi distribution (HD) to investigate certain information-theoretic measures as descriptors for a given system. We extensively investigate and analyze Shannon, Wehrl and Renyi entropies, its divergences, mutual information and other correlation measures within the context of these phase space distributions. The analysis is illustrated with an anharmonic oscillator and is studied with respect to perturbation parameter ($\lambda$) and states ($n$). The entropies associated with the Wigner distribution are observed to be lower than those of the Husimi distribution, which aligns with the findings regarding the marginals. Moreover, the real components of the entropies associated with the Wigner distribution tend to approach the entropic uncertainty bound more closely compared to those of the corresponding Husimi distribution. Moreover, we quantify the precise amount of information lost when opting for the Husimi distribution over the Wigner distribution for characterizing the specified system. Since it is not always positive definite, the entropies cannot always be defined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16338v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vikash Kumar Ojha, Ramkumar Radhakrishnan, Siddharth Kumar Tiwari, Mariyah Ughradar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Convolutional Neural Network: A Hybrid Quantum-Classical Approach for Iris Dataset Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16344v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a hybrid quantum-classical machine learning model for classification tasks, integrating a 4-qubit quantum circuit with a classical neural network. The quantum circuit is designed to encode the features of the Iris dataset using angle embedding and entangling gates, thereby capturing complex feature relationships that are difficult for classical models alone. The model, which we term a Quantum Convolutional Neural Network (QCNN), was trained over 20 epochs, achieving a perfect 100% accuracy on the Iris dataset test set on 16 epoch. Our results demonstrate the potential of quantum-enhanced models in supervised learning tasks, particularly in efficiently encoding and processing data using quantum resources. We detail the quantum circuit design, parameterized gate selection, and the integration of the quantum layer with classical neural network components. This work contributes to the growing body of research on hybrid quantum-classical models and their applicability to real-world datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16344v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. M. Yousuf Iqbal Tomal, Abdullah Al Shafin, Afrida Afaf, Debojit Bhattacharjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semidefinite optimization of the quantum relative entropy of channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16362v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces a method for calculating the quantum relative entropy of channels, an essential quantity in quantum channel discrimination and resource theories of quantum channels. By building on recent developments in the optimization of relative entropy for quantum states [Kossmann and Schwonnek, arXiv:2404.17016], we introduce a discretized linearization of the integral representation for the relative entropy for states, enabling us to handle maximization tasks of the relative entropy of a channel over input states. Our approach here extends previous work on minimizing relative entropy to the more complicated domain of maximization. It also provides efficiently computable upper and lower bounds that sandwich the true value with any desired precision, leading to a practical method for computing the relative entropy of channels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16362v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gereon Ko{\ss}mann, Mark M. Wilde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to generate high-dimensional distributions with low-dimensional quantum Boltzmann machines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16363v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In recent years, researchers have been exploring ways to generalize Boltzmann machines (BMs) to quantum systems, leading to the development of variations such as fully-visible and restricted quantum Boltzmann machines (QBMs). Due to the non-commuting nature of their Hamiltonians, restricted QBMs face trainability issues, whereas fully-visible QBMs have emerged as a more tractable option, as recent results demonstrate their sample-efficient trainability. These results position fully-visible QBMs as a favorable choice, offering potential improvements over fully-visible BMs without suffering from the trainability issues associated with restricted QBMs. In this work, we show that low-dimensional, fully-visible QBMs can learn to generate distributions typically associated with higher-dimensional systems. We validate our findings through numerical experiments on both artificial datasets and real-world examples from the high energy physics problem of jet event generation. We find that non-commuting terms and Hamiltonian connectivity improve the learning capabilities of QBMs, providing flexible resources suitable for various hardware architectures. Furthermore, we provide strategies and future directions to maximize the learning capacity of fully-visible QBMs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16363v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cenk T\"uys\"uz, Maria Demidik, Luuk Coopmans, Enrico Rinaldi, Vincent Croft, Yacine Haddad, Matthias Rosenkranz, Karl Jansen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boosted Bell-state measurements for photonic quantum computation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16380v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fault-tolerant fusion-based photonic quantum computing (FBQC) greatly relies on entangling two-photon measurements, called fusions. These fusions can be realized using linear-optical projective Bell-state measurements (BSMs). These linear-optical BSMs are limited to a success probability of 50%, greatly reducing the performance of FBQC schemes. To improve the performance of FBQC architectures, a boosted BSM scheme taking advantage of ancillary entangled photon pairs and a 4x4 multiport interferometer has been proposed. This scheme allows the success probability to be increased up to 75%. In this work, we experimentally demonstrate this boosted BSM by using two Sagnac photon-pair sources and a fibre-based 4x4 multiport beam splitter. A boosted BSM success probability of $(69.3\pm0.3)\%$ has been achieved, exceeding the 50% limit. Furthermore, based on our BSMs, we calculate photon-loss thresholds for a fusion network using encoded six-ring resource states. We show that with this boosted BSM scheme an individual photon loss probability of 1.4% can be tolerated, while the non-boosted BSM leads to a photon-loss threshold of 0.45%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16380v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nico Hauser, Matthias J. Bayerbach, Simone E. D'Aurelio, Raphael Weber, Matteo Santandrea, Shreya P. Kumar, Ish Dhand, Stefanie Barz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Runtime Reduction in Linear Quantum Charge-Coupled Devices using the Parity Flow Formalism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16382v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using the Parity Flow formalism, we show that physical SWAP gates can be eliminated in linear hardware architectures, without increasing the total number of two-qubit operations. This has a significant impact on the execution time of quantum circuits in linear Quantum Charge-Coupled Devices (QCCDs), where SWAP gates are implemented by physically changing the position of the ions. Because SWAP gates are one of the most time-consuming operations in QCCDs, our scheme considerably reduces the runtime of the quantum Fourier transform and the quantum approximate optimization algorithm on all-to-all spin models, compared to circuits generated with standard compilers (TKET and Qiskit). While increasing the problem size (and therefore the number of qubits) typically demands longer runtimes, which are constrained by coherence time, our runtime reduction enables a significant increase in the number of qubits at a given coherence time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16382v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico Dom\'inguez, Michael Fellner, Berend Klaver, Stefan Rombouts, Christian Ertler, Wolfgang Lechner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring spin-noise correlation function via time reversal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16413v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a simple method of measuring the autocorrelation function of a spin noise based on multiplication and averaging two digitized signal traces, with one of them being a time-reversed copy of the other. This procedure allows one to obtain, with lower computational expenses, all the information usually derived in the Fourier transform spin-noise spectroscopy, retaining all the merits of the latter. We successfully applied this method to the measurements of spin noise in cesium vapors by using a digital oscilloscope in the capacity of the analog-to-digital converter. Specific opportunities of this experimental approach as applied to a more general problem of studying the nature of light-intensity noise are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16413v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. V. Dubinin, A. A. Fomin, G. G. Kozlov, M. Yu. Petrov, V. S. Zapasskii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Qudit Gate Decomposition Dependence for Lattice Gauge Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16414v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate the effect of decomposition basis on primitive qudit gates on superconducting radio-frequency cavity-based quantum computers with applications to lattice gauge theory. Three approaches are tested: SNAP &amp; Displacement gates, ECD &amp; single-qubit rotations $R(\theta,\phi)$, and optimal pulse control. For all three decompositions, implementing the necessary sequence of rotations concurrently rather then sequentially can reduce the primitive gate run time. The number of blocks required for the faster ECD &amp; $R_p(\theta)$ is found to scale $\mathcal{O}(d^2)$, while slower SNAP &amp; Displacement set scales at worst $\mathcal{O}(d)$. For qudits with $d&lt;10$, the resulting gate times for the decompositions is similar, but strongly-dependent on experimental design choices. Optimal control can outperforms both decompositions for small $d$ by a factor of 2-12 at the cost of higher classical resources. Lastly, we find that SNAP &amp; Displacement are slightly more robust to a simplified noise model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16414v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Do\~ga Murat K\"urk\c{c}\"uo\~glu, Henry Lamm, Andrea Maestri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How much secure randomness is in a quantum state?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16447v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: How much cryptographically-secure randomness can be extracted from a quantum state? This fundamental question probes the absolute limits of quantum random number generation (QRNG) and yet, despite the technological maturity of QRNGs, it remains unsolved. In this work we consider a general adversarial model that allows for an adversary who has quantum side-information about both the source and the measurement device. Using links between randomness extraction rates and sandwiched R\'enyi entropies, we provide compact, easy to compute, achievable rates of secure randomness extraction from quantum states. In turn, this provides a simple to evaluate benchmarking tool for the randomness generation rates of QRNG protocols.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16447v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kriss Gutierrez Anco, Tristan Nemoz, Peter Brown</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bosonic Mpemba effect with non-classical states of light</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16463v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Mpemba effect refers to the surprising observation where, under certain conditions, a far-from-equilibrium state can relax toward equilibrium faster than a state closer to equilibrium. A paradigmatic example is provided by the curious fact that hot water can sometimes freeze faster than cold water. The Mpemba effect has intrigued scientists since long time and has been predicted and observed in a variety of classical and quantum systems. Recently, the search for Mpemba-like effects of purely quantum nature has raised a major interest. Here we predict the emergence of Mpemba effect in the quantum optics context exploiting non-classical states of light. By analyzing the decay dynamics of photon fields in a leaky optical resonator or waveguide, it is demonstrated that the Mpemba effect emerges in the context of the quantum nature of light. Specifically, the relaxation dynamics is strongly influenced by the photon statistics of the initially trapped light field. The Mpemba effect is observed when comparing the decay dynamics of classical light fields (coherent states) with certain non-classical states, such as squeezed states and Schr\"odinger cat states</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16463v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Longhi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hidden quantum correlations in cavity-based quantum optics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16479v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In multimode optical systems, the spectral covariance matrix encodes all the information about quantum correlations between the quadratures of Gaussian states. Recent research has revealed that, in scenarios that are more common than previously thought, part of these correlations remain inaccessible to standard homodyne detection scheme. Formally, this effect can be attributed to a non-real spectral covariance matrix. In this work, we provide a systematic framework and explicit criteria for identifying experimental configurations leading to such a behavior. This study will facilitate the proper exploitation and optimal engineering of CV quantum resources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16479v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bakhao Dioum, Virginia D'Auria, Giuseppe Patera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defining coherent states: why must they be eigenstates of the annihilation operator?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16483</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16483v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This is a pedagogical paper where we present a physically motivated approach to introduce the coherent states of a harmonic oscillator from which it is simple to rigorously derive their mathematical definition. We do this in two different ways that turn out to be equivalent but emphasize two related but different aspects of classicality. First, we analyze which are the quantum states that are the closest one can get to a point in phase space and demonstrate the validity of the following theorem: (i) The product of the uncertainty in position and that of momentum saturates the bound imposed by Heisenberg uncertainty relations for all times if and only if the state is an eigenstate of the annihilation operator. Second, we analyze the way in which the difference between the expectation value of the energy and the energy associated with the expectation values of position and momentum depends on the state, and show the validity of the following theorem (ii) the difference between the expectation value of the energy and the energy associated with the expectation values is minimal if and only if the state is an eigenstate of the annihilation operator. We also show that the reason why coherent states are chosen as the most classical ones by the decoherence process induced by coupling the particle to an environment in the standard Quantum Brownian motion model, is precisely due to the validity of the two above theorems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16483v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan Pablo Paz, Augusto J. Roncaglia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ER = EPR is an operational theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16496v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that in the operational setting of a two-agent, local operations, classical communication (LOCC) protocol, Alice and Bob cannot operationally distinguish monogamous entanglement from a topological identification of points in their respective local spacetimes, i.e. that ER = EPR can be recovered as an operational theorem. Our construction immediately implies that in this operational setting, the local topology of spacetime is observer-relative. It also provides a simple demonstration of the non-traversability of ER bridges. As our construction does not depend on an embedding geometry, it generalizes previous geometric approaches to ER = EPR.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16496v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chris Fields, James F. Glazebrook, Antonino Marciano, Emanuele Zappala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of string breaking on a (2 + 1)D Rydberg quantum simulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16558v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Lattice gauge theories (LGTs) describe a broad range of phenomena in condensed matter and particle physics. A prominent example is confinement, responsible for bounding quarks inside hadrons such as protons or neutrons. When quark-antiquark pairs are separated, the energy stored in the string of gluon fields connecting them grows linearly with their distance, until there is enough energy to create new pairs from the vacuum and break the string. While such phenomena are ubiquitous in LGTs, simulating the resulting dynamics is a challenging task. Here, we report the observation of string breaking in synthetic quantum matter using a programmable quantum simulator based on neutral atom arrays. We show that a (2+1)D LGT with dynamical matter can be efficiently implemented when the atoms are placed on a Kagome geometry, with a local U(1) symmetry emerging from the Rydberg blockade, while long-range Rydberg interactions naturally give rise to a linear confining potential for a pair of charges, allowing us to tune both their masses as well as the string tension. We experimentally map out the corresponding phase diagram by adiabatically preparing the ground state of the atom array in the presence of defects, and observe substructure of the confined phase, distinguishing regions dominated by fluctuating strings or by broken string configurations. Finally, by harnessing local control over the atomic detuning, we quench string states and observe string breaking dynamics exhibiting a many-body resonance phenomenon. Our work paves a way to explore phenomena in high-energy physics using programmable quantum simulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16558v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Gonzalez-Cuadra, Majd Hamdan, Torsten V. Zache, Boris Braverman, Milan Kornjaca, Alexander Lukin, Sergio H. Cantu, Fangli Liu, Sheng-Tao Wang, Alexander Keesling, Mikhail D. Lukin, Peter Zoller, Alexei Bylinskii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental simulation of daemonic work extraction in open quantum batteries on a digital quantum computer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16567v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The possibility of extracting more work from a physical system thanks to the information obtained from measurements has been a topic of fundamental interest in the context of thermodynamics since the formulation of the Maxwell's demon thought experiment. We here consider this problem from the perspective of an open quantum battery interacting with an environment that can be continuously measured. By modeling it via a continuously monitored collisional model, we show how to implement the corresponding dynamics as a quantum circuit, including the final conditional feedback unitary evolution that allows to enhance the amount of work extracted. By exploiting the flexibility of IBM quantum computers and by properly modelling the corresponding quantum circuit, we experimentally simulate the work extraction protocol showing how the obtained experimental values of the daemonic extracted work are close to their theoretical upper bound quantified by the so-called daemonic ergotropy. We also demonstrate how by properly modelling the noise affecting the quantum circuit, one can improve the work extraction protocol by optimizing the corresponding extraction unitary feedback operation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16567v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seyed Navid Elyasi, Matteo A. C. Rossi, Marco G. Genoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>(Quantum) Indifferentiability and Pre-Computation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16595</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16595v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Indifferentiability is a popular cryptographic paradigm for analyzing the security of ideal objects -- both in a classical as well as in a quantum world. It is typically stated in the form of a composable and simulation-based definition, and captures what it means for a construction (e.g., a cryptographic hash function) to be ``as good as'' an ideal object (e.g., a random oracle). Despite its strength, indifferentiability is not known to offer security against pre-processing attacks in which the adversary gains access to (classical or quantum) advice that is relevant to the particular construction. In this work, we show that indifferentiability is (generically) insufficient for capturing pre-computation. To accommodate this shortcoming, we propose a strengthening of indifferentiability which is not only composable but also takes arbitrary pre-computation into account. As an application, we show that the one-round sponge is indifferentiable (with pre-computation) from a random oracle. This yields the first (and tight) classical/quantum space-time trade-off for one-round sponge inversion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16595v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joseph Carolan, Alexander Poremba, Mark Zhandry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear semiclassical spectroscopy of ultrafast molecular polariton dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16630v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a theoretical framework that allows for the systematic and efficient description of the ultrafast nonlinear response of molecular polaritons, i.e., hybrid light-matter states, in the collective regime of large numbers of molecules $\mathcal N$ coupled to the cavity photon mode. Our approach is based on a semiclassical, mean-field evolution of the molecular Hamiltonian and the cavity field, which is complemented by a perturbative expansion of both light and matter counterparts in the input fields entering the cavity. In addition, expansion in terms of the pulse phases enables us to disentangle different excitation pathways in Liouville space, thereby distinguishing contributions to the nonlinear response. The formalism extends traditional free-space nonlinear spectroscopy by incorporating the feedback of matter onto the light field via the induced polarization. We demonstrate the utility of the framework by applying it to the calculation of pump-probe polariton spectra and show how, by storing the pulses, the cavity facilitates additional excitation pathways which are not possible in free space. Our method, which does not scale with $\mathcal N$, is broadly applicable and can be extended to a wide range of current experiments investigating the dynamical nonlinear response of hybrid light-matter states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16630v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Reitz, Arghadip Koner, Joel Yuen-Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounding the Sample Fluctuation for Pure States Certification with Local Random Measurement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16635v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Remarkable breakthroughs in quantum science and technology are demanding for more efficient methods in analyzing quantum many-body states. A significant challenge in this field is to verify whether a quantum state prepared by quantum devices in the lab accurately matches the desired target pure state. Recent advancements in randomized measurement techniques have provided fresh insights in this area. Specifically, protocols such as classical shadow tomography and shadow overlap have been proposed. Building on these developments, we investigate the fundamental properties of schemes that certify pure quantum states through random local Haar measurements. We derive bounds for sample fluctuations that are applicable regardless of the specific estimator construction. These bounds depend on the operator size distribution of either the observable used to estimate fidelity or the valid variation of the reduced density matrix for arbitrary observables. Our results unveil the intrinsic interplay between operator complexity and the efficiency of quantum algorithms, serving as an obstacle to local certification of pure states with long-range entanglement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16635v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Langxuan Chen, Pengfei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>p-SWAP: A Generic Cost-Effective Quantum Boolean-Phase SWAP Gate Using Two CNOT Gates and the Bloch Sphere Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16641v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A generic Boolean-phase SWAP gate is introduced for quantum cost-effectiveness. This gate is termed the "p-SWAP", and p is a customizable phase difference between the swapped qubits, where 0 &lt;= p &lt;= ${\pm \pi}$ radians. The cost-effectiveness of p-SWAP gate comes from a lower quantum cost for its final transpiled quantum circuit into a real quantum computer. The p-SWAP gate only utilizes two Feynman (CNOT) gates, as compared to the standard SWAP gate constructed from three CNOT gates. The quantum circuit of p-SWAP gate is geometrically designed using our Bloch sphere approach. The generality of p-SWAP gate is proposed for Phase oracles requiring a desirable p for a combination set of swapped qubits, as well as for Boolean oracles requiring a cost-effective SWAP gate when p is ignored. In this paper, after transpilation (synthesization) into a real quantum computer, it was concluded that the transpiled quantum circuit of p-SWAP gate has a lower quantum cost than that of the standard SWAP gate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16641v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Al-Bayaty, Marek Perkowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoherence of Quantum Emitters in hexagonal Boron Nitride</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16681v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Coherent quantum emitters are a central resource for advanced quantum technologies. Hexagonal boron nitride (hBN) hosts a range of quantum emitters that can be engineered using techniques such as high-temperature annealing, optical doping, and irradiation with electrons or ions. Here, we demonstrate that such processes can degrade the coherence, and hence the functionality, of quantum emitters in hBN. Specifically, we show that hBN annealing and doping methods that are used routinely in hBN nanofabrication protocols give rise to decoherence of B-center quantum emitters. The decoherence is characterized in detail, and attributed to defects that act as charge traps which fluctuate electrostatically during SPE excitation and induce spectral diffusion. The decoherence is minimal when the emitters are engineered by electron beam irradiation of as-grown, pristine flakes of hBN, where B-center linewidths approach the lifetime limit needed for quantum applications involving interference and entanglement. Our work highlights the critical importance of crystal lattice quality to achieving coherent quantum emitters in hBN, despite the common perception that the hBN lattice and hBN SPEs are highly-stable and resilient against chemical and thermal degradation. It underscores the need for nanofabrication techniques that are minimally invasive and avoid crystal damage when engineering hBN SPEs and devices for quantum-coherent technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16681v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jake Horder, Dominic Scognamiglio, Nathan Coste, Angus Gale, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Mehran Kianinia, Milos Toth, Igor Aharonovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning shallow quantum circuits with many-qubit gates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16693v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the first computationally-efficient algorithm for average-case learning of shallow quantum circuits with many-qubit gates. Specifically, we provide a quasi-polynomial time and sample complexity algorithm for learning unknown QAC$^0$ circuits -- constant-depth circuits with arbitrary single-qubit gates and polynomially many $CZ$ gates of unbounded width -- up to inverse-polynomially small error. Furthermore, we show that the learned unitary can be efficiently synthesized in poly-logarithmic depth. This work expands the family of efficiently learnable quantum circuits, notably since in finite-dimensional circuit geometries, QAC$^0$ circuits require polynomial depth to implement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16693v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francisca Vasconcelos, Hsin-Yuan Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resolvability of classical-quantum channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16704</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16704v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Channel resolvability concerns the minimum resolution for approximating the channel output. We study the resolvability of classical-quantum channels in two settings, for the channel output generated from the worst input, and form the fixed independent and identically distributed (i.i.d.) input. The direct part of the worst-input setting is derived from sequential hypothesis testing as it involves of non-i.i.d.~inputs. The strong converse of the worst-input setting is obtained via the connection to identification codes. For the fixed-input setting, while the direct part follows from the known quantum soft covering result, we exploit the recent alternative quantum Sanov theorem to solve the strong converse.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16704v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masahito Hayashi, Hao-Chung Cheng, Li Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring error rates of mid-circuit measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16706</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16706v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High-fidelity mid-circuit measurements, which read out the state of specific qubits in a multiqubit processor without destroying them or disrupting their neighbors, are a critical component for useful quantum computing. They enable fault-tolerant quantum error correction, dynamic circuits, and other paths to solving classically intractable problems. But there are almost no methods to assess their performance comprehensively. We address this gap by introducing the first randomized benchmarking protocol that measures the rate at which mid-circuit measurements induce errors in many-qubit circuits. Using this protocol, we detect and eliminate previously undetected measurement-induced crosstalk in a 20-qubit trapped-ion quantum computer. Then, we use the same protocol to measure the rate of measurement-induced crosstalk error on a 27-qubit IBM Q processor, and quantify how much of that error is eliminated by dynamical decoupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16706v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Hothem, Jordan Hines, Charles Baldwin, Dan Gresh, Robin Blume-Kohout, Timothy Proctor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamics of a Quantum Subsystem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16721</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16721v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Prior attempts to formulate the Laws of Thermodynamics for a small region within a larger quantum system have led to inconsistencies and unexplained infinities. The entropy and external work, in particular, require careful analysis when partitioning over the various subsystems. In this work, we analyze the thermodynamics of a quantum subsystem driven quasi-statically by external forces. We show that the thermodynamic functions of a quantum subsystem can be defined dynamically in terms of its local spectrum. The external work is found to be intrinsically nonlocal due to the nonlocal character of the underlying quantum states. This nonlocal quantum work can be harnessed in a "quantum lever" to provide up to 100% amplification of the local work done on a quantum subsystem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16721v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Parth Kumar, Charles A. Stafford</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum metrology timing limits of biphoton frequency comb</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16841</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16841v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Biphoton frequency comb (BFC), which encompasses multiple discrete frequency modes and represents high-dimensional frequency entanglement, is crucial in quantum information processing due to its high information capacity and error resilience. It also holds significant potential for enhancing timing precision in quantum metrology. Here, we examine quantum metrology timing limits using the BFC as a probe state and derive a quantum Cram\'er-Rao bound that scales quadratically with the number of frequency modes. Under ideal conditions (zero loss and perfect visibility), this bound can be saturated by both spectrally non-resolved Hong-Ou-Mandel (HOM) interferometry at zero delay and spectrally resolved HOM interferometry at arbitrary delays. In particular, under imperfect experimental conditions, Fisher information rapidly increases up to its maximum as the mode number increases for a fixed time delay close to zero, indicating that increasing the mode number is an optimal strategy for improving the timing precision in practice. Furthermore, compared with spectrally non-resolved measurement, spectrally resolved measurement is a better strategy due to its higher Fisher information, shorter measurement times, and ambiguity-free dynamic range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16841v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baihong Li, Qi-qi Li, Boxin Yuan, Ruifang Dong, Shougang Zhang, Rui-Bo Jin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spontaneously induced emitter-radiation entanglement due to confinement to photonic band gap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16844v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The study of spontaneously induced nonclassicality as a result of the interaction of an ensemble of two-level emitters embedded onto crystal structure embodying photonic band gap (PBG) is presented. The method of coherent-state propagator is applied upon expressing collective atomic operators in terms of boson operators in view of Schwinger's representation. The autocorrelation of photon number of the radiation alone is shown to display super-Poissonian statistics and chaotic photon character. However, the state of the coupled system is found to exhibit entanglement and nonclassical intensity correlation attributed to the confinement, where intensity of the emitted radiation and degree of entanglement are enhanced near the edge. The prospect of embedding emitters onto PBG can hence be taken as a reliable testing ground for examining fundamentals of emitter-radiation interaction and implementing quantum information processing task that requires mapping of stationary memory with flying message.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16844v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sintayehu Tesfa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TE-PAI: Exact Time Evolution by Sampling Random Circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16850v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Simulating time evolution under quantum Hamiltonians is one of the most natural applications of quantum computers. We introduce TE-PAI, which simulates time evolution exactly by sampling random quantum circuits for the purpose of estimating observable expectation values at the cost of an increased circuit repetition. The approach builds on the Probabilistic Angle Interpolation (PAI) technique and we prove that it simulates time evolution without discretisation or algorithmic error while achieving optimally shallow circuit depths that saturate the Lieb-Robinson bound. Another significant advantage of TE-PAI is that it only requires executing random circuits that consist of Pauli rotation gates of only two kinds of rotation angles $\pm\Delta$ and $\pi$, along with measurements. While TE-PAI is highly beneficial for NISQ devices, we additionally develop an optimised early fault-tolerant implementation using catalyst circuits and repeat-until-success teleportation, concluding that the approach requires orders of magnitude fewer T-states than conventional techniques, such as Trotterization -- we estimate $3 \times 10^{5}$ T states are sufficient for the fault-tolerant simulation of a $100$-qubit Heisenberg spin Hamiltonian. Furthermore, TE-PAI allows for a highly configurable trade-off between circuit depth and measurement overhead by adjusting the rotation angle $\Delta$ arbitrarily. We expect that the approach will be a major enabler in the late NISQ and early fault-tolerant periods as it can compensate circuit-depth and qubit-number limitations through an increased circuit repetition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16850v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chusei Kiumi, B\'alint Koczor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Typical Quantum States of the Universe are Observationally Indistinguishable</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16860</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16860v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper is about the epistemology of quantum theory. We establish a new result about a limitation to knowledge of its central object -- the quantum state of the universe. We show that, if the universal quantum state can be assumed to be a typical unit vector from a high-dimensional subspace of Hilbert space (such as the subspace defined by a low-entropy macro-state as prescribed by the Past Hypothesis), then no observation can determine (or even just narrow down significantly) which vector it is. Typical state vectors, in other words, are observationally indistinguishable from each other. Our argument is based on a typicality theorem from quantum statistical mechanics. We also discuss how theoretical considerations that go beyond the empirical evidence might bear on this fact and on our knowledge of the universal quantum state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16860v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eddy Keming Chen, Roderich Tumulka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical formulation of low-frequency scattering in two and three dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16906v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The transfer matrix of scattering theory in one dimension can be expressed in terms of the time-evolution operator for an effective non-unitary quantum system. In particular, it admits a Dyson series expansion which turns out to facilitate the construction of the low-frequency series expansion of the scattering data. In two and three dimensions, there is a similar formulation of stationary scattering where the scattering properties of the scatterer are extracted from the evolution operator for a corresponding effective quantum system. We explore the utility of this approach to scattering theory in the study of the scattering of low-frequency time-harmonic scalar waves, $e^{-i\omega t}\psi(\mathbf{r})$, with $\psi(\mathbf{r})$ satisfying the Helmholtz equation, $[\nabla^2+k^2\hat\varepsilon(\mathbf{r};k)]\psi(\mathbf{r})=0$, $\omega$ and $k$ being respectively the angular frequency and wavenumber of the incident wave, and $\hat\varepsilon(\mathbf{r};k)$ denoting the relative permittivity of the carrier medium which in general takes complex values. We obtain explicit formulas for low-frequency scattering amplitude, examine their effectiveness in the study of a class of exactly solvable scattering problems, and outline their application in devising a low-frequency cloaking scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16906v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Farhang Loran, Ali Mostafazadeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong symmetries in collision models and physical dilations of covariant quantum maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16907v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum maps are fundamental to quantum information theory and open quantum systems. Covariant or weakly symmetric quantum maps, in particular, play a key role in defining quantum evolutions that respect thermodynamics, establish free operations in resource theories, and are consistent with transformations of quantum reference frames. To implement quantum maps in the lab, one typically engineers a physical dilation, which corresponds to a unitary evolution entangling the system with an environment. This work systematically explores how weak symmetries of quantum maps manifest in their dilations. We demonstrate that for various classes of physical dilations, including Hamiltonian-driven dilations and short-time collision models that simulate Markovian open quantum dynamics, weak symmetries always lead to strong symmetries in the dilated evolution, resulting in conserved quantities in the system-environment space. We also characterize the subspace where these symmetries arise using Krylov subspaces. Moreover, we show that some different types of physical dilations have no constraints on the dilated evolution, requiring no strong symmetry. Finally, we complement our findings with a variety of illustrative and pedagogical examples. Our results provide essential guidelines for constructing physical dilations of quantum maps, offering a comprehensive understanding of how symmetries shape their implementations in a laboratory or on a quantum computer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16907v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Cattaneo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum many-body scars as remnants of stable many-body periodic orbits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16916v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum many-body scars (QMBS) represent a weak ergodicity-breaking phenomenon that defies the common scenario of thermalization in closed quantum systems. They are often regarded as a many-body analog of quantum scars (QS) -- a single-particle phenomenon in quantum chaos -- due to their superficial similarities. However, unlike QS, a clear connection between QMBS and classical chaos has remained elusive. It has nevertheless been speculated that in an appropriate semiclassical limit, QMBS should have a correspondence to weakly unstable periodic orbits. In this paper, I present a counterexample to this conjecture by studying a bosonic model with a large number of flavors. The dynamics of out-of-time-ordered correlators (OTOCs) suggest that QMBS do not display chaotic behavior in the semiclassical limit. In contrast, chaotic dynamics are expected for initial states not associated with QMBS. Interestingly, the anomalous OTOC dynamics persist even under weak perturbations that eliminate the scarred eigenstates, suggesting a certain robustness in the phenomenon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16916v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keita Omiya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrating Window-Based Correlated Decoding with Constant-Time Logical Gates for Large-Scale Quantum Computation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16963v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Large-scale quantum computation requires to be performed in the fault-tolerant manner. One crucial issue of fault-tolerant quantum computing (FTQC) is reducing the overhead of implementing logical gates. Recently proposed correlated decoding and ``algorithmic fault tolerance" achieve fast logical gates that enables universal quantum computation. However, for circuits involving mid-circuit measurements and feedback, this approach is incompatible with window-based decoding, which is a natural requirement for handling large-scale circuits. In this letter, we propose an alternative architecture that employs delayed fixup circuits, integrating window-based correlated decoding with fast transversal gates. This design significantly reduce both the frequency and duration of correlated decoding, while maintaining support for constant-time logical gates and universality across a broad class of quantum codes. More importantly, by spatial parallelism of windows, this architecture well adapts to time-optimal FTQC, making it particularly useful for large-scale computation. Using Shor's algorithm as an example, we explore the application of our architecture and reveals the promising potential of using fast transversal gates to perform large-scale quantum computing tasks with acceptable overhead on physical systems like ion traps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16963v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaxuan Zhang, Zhao-Yun Chen, Jia-Ning Li, Tian-Hao Wei, Huan-Yu Liu, Xi-Ning Zhuang, Qing-Song Li, Yu-Chun Wu, Guo-Ping Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Downtime Required for Bitcoin Quantum-Safety</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16965v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum devices capable of breaking the public-key cryptosystems that Bitcoin relies on to secure its transactions are expected with reasonable probability within a decade. Quantum attacks would put at risk the entire Bitcoin network, which has an estimated value of around 500 billion USD. To prevent this threat, a proactive approach is critical. The only known way to prevent any such attack is to upgrade the currently used public-key cryptosystems, namely ECDSA, with so-called post-quantum cryptosystems which have no known vulnerabilities to quantum attacks. In this paper, we analyse the technical cost of such an upgrade. We calculate a non-tight lower bound on the cumulative downtime required for the above transition to be 1827.96 hours, or 76.16 days. We also demonstrate that the transition needs to be fully completed before the availability of ECDSA-256 breaking quantum devices, in order to ensure Bitcoin's ongoing security. The conclusion is that the Bitcoin upgrade to quantum-safe protocols needs to be started as soon as possible in order to guarantee its ongoing operations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16965v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jamie J. Pont, Joseph J. Kearney, Jack Moyler, Carlos A. Perez-Delgado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Optical HMW Geometric Phase and the Abraham Minkowski Controversy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17010v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The question of the correct formulation for the momentum of light in a dielectric medium is typically referred to as the ``Abraham-Minkowski controversy". Experiments conducted to elucidate the issue have primarily focused on measuring forces and momentum transfers. In this work, we propose an interferometric approach using matter waves to measure the light-induced version of the He-McKellar-Wilkens (optical HMW) phase for a neutral atomic dipole in dynamical electromagnetic fields. Beginning from the action principle, we show that this geometric phase is directly related via the Euler-Lagrange equations of motion to the Abraham force lying at the heart of the controversy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17010v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Hainge, N. Miladinovic, D. H. J. O'Dell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Security Enhancement of Quantum Communication in Space-Air-Ground Integrated Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17048</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17048v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates a transmission scheme for enhancing quantum communication security, aimed at improving the security of space-air-ground integrated networks (SAGIN). Quantum teleportation achieves the transmission of quantum states through quantum channels. In simple terms, an unknown quantum state at one location can be reconstructed on a particle at another location. By combining classical Turbo coding with quantum Shor error-correcting codes, we propose a practical solution that ensures secure information transmission even in the presence of errors in both classical and quantum channels. To provide absolute security under SAGIN, we add a quantum secure direct communication (QSDC) protocol to the current system. Specifically, by accounting for the practical scenario of eavesdropping in quantum channels, the QSDC protocol utilizes virtual entangled pairs to detect the presence of eavesdroppers. Consequently, the overall scheme guarantees both the reliability and absolute security of communication.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17048v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yixiao Zhang, Wei Liang, Lixin Li, Wensheng Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engineering Fault-tolerant Bosonic Codes with Quantum Lattice Gates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17069v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bosonic codes enable the protection and correction of quantum information in a single continuous variable system. In this paper, we propose a systematic framework to engineer bosonic code states for fault-tolerant quantum computing based on Floquet Hamiltonian engineering. We construct the target Hamiltonian directly from the target state and engineer the codes states with an adiabatic ramp protocol. We introduce a new universal set of quantum lattice gate composed of only one type of gate element, and develop a systematic decomposition of complex code state preparation and transformation processes into sequences of quantum lattice gates. We apply our method to three basic code states engineering processes, including single code state preparation, code space embedding and transformation. We also discuss the automatic quantum error correction against photon loss with four-legged cat codes. Our proposal is particularly well-suited for superconducting circuit architectures with Josephson junctions, where the full nonlinearity of Josephson junction potential is harnessed as a quantum resource.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17069v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lingzhen Guo, Tangyou Huang, Lei Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Achievable Entanglement-Assisted Communication Rate using Phase-Modulated Two-Mode Squeezed Vacuum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17181v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We derive a closed-form achievable rate for entanglement-assisted classical communication over a lossy thermal-noise bosonic channel, where the entanglement is in the form of a Two-Mode Squeezed Vacuum (TMSV) modulation restricted to Phase Shift Keying (PSK). The achievable rate is non-asymptotic in terms of the mean signal photon number, mean noise photon number, and transmissivity defining the communication channel, which provides insights into the interplay of these physical parameters and bridges recent experimental demonstrations of entanglement-assisted communications with the coding theorems used in information-theoretic proofs. The key challenge we address is deriving an analytical bound for the von Neumann entropy of the non-Gaussian mixed state resulting from the phase modulation of one arm of a TMSV. Our approach hinges on two key observations: 1) as the size of the PSK modulation increases, the resulting mixed state converges in trace distance to a diagonal state in the Fock basis; 2) the Fock-basis representation of the diagonal state involves hypergeometric functions that can be appropriately bounded to offer a tractable lower bound for the Holevo information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17181v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shang-Jen Su, Shi-Yuan Wang, Matthieu R. Bloch, Zheshen Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Technical Report: Toward Applying Quantum Computing to Network Verification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17184v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Network verification (NWV), broadly defined as the verification of properties of distributed protocols used in network systems, cannot be efficiently solved on classical hardware via brute force. Prior work has developed a variety of methods that scale by observing a structure in the search space and then evaluating classes within the search space instead of individual instances. However, even these classification mechanisms have their limitations. In this paper, we consider a radically different approach: applying quantum computing to more efficiently solve NWV problems. We provide an overview of how to map variants of NWV problems into unstructured search problems that can be solved via quantum computing with quadratic speedup, making the approach feasible in theory to problems that are double in size (of the input). Emerging quantum systems cannot yet tackle problems of practical interest, but rapid advances in hardware and algorithm development make now a great time to start thinking about their application. With this in mind, we explore the limits of scale of the problem for which quantum computing can solve NWV problems as unstructured search.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17184v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3696348.3696891</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Kahlil Dozier, Justin Beltran, Kylie Berg, Hugo Matousek, Loqman Salamatian, Ethan Katz-Bassett, Dan Rubenstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random Real Valued and Complex Valued States Cannot be Efficiently Distinguished</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17213</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17213v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this short note we show that the ensemble $\{O \vert 0\rangle \langle 0 \vert O^\top \ \vert \ O \in \mathbb{O(d)}\}$, where $O$ is drawn from the Haar measure on $\mathbb{O}(d)$ cannot be distinguished from $t$ copies of a Haar random state unless $t = \Omega(\sqrt{d})$. Our proof has the benefit of exactly computing the trace distance, which scales as $\Theta(t^2/d)$ for $t = O(\sqrt{d})$, between the moments as well as being surprisingly short. Lastly, we show that twirling certain states with orthogonal matrices yields exact $t=3$ designs, yet the same cannot be true for $t&gt;3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17213v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis Schatzki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semiclassical origin of suppressed quantum chaos in Rydberg chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17223v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The surprisingly long-lasting oscillations observed in the dynamics of highly excited states of chains of Rydberg atoms defy the expectation that interacting systems should thermalize fast. The phenomenon is reminiscent of wavepackets in quantum billiards that trace classical periodic orbits. While analogs of the associated scarred eigenfunctions have been found for Rydberg chains, an underlying classical limit hosting periodic orbits has remained elusive. Here we generalize the Rydberg (pseudospin $S=1/2$) system to a chain of arbitrary spin $S$. Its classical limit features unexpectedly stable periodic orbits that are essential to understand the emergence of robust, parametrically suppressed quantum chaoticity, with semi-classical coherence times diverging as $\sqrt{S}$. The classical limit successfully explains several empirical features of the quantum limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17223v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Markus M\"uller, Ruslan Mushkaev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving the Independent Domination Problem by Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17227</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17227v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the wake of quantum computing advancements and quantum algorithmic progress, quantum algorithms are increasingly being employed to address a myriad of combinatorial optimization problems. Among these, the Independent Domination Problem (IDP), a derivative of the Domination Problem, has practical implications in various real-world scenarios. Despite this, existing classical algorithms for IDP are plagued by high computational complexity, and quantum algorithms have yet to tackle this challenge. This paper introduces a Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA)-based approach to address the IDP. Utilizing IBM's qasm_simulator, we have demonstrated the efficacy of QAOA in solving IDP under specific parameter settings, with a computational complexity that surpasses that of classical methods. Our findings offer a novel avenue for the resolution of IDP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17227v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoqian Pan, Changhong Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Floquetifying stabiliser codes with distance-preserving rewrites</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17240</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17240v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ZX calculus is a graphical language for representing and rewriting quantum circuits. While its graphical rewrite rules preserve semantics, they may not preserve other features. For example, applying rewrites to a circuit that implements an error-correcting code can change its distance. Here, we define the notion of distance-preserving rewrites that enables the transformation of error-correcting codes without changing their distance. Using these rewrites, we propose an algorithm that transforms a high-weight Pauli measurement into an equivalent quantum circuit with only single- and two-qubit operations. Since we only use distance-preserving rewrites, we guarantee that errors in the low-weight implementation do not propagate to create multiple data errors. Going further, we generalise the Floquetification procedure of [arXiv:2308.15489] to arbitrary stabiliser codes. Given a stabiliser code, we synthesise a new quantum error-correcting code which encodes the same number of qubits with at least the same distance. The number of additional qubits this method requires is linearly dependent on the weight or the largest Pauli measurement. This creates a tradeoff between easily implementable low-weight Pauli measurements at the cost of additional physical qubits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17240v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Rodatz, Boldizs\'ar Po\'or, Aleks Kissinger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WKB Methods for Finite Difference Schrodinger Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14628v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this thesis, we develop WKB techniques for the finite difference Schrodinger equation, following the construction of the WKB approach for the standard differential Schrodinger equation. In particular, we will develop an all-order WKB algorithm to get arbitrary hbar-corrections and construct a general quantum momentum, underlining the various properties of its coefficients and the quantities that will be used when constructing the quantization condition. In doing so, we discover the existence of additional periodic factors that need to be considered in order to obtain the most general solution to the problem at hand. We will then proceed to study the simplest non trivial example, the linear potential case and the Bessel functions, that provide a solution to the linear problem.
  After studying the resurgence properties of the Bessel functions from an analytical and numerical point of view, we will then proceed to use those results in order to build general connection formulae, allowing us to connect the local solutions defined on two sides of a turning point into a smooth solution on the whole real line. With those connection formulae, we will analyse a selection of problems, constructing the discrete spectrum of various finite difference Schrodinger problems and comparing our results with existing literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14628v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Salvatore Baldino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamic functions of the Fermi gas at arbitrary temperatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16332v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Thermodynamic functions of the ideal Fermi gas at arbitrary temperatures are calculated using the standard Fermi-Stoner functions. The properties of the Fermi-Stoner functions are analyzed. The limiting cases of low-temperature and classical limits with taking into account quantum corrections and the special case of zero chemical potential are considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16332v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu. M. Poluektov, A. A. Soroka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum inspired factorization up to 100-bit RSA number in polynomial time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16355v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Classical public-key cryptography standards rely on the Rivest-Shamir-Adleman (RSA) encryption protocol. The security of this protocol is based on the exponential computational complexity of the most efficient classical algorithms for factoring large semiprime numbers into their two prime components. Here, we attack RSA factorization building on Schnorr's mathematical framework where factorization translates into a combinatorial optimization problem. We solve the optimization task via tensor network methods, a quantum-inspired classical numerical technique. This tensor network Schnorr's sieving algorithm displays numerical evidence of a polynomial scaling of the resources with the bit-length of the semiprime. We factorize RSA numbers up to 100 bits encoding the optimization problem in quantum systems with up to 256 qubits. Only the high-order polynomial scaling of the required resources limits the factorization of larger numbers. Although these results do not currently undermine the security of the present communication infrastructure, they strongly highlight the urgency of implementing post-quantum cryptography or quantum key distribution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16355v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Tesoro, Ilaria Siloi, Daniel Jaschke, Giuseppe Magnifico, Simone Montangero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Rotating-Wave Comagnetometer Detector for Particle Physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16360v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Many extensions of the Standard Model propose the existence of new particles or forces, aiming to answer mysteries such as the identity of the elusive dark matter. Atomic-based detectors are at the forefront of technologies designed to search for these particles or forces through their couplings to fermions, enabling the testing of well-motivated models, such as axion-like particles, which could form dark matter. These detectors also probe new long-range interactions between the detectors and spin-polarized objects, as well as interactions mediated by light particles that break CP symmetry, introducing a coupling between the detector and an unpolarized object. However, the sensitivity of these detectors is often constrained by magnetic noise, limiting their effectiveness to a narrow region of parameter space. We propose and develop a technique, which we name the Rotating Wave comagnetometer (RoW comag), that can suppress magnetic noise at tunable frequencies while maintaining high sensitivity to target signals, significantly expanding the potential reach of these detectors. We analyze its operation for testing various extensions to the Standard Model and show how it could improve current sensitivities by several orders of magnitude. This work paves the way for a new class of tabletop experiments aimed at searching for new physics, including the exploration of well-motivated axion-like particle dark matter models at higher masses than previously attainable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16360v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Itay M. Bloch, Or Katz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal time evolution of string order parameter in quantum critical systems with boundary invertible or non-invertible symmetry breaking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16402v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The global symmetry, either invertible or non-invertible, has been extensively studied in two dimensional conformal field theories in recent years. When the theory is defined on a manifold with open boundaries, however, many interesting conformal boundary conditions will fully or partially break such global symmetry. In this work, we study the effect of symmetry-breaking boundaries or interfaces when the system is out of equilibrium. We show that the boundary or interface symmetry-breaking can be detected by the time evolution of string order parameters, which are constructed from the symmetry operators that implement the symmetry transformations. While the string order parameters are independent of time if the symmetry is preserved over the whole system, they evolve in time in a universal way if the boundary or interface breaks the symmetry. More explicitly, in the presence of boundary or interface symmetry-breaking, the string order parameters decay exponentially in time after a global quantum quench, and decay as a power-law in time after a local quantum quench. We also generalize our study to the case when the string order parameters are defined in a subsystem, which are related to the full counting statistics. It is found there are also universal features in the time evolution of string order parameters in this case. We verify our field theory results by studying the time evolution of these two different types of string order parameters in lattice models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16402v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruhanshi Barad, Qicheng Tang, Wei Zhu, Xueda Wen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Bisognano-Wichmann entanglement Hamiltonian of nonrelativistic fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16433</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16433v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the ground-state entanglement Hamiltonian of free nonrelativistic fermions for semi-infinite domains in one dimension. This is encoded in the two-point correlations projected onto the subsystem, an operator that commutes with the linear deformation of the physical Hamiltonian. The corresponding eigenfunctions are shown to possess the exact same structure both in the continuum as well as on the lattice. Namely, they are superpositions of the occupied single-particle modes of the total Hamiltonian, weighted by the inverse of their energy as measured from the Fermi level, and multiplied by an extra phase proportional to the integrated weight. Using this ansatz, we prove that the Bisognano-Wichmann form of the entanglement Hamiltonian becomes exact, up to a nonuniversal prefactor that depends on the dispersion for gapped chains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16433v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viktor Eisler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Undecidability in Physics: a Review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16532v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The study of undecidability in problems arising from physics has experienced a renewed interest, mainly in connection with quantum information problems. The goal of this review is to survey this recent development. After a historical introduction, we first explain the necessary results about undecidability in mathematics and computer science. Then we briefly review the first results about undecidability in physics which emerged mostly in the 80s and early 90s. Finally we focus on the most recent contributions, which we divide in two main categories: many body systems and quantum information problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16532v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\'Alvaro Perales-Eceiza, Toby Cubitt, Mile Gu, David P\'erez-Garc\'ia, Michael M. Wolf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QIXAI: A Quantum-Inspired Framework for Enhancing Classical and Quantum Model Transparency and Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16537v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The impressive performance of deep learning models, particularly Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs), is often hindered by their lack of interpretability, rendering them "black boxes." This opacity raises concerns in critical areas like healthcare, finance, and autonomous systems, where trust and accountability are crucial. This paper introduces the QIXAI Framework (Quantum-Inspired Explainable AI), a novel approach for enhancing neural network interpretability through quantum-inspired techniques. By utilizing principles from quantum mechanics, such as Hilbert spaces, superposition, entanglement, and eigenvalue decomposition, the QIXAI framework reveals how different layers of neural networks process and combine features to make decisions.
  We critically assess model-agnostic methods like SHAP and LIME, as well as techniques like Layer-wise Relevance Propagation (LRP), highlighting their limitations in providing a comprehensive view of neural network operations. The QIXAI framework overcomes these limitations by offering deeper insights into feature importance, inter-layer dependencies, and information propagation. A CNN for malaria parasite detection is used as a case study to demonstrate how quantum-inspired methods like Singular Value Decomposition (SVD), Principal Component Analysis (PCA), and Mutual Information (MI) provide interpretable explanations of model behavior. Additionally, we explore the extension of QIXAI to other architectures, including Recurrent Neural Networks (RNNs), Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) networks, Transformers, and Natural Language Processing (NLP) models, and its application to generative models and time-series analysis. The framework applies to both quantum and classical systems, demonstrating its potential to improve interpretability and transparency across a range of models, advancing the broader goal of developing trustworthy AI systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16537v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John M. Willis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Lindbladian for exact renormalization of density operators in QFT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16582v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In arXiv:1609.03493, the authors extended the exact renormalization group (ERG) to arbitrary wave-functionals in quantum field theory (QFT). Applying this formalism, we show that the ERG flow of density matrices is given by a Lindblad master equation. The Lindbladian consists of a "Hamiltonian" term which is the sum of a scaling and a coarse-graining (disentangling) operator, and a dissipative term with absorption and emission rates for each momentum mode. We consider as examples the flow of Gaussian states and the perturbative ground state of $\lambda \phi^4$ theory, and highlight the role of the dissipative terms in generating the correct flow of couplings. Integrating the Lindblad master equation, we find that a finite ERG flow of density matrices is described by a quantum channel. It follows from the data processing inequality that any distinguishability measure of states is an ERG monotone.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16582v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Goldman, Nima Lashkari, Robert G. Leigh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12-spin-qubit arrays fabricated on a 300 mm semiconductor manufacturing line</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16583v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Intels efforts to build a practical quantum computer are focused on developing a scalable spin-qubit platform leveraging industrial high-volume semiconductor manufacturing expertise and 300 mm fabrication infrastructure. Here, we provide an overview of the design, fabrication, and demonstration of a new customized quantum test chip, which contains 12-quantum-dot spin-qubit linear arrays, code named Tunnel Falls. These devices are fabricated using immersion and extreme ultraviolet lithography (EUV), along with other standard high-volume manufacturing (HVM) processes, as well as production-level process control. We present key device features and fabrication details, as well as qubit characterization results confirming device functionality. These results corroborate our fabrication methods and are a crucial step towards scaling of extensible 2D qubit array schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16583v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hubert C. George, Mateusz T. M\k{a}dzik, Eric M. Henry, Andrew J. Wagner, Mohammad M. Islam, Felix Borjans, Elliot J. Connors, Joelle Corrigan, Matthew Curry, Michael K. Harper, Daniel Keith, Lester Lampert, Florian Luthi, Fahd A. Mohiyaddin, Sandra Murcia, Rohit Nair, Rambert Nahm, Aditi Nethwewala, Samuel Neyens, Roy D. Raharjo, Carly Rogan, Rostyslav Savytskyy, Thomas F. Watson, Josh Ziegler, Otto K. Zietz, Ravi Pillarisetty, Nathaniel C. Bishop, Stephanie A. Bojarski, Jeanette Roberts, James S. Clarke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement in Algebraic Quantum Field Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16599v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: There has been some recent interest in applying the techniques of Algebraic Quantum Field Theory (AQFT) to entanglement problems in perturbative QFT. In particular, the Hilbert space independence of this formulation makes it particularly interesting in the context of curved spacetimes and the emphasis on the algebra of observables makes the treatment of Bell inequalities in QFT resemble such treatment in non-relativistic Quantum Mechanics. In this work, we present the mathematical structures needed for formulating AQFT in terms of the Haag-Araki-Kastler (HAK) axioms and discuss their implications. Moreover, we discuss the algebraic approach to quantum entanglement in the form of Bell inequalities. We provide an extension of this formulation to general globally hyperbolic spacetimes using the so-called Locally Covariant approach to QFT, which extends the HAK axioms to general spacetimes by means of the Category Theory language.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16599v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael Grossi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscopic theory for a minimal oscillator model of exciton-plasmon coupling in hybrids of 2d semiconductors and metal nanoparticles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16796</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16796v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The common model to describe exciton-plasmon interaction phenomenologically is the coupled oscillator model. Originally developed for atomic systems rather than solid-state matter, this model treats both excitons and plasmons as single harmonic oscillators coupled via a constant which can be fitted to experiments. In this work, we present a modified coupled oscillator model specifically designed for exciton-plasmon interactions in hybrids composed of two-dimensional excitons, such as in a transition metal dichalcogenide (TMDC) monolayers and metal nanoparticles while maintaining the simplicity of the commonly applied coupled oscillator models. Our approach is based on a microscopic perspective and Maxwell's equations, allowing to analytically derive an effective exciton-plasmon coupling constant. Our findings highlight the importance of the spatial dispersion, i.e., the delocalized nature of TMDC excitons, necessitating the distinction between bright and momentum-dark excitons. Both types of excitons occur at different resonance energies and exhibit a qualitatively different coupling with localized plasmons. We find a strong coupling between the plasmon and momentum-dark excitons, while a weakly coupled bright exciton manifests as an additional, third peak in the spectrum. Consequently, we propose a realistic modeling of the primary spectral features in experiments incorporating three harmonic oscillator equations instead of the conventional two. However, we also shed light on the limitations of the three coupled oscillator model in describing the line shape of extinction and scattering cross section spectra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16796v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lara Greten, Robert Salzwedel, Diana Schutsch, Andreas Knorr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerated Quantum Circuit Monte-Carlo Simulation for Heavy Quark Thermalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16863</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16863v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Heavy quark thermalization in the quark-gluon plasma (QGP) is one of the most promising phenomena for understanding the strong interaction, where their energy loss and momentum broadening at low momentum can be well described by a stochastic process with drag and diffusion terms. We propose an accelerated quantum circuit Monte-Carlo (aQCMC) framework that ultilizes the quantum amplitude estimation (QAE) algorithm to simulate heavy quark thermalization with quadratically less resources. Specifically, we simulate the thermalization of a heavy quark in both 1D and 2D and in isotropic and anisotropic mediums using an ideal quantum simulator and compare that to analytical thermal expectations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16863v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenyang Qian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Industrially fabricated single-electron quantum dots in Si/Si-Ge heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16913</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16913v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper reports the compatibility of heterostructure-based spin qubit devices with industrial CMOS technology. It features Si/Si-Ge quantum dot devices fabricated using Infineon's 200 mm production line within a restricted thermal budget. The devices exhibit state-of-the-art charge sensing, charge noise and valley splitting characteristics, showing that industrial fabrication is not harming the heterostructure quality. These measured parameters are all correlated to spin qubit coherence and qubit gate fidelity. We describe the single electron device layout, design and its fabrication process using electron beam lithography. The incorporated standard 90 nm back-end of line flow for gate-layer independent contacting and wiring can be scaled up to multiple wiring layers for scalable quantum computing architectures. In addition, we present millikelvin characterization results. Our work exemplifies the potential of industrial fabrication methods to harness the inherent CMOS-compatibility of the Si/Si-Ge material system, despite being restricted to a reduced thermal budget. It paves the way for advanced quantum processor architectures with high yield and device quality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16913v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Till Huckemann, Pascal Muster, Wolfram Langheinrich, Varvara Brackmann, Michael Friedrich, Laura K. Diebel, Verena Stie{\ss}, Dominique Bougeard, Claus Dahl, Lars R. Schreiber, Hendrik Bluhm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Phonon Dynamics Induced Spontaneous Spin-Orbit Coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16944v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spin-orbit coupling in solids is typically a single-body effect arising from relativity. In this work, we propose a spontaneous generation of spin-orbit coupling from symmetry breaking. A spin-dependent electron-phonon coupling model is investigated on a half-filled square lattice, which is solved by sign-problem-free quantum Monte Carlo simulations. The phase diagram as function of phonon frequency $\omega$ and coupling constant $\lambda$ is fully investigated. The spin-orbit coupling emerges as an order in the ground state for any $\lambda$ in the adiabatic limit, accompanied by a breathing mode of lattice distortion and a staggered loop spin-current. This phase dominates in the entire range of $\omega$ with $\lambda&lt; \lambda_{\infty}$, a critical value in the $\omega \to \infty$ limit. With increasing $\omega$ and $\lambda &gt; \lambda_{\infty}$, the emergent spin-orbit coupling is suppressed and a phase transition occurs leading to charge-density-wave degenerate with superconductivity order. Our work opens up the possibility of hidden spin-orbit coupling in materials where it is otherwise forbidden by lattice symmetry and paves the way to explore new usable materials or devices in spintronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16944v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiangyu Zhang, Da Wang, Congjun Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing Bell inequalities and probing quantum entanglement at CEPC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17025v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study quantum entanglement and test violation of Bell-type inequality at the Circular Electron Positron Collider (CEPC), which is one of the most attractive future colliders. It's a promising particle collider designed to search new physics, make Standard Model (SM) precision measurements, and serving as a Higgs factory. Our study is based on a fast simulation of the $Z$ boson pair production from Higgs boson decay at $\sqrt{s} = 250$ GeV. The detector effects are also included in the simulation. The spin density matrix of the joint $ZZ$ system is parametrized using irreducible tensor operators and reconstructed from the spherical coordinates of the decay leptons. To test Bell inequalities, we construct observable quantities for the $H \to ZZ*$ process in CEPC by using the (Collins-Gisin-Linden-Massar-Popescu) CGLMP inequality, whose value is determined from the density matrix of the Z boson pairs. The sensitivity of the Bell inequality violation is observed with more than 1$\sigma$ and the presence of the quantum entanglement is probed with more than 2$\sigma$ confidence level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17025v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youpeng Wu, Ruobing Jiang, Alim Ruzi, Yong Ban, Qiang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One-shot Multiple Access Channel Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17198v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the problem of shared randomness-assisted multiple access channel (MAC) simulation for product inputs and characterize the one-shot communication cost region via almost-matching inner and outer bounds in terms of the smooth max-information of the channel, featuring auxiliary random variables of bounded size. The achievability relies on a rejection-sampling algorithm to simulate an auxiliary channel between each sender and the decoder, and producing the final output based on the output of these intermediate channels. The converse follows via information-spectrum based arguments. To bound the cardinality of the auxiliary random variables, we employ the perturbation method from [Anantharam et al., IEEE Trans. Inf. Theory (2019)] in the one-shot setting. For the asymptotic setting and vanishing errors, our result expands to a tight single-letter rate characterization and consequently extends a special case of the simulation results of [Kurri et al., IEEE Trans. Inf. Theory (2022)] for fixed, independent and identically distributed (iid) product inputs to universal simulation for any product inputs. We broaden our discussion into the quantum realm by studying feedback simulation of quantum-to-classical (QC) MACs with product measurements [Atif et al., IEEE Trans. Inf. Theory (2022)]. For fixed product inputs and with shared randomness assistance, we give a quasi tight one-shot communication cost region with corresponding single-letter asymptotic iid expansion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17198v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aditya Nema, Sreejith Sreekumar, Mario Berta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational Benchmarks for Quantum Many-Body Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.04919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.04919v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The continued development of computational approaches to many-body ground-state problems in physics and chemistry calls for a consistent way to assess its overall progress. In this work, we introduce a metric of variational accuracy, the V-score, obtained from the variational energy and its variance. We provide an extensive curated dataset of variational calculations of many-body quantum systems, identifying cases where state-of-the-art numerical approaches show limited accuracy, and future algorithms or computational platforms, such as quantum computing, could provide improved accuracy. The V-score can be used as a metric to assess the progress of quantum variational methods toward a quantum advantage for ground-state problems, especially in regimes where classical verifiability is impossible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.04919v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1126/science.adg9774</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Science 386, 296-301 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Dian Wu, Riccardo Rossi, Filippo Vicentini, Nikita Astrakhantsev, Federico Becca, Xiaodong Cao, Juan Carrasquilla, Francesco Ferrari, Antoine Georges, Mohamed Hibat-Allah, Masatoshi Imada, Andreas M. L\"auchli, Guglielmo Mazzola, Antonio Mezzacapo, Andrew Millis, Javier Robledo Moreno, Titus Neupert, Yusuke Nomura, Jannes Nys, Olivier Parcollet, Rico Pohle, Imelda Romero, Michael Schmid, J. Maxwell Silvester, Sandro Sorella, Luca F. Tocchio, Lei Wang, Steven R. White, Alexander Wietek, Qi Yang, Yiqi Yang, Shiwei Zhang, Giuseppe Carleo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Stationary Long-Term Dynamics via Selected Incomplete Dual Bases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.07407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.07407v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Simulating the dynamics of non-stationary, long-term many-body quantum systems poses significant challenges due to the large size of the state space. We are examining how traditional basis sets struggle to accurately represent long-term dynamics when using incomplete sets. To address this issue, we propose using an SU(2) coherent state basis and deriving equations of motion for both time-independent and time-dependent Hamiltonian. This methodology involves a sampling approach, where a subset of relevant configurations is chosen based on energy criteria, and a projection method is used to enhance the accuracy of wavefunction propagation while reducing computational cost. We evaluate this method through numerical simulations of a seven-qubit system, calculating key physical observables such as state probabilities and domain-wall densities. Our results indicate that while complete basis sets offer accurate dynamics, selected incomplete sets can recover essential features, especially with the assistance of a projector. Our conclusion suggests that the selected incomplete dual basis method can efficiently capture both short-term and long-term dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.07407v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hsiao-Han Chuang, Abhijit Pendse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Complexity for Discrete Logarithms and Related Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.03065</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.03065v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper studies the quantum computational complexity of the discrete logarithm (DL) and related group-theoretic problems in the context of generic algorithms -- that is, algorithms that do not exploit any properties of the group encoding.
  We establish a generic model of quantum computation for group-theoretic problems, which we call the quantum generic group model. Shor's algorithm for the DL problem and related algorithms can be described in this model. We show the quantum complexity lower bounds and almost matching algorithms of the DL and related problems in this model. More precisely, we prove the following results for a cyclic group $G$ of prime order.
  - Any generic quantum DL algorithm must make $\Omega(\log |G|)$ depth of group operations. This shows that Shor's algorithm is asymptotically optimal among the generic quantum algorithms, even considering parallel algorithms.
  - We observe that variations of Shor's algorithm can take advantage of classical computations to reduce the number of quantum group operations. We introduce a model for generic hybrid quantum-classical algorithms and show that these algorithms are almost optimal in this model. Any generic hybrid algorithm for the DL problem with a total number of group operations $Q$ must make $\Omega(\log |G|/\log Q)$ quantum group operations of depth $\Omega(\log\log |G| - \log\log Q)$.
  - When the quantum memory can only store $t$ group elements and use quantum random access memory of $r$ group elements, any generic hybrid algorithm must make either $\Omega(\sqrt{|G|})$ group operations in total or $\Omega(\log |G|/\log (tr))$ quantum group operations.
  As a side contribution, we show a multiple DL problem admits a better algorithm than solving each instance one by one, refuting a strong form of the quantum annoying property suggested in the context of password-authenticated key exchange protocol.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.03065v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-031-68391-6_1</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Minki Hhan, Takashi Yamakawa, Aaram Yun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Realism and causality imply information erasure by measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.03134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.03134v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum measurements generally introduce perturbations into the subsequent evolution of the measured system. Furthermore, a projective measurement cannot decrease the uncertainty on the system if the outcome is ignored; that is, the von Neumann entropy cannot decrease. However, under certain sound assumptions and using the quantum violation of Leggett-Garg inequalities, we demonstrate that this property is not inherited by a faithful classical causal simulation of a measurement process. In the simulation, a measurement erases previous information by performing a partial reset on the system. Thus, the measuring device acts as a low-temperature bath absorbing entropy from the measured system. Information erasure is a form of Spekkens' preparation contextuality. Our proof is straightforward if one assumes that maximal ignorance of the quantum state is compatible with maximal ignorance of the classical state. We also employ a weaker hypothesis. Information erasure is related to a theorem of Leifer and Pusey, which states that time symmetry implies retrocausality. In light of our findings, we discuss Spekkens' preparation contextuality, as well as a weakness in the hypothesis of time symmetry as defined by Leifer and Pusey.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.03134v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Montina, Stefan Wolf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stable dynamic helix state in the nonintegrable XXZ Heisenberg model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.06146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.06146v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the influence of external fields on the stability of spin helix states in an XXZ Heisenberg model. Exact diagonalization on a finite system shows that random transverse fields in the x and y directions drive the transition from integrability to nonintegrability. In such a system, the helix state can be regarded as a quantum scar. Simultaneously, the presence of uniform z field enables the helix state to better maintain its dynamical nature, allowing for a clearer understanding of its evolutionary behavior. However, the entanglement entropy reveals that irrespective of the presence of a uniform z field, as long as the system remains chaotic, the scar extent of the helix state shows no significant variation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.06146v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1402-4896/ad5886</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physica Scripta, 2024, 99 (7): 075119</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gang Zhang, Zhi Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving Superconducting Quantum Circuits in Dirac's Constraint Analysis Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.10611</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.10611v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work we exploit Dirac's Constraint Analysis (DCA) in Hamiltonian formalism to study different types of Superconducting Quantum Circuits (SQC) in a {\it{unified}} way. The Lagrangian of a SQC reveals the constraints, that are classified in a Hamiltonian framework, such that redundant variables can be removed to isolate the canonical degrees of freedom for subsequent quantization of the Dirac Brackets via a generalized Correspondence Principle. This purely algebraic approach makes the application of concepts such as graph theory, null vector, loop charge,\ etc that are in vogue, (each for a specific type of circuit), completely redundant. The universal validity of DCA scheme in SQC, proposed by us, is demonstrated by correctly re-deriving existing results for different SQCs, obtained previously exploiting different formalisms each applicable for a specific SQC. Furthermore, we have also analysed and predicted new results for a generic form of SQC - it will be interesting to see its validation in an explicit circuit implementation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.10611v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akshat Pandey, Subir Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imaginary-Temperature Zeros for Quantum Phase Transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.05531</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.05531v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: While the zeros of complex partition functions, such as Lee-Yang zeros and Fisher zeros, have been pivotal in characterizing temperature-driven phase transitions, extending this concept to zero temperature remains an open question. In this work, we propose a solution to this issue by calculating the imaginary-temperature zeros (ITZs), which are defined as the roots of the imaginary-temperature partition function. We illustrate the analytical properties of ITZs in the transverse-field Ising chain, showing that the ITZs' distribution can distinguish between various phases and signify the critical exponents. Universal singular behaviors manifest in such quantities as the edge density of ITZs and the magnetization, with the scaling exponents remarkably differing from those in Lee-Yang theory. We further illuminate the consistency between ITZs and the zeros of the spectral form factor, which offers a practical path for the experimental detection of ITZs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.05531v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.134313</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 134313 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jinghu Liu, Shuai Yin, Li Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precision Multi-Mode Microwave Spectroscopy of Paramagnetic and Rare-Earth Ion Spin Defects in Single Crystal Calcium Tungstate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.05199</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.05199v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present experimental observations of dilute ion spin ensemble defects in a low-loss single crystal cylindrical sample of CaWO$_4$ cooled to $30$ mK in temperature. Crystal field perturbations were elucidated by constructing a dielectrically loaded microwave cavity resonator from the crystal. The resonator exhibited numerous whispering gallery modes with high $Q$-factors of up to $3\times 10^7$, equivalent to a loss tangent of $\sim 3\times 10^{-8}$. The low loss allowed precision multi-mode spectroscopy of numerous high $Q$-factor photon-spin interactions. Measurements between 7 to 22 GHz revealed the presence of Gd$^{3+}$, Fe$^{3+}$, and another trace species, inferred to be rare-earth, at concentrations on the order of parts per billion. These findings motivate further exploration of prospective uses of this low-loss dielectric material for applications regarding precision and quantum metrology, as well as tests for beyond standard model physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.05199v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0224102</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Appl. Phys. Lett. 125, 164001 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Elrina Hartman, Michael E Tobar, Ben T McAllister, Jeremy Bourhill, Maxim Goryachev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast storage of photons in cavity-assisted quantum memories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.17394</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.17394v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Ideal photonic quantum memories can store arbitrary pulses of light with unit efficiency. This requires operating in the adiabatic regime, where pulses have a duration much longer than the bandwidth of the memory. In the non-adiabatic regime of short pulses, memories are therefore imperfect, and information is always lost. We theoretically investigate the bandwidth limitations for setups based on individual atoms, or ensembles thereof, confined inside optical cavities. We identify an effective strategy for optimizing the efficiencies of the storage and retrieval process regardless of the duration of the pulses. Our protocol is derived almost completely analytically and attains efficiencies better than or comparable to those obtained by numerical optimization. Furthermore, our results provide an improved understanding of the performance of quantum memories in several regimes. When considering pulses defined on an infinite time interval, the shapes can be divided into two categories, depending on their asymptotic behaviours. If the intensity of the pulse increases with time slower than or as an exponential function, then the storage efficiency is only limited by the pulse width. For pulses defined on a finite interval, on the other hand, the efficiency is determined by the shape at the beginning of the storage or, correspondingly, at the end of the retrieval process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.17394v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevApplied.22.044038</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Applied 22, 044038 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Johann S. Kollath-B\"onig, Luca Dellantonio, Luigi Giannelli, Tom Schmit, Giovanna Morigi, Anders S. S{\o}rensen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entangling two exciton modes using exciton optomechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.02710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.02710v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Exciton optomechanics, bridging cavity exciton polaritons and optomechanics, opens new opportunities for the study of light-matter strong interactions and nonlinearities, due to the rich nonlinear couplings among excitons, phonons, and photons. Here, we propose to entangle two exciton modes in an exciton-optomechanics system, which consists of a semiconductor microcavity integrated with two quantum wells. The quantum wells support two exciton modes, which simultaneously couple to an optical cavity mode via a linear dipole interaction and to a mechanical vibration mode via a nonlinear deformation potential interaction. We show that by strongly driving the microcavity with a red-detuned laser field and when the two exciton modes are respectively resonant with the Stokes and anti-Stokes sidebands scattered by the mechanical motion, stationary entanglement between the two exciton modes can be established under realistic parameters. The protocol is within reach of current technology and may become a promising approach for preparing excitonic entanglement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.02710v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuan Zuo, Zhi-Yuan Fan, Huai-Bing Zhu, Jie Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital quantum simulation of a (1+1)D SU(2) lattice gauge theory with ion qudits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.07987</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.07987v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a quantum simulation strategy for a (1+1)D SU(2) non-abelian lattice gauge theory with dynamical matter, a hardcore-gluon Hamiltonian Yang-Mills, tailored to a six-level trapped-ion qudit quantum processor, as recently experimentally realized. We employ a qudit encoding fulfilling gauge invariance, an SU(2) Gauss law. We discuss the experimental feasibility of generalized M\"olmer-S\"orensen gates used to efficiently simulate the dynamics. We illustrate how a shallow circuit with these resources is sufficient to implement scalable digital quantum simulation of the model. We also numerically show that this model, albeit simple, can dynamically manifest physically-relevant properties specific to non-abelian field theories, such as baryon excitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.07987v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PRXQuantum.5.040309</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PRX Quantum 5, 040309 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Calaj\`o, Giuseppe Magnifico, Claire Edmunds, Martin Ringbauer, Simone Montangero, Pietro Silvi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limits of noisy quantum metrology with restricted quantum controls</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.18765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.18765v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Heisenberg limit (HL, with estimation error scales as $1/n$) and the standard quantum limit (SQL, $\propto 1/\sqrt{n}$) are two fundamental limits in estimating an unknown parameter in $n$ copies of quantum channels and are achievable with full quantum controls, e.g., quantum error correction (QEC). It is unknown though, whether these limits are still achievable in restricted quantum devices when QEC is unavailable, e.g., with only unitary controls or bounded system sizes. In this Letter, we discover various new limits for estimating qubit channels under restrictive controls. The HL is shown to be unachievable in various cases, indicating the necessity of QEC in achieving the HL. Furthermore, a necessary and sufficient condition to achieve the SQL is determined, where a single-qubit unitary control protocol is identified to achieve the SQL for certain types of noisy channels, and for other cases a constant floor on the estimation error is proven. A practical example of the unitary protocol is provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.18765v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.170801</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review Letters 133, 170801 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sisi Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-inspired activation functions in the convolutional neural network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05901</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05901v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Driven by the significant advantages offered by quantum computing, research in quantum machine learning has increased in recent years. While quantum speed-up has been demonstrated in some applications of quantum machine learning, a comprehensive understanding of its underlying mechanisms for improved performance remains elusive. Our study address this problem by investigating the functional expressibility of quantum circuits integrated within a convolutional neural network (CNN). Through numerical experiments on the MNIST, Fashion MNIST, and Letter datasets, our hybrid quantum-classical CNN model demonstrates superior feature selection capabilities and substantially reduces the required training steps compared to classical CNNs. Notably, we observe similar performance improvements when incorporating three other quantum-inspired activation functions in classical neural networks, indicating the benefits of adopting quantum-inspired activation functions. Additionally, we developed a hybrid quantum Chebyshev-polynomial network (QCPN) based on the properties of quantum activation functions. We demonstrate that a three-layer QCPN can approximate any continuous function, a feat not achievable by a standard three-layer classical neural network. Our findings suggest that quantum-inspired activation functions can reduce model depth while maintaining high learning capability, making them a promising approach for optimizing large-scale machine-learning models. We also outline future research directions for leveraging quantum advantages in machine learning, aiming to unlock further potential in this rapidly evolving field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05901v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shaozhi Li, M Sabbir Salek, Yao Wang, Mashrur Chowdhury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A circuit-generated quantum subspace algorithm for the variational quantum eigensolver</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.06534</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.06534v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent research has shown that wavefunction evolution in real- and imaginary-time can generate quantum subspaces with significant utility for obtaining accurate ground state energies. Inspired by these methods, we propose combining quantum subspace techniques with the variational quantum eigensolver (VQE). In our approach, the parameterized quantum circuit is divided into a series of smaller subcircuits. The sequential application of these subcircuits to an initial state generates a set of wavefunctions that we use as a quantum subspace to obtain high-accuracy groundstate energies. We call this technique the circuit subspace variational quantum eigensolver (CSVQE) algorithm. By benchmarking CSVQE on a range of quantum chemistry problems, we show that it can achieve significant error reduction in the best case compared to conventional VQE, particularly for poorly optimized circuits, greatly improving convergence rates. Furthermore, we demonstrate that when applied to circuits trapped at a local minima, CSVQE can produce energies close to the global minimum of the energy landscape, making it a potentially powerful tool for diagnosing local minima.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.06534v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0224883</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Chem. Phys. 161, 164103 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mark R. Hirsbrunner, J. Wayne Mullinax, Yizhi Shen, David B. Williams-Young, Katherine Klymko, Roel Van Beeumen, Norm M. Tubman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performant near-term quantum combinatorial optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16135v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Combinatorial optimization is a promising application for near-term quantum computers, however, identifying performant algorithms suited to noisy quantum hardware remains as an important goal to potentially realizing quantum computational advantages. To address this we present a variational quantum algorithm for solving combinatorial optimization problems with linear-depth circuits. Our algorithm uses an ansatz composed of Hamiltonian generators designed to control each term in the target combinatorial function, along with parameter updates following a modified version of quantum imaginary time evolution. We evaluate this ansatz in numerical simulations that target solutions to the MAXCUT problem. The state evolution is shown to closely mimic imaginary time evolution, and its optimal-solution convergence is further improved using adaptive transformations of the classical Hamiltonian spectrum. With these innovations, the algorithm consistently converges to optimal solutions, with interesting highly-entangled dynamics along the way. We further demonstrate the success of this approach by performing optimization of a truncated version of our ansatz with up to 32 qubits in a trapped-ion quantum computer, using measurements from the quantum computer to train the ansatz and prepare optimal solutions with high fidelity in the majority of cases we consider. The success of these large-scale quantum circuit optimizations, in the presence of realistic hardware constraints and without error mitigation, mark significant progress on the path towards solving combinatorial problems using quantum computers. We conclude our performant and resource-minimal approach is a promising candidate for potential quantum computational advantages.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16135v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Titus D. Morris, Ananth Kaushik, Martin Roetteler, Phillip C. Lotshaw</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental preparation of multiphoton-added coherent states of light</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10403</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10403v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Conditional addition of photons represents a crucial tool for optical quantum state engineering and it forms a fundamental building block of advanced quantum photonic devices. Here we report on experimental implementation of the conditional addition of several photons. We demonstrate the addition of one, two, and three photons to input coherent states with various amplitudes. The resulting highly nonclassical photon-added states are completely characterized with time-domain homodyne tomography, and the nonclassicality of the prepared states is witnessed by the negativity of their Wigner functions. We experimentally demonstrate that the conditional addition of photons realizes approximate noiseless quantum amplification of coherent states with sufficiently large amplitude. We also investigate certification of the stellar rank of the generated multiphoton-added coherent states, which quantifies the non-Gaussian resources required for their preparation. Our results pave the way towards the experimental realization of complex optical quantum operations based on combination of multiple photon additions and subtractions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10403v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41534-024-00885-y</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>npj Quantum Inf 10, 89 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ji\v{r}\'i Fadrn\'y, Michal Neset, Martin Bielak, Miroslav Je\v{z}ek, Jan B\'ilek, Jarom\'ir Fiur\'a\v{s}ek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement dynamics in double Jaynes-Cummings model and intensity-dependent double Jaynes-Cummings model for squeezed coherent thermal states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10564v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, the entanglement dynamics of different subsystems such as atom-atom, atom-field and field-field with radiation field in squeezed coherent thermal states for the intensity-dependent double Jaynes-Cummings model (IDDJCM) and double Jaynes-Cummings model (DJCM) are investigated. The effects of both squeezed photons and thermal photons on entanglement dynamics is observed. The main feature of the double Jaynes-Cummings model - entanglement sudden death is observed for every subsystem. The effects of various interactions such as Ising interaction, single photon exchange interaction and dipole-dipole interaction on entanglement dynamics are studied. The effects of detuning, Kerr-nonlinearity on the entanglement dynamics are investigated for every subsystem. It is noticed that proper choice of the interactions parameters, detuning and Kerr-nonlinearity effectively removes entanglement deaths from the dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10564v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koushik Mandal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The formation of Schrodinger cat-like states in the process of spontaneous parametric down-conversion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14526v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show the formation of Schrodinger cat-like states during the spontaneous parametric down-conversion process (SPDC) when the pump mode is considered quantum and depleted. For the first time, we show the formation of the Schrodinger cat-like states in the fundamental and second harmonic modes under non-dissipative and dissipative regimes. For certain initial state conditions and interaction lengths, negativity is obtained in both modes. The Wigner function is used to visualize qualitatively Schrodinger cat-like states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14526v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ranjit Singh, Alexander E. Teretenkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Few-Photon SUPER: Quantum emitter inversion via two off-resonant photon modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20095</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20095v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: With the realization of controlled quantum systems, exploring excitations beyond the resonant case opens new possibilities. We investigate an extended Jaynes-Cummings model where two photon modes are coupled off-resonantly to a quantum emitter. This allows us to identify few-photon scattering mechanisms that lead to a full inversion of the emitter while transferring off-resonant photons from one mode to another. This behaviour connects to recent measurements of a two-level emitter scattering two off-resonant photons simultaneously. Furthermore, our results can be understood as quantized analogue of the recently developed off-resonant quantum control scheme known as Swing-UP of quantum EmitteR (SUPER). Our intuitive formalism gives a deeper insight into the interaction of a two-level emitter with off-resonant light modes with the prospect of novel photonic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20095v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quentin W. Richter, Jan M. Kaspari, Thomas K. Bracht, Leonid Yatsenko, Vollrath Martin Axt, Arno Rauschenbeutel, Doris E. Reiter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mechanical dynamics around higher-order exceptional point in magno-optomechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01060v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We theoretically study diverse exceptional points (EPs) in an experimentally feasible magno-optomechanics consisting of an optomechanical subsystem coupled to a magnomechanical subsystem via physically direct contact. By adiabatically eliminating both the cavity and the Kittel mode, dissipative and parity-time symmetric exceptional points can be observed. When only the cavity mode is eliminated, a second (third) -order pseudo-Hermitian EP emerges for nondegenerate (degenerate) mechanical modes. The distinct dynamical behavior of two mechanical modes around these EPs are further studied. Our proposal provides a promising way to engineer diverse EPs and quantify non-Hermitian phase transition with exceptional dynamical behavior in magno-optomechanics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01060v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Di He, Xiao-Hong Fan, Ming-Yue Liu, Guo-Qiang Zhang, Hai-Chao Li, Wei Xiong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric representations of braid and Yang-Baxter gates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.08320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.08320v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Brick-wall circuits composed of the Yang-Baxter gates are integrable. It becomes an important tool to study the quantum many-body system out of equilibrium. To put the Yang-Baxter gate on quantum computers, it has to be decomposed into the native gates of quantum computers. It is favorable to apply the least number of native two-qubit gates to construct the Yang-Baxter gate. We study the geometric representations of all X-type braid gates and their corresponding Yang-Baxter gates via the Yang-Baxterization. We find that the braid and Yang-Baxter gates can only exist on certain edges and faces of the two-qubit tetrahedron. We identify the parameters by which the braid and Yang-Baxter gates are the Clifford gate, the matchgate, and the dual-unitary gate. The geometric representations provide the optimal decompositions of the braid and Yang-Baxter gates in terms of other two-qubit gates. We also find that the entangling powers of the Yang-Baxter gates are determined by the spectral parameters. Our results provide the necessary conditions to construct the braid and Yang-Baxter gates on quantum computers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.08320v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1751-8121/ad85b2</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. A: Math. Theor. 57 445303 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kun Zhang, Kun Hao, Kwangmin Yu, Vladimir Korepin, Wen-Li Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DisQ: A Markov Decision Process Based Language for Quantum Distributed Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09710v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The development of quantum computers has reached a great milestone, in spite of restrictions on important quantum resources: the number of qubits being entangled at a single-location quantum computer. Recently, there has been some work to combine single-location quantum computing and quantum networking techniques to develop distributed quantum systems such that large entangled qubit groups can be established through remote processors, and quantum algorithms can be executed distributively. We present DisQ as a framework to facilitate the rewrites of quantum algorithms to their distributed versions. The core of DisQ is a distributed quantum programming language that combines the concepts of Chemical Abstract Machine (CHAM) and Markov Decision Processes (MDP) with the objective of providing a clearly distinguishing quantum concurrent and distributed behaviors. Based on the DisQ language, we develop a simulation relation for verifying the equivalence of a quantum algorithm and its distributed versions. We present several case studies, such as quantum addition and Shor's algorithm, to demonstrate their equivalent rewrites to distributed versions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09710v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.PL</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Le Chang, Saitej Yavvari, Rance Cleaveland, Samik Basu, Liyi Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of Electron Paramagnetic Resonance of Two Electron Spins Using a Single NV Center in Diamond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19691v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: An interacting spin system is an excellent testbed for fundamental quantum physics and applications in quantum sensing and quantum simulation. For these investigations, detailed information of the interactions, e.g., the number of spins and their interaction strengths, is often required. In this study, we present the identification and characterization of a single nitrogen vacancy (NV) center coupled to two electron spins. In the experiment, we first identify a well-isolated single NV center and characterize its spin decoherence time. Then, we perform NV-detected electron paramagnetic resonance (EPR) spectroscopy to detect surrounding electron spins. From the analysis of the NV-EPR signal, we precisely determine the number of detected spins and their interaction strengths. Moreover, the spectral analysis indicates that the candidates of the detected spins are diamond surface spins. This study demonstrates a promising approach for the identification and characterization of an interacting spin system for realizing entangled sensing using electron spin as quantum reporters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19691v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuhang Ren, Susumu Takahashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physical proof of the topological entanglement entropy inequality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04592v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently it was shown that the topological entanglement entropy (TEE) of a two-dimensional gapped ground state obeys the universal inequality $\gamma \geq \log \mathcal{D}$, where $\gamma$ is the TEE and $\mathcal{D}$ is the total quantum dimension of all anyon excitations, $\mathcal{D} = \sqrt{\sum_a d_a^2}$. Here we present an alternative, more direct proof of this inequality. Our proof uses only the strong subadditivity property of the von Neumann entropy together with a few physical assumptions about the ground state density operator. Our derivation naturally generalizes to a variety of systems, including spatially inhomogeneous systems with defects and boundaries, higher dimensional systems, and mixed states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04592v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 165154 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Michael Levin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards tolerant testing stabilizer states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06289</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.06289v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the following task: suppose an algorithm is given copies of an unknown $n$-qubit quantum state $|\psi\rangle$ promised $(i)$ $|\psi\rangle$ is $\varepsilon_1$-close to a stabilizer state in fidelity or $(ii)$ $|\psi\rangle$ is $\varepsilon_2$-far from all stabilizer states, decide which is the case. We show two results:
  (i) Assuming $|\psi\rangle$ is a phase state, i.e., $|\psi\rangle=\frac{1}{\sqrt{2^n}}\sum \limits_{x \in \{0,1\}^n} {f(x)}|x\rangle$ where $f:\{0,1\}^n\rightarrow \{-1,1\}$, then we give a $\textsf{poly}(1/\varepsilon_1)$ sample and $n\cdot \textsf{poly}(1/\varepsilon_1)$ time algorithm for every $\varepsilon_1 &gt; 0$ and $\varepsilon_2 \leq \textsf{poly}(\varepsilon_1)$, for tolerant testing stabilizer states.
  (ii) For arbitrary quantum states $|\psi\rangle$, assuming a conjecture in additive combinatorics, we give a $\textsf{poly}(1/\varepsilon_1)$-sample and $n\cdot \textsf{poly}(1/\varepsilon_1)$-time algorithm for this task for every $\varepsilon_1&gt;0$ and $\varepsilon_2\leq 2^{-\textsf{poly}(1/\varepsilon_1)}$
  Our proof includes a new definition of Gowers norm for quantum states, an inverse theorem for the Gowers-$3$ norm of states and new bounds on stabilizer covering for structured subsets of Paulis using results in additive combinatorics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.06289v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Srinivasan Arunachalam, Arkopal Dutt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A solution of the generalised quantum Stein's lemma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.06410v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We solve the generalised quantum Stein's lemma, proving that the Stein exponent associated with entanglement testing, namely, the quantum hypothesis testing task of distinguishing between $n$ copies of an entangled state $\rho_{AB}$ and a generic separable state $\sigma_{A^n:B^n}$, equals the regularised relative entropy of entanglement. Not only does this determine the ultimate performance of entanglement testing, but it also establishes the reversibility of all quantum resource theories under asymptotically resource non-generating operations, with the regularised relative entropy of resource governing the asymptotic transformation rate between any two quantum states. As a by-product, we prove that the same Stein exponent can also be achieved when the null hypothesis is only approximately i.i.d., in the sense that it can be modelled by an "almost power state". To solve the problem we introduce two techniques. The first is a procedure that we call "blurring", which, informally, transforms a permutationally symmetric state by making it more evenly spread across nearby type classes. Blurring alone suffices to prove the generalised Stein's lemma in the fully classical case, but not in the quantum case. Our second technical innovation, therefore, is to perform a second quantisation step to lift the problem to an infinite-dimensional bosonic quantum system; we then solve it there by using techniques from continuous-variable quantum information. Rather remarkably, the second-quantised action of the blurring map corresponds to a pure loss channel. A careful examination of this second quantisation step is the core of our quantum solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.06410v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ludovico Lami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High Precision Fault-Tolerant Quantum Circuit Synthesis by Diagonalization using Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.00433</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.00433v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Resource efficient and high precision compilation of programs into quantum circuits expressed in Fault-Tolerant gate sets, such as the Clifford+T gate set, is vital for the success of quantum computing. Optimal analytical compilation methods are known for restricted classes of unitaries, otherwise the problem is intractable. Empirical search-based synthesis methods, including Reinforcement Learning and simulated annealing, can generate good implementations for a more extensive set of unitaries, but require trade-offs in approximation precision and resource use. We leverage search-based methods to reduce the general unitary synthesis problem to one of synthesizing diagonal unitaries; a problem solvable efficiently in general and optimally in the single-qubit case. We demonstrate how our approach improves the implementation precision attainable by Fault-Tolerant synthesis algorithms on an array of unitaries taken from real quantum algorithms. On these benchmarks, many of which cannot be handled by existing approaches, we observe an average of 95% fewer resource-intensive non-Clifford gates compared to the more general Quantum Shannon Decomposition. On a subset of algorithms of interest for future term applications, diagonalization can reduce T gate counts by up to 16.8% compared to other methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.00433v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mathias Weiden, Justin Kalloor, Ed Younis, John Kubiatowicz, Costin Iancu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transmon qubit modeling and characterization for Dark Matter search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.05988</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.05988v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study presents the design, simulation, and experimental characterization of a superconducting transmon qubit circuit prototype for potential applications in dark matter detection experiments. We describe a planar circuit design featuring two non-interacting transmon qubits, one with fixed frequency and the other flux tunable. Finite-element simulations were employed to extract key Hamiltonian parameters and optimize component geometries. The qubit was fabricated and then characterized at $20$ mK, allowing for a comparison between simulated and measured qubit parameters. Good agreement was found for transition frequencies and anharmonicities (within 1\% and 10\% respectively) while coupling strengths exhibited larger discrepancies (30\%). We discuss potential causes for measured coherence times falling below expectations ($T_1\sim\,$1-2 \textmu s) and propose strategies for future design improvements. Notably, we demonstrate the application of a hybrid 3D-2D simulation approach for energy participation ratio evaluation, yielding a more accurate estimation of dielectric losses. This work represents an important first step in developing planar Quantum Non-Demolition (QND) single-photon counters for dark matter searches, particularly for axion and dark photon detection schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.05988v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Moretti, D. Labranca, P. Campana, R. Carobene, M. Gobbo, M. A. Castellanos-Beltran, D. Olaya, P. F. Hopkins, L. Banchi, M. Borghesi, A. Candido, H. A. Corti, A. D'Elia, M. Faverzani, E. Ferri, A. Nucciotti, L. Origo, A. Pasquale, A. S. Piedjou Komnang, A. Rettaroli, S. Tocci, S. Carrazza, C. Gatti, A. Giachero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frequency-dependent squeezing via Einstein-Podolsky-Rosen entanglement based on silicon nitride microring resonators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09336</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09336v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Significant efforts have been made to enhance the performance of displacement sensors limited by quantum noise, such as gravitational wave detectors. Techniques like frequency-dependent squeezing have overcome the standard quantum limit in optomechanical force measurements, leading to substantial overall progress. These advancements, coupled with major developments in integrated photonics, have paved the way for the emergence of integrated Kerr quantum frequency combs (QFCs). A platform has been established for designing EPR entangled quantum frequency combs using on-chip silicon nitride microring resonators, enabling thorough analysis and optimization of entanglement performance, as well as effective noise reduction adjustments. This platform, incorporating the quantum dynamics of Kerr nonlinear microresonators, supports at least 12 continuous-variable quantum modes in the form of 6 simultaneous two-mode squeezed pairs (EPR entangled pairs). Additionally, by selecting the detection angle of the idler mode, a single-mode squeezed state is generated in the signal mode. Given the frequency-dependent nature of the detection angle, frequency-dependent squeezing is achieved. A comparative analysis of the results under different dispersion conditions is also conducted.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09336v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haodong Xu, Zijun Shu, Nianqin Li, Yang Shen, Bo Ji, Yongjun Yang, Tengfei Wu, Mingliang Long, Guangqiang He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing the set of quantum correlations in prepare-and-measure quantum chain-shaped networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17185</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17185v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a hierarchy of tests satisfied by any probability distribution $P$ that represents the quantum correlations generated in prepare-and-measure (P\&amp;M) quantum chain-shaped networks, assuming only the inner-product information of the non-orthogonal quantum states. The P\&amp;M quantum chain-shaped networks involve multiple measurement parties, each measurement party potentially having multiple sequential receivers. Specifically, we adapt the original NPA-hierarchy by incorporating a finite number of linear and positive semi-definite constraints to characterize the quantum correlations in P\&amp;M quantum chain-shaped networks. These constraints in each hierarchy are derived from sequential measurement operators and the inner-product matrix of the non-orthogonal quantum states. We apply the adapted NPA-hierarchy to tackle some quantum information tasks, including sequential quantum random access codes (QRACs) and randomness certification. First, we derive the optimal trade-off between the two sequential receivers in the $2 \to 1$ sequential QRACs. Furthermore, we have investigated semi-device-independent randomness certification in the double violation region of $2 \to 1$ sequential QRACs. Second, considering the presence of eavesdropper (Eve) in actual communication, we show how much global and local randomness can be certified using the optimal trade-off of $2 \to 1$ sequential QRACs. Additionally, we quantify the amount of local and global randomness that can be certified from the complete probabilities generated by the two sequential receivers. We conclude that utilizing the complete set of probabilities certifies more local and global randomness than relying solely on the optimal trade-off relationship.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17185v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanning Jia, Fenzhuo Guo, YuKun Wang, Haifeng Dong, Fei Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Certified Randomness implies Secure Classical Position-Verification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03982</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.03982v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Liu et al. (ITCS22) initiated the study of designing a secure position verification protocol based on a specific proof of quantumness protocol and classical communication. In this paper, we study this interesting topic further and answer some of the open questions that are left in that paper. We provide a new generic compiler that can convert any single round proof of quantumness-based certified randomness protocol to a secure classical communication-based position verification scheme. Later, we extend our compiler to different kinds of multi-round proof of quantumness-based certified randomness protocols. Moreover, we instantiate our compiler with a random circuit sampling (RCS)-based certified randomness protocol proposed by Aaronson and Hung (STOC 23). RCS-based techniques are within reach of today's NISQ devices; therefore, our design overcomes the limitation of the Liu et al. protocol that would require a fault-tolerant quantum computer to realize. Moreover, this is one of the first cryptographic applications of RCS-based techniques other than certified randomness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.03982v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Omar Amer, Kaushik Chakraborty, David Cui, Fatih Kaleoglu, Charles Lim, Minzhao Liu, Marco Pistoia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Absence of Bound States for Quantum Walks and CMV Matrices via Reflections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.11024</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.11024v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We give a criterion based on reflection symmetries in the spirit of Jitomirskaya--Simon to show absence of point spectrum for (split-step) quantum walks and Cantero--Moral--Vel\'azquez (CMV) matrices. To accomplish this, we use some ideas from a recent paper by the authors and their collaborators to implement suitable reflection symmetries for such operators. We give several applications. For instance, we deduce arithmetic delocalization in the phase for the unitary almost-Mathieu operator and singular continuous spectrum for generic CMV matrices generated by the Thue--Morse subshift.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.11024v2</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.4171/JST/533</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Spectr. Theory 14 (2024), no. 4, pp. 1513--1536</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Christopher Cedzich, Jake Fillman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The classical-quantum hybrid canonical dynamics and its difficulties with special and general relativity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07723</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07723v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We discuss the Hamiltonian hybrid coupling between a classical and a quantum subsystem. If applicable to classical gravity coupled to quantized matter, this hybrid theory might realize a captivating `postquantum' alternative to full quantum-gravity. We summarize the nonrelativistic hybrid dynamics in improved formalism adequate to Hamiltonian systems. The mandatory decoherence and diffusion terms become divergent in special and general relativistic extensions. It is not yet known if any renormalization method might reconcile Markovian decoherence and diffusion with relativity. Postquantum gravity could previously only be realized in the Newtonian approximation. We argue that pending problems of the recently proposed general relativistic postquantum theory will not be solved if Markovian diffusion/decoherence are truly incompatible with relativity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07723v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.084052</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 084052 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lajos Di\'osi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Relaxometry of Methemoglobin by Widefield Nitrogen-Vacancy Microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.08227</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.08227v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Hemoglobin (Hb) is a multifaceted protein, classified as a metalloprotein, chromoprotein, and globulin. It incorporates iron, which plays a crucial role in transporting oxygen within red blood cells. Hb functions by carrying oxygen from the respiratory organs to diverse tissues in the body, where it releases oxygen to fuel aerobic respiration, thus supporting the organism's metabolic processes. Hb can exist in several forms, primarily distinguished by the oxidation state of the iron in the heme group, including Methemoglobin (MetHb). Measuring the concentration of MetHb is crucial because it cannot transport oxygen, hence higher concentration of MetHb in the blood causes methemoglobinemia. Here, we use optically detected magnetic relaxometry of paramagnetic iron spins in MetHb drop-casted onto nanostructured diamond doped with shallow high density nitrogen vacancy (NV) spin qubits. We modify the MetHb concentration in the range of 6 x 10^6 - 1.8 x 10^7 adsorbed Fe+3 spins per um^2 and observe an increase of the NV relaxation rate G1 (= 1/T1, T1 is NV spin lattice relaxation time) up to 2 x 10^3 s^-1. NV magnetic relaxometry of MetHb in phosphate-buffered saline solution shows a similar effect with an increase of G1 to 6.7 x 10e3 s^-1 upon increasing the MetHb concentration to 100 uM. The increase of NV G1 is explained by the increased spin noise coming from the Fe+3 spins present in MetHb proteins. This study presents an additional usage of NV quantum sensors to detect paramagnetic centers of biomolecules at volumes below 100 picoliter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.08227v2</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0217987</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Appl. Phys. Lett. 125, 114002 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Suvechhya Lamichhane, Evelyn Carreto Guevara, Ilja Fescenko, Sy-Hwang Liou, Rebecca Y. Lai, Abdelghani Laraoui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite-temperature properties of string-net models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19713v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a refined version of the string-net model which assigns a different energy cost to each plaquette excitation. Using recent exact calculations of the energy-level degeneracies we compute the partition function of this model and investigate several thermodynamical quantities. In the thermodynamic limit, we show that the partition function is dominated by the contribution of special particles, dubbed pure fluxons, which trivially braid with all other (product of) fluxons. We also analyze the behavior of Wegner-Wilson loops associated to excitations and show that they obey an area law, indicating confinement, for any finite temperature except for pure fluxons that always remain deconfined. Finally, using a recently proposed conjecture, we compute the topological mutual information at finite temperature, which features a nontrivial scaling between system size and temperature, similar to the one-dimensional classical Ising model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19713v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.155147</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 155147 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Anna Ritz-Zwilling, Jean-No\"el Fuchs, Steven H. Simon, Julien Vidal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extending Radiowave Frequency Detection Range with Dressed States of Solid-State Spin Ensembles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14483</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14483v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum sensors using solid-state spin defects excel in the detection of radiofrequency (RF) fields, serving various purposes in communication, ranging, and sensing. For this purpose, pulsed dynamical decoupling (PDD) protocols are typically applied, which enhance sensitivity to RF signals. However, these methods are limited to frequencies of a few megahertz, which poses a challenge for sensing higher frequencies. We introduce an alternative approach based on a continuous dynamical decoupling (CDD) scheme involving dressed states of nitrogen vacancy (NV) ensemble spins driven within a microwave resonator. We compare the CDD methods to established PDD protocols and demonstrate the detection of RF signals up to $\sim$ 85 MHz, about ten times the current limit imposed by the PDD approach under identical conditions. Implementing the CDD method in a heterodyne synchronized protocol combines the high frequency detection with high spectral resolution. This advancement extends to various domains requiring detection in the high frequency (HF) and very high frequency (VHF) ranges of the RF spectrum, including spin sensor-based magnetic resonance spectroscopy at high magnetic fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14483v2</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jens C. Hermann, Roberto Rizzato, Fleming Bruckmaier, Robin D. Allert, Aharon Blank, Dominik B. Bucher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical evaluation of orientation averages and its application to molecular physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17434</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17434v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In molecular physics, it is often necessary to average over the orientation of molecules when calculating observables, in particular when modelling experiments in the liquid or gas phase. Evaluated in terms of Euler angles, this is closely related to integration over two- or three-dimensional unit spheres, a common problem discussed in numerical analysis. The computational cost of the integration depends significantly on the quadrature method, making the selection of an appropriate method crucial for the feasibility of simulations. After reviewing several classes of spherical quadrature methods in terms of their efficiency and error distribution, we derive guidelines for choosing the best quadrature method for orientation averages and illustrate these with three examples from chiral molecule physics. While Gauss quadratures allow for achieving numerically exact integration for a wide range of applications, other methods offer advantages in specific circumstances. Our guidelines can also by applied to higher-dimensional spherical domains and other geometries. We also present a Python package providing a flexible interface to a variety of quadrature methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17434v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0230569</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Chem. Phys. 161, 131501 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Blech, Raoul M. M. Ebeling, Marec Heger, Christiane P. Koch, Daniel M. Reich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dephasing-assisted transport in a tight-binding chain with a linear potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21715v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: An environment interacting with a quantum system can enhance transport through the suppression of quantum effects responsible for localization. In this paper, we study the interplay between bulk dephasing and a linear potential in a boundary-driven tight-binding chain. A linear potential induces Wannier-Stark localization in the absence of noise, while dephasing induces diffusive transport in the absence of a tilt. We derive an approximate expression for the steady-state current as a function of both dephasing and tilt which closely matches the exact solution for a wide range of parameters. From it, we find that the maximum current occurs for a dephasing rate equal to the period of Bloch oscillations in the Wannier-Stark localized system. We also find that the current displays a maximum as a function of the system size, provided that the total potential tilt across the chain remains constant. Our results can be verified in current experimental platforms and represents a step forward in analytical studies of environment-assisted transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21715v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3389/fphy.2024.1474018</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Front. Phys. (2024) 12:1474018</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Samuel L. Jacob, Laetitia P. Bettmann, Artur M. Lacerda, Krissia Zawadzki, Stephen R. Clark, John Goold, Juan Jos\'e Mendoza-Arenas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement renormalization of fractonic anisotropic $\mathbb{Z}_N$ Laplacian models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18206v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Gapped fracton phases constitute a new class of quantum states of matter which connects to topological orders but does not fit easily into existing paradigms. They host unconventional features such as sub-extensive and robust ground state degeneracies as well as sensitivity to lattice geometry. We investigate the anisotropic $\mathbb{Z}_N$ Laplacian model [1] which can describe a family of fracton phases defined on arbitrary graphs. Focusing on representative geometries where the 3D lattices are extensions of 2D square, triangular, honeycomb and Kagome lattices into the third dimension, we study their ground state degeneracies and mobility of excitations, and examine their entanglement renormalization group (ERG) flows. All models show bifurcating behaviors under ERG but have distinct ERG flows sensitive to both $N$ and lattice geometry. In particular, we show that the anisotropic $\mathbb{Z}_N$ Laplacian models defined on the extensions of triangular and honeycomb lattices are equivalent when $N$ is coprime to $3$. We also point out that, in contrast to previous expectations, the model defined on the extension of Kagome lattice is robust against local perturbations if and only if $N$ is coprime to $6$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18206v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuan Xue, Pranay Gorantla, Zhu-Xi Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supersonic shear waves in dipolar supersolids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16060v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dipolar supersolids--quantum states which are simultaneously superfluid and solid--have had their superfluid nature rigorously tested, while its solid nature remains uncharted. Arguably, the defining characteristic of a solid is the existence of elastic shear waves. In this work, we investigate transverse wave packet propagation in dipolar supersolids with triangular and honeycomb structure. Remarkably, the honeycomb supersolid displays anomalous dispersion, supporting waves traveling faster than the transverse speed of sound: a supersonic shear wave. For both supersolid phases, we calculate the shear modulus, a key parameter that quantifies the material's rigidity. Our findings are pertinent to current experimental efforts scrutinizing the fundamental properties of supersolids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16060v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pramodh Senarath Yapa, Thomas Bland</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
